Let me now introduce Professor Dame
Fiona Murray. Fiona is the associate
dean of innovation at the MIT Sloan
School of Management and she is the
William Porter Professor of
Entrepreneurship within the Sloan
School. Fiona, over to you.
>> Brilliant. Thank you very much, Ron. Um,
it's really a pleasure to be joining
ILP. Uh, my name is Fiona Murray. As Ron
said, I've actually been an MIT faculty
member for over 25 years, and that has
meant 25 years of partnership with ILP.
Uh really having the opportunity not
only to pursue the sort of frontiers of
knowledge and research, but work with
corporate partners, government partners,
and others to make sure that our ideas
really make a difference in the world.
And I'm especially pleased that in this
webinar I'll be joined by my colleague
and co-author, Dr. Phil Buden. uh we've
had the opportunity to do uh a
significant body of work together and uh
what we're talking about today uh is
very much grounded in our book um
accelerating innovation. But what I want
to do is sort of take a few minutes at
the beginning to sort of set the scene
and particularly to pick up on this
topic of innovation in the context of
this era of geopolitics. So I wonder Ron
with permission from you if I might
share my slides.
So, as I've said, I want to talk about
innovation in this era of geopolitics. I
don't think I'm going to need to really
persuade any of you that we really are
in a new phase. Um, many things are
going to characterize this, but I think
there are at least three. One is
absolutely the sense that we have moved
into a period of great power
competition, particularly between uh the
United States and China. This is
something really very novel for our
generation and for our organizations to
be confronted I think with a peer
adversary. Uh secondly, there's sort of
tension and complexity between
traditional allies. So you'll see here
this nice headline from the Financial
Times, the US needs a new geopolitical
comp compass. As we think about the
relationship amongst allies and
partners,
those relationships are continually
being rewired. I just came back from the
NATO summit and you could really see
some of that in action uh in all the
meetings that were taking place. And
third, of course, we are in a period
where there are a number of wars around
the globe uh not least uh the Ukraine
war. And so those at least those three
things together are absolutely sort of
creating a heightened sense of the sort
of complexities of geopolitics.
And I would say that more than any other
period, this new era puts um sort of
economics, innovation, industrialization
in the spotlight. We've often
traditionally thought about geopolitics
as something that really does affect
governments. It's a thing that causes
governments to talk to each other and
engage in different ways. Or it might be
something that sort of shapes very
narrow set of industries. But today we
see not only um economics and innovation
really being at the heart of war. Uh
think about the implications for
Ukraine's economy and Russia's frankly
of um the ongoing war. But it's also
meant that in some industries that are
considered particularly strategic for
example you know rare earths and mining
you know an industry that has always
been sort of royal by politics in the
particular locations but that's one now
absolutely sharply in the spotlight as
you see Pentagon moving to sort of
secure the US rare earth uh mineral
needs but also how we think about
dependence on technology and whether or
not if you're based in Europe as you
know I spend much time in Europe and the
UK as does Phil um you know how we
really understand that and so these are
ongoing and very rapidly moving kind of
questions and so again but why why now
what is it particularly that means that
I believe that in every boardroom in
every investment committee and every
startup accelerator geopolitics has to
be on the agenda and we need this new
geopolitical calculus through which to
make our decisions around innovation
industrialization um and investment well
you know so we we see this sort of not
only entering ing the boardroom but also
the ecosystem these places where
innovation is absolutely being generated
and it is affecting these key five
stakeholders. These are the five
stakeholders that in the work that Phil
and I have done together we see as
absolutely essential to driving the
ingenuity the experimentation of early
stage innovation and each one is going
to be shaped by uh the geopolitical
environment around them. Now you know
again we might say why today and what is
it that makes this particularly
difficult as a calculus? why do we have
to talk about it as opposed to saying
all right you know there's a very narrow
number of industries they're going to
become more important when I think it
actually goes back to something that um
was really an observation that Phil made
um he often and I hope we pick this up
Phil in a fireside chat portion talks
about the fact that um Tom Freeman wrote
this quite interesting book in 2005 the
world is flat and we know very well and
what was he was really talking about was
globalization now by 2025 it's very
clear that at least for innovation It's
not flat. It's actually highly
distributed across the world um in
places that we call innovation
ecosystems. These places that have very
high concentrations of innovative
activity. You'll see from this map,
these are ecosystems that we've worked
with through our regional
entrepreneurship acceleration program.
These ecosystems are no longer just in
Silicon Valley and Boston. They are
distributed worldwide. And that's going
to be really important as you accelerate
innovation and build competitive
advantage through your ecosystem
engagement. And that's really the topic
of our book. But at the same time, not
all locations are created equal from a
geopolitical point of view. Engaging
with some of them has become more
complicated. Engaging with others has
become more preferable from the
perspective of our various governments.
And even more so, the industrial base
that sort of connects them all together
is itself extraordinarily globalized.
And so these decisions are sort of being
made on a changing global terrain that
it's worth us thinking about. Now the
other thing I would say um is that it's
the first time really in recent history
that the US has faced a peer adversary
with comparable expertise in technology
across a really wide range of
technological domains. Now you may say
hold on you know Russia was very good at
these two things and you know we were
always focused on for example nuclear
technology. What's particularly
interesting about China is its
extraordinary frontier innovation
capabilities in some very very important
areas of technology. Um it's not just
hypersonics, it's also in the life
sciences and increasingly it's in areas
like battery storage, hydrogen, bio
energy. The chart on the left shows you
some of the patents that have sort of
been increasing from Japan, China,
elsewhere, but particularly China, this
very rapid rise. Um if any of you have
read the New York Times this morning, uh
you'll see an article which very much
demonstrates that China is absolutely at
the forefront with clean energy
technology. And so we see this across
this wide range of technological domains
and we must take that very very
seriously. But the second I think is the
increasing use of this technological
interdependency that we are now for
example in the United States deeply
dependent upon China for example for
lithiumion batteries as a source of
power projection. So as we tap into
these ecosystems for ideas, as we tap
into these industrialized bases for you
know the supply chains and the
production particularly the supply
chains this allows countries to hold one
another sort of to ransom essentially
and we saw that when uh China halted
critical exports as the trade war
intensifies and so we absolutely see
this going on um as a new context that
really puts this geopolitical calculus
front and center.
I just want to give you a sort of a
couple of examples and so drones I think
are an important case in point. Um as
many of you know the war in Ukraine is
perhaps one of the first wars that has
been fought um around both the
sophisticated technology of drones but
frankly many of the drones being used
are hobbyist drones that have been sort
of adapted and changed. And so the real
opportunity here is both the innovation
that's happening but also the ability to
produce at scale. And yet the U the
Ukraine has found itself caught in the
middle of the US China trade hostilities
because it can't get all the parts that
it needs. And you might say, well, isn't
uh you know Ukraine getting its parts
from the United States for the the
drones or or from Europe? And the answer
turns out to basically be no. In the
work I did jointly with Edin Lavine,
you'll see this chart on the right that
basically says, well, is this inevitable
that every single one of the drone
components can basically largely only be
sourced at scale in China? And so we
sort of work backwards and say, well,
perhaps that's just because that's where
they were invented. And it turns out
that's not the case. That the ingenuity
and the origin of many of these ideas
was in the US, in Japan, uh, in Europe.
And yet now we've seen that sort of move
to the production of those things at
scale um, in China. And so this has
become, you know, very significant
challenge for Ukraine and something that
allied and partner governments are
thinking about very extensively as they
start to think about the sort of the
geopolitics of of that kind of map that
you see on the right hand side. And in
the work that Phil and I have done
understanding the um what's been
happening in Ukraine in terms of drone
design and development, we've absolutely
seen the role of their domestic
innovation ecosystem and them trying to
build up their own domestic industrial
base to actually support uh what they're
doing and certainly winning if you like
from the drone point of view but really
sort of constrained uh by the sort of
entangled supply chain. So this is a
sort of interesting case that reminds us
that at least in technology that's
relevant in defense. This is a big
challenge to deal with. Now most of our
organizations many of your corporations
will say look I'm not making defense
technology so this really doesn't apply
to me. But I want to sort of suggest
that with the role of economic
statecraft actually this is something
that most of our corporations really are
going to have to worry about. And we see
statecraftraft as having sort of two
faces. One is industrial policy that is
how are our governments trying to
support domestic industries that they
think is strategic. There's certainly a
sort of a playbook around more market
support and so on. I think that is
potentially quite powerful um and
requirements though for an industrial
base that is more domestic and more
resilient but also tools like export
controls, foreign investment provisions,
limits to foreign IP licensing. So
definitely a sort of entanglement
um of tools that we now have to
understand and and put into you know our
calculus as we think about making
important strategic decisions in our in
our boardrooms and in our senior
leadership team. And on the other side
we see statecraft as a sort of form of
foreign policy. And so that is
absolutely includes things like tariffs
and sanctions and limited limits to
outward capital flows as well as really
reframing economic relationships with
allies and partners. that is
particularly obviously at the moment a m
a moving uh target but something just
really worth thinking through. And I
want to just sort of leave us with a a a
couple of examples to say this is not
just for those uh organizations that are
thinking about traditional technologies
of defense and security that in fact
economic security is now seen across
this whole spectrum of technologies
whether it is sort of energy
technologies uh the technologies for
health and well-being so uh the life
sciences um whether it is you know some
of the most sort of fundamental
foundational technologies like
semiconductors and future quantum
computers. And so the the technological
landscape
that is going to be subject to this
economic statecraft I think is extremely
wide. And so let me just give you an
example. So if you were out there you
know as an entrepreneurial company this
is really something that you know we
never used to teach our startup
entrepreneurs to think about
geopolitics. We said have a great idea
build your company get the best talent
money market opportunities manufacturing
around the globe. and and we said to
them, look, really just try to be as
quick and as costefficient as possible.
But now the calculus is shifting. A
company like Commonwealth Fusion
Systems, a fusion energy company spun
out of MIT, um I shall never forget, you
know, visiting them with um a quite
senior member of a of a national
intelligence um organization who said to
them, "Have you thought about the threat
from hostile state actors?" And you
could see and this was many years ago
when this was a real startup
Commonwealth Fusion team looking a
little bit startled. Um but very quickly
having to deal with the fact that some
of their core technology like the high
temperature superconducting magnets you
know much of the provision of that
technology and that tape that they
needed for their core component this
extraordinary tokomeac was initially
only available at any quantity in Russia
and having to really sort of think about
those dynamics and I've recently done
some work again with my colleague Edelyn
and and others Dan and and Rory really
sort of raising the question will we
lose the race for fusion energy not
because we haven't actually built the
innovation ecosystem for the core
technology but because we haven't
actually attended to the wider supply
chain of some of those absolutely core
inputs and so if you're in industries
like um you know whether it be sort of
isotopes or power electronics then these
things really are going to matter as you
build your business and as you support
these emerging industries of the future
unless we think that this is really a
topic that um is only for startups and
their investors to worry about. I I want
to come back to the fact that large
corporations are also thinking about
this. Boardrooms that I spend time in,
this is very very high up on the agenda.
There are lots of examples that we could
talk about. Some of them are
confidential. So I don't want to do
that. But I do want to give you um just
a sense of this if you put in your mind
right the fact that you know
particularly engagement with China but
also more broadly you know an
organization like Apple right has a
trade war problem that investors can't
ignore increasingly there are indices um
of corporate exposure to countries
through their supply chains and
manufacturing that just provides more
sort of geopolitical vulnerability and
as a large corporation as you think
about making acquisitions around the
world to tap into those global
ecosystems. Where are those countries?
How should you be thinking about that?
How do you think about the talent? What
about the sources of capital? And also,
how do you think about markets? So,
which markets do you want to participate
in? And that's before we layer on this
extremely moving target of tariffs. But
it very much I think is part and parcel
of you know a really different I think
set of conversations that we haven't had
in boardrooms in investment committees
you know in um in startup communities
really I think for decades or frankly
ever of this particular type. And so as
we start to try to sort of put the
ecosystem innovation ecosystem logic and
that logic of the sort of global
industrial base and industrial clusters
into this new geopolitical context, I
think we absolutely need this
geopolitical calculus. Um as I say in
our boardrooms and elsewhere, this is
not just a calculus that is for
government officials. It's absolutely
one for corporate leaders and
entrepreneurial leaders. And we have to
think about our sources of talent and
the location of those ideas. the capital
where we get that from manufacturing
choices, supply chains, customer base.
And so really in a sense our entire
strategic approach is going to have to
be sort of read through this rather
different and distinctive calculus. And
this is something that I think
simultaneously is a new and important
challenge. It's something that the
universities themselves, MIT included,
have to think about very very deeply as
we continue to build and support our
institution as a global institution. But
also we want to help organizations like
yours I think in really understanding
this and be part of that journey uh that
you're going on to really sort of shape
you know this intersection between
corporate innovation and geopolitics.
So I think having that calculus in the
boardroom matters today more than ever
frankly because I think these
geopolitical dynamics are here to stay.
They are dynamics and they are changing
at a pace that I think is is almost
unprecedented and that means that
decisions around innovation,
industrialization, investment, you know,
all being made in this ever changing
context and so we have to really sort of
understand that I think and I hope that
we can be part of supporting your
discussions and your debates uh in those
activities.
And so with that, thank you. I'm going
to stop sharing.
Thank you so much Fiona. Um
>> a big topic for a short amount of time.
So I hope that um I managed to get in
enough but not too much for everybody.
Thank you everyone.
>> Well, we're not finished with you. So so
so stay around. Um but yes, it's always
fascinating to hear what you have to say
and and these days it's become so much
more complex and and that you're across
that is is wonderful. You know, I
reflect every morning as I read the
headlines. you mentioned the New York
Times um about how much and how rapidly
the world is changing again. I was
finishing my doctorate in aeronautics
and astronautics as the cold war was
ending. So that was the last big shift.
And I remember thinking then that the
road ahead was sunny as far as one could
see. And it it just if if you need a
reminder of just how complex the world
remains, stubbornly complex, we just
need to hear what you just had to say.