Thank thank you all for being here and
for having me. I apologize for the raspy
voice. I think I'm caught between the
cold weather and having so many meetings
over the past week that at the end of
Friday I was I was in worse shape. So
I'm I'm doing better. Uh and it's great
to be here and to tell you about
manufacturing. Uh we've launched a new
initiative at MIT focused on
manufacturing called the initiative for
new manufacturing. And in the time we
have, I'll share the details of that
with you wrapped within a perspective of
where I see manufacturing today and uh
hopefully where it is headed going
forward. And I welcome your feedback and
comments and questions uh as well.
So let's think about manufacturing.
Let's think about how physical products
are made. And I love Lego bricks.
Perhaps the most
high volume product across the history
of the world in terms of being, you
know, similar in its size and shape. And
imagine what it would take to describe
to someone how a Lego brick is made.
Maybe you know that it's made by
injection molding,
injecting molten plastic into a metal
cavity. uh and you know while it be
straightforward to tell that to someone
to provide the dimensions in the 3D CAD
model it would be a lot harder perhaps
impossible in in one stream of
communication to explain how to achieve
the tolerances the accuracy the surface
finish and all the things needed to
make the Lego brick have the
capabilities that an ordinary Lego brick
has so many times times over. And then
imagine what it would take to describe
how to make a smartphone. The incredible
information
content density
that's embedded in the materials, the
components, the supply chains, the
software and so on and everything that
works in synchrony together. So my point
is that
perhaps obviously ma manufacturing is
hard and in a way I feel the next
generation of manufacturing or the
emergent generation of manufacturing is
about understanding how to build an
equilibrium between
knowledge,
technology,
data and of course humans. And that
applies to all industries, all products,
all sizes of companies, uh, and arguably
all geographies.
Now, we're also, in my opinion, in a
very interesting time for manufacturing,
both domestically here in the US and
worldwide.
The world is always growing and
manufacturing as a result is always
growing because we need more stuff. uh
and manufacturing advances our daily
lives in so many ways.
But specifically here in the US, I feel
we're at a time where more so than in
perhaps one or two generations, there's
a renewed interest in the importance of
manufacturing to our economy, to our
national security, and to a sense of of
of accomplishment in our society. And
that statement is not political from one
angle to the other. It's it's it's
broadly recognized and that's reflected
by, you know, corporate interest in
building more manufacturing here. That
said, if you look to this report from
the United Nations in 2024, there's also
a prediction that manufacturing is going
to continue to grow and concentrate in
Asia, specifically in China. This
prediction is that manufacturing in
China by 2030 will be an astounding 45%
of the total value added worldwide. And
so we have to keep in mind that
manufacturing is this dynamic balance.
And how do we insert new technologies?
How do we build new companies? How do we
evolve established companies from small
to large to help craft this
continued improvement of the quality,
the efficiency, the capabilities of
products that are manufactured.
looking now with a with a slightly
tighter lens to the status of things
here in the US. Regardless of the
decline in manufacturing that's happened
in in total volume over the past 20 to
30 years, the US is still the world's
second largest manufacturing economy.
And as evidence of the importance of
manufacturing to the country,
manufacturers perform over half of
private sector R&D. And every dollar
of value created in manufacturing, every
job created has a multiplier effect. $3
more added to the economy and five more
employees hired. And and all these
questions always have to be evaluated in
a business context. uh in in other
contexts but manufacturing is a huge
multiplier. It's kind of the hourglass
uh is the tightest part in the in the
value and we often look at the value
from production overall and real must
realize it casts value upstream as well
as downstream. And on the right side uh
the two charts express the the dilemma
that we face particularly in the US but
I think in in in certain parts of the
world outside of the US. The fact that
on aggregate if you look across
industries and you look at many but not
all industries productivity uh
manufacturing value add per unit of
labor has more or less stagnated for the
past 15 years. And at the same time, we
don't have enough new
individuals, young people entering the
manufacturing workforce. There are a
number of reasons for this
transition from the era of lean
manufacturing to an era of technology
adoption,
offshoring, you know, declining
expertise and the lack of sufficiently
broad awareness that manufacturing is an
exciting, technology-rich, rewarding
long-term career. But we really need to
confront this dilemma, confronts this
juxtiposition if we are able to
contribute to at MIT and elsewhere
building a next generation of
manufacturing and going from labs to
practice and classrooms to broader
audiences which is what I'll talk about.
And we need in a way more examples like
this. Right? I'll use this
example of the SpaceX rocket engine to
articulate a broader point. Over several
years, SpaceX has
built a high performance culture of
quick iteration, rapid cycles of
learning that uses advanced
manufacturing technologies to quickly
iterate from one version to the next.
This example is using 3D printing at
scale to enable more and more of their
rocket engine to be optimized for higher
performance for lower cost. And you see
this kind of transformation right from
complexity to
simplicity in a in a general sense. So
how do we in a way do more with less or
do more with new approaches?
And that's in
a way the goal of the MIT initiative for
new manufacturing which we launched in
May of 2025 about six months ago. And
this is like MIT's other strategic
initiatives uh an MITwide effort
bringing together research education and
partnerships here to focus on
manufacturing that meets metrics that we
can call verifiably new. By new
manufacturing, we don't mean only brand
new manufacturing like only creating new
businesses or new factories. Uh while
that's certainly a part of it, we mean
infusing new technology uh evolved
organizational approaches into industry
through our classrooms, through our
research, and through our partnerships.
And this initiative, as I'll describe
today, is broad. It stretches across
campus and is focused not on one
technology domain or another, but as
enabler for MIT to make more impact in
manufacturing through the lens of
industry verticals from semiconductors
to biio manufacturing to the built
environment as well as addressing
crosscutting themes like the deployment
of AI and databased approaches in
organizations in manufacturing
addressing the hard problems while
trying to sort of set the stage for the
future.
Why is MIT doing this? Well, you know,
well, well, my opening words said, well,
kind of the time is now, and that's very
much the case. It's because
manufacturing is in MIT's DNA, right?
MIT's motto is mind in hand, right?
Combining the theory with the practice.
And from MIT's origins, rooted in
industrial practice and creating value
for industry, manufacturing has been
there. Today there's research in
manufacturing across all departments and
arguably all of the schools in a
different way. Uh from automation for
chemical synthesis to fast ways to 3D
print new furniture, advanced materials
processing and of course studying
the emergent embodiment of AI and how to
adopt technology. There's also a history
of MIT doing landmark studies such as
the machine that changed the world which
is the study that brought
lean manufacturing and an understanding
of lean manufacturing to
the world through working closely with
the domestic and Japanese auto industry
or the production the innovation economy
study about 10 years ago where we asked
and affirmed the question uh Is
manufacturing necessary for innovation?
In other words, product and process
innovation go so deeply handinand. And
of course, in MIT's DNA, and one reason
you all are here today is MIT's emphasis
on taking technology to the world
through industry partnerships and
through startup companies. And I've seen
in my 12 years on the faculty here an
immense growth in student and faculty
interest in not only creating
manufacturing oriented startups with new
manufacturing technologies and new you
know uh uh productivity approaches but
also in understanding how manufacturing
fits into the critical path to scale of
technologies in energy, biotechnology,
electronics and more
and we started the initiative not by
honestly a a
top level strategic decision of MIT but
bottom up by building a community of
faculty of students with a strong
interest in manufacturing and figuring
out what should MIT do to contribute to
this important need for society and
we've held some really amazing events
hosting Morris Chang, the founder and
CEO of TSMC
uh and also an MIT alum at our launch
event in May with JB Strable, co-founder
of Tesla and now leading Redwood
Materials, which is uh developing a
circular workflow for battery recycling.
Uh and most recently, our event focused
on the defense industrial base with
startup leaders and executives from
established companies.
Now being an MITwide initiative, the INM
is one of a handful of strategic
initiatives and perhaps you've heard
about these if not today in another
venue. Reporting into the provost and
the president is a family of initiatives
including MIT's climate project, the
health and life sciences collaborative
called heels and the genative AI
consortium which goes by the acronym
magic. And the initiative for new
manufacturing for INM is in that family
and as a result of its centrality you
could say as a strategic initiative
means we have by definition an MITwide
mandate and MITwide reach and I'm one of
four faculty co-leads alongside Suzanne
Burer an institute professor and
political scientist Chris Love professor
in chemical engineering with a
particular focus on biio manufacturing
and professor Karen Zang who's a
professor in the Sloan School of
Management and focus on supply chains.
And our steering committee, our kind of
internal advisory board is chaired by
Paula Hammond, executive vice provost
and Rick Lockach, the dean of the Sloan
School of Management. And I go through
this to to to to articulate how for MIT
manufacturing is an institutewide effort
and the uh real impact I think will come
through collaboration between
disciplines, technology and social
sciences, technology and management. uh
and let us therefore make impact and
educate students across scales.
We have four themes uh four crosscutting
themes again uh agnostic to industry
manufacturing technologies and systems
elevating productivity and experience
scaling new manufacturing as I defined
earlier on and transforming the
manufacturing base. Collectively, these
speak to
work in our labs, bringing work from lab
to market, understanding how
technologies and humans work together
more effectively to increase
productivity to amplify human capability
as well as intentionally addressing
enterprises at all scales, small,
medium, large enterprises across the
manufacturing ecosystem in the US and
beyond. We have a number of program
areas and I'll highlight a few of those
for you today. The first is what we're
calling new manufacturing research and
this is a look at at uh exemplars in
manufacturing across industries and then
look into what questions can MIT answer
to help uncover best practices and help
learn how technology and organizations
go together in the future. So in a very
quick fashion, some things we've learned
through different studies are, for
example, what makes the latest electric
vehicle companies such as Tesla and
Rivian in the US unique. Well, here are
examples where manufacturing is achieved
uh at a worldclass level, it takes some
time, but by building brand new
manufacturing, by building new plants,
and there's a huge emphasis on
softwaredefined manufacturing. These
companies and their veterans who've
dispersed across other industries talk
about the role of software and
automation in enabling rapid changes to
products and process.
Back to Lego, right? I talked about the
Lego brick at the beginning. Here you
have, you know, from an architecture
perspective, something much less complex
than an electric vehicle, but incredible
efficiency in quality in supply chain
and exacting tolerances for simple
products, but uniformity of those
capabilities across a global supply
chain with regional nodes. And it's very
interesting to learn how
LEGO goes from idea to production,
combines the market need with the
capability of their supply chain to
ultimately create products that define
new experiences.
There are also industries such as craft
brewing that are more like local modular
manufacturing. The craft brewing
industry, which has grown significantly
in the US over the past decade, is an
example of local economies in action.
There are 8,000 or more craft breweries
of beer in the US. Essentially a modular
biio manufacturing process. And here you
have examples of short adaptable supply
chains and flexibility and agility to
change market demands.
And last but not least, uh our
colleagues at Sloan, including Professor
Fiona Murray, have taken a deep dive
into drone technology and in particular
how the example of the conflict between
Ukraine and Russia also reveals very
interesting insights about innovation
ecosystems, right? the fact that lowcost
drones largely lean on the established
supply chains in China uh and the
ability to interchange standard
components and core technologies makes
innovation so affordable and so rapid
and there's interesting questions of
what happens in the next generation of
this model how big could the scale get
and how could this model be applied or
be be incompatible with uh development
of other other products going forward
forward
and I also pause and reflect on you know
the power of new companies to uh
take new perspectives on established
technologies and industries. So I know
you'll hear about many uh great startups
in the next session through the startup
exchange. Uh a company I've gotten to
know over the past uh year or so uh is
focused on metal casting. uh metal
casting being one of the you know
largest uh manufacturing processes for
making parts ranging from like jet
engine turbine blades to drain covers on
the street. uh and uh a very young
company called Fabri started by Steven
Davis who's a recent bachelor's graduate
from mechanical engineering who's did
some internships in the space industry
is attempting to reimagine the workflow
for metal casting combining established
expertise right folks who know how to
cast metal parts and know all the
problems that can't be written down
easily with a digital workflow 3D
printing of a model what's called the
core for the investment casting process
as well as advanced simulation that
allows them to simulate the casting
process before they make a single part.
And the company is very early in its
journey, but it's an example of this
combination of new and old that I feel
is very beautiful. And they're able to
significantly shorten the time it takes
to go from input from a company to the
finished part and therefore push the
existing supply chain.
So combining uh all of these examples
right we're looking at what are the
crosscutting themes right there's no one
example for how manufacturing works
across different industries but we can
learn a lot from the comparison and the
limit cases between examples right where
is manufacturing going giga where is
manufacturing going micro or going
modular and more deployed and what is
the balance between you know uh to use
you know defense techn technology as an
example here between the multi-deade
engineering flagships and agile
innovation quick iteration and we feel
there's a number of crosscutting themes
to be studied financial models firm and
industry structure how knowledge is
centralized and distributed and what co
limits the pace of innovation and the
adoption of new manufacturing
technologies
without more details one of our initial
activities in the in the INM M has been
to fund a series of white papers to fund
faculty to define and answer questions
related to for instance how can
automation team with humans for high
mixed low volume production in
activities such as repair and
maintenance or how are large firms
viewing decarbonization these days and
the business value of it uh and
combining you know profitability
emission measure measurement, corporate
strategy and pol policy uh incentives
and these white papers and others will
be published as a collection in the
first half of 2026.
We also have a deep focus on education
and workforce uh both on campus and to
broader audiences which I feel is an
increasingly important part of MIT's
core mission.
We've looked systematically at a span of
education and manufacturing from campus
to the workforce at scale. Uh so we of
course have courses and degree programs
on campus in mechanical engineering. Our
students make a 100 yo-yos uh each uh
and go through the whole design to
manufacturing process. And we have
workforce training programs focused on
community college audiences. Dr. John
Louu leads the Techamp program which is
deploying out into a network of
community colleges in the United States
uh and hoping to take nationwide. And
alongside of the traditional way of
teaching manufacturing hands-on which I
feel should never go away, we have to
think of how we can bring more
visualization
digital rich content into students and
out to broader audiences. So there's big
efforts on using augmented and virtual
reality to for instance enable students
whether at MIT or halfway around the
world to do virtual product disassembly.
Uh and on the bottom right which comes
here uh
virtual machine shop training. So this
is an activity that we're prototyping in
our machine shop where before our
undergraduates
step into the shop and learn to use a
milling machine as first or second year
undergrads they take a virtual training
and they're able to follow instructions
and go through a process flow and also
fail also make mistakes and uh we think
that's a really interesting new paradigm
also to study the pedagogy of we have a
a large course in mechi focused on AI
and machine learning for engineering
design. So not just manufacturing but
design and colleagues uh such as
professor Brian Anthony who've developed
a kit-based approach for kind of
portable learning of AIdriven datadriven
manufacturing principles. This FRED
device stands for fiber extrusion
device. So, it uses the extrusion of
polymer fiber as a test bed to
understand and control manufacturing
processes where a group of students
could have this $200 kit sitting next to
them or it could be remotely connected
through the internet.
So, as I move toward uh the end here, my
last section is a short perspective on
where AI is headed for design and
manufacturing. uh and we uh wrote a
perspective in 2024
which you can look up here on where we
feel AI is headed from the current state
which is moving very quickly to a future
state where artificial intelligence is
multimodal involves you know real-time
data text images video and also combines
with simulation engineering tools and
human knowledge and outlined a series of
capabilities that we hope in the future
AI could be impactful for throughout the
design and manufacturing workflow. And a
related question uh that is being
actively researched today is how can we
develop AI models for manufacturing
environments within companies or across
supply chains that enable secure cross
learning? Can we take advantage of
federated learning approaches to train
uh local models and then contribute to
global models that can advance
collective understanding of
manufacturing processes? Could the
injection molding company of the future
rapidly identify their process
conditions by subscribing to a global
model that would be that would learn
from data sources without breaking the
security of that data.
And there's many examples of research
across the spectrum at MIT. work on
creating virtual quality sensors uh
that's deployed to manufacturing
facilities. Automating sequence planning
for assembly operations,
work on robotics from collaborative
robotics to
dextrous manipulation uh as well as
developing physics-based digital twins
for biioarma for automated manufacturing
processes and so on. So it's a very very
rich area where I feel we can contribute
a lot going forward and you may so know
know some of this research already. An
example from my own work uh connected to
my lab's expertise in 3D printing or
additive manufacturing is an effort to
use a machine learning driven pipeline
to identify aluminum alloys that are
uniquely suited for use in 3D printing.
And we discovered a set of alloys that
appear to have higher strength than
established conventional aluminum
alloys. And importantly, uh the
discovery process included manufacturing
constraints upstream. So we're able to
start with 500,000 combinations, right?
a number that you the human mind or
manual uh computation couldn't handle
and ended with a small number of
candidates and only one that we tested
and verified at the end with actual 3D
printing and we're also working with
professor Fiazamemed's group who was the
lead author of that perspective on how
we can train multimodal models to uh
help in the reverse engineering process.
Can AI generate and recognize parametric
CAD data? Very important in an
engineering and manufacturing process
such that we could have a tool that can
scan any arbitrary 3D geometry like a
bracket or a gear and create a
parametric CAD model that is editable
that can be re-engineered, can be
scaled, can be remanufactured. And we
haven't quite sliced that problem yet,
but we've made important progress to
date.
This huge footprint and enthusiasm in uh
AI for manufacturing has prompted us to
identify a set of themes
manufacturing focused robotics agentic
AI for manufacturing process
intelligence control knowledge synthesis
from multimodal data uh and the
remaining list and issue a call for
proposals across MIT where we got about
50 ideas in a span of three weeks. and
we're going to be able to through the
initiative fund about 8 to 10 projects
uh and then you'll hear more about those
if you follow us going forward. And last
but not least, I apologize for the
perhaps overt plug, but we do have a
very uh
fundamental way that we're working with
industry within the manufacturing
initiative and that's through a
consortium structure. We have seven
founding members that we announced in
July and the members of the
manufacturing initiative are engaging in
all the activities I describe and more.
The support from those companies has
directly informed the themes that we
identified for AI and automation
research. The companies are deeply
engaged in education and workforce
development and participating in
deployment of the technologist program
at their manufacturing sites and
dialogue with the companies is informing
our research and providing opportunities
to meet with and recruit students. So
I'm very happy to hear if you have
comments, questions on the initiative as
well as ways that we might be able to
understand your needs and explore how to
work together. Uh, and I'll stop there
and if time permits would love to take a
question or two. One question.
>> I'm going to take the first one. Uh,
thank you anonymous. How does computer
simulated virtual training videos
improve over standard video training? So
that's actually a question we are we are
focused on answering doing the research
to say between a cohort of individuals
who've done the ARVR training and then
the conventional training versus just
the conventional training is the
knowledge retention is the ability to
solve problems is the time it takes just
to get through it all different and are
there statistical significancees and
differences or not and and and maybe the
answer is you know some things are are
are improved and some things are not
improved for our uh our our less
can the US onshore manufacturing be
competed on global marketplace I think
so but not in all categories the new
manufacturing is not the manufacturing
of old and it's not that everything can
and should come back it's about
technologydriven manufacturing to
differentiate and to enable more
productive output uh and that's a a
question that uh you know we're just
starting to to think about as
Thank you.
[applause]