How do we learn what we know? That
includes how to talk, how to walk, how
to read, how to do math, science,
history. They were either in your genes
when you were born or you learned them
through the experiences that [music]
changed who you are. So what do we want
from learning? We want to know how to
predict the future on the basis of past
[music] experience. And we also want to
imbue the world with meaning. There are
two kinds of learning that we can think
about. One is called associative
learning. Learning where one thing
predicts [music] another thing. A
simpler form of learning is
nonassociative learning that simply
increases or decreases [music] our
response to something in our
environment. So one form of simple
nonassociative learning is habituation
where [music] we reduce our response to
a repeated environmental stimulus. Let's
say you move into an apartment which has
much more street traffic than [music]
you used to. At first the noises wake
you up but over time you get used to it
or you habituate to it and you respond
less to that noise and get a better
night's sleep.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.