So today we're going to turn from the
analytics and the positive analysis of
international trade to the normative
analysis of international trade and
we're bring our tools of welfare
analysis to thinking about how we
evaluate International Trade okay so
we're going to we're going to start by
talking about the welfare
impacts of trade of international trade
and how we how that helps us think about
the debate over free trade now we showed
L what we're going to start with is the
standard model and the standard model is
going to show us that free trade
unambiguously raises social welfare and
the intuition I'll do that I'll do the
graphics in a second the intuition is
pretty clear which is international
trade allows for New
Opportunities where people value Goods
at more than what they cost to produce
anytime you have a new
opportunity where which allows people to
value a good at more than it's produced
you raise welfare it's that simple so
let's actually see it graphically let's
go to the market for
Roses okay in figure 191 we have the
market for Roses under artari remember
our word for no trade you've got and let
me be very clear this figure and the
figure show so now doing National trade
we have to be very clear on what kind of
figure we're looking at this is the
figure for the US Rose Market okay we're
going to look at different figures
different countries and different Goods
so it's important to keep track this is
the figure for the US Rose Market and
this is in figure 191 we have what's
that market look like before trade well
before trade you have um a domestic
demand for
roses a domestic supply for Roses you
get a equilibrium Price p
a and an equilibrium quantity
QA and you end up with a consumer and
producer surplus of the type we derived
a few lectures ago in a standard Mark in
a standard
market now let's imagine we open up to
international trade and let's imagine
that tra comparative advantage is such
that the US Imports
roses remember last time we're talking
about a two good model like computers
and Roses now we're just focusing on the
market for Roses but let's say that two
good model delivered the outcome that
the US would import roses as it implied
last time what would that
do well Imports do not affect domestic
demand and Supply domestic demand has
not changed people still want roses
domestic supply has not changed the
marginal cost of producing a rose has
not changed just because we can now
import them from Colombia what's changed
is the is the equilibrium price which is
now essentially we have lowered the
price by incorporating a new source of
outside
Supply okay another way you could do
this it's not you know you could ask
where's this new line come from Imagine
you could if you want imagine a new line
which is below the domestic supply line
which is domestic plus International
Supply that would be a line parallel to
the red line and that would intersect
domestic demand at the price PW so think
of a new supply curve below that but
that's not really true so we don't draw
it but that's sort of a way to think
about how we get to this new price that
by allowing in cheap roses you've
lowered the price and basically people
canot have more roses so now at that new
price people want C subt roses at that
new lower International Trade price
people want C subt
roses
okay um uh and now we're going to assume
that world Supply
here's an important assumption okay this
is a very important assumption often
made in trade models World Supply is
perfectly elastic with respect to
domestic markets let me restate that
we're assuming that world
Supply is perfectly elastic with respect
to domestic markets that is this is what
we typically call a small open economy
model small country open economy model
we're assuming the US is so small that
demand from the US can't actually affect
the the underlying supply of roses now
that's not true for many markets us is
that big but for but just think about a
case where the US is a small enough
share of the World Market that basically
it's a bunch of that it's basically like
facing uh a a a perfectly uh uh a market
with a perfectly competitive perfectly
elastic supply curve so basically the
production the key point is we're going
to assume the production of roses in the
US doesn't impact world supp supp and
that's probably true in roses right
because we're small we're small producer
of roses so how many Ros are us produced
didn't really matter for World Supply
it's certainly not true in computers and
it's sort of unclear about oil okay you
know most oil comes from outside the
world we do produce some oil here in the
US but for Rose it's a pretty fair
assumption it's pretty fair to assume
that the domestic supply of roses is
Trivial Rel to the world supply of roses
so we get this flat supply curve so what
do we get well the US consumers now want
that should be a q by the way um uh that
should be a q subt uh so the US the US
consumers now want that change that to
from CCT to Q subt the US consumers now
want Q sub T
roses okay but at that new low price
domestic producers don't want to supply
cupt remember domestic producers have to
respect their supply curve they only
want to produce where price equals Mar
marginal cost so they're going to
produce Q subt oh I'm sorry that's what
I got backwards yes I'm sorry that is C
subt that's what I miss scratch what I
said earlier C subt is domestic quantity
demanded Q subt is domestic quantity
produced that's what I got wrong so
leave at C subt I was wrong about that Q
subt is domestic quantity supplied C
subt is domestic quantity
demanded okay consumers at this new La
price low price want C subt producers
want to produce Q subt what's the
difference the difference is the roses
that come from other countries which we
call
Imports so the Dynamics
are we open the market to
Colombia because of that the price of
roses
Falls at that lower price consumers want
see subt
roses producers only want produce Q subt
roses what's the difference the ones we
import from Columbia okay questions
about
that got understand that basic graph
because now we're going to use that to
look at
welfare now let's go to figure 193 and
think about what are the welfare impacts
of this trade
well here what we have is initially we
start with domestic Supply and domestic
demand before trade we have QA roses
being sold in the US at a price PA so
the
pre-trade consumer surplus
before trade the consumer surplus so
under
autarchy consumer surplus is
w and producer Surplus is X Plus
y okay that's a producer consumer
surplus before there's
trade now we open up to trade what
happens under Trade is now consumers get
to consume C subt so consumer surplus is
now
W plus
x w + x plus
Z consumer surplus is is W plus X Plus
Z producer Surplus has fallen all the
way to
Y okay so basically what we've done is
by expanding the trade we we've done two
things we've transferred
X from producers to
Consumers but we've added
Z so welfare has gone up it's the
opposite of the Dead weight loss case
the dead weight loss case it with a
minimum wage or other regulation
restrictions we would transfer but we'd
have an efficiency loss in that transfer
here's a transfer with an efficiency
gain this the opposite of those cases
remember before whenever you saw
transfers before they came along with
deadweight losses here's a transfer that
comes along with the Dead We with the
gain okay we've now transferred X to
Consumers but also given them Z so
consumers
win by a lot and producers
lose okay and that's the welfare
analysis of international trade of
imports questions about
that consumers win producers lose
consumers win because they get a ton of
cheap
roses consu producers lose because they
lose that production
to
colia now of course International Trade
consists of both imports and exports
let's look at
exports so now let's turn to the market
for
computers okay now we have a 194
computers now here we're gonna we're
going to continue to assume World
supplies in perfectly elastic that's
probably wrong the US is big enough to
affect the mark for computers but let's
just assume the US is small for a second
makes life much easier
so what happens is we're initially in
autarchy at Point Q sub a p sub
a now the US says we're going to send a
bunch of the computers we're making in
the US and send them to
Colombia what does that do that means
that there's fewer computers in the US
so the price goes
up okay Supply there's less Supply in
the US the supply curve hasn't changed
underlying marginal costs haven't
changed it's just that they're taking
some of those
computers that they used to produce for
the US and produced for columia as a
result you move up the supply curve to
the new higher price PW that's the new
higher price once you open up to trade
that's good for the computer producers
they can now sell to more
people so now at that higher
price okay producers want to produce cup
te but consumers only want CES sub te we
flipped it consumers now want to produce
Q subt the price is up they don't
produce a lot of computers consumers are
like look computers are more expensive I
don't want the
computers so you end up with Q subt
being
produced C subt being domestically
demanded and the difference is
exports so it's the flip case okay for
imports we open up Columbia they lower
the price of roses you end up with more
cons consumers wanting more roses than
the producers willing to produce you get
Imports with exports we open Market to
Colombia producers in the US produce
fewer computers raise the price goes up
so you have more computers being
produced than people want so prod few
computers they raise the price because
they can sell at a higher price in the
World Market you have more computers
being produced than people want and you
up with exports now what's the welfare
analysis of exports this is quite
interesting let's go to figure
195 okay under
autarchy what is the consumer surplus
well under art tarkey the consumer
surplus is w+
X and what is the producer Surplus it's
y now what happens under Trade well
under Trade you move from PA to PW so
consumer surplus shrinks it's only
W consumers aren't getting as much
Surplus because they're paying more for
computers but what's producer Surplus
now well it's X Plus y + z
so we have the flip case now we've
transferred Surplus from consumers to
producers and producers have also gotten
Z so it's a transfer with a
gain you've got consumers losing by X
producers winning by X Plus Z total
social welfare goes up by the area
Z so this is kind of bizarre if you
think about it Imports increase social
welfare and exports increase social
welfare it's kind of crazy but it's true
basically both are true because you are
creating gains from trade by opening up
to New
Market so in either case you get gain
you get welfare increases from
trade this is the fundamental analytics
of international trade that economists
grow up with okay it's whispered to us
at bedtime okay okay free trade is good
why is free trade good free trade is
good because it opens up new
possibilities for welfare improving
trades it opens up new possibilities for
people who value a good to get it at
above what it cost to produce it full
stop okay now you might say well that is
great we know everybody listens to
Economist of course so that seems the
end of the problem but in fact it's not
in fact if you follow the news at all
you'll know that this is not necessarily
a consensus view that there's a lot of
debate in the policy world and in the
economics World about trade
policy there's a lot of debate about
trade policy let's start with the
simplest
case Imports are a job
killer Imports are a job killer why are
Imports a job killer well because since
we are growing more rows than Columbia I
and fewer here producer Surplus is down
fewer roses are grown in the US so fewer
Rose workers are needed so they get
fired there were presumably thousands of
people employed in producing Ros in the
US that now no longer have a job because
we get them from
Colombia so as a result people say we
should limit Imports because they're
killing American jobs they always use
the word kill it's very violent they're
not you know taking away their Killing
American jobs okay so we should that's
the that we should have some limitation
trade policy okay so basically for
example we could impose a tariff I
mentioned this earlier in the course a
tariff is a tax on imported goods so we
could say that any roses that come from
Columbia we will tax them so it's a a
tariff is a specific tax on import
well as I'll show you in a minute but I
think your intuition could tell you
already this turns out to be a bad idea
because while it does help producers it
hurts consumers more and to see that
let's go to figure
196 now we're back to the market for
Roses the red and blue lines are
autarchy under World Trade we went down
to
PW and we imported Q the difference
between q1 and C1 okay slightly
different slightly different magnitudes
here so once again Under World Trade
went from the initial equilibrium down
to PW producers only produced q1 so a
lot of jobs got lost consumers wanted
see1 see had a lot of
imports now we impose a tariff well what
does a tariff do it raises the price of
columia specific roses
in particular if the Tariff was the was
the exact difference between P PT I'm
sorry between between the initial price
it's not marked here but PA where the
red and blue lines intersect if the
Tariff was the actual difference between
PA the initial the autarchy
price and the world price then you'd
shut down Imports there' be no reason to
import them because you get them from
the same price in the US but that's an
unting case uninteresting case let's
imagine a tariff but it's not quite as
big as the differ
between the price the world price and
the US price so a tariff now of an of an
amount that raises the price from PW to
PT we put in a tariff but it's not
enough to wipe out Colombia's Advantage
it just reduces Columbia's
advantage and why is that a shift up of
the line because essentially we've done
is we've made the imported roses more
expensive so that raises the price those
imported roses face so we move now to
PT okay and we move to New equilibrium
where consumers consume fewer roses
C2 producers in the US remember it's a
US
diagram producers in the US produce more
roses Q2 and we end up with a smaller
level of imports after tariff the
Imports have shrunk from C1 minus q1 to
C2 minus Q2 questions about the
analytics I know I'm going fast here
this is sort of a new world so please
stop me if there's questions about this
okay now let's look at the let's then
take that and look at the welfare
analysis of
tariffs well now we're going to compare
a world with free trade to a world with
a tariff with free
trade we are at q1 and
C1 with the Tariff we've dropped to Q2
and C2 what has happened well by moving
from Q q1 to
Q2 okay we have increased producer
Surplus by
a make sure you see that produ Surplus
up by a why is produ Surplus up by a
because the price is up from PW to PT
and they're selling more roses produc
Surplus is up by
a consumer
surplus however has
fallen by b c consumer I'm sorry so
consumer surplus has
Fallen um by uh by all of uh AB C and D
consumer surplus is down by the entire
trapezoid
ABCD that's all come out of consumer
surplus that's all sales that were under
the demand curve above the price that
are now gone okay so can people see that
whole trapezoid I've added four letters
but it's really just one trapezoid that
whole trapezoid is
gone okay because that's the area under
the demain cover above the price that's
now no longer there so consumers have
transferred a to producers but they've
lost a plus b plus C plus
d now here's the extra
wrinkle C is different than b and
d
c is not dead weight loss normally say
well if producers didn't gain it and
consumers lost it it's dead weight loss
but what have what have we forgotten
here what's the other party in play here
why is this not a deadweight loss rather
a transfer and who's it a transfer to
yeah the government yeah it's a transfer
to the government because the tarist
rais money give her a high five there
she got it okay because the government
raised money all right the government
raises money by this tariff and that's
another transfer so essentially and the
amount of money the government raises is
what well the amount of remaining
Imports C2 minus Q2 times the size of
the Tariff which is the rectangle
C so what's happened here is consumers
have lost
AB c
d producers have gained
a the government has gained C and B plus
d are welfare our dead weight loss so
the Tariff has overall lowered welfare
we are worse
off in order to transfer C to the
government and a to
producers we've given up as well B plus
d so we're worse off so Society is worse
off from restricting that okay so the
fundamental a for trade free trade is
once again a barrier to free trade
lowers welfare this is just a corollary
of the previous proof which show the
free trade maximize welfare well here
we're showing how a barrier to free TR
this is operationalizing how does a
barrier to free trade lower
welfare okay questions about
that now that's why economists like free
trade but it's not the only reason
economists like free trade there's two
there's fundamentally three Arguments
for free trade the first of free trade
is the basic welfare
analysis welfare
maximization the second analysis for
tree
trade is
that when you impose that tariff you're
not done because what's going to happen
then what's Colombia going to
do what's Columbia going to do yeah
on Us's what
computers
remember our welfare was maximized for
exports by opening up the trade to
exports well Colombia is can to say well
screw you got a tariff on my roses I'm G
have a tariff on your computers well I
don't do the example here you should be
able to go back and show yourself how a
Colombian tax tariff on our
exports okay it's going to it's going to
raise the price in Colombia imagine a
Colombian domestic Market just like our
tariff so imagine instead of the market
for roses in the US do the market for
computers and
Colombia what you'll see is a tariff on
us computers will lower the number of
computers sold in Colombia well that
hurts our
producers so by imposing this tariff and
starting a potential trade War which
isn't nearly as cool as it sounds okay
by starting a trade War what we've done
is essentially hurt not only our
consumers we've also hurt our producers
remember the whole idea was to help our
producers but by helping the rose
producers we've now hurt the computer
producers so it's not even clear we
raise producer Surplus at all we clearly
lower consumer surplus it's not clear we
raise producer Surplus at
all okay so first of all the welfare now
is even stronger than you think because
you're missing the fact that if there's
a trade War our exporters get hurt
too second of all what have we forgotten
in our typical American americ
fashion that there's other people out
there in the world that matter
too okay and just as free trade makes us
better it also makes other countries
better so you could redo this whole
analysis I've done you guys have plenty
of free time do it for fun sometime read
this whole analys I've done from
Colombia's perspective and show how
opening up to
trade to the US made Colombia better off
it increased consumer surplus more than
producer Surplus for
computers okay and uh I'm sorry for rce
Consumer for for for yes for computers
and uh and basic and and for Roses uh
Society also is made better off you can
do the same flip of the analysis and
show that free trade helped Columbia too
so even if you don't buy the welfare
maximization argument even if you don't
buy the trade argument if you care at
all about people around the world then
that's another for free trade you're not
only helping us you're helping everyone
else okay I have never seen that as
vividly as when I went to Vietnam I
talked about the Vietnam rice example a
few lectures
ago you know Vietnam was in a really
horrific war with the US and it's an
incredibly moving place to go for that
reason especially people of my
generation live through that war but
they love
Americans and they asked why they said
because we were a desperately poor
starving country until you opened to
free trade in 1994 build Clinton's their
hero when you open a free trade in 1994
and allowed us to export our rice to
America it massively incre our wealth
increased our wealth levels and I saw I
showed you one results of that there was
less child labor in Vietnam but
generally their standard L just went way
up and it really brought home to me this
argument okay which is that we can help
other countries by allowing free trade
too and we shouldn't forget
that okay now this is it this has if you
think about it this kind of smacks of
the
flavor of the Nash model with
non-cooperative and Cooperative
equilibria free trade is a Cooperative
equilibria where we're all better off by
cooperating we're not explicitly forming
a a a uh a cartel but we're cooperating
to allow free trade by lowering barriers
to trade we're making everyone better
off whereas the non Afric Li is wow I
don't want I don't want my guys to lose
job so I'm impose a tariff so you impose
a tariff and we both end up horse off so
this very much feels like Cooperative
versus non-cooperative equilibrium the
Nash model and in fact that's been
realized enough over time that there's
been more and more movement towards free
trade so if you look at the
decades from really World War II all the
way up to about
2007 was a steady movement towards free
trade around the world
there were arrangements and the way that
was done was by a number of rules that
were set up to impose free trade
essentially the world the companies got
together and formed a cartel and they
said look we're going to make sure we
trade fre each other by setting up rules
that don't allow any one country to
impose tariffs and start a trade War so
it's like a unilateral
disarmament among countries there were
agreements there was the World Trade
Organization was set up which it's
trying to promote free trade by setting
rules that uh setting rules that um have
trade be free around countries there was
very importantly in the US NAFTA the
North American Free Trade Agreement
which was once again signed in the
Clinton
Administration okay which established
virtually taror free trade between
Canada the US and
Mexico and a number of other free trade
agreements were negotiated around the
world and once again let me be very
clear what's stunning from my
perspective is that it was Democrats as
well Republicans were into this when I
grew up Democrats were against free
trade Republicans were for it that
changed Bill Clinton really led the
charge so really we had a world where
there was sort of a universal consensus
for free trade okay now I'm not saying I
shouldn't say Universal there was a lot
of movement plenty people are upset
about it for various reasons I remember
my sister graduated univers Chicago in
1999 and Bill Clinton was a presidential
speaker and a bunch of people wouldn't
shake his hand because they didn't like
the free trade deal he'd signed I
thought that was pretty intense so BAS
basically uh it wasn't Universal
agreement but certainly there was a
large move in that direction for many
many decades and that completely
reversed and It reversed it was starting
to reverse pre-co and it's really
reversed
postco okay and basically we are now
moving away from that President Trump
put in a lot of
anti-trade Provisions in particularly a
large tariff on Chinese Goods
and to be honest President Biden has
kept a lot of it I mean he got rid of
some of it but he's kept more than he's
gotten rid of in terms of international
trade restrictions so it's sort of that
we've gone from a cons very rapidly from
a consensus for Inter National trade to
one against and Co made it much much
worse why did Co make it much much worse
because Co exposed the problem with
international trade which is it creates
interdependencies in production chains
you often heard the term supply chain as
a problem what was going wrong during
covid because of free trade we created
production processes that were
integrated around the world and when
trade shut down during covid that's
those Supply process he sort of
collapsed the most Vivid example
semiconductors semiconductors are the
core of every modern thing we own from
our car s phones to now in toilets and
everything okay and I and basically as I
think I mentioned before 75% of all
semiconductors are produced in
Taiwan okay and we couldn't get them all
of a sudden and the us and we saw prices
for cars go through the roof I don't if
you know but during Co prices for cars
went up two or three times it largely
just because of the shortage and
semiconductors okay so now there is
basically uh a lot of people arguing
against free trade and what are their
basic arguments Okay so why do people
oppose free trade well one argument is
the new one I mentioned which is sort of
supply chain
dependencies supply chain dependencies
slash National
Security so the argument is
look if 75% of semiconductors are
produced within 100 miles of China and
we feel that we might go to war with
China we're pretty screwed if we don't
have a domestic semiconductor
industry well how do you make a domestic
semiconductor industry well you can do
two things one is you can tax Chinese
Taiwanese semiconductors but we don't to
do that because Taiwan is an ally of
ours the other thing you could do is you
could subsidize the American
Semiconductor
industry think about the American
Semiconductor industry they are doing
the same analys done marginal cost
marginal benefit they're saying look the
truth is at the price point for
Semiconductor today we can't produce
them cheaply enough so we're just going
to let them come from Taiwan what if he
said to them you know what we'll give
you a bunch of money if we produce
semiconductors and might say well if you
give us enough then we can produce them
even if it's we can't compete
effectively with Taiwan and that's what
we did we set up we passed the chips
plus science act which puts 52 billion
dollar aside for us domestic
semiconductor
manufacturing to try to build that and a
lot of the argument was we don't want to
spend the supply chains that China make
a control and would and part of the
reason is National Security so that's
one reason people are proposing free
trade okay the second argument is the
one where economists have probably
fallen down the
most which is we might call this
argument non-compensation of the
losers the basic argument for free trade
that I grew up with runs as follows if
you allow Imports
consumers will gain more than producers
will
lose as long as we take some of that
extra and transfer it back to producers
everybody wins let's go up to here
imagine that we move this is with
trade we move to trade remember trade
took consumer surplus from W to W plus X
Plus Z produc Surplus from X Plus y to
Y what if we took the x from consumers
and moved it over here
well then what happens consumers are
better off they still have W plus Z
producers are no worse off they're the
same as they were before so we can make
everybody better off we can create no
losers from free trade by simply taking
some of the extra benefits that created
and giving them to the losers it's
theoretically brilliant it's a great way
to argue I free trade's good because as
long as the winners win by more than the
losers lose you can take some of the
winners winnings and give it to the
losers keep them whole and everybody's
better off or at least no worse
off okay the problem is we haven't done
that in theory it works in practice we
don't do it and this is made no more
evident than by the fascinating research
of my colleague David
otter David otter who's an outstanding
labor Economist has looked at what
happened around the US due to Rising
imports from China and is a very clever
study where he looks at as looks at
Industries basically Chinese Imports
became much cheaper after he passed the
Free Trade Agreement it looks at
industries that were more and less
susceptible to Chinese Imports and where
they're
located and what he found was the
industries that were most Su set to the
chines Imports basically got crushed and
those communities lost millions and
millions of
jobs now at the same time life for
consumers was great this based on how
walm smart
functions okay I was like you know I've
got this sweater here okay this sweater
you can't really see it's a nice you
know it's like mediocre sweater okay
this sweater probably cost me I don't
know 30 bucks okay when I was a kid when
prices were a third of what they are now
the sweater would cost me maybe 40
bucks okay would be 120 today's dollars
why because imports from China because
when I was a kid that had to be made in
North Carolina our textile mills in
North Carolina and they were more
expensive now I get it from China it's
cheap the techy guys had no longer have
jobs well the easy answer is tax me on
my sweater imagine if with this $30
sweater they imposed a $15
tax well I'd still be way better off
than I would have been without trade
this would have been 120 bucks without
trade so I'm still way better off and
that money could have compensated all
the textile workers who lost their jobs
everybody wins but we didn't do
it as a result while theoretically we
can make everybody better off in
practice we
haven't and that has led to a lot of
opposition or free trade okay this gets
in a big issue which is well gee
couldn't we just help these texti
workers some other way and we'll talk in
a couple lectures about that that's
about redistribution policy but in
practice that's what least the
opposition
yeah that's a great question so that's
the other argument for free trade
actually I should put that is another
argument this sort of relay to the trade
War argument for free trade which is
that basically um the idea is economists
say here's another way to think about
this the rose workers lose their jobs if
we train them to be computer
workers then everybody's better off the
rose workers move into a better sector
computer workers make more than Rose
workers consumers in the US get cheaper
roses everybody wins so the way you
could do this is by literally just
retraining workers but that takes money
and we didn't do it and a lot of workers
turns out it's hard to become a computer
programmer okay or you know or you know
uh be electrical engineer you know I
mean you're all studying to do that okay
it's hard for these people who didn't
grow up with proper education or work in
the Rose sector to do that so as a
result in theory you can do that in
practice we
didn't so that's one big that's a second
big reason people oppose free trade and
the third reason people oppose free
trade I already talked about last
lecture which is socially damaging
comparative advantage and I talked about
that last
lecture with with Chinese battery plant
and the fact they built this battery
plant and since they have no
environmental regulations the stuff
leaked and killed a bunch of
people okay that's the third issue
finally the last issue and the most
controversial is trade as a foreign
policy tool
which is we have many
reasons okay to be mad at China there's
many reasons Trump was mad at China now
some were're irrational Trump was upset
about our trade deficit with China as I
said that's just a Pikachu deficit we
shouldn't care okay but Trump had
legitimate reasons for being mad at
China for example we have a larger World
Trading System under the World Trade
Organization that as I said is like a
club that imposes a set of free trade
rules to try to have welfare maximizing
trade around the world China's been
violating the rules that organization
repeatedly over and over again China's
been doing things which violate the
rules so for example it says you can't
import any Goods into China that aren't
you could be have foreign Goods in China
but they must be produced in Chinese
factories well that's not free trade if
you say you can't have computers sold in
China by American companies unless you
come here and build a factory here in
China you can own it America
but you got to come here and employ
Chinese workers and build a factory here
well that's against the rules of the WTO
that's against the Free Trade Agreement
and China's been doing that for years
there's also significant industrial
Espionage now I'm not saying we don't do
it too but there's a lot of evidence of
the fact that free trade has opened up
the exposure of our companies to other
countries and they've been studying and
copying our
methods and that's another reason that's
another kind of bad behavior we should
be worried about these are significant
problems
so you might say well gee China's a bad
actor why not then slap a tariff on him
why isn't that the right answer and it
turns out it's a bad answer as a way of
getting back at this problem be for
three
reasons there's three reasons why using
trade restrictions as a tool of foreign
policy makes no
sense okay reason one is the standard
welfare
analysis which is sure you strike back
at China but along the way you hurt
American
consumers okay indeed um there was a lot
of evidence that the price of goods that
were produced using Chinese Parts went
through the roof once Trump not through
the roof but went up a lot once Trump
raised his
tariffs so that's the first argument the
second
argument is that it's not even clear how
you do this because what is made in
China
take a
car where the construction the bodies in
the US but all the components come from
China is that a Chinese good and
American good and if you POS a tariff on
that you're hurting American car
companies they use that as an input in
their production which will kill
American
jobs so you're actually if the idea of a
tariff to protect American jobs but the
Tariff doesn't make it more expensive
the inputs that Americans need for their
jobs you actually hurt American
jobs okay so that's the second argument
the third argument is you need
coordination which is the US isn't the
only party that trades with
China the US is not the only party that
that that trades with China so suppose
you're trading your Pokemon with your
friends but your friend has a bunch of
people he's trading with and you decide
because your friend pissed you off you
won't trade with him he'll just trade
the cards to someone else now he might
not get quite as good a deal but he's
not as he not suddenly like he can't
trade his cards he just got to trade in
with someone else and basically uh
that's what happened is China just
started selling their goods to other
countries so basically the reason that
this was a bad way to approach our
problems with
China was it's bad for American
consumers it might be bad for American
Producers it doesn't do much if you
don't coordinate internationally that's
why most economists who are smart in
this area said we should have serious
trade re repercussions against China we
should think about barriers trade with
China but has to be done an
internationally coordinated way and that
wasn't what was
done so basically you end up with fairly
ineffective trade barriers on
China okay now the latest attempt of
this to use foreign po to use trade as a
foreign policy tool was s on Russian
oil not allowing people to buy Russian
oil because the Ukraine war once again
this didn't work so well because other
countries were still Rising other
countries were still
buying okay and that's a and b this
became incredibly painful for Europe
because Europe depended so much on
Russia for their fuel and the question
is can Europe really are you going to
break apart the European Coalition
because they don't want to keep placing
such high high prices for fuel
okay on the other hand if you if you um
if you uh tell countries they can't
export goods to Russia that might be
more effective because that makes life
the life miserable in Russia maybe
they'll throw off their leader they
probably won't but that would be another
way you could approach it so these are
really interesting and difficult issues
to think through and exciting think
about how we can once again use the
tools of microeconomics to come at this
questions about
that yeah
that it's it's it's a great point so the
trade War you're asking about this
argument the trade War argument is less
powerful if you're talking about country
we don't really sell them much now North
Korea is different we have that's
sanctions that's just we won't deal with
them but if you think about a small
country if you think about suddenly we
got mad think about Columbia they don't
buy that many computers okay so you
might say this argument is not super
relevant uh if the country is small okay
I agree with
that okay let me talk about one other
since I haven't been controversial
enough today let's talk about one other
non-controversial topic which is
immigration
immigration the same set of principles
that applies to free flow of goods
applies to the free flow of
workers so look at figure
198 think about producing fruit in the
US okay originally under art tarkey we
have L1 workers
producing fruit at a wage of
W1 now if we allow
immigration that shifts out the supply
of workers shifts
out now we have S2
workers at a lower
wage well what does that do to the
market for fruit let's go to figure 199
so this is I'm sorry 8 is not the market
for fruit this is this a bit unclear 98
is the labor market for people producing
fruit very clear 198 is the labor market
diagram in Fruit production 199 is the
fruit
market well what's happened I just
showed you in
198 that the wage went down if the wage
goes down marginal cost goes down so
supply curve shifts out from S1 to S2
what does that do it allows more fruit
at a lower
price so this is why economists
generally favor relatively free
immigration because by having immigrants
come in and do jobs we allow Goods to
produce more cheaply and it creates
consumer
surplus okay on the other hand figure
198 is why many people in America don't
like
immigration which is the wage
Falls so it's once again a standard
tradeoff much like trade by allowing
immigrants in we allow more consumer
surplus through cheaper
fruit but we lower the wage that workers
get in the fruit producing sector and I
don't need to go through the graphs to
show you that the former dominates the
latter overall we're better off with
immigration now we're only overall
better off immigration however however
if we can make some mechanism to
compensate the losers if we for example
said well look we're now going to tax
fruit fruit's cheaper we're going to tax
fruit and give the money to the former
fruit producers then that would work but
we're not doing it not do anything to
help those frood
producers okay so the question is how
big a problem is this and the there's
actually a number of really good
studies of how does
immigration affect domestic wages and
prices what they find is more
immigration does lower
prices what they also find is more
immigration doesn't much lower has if
anything a negligible effect on the
wages of us born workers
relatively small
effect which could be for two reasons
one reason could be because of
elasticities the other could be because
they're in sectors that people don't
want to work in people don't want to
pick fruit they don't want to work at
the gas station of
7-Eleven okay so basically this is one
reason I'm not alling wages is because
these are jobs people didn't
want okay but here's the fascinating
Fact one group does get hurt by more
immigration the previous
immigrants so people who actually hurt
by this the group for which wages fall
are the last generation of immigrants
because they are working in those
sectors this leads to the fascinating
Paradox at the heart of a concern in
politics that many have on the left
which is GE why are immigrants turning
against the Democratic party turning
against free trade turning its free
immigration why don't immigrants the
Democrats are clearly the party of much
freeer immigration than the republ
Republicans yet they're losing immigrant
votes well actually it kind of makes
sense if you think about it because the
future immigrants are going to hurt the
wage of the existing immigrants so it
kind of makes sense it's sort of a pull
the ladder up behind me argument once
I'm in and I want more people in once
I've got my job in the fruit picking
sector I don't want more people to come
in I'll lower my wage so it's Pro it's
perhaps not irrational for some
immigrants to oppose additional
immigration because they're the one not
not us-born people but immigrants
previous immigrants the ones whose wages
will
suffer so once again a subtle but
important arguments we think about
obviously with immigration there's a ton
of other issues we won't get into here
that aren't about economics I'm not
claiming this is the the end point of
immigration policy discussion but it's
important to remember that the tools I
taught you about trade can be applied
broadly including the immigration debate
okay let's stop there