And finally, our last speaker is Brian
Erl, who is a senior vice president at
Salis O'Brien and their director of
geothermal operations, and he'll be
joining us virtually.
>> Yeah, good morning everybody. Uh, sorry
I can't be there. Um, I'm actually going
to be in Boston all next week for more
geothermal and thermal energy network uh
uh conferences and and symposiums and uh
looking forward to that next week. But
um uh let's see is that in screen?
Sorry.
There we go. Okay. Um yeah, thanks for
having me. So I'm going to talk a little
bit about uh the introduction to
designing geothermal energy networks or
thermal energy networks. Um I know
Nicholas and thank you for that uh
mentioned something about a case study.
I think maybe the agenda might have
gotten changed a little bit but um so
we're going to talk a little bit briefly
about uh you know kind of the highlevel
technical aspects of design
considerations for thermal energy
networks and and geothermal energy
networks. So primarily these are the six
kind of uh um most important topics or
design considerations that in my mind
when looking at these systems that you
have to really consider think very you
know thoroughly through and understand
uh as you move forward in the design. So
number one site selection uh obviously
extremely important. Now I'm going to
talk specifically about the technical
aspects of this uh of the design.
Obviously with site selection there's
all kinds of other ramifications and and
you know aspects of why you might choose
a site uh over certain technical aspects
but just from a technical perspective
we'll go through that. We'll talk a
little bit about thermal resources but
obviously you've been hearing all about
that and and so I'm not going to spend a
lot of time there. Uh we'll also just
dive into a little bit about the
differences between a single pipe
ambient loops versus two-pipe ambient
loops and then what's an energy transfer
station, why or why may you may or may
not uh incorporate that into a design,
what impacts that may have. Uh and then
some of the infrastructure
ramifications, pump houses primarily,
because we're pumping fluid, we've got
to have a lot of these types of uh uh
systems throughout the network. And so
where do they get located? Um and that's
always a really big uh topic and
discussion with the client and the
community about you know uh where do
where do these go? How do you locate
them and uh what they might look like?
uh then also talk just briefly about
modeling these systems because it's ex
you know these are relatively new from
um the modeling community and so to try
to dynamically model the impacts and the
optimization of these systems I think is
really important and then of course
gathering data on existing systems so we
can continue to refine the modeling is
also you know extremely important which
we know HEAT is doing a fantastic job
with uh with their leg up program and
And uh you know thinking about future
expansion, we've got a lot of pilot
projects going on in the country right
now, but we need to think about and have
as part of the design consideration, how
do we expand these systems and what that
might look like and make sure that we're
incorporating proper um fundamentals
within the system to be able to to to
accommodate that expansion in the
future.
So first of all, site selection. Just
looking at this from a technical
perspective again, first thing we always
look for when we're looking at sites is
are there thermal assets that are
available and accessible within that
site. And what I mean by accessible is,
you know, through both regulation and
land uh uh agreements or access, can you
can you make that thermal asset
available to the system? So that's
really important. So it might be
vertical bore holes, but where do those
go? Are they on somebody's private
property? Are they within the street?
Um, are they in a parking lot? You know,
what does that look like? Is it is there
a river or a or a surface body of water
nearby? Uh, you know, any of those
things that are going to be utilized,
are they accessible and available? And
then how do you get to those uh sites
and incorporate that into your into your
system? The next thing would be the
building stock. You know, number one, we
always want to look for a diverse load
profile within the building stock that's
going to be uh connected to the system.
The reason for that is really just to
try to reduce capital costs and peak
loads and try to share energy. If we're
not sharing energy during peak times, we
still have to size the total for the for
the for the sum of the peaks, right? So
we don't get a real benefit from the
diverse loads on the on the peak sizing
which then doesn't offset any capital
expenditures. So what we're really
looking for is commercial buildings that
have in in heating dominant climate
zones have cooling dominant load
profiles so we can share that energy
with then some residential buildings on
that same network. That's really
important. as you were going south in,
you know, uh, in into cooling dominant
climate zones, then you would look for
things like domestic hot water and
things that are using, uh, uh, heat
versus, um, getting rid of heat. So, it
depends on, of course, where this is
being done. Uh, number one, most of the
systems we're seeing today are in
heating dominant climate zones. So,
we're looking for that commercial
offtaker that can give heat to the
system. And, uh, and then also the
building density. You know, we don't
want to run miles of pipe and only
connect a few buildings. We want to make
sure that our building density is such
that we have enough connected customers
to reduce that overall cost of the
network. And and it makes sense to do
that. Um and then of course the site has
to have uh areas for infrastructure.
Where does the infrastructure go? Where
do these pump houses or vaults go? Where
do where do we put the thermal assets in
in and how we connect those systems?
Because with these systems, you're going
to have infrastructure that has to be
placed somewhere both electrically uh
hydraulically. Um so are they within
buildings? Are they out uh um you know
uh freestanding buildings? Are they
built into maybe new developments? Uh
you know, where do those things um uh
you know, where are they going to be
located? And that's really important
because as these get built out, I think
the last thing a lot of communities want
to see is all kinds of just uh
infrastructure that has to do with
operating the system throughout their
neighborhoods. So that's certainly uh
technically we have to understand that
and figure out where we're going to put
it. And then of course the building age
and the community that you're looking
at, you know, what is the age of the
buildings? Typically the older buildings
are going to be harder to heat because
of the envelopes. They need to be
improved. They don't have as good of
insulation. uh you know windows etc. And
then also the HVAC systems are probably
such that they're not easily
retrofitable to a geothermal heat pump
system. So the deeper the retrofits of
course the higher the cost. So those are
all things when it comes to the
technical site selection that we take
into account when looking at that and
helping our clients really pick the best
sites for these projects moving forward.
Thermal assets or thermal resources. We,
you know, uh, Nick did a really good job
talking about this. Um, you know,
obviously we've got all kinds of
different earth energy type systems
where you're talking about vertical
closed loop, surface water, uh, openloop
reinjection, energy piles. Uh, there's
all kinds of really good geothermal
resources, but there's also that waste
heat, the waste heat that's around all
of our communities that we can try to
take advantage of. And so those are the
thermal assets that we've always try to
analyze, look at and figure out is it
available, is it accessible and then
what's the cost implication to that
thermal asset
single pipe versus two pipe uh ambient
temperature loop. So the connect the
interconnecting pipe that runs around
the community or the network and how to
connect these buildings is really
important. Number one, uh technically to
to put stuff in existing streets, to put
new infrastructure in existing streets,
you have to coordinate with all the
other utilities and and a lot of these
older neighborhoods and communities have
a lot of utilities in the streets. So
having a two-pipe system versus a one
pipe system makes that a bit more
challenging and a bit more cost costly
to install. Uh the other nice thing
about the single pipe versus the two
pipe is it's much more flexible for
expansion for distributed resources and
distributed uh uh assets. So you can
have multitude of of thermal assets and
you can place those in different
locations where with a two pipe it's a
lot harder hydraulically to interconnect
all of those systems and it also becomes
a little bit more challenging. Um and
then and just the building connections.
Now uh the downside to a single pipe is
if you only had one thermal resource to
draw from then you have to size and pump
the single pipe such that all the
customers are still getting roughly the
same temperature uh to those heat pumps.
Usually we try to you know maintain less
than a 5°ree delta t Fahrenheit between
all of those buildings because that way
everybody's getting the same efficiency.
If you start to allow 7 8 10° between
buildings, now you're impacting, you
know, the person uh that's first off of
the line versus the last off of the
line, you know, uh differently. And
that's not necessarily equitable and
fair to to those customers. So, um
that's one reason why when you're
looking at a single pipe ambient system,
distributed thermal resources are key to
those uh designs. Whereas a two-pipe
system, you know, everybody's getting
the same temperature. You can locate one
larger uh thermal asset and everybody
gets the same temperature. So, it's a
little bit easier to manage uh with a
two-pipe system.
I'll also say that the single pipe
systems generally on average have lower
flows through that single pipe through
the ambient loop, which means smaller
pipe, smaller pumps, less energy to
operate. So those are also some benefits
of the singlepipe system versus the
two-pipe system. The other thing that
just touch on briefly is the energy
transfer station or or basically uh in
layman terms would be just a hydraulic
isolation between the building fluid and
piping system and the infrastructure uh
fluid and piping system. The reason why
you do that is uh especially for larger
buildings is if you have a lot of piping
in your building, you have a lot of
fluid, a lot of connections, a lot of
joints, you have a larger risk for
potential leaks and and breakage that
would impact the entire infrastructure.
So, a heat exchanger to isolate the
building from the infrastructure then
allows you know every building to have
its own system. uh the infrastructure is
completely isolated and that way the
fluids don't mix, the pressures don't
mix. If I had a mid-rise or a high-rise
building on one of these systems, that
pressure would would impact the
infrastructure pressure if I didn't
isolate that. So, most systems we see
today have what we call an ETS or an
energy transfer station to isolate those
systems. Keep in mind every one of those
heat exchangers though do reduce the
temperatures
uh and efficiency of the system because
we're not getting a a straight through
zero degree approach from infrastructure
temperature to building temperature. You
generally lose a couple of degrees which
then again you know can negatively
impact the heat pump performance
slightly. Not a huge deal but it does
there is an impact there. Uh if you had
all residential homes and all just one
heat pump per home, maybe an energy
transfer station isn't necessary. Uh
there's a great case study uh the one in
in in Markham, Ontario, where all 300
homes do not have an energy transfer
station because there's very limited
piping. There's no pressure implications
of additional building height. It's all
single family. So again, project
specific, but just understand what the
differences are and why you might use
that uh versus when you maybe wouldn't
use it.
And then let's talk a little bit about
these pump houses and and infrastructure
and where do we put those? Uh you know,
the above grade pump houses uh obviously
need to have architectural designs to
meet any city standards and neighborhood
standards from an from an architectural
perspective. Um, you obviously have to
have uh uh in certain cases have to have
conditioned space. Uh when you get over
certain square footages, we've uh in
certain areas the code would require
potentially a bathroom to be installed.
So, you know, designing above grade
structures, number one, there's a lot
larger cost implications. It's something
that people are going to see. So, where
do you put that? What does it look like?
um you know, great for educational
purposes, but other than that, you know,
it's really just there to operate the
system. Uh are you going to have, you
know, actual hardware installed there to
operate the system, or is everything
remote, you know? So, what goes into
this pump house? How big is it? Uh some
of these that we've seen on some of
these pilot projects are 20x 40 foot
long. So, a relatively large pump house
uh that needs quite a bit of space and
obviously can be, you know, can be seen.
So, so you know, when you're into the
beginning concepts, where do you put
these? What do they look like? What are
the sizes? Uh what are the implications
of having above grade structures? And
you know, you might have one, you may
have more than one depending on how many
different pump stations you might have
in a system. So, those are things that
need to be considered.
The other thing you could consider is
what if we do this below grade? Okay, so
now we don't have to look at anything.
Everything is below ground. Uh but what
are the implications of that? Well,
number one, anybody that's owning,
operating, and maintaining these
systems, you have to have confined space
uh trained and and certified uh uh
service technicians to be able to access
those vaults and be down inside those
spaces. It does make for a bit more
challenging for that maintenance and
repair if if needed. Um, you also have a
very uh high humidity environment. So,
you have to be careful with some of the
materials that are used. And then where
do you place these? Where do you have
room for these? Generally, in the
street, you may not have room because of
all the other utilities. So, are they
going to be placed in private property?
If so, you have to have easements and
and land access agreements to access
these vaults. Um, so just thinking that
all through about number one, who's the
owner? Who's going to own and operate
and maintain the system? What are their
capabilities? Where do you have space
for this stuff? And then, you know,
what's the longevity? What are what are
the service and maintenance implications
of having something below grade? If this
was in the street, it has to be vehicle
load rated, etc. Here's just a couple of
pictures of a project. Uh uh this was
the one I mentioned up in Markham,
Ontario. Uh that's been installed and
operating for a couple of years now. And
these uh they have 15 belowgrade vaults
all located in the street. So, as you
can see, you know, you have to access
those from a manhole down into the vault
to be able to get at the pumps, etc. Uh,
you still have electrical and some water
um uh pedestals above grade that you're
still going to see within the community.
So, where do you put those? Is that on
someone's private property or or is it,
you know, public property? Where does
that get located? So with these systems
we do have to con you know consider
technically where does all this stuff um
uh you know where do we place all of it
and um uh you know uh what are the cost
implications and then what are the
maintenance and future you know
accessibility to these systems uh look
like
and then I just talk a little bit about
modeling uh modeling these systems can
get quite complicated uh the bigger the
systems the different types of energy
sources is when you're adding in any
type of supplemental or hybridization of
the systems. Uh you know uh depending on
the building loads and the different
diversity of each of the buildings,
you're you need to model these in a
dynamic transient way that we can
actually really number one understand
how they're going to operate hour by
hour, yearbyear, you know, over the long
term. uh we need to understand and be
able to run sequence sequencing and
operational models or dispatch models so
we can really understand how to build
proper control schematics on on how to
operate these so we can give those to
the client. And then also just looking
at long-term what happens to the system
or throughout the year what happens when
you know one building shifts from
heating to cooling or uh you know maybe
one asset isn't available because of the
temperature profile or you know so so
there's a lot of different things that
are happening within these systems. And
then we can also really look at not just
the heat pump efficiencies we can also
dive into the the parasitic pump loss
efficiencies. And because one thing you
see with these large um uh thermal
energy networks is there's a lot of pump
energy. You the bigger they get, the
more pumping you have. And so how much
are we being penalized by connecting all
this together? Or is there different
ways we can do this to maintain small
parasitic losses on the pump side? And
so the cost to operate the system
doesn't offset as if you were to go
through and and maybe do these in
smaller pieces. So those are all things
that we need to really understand and
need to model correctly uh as we're
designing these systems. So again the
temperature profile of the ambient loop
I mentioned earlier we want all the
buildings to get roughly the same
efficiency and the same temperature. So
with that we need to model that
temperature profile throughout the year
and then obviously at the very coldest
point and the and the warmest point in
the year and what that looks like. So
this is that project in Markham, Ontario
where you can see all the different
energy sources injecting or rejecting
heat into that ambient loop and then how
it uh the temperature profile follows
that 2 miles of pipe around the
development. So we know that based on
this nobody's getting more than a 5
degree difference which means
everybody's getting really good and
pretty close to the same efficiencies at
their home.
And then of course we always look at
long-term net effects of of the system
especially when we're looking at
vertical ground loop heat exchangers and
if we have large uh um uh bore fields
that we could impact with either putting
too much heat in or taking too much heat
out and how that impacts the earth over
time. Uh and that's the other beautiful
thing about you know distributed thermal
assets is the smaller you make them and
the more distributed the less we're
going to have any impact of the earth
over the long haul versus if we put all
that into one area. Um so you can see
here that we've you know you model five
years you model 10 years um even as much
as 30 40 years just to see you know
what's the trend of that of that model
look like and you can see here that
there is no trend either going up or
down which means that we have a very
stable and consistent load profile both
energy in energy out so the ground is
going to be very stable over the long
term
and then we can also model all the
efficiencies of the system so these are
the the heat pumps throughout throughout
the year um or for one year of operation
that was in the third year both heating
and cooling. So that's every heat pump
in the system and looking at the coops
of those uh different buildings and how
they're operating on the system. So we
can look and go okay everybody's pretty
much operating around the same
efficiencies and we can also just get an
aggregate of the total coop of the
system not including pump energy but of
the heat pumps in the in the customers
that are being served by the system. So
we can really get a good snapshot of you
know how efficient these systems are and
is it is it penciling out to what you
know the consumers are going to expect
on their utility bills.
And then the last thing I would just say
uh you know when designing these systems
we really have to consider the expansion
of these systems in the future and how
are we doing that. Um, for instance, one
of the projects we worked on, uh, with
heat actually in Framingham, um, you
know, they had put some TE's and some
valves on the piping, thinking about
expansion, and then as we got into
designing the expansion, we realized
that that really wasn't done, uh, in a
way that could do it um, uh, the the
most optimized way for hydraulics and
for energy sharing. uh what what it was
initially thought was that you could
just use the entire center pipe as the
mix loop for connecting the two. Well,
hydraulically when you add the flow rate
of the second loop that increased the
pump sizes. Whoops. Uh it increased the
pump sizes dramatically for both
systems. Um so that really wasn't the
most optimized way to do that and
because the pipe wasn't large enough. So
rather than digging up and replacing
that entire section, creating two
smaller 20- foot mix loop sections on
each end and just replacing that section
uh and then modeling that to make sure
we can still transfer enough energy
within that 20 foot and see how that
worked to see whether or not that was a
good way to expand the system. But we
have to understand what is you know when
we look at a a system where would you
expand what's the building stock get
high level what are the loads of that
potential expansion loop are there
energy resources available on that
particular expansion loop or do I need
to feed it all from the original loop
you know how does that all work together
and so um this is showing how that mix
loop actually works those two different
spots which you can see here at the
beginning um and then at the at the
center of the loop where the two come
together for 20 foot and mix. You can
see that the temperatures actually do
benefit one another and bring the two
closer together as they operate uh
simultaneously. Even though you only
have two 20ft sections, we're still
getting shared energy benefit across
both of the loops. And actually the red
loop is is being benefited more from the
black loop because we've got a little
bit better temperatures on the on the
second loop, I should say, the phase 2
loop. Um so that's benefiting phase one.
Okay. And so uh as you can see here
we've we've lo you know um put numbers
on that where the actual mix loops are
one and three which is here one and
three and then how the systems kind of
operate together. So thinking about
expansion which direction you might
expand um and and then just thinking
about you know the hydraulics of it and
also the energy where is the energy
going to come from? Will there be new
energy assets being installed or does it
need to come from phase one of the
project? And so those are just kinds of
things that you can think through high
level as as you're designing a project
and asking clients, you know, is this
potentially going to be expanded? Which
direction would you expand? Are there
more customers that you already have in
mind that you want to add later on? Um,
so those are all some of the design
considerations that I consider when
designing these geothermal energy
networks. Really critical. um you know
from from the kind of major or six six
most critical uh considerations. So with
that, I thank you uh for your time.
Again, apologize I can't be there in
person. Wish I could have. Uh I'm sure
I'll see a bunch of you next week. And
uh I guess we're opening it up for
questions.