Okay. Uh I think we'll start off this
panel. Uh we have a uh a great uh
cross-section of uh people from
different types of companies. So uh
probably the best way to introduce
everyone is to let them introduce
themselves their names and what their
role is at their organizations as well
as maybe uh a one sentence about uh your
your take on software engine AI and
software engineering. So uh Lis Lisa you
want to take it away. Thank you. Uh so
I'm Lisa Meanie. I'm from IBM Research
uh just down the road 314 uh Maine. So I
am the uh the site lead exec for IBM
Research Cambridge. uh but my real day
job is that uh I leave our I lead our uh
global research strategy on u uh AI for
data platforms. So it's kind of
interesting that uh Kion went just
before us and was talking about
structured data uh because uh you know
as you can imagine IBM has a lot of data
products. So databases, data warehouses,
uh data lakeouses, knowledge catalogs,
uh ETL systems. So we have a lot of
products that are really around this uh
structured data structured
semi-structured uh we obviously do some
as well as unstructured. Uh and what
we're doing is to basically uh infuse AI
uh to accelerate those systems, make
them much more uh self-service. So
natural language access to your
databases to make them more uh
efficient, to make them more
explainable. Um and then what we're also
doing is to try to make those systems um
better serve the data for Genai and um
um Agentic workflows. Uh so accelerate
them, you know. So one of the big topics
these days is can we uh take re reinvent
databases data lakeouses these sorts of
things uh and optimize them on on GPUs
as is just one example. So so there's a
lot of examples but just to try to give
you uh you know a feel for that. Uh and
in terms of the perspective on um you
know AI for uh for software engineering
uh obviously you know I'm I'm at IBM
research and we're creating a lot of you
know we're doing this we're trying to
create the tools are trying to uh to
create the technologies for this. So
obviously uh you know I have a very
positive view a lot of what I do is um
software engineering in that data space.
So it turns out that in addition to the
databases and so on there's a lot of
code around it. Um so you know SQL code
so uh so generating SQL code generating
GraphQL uh code uh being able to
generate code for managing and operating
uh these systems. So we do a lot in uh
generating that that type of um of
codes. Great Wilco. Awesome. Uh hello
I'm Wiling. I'm the senior director in
industrial robotics and vision at
Symbotic. Symbotic we are reinventing
the warehouse. Imagine a warehouse that
delivers groceries uh to your store or
anything else really. Um we use robots
um mostly to do that. So any kind of
robot you can really imagine. We have a
number of robot arms at all of our
sites. Um we also have Simbots which are
basically small autonomous systems,
autonomous robots which drive around and
deliver goods um inside the the
warehouse that we have. Um the
interesting thing is that we are really
operating at scale. We have robotics
deployed at scale. We are at around 50
warehouses in the US and each of these
warehouses we have hundreds of robots
and thousands of symbots. And you can
imagine that um that's a lot of scale
just to think about all the data that we
get in and like one of the interesting
components I think that we realize is
that you can engineer against 99.9% of
what's really happening right but the
0.1% is really what gets you. And at
every at any given day we touch about 10
million cases in the US alone. And
that's that's a lot of cases that go
wrong if.1% is what's failing you right.
So we need to really build the these
these pipelines that we cannot engineer
against and bring down over time the
issues that we see think about
automating uh the processes to identify
these issues cluster them and then pick
up the engineering processes to bring
them down over time. Right? And you can
imagine there's a lot of R&D involved in
this process and um yeah AI in software
engineering really helps us to bring
down this kind of um R&D process right
so in R&D you really try to reduce the
amount of time it takes for you to
derisk
something for you to solve a problem
right so if you can suddenly start doing
these things it may not be like the
final approach that you're actually
executing but it's maybe the the um the
direction that you would derisk and say
this is the right way to do it and then
we bring it to to engineering and
finally productionize it. I think that's
one of the main um progress areas where
we currently see like the main benefit.
Yeah.
Simon. All right. Uh Simon Lee um from
Humanana. Uh for those of you that have
heard of Humanana, you might probably
know us more as a health insurance
company. We serve um many Medicare and
Medicaid members, but recently of course
uh we've been more vertically integrated
into the healthcare industry. So we
actually operate a lot of primary care
clinics now. Uh we have a sizable
pharmacy business. So we really are
vertic we really are a more of a
healthcare delivery and a payer as well.
So uh as for my day job uh my role is a
director in data science but what I
actually do is I lead a small team um
and we serve as basically the innovation
lab for the enterprise. Um we are
cross-disciplinary all inhouse. Uh
software building is a team sport deeply
rooted in human- centered design
methodologies and we practice them on a
daily basis in order to achieve uh
desired outcomes for the users of the
solutions that we implement. Um recently
as you can tell like for in any
innovation sort of uh fashion AI is a
very large part of what we are really
investigating. Um, for me in terms of
like uh what AI really means for me is
it's the newest tool in the toolbox for
us to be able to utilize in order to
create engaging software and experiences
for our members, our patients, our
associates. And you're looking for
various ways we can apply the emerging
technologies in order for us to come up
with new solutions that achieve business
outcomes.
Great. uh I think to to sort of um delve
in a little bit deeper into your
introductions
uh can you uh give any feedback on what
specific AI tools that you're using now
and maybe or or just in general like
what the current state of AI and
software engineering at your
organizations what are you finding
that's working uh and maybe even more
important are there any things that are
sort of disappointing or maybe a little
bit further off than that the hype would
suggest. um when it comes to AI and
software engineering.
How do you want to uh look look like you
want it safe? Okay. Okay. So, uh you
know, as you can imagine, right, in
terms of the tools, um obviously there's
a lot there in terms of the ids, right?
So, copilot and uh you know, uh most
recently, I think there's a new update
for the uh like the cursor, which is
actually pretty uh pretty impressive in
terms of what they've done with with
MCP. And so, MIT grads. Yeah. Yeah. It's
it's it's good work, right? So I think
especially the the latest release if you
haven't tried that you know it's I you
know it's not an IBM product but I think
it's quite good. Um IBM has our own
Watson code assistant as well. So that's
used pervasively. Uh so what I would say
is you know when you hear at least from
my perspective when you hear like some
people are saying you know 90% of the
code uh you know that in my production
environment is you know AI generated you
know I kind of think maybe a lot of that
is autocomplete types of things you know
maybe little smaller things that might
get generated like a web landing page
these sorts of things um as opposed to
the kind of enterprise uh software that
that we see. Um so what I thought I'd do
is maybe talk about um you know some of
that and how that's kind of changing um
um software engineering. So one of the
big trends that we see uh in terms of
how AI is influencing this is that you
know entire enterprise applications are
being uh restructured right. So it used
to be that you would have you know you
would have applications that were
holistically written to take on you know
HR uh or to take on you know supply
chain or you know all these different uh
software uh media components that you
would need to have. Uh and one of the
big problems was okay how do you
integrate all of this data across this?
So you know a lot of times you have some
you know part of your application that
you're building is trying to go against
these APIs for this system or maybe it's
against these databases trying to pull
that data back trying to do some
business logic upon that maybe mapping
it to fields in another uh you know API
or database or these sorts of things you
know that's that's not so easy for the
AI to just figure out how it's going to
write it's not even that easy for a
human to say what they would want from
that in in natural language. Um so the
other approach that we're seeing there
that I think is a big change for
software engineers for software
engineering uh is the way that those uh
are being structured. Um so what's
happening is that there's you know it's
kind of the I would say it's sort of the
next generation of the chatbot. The
first thing of the chatbot was just let
me ask my question and give me back some
data. Okay that's good. It's give me
back some information and I can
interact. uh the next stage the next
wave was to say okay well I should be
able to get that from basically any
system across the enterprise right and I
should be able to so this is kind of
moving from chatbots and interactions
more to process orchestration uh process
automation right uh and then so these uh
these are being written very differently
uh in terms of saying okay I just need
to sort of specify what are the tools
meaning the APIs or the tools that help
me to access those I need to uh think
about different sequences and when those
need to be um uh you know invoked and so
on. I would like to try to do that as
autonomously as possible with these
agentic approaches and so on. Um and so
I think this is going to cause uh a very
significant uh change of how because
that's AI underneath that's allowing you
to do that. It's AI that's allowing you
to uh you know generate the uh you know
the code from the natural language that
would then you know decide on how to
orchestrate which of the different tools
to call and all of these sorts of
things. So, so that is AI deeply infused
for many different tasks um that would
traditionally uh be a much more complex
uh software engineering um task. So, um
I think that's something that's uh kind
of a big a big area that you want.
Um I would say as far as like code
generation, we're still learning. Um
we're we're we've tested out a few
different solutions so far. Kodium,
we're currently testing out Co C-Pilot.
Um we're not seeing as much of a
productivity like enhancement,
especially with some of our senior
engineers versus what we normally get
out of like ReSharper if we're doing C#
because like 40% of it for like
boilerplate code that you just in
anyways.
So for more seasoned engineers, I think
we haven't seen a whole lot of
productivity gain. For newer engineers,
junior engineers, it's a great learning
tool. Um, and I think it's a it's it's a
a way for them to start like um getting
more experience, hands-on keyboard type
experience coming up to spec. That's
what we've sort of seen.
Um, but as far as like it being like
deep productivity, it's not a panacea.
It's it's not something that's going to
solve all your problems. It it can
definitely be an assistant, but
everything that comes out of it, you're
always going to have to sort of like
give it another overview and look and
and and be and be sure that it is
accomplishing the actual task that
you're looking to accomplish. So, for
the most part, I think it's been it's
been great. like um all of our software
engineers especially at the XC love
using AI assisted uh code generation
just because it is
a if anything it at least allows you to
save a few keystrokes on the keyboard.
Um but as far as like being able to
trust everything that comes out of it
you it's not there yet. Um so another
area that we definitely are looking at
um like I said before software
engineering building software solutions
as a team sport. So reducing cognitive
burdens on like keyway testers um making
uh we're doing a lot of work right now
on
um trying to generate uh uh regression
test cases um for actual like
point-and-click regression solutions.
Um, but we
found generally that like out of the box
solutions are missing some of the sort
historical context that like our testers
are used to seeing. Um, so it's it's not
that it doesn't provide good test cases.
it just it's missing sort of the way we
used to write test cases so that people
like understand and be able to um run
the test cases like they normally would
right so and people are very adaptable
so like I'm sure that learning curve
would would be fairly quickly um but the
initial sort of roll out and sort of the
negative responses to this uh the test
cases that were generated has been
um it's been a little bit more uh uh
intense than what we initially thought.
So going something like a rack pattern
utilizing previous test cases to inject
some context into like how our
organizations and enterprises and teams
have generally written test cases to fit
a certain scenario to be able to like
then enhance the actual outputs going
back to the solution. I think that's but
that's that's that's one uh much more
positive experiences from the actual end
users and like the our QA test case
writers and whatnot in order for those
solutions to be sort of more acceptable.
So okay there a couple areas that we're
we're looking into. Yeah. Anything to
add Wilco? Uh maybe like one or two
things I think
one I think under uh appreciated benefit
of of these like chat bots in general. I
think but also the idees that you
mentioned is that you cannot get over
your pro procrastination hump right so
there's a lot of work that is that I'm
struggling to get started with right and
I know there's like a lot of burden
until I actually get to my idea that I
want to execute on right so if I can
bring down that burden much more I
actually get to the stuff that I want to
do and like I want to prove that works
much quicker and I think that's one of
the main benefits that I see that our
engineers basically don't get bogged
down in the details but they can focus
more on the big picture kind of things
that they want to execute on. And that's
a huge benefit. Not just yes, they're
more productive, but it's also they're
happier working on the things that they
actually want to work on rather than the
minor things. Um, and then another thing
is like there already a lot of quick
wins that you can get like one is for
example writing back better
documentation, right? I mean these are
like things that we struggle with. It's
always something that comes last that
should come first, right? Same thing for
writing tests, right? I think we can all
do better at writing tests. So, I mean,
I'm not saying you should autogenerate
all your tests, but like if they can
help you to discover more test case that
you haven't even thought about, that's
great, right? Um, you still need to
check your code. I agree though. Yeah.
Um, I think these are like things I want
to add. Um just sort of a as I did some
research for this uh forum today just
listened to a lot of current software
engineers talk about their job and what
they see as it impacting and um one of
the areas and and we didn't bring this
up today but some of the things in the
news that would you know maybe scare
some young software engineers is Mark
Zuckerberg saying yeah we're we're going
to hire less software engineers and um I
think Sam Alman made a a similar
claim the CEO of Nvidia
uh and uh a lot of what I'm hearing that
if you are specialized in say writing
code then that that's sort of
problematic because as a software
engineer you're going to have somebody
who's going to have to be able to one
probably the I would say the most
important thing would be requirements
analysis being able to understand what
what the heck the problem is because
anyone who's been a software engineer
has delivered software and then user who
signed off on the spec said that's not
what I want. Uh so uh never happened.
Never not ever. Uh you know so so being
able to understand the problem is is is
a is a big deal. Um uh maybe writing
code to do a a simple routine is an easy
easier thing that will be replaced
first. And it sounds like maybe that
sort of
offloads more mundane tasks for a
software engineer that you you sort of
go from being a coder to maybe you know
orchestrating the the whole process
whether it's from requirements analysis
to coding testing software life cycle
project management planning planning it
out uh and then you know security part
of that of course so is is that
something you and then a lot of what I'm
hearing you're saying now is I'm
wondering are are some of these things
problematic at the moment but are
problems that going to be solved and I
guess one of the things we talked about
be when we all met uh to talk about the
panel is we want to convey to the
audience okay if your profession is
software engineer where do we think that
you should be going what should you be
focusing on in order to sure ensure you
know one that you're employed and and
and your your career thrives in the the
near and distant future. So, uh that
being said, okay, I know if nobody uh
and and also the audience, we we have
some microphones and we could probably
at this point just open it up if you
have some input. I'm sure there's many
people that are are are having thoughts
in this area. Yeah, I can say a few
words on this one. So I would say that I
think first off in terms of you know uh
imminent doom for software engineers in
terms of not being needed uh you know
clearly we're not there right I mean we
not quite yet there right um however
what I would say is that um the field of
software engineering will change you
know what we do as software engineers uh
will change um but it always has right
so I don't think that that's any
different from things we've faced in the
past um I think what will happen is that
um you know some of the mindset uh for
how we develop software will change
right so it's it's like you know we used
to worry about how to build you know
very large complex systems you know they
talked about these waterfall models for
how you would design all of this uh and
and we sort of changed to doing much
more iterative kinds of things putting
things together integrating going cross
system mapping migration all these sorts
of things so I think that's one change
that we already are seeing and that's
what I was uh talking about earlier and
and AI is going to to help with that um
so I think there's there's first off
there's kind of a change in in even
mindset and and then the way we approach
the problems much more iterative, right?
Like you you kind of get started with
some of the tools, you start to test
things out or you know you start off
with you know you're looking at a piece
of code and you ask for a summary or you
you know or you generate a you know a
code tree or these sorts of things and
those can help you uh to get into it
much more uh quickly. Um I think the
other thing is that what what you're
seeing with some of this code Jen is
that it's true that some of the code
could be written uh with someone who is
less skilled maybe you know a more
junior person can go further uh using
some of these tools but I think the
other change would be that yes it's
possible that with the code generation
someone who is more of like um you know
even a higher level who might be more in
the business or a business user uh by
you know expressing what they not have
code generated and and brought to them.
But that takes a lot of complex, you
know, software underneath there. You're
not just going to point a business user
at uh, you know, chat GPT and have them,
you know, generate these very complex
uh, subsystems. That's that's a that's a
that's quite a long ways off at at best.
Um I also think that uh you know uh what
happens is that it's you know each time
we say oh you know this is you know
something's happening and we don't need
to you know do this anymore we don't
need the software engineers uh I think
what's going to what you'll see is
you'll see a lot more code being written
right so it's not maybe it's not so much
that you know software is you know that
if we said that we were constraining you
know we're saying okay exactly the same
amount of code is needed forever right
and more of that code can be written by
AI then okay might maybe that affects
you know the the need for software
engineers but I think that what will
happen instead is the amount of code uh
you know and code maybe for special
purpose for special uses you know in the
moment that's needed and so on can be
generated um than what we could do
before right and so that sort of changes
the dynamic but it doesn't necessarily
mean that there's not that continued
need for for good uh software
engineering skills um I think the other
thing is that you know you have to think
about not only the iterative approach um
but also uh for these large uh systems
thinking about systems of software right
so it's going to be systems of models
systems of tools systems of workflows
working together those can get very um
you know very uh complex and so I think
that uh there's a lot of need for these
different levels of software engineers
um that would you know look into uh and
be expert in in in various areas so it
used to be you know there was like web
developers primarily arily so you know
will this change web development I think
probably you know we are seeing some in
terms of you know even some of these
tools you know full stack you know at
least to get started more rapid
prototype there's a lot of complexity
and more need for more software that I
feel uh very good about uh you know
students and people going into the
software engineering field and will be
needed for quite some time. So are you
all still hiring software engineers
here? Yes. Anyone bring their resume
today?
We have a career fair following this. So
maybe we'll come maybe I can address
this from like a macro perspective
because in the robotics space we've
always had this fear that everybody gets
replaced by robots over time, right? And
I mean this is like decades old. I would
say hasn't really happened yet. And I
mean maybe you can argue that there's
some component here in the velocity of
what we do. But I I would see the world
is not as a fixed pie or like a zero sum
game, right? We will all be productive.
We will just do more awesome things over
time, right? So, and I think the the
point I want to make here is that we can
actually focus more on the things that
we really want to do rather than like
get boggled down in the minor things,
right? And I think that bringing down
the barrier that junior folks can do
this is I think is a positive thing. But
the other thing is also there's still
the need for experience over time,
right? It's more maybe on a higher level
where you can think about more of a
complex system that you can actually
tackle where previously you would have
to just for the communication across all
these teams that you would have to
negotiate over and like deal with over
time. It would just take it 10 years to
get something done that suddenly can
actually be done in one year and
suddenly it's not that you these
projects you would not have done in the
first place before because they would
have been just too too big and too
expensive and suddenly we have this
enabler we can suddenly start doing
these things right and that's amazing um
and yes symbolic is still hiring and uh
we do awesome stuff here so right
um I guess I'll nerd out for a bit uh so
to me like software engineers in the
future
I I definitely see AI impacting sort of
the way they learn software engineering,
not in academia, but like in actual
practice because if I think about the
way um I gained my experience as a
junior developer and working my way up
to senior and lead and so on and so
forth, I've probably spent countless
hours on MSDN. First time I looked at as
a junior developer and looking at all
those angle brackets, I had no idea what
I was looking at. It took time for me to
figure out like how to read those
documents, how to understand the
interfaces. Earlier, uh, one of the
presenters said like a good portion of
enterprise development is basically
negotiating those API interfaces um, and
being able to understand that and
looking through the document. It's a
skill to be able to read those types of
tech docs, right? I don't think you
really need to do that anymore as a
junior developer. You just ask the AI,
how do you implement this interface and
it's it's done, right? You don't
necessarily have to look look at all
those nested angle brackets and figure
out like this interfaces are coming from
that subclass and everything else. So I
think um just for productivity gains, I
think that's going to be huge because a
good portion of my time especially as a
junior developer was negotiating those
interfaces, especially in Java and C.
Um, and I don't think those languages
are going away anytime soon. Um, even
though everybody loves Python. Uh, and
secondarily, I think because of that,
it's going to be imperative that
people come into it because part of that
skill learning to read those technical
documentation, understanding those
interfaces is you sort of get a better
idea on the underlying software
engineering practices. What is a factory
method? What's the factory pattern? um
polymorphism versus inheritance. When
are you supposed to use those? If you
have and and you develop intuition in
your gut as a software engineer, you you
looking at a peerreview code and you
see, you know, something like private
static int count, you're like
no, no, that is not a thing that we do.
So,
um, because of all of that, like I think
when you're,
um, learning to
compose different modules together, it's
not necessarily the act of writing the
code, but it's understanding how to put
systems together is really where
software engineers in the future are
going to have to put their uh, focus on
learning is how, especially in an
enterprise environment, how different
components and modules fit together in
order to actually deliver the solution
and solve a problem for people. Great.
Um I I want to see at this point does uh
anyone from the audience want to Yes.
That's right. Uh do we have the
microphone?
I I work in an enterprise of 200,000
people
which is on the technology organization
and the question that um Thank you. A
question I have maybe it's a long shot
but do you have so yesterday we were
talking about the expertise used to be a
collection of factual information and
then we built experts on career paths on
our IT organizations information
organizations accordingly now it's
changed with
the rapid change in AI landscape how are
we going to change how we think about
human resources in bigger contexts so in
a small startup scale up maybe easier
you know what is the bleeding edge skill
you need in that team however what it
would look like in an enterprise that
you already have like tens and thousands
of people
sure I fully understood the the question
you're saying what would the career path
or the yeah so the skills will change
yes the jobs will change so do you have
a view what the new groups of job
families and career pathway oh Okay,
that's a good question.
Um, so yeah, I'm I'm not sure that I
Yeah, so we haven't gone and and sort of
reorganized uh completely. What I would
say is that you know what we are seeing
is um a lot more uh you know it used to
be application developers for example
now a lot of we refer to as a as a as an
AI developer AI engineer what they need
to have is they need to have a lot they
need to have savvy both in software
engineering as well as AI and how to use
um the models you know for their uh for
their uh you know in order to accomplish
their their tasks and so
We haven't um I don't think we've
changed our our roles per se. So
there's probably some additions AI cyber
security for example that didn't exist
before definitely need that now. Yeah.
Yeah. Application. Yeah. So my my
question was on the similar line but
it's different like you know the train
has left the station. We know that
sometime there is going to be that
convergence between here are the skill
gaps that got or the new skills that
will be required in future and here are
the skills that's going to slowly go
away or taken over by AI but when it
comes to timeline right you know from
academic point of view are there new
subjects new areas new certification
programs that's going to be rolled out
so that they're aware
this is where you need to upskill. This
is where you need to go and gain more
you know certification so you're
prepared for when that thing dies here
is where you are headed. Okay. Okay.
That that helps. Um. Yeah. So, so from
from my perspective at least, I think
one of the spaces I would advise people
that are in the software engineering
space is to spend. So, first thing would
be uh you really need to keep up with
the frameworks, right? So, you know, uh
lang chain, you know, lang flow,
langraph, uh llama index, uh you know,
uh MCP, uh you know, um crew crew AI,
you know, there's just a lot of
frameworks for being able to develop
applications with AI. That's kind of one
piece of it. And then the that's kind of
like just the base of like you said
understanding the API books and and and
that first part right uh and then I
think that the next part is that I do
believe um that uh you know as we write
things as uh multiple agents uh and
engaging with
tools our our our ideas of architecture
change uh quite a bit right uh you know
it used to be you know we you know there
was precision in APIs what the call
would do what you would get back at
least you know you know yes there were
you know issues people but you know you
were well constrained in terms of inputs
and outputs and all these sorts of
things um and yes it is you know
adjusting uh these agentic uh model
interfaces are adjusting and originally
it was just natural language in now
there's more structured um interfaces to
them paidantic AI and these sorts of
things that give you some structure but
uh nonetheless what I would say is that
I think there's going to be a major
transformation in how we do software
engineering with these Eentic approaches
where it is much more iterative than uh
what we've seen before where uh you know
you instead of just uh API in you make
your API call and you get exactly what
you want back uh in this case you know
you you you uh you make your you know
call to the tool or whatever you get
something back right uh you may need
some refinement some iteration on that
you know you you would also need um so
so there's the systems themselves that
are doing and then there are checkers
right validations and so on need to
happen. Um, you know, there's agents
that sit, you know, one of the big
things that we do is agents not just
agentic approach is not just to
accomplish the task. Um, but agents for
being able to for these systems be able
to monitor to detect uh problems to uh,
you know, generate what might be a
description of the problem that could be
in a you know, put into a git issue. uh
be able to, you know, look at that,
diagnose, generate a plan, be able to uh
generate, you know, maybe code to to do
the patches, you know, to be able to
generate code that would test, generate
that code that would validate that. So
there it's just it's a it's it's kind of
it's a very different way of
architecting these systems. And so I
would say, you know, like I said, the
frameworks first. Um that's just basic
learning. uh and then really getting in
and getting your hands dirty and
thinking about how your ideas of design
and architecture change if you're
approaching it with this agentic and and
more iterative approaches uh with more
validation uh confirmation more back and
forth more of maybe consulting a human
as opposed to the human being the
director uh for you know for the task
and asking for things right I want to
tie this like back to the previous
question I think like we also need to
take a look at like how organization
changes not just the roles themselves
But I think it's much more important
because people can do much more now.
It's I think organizations will be much
flatter and I think organizations will
be also uh giving people much more um
like responsibility of what they can do
what they can do right so I think we
will reward agency high agency much more
individualism and basically just going
out there and doing it right so we're
not here to just write code right we're
writing basically code to solve problems
and the problem solving I think is more
what's going to be at the core and I my
hypothesis is that people
will be better at being generalists and
basically interdisciplinary across
different domains rather than pure
specialists because I can become a
specialist maybe not at like the perfect
level, right? But I can become a
specialist like pretty quickly in like 5
minutes on like a domain that I have
know nothing about, right? And maybe it
takes me now a month to study something
in very very like strong depth, but I
can do it, right? And if the quicker you
can become a specialist in something
that that ability right so it's not that
you are the specialist for this but the
quicker you can become the specialist
that's how we would reward how good you
are in your job
and the other aspect was from the like
we are doing one LP right of the ILP
that your innovation partners innovation
ideas You open it up for like the
software engineer engineers from you
know these different companies to come
and partner with you
students have that kind of understanding
and training on hand with them.
So this is a question for me. I thought
I was just the moderator. Um I mean
there there are something like 63
different uh entrepreneurship programs
and such that we we run with students
here at MIT. So, um, the answer is yes,
but there are many different ways for
you to engage with them. And I would,
um, I would, uh, suggest you talk to
Peter Brousard, who's your ILP program
director, about that type of, uh, type
of work. Um, so I I I hope that helps. I
feel like I'm punting out an answer, but
uh, it it really it requires, I think, a
detailed discussion to to do that. I was
trying to ask more general question but
in a more generic form right right now
if there is an innovation idea usually
MIT students are working on it right the
software engineers from my company could
come and participate in those innovation
time with those yeah like I said I I
think it's doing it justice is kind of
difficult off off the cuff but there
things like getting involved in capstone
projects X and you know then and those
happen really across the institute
whether it's Sloan and data analytics or
uh you know in in computer science uh
but I I I I would I would definitely
talk to uh Peter about that and uh I
think he'd be happy to those ideas.
Yeah. Yeah. I think it's a great idea
and I know that yeah we we
we do that. I I could think of a few
different ways to answer that and
specific programs but uh absolutely.
Okay, we're going to take one more
question. Okay. Hi. So, I'm curious uh
to hear your thought about uh what do
you think about the interaction of
specific teams like talking about data
science teams versus software
engineering teams. Now with the
development of such you know there are a
lot of uh
abstractions like lchain like hagging
face like data science can do a lot more
but software engineering can do a lot
more too. So how do you see the teams
are changing now in terms of the scope
of the task and the interaction between
the two because you know in the past
traditionally data science teams were
more focused on data curation training
things like that and then they kind of
move it to the engineering team to scale
or
uh you know make it more robust but
today it's a bit different I feel so how
do you see it in your areas so in my
area I would they that they kind of
merging right you don't separate anymore
from just the data and the engineering
side cuz I mean I would say in the first
place it didn't make a lot of sense that
we did that I mean we did that because
we needed the specializations right um
to have people who are really good at
data science and people who are really
good at engineering and they couldn't do
both but at the end of the day we want
to solve a problem to focus on the
wholesome thing right so if we can have
people who can focus on both because
they get the support from the AI agents
where whatever we will be developing in
the future that I think is the way to
go. Yeah, I I would agree with that. I
see that more emerging right we see
software engineers need to do more
things with the data to understand
what's happening in the system you know
design experiments so that they
understand how things are performing
collect analyze it and so on. We need
the you know the data scientists as well
kind of moving into um you know and
merging more with the different uh you
know spaces the data engineers the
people who are maintaining and running
infrastructure. So I think the good news
is data science type skills needed kind
of much more pervasively and in many
more uh domains um uh not just you know
kind of as a you know in many
organization including IBM you know we
had kind of our data science silo um and
now it's it's really moving and emerging
and embedding uh data scientists in all
of these teams. I'm going to veer
left. So that for my industry at least,
we're a very highly regulated industry
with dealing with a lot of health data.
Um so data
scientists working with actual realtime
data is something that software
engineers generally haven't had real
access to in the past. they understand
some of the context of it, but
especially with like clinical analytics,
you don't really have software engineers
going in there and analyzing, but really
having to understand like population
health metrics for example. Um, so uh
there's for us at least there's still
sort of that separation between data
science teams and software engineering
teams. Um but there are other areas
especially in terms of like customer
relations and stuff like that that the
teams are sort starting to merge but
like our actual data science teams
they're sort of still like locked away
and they're operating as two separate
verticals.
Okay, I think we're uh going to wrap
things up. Let's hear it for our
panel. I I
also before I forget I want to thank our
AV people in the corner over here. I I
think uh MIT
audiovisisual you need to be a licensed
therapist to take that because you put
up with all my neurotic quest requests
all morning. Uh just a couple of things.
Uh we are going to have lunch now. So if
you want to network with people
hopefully you can now keep continue with
the exchange of ideas. I wish this forum
lasted a couple of days. It seems like
there's enough content. We also uh are
having in the afternoon the uh MIT
startup exchange live demo day. So we we
uh focused on getting startups that are
uh in the AI area or AI adjacent. So
it's a lot of great companies you can
see actually doing real things. And then
uh this is uh it's been kind of a secret
to now but we we're bringing in a bunch
of pizzas and beer at four o'clock. So
if you want to hang out and network then
it's um totally secret. We didn't uh
have registration for that. The the
password is pepperoni to to get into
that. So uh and I hope a lot of you hang
around and uh enjoy some pizza and beer
with us. Thank you. Thanks so much.