good afternoon and thanks uh for having
triangulate Labs here uh yeah as you
said I'm Bill Hall co-founder and CEO of
triangulate labs um I have three degrees
from MIT and served as a lecturer for a
few years so I'm excited to tell you
about our product Skin Map and to
explore how it might be useful um the
backstory of this I founded triangulate
Labs after I lost my little sister to a
rare cancer um that was not on the skin
um but that made me focus on cancer and
I realized there was a need to document
the skin in accurately for skin cancer
and it turns out for many other things
um so first I'll just say a quick bit
about skin cancer and then go on to some
of the other follow on someone dies from
skin cancer every four and a half
minutes and they don't really have to um
it's easy to cure when it's found early
and it's right here on our skin where we
should be able to find it early but we
don't um because to catch skin cancer in
110 million Americans at high risk and
many more around the world we need an
accurate test and people need to take
that test our best test is a total body
skin exam by a dermatologist which
hasn't been found sufficiently accurate
for screening by the US preventive
Services Task Force or many other bodies
around the world um but it has been
shown that if a dermatologist can see
how the skin is changing that they're
more accurate um there are some
approaches to doing this called total
body photography but the existing
systems uh for total body photography if
you're too cost prohibitive or slow for
the clinic so we built Skin Map which is
being used by dermatologists now they're
10 million dermatologists in the US uh
or 10 million patients who see
dermatologists uh in the US every year
but that's only about 10% of the at risk
population so for them we're developing
AI but let me just show you how the
basic skin documentation piece works
this is what's in the clinics now you
use um currently it's an iOS device on
and it's an app that runs on an iOS
device with an AWS back end so you
capture images by just passing the
smartphone over the skin our patented
software then recognizes where each
pixel belongs in the body so that then
you can compare and look at how it how
uh the skin looks now compared to how it
was before the software can
automatically reproject the 3D
information it's capturing into the same
perspective that you're looking at so
for instance if if something's changed
it seems to Blink at you which is why we
call this a blink detector um so the
dermatologists who like this uh the the
thing that really makes it work for them
is that it's fast it takes us 60 seconds
to capture about 500 images in a scan um
and that works in the clinic they can
fit it in a typical dermatologist sees
seven or eight patients per hour um the
competition is usually a 10 or 15 minute
process and to take take that long they
would need three times as many exam
rooms and space in their in their
clinics um a second direction we're
looking is remote clinical studies and
General Skin
documentation uh you probably all
understand in-person studies are
expensive you it limits the enrollment
to the catchment area of the Imaging
Center and uh so we're beginning with
one consumer goods company to look at
product testing and enabling uh going
out to remote studies uh and and
allowing the the participants to capture
the information better uh it also
because we're capturing 3D we can
measure without the 2D effects of
traditional
photography um more broadly we see the
potential to extend this to other areas
uh such as diagnosing rare diseases with
cutaneous
presentation um so uh we're interested
in collaboration of pilots and any those
areas I've discussed so related to
catching skin cancer deployment to
dermatologists and other uh providers um
helping with research that would benefit
from the ability to build large skin
data sets uh for use in accurately
measuring skin Evolution uh such as
decentralized studies and um expanding
internationally we're currently in the
us and we're very interested in going
internationally where we see the bigger
market for us so thank you my contact
info is there and uh look forward to
talking to you Bill thank you so much um
talking about um that geographies um and
all that how um what's the timeline that
you could share and also what costs
could be associated with this for
companies to work with
you um so for geographies
going some of the we're we're we're
early in the stage and so understanding
the regulatory uh effects if it's being
deployed in healthcare um and uh so
looking for partners who who've gone
there um the costs to use our system are
really pretty minimal it's it's an app
it's a scalable the main costs are Cloud
type costs um so it's uh it's it's
pretty
reasonable and um I guess it is fit for
tele medicine but could you expand a
little more on that sure yeah that's
that's a great observation um tele
medicine in fact we've got a study
kicking off uh with a collaborating
group in in mayo uh In
Minnesota where we're evaluating the
ability of dermatologists to recognize
skin cancers uh from Skin Map scans so
you could technically um reach in the US
there are 50 million Americans that uh
who don't have a dermatologist in the
area and they're at Double a risk of
death from melanoma so we want to we
want to reach out to them and right now
there's no good way to do that uh we
think Skin Map is going to work for that