I promise I'm going to be brief because
I hate to stand
between
um between everybody in their lunch um
but at first I gotta you know we should
have had a panel because I've got to
answer some of the questions that that
that you asked earlier especially of
Patty you asked whether um these
technological innovations were who they
going to benefit whose Ox is going to
get gored and who's going to get rich as
a result of them and uh and what she
said was exactly right um the media
laboratory is about democratization it
is about that and and that is our dream
and our hope does that dream always work
out I can't say but what I can do is
something I hate to do which is when
somebody asks me a question instead of
giving them the answer I tell them where
they can look for the answer right you
know and I'm going to do that but
there's a new book out called power and
Progress written by Deron asoglu and
Simon Johnson uh at the Sloan School in
MIT and it's it's kind of thick but it's
a good read and it it dwells on exactly
that historically from the Middle Ages
to the present and the future and and
the results are are are um surprising
okay in the sense that sometimes it does
benefit some differentially and other
times it is a democratizing agent so I I
commend that book to you Simon is going
to join us at the media lab in in a
couple of weeks um the second question I
could spend all day on and I won't and
that was um about
misinformation and uh uh boy
you know there's good newss and there's
bad news right I mean misinformation and
detection of of misinformation has been
widely studied and it's imperfect
because nobody can characterize what
misinformation is is it Omission is it
bias is it a deliberate lie and what's
even worse is that we've seen the
Perfection of a variety of techniques
originated by Geral in World War II
where if you give people enough
information you undermine their
epistemological epistemological basis
for making a decision in other words if
I pepper you with lies you won't be able
to deduce the truth from among them
because your ability to reason has been
undermined by all of those but the good
news is um we will get better at it and
you don't have to be perfect the bad
news is who cares okay because the
people who are biased by misinformation
are not going to use Hussein's app and
they're not going to use Patty's app and
they're not going to look for the truth
because that's the problem as well um so
it's it's difficult and I could I could
spend forever on it you know the
statement the lies travel around the
world before the truth gets its boots on
um that statement was made by Jonathan
Swift 300 years ago so this problem is
pervasive and what you don't know
necessarily is the followon sentence to
that which is that and by the time the
truth catches up it's done its damage um
so indeed it is a problem and indeed
many of us in the laboratory work on it
I also omitted from when I gave you the
introduction um something that should be
clear in what what goes on throughout
the laboratory as a whole and that is
that um to some extent AI is an
infrastructure it's been part of our
course since the beginning Marvin Minsky
was in the AI lab uh sorry in the media
lab um from well before it started so
we've been developing that kind of thing
but it's implicit it's implicit in the
work that goes on throughout the
laboratory because that's the goal
solving human ends as Patty demonstrated
and AI is an
infrastructure um to do that so I'm
going to give you a couple of examples
of of of the work in my group and I I
promise I I won't keep you uh for for
very long and some of you will be able
to go and and try them um but the idea
is is that wisdom perspective
observation okay speculation imagination
introspection Common Sense humor these
are all facets of of of Being Human that
we have not yet implemented in a machine
okay uh maybe someday we will and there
are people who believe in self-driving
cars and all kinds of M magic like Ai
and stuff like that that it will become
perfect and it will become human and it
and it will become intelligent um I
believe like many of the others who
you've heard uh today uh that uh that
doesn't matter in the long run because
in the immediate term we can use these
systems to make us better and Patty
showed you several examples of it um so
so the idea is is to use AI in service
of these human traits of these traits of
wisdom of these traits of speculation of
these traits of of observation that
haven't been implemented in machines
when I was in high school I and my group
of friends would wander around and the
people that we admired most were people
who simply walked around noticing things
these were people who would say to you
did you know that there's a different
version of Columbus's ships every 6 feet
in the 59th Street lumus Circle subway
station in New York or Marvin walking
down the street with Nicholas musing to
himself and turning to Nick and saying I
wonder how glue works it was observation
it was noticing it was being prodded and
thinking about new things so that's the
kind of stuff that that my my group
works on the means by which we do that
is through interactions I've spent my
life building interactive systems the
goal is that we learn through activity
and conversation the goal is that we
learn through that action if I could
inject French or tennis into your head
you wouldn't know French or tennis you
might have some facility with it but it
is the experience of interacting and
learning it which is the vehicle for
learning when we tried doing this 40
years ago it was unbelievably
complicated because if you wanted to
make something interactive you had to
essentially create and in advance all of
the options and Alternatives and twists
and turns that that conversation might
make plus you had to lace them together
into a coherent hole it was a lot of
work and not only that Society wasn't
even necessarily ready for it so they
weren't used to that form of interaction
people thought of video as a laid-back
experience you just let it flow over you
they didn't think of it as something
that that could draw you in well things
have changed for one thing there's lots
of data out there
so you don't have to gather it all for
another maybe there's some help in
organizing it um by using some of the
large language models that we have to
give you some sense of the benefit of
that conversation one of the ways that I
often describe it is to say look your
mother isn't always right but you do
learn something from talking with her
usually and so so you do so so the nice
thing about building systems that are
based on this interaction is that the
system you're interacting with needn't
be perfect okay we're not building
answer machines where if the answer is
wrong it's a problem we're building
machines whose goal is to provoke whose
goal is to create activity whose goal is
to inspire and let you do things so up
there is is one of one of the examples
that that some people are interested in
um this is an organizational
representation of the 4,000 projects in
in the recent memory of of of the media
laboratory so when I told you what the
diversity of the laboratory was this is
a an example a portrayal of of exactly
that diversity now if if I want to
consign somebody to infinite hell and
they ask me about the media lab then I
say oh that's easy just go to our
website that that could take forever and
you'll never find what you're looking
for so instead we took the raw text of
those 4,000 projects created an
embedding of them about 1500 vectors
then created a visualization of that and
used that text to Cluster the
information and see which correlates
with it so the different colored dots on
that screen are representations of the
different groups within the laboratory
and the clustering shows the overlaps
and the title now of course as you can
imagine you can zoom in and explore that
and go all the way down to the project
level and you can see which projects are
are close by and adjacent to that um
more
interestingly what you can also do is
you can play a movie of how that's
developed over the years so in this case
i' I've given you just a snapshot not
the entire movie um but the snapshot
here is showing what the lab was like
from
1984 until around 2000 the groupings
change the clusterings change it's all
Dynamic and uh and the areas of you can
see have changed and evolved over the
years from what it was in
1984 um to what it is to what it is
today um in addition to that you can
view this data in the context of other
data sets so what you're looking at now
is the media
lab's domains of research overlapped and
viewed in the context of published
papers by Microsoft research okay so
Microsoft research is shown in yellow
our work is shown in purple you can see
the areas where there's overlaps you can
see the areas where there's differences
between those two now the clusterings
may not be perfect they may not be exact
but the idea is for you to be able to
explore those and think of ideas and
think of overlaps with your own data and
with your own goals and if you like you
can take this system and propose a
project of course you can search but
this is about exploration not search
likewise it's about provocation so you
can propose a project you can propose a
project by picking ones that exist and
saying what happens if I merge these two
can you help me create a project that's
the admixture of both of those and we
can do that very often what it comes up
with is a absurd not not something that
you would necessarily want to do but
that doesn't matter you see because
that's the conversation with your mother
it doesn't matter what happens is it's
there for you to learn it's not there
for it to learn you can propose your own
project and it will find ones that
overlap and coincide with that um well
who cares about that well it turns
out um that when we talk with our
supporters in the laboratory they've
found uses for this kind of thing that
that we never thought of they use it for
competitive intelligence and they take
public data to find out what other
companies are doing and what other ideas
are becoming popular and they use that
to explore that rich database and decide
where they're going some of them like
Delite uses it for example for
brainstorming now you bring a group of
people together and you start putting up
data and information unstructured that's
the whole point our system and what
large language models um bring to the
table as they bring you the ability to
have some proposed structure presented
to you and computed for you so they use
it as a brainstorming solution others
use it to explore the patent space one
of the databases we have is uh I forgot
how many a million patents you know from
the last 10 years you can explore those
and find holes in the world of of patent
space some people use it for marketing a
variety of people use it just simply to
organize their own corporate history
you've probably run across this right
especially if you're in a large
corporation the most valuable people in
that Corporation are the people who know
what everyone else is doing not
necessarily because they've done it all
themselves these are the critical social
nodes that um distribute information
throughout the company everybody's got
records prints and all of these kinds of
things can you ever find any of those
and that was what originally motivated
us with the media lab's research and the
answer is no um where are we going to go
with it well we're going to take it in a
lot of other directions obviously the
question is begged to make it be
multimedia so it's not just words that
it takes um but rather that it accepts
pictures and sounds and movies and
slides and all of those kinds of of data
so the integration of all of of those is
is what we're doing and allowing you to
manipulate the clustering is another
kind of one of the the next obvious
Dimensions we've dictated the clustering
and the layout of the graph but letting
you play with that as a plastic surface
to explore as well as using it as a lens
into which to focus is probably where
we're going to take that next for those
of you who are coming by the laboratory
you'll be able to see it for those of
you who are not you are welcome to use
it uh the URL I should have put in the
slides is latent lab. a okay so and
that's public so you can do that you're
welcome to look at the media labs and
all of the other public databases that
are in the system there's nothing
private to it and so feel free to
explore all by yourself so that's an
example of what we do um it's
provocative it's conversational it's a
learning system it's it's not a
searching system it's an exploration
system another thing that we work on is
more specul speculative rather and and
the idea is for those of you who are you
know American or in the United States
you probably heard there's a television
show called Last Week Tonight by John
Oliver it's a I actually like like the
show well we said about the task of
saying what if we could make our own
show and we'll call it next week tonight
okay so in this case now what we're
doing is we're using um Ai and these
large language models to speculate or
predict the future but really as an
exploration engine for you now if you
think about the future particularly with
respect to things like news I don't know
how much of you how many of you are news
mavens but if you read the newspaper
most of the time or listen to the radio
most of the time tomorrow's news is the
same as today's okay yeah we had seven
days of speculation before the debates
um a couple of weeks ago and then when
the debates came along we had three days
of speculation as to who did best in in
the debates right but pretty much it's
like Steph J ghoul's theory of evolution
we live in a world of punctuated
equilibrium and that is to say things
move along in a predictable way and then
there's suddenly a major event like an
asteroid falling in Mexico that changes
that equilibrium or the Cambrian
explosion that changes that so if you
think about it and look at it maybe it's
a bit like a power law most often
tomorrow's news is going to be like
today's and the impact that that's going
to have the unforeseen impact is is
small but
occasionally less often than continuity
there'll be a weather event maybe
there's going to be a flood maybe a
hurricane form something like that and
the impact of that is greater uh maybe
someone will discover a new source of
lithium and that will change the balance
of how we build Energy Systems and
batteries in the future or
Transportation you never know uh a barge
or a ship might crash into a bridge uh
it's been known to happen but you know
there are Transportation things the
impact of which is larger and the
occurrence of them is rarer and of
course nuclear disasters uh let's hope
those are extremely rare but we know
that the impact of those is higher so
now what we can do is we can both take
that and we can take your own
suggestions as to what you think might
disrupt your operations and I don't know
whether it's a business plan or whether
you're just planning a picnic for the
weekend and say what would happen if the
following things occurred Federal
Reserve reduces interest rates by 2%
which I suppose by now they might well
have done uh if not they'll be doing it
later this
afternoon and you we can create for you
a set of news articles that show and a
narrative form what the impact of those
might be and allow you to explore and
juggle those I showed you my power law
of Impact versus versus likelihood of
occurrence but you all have a different
one because you all have your own set of
potentially disruptive events and what
you want to see is what might happen if
any of those occurred so we present that
as news and let you interact with that
the narrative is important because it
needs to be again conversational and
draw you out in a way that a list or an
Excel spreadsheet wouldn't so that's
where we be come truly speculative where
making up the news I have no idea
whether this is a good idea or a bad
idea um but it's an example of one of
the kinds of things that that we're
going to try and we're going to test and
see how much we can learn from we're not
going to test how accurate we are okay
we're not going to wait for those black
swans to occur because let's hope that
many of them don't occur but we're going
to test whether you are prepared learned
or what would happen in a variety of
scenarios associated with those and
finally and I'm only going to talk about
this one very briefly um we're trying to
use these interactions in real scenarios
to allow you to explore and learn and
focus and concentrate so this is a
project on audio focus the Genesis of
which was simply to allow you to use
your head to focus your attention so
that you could diminish the background
distractions that make it hard and allow
you to focus more on what you wanted to
hear I have an image of friends with a
hearing aid they put the microphone down
on the table but they get all the noise
from the rest of the restaurant and it's
very difficult for them to direct that
attention or think of sitting at a
Thanksgiving table dinner and you end up
having a conversation with the people on
your end but sometimes you need a way to
be able to focus on and bring into
attention the others so we're using that
and we're using AI to change and
disambiguate and clarify the sounds that
you can hear and there are uses for that
that we didn't even think of when we
started like for example if you have a
debate where several people are talking
in turn maybe you can organize that
debate by topic let them all talk at
once and you can let your attention go
between the so that you can pick out
what you want to learn from that debate
in onethird of the time as opposed to
listening to the entire time so that's
all I'm going to say now and I won't
keep you long from lunch but keep in
mind that's the idea it's that diversity
it's that merging of passion fun and the
search for knowledge and that ability to
work across disciplines and across ideas
that characterize the way we do
invention ions people think we innovate
I don't think we innovate I was finally
told the difference between invention
and Innovation by a friend Jack
Greenberg who was CEO of McDonald's for
a while he said I get it Andy um
Innovation invention is a bunch of guys
messing around in the laboratory
Innovation is a change in business
process we concentrate on the invention
but it isn't messing it's pointing you
the way for you to innovate in the
future so I hope you enjoyed the morning
and we'll talk again thank you thank you
very much
Andie thank you again okay