It is uh my pleasure to introduce our
next speaker uh Morgan Andrea. He is the
executive director of the future energy
systems and the MIT NE Alliance at the
MIT Energy Initiative which is
affectionately known as Mighty. So let's
let's give a warm welcome for Morgan.
>> Thanks Jim. Uh, good morning or I guess
good afternoon everybody and I know
we're getting really close to lunch so
I'm going to try to move this along
quickly. Um, thank you to Jim and the
ILP team for giving us a giving me a
chance to tell you a little bit about
some of our activities in the data
center space.
Um, I did want to explain a little bit
about mighty the MIT energy initiative.
We are an umbrella group that tries to
work with industry to sponsor research
on campus on energy topics. We're not a
department and that's by design
recognizing that a lot of these energy
topics are interdisciplinary and cut
across many different departments and
groups. And so the uh motivation behind
creating our group was to try to create
uh a focus on some of these energy
topics and and create the ability to
pull in the right resources. So we work
with researchers in pretty much every
department across campus on energy
topics whether it's engineering,
fundamental physics and chemistry,
economics, policy, um all different
aspects.
data center power challenge. As we focus
on energy, one of the big topics right
now that's getting a lot of attention is
uh energy topics related to data
centers. And there's there's multiple
different dimensions of this topic,
which makes it complicated, which makes
it an interesting problem for us to work
on. Um for the last 15 years or so,
there has not been a whole lot of growth
in electricity demand in the US. Um
there's a variety of different reasons
for that, but that is changing in the
last couple years. And I think one of
the the elements that's really driving
that demand is uh more demand for data
center power. Uh probably 10 years ago,
a lot of the data centers that were
getting built were
somewhere in the 10 to 30 megawatt size
scale. um today much much bigger and I
think it's not just uh electricity for
data science there's also a lot of
electricity for other applications
uh EV uh decarbonization of
manufacturing
um a variety of other uh demands
electrification of buildings um and
again this is a paper from Lawrence
Berkeley but there are projections that
in the next 5 years or so demand for uh
data center power as a as a fraction of
the whole US electricity demand could
grow to somewhere between 6 to 12%. So
that's a a big increase.
Uh and again I think this uh this
demand growth um raises a lot of
questions. I think there have been a
number of different uh
periods over the last 20 years where new
technology in the software space has
created a lot of excitement, a lot of
investment. I'd say this one is a little
different in that it's driving a lot of
investment in hardware and in equipment.
Um, and if you look at the lower left
chart, that sort of shows where we're
seeing a lot of this investment. And I
think there's a talk coming up later,
but it's it's a lot of big investment
from the big tech companies. Um, it's
not all evenly distributed. It is
concentrated in a few different places.
If you drive around Northern Virginia,
it is amazing the amount of of new
construction
with these these massive sites. Um, and
that's just a picture of one in Lowden
County, Virginia, which is a little bit
west of DC. Uh so that's one of the big
focus areas for building out this this
infrastructure. Um but I think as we see
this infrastructure getting built out
that does raise lots of complicated
questions. How are we going to deliver
that power when our grid isn't set up to
to manage those loads?
How do we meet the demand? How much
power is really uh going to be needed? I
think there's still some uncertainty
there. When is it going to be needed?
Where are we going to have that load?
What's the impact of putting that load
in different places? Um and and how does
that interact with the grid? So, I think
those are all complicated questions. Um
we're trying to pull together again
researchers across campus. We are doing
work on these topics today. Um and we're
creating something called the data
center power forum. We're going to
leverage some of the consortium work
that we're already doing and try to pull
together industry partners to sponsor
work in this area and address some of
the critical cross-disciplinary
questions that I think are really
important here. And I think you know
ultimately our goal is to help um
identify what are the big challenges and
help our members understand what are the
the uh potential solutions, what are the
trade-offs, what are the complexities
and hopefully also have some influence
on policy makers and building consensus
across industry to define the path
forward. And again, we're not an
advocacy group, but we are trying to
make sure people have the best
information possible when they make
decisions on these these um topics
that'll influence our power system for
the foreseeable future. This is just a
snapshot with lots of words on it and
I'll just highlight a couple points. So
it's these are existing projects that we
have today on a lot of the relevant
topics on infrastructure on the supply
of energy.
Where do we put those data centers? that
has a big impact on the supply side of
the question in terms of what resources
are available in different locations and
and what's the the impact on emissions
of putting your data center in Northern
Virginia versus West Texas versus the
Pacific Northwest.
the electricity uh grid in those
locations is quite a bit different and
so the overall impact um you know we can
see very different impacts with those
those sighting choices. Um looking at at
grid management and design
um as we were just hearing about cyber
security is a big issue resiliency
um is is critical particularly for the
data centers. I I think one of the
things that we are going to face is as
we're bringing on all of this new load
um how do we do that in a way that
doesn't disrupt the stability of the
rest of the grid particularly with some
of the the hyperscalers being committed
to sustainable power. Right? I think
we're likely to see a lot more
renewables coming online. But again, how
does that impact resiliency and and our
ability to have firm power? Um, and
again, as as I mentioned, a lot of this
ties into policy questions. And so we
work pretty closely with the Sloan
School with policy experts here on
campus to try to identify some of these
these questions and look at um you know
what happens when we put power uh a new
big load on the grid. What are the
options? Are there options where we can
put it behind the meter? Is that a
faster way forward to enable us to meet
that power demand? Does that negatively
impact the grid if we suddenly have a
bunch of loads behind the meter and we
don't have some of our our big power
companies participating as actively in
the grid for everybody? If we put it on
the grid, who pays for those upgrades to
transmission? So these are all questions
that are that are complex and I think
figuring out the right path forward
again will have a have a big impact on
our energy system and and certainly I
think a lot of topics around
infrastructure whether that's the design
of the buildings whether that's um
looking at how do we supply backup power
how do we optimize the energy storage
with UPS and backup power together um
can we be smarter about how we design
some of those systems to make them more
robust. And and I think one of the big
questions again that gets into computing
and uh data center design and um a
number of different use cases is what
kind of flexibility do we have in our
computing and do we have what's the
opportunity with flexibility to optimize
our investment in our energy system. So,
I think that's a really complicated
question that again our our researchers
are excited to to dig into. I think
there's a lot of other questions here
that we're digging into and looking at.
I'd be happy to to talk with any of you
afterwards if you if you want to talk
more. I would like to uh point out two
of our our team members, JJ Laidus and
Deep Da who's going to be our program
manager um who are also here and we're
happy to chat with any of you later. But
again, like I said, the the whole point
here is to try to bring together
industry partners and researchers to
address some of these these really
complicated interesting questions.
Um, with that, I'll pause for questions
and maybe give back a little bit of
time. Yeah.
Traffic Arabi AMD on your forecast for
power demand. I wonder like uh at what
point do you think nuclear power would
become maybe the only or the most
lucrative option for data centers?
>> Great question. Um I think there's a lot
of interest in nuclear as a pathway for
uh lowcarbon firm power. Um we're seeing
a lot of investment um by some of the
hyperscalers uh and some of the big
utilities u in expanding the capacity of
existing nuclear sites. I think the only
there's two big challenges with nuclear.
One is the cost. Two the timing in order
to bring a new facility online. I I
think there's a high probability that
we'll see more nuclear in the pipeline.
Current administration seems to to uh
support it. Um I think it'll happen, but
I do think the the time for us to bring
those loads online is 5 to 10 years. I
mean those those that capacity online 5
to 10 years the data centers are getting
built today. So, I think it's it's just
not we're not going to be able to bring
that new power online
quickly enough in the form of nuclear. I
think it's probably a lot easier to
bring solar online more quickly,
although it is not as currently in in
fashion with the the current
administration.
>> Hi, uh Gene Vincent Avon, thanks for the
talk. Really good. You mentioned there's
some particular areas where there's a
lot of construction going on and you
said specifically like Virginia I think.
So what's driving that? Why? And then
the talk we heard before you was okay
maybe we want to build it somewhere else
where it's cooler. I didn't see any big
dots in in those areas. So
>> what what's going on? Why can't we drive
it to be in the right spot?
>> Yeah. Uh I mean I it's I think happening
in a couple spaces for good reasons for
for rational reasons let's say not maybe
not good for rational reason. So in
Northern Virginia there's scale with a
lot of the infrastructure and the um
skill sets needed to build a new data
center. So when you go to build a new
data center in Lowden County or Fairfax
County or further out in near Co Pepper
or one of those towns, you just call
somebody up and say, "Hey, we're
building another data center. They've
got all of the skilled workforce right
there ready to do it. They've just built
10 data centers. One more. No big deal."
So not every area of the country has
those skills and sort of the
not quite as easy to deploy them. I
think there are some other areas of the
country that have um they've
from what I understand from a regulatory
perspect perspective made it a lot
easier to bring new power online and um
and and made it favorable to site some
of the data centers in terms of
economically providing power fairly
quickly. I'm thinking of Texas in
particular. Um, I think there's no
reason we couldn't put some of these
data centers in other locations and
there might be some advantages
um to doing that, but it would require a
um, you know, proactive, thoughtful
policy approach,
which again we hope to inform with some
of this work. So, thank you.
>> Okay, let's hear it from Morgan.