so uh Richards please take over and tell
us a story of the
journey well thank you
vadir um nice to meet everybody nice uh
nice to be back again uh four years
later for Nano Explorations um uh
Vladimir is correct I'm no longer at MIT
so I gave my talk in 2020 I graduated in
2021 uh and have been with active
surfaces now uh for about two years so
my current
role uh is in being uh one of the
operational co-founders and chief
technology officer my co-founder shiv
bakta is also an MIT grad uh in the
MBA uh MS program he comes from us doe
Department of energy both of us have
some VC experiment
background um just maybe a month ago or
so we closed a preed round uh so we're
very early stage company we're at about
eight people now full-time 15 if you
include uh all of our part-time staff
and we're really excited about kind of
what the future holds uh with us uh and
our
growth publicly we're known pretty much
as a Solar Company that's what I gave my
talk on in 2020 uh but but the reality
is is that we're actually a printed
electronics company uh we do a few
different things that uh have come out
of MIT most notably uh the thin film
flexible solar cells that have hit MIT
news but also uh some PE electric and Ms
work uh that we do mostly in
Partnerships with other companies uh now
why is this uh the reality is just like
PVD cvd and other things that kind of
the MIT Nano Community would be working
on uh printed electronics are also a
plat form technology uh so if you can
dissolve it in an ink and you can put it
into kind of a slot die head uh you can
print different materials and
semiconductor systems and ultimately
provide value for different sort of end
use
cases uh but we mostly work on energy
today uh and so I'll give a little bit
of background and kind of like
why uh solar of course everybody sort of
knows this but uh We've installed a lot
it's a relatively uh large Market
operationally since it's kind of
beginning of growth uh in the 50s in the
Space Race uh Humanity has collectively
installed about a terawatt uh in terms
of 2023 uh but to fully decarbonize we
need about 20 terawatts uh and that's
just a low uh a low capacity projection
the reality is probably it will need to
be closer to 30 to 50 terawatts uh to
account for things like
electrification uh and other
directionalities um
that's a lot of solar and that's a lot
of land most of the time we kind of put
these in
fields um but the better way to do it is
to put it in places where we've already
built um The Challenge though is that
it's very expensive it's about $3 a watt
to put solar on a rooftop only about 10%
of that ends up being the actual
Electronics uh and the rest of it is
really just installation and structural
labor and it's all really kind of uh pin
held by silicon which is the core
technology in about 98% of the market
today uh it's really heavy uh and
because of kind of its brittle nature uh
as a uh as a wafer ceramic it has to be
encased in at least three three mimers
of glass uh surrounded by aluminum to
prevent damage this makes each
individual panel about 60 pounds you put
this on a building that's a lot of
weight um with the form factor sizes and
kind of the limitations of uh 4inch
Wafers which is what solar started on
and then going to six-inch wafers
uh form factors have not changed uh
meaning that labor teams uh and
deployment is
unoptimized uh and the reality is this
kind of limits where you can put them
and again we mostly put these in
fields um in the commercial Market which
is where we as a company kind of pursue
only about 3% of rooftops actually have
solar um but the reality is due to these
constraints only about 30% of buildings
can actually be
accessed uh and this limitation is not
not a theoretical number it's actually
being hit in places like Japan and
Singapore which do have kind of maxed
out penetrations around the 30% Mark uh
in the us alone this leaves about 20 gws
of
opportunity uh just on commercial
buildings so that's not even like
households that's not even uh you know
all the solar we would ever need and our
approach is really to kind of uh solve
this problem with something that's
lightweight integratable Deployable and
much easier to
installed um but my talk is not on the
technology of active surfaces today and
kind of what we're pursuing but kind of
uh where I started so my talk about four
years ago was on manufacturing large
area prop skites um and I'm not going to
go through the whole talk uh it was
midway through my uh
PhD uh but just give a little background
prets are these really
interesting uh absorbers uh for the
solar Market uh they're very interesting
Material Science compounds lots of
opportunity in terms of different things
you can discover uh but my work at M was
all on around the hidden challenges of
manufacturing so toxicity that goes into
kind of printing these things how we go
and make new ink systems that can
actually deploy these at relatively
cost-efficient ways uh and then some of
the other hidden things that need to go
into final uh module manufacturing like
EPA limitations around uh toxicity and
the use of lead and kind of the work
that we were doing solving
it um active surfaces uh did spin out of
this and I could tell kind of the whole
story but it's very long uh the real I
gave the talk in 2020 um I ended up
giving my defense also over
Zoom uh on kind of the final results of
what this accomplished which was really
kind of high production speeds and high
efficiencies in the range of like
20% uh I did that mid
2021 active surfaces was founded July
11th
2022 I would meet shiv my
co-founder uh just a few months after
that uh in the fall semester of 2020
uh3 and then we'd go on and start uh
actually generating kind of the
motivation that most people see us
publicly we first uh our first public
pitch competition was the Harvard
climate Symposium that same year uh shiv
pitched at the MIT 100K pitch uh and
then that really propelled us into to
real spinning out of MIT uh which for us
started at Greentown Labs uh and I'm
currently sitting in our new office in
wubber
Massachusetts through that timeline
we've gone through pretty much three
eras uh
formation uh where it was really just me
and I was trying to paper the company
and find a
direction uh to meet eating shiv going
from two people and then eventually to
our first two
interns uh where we're trying to
generate excitement toine ourselves
Define what the company was going to
establish Define what we were going to
try to pursue uh and then to today uh
having closed the preed of around five
and a half million growing out the team
building our new lab space uh and really
trying to get to something
commercial uh and so I thought an
interesting and fun thing to do is to
actually tell three stories from these
three stages of active surfaces and kind
of my takeaways and
Reflections so the first one which is
not that fun of a story uh but one
that's interesting
nonetheless in the very early days uh I
got kicked out of iore and then got
immediately backstabbed by a friend and
so context here is relatively important
um uh again it was just me in the
company I had graduated at this time uh
I came off of an intership in VC uh and
we had kind of this uh early inkling
that there was something interesting
with regards to my PhD work and others
uh to kind of form it into a startup and
pursue something valuable but uh in the
Deep Tech world it's really hard to know
exactly where you need to go
commercially and so a lot of those early
questions were kind of where to start
how to start what do we pursue and why
um and so I was trying to find uh the
direction for the company at that point
we were called the
year uh which I think is a funny story I
did the engine blueprints program and
then the nsfi core uh right after that
uh and at the same time because it was
just me it was a lot of uh burden in
terms of the work in terms of spinning
out what the company was actually going
to be and really papering
everything um so a lot of things were
going on nothing was really solidified
and what ended up happening
is uh I did iore largely because at the
time we thought Acoustics was more
interesting to start with
first um and if you've ever done iore
you know that it's an interview uh
numbers game so you have about three
weeks you know I think you have to hit
something like 50 interviews on customer
Discovery you report back they critique
you on kind of how well you did um about
two weeks in it was clear I wasn't going
to hit it uh I know now that the
Acoustics Market is very Consolidated
and the amount of people that I can
actually approach is not very big um and
my mentor in iore program after those
two weeks said you're not putting in
enough effort you're clearly not
interested and you should just drop out
figure out what you want to do and then
maybe do this
later that hurt at the same
time I was introduced to a friend who
had a
friend uh and a small team interested in
kind of joining early stage startup they
were part of the MIT Network and I was
kind of doing the founder matching you
know uh dating aspect to try to uh
reduce some of this burden that I was
really stressed out about uh trying to
find where to go and what to do now
ultimately it didn't work
out um I think they had different
mindsets about what active surfaces
should have been ramp up timelines were
aggressive for my taste and what I
thought was accomplishable with a new
semiconductor based Tech technology and
it was clear they didn't really value
engineering uh and wanted to place a
high focus on Business Development which
also I didn't really like so I told them
that we needed to go our separate ways
I'd find out something else to do or do
this on my own as a soul founder uh and
that group ended up forming a separate
company within a few days and attempted
to license uh the MIT patents out from
under me in order to pursue something
without me involved and I like the story
because that is why active Services is
founded on July 11th um it wasn't this
culmination of people it wasn't this uh
culmination of ideas there's nothing you
know uh Bountiful about it uh active
surfaces got founded July 11th uh and
has the name active surfaces because it
was the least aggressive name it was
free with Delaware C uh filings and we
needed a company fast to start trying to
uh not have the license ripped out away
from
us now ultimately uh this got solved
very quickly uh at the time it was
horrible uh I felt like the company was
going to die before it even
started uh but you have to remember
about a month later I met shiv uh and
about three months after that uh we
started winning our prize
monies uh and so the company is still
fine again we're we're up at 10 people
now uh but my takeaways
here uh kind of in these early days uh
that I share with you is that uh with
regards to iore and kind of this idea
around customer
Discovery most startup programs kind of
lean on uh a method Top by Steve blank
Stanford uh which is kind of the lean uh
startup model uh in and around Agile
development uh and it's really good you
know it works for many many startups it
works for for getting sort of that early
sort of business Direction uh it is
adopted by just about every program so
it's adopted by NSF iore theb the engine
blueprints program does it too anytime
you see a program that gives you a
business model canvas it almost
certainly originated uh from Steve
blank
um lean startups rely on Direct Customer
interviews that's the first thing you do
you start asking about value uh try to
get value of the thing that you'd
eventually sell
um with deep Tech the thing I've learned
going through this now four years in is
that this is actually the wrong question
um you should not be this early on
asking customers for feedback on a thing
that doesn't exist you should be asking
if this thing does exist how does it
change consumer Behavior now of course
that still relies on on knowing the
market and talking to people but asking
what their actual value is to pay is is
kind of
useless uh and similarly in those early
days especially when I was looking for a
co-founder I was asking the wrong
question I was asking for someone to
spread the workload with me I was
looking for operators people who who
knew things like I didn't like
taxes or uh how to assess uh different
sort of top- down Market
models uh and that was wrong because I
shouldn't have been searching for
someone to take the load off me I should
have been asking who can I rely on to
push the vision forward
and ultimately that ended up being the
more successful way to find a co-founder
um again I met shiv and we've done great
together uh since
then second thing I want to share with
you is that uh and again if you know us
we we ended up winning MIT 100K in
2023 uh but we bombed at the rice
business plan
competition uh one day
before uh so set the scene again uh
we're now two people in the company uh
we're in a phase where we're established
we're
papered and we're trying to figure out
uh and generate a lot of excitement
around the motivation and the idea you
know um this was actually shiv's idea
this was not mine so I gave him all the
credit uh and ultimately he was right is
to sort of uh Market yourselves and
Market the team as early as
possible um so we were trying to build
this momentum uh we were applying to
just about everything we could um but we
couldn't actually do anything
operationally we had no money uh I was
not taking a salary at the time shiv was
still in school uh and we're doing all
this to kind of find investors and gain
some
traction
uh so what ended up
happening so success is objective uh I
guess we did officially win something
although it was a minor prize uh it was
on the uh sustainable investment prize
um the reality is that the major prizes
were in multi-millions of dollars I
think upwards of like three to four
million were actually given out uh at
this
competition uh everybody who won was a
SAS company or a fintech
company uh and this was a big letdown
for us because Houston uh the center of
oil is known as the city of energy uh
and we thought that being an energy
based kind of play uh with regards to
our our commercial direction would
actually resonate here uh and it didn't
the the judges were extremely judgmental
about our uh timelines to development uh
or technology Readiness levels uh they
were mostly Angel groups uh who wanted
to give out kind of small money and get
really high returns uh and it was just a
really big letdown at the end of the day
um
um right after that uh right after that
that photo was taken we spent 12 hours
in the Houston Airport uh on a delayed
flight uh we got into Boston I think
like 2 am uh I live up here in saem
Massachusetts so I didn't get home till
3:00
a.m. uh and the MIT 100K I think I we
had to be there like 11 or 12 something
like that for uh pre-practice before the
event actually started now the result of
this is that we actually won uh we s
house we had both the audience award uh
and won the full thing uh very proud of
that I think it was a very key milestone
in our
development uh but a big takeaway here
for me uh as I move
forward is
that in the early stages of being a
startup you have lots and lots of ups
and downs um it can get very mentally
exhausting one week you're on a high the
next week you think the company's going
to go under and it's this cyclic you
know rise and fall where you don't
really know where you're going to land
and it takes a lot of mental
perseverance uh something I still kind
of remind myself of that
like if things are bad today they will
be better tomorrow and I shouldn't get
myself down but a quote that I really
resonate with uh through this is that
even if the company does poorly uh my
career will actually be fine uh the
path of going through this is more
important uh than the overall outcome in
terms of the entire
industry um now through this again we
were successful uh that Rice business
plan was kind of a lull and an otherwise
relatively successful year for us uh we
operated out of Greentown Labs we
actually still do to a minor extent uh
did relatively well at clean teac openen
uh and we're part of a number of uh
smaller like Excel the Swiss next
climate collider Venture for climate
Tech and now we're still in third
derivative ET program uh so overall we
did really well uh and I'm ultimately
really proud of where uh we came through
on that year um getting to the growth
stage um and this is kind of more just a
funny story for me um which we're still
in by the way uh we we closed our
financing earlier this year uh we've
been building building building ever
since we're actually still hiring um so
I'm just going to make that as my first
plug of that um this was our lab about
two months ago uh I think that one week
we had the first of many shipments come
in and the the whole thing looked like a
mess um and the reality is that uh some
of the things again the compressed dryer
system has been one of the biggest pains
in my ass for about six months now um
we're a chemistry company uh Material
Science company um manufacturing company
however you want to describe it
[Music]
um and it was clear to us very very
early on that we needed nitrogen and
clean dry air uh in order to support our
entire kind of tool set um we started
this even before we closed financing I'm
kind of specking this out uh nitrogen is
relatively easy to install if you ever
have to do it um you mostly just go to
air gas and get permitting uh it takes a
long period of time to do that uh but
for us the clean dry air was actually
unique uh we spec it out pretty
differently to how most people
would uh they have very specific
requirements and and I would consider a
non-standard
installation uh kind of due to our
specific
needs um and installing it has been an
absolute nightmare
it took about two months to pick it out
I think I rotated through like three or
four
Consultants uh trying to to estimate
what what we needed and why and and sort
of pick out something despite the fact
that we didn't have a good idea of
everything we'd eventually
build um when you're an early stage
startup and you don't have credit
ordering something of that size can be a
hassle too uh so we ordered it had to
prepay for everything uh even though
delivery and timelines I think took
about two and a half
months uh when we finally got it uh we
moved it in and wired it uh we don't
have a loading dock so that was a hassle
uh and one of the legs actually got
damaged kind of in
transit our initial electrician wired it
wrong uh then our machine installer who
was supposed to Plum it into our CDA
line plumbed it wrong uh then went back
and rewired it wrong and it's been this
kind of cylic cylic issue uh and the
last fun thing is that even when it got
in and it was finally plumbed right and
finally wired right now it overheats uh
based on where it is and so we need to
install kind of direct exhaust to this
machine and it's safe to say that my
entire team probably all 15 of us at
some point has put time and effort into
contributing some way that this uh
compressor gets in uh to our lab now I
think it's relevant uh in this story to
give kind of a brief history of
compressed dry air uh compressed air was
first used industrial settings in the
1820s uh the first portable ones uh were
used in uh
1857 uh kind of that photo there shows
what they what they look like uh they
actually predate Electric Tools um so
their first kind of industrial uh hand
tools used in industry uh and today
clean dry a is sometimes refer as the
fourth utility
so you'd think this would be easy it was
not and my takeaway to this is that
building something unique and different
even if it's a non-standard installation
of a compressor takes a lot of
time and the things that can take the
longest are not necessarily the most
exciting it's not us sitting down and
building solar cells or building them as
devices for us that's actually kind of
easy it's it's these kind of
non-standard things where we rely on
others that take the longest and the
reality is that the quality of people
that you surround yourself with how
willing they are to actually solve this
problem and roll up their sleeves how
much they actually believe in what the
Company's trying to to really pursue and
build are the Absol most important
things to success and I'm really glad
that we surrounded ourselves with the
right people uh because otherwise this
compressor would never have gone
in so in summary uh to kind of conclude
my talk um and sort of sum it up into
three bullet points from when I first
presented in 2020 to
now um building things requires a few
different key things but first and
foremost you need to ask the right
questions about what you're building and
why you need to believe in yourself on
how to actually do it and you need to
find people and surround them who will
do the
same and my last plug on this we're
still hiring so if you know material
chemist or someone with ro to- roll
experience uh please send them my way to
sh or Vladmir they'll definitely get you
in contact with me uh for this so with
that uh I'd like to hand it back to
Vladimir uh and take any questions that
were sent through the talk to the
crowd Richard uh thank you very very
much uh it is awesome to hear the
journey and I have seen many of those
ups and downs uh as you indeed
progressed from one stage to the next uh
your perseverance is remarkable and it's
I'm glad it yielded uh the active
surfaces where it is right now U if you
have questions for Richard there are
really three ways that uh you can indeed
submit them one of them is the Q&A
button uh that you see on the bottom of
the screen the another version would be
by sending it through a chat or lastly
simply raise your hand and uh we'll
recognize and call upon you
and uh we can then have you ask the
question verbally to Richard uh so let
me open the floor for any questions that
uh might be uh of
interest um I see uh jerson um paralta
is rais if you would like to uh unmute
yourself and just ask the
question J
yes can you hear me yes seems oh thank
you very much see that I was had my mic
off thank you very much richer for the
for the the talk it is amazing and
inspiring actually um I would like to
know one of the things I wonder every
time I think about uh starting myself
with a company is
um which kind of investment did you have
did you have at the beginning at the
early ear times and how you how did you
face that time that it was probably a
little bit with a high uncertainty un
unability from your
side yeah um that's a good question I I
I'll answer in two ways I'll directly
answer you uh so
the uh earliest money that we got in was
Venture Capital um so we pretty much
immediately went as a company to venture
capital um that being being said that's
not a very common route uh I would say
everybody's journey is different and my
advice is
usually um to look at your own industry
and see kind of
how uh how people are progressing uh
with that
um uh yeah there's lots of reasons why
we went to VC first um I don't know if I
have time to really list them all um I
think the reality though is like like
there is always going to be that early
point where it's just going to be you
kind of self financing it pulling
pushing it Forward uh for me that lasted
about six months uh before we kind of
finally got our first money in some of
it Grant winnings and Pitch competitions
and then uh like I said the first first
first money in is actually venture
capital in a very very
small Safe
Note uh couple of questions maybe to
continue on that uh from the Q&A um what
would you have done differently to
better facilitate investment more
quickly and added to that uh do you
still feel that the VC Community is
biased against
hardtech um these are good questions uh
I feel like I could spend all day on
them
um I think uh I mean looking back on it
um I wish I wish we didn't spend so much
time with investors we knew were the
wrong fit
um I think it wasted a decent chunk of
time I think we would have been a little
bit
earlier uh to kind of where we are now
um you know when when you do so like I I
talked kind of about like founder
matching in this talk with the reality
is you need to do it too with with
Venture Capital like putting the right
people around you is incredibly
important
um we've been very lucky where we've had
you know not only the right people uh
but we kind of got the choice of it not
everybody really has that
um but yeah there there was a lot of
times I think we we kind of were in the
VC like looking around the VC market and
I think we just spent too much time
exploring and not really just like
locking down the people we knew we
wanted um in terms of bias uh
yes and no um I don't think the bias is
against hard tech specifically I think
the
bias um is against the timeline of
hardtech or deep Tech so there's
distinctions now between those two words
um I think a lot of a lot of investors
really can't handle long timelines or or
whatnot and the way that I kind of
describe it most people don't really
understand how this works is um is
VCS uh there's the general Partners
which are like operational and then they
actually have their own investors so so
they're actually more like
middlemen uh and they actually also kind
of act like startups and so uh so a fund
is raised and then usually progresses
through like a three-year
timeline um before like they have to
fund raise again for another fund if
they're going to continue to to kind of
operate um and so what
that places it places pressure kind of
on startups to really exit or or show
growth within those timelines so that
they actually can keep their jobs uh to
their own
investors um and so that's I think where
the bias comes in is that hardtech is
just really difficult to to kind of grow
on those time
scales um and and I think that's where
really the bias comes in
um u a question that follows
uh because people are excited about
active
surfaces uh is uh about your next hiring
at your team uh are you interested in
growing your team with PhD students at
this stage or other
Talent
um so so I'll go back to the team slide
right now
um uh we we hire
um on kind of two main so our hiring
process for these guys was actually kind
of long and and the reason why is
because we weren't hiring on
Direct uh like a research experience I
know a lot of like our competitors kind
of do that they look at Publications we
don't actually care too heavily about
publication
history um with our hiring uh we care
about kind of foundational knowledge
willingness to learn and excitement to
the uh to the end goal um everyone on
our Tech Team Jeremiah Austin Matt um
well not Jay I guess but he has a
relatively long amount of time in the
lab and then Elise are all
phds um so Jeremiah's late stage career
I mean got his PhD from Yukon but it's
not relevant anymore Austin's from Rice
Matt's from pit uh Elis is from
Stanford um so the materials engineer
position that we do have open right now
on our site that's uh mostly for an
early career p HD uh graduate uh the
other one the RO to uh we kind of
flip-flop it it hasn't been officially
posted yet but it's probably going to be
uh more dependent on the the type of
applicant we get rather
than the U another question yeah another
question is just uh the way you're
thinking about finding that appropriate
VC um uh the question is what kind of
investor and people would you suggest
looking for especially keeping a balance
between the trust and Technology
understanding what kind of insights you
might have on
that trust is the most important thing
um I think a lot of the reason
why we fundrais the way we did is
because uh the
built uh through personal relationships
prior to
investment
um you know maybe another way to phrase
it on kind of how to think about this
and the way I think about a lot is like
okay someone someone and it's a single
person or two people is going to
eventually make the decision that
they're going to give
you either five figures or six
figures what in your own mind would you
want to see to like validate that among
yourself and like some of it is
technical confidence and then some of it
is like just trust that this person's
not going to screw with you and that
second part is the hardest one uh
technical confidence is metrics and
trust is is personal
relationships I can't I can't agree with
you
more um I see uh uh Alan tan Alvin tan
uh raised his hand uh do you mind
unmuting yourself and uh asking a
question hi Richard U this Alvin calling
from
Singapore good to see you uh thank you
for youred
sharing um so you had a really
interesting quote there um it went
something along like uh even if the
company doesn't do well your career will
be fine I thought that was really
interesting and uh kind of paradoxical
so I wonder if you would like to
elaborate more on
that yeah um so it's it's kind of
paraphrased from a conversation I had
with Mitchell from
inab uh at one point um and I've talked
to other Founders about it too um
especially when like the company their
company has gone under in some way shape
or form and like what that transition
was between uh first company and second
company if they do that or first company
in some other
role
um yeah it's I I don't know I don't I
don't have a good way to like single
describe that it's just kind of
something that that you see more and
more is that like okay if the company
fails itself right and and doesn't do
well and and we don't create market
value and we don't scale up um
you know all the skills that I would
have learned throughout the way of
managing a team you know doing books
doing taxes doing SEC filings
doing uh Tech development leading a
group all those things are translatable
to something else uh maybe not
necessarily solar if there are no other
solar companies interested but
definitely uh is useful advice to to
some someone new who wants to come along
and uh try something else in the market
um you know you learn a lot of things
that are not I guess specific to your
own industry and those things are just
as valuable for your personal career
growth um as is the companies I guess is
the way about it so there's a lot of
people try to isolate this um I guess is
another way to say it like there's your
personal career growth and then there's
the company's growth and like you have
to separate those two out um to
uh prevent I guess the the the low days
from being as low as they are because
like your personal career is not really
going to be affected when the company
itself has is a negative
day that's great perspective thank you
for
sharing Alvin thank you so much for
asking I I think that is fantastic
moment to unfortunately have to stop uh
this uh Nano exploration seminar Richard
thank you thanks a ton uh for being
frank sharing your journey uh it is many
ups and downs uh that have led you to
the present state of being way up from
where you started um thank you
congratulations uh on launching active
surfaces and building it to where it is
and you know if you don't mind four
years from now we'll call you again when
uh active surfaces is reaching million
users and and changing the world uh just
to give us yet another seminar on uh
what success of building a basic idea
can grow
into so with that uh I will conclude uh
this seminar I would like to also tell
you that this is the last one for the
Academic Year 23 24 uh we look forward
to seeing many many of you back uh
starting in September well we'll
reinitiate these thank you very much for
being here today all the best last