hi everyone today's topic is protein
structure determination with cryoem uh
cryoem as an experimental technique has
existed for over half a century but it's
really been growing in popularity
probably over the past decade both
amongst biologists who want to you know
push forward Discovery but also amongst
computationalists who you know are faced
with new challenges in processing the
data um and so I'm really excited to be
giving this intro on what the method's
about and then in about an hour Ellen
will pick up and talk about how our
research group is um actually
implementing tools to process this sort
of
data um so as a starting point uh as we
all know proteins are really fundamental
to all the processes that go on in our
body uh from catalyzing reactions to
being the building blocks of our bodies
to transmitting signals um and so
understanding proteins is really
fundamental not only to understanding
life but also intervening rationally
within medicine and health uh and also
driving innovation in Industries like
nanotech and
biotechnology there are many different
lenses through which we can study
proteins but today we're specifically
interested in studying proteins through
the lens of structure uh so proteins
take on really a wide range of
structures and just as importantly
proteins are also highly dynamic so
they're flexible subunits can bind
unbind um and this Dynamic structure is
really critical to their function across
multile scales so on the left here you
can see that these sort of really local
fluctuations of side chains Within These
binding Pockets Drive binding to
substrates um in this dining molecule
Global movements of domains allows this
protein to carry cargo across the cell
and on the very right is the nuclear
pore complex which consists of hundreds
of different protein subunits which are
interacting in concert to selectively
allow passage of substrates into and out
of the
nucleus and so there are multiple
techniques we can use to study this
structure they broadly fall into three
categories one is experiment including
Kow crystallography NMR where you know
we use experimental techniques to
directly probe samples of proteins
physics based methods like molecular
Dynamics where we use our knowledge of
biophysics to simulate the Dynamics of
proteins and finally statistical methods
like Alpha fold which use these data
driven driven priors to make sort of
plausible hypotheses about structures
from their
sequence today again we're specifically
focusing on cryo electron microscopy
which is an experimental technique again
it's been around for a while but um
currently it's going what sometimes
called a resolution Revolution where due
to advances both on the hardware side in
the microscopes as well as on the
software side in terms of processing
algorithms we're now able to process a
much broader range of proteins and also
uh achieve really high resolution
structures um like you can see on the
right um this also comes with a whole
new host of computational challenges and
opportunities and so the plan for today
I'll start off with an overview of the
whole crym pipeline going from you know
if you're a structural biologist
interested in studying some protein how
do you go from an idea of that Target
protein to actually depositing a
structure in the in a database like the
protein datab Bank um and then I'll
spend some time talking about the
classical algorithms for cim
reconstruction just to get the
underlying uh Theory and then that'll
set up the final part of my talk on
Modern methods for heterogenous
reconstruction um and then finally
leading into Ellen's talk giving some
broader cont text for these methods um
and some of the newer developments
within our lab tackling these
challenges so starting out with an
overview of the
pipeline the first step is that given a
Target protein I'm first going to purify
amplify and purify that protein from my
cells and flash freeze it or vitrify it
under liquid nitrogen conditions so this
freezing process a it TR traps the
molecules in place so that we can image
them under long exposures um and it also
increases their tolerance to radiation
damage within the microscope um one
other important aspect of this freezing
process is that uh for context one of
the other major experimental techniques
for structure determination is X-ray
crystallography and in crystallography
you typically have to well you have to
crystallize the sample and that's often
a very difficult thing especially when
you have highly flexible molecules um
really large complexes consisting of
multiple subunits um and so cryo first
of all has really allowed uh access to a
broader range of protein specimens uh
because more samples are amenable to
just flash freezing than they are to
crystallization yeah I think I might ask
some basic questions during your talk
because it's outside of of my field but
um I find them fascinating so uh for
x-ray Crystal crystallography I think
I've heard of it in context of uh
individual proteins like proteins
uh use being used for proteins to
determine structure but is it done on a
cell level like cryoem is or am I
confusing it with something else uh
sorry could you repeat on on the what
level um so with crym you take cell
level images right uh do you get that
for um x-ray c crystallography as well
or is it like for
molecules all like distribution of you
know um different proteins in the cell
yeah so I guess in both for the crym
that I'm presenting here it also is a
similar setup as fortography Where We
Are
we're not Imaging a cell we are just
purifying um a specific protein and
imaging that sample um there's an
extension of CM for this Inu cellular
samples which I'll talk about okay I see
thank you y um yeah so we freeze our
sample and the other really important
aspect of this freezing process is that
because the freezing process so fast
we're trapping these molecules in sort
of a native state um where the
confirmations of each of those
individual particles in the s Le will be
approximately distributed according to
the sort of thermodynamic equilibrium
and so that provides us with a really
powerful opportunity to study not just
you know the single sort of average
static structure but actually access
this full confirmational
landscape so once we've gotten this
sample we can put it into an electron
microscope which looks like the thing on
the left and IR radiated with electrons
and so what the microscope gives us is a
micrograph or a collection of
micrographs which is a 2d ection of the
electron scattering potential the
sample um the key idea is that uh you
know you have water and then you have
these particles embedded within them and
so due to you know differential
scattering um you end up getting sort of
the contrast in these
images so in the micrograph each one of
those dark spots you see is one
individual molecule of the protein and
so in order
to do structure processing the first
thing we have to do is actually extract
each one of those individual particles
this can be done in a variety of ways
including you know machine learning
techniques or using prior structural
templates but after extracting those
particles what do we end up with is
usually between 10,000 up to maybe even
10 million of these individual 2D images
and each one of those consists of a
unique particle captured from the
sample One Challenge in general in crym
data sets is that there tends to be a
lot of junk or outlier particles this is
both due to um imperfections in the
purification and freezing process um as
well as inaccuracies in the particle
picking process yes oh can I ask you
thank you can I ask you a quick question
about the electron microgram so I know
like cry kind of took off a lot in the
last like maybe 10 or 15 years and I
heard one of the reasons was like just
Imaging got better or the cameras got
better is that correct or am I imagining
yeah that uh I don't know the exact year
but yeah direct electron detectors where
you can get um yeah direct counts of
electrons uh spatially uh yeah gave much
better S of signal signal in these
images um and if you have additional
context
here just echoing R like better Hardware
increasing the amount of signal in the
collected images such that now you can
get Atomic resolution solution
structures this was about like
2013 um yeah so characteristically these
data sets do contain a lot of partic
junk particles and so this is going to
be a processing challenge that comes up
later in Ellen's results again but at
this phase at the 2D level there are
certain things we can do specifically
sort of grouping similar looking images
and sort of throwing out classes um that
correspond junk and finally the core
comput
uh question that we're interested in is
the 3D reconstruction problem of how do
we go from all these really noisy 2D
projection images of these particles um
viewed at different angles and go to the
underlying 3D structure or 3D uh
electron scattering map uh this is in
general a very challenging problem both
because as you can see the images are
very noisy the signal to noise ratios uh
can be you know as high as 0.1 but also
as low as 0.01 so sort you know signal
to noise ratio sort of 1 to 1,000 um
also the particle orientations are
unknown um and so you know in the sample
all those individual molecules are
rotated randomly um and so in order to
sort of combine the signal we need to be
able to have a common reference frame
that we can average that signal and so
the second thing is that we don't know
what orientation each of those particles
is in and so we're going to have to
estimate those parameters in addition to
the underlying
structure another challenge but also a
major opportunity as I said is
structural
heterogenity um so each one of those
images again corresponds to one
completely unique molecule and so this
gives us the ability instead of
reconstructing a single average
structure to reconstruct a full
distribution of structures um again
that's a major opportunity that allows
us to understand more about biology but
also presents challenges
and then finally uh after usually long
processing pipelines if you achieve a
sufficiently high resolution 3D
reconstruction you can then use that to
guide building an atomic model which is
typically what gets deposited in a
database such as the protein
dat okay so that's a lightning overview
of the cryan processing pipeline um next
I'll talk about how this reconstruction
problem of 2D images 3D structure has
traditionally been tackled quick
question yeah can can you briefly
address the difference between cryo em
and cryo ET sure yeah um so in actually
yeah this is a good side to explain that
on so in cry em so there's your sample
and we acquire just one one micrograph
one
image um in cry we then tilt the sample
and acquire multiple different views of
the same sample and so you can
essentially treat cry cry stands for
tomography so you can treat cry as the
multi view version of crym and the
reason why that's helpful um is because
especially when you want to study
structure within the cellular context so
you know you want to look at these
molecules in the context of membranes
and organel um and you know other
aspects of the cell uh you typically
want you know a full 3d reconstruction
of the sample containing all those
different organal um
and so yeah that's where a situation
where tomography can be helpful where
you acquire multiple views at different
angles and then you can do a back
projection to get um you know a full
tomographic volume so I guess that for
that one you wouldn't go about with
purification so this one you would
purify the protein before you do cryoem
and there you would just use like a cell
or a tissue directly yeah exactly yeah
y um so before talk about reconstruction
uh we first need to build a model of how
these images are
formed and so this equation here is
showing that um so let V be the
underlying structure so here I'm just
assuming homogeneity so we just have one
single structure that doesn't have any
confirmational changes so we're going to
call that structure V any one of these
images is obtained by projecting that
volume along some direction some angle
that angle I'm going to call f i and P
is just the projection operator
essentially integrating or summing
across that volume
projection that image is then uh
corrupted with the contrast transfer
function which describes the aberration
of the
microscope and then finally we add
gaussian noise this noise corresponds to
shot noise of the microscope detector um
sort of owing to the quantum random
nature of
electrons and so that forms uh one image
which we denote by
XI um another Point actually this this
fii this orientation or this pose I
talked about actually consists of two
components so one is a random
orientation of this molecule within the
sample the second is a 2d translation
because when we do our particle picking
uh typically without a 3D reference um
the particles within those 2D images are
going to be a little offs so we both
need to account for this random
orientation as well as this 2D
translation
so then the CM reconstruction problem is
the inverse of that image formation
model where what's observed is a data
set of these exis these images and what
we aim to find is the underlying map
v um a note that just in what follows
I'm going to assume that those contrast
transfer function values C are known and
fixed that's a reasonable assumption
because you can estimate those
parameters to typically earlier in
processing in the 2D stage um however
again the poses are unknown um and so
that is something we're going to have to
estimate
yeah I guess uh for the gaussian noise
uh model is this kind of is this
actually backed by the the data as in if
I run it on something blank I get out
gaussian noise or is this just to make
it tractable and easy to solve post fact
um in terms of being physically
realistic it's there are more realistic
models um so it is shot or more like
aonian noise uh and also the forward
model even in the forward model uh
treating it as a just straight
projection is uh usually a reasonable
assumption but you can have even more
expressive models where you do like
multi slice wave propagation um and yeah
so sorry so should I think of this as
like a counts of how many times I'm like
my Imaging modality kind of went through
and hit the sensor underneath I so it's
fully a positive kind of uh thing that
I'm
observing uh yes it is an electron count
yeah interesting
thanks yes uh hi sorry one more question
um why do you like if you're
automatically segmenting out the
particles like why wouldn't you just
assume that they were
centered like if you're just yeah yeah
so they'll be they'll the particles will
be centered with respect to the image
that they're in but once you when you
need to combine all these images into a
3D reconstruction you then are going to
have to sort of shift those images a
little without a 3D reference the notion
of a center for a 2D image is still
defin
yeah okay um so this is the the problem
we interested in again so we observing
the xise these images and we aim to
recover the underlying
structure
um we can think of this in a
probabilistic
framework um and so we can frame the
Reconstruction problem as finding a set
of parameters so the structures and
these orientations that maximizes the
likelihood of the data given the
parameters each one of those images is
independent so the full likelihood is
just going to be the product of the
individual likelihoods of observing each
of those
images One sort of assumption we can
make at this phase is the thing we
really care about is optimizing that
volume v and those particle orientations
or poses are just nuisance parameters um
that we don't directly care about and so
we can marginalize over all those
poses
um the marginalization is over the space
of poses which consists of an element of
s SO3 so rotations and an element of uh
R2 which is a
2d okay so from this all we need is
really an expression for this so what is
the likelihood of a single image given a
volume and a pose to get that we can
think back to our image formation model
so again we said an image is formed by
projecting this volume and then adding
some gausian noise alternatively we can
reformulate that by saying that the
image itself is a sample from some
gaussian multivaried gausian
distribution centered on that clean
projection image with and with the
variant
Sigma and so given that interpretation
of the image uh the likelihood of
observing these image the image given
the model of parameters is just going to
be what you get when you plug um the
image to the gaussian PDF for the
multivaried gausian centered on this
mean which is the clean image um and
with that Sigma and so you know if you
recall sort of the gaan PDF this takes a
form like this it's sort of the L2 Norm
between um the point and the mean with
this you know normalization constant out
front okay
sorry okay so we have this expression
for the full likelihood we have this
expression for the likelihood of a
single image so all we have to do is
then take this and and plug it into
there oh can I can I ask a question yeah
you said that like the uh the protein
itself is in a range of confirmations so
is the V also like a distribution the
cryoem density oh yeah so uh in what I'm
showing here I'm assuming that this is a
protein that is static so we just have
one underlying structure um I'll I'll
sort of build up to the case of having
yeah that full
distribution so we can take that uh you
know the single image likelihood plug it
into the total likelihood you get an
expression like that um and then the
optimization problem essentially ends up
being maximizing that full likelihood
with respect to the volume B and you get
an expression like
that
um so again this expression is saying
that you know we want to find the volume
v that you know maximize the likelihood
over all the images again marginalizing
over the
poses unfortunately this expression is
intractable we won't be able to solve
for V in a close form solution and so we
will need another technique um so the
way this is typically done is
expectation maximization which is a very
common approach in these sort of
problems and the idea is that the um the
margin alized full log likelihood that
we just computed is intractable
unfortunately but we can actually
optimize a different quantity instead
which is this expected log likelihood um
you can read more on the evidence lower
bound or elbow but the basic idea is
that this objective it's not the same as
the true objective I showed but it's a
lower bound on it and by optimizing this
we can get a reasonably good
optimization of the true objective as
well if we take a look at this quantity
that we want to optimize um there two
ways to sort of maximize this right one
so this is ex this is saying this is an
expectation of this log likelihood over
the space of poses and so to maximize
this there essentially two things we can
do one is to draw these poses from a
distribution that matches the true
distribution of
poses the second thing we can do is
choosing a volume that that maximizes
this expectation um and so the M
algorithm is essentially alternating
between these two steps in the Eep what
we're doing is estimating the best um
estimating the likelihood of different
poses so um first of all okay recall
that the post space is is continuous
right both translations and rotations in
order to make things easier for us we're
going to discretize um into sort of set
of candidate poses that we want to
evaluate and so this is saying that in
the Eep for each one of those images
we're going to evaluate uh you know How
likely is that image to arise from each
of those candidate poses and so we
essentially get a posterior distribution
um of of again How likely each pose is
for that
image and then the M step is given those
estimates of the poses then choosing a
volum that that maximizes that
expectation um so again key idea we're
just going to alternate between a
optimizing the orientations or poses and
then optimizing the volume given those
orientations luckily uh this is you know
sort of a complex equation but um the
key takeaway is that this form of the
objective does have a closed form
solution so by going from that original
objective to this lower bound but we end
up with is um an explicit expression for
the volume that maximizes that objective
and if you try to interpret what this is
saying it's saying that the optimal
volume is essentially in 3D
space taking all your images and
basically taking a weighted sum over
them so every image for every single
orientation taking this weighted sum
where the weights are higher for
orientations that are sort of more
likely to produce that image
um just to make this more intuitive uh
here is a graphic so again the Eep
consists of estimating the best
orientation parameters given the current
volume so here's let's say our current
volume we can create a bunch of we can
use the forward simulation model to
create a bunch of clean projection
images for each of those candidate poses
and then we can compare each of those
projection images against the True Image
and compute the error between them this
will give us a sense of which ones of
those candidate poses were good poses
which ones of those were likely and
which of those is
unlikely and so this gives us that
reprojection era gives us these weights
of you know what again what poses are
the most likely so given those estimates
of the poses the M step is then
essentially back projecting all those
images
according to the poses um when say back
projection you can think of it as the
inverse of the projection operator right
so for projection we took this volume
and we essentially integrated or summed
we did a projection back projection
essentially corresponds to doing the
opposite process taking this 2D and
going back into 3D what does that
actually mean I think it's easier to
interpret um in Fier space so far I've
been talking about you know the real
physical space um fora space is the
space of uh spatial frequencies and so
in this space according to something
called the Fier slice theorem in real
space again you have a volume you
project it you get a 2D image it turns
out in Fier space um that the Fier
transform of an image is a central slice
of the forier transform of the volume so
the image is just the slice of the
forier volume and so that's what we mean
when we say back projection when we say
we back project an image According to
some pose it means we're just going to
insert that image into the 3D Volume
along some orientation in 4A space and
this corresponds to the inverse of the
forward operation so again just to recap
Eep estimate the best poses M step
according to those best poses basically
place all these images back and do a
back projection in order to recover the
underlying volume and keep iterating
going back and forth between these two
steps so this is like a very general
framework for how to to do
reconstruction um you know it's not even
specific to cryo this is sort of a you
know a general way of formulating any
sort of tomographic reconstruction
problem um specifically in cryo there
are some remaining challenges which
prevent that procedure from being
effective and that's a a one just
property of the expectation maximization
algorithm is that it always improves the
likelihood uh but that also means that
it will probably get stuck in a local
Optima unless you initialize it properly
second as we see these images are
extremely noisy and so during this
process of aligning images to the volume
it's very easy to overfit to the noise
in the images rather than the underlying
signal um and so we need some strategies
for dealing with both these problems for
dealing with the first problem of how do
we deal with initialization so that em
actually converges uh
one uh Innovation introduced around 2017
by this software package cryos spark was
to you know before directly running the
expectation maximization algorithm on a
completely random initialization of the
volume they first do gradient descent on
that true objective so this is the true
objective that we initially derived even
though we don't have a close form
solution for it we can do gradient
descent on it um and so they start out
just doing gradient descent to optimize
the volume with respect to that true
objective that gives you not a great
volume but a reasonable initialization
you can then feature the EM algorithm uh
to increase the chances of actually
finding that Global
minimum the second Innovation pertaining
to how do we prevent overfitting our
parameters to the noise in the images uh
this was introduced by
ReliOn uh which is a different software
package and the idea is that the
objective I presented was the maximum
likelihood estimator but you can also
formulate this in a basan framework and
do a maximum uh a posterior
posterior uh uh objective um so the map
estimator is going to have the mle
objective along with this prior term
which serves as
regularization that prior term is
typically just saying that each of the
Fier components so each of those um the
powers of each of the spatial
frequencies within the volume is drawn
from a zero mean I uh it's a relatively
simple prior uh but the variance of that
prior is usually also optimized during
this process um and the idea is that we
can sort of estimate reasonable
frequency dependent variances depending
on our sort of known knowledge of the
power spectrum of of crym images um so
this essentially just provides a form of
regularization uh where especially early
in training when the amount of
information content that those high
frequencies is quite low this object uh
this regularization um sort of prevents
overfitting to those high frequencies
and sort of dampens those components
early on in the
process okay so that's sort of the EM
algorithm question was just asked on how
do we actually discretize the poses so
again the specific um thing we're
interested in is again I presented uh
this way of optimizing the volumes and I
said we can take that integration over
the entire space of poses and turn it
into a sum over a discrete set of
candidate poses so one question is how
do we actually dis discretize the space
um so we can think about how to do it uh
what if we just brute force it right so
what if we take the space of poses and
just break it up into a really fine grid
uh that's not going to work because if
you look at uh you know how many poses
we'd have to get you know one degree one
degree of rotation error it would
correspond to nearly 19 million
different poses and you can do some back
of the envelope math if you have a if
your images are of size you know 128 by
128 um even for a single image Computing
like a repr projection error doing a
back projection it's going to be on the
order of 310 billion operations now we
have you know hundreds of thousands or
millions of images larger images and we
need to run em you know in an iterative
man and so this just becomes completely
intractable and so we need a strategy
for for discretizing the space better
and so we're going to do two
things um and they're both sort of based
on this observation that in general the
the error
between uh the pose error is uh smooth
with respect to the pose
meaning you know it doesn't jump around
a lot right this is the optimal pose as
I move away from the pose it sort of
there sort of falls off gradually so we
can make use of this observation to do a
couple of of her
istics um and again so they're based on
this idea again that we have large areas
of post space that are either good or
bad so we can reject large areas at a
time the first idea is subdivision or
hierarchical git search uh which says
you know we can start out with a very
coarse sampling of poses so split up the
space very coarsely you know find the
best poses within this coar space only
take the best ones divide them up even
more search again take the best ones
divide them further search again and
essentially um you only evaluate the
really fine uh fine samplings for just a
few poses instead of all of
them that's one idea um the second idea
is that when we compute um when we
compute that pose error that
reprojection error between you know this
clean image and our uh our real image so
again that's that error right so X is
the real image
um cpv is that reprojection and taking
the L2 Norm gives us uh measure of the
air between those two things I measure
how good that poses we note that this is
just summing over all the pixels right
so just compute the error pixel by pixel
sum over all of them which means we can
also split it up into two terms one
corresponding to just low frequency
components of the image and one
corresponding to the high frequency
components of the image and now one key
observation we can make is that
typically this POS estimation process
aligning these images is dominated by
low frequency components and so we can
actually ignore those higher frequency
terms and only compute the error on the
low frequency terms um and so that
is that is a cheaper right because we're
only Computing it on a subset of the
frequencies uh but it also actually
improves the alignment because you know
it avoids again sort of aligning to the
higher frequency noise comp um and in
practice uh you know one question is
like how do you actually choose what
constitutes low frequency typically uh
the bandwidth is increased over time so
very early on training uh when you don't
have a good volume you just have a blob
you use a very low value of L meaning
you only evaluate these errors on the
very low frequencies and as you progress
in training you just keep increasing to
include higher and higher frequency
components as you build up this higher
resolution Rec Construction
um one last note is that I've sort of
presented all that with uh in terms of s
SO3 so rotations but like I said we do
also have to estimate these 2D
translational shifts um and doing so we
can use very similar techniques as I
said for the rotations in particular you
know we can still do the sort of
hierarchical grid search discoring the
space of 2D
translations one other note I'll make is
that when I presented the algorithm I
presented in a sort of a purely
probabilistic framework where we um
essentially assigned a like assigned a
probability each possible pose for each
possible image What's Done in practice
in a lot of programs is that instead of
con constructing that full posterior of
poses you actually just take the the
best pose and so you alternate between
estimating the absolute best pose and
then using the best pose to um then
update your volume reconstruction
okay and then finally um so again
everything I presented was through the
lens of homogeneous reconstruction so
assuming we just have one single
underlying static structure uh but now
we can start thinking about how do we
incorporate the structural heterogenity
we have multiple underlying
structures so we can modify our image
formation model so assume we have a
setting like this so here is a ribosome
and this is an ass uming ribosome so
essentially as the ribosome is maturing
different subunits get added on um and
so here we have this case of discrete
heterogenity where each of those images
may arise from one of let's say those
four structures so how do we account for
that where we want to reconstruct all
four of those structures from our
Imaging data um we can modify our image
formation model so now it's going to
look extremely similar except instead of
having just a single V I have this V
indexed by AI where AI is the class um
of of that particular
image so now the multiclass
Reconstruction problem is again instead
of finding a single volume find the
entire set of optimal volumes um
assuming that we have K volumes given
the data again the challenge here is
that all we have is this raw 2D image
data set we don't have labels on each
image of which structure it Rose from so
we'll have to both find the volume but
then also find those class assignments
of which particle belongs to which
volume um I won't go through the the
full derivation here this is just to
show that uh the objective looks very
similar to what we saw in the
homogeneous case so um I'm assuming here
that we know the poses ahead of time
that's actually a reasonable assumption
to sometimes you do the sort of 3D
classification after doing an initial
homogeneous reconstruction so with that
assumption uh we saw in the original
objective we were essentially
marginalizing over the space of poses
here we're just marginalizing over the
class assignments okay so that's the
only thing that really changes in the
objective and the EM algorithm is going
to look very similar again recall in in
what I just presented we alternated
between estimating the poses and
updating these volumes we're going to do
the same thing here we're going to um in
the Eep we're going to instead estimate
the class assignments or the
probabilities of an image belonging to
different classes and then using that in
the m step we're again going to update
the volume um where if you look at the
update equation the volume for a given
class is going to be again the sort of
weighted average over every image
weighted by How likely is it that that
image belongs to that class yeah um
every class we still have different
possible poses though right yes that is
true um so it is uh right in in a full
formulation there is a per class CL pose
as well it sort of depends on the route
you take during processing so this one
route do a homogeneous first just use
those poses purely classify there other
routes where you can do the joint
optimization um yeah so the process is
going to look very similar just doing
this optimization over class assignment
um in practice uh 3D classification
which I just showed is still uh it's
called challenging um for a multitude of
reasons uh first you know we assume that
each image arises from a single uh from
you know one of K structures this is you
know well suited for the example I
showed where you have this rabis in
discrete States um but for a lot of
molecules they exhibit more continuous
motions right where like a domain is
moving around and so it's hard to
represent those forms of heterogen with
just a discrete set of
structures um generally ALS also we have
to set K ahead of time which can be very
ad hoc and challenging if you don't know
what's in your data set you sort of have
to sweep or guess the values of K and
there's also optimization tends to be
challenging especially because as you
increase K it you dilute the number of
particles in each of those classes um
and so that you know makes each of the
volumes worse harder to
op okay so that's a rundown of sort of
classical reconstruction um and you know
those really highlight the core
principles understanding you know the
more modern outs that we'll talk
about
um so in terms of you know how do people
do reconstruction now for these more
challenging forms of heterogenity so
again we'd really like to tackle cases
like this right of continuous
heterogeneity we cannot represent um you
know such variability with just you know
K volumes so we really need to learn a
full distribution over
volumes again in terms of the image
formation model we can modify it again
now instead of a single structure or you
know multiple volumes index by K we're
now going to have a full distribution of
volumes which we say V Theta z z is some
latent variable which represents the um
represents the confirmation of a
particular image and in terms of um
continuous heterogenity you can you can
imagine you have a molecule with some
domain
that under goes some sort of linear
one-dimensional
motion this Z you can think of as some
Laten variable corresponding to values
of of that reaction coordinate along
which that domain moves um and so this
expression is saying um for the
confirmation of a given particle we plug
this into this uh this distribution
which parametrizes a volume given that
specific
confirmation so again our our goal for
reconstruction is going to be to
optimize that full volume distribution V
Theta um and also jointly on a per
particle basis estimate uh this
representation of its confirmation
C in general there are a lot of choices
we can take on how to uh how to model
this problem um and so the multiclass
discrete setting that I talked about you
can sort of view where we still have a z
there representing the confirmation with
Z corresponds to you know a discrete set
class
indices um but now we'd like to tackle
this case where Z belongs to some you
know continuous range of values which
will help us parameterize you know more
continuous motions um and in general we
can have both nonlinear and linear
parameterizations uh and so there set of
tools 3D vaa rovar where the mapping
from this confirmation to the volume is
linear so it use this techniques like
PCA and then there also classes of
models uh for example using deep
learning that have a nonlinear mapping
from Z to this volume
space um and again within this nonlinear
parameterizations uh there many
different design choices you can make uh
just using neural representations which
I'll talk about next um but you can also
encode different assumptions for example
deformable GMM or flow Fields where you
make sort of assumptions that you have
like a single canonical volume that
deforms along some coordinate so
essentially there are many different
design choices we can make um I won't
get into all of them but specifically
I'll talk about um the principles
underlying cryo Dragon which is the tool
and software package that we work on in
our lab um and so to introduce the
architecture first we can think about
how to efficiently parameterize volumes
in this new setting right so in the
homogeneous case we essentially
optimized the volume of this we had this
cubic grid of voxal right and we
optimized the values of each of those
voxels to to build up this volume um we
there's another way we can parameterize
the same volume which is using something
called a neural field and the idea of a
neural field that we're going to
implicitly instead of storting an
explicit cubic grid of oxil we're going
to implicitly represent that volume
through a function in this case the
function takes on the form of a neural
network but when I say a function it's
some mapping from a point in 3D space to
the value the density at that space at
at that
point um and so in
particular instead of again explicitly
representing every voxel here in order
to build up a volume we'd take this
function and evaluate it at a bunch of
3D coordinates sort of to sort of
rasterize you know voxal by voxal build
up this
volume
um some other details uh you might
wonder you know are both of these like
equivalent in terms of accuracy Um this
can be sometimes harder to optimize
implicitly but there are sort of Tricks
we can add to make it uh to make it
accurate uh in particular uh one key
Insight that Ellen had When developing
this um was that instead of giving this
network this function this raw 3D
coordinates we can featu these 3D
coordinates into some higher dimensional
Space by transforming it with a bunch of
sinusoidal functions and that sort of
helps the optimization um of these
neural fields and representing these
volumes um this concept of a oh and this
is just illustrating that same point so
U there's this experiment where you can
do where like ignoring reconstruction
you can do this very simple test of you
know can one of these neural networks
just learn a single 2D image and if you
just try to have it learn this image
just using those raw 3D coordinates it
turns out that because of the inductive
biases in neural networks you get
something very blurry but then by
transforming those coordinates into this
higher dimensional sinal space we're
then able to learn um learn these high
resolution
images and so in general this technique
of neural uh
okay and this is just one more
demonstration that again for pretty high
resolution you know images of size you
know 360 by 360 both the explicit voxal
based representation and the neural
representation um Can converge to high
resolution is the positional encoding
equalent to a forer transform of the
point essentially to do a for transform
of of anything you you you take the
sinusoidal and Co Co cosiness at
multiple frequencies and just add them
up right right we're not representing
the amplitudes of the components of the
forier so it's it's like a forier
spectrum instead of a point is that a
fair way to think about it or am I
missing something I think it's not
exactly so it's is the same so yes you
do uh it's similar in the sense that
yeah you're transforming into a set of
sinusoids um it's not a direct I guess
forier transformation we're not adding
them the the coefficients for all those
forier components there're different
choices you can make but I think by
default we just draw them from a gausian
so yeah the coefficients of all those
different sinusoids are sort of random
they don't corespond to the actual
forier um and this is just a slide
saying that this idea of like neural
field representations of volumes or
images is not C specific thing um and in
general after the development of it it's
seen a use in really a wide range of
fields um just in general sort of see an
understanding robotic planning and
other okay
um what I just showed was just two
different ways of representing the same
volume right either explicitly or
implicitly to this function why is that
actually useful um it becomes more
useful once we start thinking about
heterogen right and so in particular
when it comes to these explicit voxal
based represent ations in order to
represent heterogenity you need to store
and optimize multiple discrete volumes
whereas in the neural field setting this
is so much more expressive because what
we can do to represent heterogenity is
to Simply feed in an additional input to
the network which corresponds to that
confirmation V see right so in addition
to this 3D coordinate um you know
whether we want this function to
represent one structure or 10 structures
or 10,000 structures the size of the
network doesn't grow right we still have
have just this same structure of the
network all we change is the value of
this confirmation Z and so in this
manner um the implicit representation is
a much more scalable way of representing
multiple volumes corresponding to
explicitly storing and optimizing
explicit
box um one remaining question is that
I've been talking about this
confirmation latent Z which represents
the confirmation of each particle uh
where do we actually get that
confirmation from to feed into this
neural field
we do that using a second neural network
and so this PRI Dragon tool for
heterogenous reconstruction the full
architecture is a variational auto
encoder consisting of two main parts the
first is an encoder the encoder takes as
input a single one of those 2D images
and based on this Maps it to this
confirmation lat Z and then the decoder
which is this neural field we just
discussed takes as input that lane
variable and produces a volume
corresponding to that specific
confirmation which has been estimated
from
this how do
we train such a model
um so if we consider a single training
example right so we take our image we
push it through the encoder this gives
us again this Laten variable z um by the
way Z typically Ty Al takes on uh we
empirically find that between eight and
16 Dimensions Works in general the Z
should be as many dimensions as there
are degrees of freedom within the
underlying molecular
system um so again image goes to the
encoder you get this Lane variable
representing that image's confirmation
push it through the decoder and for the
sake of training again we note based on
the Fier slice theorem that this input
image is a centrally oriented slice of
the output vol volume so we can do and
also recall that the neural field maps a
single coordinate in space to the
density at that space so if we know the
poses assume we know the pose for this
image know the
orientation we can evaluate the decoder
along each one of the points
corresponding to that pose right so we
know that this image fits into the
volume in some specific pose so we can
evaluate the decoder along every Point
corresponding to the image plane of that
of that image um and then we can take
the loss just the the error MSE error
between the predicted image and the
original image and that sort of provides
this training signal which optimizes the
values um of the decoder as well as the
encoder sort of this end to end
fashion
um great the main takeaway here I think
is just that uh this is sort of a really
expressive model especially if you're
continuous heterogene right we're not
optimizing multiple discreete voxal
grids we're essentially mapping each
images this continuous space of
confirmations and then using that to
decode continuous distribution of
volumes um one last point just
connecting this back to sort of the
classical reconstruction uh even though
the architecture looks maybe quite
different from the EM algorithm we
discussed for reconstruction there
actually do exist some deep connections
particularly in the algorithm you know
the the poses and the class assignments
were also Laten variables that we sort
of did this marginalization over by
Computing with the full posterior um in
the same regard these confirmation
variables Z are also a form of Laten
variables in general it's much harder to
um compute the you know full posterior
over these right so for poses we
enumerated a bunch of poses and and Tred
out each one it's much harder to do for
this L the confirmation variable Z
because again the space is much more
High dimensional you know maybe eight or
16 Dimensions it's sort of unbounded um
and so we need better ways of sort of
predicting that confirmation Z which is
why we bring in an encoder uh this is
sort of the idea of a mortised inference
which says we can um instead of like
trying out every value of Z you can sort
of reduce the space and find plausible
ones by mapping directly from the input
image to that value
Z okay um finally in the last couple of
minutes um you know uh so that that's
the underlying Cry Dragon architecture
and training how does this get applied
to real data um so first of all once
you've trained this model in the fashion
I said you can encode all your images
again to get a latent variable
representing the confirmation for each
one of those images you can plot them
and so you get a plot like this again
each one of the points corresponds to
that low dimensional Lane representation
for one of those images and so this
gives us sort of visualization of the
empirical data distribution um and so
from here what we can do is do things
like a we can sample volumes along you
know continuous trajectories in the
space we can cluster the space Maybe
using K means clustering to get
representative disr samples um and we
can also you know identify sort of these
clusters of particles that you can then
refine in traditional tools or filter
out in the case of
junk uh so a couple of quick
examples uh here is this again ribosome
a ribosome data set where you have
multiple States discrete states with
subunits sort of bound or Unbound
depending on where in the maturation
process this ribosome is um traditional
processing in the C 3D classification
based approach as I said leads to
procedures that tend to be very
iterative and hierarchical so you know
you run one round of 3D classification
to get you know maybe five substance
particles then you have to do more
rounds of 3D classification on each of
those subsets to divide them further Etc
and ends up being sort of this iterative
process um whereas with this more with
Cry Dragon um and in general these more
like expressive models of heterogenity
uh empirically these models are able to
learn a lot more in just a single shot
and so here training this model on this
data set each of the major clusters
corresponds to one of the major States
but then if you dig deeper within each
of those clusters you're also able to
pull out all those minor States all in
just like a single round
training um and also additionally
identify sort of these rare States um
again because you know the process isn't
super ad hoc and iterative you're really
able to pull the most out of your
data um one more example so this is a
sply the previous example showed how
even for a case of discreet heterogenity
these neural models are really
expressive um but they're you know
especially expressive when it comes to
more these more continuous forms of
heterogen um here's the spone
traditionally and what you would do to
process this is manually identify
different domains different moving parts
and reconstruct and refine each of those
separately
um this is showing that again sort of in
a single shot without any strong priers
on you know what domains are moving you
can train one of these models and
sampling these continuous trajectories
in this case the a principal component
of the lay in space allows us to
visualize these more continuous
Dynamics um right and this is just
showing uh again you really get sort of
this full distribution corresponding to
your entire data set so each one of the
particles in your data sets maps to sort
of this unique volume allowing you to
really fully explore the confirmational
landscape
okay so to summarize um prum is very
powerful experimental technique
especially when it comes to Dynamic
proteins because uh this freezing
process captures them in this near
native state this sort of equilibrium
distribution um we talked about sort of
the probabilistic techniques underlying
classical reconstruction which provide
the core principles which then motivate
this new class of heterogenous
reconstruction methods which has emerged
for the past few years um and again
these heterogenous reconstruction
methods you can make many different
design choices and code many different
priors uh I specifically presented prior
Dragon which is one particular model
which uses this implicit neural
representation uh to provide this really
expressive and sort of assumption free
model of
heterogene so tough act to follow Rish
gave an amazing overview of the kind of
fundamental theoretical aspects of
crying reconstruction ction hopefully
I'll give like broader big picture
overview of some of the things that our
group works
on so kind of at a high level the
motivation of the methods that our group
develops are to uh develop computational
methods to push forward scientific
discovery and so definitely uh something
that we have been talking about and what
I will talk about today is how we can
develop methods for cryoem and cry data
analysis in particular extracting the
confirmational ens symbols um of these
macromolecular machines in
C uh something that's particularly
exciting especially right now in this
landscape of like large kind of uh deep
learning models is connecting these kind
of large scale uh generative models with
experimental data so that's definitely a
major Focus especially for molecular and
structural biology and then finally I
won't talk about this today but
something we're very excited about is
developing new AI methods for uh small
molecules and natural products
okay there's a couple of repeats but
I'll go through a lot of the intro very
quickly the biological motivation we
want to solve proin structures and we
want to be able to visualize uh their
confirmational ensembles because that
gets us much closer to understanding the
function of these ma
machines um and you might be very aware
of breakthroughs in machine learning
methods for structural biology namely
the development of alpha fold and
related systems for predicting protein
structures um there's also been a lot of
really interesting methods kind of
connecting these structure prediction
models with protein language models uh
with generative models to do denovo uh
protein generation like chroma great uh
alpha alpha numerical proteins right
there and so one of the main kind of
takeaways is that these unified machine
Le learning Frameworks are stateof
the-art for a lot of kind of uh tasks in
protein structure space but for a lot of
the things that I think we care about as
biologists so putting our kind of
structural biologists hat on um I think
the goalposts have just Advanced so
we're still very data limited for many
problems including kind of understanding
the downstream function and
understanding kind of how these
molecules interact in C2 which is why uh
I'm very kind of uh grateful that our
group works on these methods for
advancing the type of data that we can
get hopefully even uh help with training
the Next Generation versions of these
structure um as already very nicely
introduced proteins and other biom
biomolecules form these large dynamic
macro machines and if we really want to
understand kind of the function of these
machines it would be amazing to be able
to visualize uh the entire
confirmational ensembles either at kind
of like high resolutions or even uh at
kind of broader uh in context uh in
context
environments unfortunately techniques to
study these molecular motions especially
at kind of atomic Atomic level
resolutions are rather limited so we
have NMR which is typically limited to
smaller proteins um well what I like to
call kind of avant guard crystallography
based approaches like EFX XEL
crystallography this still requires
sample crystallization but you can maybe
look at some of the mechanical
deformations of these uh of the kind of
proteins within the Crystal
lus and then in a previous life I've
worked on molecular Dynamic simulations
so can we actually kind of run long tan
scale MD simulations get an in silico
microscope into the Dynamics of these
systems um very very challenging to do
computationally and there's also a lot
of fundamental kind of challenges in the
underlying accuracy of these force
fields hacking Alpha fold I think is
pretty interesting what kind of signals
are in the underlying msas but then when
I learned about crym uh kind of near the
beginning of my PhD I was like ah this
is a very very cool experimental
technique that can allow us potentially
to extract the kind of confirmational
ensembles of these uh nanoc scale
nanometer scale machines
so I won't go over kind of construction
fundamentals because we just had an
amazing primer by Rish um but again we
have a sample flash frozen we have a
collected set of micrographs and then
from there we have a collected set of
single particle images that are
characteristically very
noisy and the name of the game is to
reconstruct in 3D the electron
scattering potential for this kind of
volume function from our Collective
images um and this I definitely won't go
over since we just had a primer on it
the goal is to estimate our volumes and
uh the poses typically with maximum
likelihood techniques and there's a lot
of state-of-the-art software packages
for doing this especially in the
homogeneous case so ReliOn carpark for
Prine and so
on um Rish also gave a quick overview
about this but I think this provides a
nice intuition for this iterative DM
algorithm that we talked about um and so
this is the furry slice theorem the
furry slice theorem states that the
furry transform of a 2d projection of a
volume is a central slice out of the 3D
for transfer of the volume where the
orientation of that slice is
perpendicular to the direction and so if
we have a set of images and we know
their poses we can convert convert or
take the ffts and then insert them as
slices into the correct kind of
orientations in 3D space and then take
the inverse fft to get back our real
space kind of visualization of the
volume and then that kind of gives the
uh intuition for how these iterative em
algorithms work given some initial
volume v you estimate your poses and
given those poses you reestimate volume
and rinse and repeat until convergence
ideally to the global minimum although
there's a lot op that and Rish already
gave an overview of these
state-of-the-art software packages for
doing that mly rely on
and okay so that was homogeneous
reconstruction but we have this
heterogenity problem uh which is the
kind of major opportunity next so each
crime image contains a unique molecule
and uh potentially a different
confirmational state so the ability to
image these heterogeneous structures is
a major opportunity in crym and
especially relative to other techniques
like crystallography where we've
experimentally rigidified each copy of
our molecule in the exact same
confirmation in we actually get the
experimental data needed to study the
kind of intrinsic structural landscape
of these macro of these protein
complexes unfortunately dealing with
this heterogenity is very challenging
and see approaches really include just
ad hoc filtering or getting rid of as
much of it as possible which is
obviously not ideal if you're interested
in intrinsic heterogen um and then
something called M Class reconstruction
which we already actually talked a lot
about um and that leads to these kind of
uh very um manually made SI figures in
all the pran papers where a practitioner
has the expertise to know like how to
sweep how to choose subsets how to
combine them uh and Main takeaway here
is that at the top of this processing
pipeline there are millions and millions
of
images but by the end um you have two
albe at high resolution structures but
you've ALS you've also thrown away a
significant portion of your data so in
this case um maybe 90%
of the question is what's in that 90% um
and so the identification and Analysis
of heterogeneity especially continuous
forms of hydrogen uh is an open problem
in PR Rec construction and this is the
problem problem um that I originally
sought to kind of answer at the
beginning my PhD so can we design a
modern machine learning method for this
heterogenity problem cm and still
continues to be kind of a major research
question in my
group so you'll also kind of be familiar
with this slide so in heterogeneous
reconstruction we extend the image
formation model instead of a single
volume uh for each image we now have
this distribution of volumes
parameterized by S variable model
and I think I think it's important to
take a step back and think about what
are the sources of heterogenity because
that motivates kind of how we design
these uh how we want to design our
volume distribution our paration of this
distribution and so
um yeah I like these acronyms because it
becomes a mouthful to say confirmational
heterogenity and compositional
heterogenity over and over again uh but
we have confet which you know can
originate from shape deformations of our
proteins our bi molecules and then we
have compet which refers to kind of
compositional differences in the so you
can think of that as like object class
um and then in practice there's usually
a lot of real het which comes from
artifacts and non- idealities during
Imaging maybe Crystal and Ice forming on
the images that get falsely picked
during the
particle and different methods there's
now a lot of different methods they use
different choices of the volume
parameterization lat variable model and
also way they do inference of all these
variables and so there's a lot of
different design traces um and then one
last thing to note is that most methods
treat poses as known before doing
heterogen okay so that's the setting of
like heterogeneous reconstruction cem
our method which is called Cry Dragon
it's an acronym it stands for deep
reconstructing dat networks and here our
task is 3D reconstruction instead of a
single kind of homogeneous structure
from our data set of unlabeled images we
want to reconstruct this load
dimensional continuous
structures um so yeah Rich already gave
an overview but we framed this
heterogeneous reconstruction problem as
unsupervised learning of a deep
generative model where the generative
models parameterized using this neural
field and particularly exciting to see
kind of the general or the broad
applicability of this classic methods in
computer vision and fundamentally moving
forward we're interested in developing
new methods that kind of broaden the
scope of what we can get out of cryan
dat andal biolog
okay so I'm going to skip over these
real quick but the main takeaway that R
already nicely went through is that BR
Dragon structures are parameterized
using a neural network instead of boxal
array and then the main reason we do
this is that it gives us a very elegant
way of modeling especially continuous
forms of het so instead of having to
model K separate boxal arrays again
there becomes as buyas variant trade-off
especially with larger numbers of K as
well as computational considerations uh
we can simply extend the input dimension
of our neural network to uh condition on
an additional L
variable okay this slide we're also
already familiar with um and so I don't
think I have anything else to say other
than it's all expressed in fur space so
each input image is a 2d planer slice
out of the volume in the free domain
even though these this image is kind
of okay and the main advantage is that
this is a very flexible model uh with
very few initial assumptions about the
data and so um this kind of neural net
networ or this coordinate basal Network
whatever kind of distribution of uh
structures it can model uh we can uh or
it can learn from the
data okay so at test time we have this
encoder and decoder um and again R
already went through this but given a
set of images we can encode them into
this low dimensional Laten space and
just directly visualize that space see
if there's anything interesting we can
even learn about maybe the clustering
and this empirical data
distribution and we can use the decoder
neural network to generate or sample
volumes at different values of our
latent variable um so we can view
representative
samples maybe given two end states of
Interest we can do an interpolation in
the latent space or maybe a random walk
in the latent space and generate the
corresponding kind of continuous
trajectory continuous
model and then we can take subsets of
our data set to either filter from a lot
of kind of real artifacts or validate
kind of an individual structure using
traditional kind of
hom quick question so so you mentioned
that this uh this approach uses none or
very few assumptions so what are the
assumptions it uses and how does it
compare with the assumptions made in the
traditional approach where you assume
it's sampled from a normal distribution
yeah um the I guess the main assumption
is that the rep uh the distribution of
structures can be represented in some
lower dimensional space like dimensional
space but we don't make any kind of more
strict assumptions about what that
distribution look
like cool so in the original development
of crow Dragon um we did a lot of
validation on synthetic data sets um
just to make sure that everything was
working but then something that I was
very kind of uh motivated to do is to
create an actual software package around
this tool that people structural
biologists and electron microscopists
can train these models to analyze their
data sets and visualize the heterogeny
and so R already went through these two
examples but we have this kind of
assembling bacterial ribosome where
we're able to discover new structures
and then this pre- catalic spliceosome
on the right where we're able to
visualize these kind of large scale
continuous dynamics of this large macro
molecular
machine at Princeton I'm very lucky to
have Michael in the group who is a
research software engineer who has taken
over like maintenance and support of
this software package that's absolutely
amazing um hopefully it's relatively
easy to use uh with a pretty
straightforward software pipeline we
have extensive tutorials maybe too much
but we'll see uh on how to use the tool
and how to kind of interpret the results
um and we're working on kind of
enhancements Integrations some of these
new kind of post estimation methods uh
getting that kind of integrated into the
main cool and so there's a lot of like
kind of interesting things we can do
with Cry Dragon but there's all the
limitations which have motivated the
kind of new directions and crime
reconstruction that our group ISR
working on so I will just give a quick
overview of a couple of these different
methods but I'll focus on Cry Dragon ET
which is how we do structure
determinations okay
so uh I think it was great to get in the
primer a deep dive into this pose
estimation problem because it's actually
very very interesting and very
engineering intensive and usually just
kind of completely skipped over but uh
to obtain kind of this rendered slice by
the fre slice serum you need to know the
orientation of that slice so we have
this pose which is a tuple of the
rotation a 2d translation so we need
some model to approximate pose or we
need some approach to approximate pose
how do we do
this um I won't go into too much detail
but a lot of the research in the group
so far has been kind of explored
exploring different ways for doing posst
estimation and this is a setting of Crum
called abon reconstruction and so that's
where we start reconstruction without
any prior estimates of poses um uh we've
talked about exhaustive search this
hierarchical kind of grid search which
is very robust to high noise levels
because we're kind of exhaustively
enumerating the whole space and testing
them all it's very slow so we're not
doing 19 million slices but we're doing
you know thousands of slices um and
especially with a neural model where we
have to do a full forward pass through
neural network
slow um our loss function is
differentiable with respect to our POS
varibles so we can you know just do
direct gradient descent on our poses
that's very fast but this requires
initialization um and then we've also
explored various kind of amortized
inference approaches or basically put on
our deep learning hats and then like ah
let's just train a model to predict the
pose given the image um this is very
fast to evaluate but this is also kind
of unstable to train it needs learning
and is tricky to show and kind of This
truly kind of generalized set okay um so
we've tried all the above and just
skipping to the
punchline um the latest version which
we've called crry Dragon AI incorporates
the exhaustive search and this SGD or
radiant disp based approach to POS and
really the research question is can we
perform singleshot abon reconstruction
of modern crime data sets they're very
large data sets that have millions of
crime images they're typically
unfiltered so there's kind of these
outliers in the distribution um and do
this in like a reasonable amount of time
so in kind of a scalable fashion um I
won't go into detail but we switch off
between this hierarchal post search and
an auto auto decoder framework um we
address kind of you know the trade-offs
between memorization of the input Imes
versus
generalization um there is
regularization from the neural model and
uh we've been able to show the discovery
of rare States from large kind of card
data sets and this is driven by axle R
and um there's a couple of directions
that we've even been extending our Cry
Dragon AI method uh and just really
quickly one is modeling complex mixtures
using a kind of mixture of neural Fields
so we call this model Hydra and kind of
One Direction we're pushing is instead
of you know a single neural field can we
have
like what what what is a bottleneck if
we really want to reconstruct a complex
mixture uh or complex sample so this is
kind of this hybrid architecture
combining Cry Dragon Ai and 3
classification um and we're doing both
inference of kind of uh which moral
field which class we're in as well as
the confirmational state and the poses
so it's a very very challenging inverse
problem um here's some results on a
synthetic data set we mix together uh
moving raboso moving spone and moving C
protein and we can reconstruct all three
classes simultaneously without any
labels of the lat unknown latent
variables and then apply to a real data
set of red blood cell lysate um we can
recover both this ryar complex and a
couple of other complexes present in the
data
set this is kind of doing the
hierarchical classification based
approach with prospark
and uh in contrast just using a single
neural field or Fri Dragon AI we get one
class that looks like the rer complex
but then the other class just or the
other region in the Laten space or it's
just one class becomes a jumble of the
other kind
of that's one extension of this abon ISU
approach the second is moving into cry
and so I'll focus a little bit on this
on the kind of last end of the talk but
I'll just mention that instead of doing
uh cem or instead of having a single
image per particle now we have a series
of images we adapt this two-stage poses
procedure this is really driven by Rish
to the abono setting for subtomograms in
C2 um and then just showing one result
slide this is the kind of translation
elongation states of the 7ds ribosome uh
from Inu data fully trained fully
aition okay so we're making progress on
abon reconstruction one thing to note is
that all these kind of reconstruction
methods we've talked about about are
purely image data driven so we don't
kind of Leverage any information we have
about the underlying kind of chemistry
or the sequence of the mes so one I
think Direction that's very interesting
and I think a lot of people are working
on it right now is can we Bridge these
methods between protein structure
prediction we're using you know the
sequence information all the
evolutionary related sequences and
protein structor determination where we
taking kind of Imaging data and doing
this inverse problem analyzing the
measurement data
PRI reconstruction methods currently
don't leverage any of this PR
information about the underlying PR
physics but if we did could we you know
um push forward what we can get out of
data yeah um On a related note it's not
really directly about the you know
protein language model to um or or the
sequence to structure but um it seems to
me
that the at least the two types of
images that uh R showed in the end there
was a ribosome in the beginning was a
different protein those looked very
different so it occurs to me that it may
be able to one may be able to classify
these to the cropped images as this
protein even if we don't know what the
confirmation is and maybe yeah do some
sort of supervision on I think that
would be really interesting uh because I
think this purely unsupervised way it's
just going to get harder and harder with
more more complex samples and we do know
a lot of stuff maybe we don't even need
the sequence we just need like templates
or something like that so I think that
would would definitely be a really
interesting Direction but it's not
really done yet no
okay good
research cool okay so I don't have
anything super kind of groundbreaking
but one kind of proof of concept
direction that we've been taking is to
use these pre-trained protein diff
Fusion models as a prior in various
types of inverse problems in protein
space um and so this we're not tackling
3D reconstruction yet but we've been
doing some toy experiments uh where
we're filling in kind of doing like
protein infilling uh kind of uh
satisfaction of NMR distance restraints
and cry atomic model building and here
we're what we're doing is turning
partial and noisy measurements from our
experimental data uh and combining this
with a uh pre-trained diffusion model
here
chome um one thing to kind of keep in
mind uh that is always top of Mind
especially when we're combining these
maybe like uh large generative models
trained on existing proteins versus new
experimental data of new proteins that
we want to solve is how much do these
kind of pre-trained models limit the
ability to discover new things so I
think that's like one maybe just core
question to ask and core question to
consider especially with respect to
validation um and just with respect to
what do you want to get out of your
expens um and so that you know led to
kind of this project on Venture Mar
right so now with these kind of large
protein generative models maybe with
some of these other reconstruction
methods that use more you know um like
opinionated forward models uh how do we
actually un how do we actually interpret
the results especially when we're
considering
K so we're in an era now where
reconstruction of these molecular movies
is possible you get these like really
compelling and beautiful visualizations
of these macro machines so here's like a
couple different
methods um the representation so like
how we actually model this distribution
of volumes matters it really can
potentially it does bias the results of
the rec construction and it should
really depend on kind of what prior
information we have about the system and
also what biological question we want to
answer one kind of
unfortunate uh you know uh truth is that
there's no ground Truth For Real data so
we don't really know what's in the data
and evaluation especially when we're
kind of comparing these different models
currently requires just benchmarking by
eye so like does this look reasonable
does not our
priors um and so in Prior bench uh this
was led by minku a graduate student in
the group uh we built a large data set a
large synthetic data set modeling
different types of p8 so I'll go over
that uh briefly and then we benchmarked
10 different methods uh both deep
learning based linear nonlinear abono
methods and also came up with new
metrics and ways of comparing these
different het construction methods um
one thing that I think is particularly
useful for methods developers is the
different kinds of data sets that we
developed so we have both kind of easier
versions of both compet and compet that
are useful for Diagnostic purposes so
this IG 1D is an IGG antibody that has
this simple onedimensional circular
motion and so what you're looking for in
the latent space is a nice Rainbow
Circle um and also ribos assembly which
is a mixture of ribosomes so very
economical PRM and then we are also
considering we designed very challenging
data sets where no methods currently
perform that well to motivate uh kind of
new methods development so one is iggl
so here we're kind of sampling random
dihedral angles from this Linker region
and so I think this is for an antibody
IGG antibody and the Fab is oriented
randomly but I think that's
representative of a lot of systems where
we have a smaller domain that's kind of
moving uh and is kind of disordered
relative to a larger fixed domain Spike
MD is a uh data set generated from a
longtime scale molecular Dynamic
simulation so instead of just like 100
underlying ground tree structures in
this data set there's 46,000 underlying
ground tree structures and so an
interesting question is how well does
the uh do the methods really approximate
this much kind of higher dimensional
spaces structures and then finally Tomo
toin 100 is a mixture of a 100 different
complexes commonly found within cells so
instead of sticking to you know four
different rib assembly ribosome assembly
States or a couple that you usually get
from these structural biology papers can
we push the envelope in terms of much
much larger sets of protein
complexes okay so cry we still
definitely want to check the results
qualitatively um so here's I think Crow
results on these different data sets so
again IGG 1D we have a nice mov Circle
ribos em we have like 16 different
clusters um and maybe in these cases for
Spike MD and Tomo 100 it becomes less
clear how we interpret the
results um and especially when we want
to compare between methods right and so
here's cryo dragon and a bunch of other
hetrogeneous reconstruction methods um
we have both rures and also plant spaces
and so yeah how do we analyze it
yeah so for like MD Spike um in this
situation like in the previous slide it
seemed like there were a continuous
distribution of States so would we
expect the um Maps over here to be kind
of as like with something doing well
would we be able to qualitatively tell
by saying like oh the um Maps look
relatively continuous in this case um
yes and no like you would think right
like if you have a continuous
distribution you would want a continuous
umap but then the layout of these latent
spaces is very arbitrary so how do you
actually you know Quant Quant quantify
the results or like quantify how well uh
these distributions are learn and what
can you really interpret of
these yeah very inspired by similar
challenges from the Single Cell
literature for
example um and so one nice thing is that
we do have quantification can because
this is synthetic data where we know all
of the latent variables all the unknown
variables that are hidden from
construction methods we can kind of
quantify these volume reconstruction
metrics um one thing that we note is no
method dominates dominates across the
different forms of hyrogen so like
compet
compet types of like confirmational
heterogenity abon reconstruction methods
are still needed so this like joint um
confirm inference and pose estimation is
very very challenging inverse problem
and these metrics they're they work you
can kind of compare you can make these
large tables which I think people in
machine learning really like um but
better metrics are still needed and I
think one interesting research Direction
especially if you come from both the
kind of ML and the structural biology
background is designing better metrics
maybe that are dat set specific that can
really answer kind of deeper questions
about you know the different
confirmational states uh in micro States
for example of them
likeed
okay
so what is this all working towards I've
talked about Avid issue reconstruction
I've talked about kind of benchmarking
and really the point of all this of this
heterogeneous reconstruction is to move
to in my opinion my opinion is to move
to more complex samples so instead of
like solving a single structure in its
confirmational state can we instead
solve
complex mixtures or even structures from
intact
cells okay now we can kind of talk about
cryo electric topography I will just do
that by showing
this um instead of a purified solution
of a molecule a purified solution of
your protein or bimolecular complex
interest here you have a whole cell a
whole cell is usually too big to be
electron transparent depending on the
cell um and so what you do is f ion be
Milling you use a beam of ions to Mill
away kind of
oblate a the top and bottom and so what
you're end up what you end up with is a
very thin cross-section of
[Music]
yourself and then instead of a single
image now we do tomography right so it's
the same electron microscope it's same
transmission electron microscope but
instead of just a single image now we
spread electron dose across a series of
images in practice 41 um so we take kind
of 41 images as we rotate this Imaging
stage and we see this 3D kind of slice
out of the cell in all these
different so this is a tomogram right
yep um so the ion beam Milling is lit
physically manipulating the cell um is
there any concern over that affecting
the
um confirmation that the proteins are in
or this
assembling yeah so it's already Frozen
beforehand but there is a lot of kind of
like sample preparation consideration so
if it's a large enough cell you want to
high pressure freeze it so it all
vitrifies at the same time and then this
is actually kind of beyond my area of
expertise but I think there's like a
plasma focused IMB Mill is less likely
to deposit a bunch of other stuff than
like a metal ion or something that so
there are you know thermofisher is
working on it and interested in people
buying their
stuff um okay and on the right this is a
tomogram so this is we take the like 41
separate images or the micrographs and
then just do a 3D reconstruction um and
we can visualize here you know a bag of
rib this is uh s
service and then I think what's been so
exciting about cry
is that even though we're looking at
things at low resolution we can
computationally kind of do the same
trick that we do in single particle PRI
so we can take individual instances of
our molecule of interest and
computationally like Orient them combine
the information aggregate the signal and
get ne Atomic resolution structures but
instead of you know a structure of your
protein in a kind of crystallin lattice
instead of the structure in kind of in
in a
aquous solution in vitro this is the
structure of the protein complex the
ribosome here in C so the actual native
structure that's closest to the
functional state of the of the molecule
of
exas um and in this case they were even
able to see the structure of a small
molecule antibiotic
M okay amazing so why don't we do this
for everything you know unfortunately
the cry processing workflow in practice
look something like this this is
literally the workflow that I think
Sager did to process some of our CR data
analysis um you can kind of appreciate
that the metadata is a lot more
complicated now because we have the set
of images 41 tilts you need to align
them all in 3D and like you know how
much you as you move the Imaging stage
but obviously you want to like
reestimate that and then you have to
like pick out the subtomograms and then
there's actually all these other
considerations on whether we take like
3D data versus 2D data and it just
becomes nightmare practice it's all
academic software as well so you know
yeah I'll just stop there um and in the
cray Dragon ET project um or I guess one
more point I want to make about this
kind of cry processing workflow is a lot
of the you know repetitive nature of it
is because of the heterogen because the
particle picking problem is not solved
although there is a recent kaggle
challenge about that you're headed by
the transer Imaging Institute um and so
you're picking a bunch of like random
stuff that's not necessarily your
protein of interest and then you are
computationally trying to filter it and
analyze the heterogenity and kind of
classify the different states and it's
very very slow and yeah that's the
heterogeneity is definitely one a
contribution to why this processing
workflow is a bit of a
nightmare um and so something that we
worked on in the group right when I
started is extending PR Dragon which
is ideally like in the ideal case useful
for single shot heterogen analysis um of
single particle data to PRI data so the
high level kind of schematic looks
pretty similar um and so the main
changes are instead of a single view
encoder we do a multi view encoder
actually this is a little bit different
than the standard way uh subtomograms
which are kind of these Sub sub volumes
are analyzed so we actually take the
under individual tilted sub
tilted images um and then the Ford Model
instead of single particle crym is cry
which is very similar we just have to
take into account kind of uh the details
about like electron dose
exposure yeah um and then kind of just
highlighting in single particle we have
single image but in soap tomogram
averaging we have kind of multiple views
which is actually kind of interesting
from a verical
standpoint and um in the kind of
development and Analysis of Cry Dragon
ET we were able to apply it to the same
um uh uh 7s ribosome from the
microplasmas pneumonia data set uh done
by the Muhammad Lab at Hy hyberg and see
the same kind of translational States um
and also in collaboration with
thermofisher they collected this very
large uh data set of plasma BM Lamela of
esier we were able to char
the confirm confirmational Landscapes of
the ribosomes and fat fatty acid
comp okay I think I'm actually going to
go through the PRI ET results kind of
quickly just to save time questions um
but again just the overall pipeline we
have a very M we reconstruct a 3D
tomogram and then we pick the individual
instances solve their structures get the
confirmational Landscapes and then in in
addition to seeing the confirmational
states we can also map them back in
spatial context so I think that's a
really powerful aspect of Cry
Dragon this is what we get out of cry
drag e so here's Laten space
representation in this case maybe like a
130,000 particles of the ribosome sorry
19,000 particles and just by visual
inspection we had one class that was one
cluster that was just like kind of drunk
particles one cluster that looked like
the ribosome in the rotated State and
one class that looked like the ribosome
where the small sub small subun small
subunit was in the non rotated
State um because we don't want our model
to be wasting its expressive capacity on
these bad particles we just filter the
data set with the good particles TR it
again we again see this nice kind of
partition partitioning of the two
rotations
St um and then we dug deeper so we're
not just looking into the two like
rotate ratcheted and not ratcheted State
we uh just like visualized mapped out
all these different Elation factors
initiation factors and also the actual
TRNA
finding um
and that sh
right so these you know especially if
you're a maybe crystallographer this is
like very Blobby uh right so you don't
like see the high resolution details but
then we what we did in this case is we
used Crow Dragon to kind of classify
these different states and then we can
do the traditional back projection using
the full resolution
higher resolution structures of these um
translation
elongation um as another kind of
demonstration instead of the ribosomes
which are very abundant we also analyzed
uh the fatty a syas complex so the
traditional kind of subram averaging
approach uh from the picked particles
looks something like this when we look
at the same data set with PRI Dragon ET
we get this Laten space and we see kind
of
a distribution of structures only one
region of which actually looks like the
fatty acid inas complex so when we take
the subset of particles and then do a uh
refinement a traditional refinement we
now get a much higher resolution
beautiful structure of the East P
acid on the left is showing kind of the
training progression of a crow Dragon ET
model um on oh so on just like the the
full data set and I think one of the
main uh takeaways was that this is hap
this happens on like you know less than
an hour so like in only a few minutes we
can actually distinguish good from bad
which would be really good for this kind
of very slow classification process that
takes like weeks or
longer we run a new model on just this
subset of around 5,000 like quote
unquote bonified particles we actually
begin to see the very subtle rotations
of this B Bas complex
um between the two known
States um kind of big picture so we can
visualize these interesting
intermolecular um confirmations one
thing that's interesting is integrating
this processing Pipeline with the
traditional proc processing pipeline um
something that Rish has been working on
recently is aono reconstruction and cry
where we have like much more complex
samples since this is the actual kind of
collection of pren compli that you see
uh in Vivo yeah in C and so can we
actually process this in silico to
reconstruct
molecular this is a slide from my Therma
Fisher collaborator although I think
he's recently moved to St Jude um
traditionally in structural biology the
analysis of data sets is per very kind
of like done by the group so each group
will analyze collect a data set analyze
it then deposit into to the pdb priority
data kind of fundamentally breaks the
Paradigm I think of structural biology
because in a couple ways one it's like
much large kind of much larger in scale
it's much more expensive um kind of
experimentally to collect the data
extremely expensive computationally to
process the data it's very very hard and
the data set doesn't just give you a
single structure it gets you kind of the
entire molecular details of the whole uh
the whole
organism um and so I think there's this
new paradigm that that uh especially
Folks at the Chan Zuckerberg Imaging
Institute are really kind of inspired to
do which is um instead of all kind of
working on different things all
collaborating together and
analyzing as a
community um and so to summarize um
again just recapitulating some of the
things that Rish said so crym and cry
are particularly interesting modalities
since we capture this new type of data
of um
um you know where molecules are in a
quote near native state sampled from a
quote equilibrium distribution cations
where these quotation marks are the
caveats uh due to sample kind of
preparation there are now many Tools in
addition to cry Dragon becoming
available to study hogen and cryoem so
as a practitioner kind of the choice and
algorithm encodes a lot of different
assumptions about the heterogeneity that
you might visualize from the model and
so that's always important to keep in
mind that's driven our bench marking
work cry dragon's kind of neural field
is a very expressive model of
heterogeneity and so I think that's nice
to be able to discover new States in a
relatively unbiased setting as well as
visualize these continuous
Dynamics um and then the last thing I
want to end on is a couple of thoughts
of crym in this post Al
era or not there we go so what's next
um I definitely think there are very
interesting things to do in just this
machine learning for cing reconstruction
setting for heterogenity how do we bring
in the kind of underlying Atomic models
um or the underlying chemistry or
physics but I do think kind of models
that break this Paradigm will be very
kind of uh beneficial for the whole carg
and processing pipeline we can really
broaden the scope to more challenging
targets or challenging systems um PRM
right now is still you know quite
bespoke and manually intensive
especially this traditional 3D
classification procedure so can we you
know commoditize and just like automate
a bunch of the crry and
processing and can kind of new machine
learning methods motivate different
paradigms for Imaging and processing
right so are really stuck to just like
single image and uh can we design
different ways of collecting the data
for header
sh obviously moving forward kind of the
uh one kind of main takeaway I have of
especially crime data is that um these
current generation of structure
prediction models don't predict dynamics
that well like the different
confirmational ensembles and so if we
can just collect the data to train the
next generation of prediction or design
algorithms I think that would be very
exciting so closing the loop between
prediction and determination and really
kind of unlocking new applications um in
kind of understanding Pro Dynamics
proing design and also the interaction
ction with other types of molecules that
are not as commonly
found and then finally bringing this all
together uh for Inu visual proteomics
with Technologies like Crow as well as
other types of biochemical and
bio with that uh thank you all for
listening to two hours of prum almost um
and I would especially like to thank
members of my group so Raman and Ryan
drove the Cry Dragon ET project Axel has
been doing a ton of work on both post
estimation as well as our APD 3D method
which with the uh chroma or the prot
fusion models Rish has played an
instrumental role in like so many of
these different projects um mq drove cry
bench and Michael um has been supporting
the software and integrating a bunch of
these new methods into PR dragon as well
as uh like to thank the other members of
my group a bunch of our collaborators um
and our funding sources and thank you
all for listening e