Okay. Hi everyone. I'm super excited
actually to be back at MIT. I left as a
PhD coming back as a
founder founder of displayed and
displayed enhances um transportation
safety thanks to a solution that
leverages data to perform bridge health
monitoring in a way that is scalable and
standardized. But let let's go a bit
back to the origin. In 2018, we had a
huge accident in in Italy. Um so I
started a PhD during on structural
health monitoring of bridges during
which I met my phenomenal co-founders
and um it brought me to MIT where I also
met professor Carloati of director of
sensible city lab as one of our founding
shareholders and altogether we decided
to bring in the market um an academic
experience uh extremely deep in the
sector to solve a pressing global
problems. Poor maintenance is the root
cause of collapses worldwide and this is
honestly
unacceptable. Notwithstanding the
technology we have, we are still relying
on this. This is the main tool to assess
maintenance which is visual inspections.
They are subjective, inherently
qualitative, expensive,
infrequent and we should use data. data
are there but basically monitoring
solutions based on data are today a
niche in the market and why is that
because there is fairly no
interpretation of this data and
management companies don't need data
they need actionable insights they
require huge initial investment that's
it's okay on the golden gate what about
all the other 99.9% of bridges and they
are not integrated um we are trying to
redefine the rules of the game We
conceived and realized a monitoring
solution suitable for widespread
adoption across the whole network. What
we offer is a monitoring as a service
which means we we start with a provision
of proprietary sensors, data collection,
data analysis that the street results of
our PhDs and then of course information
delivery thanks to a very
simple basically asset management
platform. By doing this, our solution is
able to cut 70% of deployment cost and
time, enhancing scalability and we are
three times more efficient in
identifying early on structural
anomalies. But we are at MIT. So let's
go a bit deeper into the technology. Um
we are first presenting our smart
sensor. So basically what we built is a
family of sensors with the same data
quality of traditional wire solutions
but without wires. So extremely handy,
easy to deploy, quick and that's again I
like to call them the wearables of the
bridges and they collect data that we
analyze with our algorithms. They were
tested on years of data coming for on
from more than 25 bridges. This was I
would say what we mainly developed
during our PhDs. They are they are
proven effectively uh to be able to
tackle damage scenarios potentially
critical and currently totally
unnoticeable with traditional
techniques. So all these things have to
be combined in something easy. So a
platform that's basically based on
thresholds. It has to be a traffic light
that also my mother should be able to
understand is like what you should do
where you should act and how can you
enhance the safety and efficiency of the
network through your bridges. Um a bit
back into the topic of the conference
why AI on bridges transportation
networks features a high structural
complexity large number of
infrastructures which means huge amount
of data and thus need for
standardization. This is the sweet spot
for AI technology. More than that, some
problems can be extremely challenging to
model. So through AI, we can shift from
a modelbased approach to a datadriven
one where we can inference complex
mathematical model from data. And I want
to talk you about a real case study was
2020. We were monitoring a bridge during
our PhD. We were there for a year and
then a severe flood in the bridge. Now,
can you imagine how can I model the
effect of a flood on a 100 uh year old
bridge in Italy? Impossible. But thanks
to data, we could basically learn from
what we had before and follow the bridge
day after day, saving
€300,000 to the Italian for the Italian
government and keeping the bridge open
without any traffic disruption until it
settle back to its original prefall
status. I'm not talking about the market
uh because you know uh what I want to do
is we are now operating in Italy but we
are trying to see to feel the
temperature here in the US to see if the
market is ready. We would like to talk
to government agencies, department of
transportation, city of Cambridge, city
of Boston to know if they feel this
problem as being pressing. Of course, we
refer to these as people who benefit
from our solution, but we also see this
technology to become a play in the asset
management on all large infrastructure
that are basically at at the the root
foundation of the so the soio economic
development of countries worldwide.
Thank you very much.
Thank you, Lorenzo.