Hi. So, yes. So, I'm Kathleen Kennedy
and I work now at Open Learning,
although I used to work with David at
technology review. So, it was really fun
to see that. I'm going to talk to you
about a new initiative that we're doing
over at Open Learning. But before I jump
into that, I want to ask how many people
in this room are MIT alumni? How many
people went to school at MIT?
Ah, so like maybe 5%. That's really
interesting. So I'm going to guess that
the rest of you come here to hear
conversations like this, to learn new
things, to figure out what's going on in
the world and how do we make sense of
it, right? MIT is really good at that.
And we're also really good at figuring
out new technologies. So MIT Open
Learning, let me level set about what we
do at MIT Open Learning. So we basically
take right the MIT mission of advancing
science and technology and creating
really really smart people that are
changing the world. We look at how can
we do that in our industry which is
education and how can we push the
boundaries and innovate in the education
space.
Let me take you through a little
timeline. So I've been at MIT for 25
years and so like I love looking at
something like this and seeing you know
what are the things that we have done.
So MIT became the first institute of
higher education to offer free education
for the world. Right? So we opened up
what it is that we do and made it free
to everyone. That was with something
called OCW.
Fast forward to 2011 2012 we created
actually an a group that was going to do
that not just creating muks but
basically looking at how do we really
innovative in this space of education
then in 2015
on the solve stage I don't know if any
of you have ever heard of MIT solve but
it's something that we actually launched
at technology review and then and then
spun it out for the whole institute
um that
education was one of the key aspects of
the things that we did. So we w launched
that there. Then in 2019, we launched a
program that I now lead called MIT
Horizon. That is an enterprise level
content library and way that we can
bring emerging technologies to everyone
in the world to understand what do they
do and that's specifically fine-tuned
for large organizations.
In 2020, we launched something called
the DCC, which is looking at how do we
do digital credentials in new ways.
And then what I'm here to talk to you
about today, what we're really excited
about is how do we bring MIT
to everyone in the world?
How do we deliver personalized learning
for a billion people powered by MIT,
powered by AI?
built by MIT and you think maybe we
built AI too. We'll see. We are building
a lot of AI around to power this. So
this summer we launched something called
MIT Learn which is a new front door for
all of the education things that you can
do with MIT. So everything that is not
being a student at MIT,
executive education,
open courseware, lifelong learning and
basically you can see on any MIT page
there's a footer now called lifelong
learning. So how do you do this with
MIT? So it's a singular destination that
we've basically brought together all of
the offerings that we have across the
institute to help you understand how
does AI work? How do you use it? How do
you become sort of a leader in supply
chain? How do you how do you like
understand a lot of the things that you
just heard at this panel and are hearing
throughout this conference today? Now,
we are adding a lot of really cool
things in doing this. One of them is
called Ask Tim. So, you can sort of
figure that out. That's MIT backwards.
Tim is MIT's mascot. And we've actually
created MIT mascots for our online
learning. So, they're AI tools. So,
we've got a number of Ask Tims on the
site now that are that are different
fine-tuned AI GPTs that we've built for
all of this content. So, basically, how
do you have a guidance system on what
you need to to learn next or what do you
choose to do?
How do you go deeper in understanding
what the different things are? How do
you have a TA, your own personal
teaching assistant to help you to learn
what you're doing? And then how do you
have your own tutor? Right? So instead
of like having to depend on a human to
do things, we've got a fine-tuned AI
that is doing that for all of our new
learning materials. Now, what's very
exciting is what we're building next. So
to truly be able to deliver personalized
learning and to be able to deliver on
this mission, we are figuring out how to
do holistic assessments on all kinds of
learning so that you really understand
how someone's truly following the
program. How to do translation, right? I
would imagine this is a very global
group. How do we how do we deliver
things in
20 40 any language, right? And how can
we do that instantaneously?
How do we deliver it in a a perfectly
mobile friendly way? Now, we mostly
already do that, but we know a lot of
the world that's what they use.
And then how do we do this personalized
instruction? like how do we get to what
every single one of you in this audience
how do we deliver just for you what you
want so that's what we've got some
really smart MIT students and faculty
working on so Dmitri Bert Seamus is the
associate provost of open learning and
let me just show you a few things that
that he and his students are working on
so first is thinking about online
learners all all of You have different
things that you want, different
interests, backgrounds, goals, right?
So, how do we deliver what you want?
Then secondly, each of you learn
differently. Some of you like listening
to people talk, some people like reading
things, some people like doing, right?
So, everyone learns in different ways.
So, how do we help with the time that
you have, the pace, all of these
different aspects about things?
So right now
online learning is sort of one
sizefits-all right so you have
>> let me give you some of the details of
multiple linear regression model we are
given data of the dependent variable y I
the price realization of auction I and
independent variables
x subscript i
Okay, MIT class, MIT level learning
brought to you from an MIT professor.
That's one way of doing it. And he's
it's a one to many, one-sizefits-all.
But you're in the healthcare industry.
That example didn't make sense to you.
We have a a way to be able to turn that
lecture
into
different examples so it could be
customized in real time for a different
industry. Right? Then it can be
customized for length. So
>> 30 second summary.
>> There you go.
>> We model log wine price as yi= beta plus
beta 1 x1 plus e fitted by minimizing
the sum of squared errors. SSE R² equals
1 my S SSE SST measures how much better
we do than predicting.
>> Now imagine that we want that
And then imagine that you are a student
and you got this question wrong.
How do we have a personalized tutor that
is going to give you the right answer?
Imagine that there's someone talking
right there and telling you what the
right answer is. So, there's going to be
also ways that you can this can be
customized very easily and quickly using
a back-end system of how we're doing
this because we're also developing this
not only for the world, but we're
actually building tools that all of our
MIT faculty can use and then we're
working with partner organizations all
around the world to bring this new type
of learning that is personalized for
everyone. on to do. So what we're
looking to do is actually bring learning
right now MIT students are one in a
million that in fact we want to deliver
MIT
learning to one in seven people in the
world. So we would love it if you joined
us. We've got a table in the next room.
Come check us out and thank you. Enjoy
the rest of the show.