yeah we just did the quiz and that's for
people who are watching this later
that's not on the video we're going to
do some introduction to music cognition
I don't think we're going to have time
but um we can also unlock voice leading
if we do now I'm going to put this
down great and I'm going to turn off
these
it's
okay turn off that is that okay yeah
that's better um great so music
cognition is one of these um things that
intersects with huge numbers of parts of
Music um in general music theory with
music history with performance with um
you know performance anxiety all these
things uh but it also has a big impact
on computational music especially
computational music theory um it sort of
formed this field and it continues to be
part of it I just want to uh give a
little introduction from uh professor of
Music cognition at uh Northeastern down
street and also Wesleyan uh psyche Louie
um just a couple minutes while I also
check to make sure I have the we we'll
see if the sound's still working
consider for instance this musical
example all right you might say that
sounds nice and normal kind of like
saying um I took the T here
today what about
this right if you think that sounded
normal you can come talk to me
afterwards and we might sign you up for
that tone deafness study we're doing
um now so when you heard that last core
your brain does a double take right
there's something about it that that's
like saying I took the T here octopus
nothing wrong with octopus but it just
doesn't fit the context of what happened
before it it doesn't fit the grammar now
this double take that your brain dust
can be measured using electrical
potentials on the surface of the scalp
this is a picture of my mom and getting
her brain potentials recorded and she's
got 64 electrodes on her cap there and
what those do is make recordings like
this so on the left I'm showing you our
brain responses to expected and
unexpected musical chords and and on the
right I'm showing you the the difference
between expected and unexpected on the
surface of the scalp so there's a bird
ey view of the scalp so right away you
can see that 200 milliseconds after the
on of the unexpected cord your brain is
doing this double take right saying oh
that was unexpected 500 milliseconds you
get um the brain saying oh how do I
integrate that into what happened
before so this is telling us with
millisecond accuracy that we know about
music there's something about our brains
that is very sensitive to what's
grammatical um in western music so the
question is where does this knowledge
come from how do we come to know what we
know so to answer that question we again
have to go all the way back to the
ancient Greeks Pythagoras found that if
two strings are being played together
where one string is twice the length of
the other um those two sound good
together they sound consonant so this
2:1 frequency ratio um is what
supposedly brought us closer to the
Greek gods in fact the word Symphony um
originally means vibrating in Perfect
Harmony using these mathematical integer
ratios so this 2:1 frequency ratio is
true of music all around the world now
different cultures divide that 2 to1 fre
queny ratio in different ways and our
culture the equal tempered Western
chromatic scale divides them in 12 steps
so this is how it
[Laughter]
[Music]
sounds okay then these two guys came
along and said does it have to be this
way why 2:1 why not 3:1 so the bowl and
Pier scale is based on a 3:1 frequency
ratio and within that we've got 13
logarithmic divisions of that scale so
you still get get some mathematical
inter ratio so the Greek gods are not
offended here um but what this sounds
like is completely different from
Western or other types of
[Laughter]
[Music]
music so this is a really powerful
approach um to find out what people know
about music in the laboratory so we can
be pretty sure that people have never
heard this music before but when they
come in then they can listen to this
music for a while and then we can
measure how they come to know what they
know so I'm going to play you for about
a minute um a snippet of a piece by
Stephen ye it's called reminiscences and
it's written in the bow and Pier scale
just so you get an idea
[Music]
so this really is kind of an
otherworldly new musical experience that
we're entering here um and in our lab
what we wanted to do was figure out how
people learn this new musical system so
we have these well-controlled Melodies
that people listen to for about half an
[Music]
hour so you listen to these things for
half an hour and they're they're defined
using rules and principles or
grammatical structures that we've
defined ourselves and then the question
is what can people learn from this new
musical experience first thing we found
was that memory increases with with
repetition turns out also that
preference increases with repetition so
what we're seeing here is the beginning
of musical taste right the more you
listen to something the more you begin
to like it but what I'm interested in is
how learning occurs and it turns out
that learning does not occur with
repetition but with variability in other
words the more different ways you tell
people something the more people are
able to infer the underlying structure
of what you tell them and then to
generalize those to new instances of the
same grammar now our question becomes
now
and that's where I stop for here because
we can look at that online and I want
you to um just get as excited um for our
two two guest speakers who are going to
be um talking on zoom on Friday and
after um after break uh here on campus
so we're going to be talking uh
primarily in the next couple classes
about uh the work well first clar Arthur
is going to present her own work and
then we'll be talking about two um major
figures uh in music cognition one is uh
Carol Kum hunel and uh her Landmark book
cognitive foundations of musical pitch
which is all about how do we process
pitch how do we think how do we put it
into particular areas and so that's
pretty important for music cognition but
it's also formed her work on this formed
the basis for every
computational almost every for the I
yeah I can't say the wrong things uh for
the most widely used key detection in
key algorithm finding um mechanisms so
here uh this is our favorite bwv
66.6 looking at different sizes of
amount of memory that we have and we can
see that um where is at certain um
things a major is coming up and and then
we're moving from one key to another as
uh as our cognition goes so we'll be
looking into um her
work the second uh major figure is um
David hiron whose name might have
appeared um as a secondary author of one
of the um articles that you may have
discussed on the midterm um in his his
um Landmark book sweet anticipation
music and the psychology of expectation
you're going to have access to this book
um totally on the website um in uh by
Friday and um but it's I I feel like if
there's one
thing worth spending your money to own
in sort of a physical copy coming out of
this class it's this book first off it's
not too expensive it's like 22 bucks or
something but it's just um amazing the
types of things uh and talks about his
own work but mostly it's a collection of
sort of the greatest hits of Music
cognition also by others um and so this
is a particular experiment that I think
is really great um Bolognese musicians
and American musicians were given uh a
banese Melody that was there and then
they were betting um on whether or not I
believe it was the next note goes up or
down after that and you see The
Bolognese musician and so this is how
uncertain they are so lower is more
certain the Bales musicians when they
hear this traditional Bolognese thing
they're they're just doing great they're
they're making money head over heels and
then uncertainty goes up when it goes
into a different direction CU this was a
crafted Melody designed to
uh do that and so being able to check
out things like that we'll also be
looking um a little bit at Rhythm and
rhythmic uncertainty um and the types of
things that um that music cognition
might tell us for how to generate Rhythm
so this is a this is a particularly um
slightly complex graph but um but it's
actually I think it's the simplest way
to explain this diagram say you have um
you have three
notes whatever three notes they
are say that their total duration sum up
to
one and then you can figure out how much
what percentage or what fraction of the
duration each of the notes takes up oh
gosh uh let's see that's 1 half what's
that that's 38 thank you and it's 1/8 um
and then you can place each of them
between one and zero on this chart and
this triangular chart lets you uh show
the proportion of each of three things
at the same time and one of the things
that comes out of this oh I did um is
that there's not one point where people
perceive so so there's one point where
it should be exactly right so 314 uh 211
should be exactly here on the 25% AIS
for one on the 25% access for another
and the 50% for a third one so it should
be right here and
314 um I guess in this way 38 1/8 48
should be right here and one of the
things that cognitive um studies has
shown is that people perceive things a
little bit differently so this entire
region of playing is perceived in this
experiment as the 211 or 1/2 1/4 1 qu
whereas the region that was perceived as
314 four is actually does not include
the mathematically correct 38 1/8 uh
48 and so we'll look at experiments that
try to charart the whole landscape of
rhythmic perception and you can imagine
that that could also be useful if you're
generating music that when you generate
patterns and you want people to hear
them and you don't want it to sound
computer you might do something else um
but by far the tit the title of the book
is called sweet anticipation and by far
I think the most interesting for me part
of this is studying anticipation
expectation and surprise and so I was
playing um when you all walked in a
piece by um Peter shley uh PDQ Bach um
fake Bach humorist and what I love is a
little experiment here where it's we're
going to be playing something that
breaks expectations now you'll hear some
laughter on the soundtrack that's
probably also physical cool things are
happening on stage that we can't see
because it's just an audio version but
listen to what people find funny
musically and how it has to do with the
breaking of expectations so you're going
to be listening to a little thing this
is about we're going to start about 20
seconds before this figure so there's
going to be a bunch of other things and
maybe just look for a second yourself on
what expectation might be broken here
[Music]
you hear the accompaniment in wrong
places
[Music]
there's a particular expectation for how
um how things might be um might be going
and stuff and oh um and I think these
are our two uh guests they're um both
named Claire they're in alphabetical
order though Clare Arthur will be coming
first coming from Georgia Tech and
Claire pelofi coming from nyu's music
and audio research laboratory uh I'm
bringing in guests in part because uh
this is something I music cognition is
something I think is really really
important but it's probably the weakest
topic for me as a teacher in this field
so uh you should be getting this
information from people who uh do it
much better than me so that's uh great
who uh we have seven minutes left who
wants to program and unlock and who
wants to go um if it's early unlock go
okay great have a great time have a
great uh break and I I don't want to
start a new topic in seven minutes
either so um have a good good sorry I'll
see you after break in person but I'll
see you all on Friday um so thank you