my name is Josh Santos and I'm the
co-founder and CEO of noya about 10
years ago I had the pleasure of uh of
paying my dues in the MIT chemical
engineering department I learned a lot
of fundamentals in heat and heat and
energy balances how to create flow
diagrams and uh how to properly deprive
yourself of sleep in order to get that
degree today I have the privilege of
supporting this team of about 30 people
that you see on the slide here to build
what we're thinking about as a gigaton
scale approach to direct air carbon
capture that's all electric interrupt
able and water positive now we've got an
incredible team of people that's got
skill sets ranging in all walks of
professional life everything from
engineering R&D commercial activity
project development You Name It We got
it and from institutions that are
leading in what they do places like
Tesla NG impact plenty pnnl and other
amazing research
organizations we're ultimately solving
what is the biggest challenge that
Humanity faces in climate change if you
boil down all types of climate
Technologies they sort of fall into one
of two key buckets bucket one is
technologies that are working on
preventing new emissions from entering
into the atmosphere that's this whole
gray chunk right here this is everything
like solar and wind which prevents us
needing to burn natural gas to create
electricity novel ways of making
chemicals in order to prevent new
emissions lots of fun stuff like that
there's a second bucket though that's
required and that's the removal of
historic emissions this purple chunk
here this is new we haven't really
needed to do this and it's pretty wild
to have to do it if you think about it
CO2 in the air is really dilute 420
parts per million for us to need to do
this is pretty crazy but for us to need
to do this on a billions of tons scale
is even crazier and the speed at which
we have to get there I think is the is
the is the part of this that really
boggles the Mind here we have to scale
this industry by about 50% year on-ear
for the next 25 years for us to meet
climate targets as the UN has put
forward that's a really big challenge
how do we do that well it's even harder
to think about when you couple on top of
that the fact that all of these new
emerging Technologies like artificial
intelligence are threatening to make
these goals difficult to reach whether
it's because of the fact that these
centers that are going to be performing
all of the data the data processing for
AI are incredibly carbon intensive or
whether the it's the fact that they also
require tons of water in order to
operate the cooling mechanisms that are
necessary coupling all of these things
on top of each other is a really wild
thing to have to think about
solving at Noya we're designing a an
approach to direct air capture that's
designed to meet this very moment that
we're in right now our approach to
direct air capture is all electric
meaning that it runs only uh using
electricity and it's and it can
integrate directly alongside existing
forms of renewable energy it's
interruptible meaning we can operate
intermittently like solar and wind does
and it's water positive we produce 5 to
seven cubic meters of water per ton of
CO2 and since our future commercial
projects are going to be a million tons
that's a l a lot of CO2 and a lot of
water that we'll be
producing now I'd like to talk about our
technology like it's a BRI filter but
for carbon negativity in that we clean
CO2 and water out of the air instead of
dirty gunk out of water it works by
moving excuse me it works by moving uh
moving air into contact with the
material that we've developed that
material is reactive with both CO2 and
water and it sits inside of a modular
piece of equipment that's like a solar
panel for carbon negativity in that we
can build the same exact design to
achieve whatever skill we need to we
input energy in the form of electricity
to release gaseous CO2 and water from
our material the water we give to folks
that want to use it for whatever they
need and the CO2 we inject underground
for permanent removal and
storage now we've been able to find some
incredible traction with the solution so
far we've got millions of dollars of
pre-orders for the carbon removal
credits that we'll be producing from
some of the organizations you can see on
the slide here Shopify is our biggest
customer we're excited to have their
support and uh and we're also excited to
announce today that we are partnering
with Johnson Matthew who we got
introduced to through the ILP actually
thank you for that introduction who's
going to be supporting us in scaling up
our carbon capture material to the
millions of tons scale per
year now we're looking for lots of folks
to talk to but really it boils down into
into a few key buckets if you're a
corporation that's looking to achieve
your climate targets and you want to
talk about how carbon removal can help
you do that come find me or my colleague
John who's sitting right here in the
middle if you're looking for ways to
Source water that is really hard to find
and you think that there's a way that we
might be able to help you with the pure
atmospherically generated water that we
produce said NOA would love to chat
about that again we got a lot and we
don't really have any use for it in our
own process so we're looking for
partners in that world and uh if you're
looking to to proliferate renewable
energy and want a flexible load to
deploy alongside your assets we'd love
to talk to you about that as well
ultimately the demand for clean
electrons in this country is going to
continue to up strip Supply and that's
something that we are very perfectly
poised to help solve it no of so again
we'll be at the booth over there in a
little bit come find me or my colleague
John John put your hand up so folks see
you there he is hey John come find us
later we'd love to talk to you thanks
everybody
[Applause]