culture is one of those topics that
thankfully we all know something about
this is because we're surrounded by
cultures throughout our lives and we're
actually shaped by them in important
ways we grow up in households with
cultures we grow up in towns and cities
and states and even our Nations have
cultures in our work organizations there
in many cases very visible symbols of
culture but the deeper levels of culture
really are deeply held beliefs our
ideologies or values let me give you one
example and that's the Seal of MIT you
see a man with tools and then you see
one man reading a book and that
illustrates this men's atmus which means
mind in hand and what this represents is
some of the ideals of mit's Founders
that our education has very practical
value so this very visible manifestation
of mit's culture actually has very real
and and deeper meaning for more MIT
moments from MIT open learning like
subscribe or follow