okay good
morning
so we started talking about
multicomponent systems
mixtures and our program is
that at the beginning we try to see when
it is possible to
infer the properties of the mixture as
much as
possible from the properties of the pure
components and so we we are in the
process of defining some ideal
situations in which this is
possible which as we said is a good
start
in our modeling
efforts it's like a
reference simple situation in which uh
we do not to need to
add experimental uh uh
data to model our
mixtures but then we will find that in
practice uh the ideal situation is
really only a a limiting situation which
is not fulfilled by any U uh real
mixture ex except in some
limits
nevertheless
uh we gain a lot of information by just
looking at ideal situations
so
uh we have um defined these partial
properties that
are derivatives of
functions of the chemical
potentials for
example this the partial entropy of the
constituent in the mixture which is a
function of of TP and why we will uh
have to be careful uh in distinguishing
well uh between the partial entropy of
constituent in the mixture and the s
double I TP which is going to be which
is uh the
specific uh property the specific
entropy of pure component I when at the
same temperature and pressure of the
mixture we will see that uh they are
somehow related and the difference is
measurable so we have to pay a lot of
attention to the subscripts like so
single sub subrip is a partial property
for the mixture double subscrip is
specific property of the pure
component and then we Define the partial
volume which is another derivative of
the chemical potential once we know the
chemical potentials as function of
temperature pressure and
composition we Define the partial energy
and also we Define the partial enthalpy
and let me just uh stress this one uh if
you have the expression for the chemical
potential and you divide it by the
temperature and take the derivative not
with respect to T but with respect to
the inverse of the
temperature then you get the the partial
enthalpy this formula will come out uh a
while often and uh also this one which I
better uh write here
on the
board we can write it this
way
okay so we can say that uh we can see
that the from this relation here we can
see that chemical potential can be of
the component in the
mixture can be written as this linear
combination enthalpy minus TS which
essentially is also equal to the gibbsa
free energy so this is also equal
to the uh partial gives a free
energy uh and
U and in fact the the derivative of G
with respect to ni with
at fixed T and P and the other
constituents
that's the definition of the chemical
potential in terms of the Gibs free
energy but it's also you could also call
it by analogy with these definitions the
partial Gibs free energy of the
constituent in the mixture so in other
words we're saying that the chemical
potential can be interpreted itself as a
partial property it's the partial gives
free energy of the constituent in the
mixture and the reason why we call these
properties
partial is because they
contribute
um to the pro to building up the
property
of of the mixture by simple
multiplication with their
amounts and each and you can do this for
entropy volume uh energy the free
energies the
enthalpy they all they all have the same
uh
structure of course now we we uh forget
uh the small systems and we focus on
large systems so this is the the right
hand side the highlighted formulas
because for smaller for small systems we
would have also to some contributions
that correct uh this expression in terms
of the oiler free energy
okay so
how do we
measure these partial
properties and here's a set
up we take a mixture with a given
composition in stable equilibrium of
course we the I don't not repeating it
uh uh often enough but we're still um we
are concentrating our attention out on
the stable equilibrium
State and so we take a mixture with some
given composition at a stable
equilibrium State at temperature and
pressure
p and
uh the we put it in in mutual
equilibrium with the thermal
reservoir of the kind that can
exchange uh also volume so you have also
the pressure equality as a condition for
Mutual equilibrium between your mixture
and the
reservoir then we take a little
bit of pure component
I and we add it to the mixture and we
wait until the mix
goes
again to Mutual equilibrium with that
thermal
reservo okay so this is a mixing
process in which we add a small amount
of one of the
components and then since we can measure
properties of
systems for example let me take the
enthalpy and so let me measure the
difference between the
enthalpy
of the
mixture in this final
State and the enthalpy of the composite
system of the mixture plus the pure
component in the initial
State okay so this is for the mixture in
the final State the amounts are the same
but the amount for the constituent are I
is n plus
DN this is the
initial where in the mixture I just have
ni I and the dni is separate from the
mixture so it
contributes uh with its
own uh to the enthalpy of the the pure
uh constituent through its specific
property of the pure component and
notice that
usually as I said several times enthalpy
is not an additive property but if
you're looking
at um systems that are at the same
temper pressure then enthalpy is an
additive and therefore the enthalpy of
the composite of these two subsystems is
equal to the sum of the two enthalpies
like we do here the sum of the enthalpy
of the mixture plus the enthalpy of the
pure
component okay
now if we take this and divide it by the
amount of u constituent I I that we have
um added to the
mixture that
defines the
change in the enthalpy due to the
addition
of that amount of of a small amount of
the
component and of course DN is supposed
to be small so we're taking the limit of
these which
is which can be viewed as an incremental
product at least the part with the
capital
H it's a partial derivative of Capital H
with respect to ni and then there is
this additional contribution of the
separate pure component that we have
added which uh since I divided I'm
dividing by D
ni uh adds but with a minus sign a
contribution here now now we recognize
that this derivative is exactly what we
defined as the partial
enthalpy of the constituent in the
mixture in the previous slide so here we
have the difference between the partial
enthalpy and the specific enthalpy of
pure component at the same T and P of
the
mixture this is what we call the
enthalpy of isotherm baric
mixing TP stand for
ISO isothermal and isobaric because we
are doing this uh in uh a fixed tnp
imposed by the
reservoir this can be
measured
enthalpy in a process like this is
essentially uh if you make the energy
balance this is essentially the U the
heat exchange with the uh thermal
Reservoir so you measure it with a
calorimeter
so that means that since you can measure
this with a calorimeter and you know the
properties of pure substances then you
have measured the partial enthalpy of
the component in the mixture and this
doesn't require any particular uh
assumptions uh about the mixture being
ideal or non ideal we actually haven't
even defined yet what ideal
means it's simply a tool a method with
which people
measure properties of of of
mixtures and what we have done here for
the enthalpy can be repeated U the same
way so uh I'm not repeating it here but
uh to
Define uh
the volume of
mixing so it's the difference between
the partial volume and the specific
volume at the same tnp the energy of
mixing and the entropy of
mixing and these are all things that you
can measure by energy and entropy
balances so these are ways in which you
can characterize okay this is is a oops
sorry yeah there is a an
extra
uh character there
okay all right so now let's peruse that
equation which I've written up there on
the
board and
substitute the expression of the uh
partial enthalpy
as uh hii so the specific enthalpy of
the pure component times the enthalpy of
mixing and the same for the entropy s
partial we can write it as s specific of
the pure
component times the entropy of isobaric
mixing all right so then we recognize
that also for the pure substance
um H minus TS is the chemical
potential so this gives us a
relation for the chemical potential the
component in the mixture in terms of the
chemical potential of the pure component
at the same temperature and pressure of
the mixture
plus the enthalpy of mixing minus t *
the entropy of
mixing and at this stage we should also
remember that by the definition of
partial pressures of components in a
mixture you
recall that that is defined by the
condition of mutual equilibrium across a
membrane permeable only to constituent I
so at that Mutual equilibrium across the
membrane you have a quality of chemical
potentials so the chemical potential of
a constituent in the mixture is also
equal to the chemical potential and here
there is also another mistake this
should be a double
I this is the chemical potential of the
pure component on the other side of the
um um semi- perable
membrane uh and therefore yes at the
same temperature of the mixture but at
the pressure which
is what we call the partial pressure
okay so again here I cut and paste makes
uh uh errors propagate so this should be
double I and double I okay
so the we're now taking this last
equality and putting in evidence the
difference and so taking a essentially
uh this term to the right hand
side so I have the chemical potential uh
the difference evaluated between
pressure the partial pressure and the
pressure of the
mixture pii minus
P now
here we have
already proved in a in a previous uh
slide maybe we we can just remind
ourselves of how we got here um that
um so we are having that uble I Pi I I
I'm sorry at the
T and p i i minus new double I
TP okay you see
um if I have a function of uh
X and the difference of a function
evaluated at two different points I can
always write by the integral calculus uh
equation that this is equal to the
integral from X2 to
X1 of the D derivative of that function
let's call it
um and this x Prime is a dami variable
of
integration okay so this you can write
for any for any function so
here we apply this
theorem so uh this x X2 is
p X1 is P1 I
I and the dtive we the derivative we
have to put here is the partial
derivative with respect to
P of what of the chemical potential of
the pure
component while the other variables are
TP I'm sorry
t uh and this is to
be
evaluated at at the the vales the value
of the dami variable so pble
Prime and integrated over the dami
variable
but if you look up uh the many equations
that we have derived also for the for
the pure
substance this
derivative is the specific
volume okay so this becomes
the specific
volume of the pure component evaluated
at temperature T and at the dami
pressure p of integration pble
Prime
okay all right so
that explains this integral
here but above we we've seen that this
difference in chemical potentials is
equal to the um
uh Delta H mix minus TS Delta s
mix
okay now look at U look at
this um volume
if if I have a an ideal
gas if I if I can uh if my substance I
behaves according to the ideal gas
relation uh the specific volume can be
written as
RT over p and the pressure that we
should evaluate is
P that is here so it's p double
Prime and so when I do this
integral uh RT goes outside because I'm
integrating over P pble Prime and the
integral of of uh 1 / p is the logarithm
so that gives me the formula uh
RT log
of p i i over
p and that's for the
gas if
instead I have a
liquid and I can use the
incompressible liquid
model for which the specific volume v I
I is
approximately
constant meaning independent of
temperature and
pressure well if it is a constant it
goes out of the integral and then this
becomes uh the specific volume times p i
i minus
p and here in the
slide I just switched
uh
because the pressure usually greater
than the partial pressure so I um put
this difference in parenthesis and then
I pick up a minus sign on the other side
okay so this formula will be
useful
in in a
moment and
again we see that there is a relation
between the partial
pressures very expit explicit
relations in
terms of the enthalpy and the entropies
of isobaric
mixing so this is a way in which you can
measure partial
pressures because you can measure the
properties of isothermic mixing
for example
here uh I want to sort of point you
to a couple of
references which if you go and take a
look un Veil
um uh a
huge uh
literature uh so a huge um community
that
over uh many decades or perhaps uh over
more than a than a century have been
measuring properties this
way and they're still doing it because
the applications uh are
growing for example this is a
um an experimental paper where they
collect uh uh they measure the enthalpy
of isothermic mixing of liquids and
these liquids
are molten
salts that as you may know uh are used
in various
applications
including solar thermal
applications in in those uh
collectors with
mirrors that want to achieve high
temperatures the molten Souls
allow are stable also at very high
temperatures and therefore using this
um these
um
fluids you
can collect solar energy at high
temperatures up to maybe 600
Celsius but of course uh molten souls
are used also in nuclear uh engineering
and in
uh processing Industries
for producing uh materials that are
useful for um all sorts of applications
from Electronics to to
to
magnets okay so this is for so this is a
reference in which you can see how
people uh measure and and then try to
correlate so there is also a number of
correlations which go under the names of
the inventors of the
correlations that do good jobs in uh
determining
uh these effects you see
here the gray molecule
seum uh ion is um is sort of the the
solvent is like the the prevailing or
the common U the common substance of
these uh mixtures and then you they keep
changing uh the other substance
so
um it's actually not only for dilute
it's for over the full range of
compositions from zero to one and you
can see that you have a
behavior in which the uh enthalpy of
mixing is uh negative
okay so
meaning that the
substance that when you mix the
substance the you have like an
exothermic reaction it's not really a
reaction but it's a physical chemical uh
effect which releases heat so in other
words you have to if you want to return
to Mutual equilibrium with your
Reservoir you have to cool down after
the mixing you have to cool tool down by
by this
amount and that cooling measures is is
exactly so with that's how you with the
calorimeter you can measure that uh
Cooling and and
therefore this Delta
H you can also do similar
measurements
for the volume of mixing
and here I sketched
um
the yeah I think this line should be
should belong a little lower here to the
zero level and I sketched uh this is
just to show that um it's the volume of
mixing is not always positive it can be
positive it can be
negative it can can
be positive in one range and they become
negative in the other range depending on
uh the
composition and it all depends on what
kind of molecules you have and how the
molecules interact with each
other and as you can
see these two reference where
you may want to take a look to to see
experimental data and how they're
treated date back to at least 40 years
ago
okay now this slide is also uh is just
uh parenthetical it just uh says all
right so we have seen that in practice
with those measurements you can we we
can infer the values of the chemical
potentials and therefore the partial
properties uh so the
question that we address in in this
slide is can
we is the meaning of partial that we use
in partial properties the same as the
meaning of partial as we use in partial
pressures and the answer answer is no
because the definition is different
however you can somehow somehow relate
partial properties in terms of partial
pressures and
here uh here's the way of of of doing it
uh it's just a matter of writing the
chemical potential as we see here uh
again as a function as it is of the
partial pressure so if you if you take
U the differential of this relation here
which defines the partial
pressure and then remember that the the
derivatives of the part of the chemical
potential are the partial properties
then that is where uh that relation
comes
about and here are the details so if you
like to take derivatives uh this is uh
how you can practice it
so I'm not going to
explain uh the details
here at this stage we need
to
recall something
about what happens when
molecules come close to one another
and the Leonard
John's
model gives you the potential energy of
the interaction between two molecules so
suppose I have one molecule and I stay
in uh and I sit on that molecule on the
reference frame that moves with that
molecule and I see another molecule
approaching the Leonard Jones
model is a pair interaction kind of
model it looks just uh what happens
between one molecule and the other not
the fact uh it doesn't apply well if you
have to consider also the fact that this
molecule may also at the same time be
interacting with a third and maybe a
fourth
molecule which of course is important in
liquids but okay so here's the idea I'm
sitting on that molecule and I see
another molecule
approaching now because of the
electronic U structure of atoms and
molecules the electrons that are
negatively
charged yes are attracted by the nucleus
or the nuclei of the molecule of the
atom
but as they approach other molecules
they're also a bit attracted by the
nucleus of the other
uh atom okay and that
produces these so-called Vander Val
vales attractive forces so the potential
going uh negative so if this is the
potential remember the I can calculate
the
force by taking the derivative of the
potential with respect to
distance minus sign so this force is a
vector and I is the vector that points
in the direction uh outward so further
from the molecule I am sitting on so
it's like on this axis I I subar is the
unit Vector in the r Direction in the uh
right direction
all right so the usefulness of having a
potential is that then you can calculate
forces by taking the derivative of the
potential and as you see here is the for
if the force is
negative uh it means that the the its
direction is in the opposite sign of the
unit Vector in the r Direction so it
points left so it's
attractive so and uh up to this point
which is about um
here the the derivative is
um the derivative of V is positive so
the force is negative and
uh yeah yeah okay up to up up to this
point where it is zero we get to the
minimum uh it's
attractive and from this point on it
becomes
repulsive the force becomes
positive that repulsion is due to the
fact that now the
nuclei which are positively charged
begin to F the positive charge of the
nucle of the of the particle I'm sitting
on and therefore that
repels
okay so most uh of the
times molecules are are running
around in their brunian
motion so uh in which they have some
kinetic
energy due to the velocity they
have and they have also this potential
energy some of that kinetic energy gets
transformed in potential
energy or actually when the molecule
approaches and gets an attractive force
it
gains kinetic energy so it's accelerated
towards the the particle so if this
molecule is coming from uh the right and
it's
approaching it's
accelerated towards the molecule I'm
sitting
in but
then uh all of a sudden it finds also
repulsive for so that's
deceleration of course if the kinetic if
the kinetic energy is
enough this molecule can go and hit
so make a collision eventually it will
make a collision because because the
force is going to become very large and
the repulsive Force becomes very large
and and therefore the particle is pushed
away back that's a collision it's like a
soft Collision but it's a
collision uh an even simpler model of
these would be
uh the so-called hard sphere
model in which the
potential is would be like
a
uh
okay okay would be like
this a function so
V is a function which goes to infinite
it's infinite at at this point which is
one it's the the distance one is because
we're
normalizing this to
the diameter of these molecules of these
spheres assuming they're
equal otherwise it would be like the you
have to normalize to the average
uh it's the of the radi of the two
molecules and it's zero here so the
heart sphere model assumes no attractive
Force until the sphere hits like in The
Bard uh bilard ball situation it hits
the other molecule and it gets uh
repelled by some elastic condition
elastic Collision
okay but let's return to this case Here
and Now
consider two important
regimes one regime is the ideal
gas the gas
regime so it's true that the the
molecules of the gas
very
often
uh billions of uh
collisions uh per second we we maybe
we'll have a a slide later on that does
that
calculation do have experience
collisions so these
molecules do get U uh to feel his
potential
when they
approach the other molecules and have a
collision that happens very
often but if you look up if you make an
average a Time average of how much
time this molecule
spans in this area where
the LeRon potential is is
negative is very small
most of the times on average the
particles are far
apart and therefore on
average they feel uh
zero
potential this this is why when you're
trying to measure the
properties you're actually measuring the
properties on
average because remember that somehow
the state of your system is is the is
the probability
distribution uh of things H for example
here it's the probability
distribution uh of finding finding the
particle at these various distances and
the pro that
probability uh for a
gas
is as a very small tail here and it
picks
away so most of the times
the particles are far away from each
other even though they experience a lot
of
collisions but that means that when
you're calculating the stable
equilibrium prop properties therefore
the average uh time average properties
uh this potential is irrelevant and that
is what allows you to
uh for example use the hard spere
model because that's totally equivalent
if the the particles live far away on
average uh and the details of the
potential of their interaction when they
closed is not important well uh those
details you can forget they don't enter
into determining the properties of of of
of the mixers so much that
in the ideal gas and also we'll we
hopefully have a slide also on this
uh the ideal
gas this relation here that the the
volume is RT over
P you can
derive for a particle a single particle
in a
box which is a a nice illustration
also of that's why I will have a slide
on this
uh but in other words this here in this
context is just to say that this the
properties of of of an ideal
gas so
the the origin of this uh ideal gas uh
equation of
State comes from the single particle
because the properties aable equilibrium
in this regime are are those of
particles that live on average by
themselves they don't feel the effects
of the other
particles there is another case also
which is the liquid case we'll return to
the liquid in in a while mean maybe
today but um
what's what's important is that instead
the liquid particles live very close to
one another they live near this
minimum so for
them this
potential is more
important okay
uh yeah this
um this the ler johon potential formula
can be written is written in two
different uh ways here one is in
terms of the actual distance and one is
the in terms of the distance normalized
to this uh
minimum to the to the
distance at which the minimum
occurs Sigma as I already said
is R is normalized here to Sigma so it's
one uh at the distance where um it is
equal to the diameter of the two
particles so where the particles are
colliding and uh here we also in the in
the in the plot normalized the potential
to Epsilon and
Epsilon is the depth of this
well here so it goes to minus
one so
stronger
interactions will have will be
characterized by stronger values of this
Epsilon okay
so with this introduction
let's
consider a a first ideal um Behavior
which is called which we will call Gibs
Dalton ideal
behavior and which will be a very good
approximation for gases in the gas
phase
because in practice
we will assume that not only particles
of the same kind like you would have in
a pure substance but also particles of
different kind like we have in a
mixture they also live on average far
away from one another and therefore we
can neglect the effect of their
intermolecular interactions
okay all right formally this is uh how
uh The
Story Goes we will first define ideal
behavior and just so this this will be
the our this will be the final result of
this
slide and uh the motivation is that of
this definition that we going to to do
here is that
we will find that under this
approximation or in this limit on this
when these uh uh assumptions are
valid then we obtain a famous result
which is the Dalton law of additive
partial pressures so the
pressure of the mixture is going to be
equal to the sum of the partial
pressures of the uh constituents of the
mixture but in general that is not true
not the I mean this is not true for a
for a non- ideal
mixture so the derivation goes as
follows we start from the oiler
relation written for the
mixture we write
also the oil relation for the pure
components and when I'm and here I'm
going to write it for the pure
components at uh just on the other side
of the
um semi permal membrane so they are in
at the same temperature of the mixture
but at the partial pressure okay so this
uble I
here uh I'm not writing the explicit
dependence but I'm doing it
here uh are eval to be
evaluated at T and partial
pressure then I
take these uh
individual pure constituent Oiler
relations we multi I multiply them
by the amount n i with which that
constituent is present in the mixture
and some overall
components and then I take the this
summation subtract it from the uh Oiler
relation for the mixture and here is the
result so you can still identify here
the the oil relation for the mixture is
given by this term this is TS minus PV
plus mui n
i and uh what I subtracted is the
summation of the N
with which the that are the compon the
amounts in the mixture
times the single component pure
component Oiler
relation U di I minus TS I I plus p i i
VII and
uh
plus the m
actually there's a mistake here because
this there shouldn't be a summation here
this is again a cut and space problem
this should be I hope I'll remember all
these uh things to correct in the view
graphs um yeah so for the pure component
there is only one and so there is no
summation
okay now
look at these uh elements of the last
summation they are identically zero
because of the condition for Mutual
equilibrium that the the chemical
potential of component I in the mixture
is equal to the chemical potential of
the pure component when evaluated at the
partial pressure so these are
zero and then I get a relation here
which contains the pressure and contains
the partial pressures because after all
what we wanted to see here is is there a
relation between pressure and partial
pressures and here is the result so I
put in evidence I solve this expression
for the total
pressure and here is how it depends on
the partial pressures that's all
over
however if I make these three
assumptions you see this the first
assumption kills these terms in
parenthesis the second assumption kills
this other
term the third assumption and note here
that this is not a
mistake here there is no sumission
sign so if this holds then we'll discuss
what it means but uh if this holds holds
it means that inside this summation
where every time I see n i * VI
I I can put capital
V which doesn't depend on I it doesn't
have a subscript so it goes outside of
the summation and and it cancels with
the V and the denominator and then what
I'm left with the Su with the summation
is just the partial pressure so I
finally get that the
pressure if these three assumptions are
together all uh holding
uh the pressure is equal to the sum of
the partial pressures and this is
Dalton's
law let's see how we could
U
interpret those conditions
that Define the ideal Gibs Dalton
Behavior essentially it says that I can
see the mixture or at least I can model
the properties of the
mixture as the model as a properties of
a composite
system in which I have the pure
components
leaving each one in the same volume of
the mixture so boxes of the same
size at the same
temperature and at the partial
pressure
okay then in this
conditions uh this is the specific uh
they have a specific energy since
they're pure for example this is
component say component I has a specific
energy which is u I evaluated at the T
and P because here it is at the partial
pressure the same for the
entropy and now if
I
um use the fact
that energy and entropy are additive
properties the
energy of this one is N1 *
u11 and so I sum up n i time uii and
that gives
me the
properties the property of the mixture
so sum of N i *
uii so
that's this last equation is the
defining uh equation for ideal Gibs
Dalton
Behavior the first one here I have added
also the general expression which is
valid always which gives the property in
terms of the partial
properties so same for the entropy so
it's additive so I can view
this and instead and here I I've used
the fact that
each you see here I could also write the
specific volume of the constituent the
partial
pressure and the fact that it um that in
the same amount of the mixture it
occupies the same volume of the mixture
is the sort of interpretation of this
formula
here it
also goes
together with the
idea that in the in the gas limit when
molecules live far apart from one
another think in either this or the
Leonard jnes kind of potential if if
they're on average they live
here
uh essentially they they stay in they
occupy the volume of the mixture if as
if they were by themselves each molecule
by
itself and that's
why we have they obey the ideal gas law
which is valid for the single molecule
in a
box even if I have many box many many
particles in that box but is it is as if
each one uses the Box by itself it
doesn't recognize on average the
presence of the other even though it
does continuously collide with the other
but the
time uh that it take the that the
collision and
so that it lasts the time that the
Collision lasts is very short with
respect to the rest of the time that the
particle moves uh freely in space before
encountering the same the other uh
molecule for the next
Collision okay so that's the ideal uh
Gibs Dalton
behavior and if we apply it now uh we
haven't assumed yet ideal
gas so now if we in addition to those we
also assume that
each pure
substance
behaves uh as an ideal gas so it it
obeys the equation of state of an ideal
gas in the full range of pressures from
the partial pressure to the total
pressure of the
mixture I shouldn't call it total to the
mixture so I can write that the equation
of State for the gas PV equals RT uh
both at the partial pressure and at the
pressure of the
piure then you see from assumption
three which is this I
substitute
this and obtain this
result so I obtain the partial pressure
written this
way now I'm using what we proved
in the Gibs Dalton uh theorem about the
Dalton
law uh that the pressure of the mixer is
the sum of the partial pressures so we
take the sum of these
ones see RT and V do not have subscripts
so they go out of the summation I'm left
with the sum of the NS which is just the
total n of the particles in the mixture
so here here what what do I got what do
I get that PV equals nrt so it means
that
also the
mixture behaves as an ideal gas so what
I what we what this proves is that an
ideal Gibs Dalton mixture of Ideal
gases obeys the equation of state of an
ideal gas so it is an ideal gas itself
and the
other uh important result is that if you
extract um RT over V from here you see
that you can write it as partial
pressure over the amount and RT over V
from here it's the pressure over the
total
amount so that's essentially you combine
these
two and obtain that the ratio of the
partial pressure to the total pressure
is equal to the ratio of the uh
individual amount with the total amount
which is the mole
fraction in other words the partial
pressure is given by the mole fraction
of that constituents times the
pressure of the mixture
and this relation if we put it uh in
this relation that we have derived
before so Pi I I over
P becomes in the
limit of a Gibs Dalton
mixture that
is the mole fraction so this is RT
the logarithm of the mole
fraction and this is a very important
relation it gives the chemical potential
of one constituent in in the mixture in
terms of uh the the chemical potential
that it has when it is a pure substance
at the same temperature and pressure of
the
plus RT the
log of its mole fraction of the mole
fraction with which it appears in the
mixture so it doesn't depend on other
things of the mixture for example what
are the other
components or how many they are except
that all
uh we need is to know what fraction our
component as occupies uh in in the
mixture
okay the first
few lines of this slide
are just a cut and paste from the
previous but here we add some other
items for example we compute the entrop
the partial uh
entropy of the component in the
mixture which as you
remember is this
derivative it is equal to
um the pure component
entropy uh
plus a term that in when we defined the
entropy of mixing at the beginning today
uh this is Delta SI I
mix
but if we since now for for this ideal
gas mixture of Ideal gases we have the
the expression for the chemical
potential in terms
of explicitly here taking the derivative
with respect to t you see leaves just R
time the log of
Y and since there is a minus sign here
this is minus r log of Y so essentially
this and we'll return to this in later
but this says that
the uh entropy of isothermal ISO baric
mixing of that molecule of that molecule
is equal to minus r log of
Y and this is also
equal to the pure component
entropy
evaluated at the p
I this is
because you
remember for
um for a
gas for an ideal
gas if I
evaluate the difference in the
entropy at different temperature and
pressure
um okay this is equal
to uh and and this is a perfect suppose
it's a perfect gas uh it's T2 over
T1 Min - R log P2 over
P1
so in this relation here uh we have uh
s AAL ated at
p p all right let's say
p p
uh Pi I I minus
s evaluated at P same temperature so
this doesn't give any contribution so
I'm left with minus r log
of p i i over P but that's in our limit
of Ideal mixture is uh um is the mole
fraction
okay
so hopefully what are written on the
board is this relation here that's to
justify this equal
sign we can also compute the partial
volume taking the derivative of this
with respect to
p and you see that since this last term
doesn't have pressure I just pick up
something from uh uh the derivative of
the chemical potential of the pure
component and that's uh the specific
volume so here we see that there is no
volume of mixing there is no ISO the
Delta essentially we we proving that
Delta V I mix for a Gibs Dalton mixture
of Ideal gases and so on is equal to
zero up here we prove that this is equal
to Delta S I mix for a Gibs Dalton
mixture of Ideal
gases I should I should write it because
otherwise
okay the same for the
enthalpy remember that derivative that I
emphasized this morning uh earlier
um if I take the expression for the
chemical potential divided by T and take
the with respect to T to one /
T okay well if I divide this by T it
becomes independent of temperature so
when I take the derivative with respect
to any function of temperature it
doesn't contribute anything so that
means that the uh enal the um the
partial
enthalpy is related just to uh the
specific enpy of the
gas which here Al so I remove the
temperature the pressure dependence
because for a for an ideal gas the
enthalpy depends only on
temperature and similarly for the uh so
that also
proves that also Delta
H
makes equal
zero remember what that what this proper
are these are the things that I measure
when I add a little bit of a substance
to my mixture if I do it with an ideal
mixture of Ideal gases uh those are
zero we can also
prove for a gas for this kind of mixture
uh the so-called amagat low of additive
volumes which can be interpreted this
way U suppose I
take
my pure
components that you remember from the
when you we interpreted the the the the
mix before if they are at the partial uh
pressure
they occupy the entire volume of the
mixture but if I squeeze
them from the partial pressure to the
pressure of the
mixture they are going to occupy a
volume which is called the proper volume
v
Prime which see this is not so this is
the the volume they occupy at the same
temperature and pressure of the mixture
when pure
okay and I do the same for all of them
so they're all squeezed at the same
pressure of the mixture well it turns
out that the sum of these volumes is
equal to the volume of the
mixture okay and that is amagat law of
additive volumes
okay
so now let's uh apply for the for
example for an an important
example uh what we have what we have
seen so we want to compute the so-called
uh this bottom line here is the formula
that we call the entropy uh of
spontaneous uh
mixing which is actually going to be an
ISO thermobaric
mix so the idea here is that we start
with a
container which is isolated so it
doesn't experience any
um uh there is no heat
buff no uh thermal Reservoir no contact
with thermal res reservo it's just
isolated and I have my our
constituents uh all in mutual
equilibrium at the same temperature and
pressure because these
partitions uh that separate them are
movable and therefore allow exchanges of
volume and and energy so the conditions
for Mutual equilibrium is equality of
temperature and
equality of
pressure then
I make those partitions those yeah
moving
partitions
disappear as you
know since we are within the simple
system model taking the partition away
doesn't doesn't
change uh the properties of uh any of
the
properties and the moment I do that
removal the
particles are still
separated so the
particles which start from here and my
system is the system with the
partitions when I remove the
partitions the stable equilibrium
State and the new there have a new
system because I've changed the the
internal
structure it has a
new curve for the stable equilibrium
States
and the moment I have
removed the partitions and the
properties hav changed this state here
which is which was a stable equilibrium
state with the partitions becomes a
non-e equilibrium state with respect to
the system without
partitions and the system will tend to
evolve
spontaneously towards a new equilibrium
which is going going to be the
mixture the particles will mix and each
one of
them if you think in terms of the single
particle contribution each particle
here was squeezed to a small
volume and now it sees the entire volume
available so it
expands and the same for the particles
here and the same particles there so
each one experiences a spontaneous
expansion it's
like if you take the single particle
view say say particle one and here I
have
vacuum
okay I remove the
partition and the particle now fills the
entire volume and fills the the the
entire volume
there's no more
vacuum because at the beginning I had
zero probability of finding my particles
here and probability one of finding it
there when I remove the partition the
particle is still
one uh but now I have an even
probability of finding it
everywhere
okay so for the
we want to
describe uh that spontaneous
process and so we want to analyze our uh
process here we have a final State and
an initial State and the tools are as
usual the energy balance and the entropy
balance plus the auxiliary balances that
are
uh balance for the volume balance for
the amounts of the constituents
so I need to write the various
ingredients of those balance equations
which are the expressions for the energy
the volume and the entropy in the
initial
State and in the final State I've called
this final State B
Prime uh and I call that final
temperature T Prime and pressure p Prime
for the initial state things are easy
because the components are separate so
these are this is just a
composite uh
of separate pure
substances we know how to compute
properties of pure substances and here
in particular they are ideal gases even
simpler and so we simply have to use
additivity for energy for volume and for
entropy and sum up the energy of each
one of them since U is a specific energy
the energy of this system is obtained by
the specific energy times the amount and
then I sum and that's the additivity and
the same for volume the same for entropy
in the
final
state in the final state things are not
as simple because it's a
mixture so we have to take a model for
mixture Behavior so here we're going to
adopt the Gibs Dalton uh ideal GBS Delon
mixture model for this
data
therefore the energy for the mixture is
equal to the the sum weighted by the
amounts of
the
um specific properties of the pure
components evaluated at the temperature
and the partial pressure
so here in principle I should have
written comma
pii but I didn't because I remember that
uh for an ideal gas the energy is a
function only of temperature so that
dependence isn't
there because if you
remember
du is equal to CV DT and for an ideal
gas there is nothing no pressure
dependence and here we're talking about
something that holds for each of the
pure
substances
then we can use uh the relation for the
uh this is amagat's relation or uh you
can use any in any case the equation of
State uh
and uh and we already proved that V is
equal
to that the the the mixture of Ideal
gases under the Gibs Balton
model behaves itself as an ideal gas so
there is a the relation equation of
State PV equals
nrt for the entire mixture here and
that's what we use
here and then for the entropy
the
entropy is the sum of the entropies of
the specific entropies evaluated at the
uh paral
pressures now the entropy does depend on
pressure so I did
leave uh the partial pressure that the
components have in the final
state so these are just the ingredient
of the balance equation now I make the
balance equation so the balance
equation when the system is completely
uh isolated is that the energy is
conserved so U final minus U initial is
equal to
zero so I have U final I have U initial
I subtract
them I can put this under the same
summation then I remember this equation
here and
uh so for each of the constituents I can
write that is that the integrate from uh
from T to T Prime this
difference uh so this is the integral
from T to T Prime of CV and here there
should be a CV I I
okay okay so this integral has to be
equal to
zero now when when can that be equal to
zero now here we we have to remember a
few things that uh for
each uh pure substance the specific
Heats are non negative are greater than
zero we proved it because they're
related to the second derivative of the
fundamental relations Is they're related
to the to this concavity
here so we have an
integral of positive quantities of a
positive
function weighted and then multiplied by
positive numbers because the amounts can
only be positive of course cannot be
have a negative
amount so you can view this as an
integral of a
function an integral from say X1 to
X2 of a
function that has to be equal to zero
while this
function is
positive so here's a
function positive and the
integral is equal to this area now from
X 1 to
X2 so if the function is positive and I
want the integral to be zero the only
way is that the interval of integration
must be
zero so that
implies that this integral is equal to
zero only when X2 is equal to
X1 so that
proves that the final temperature must
be equal to the initial temperature
we have no need to making any
assumptions of what these functions are
whether they are functions of whether
they are constant or not they can be
functions arbitrary functions of
temperature still get the same
result then if I
make the volume balance
equation here's another mistake this is
a v not a
u um so the final volume since we are in
the same overall box fin final volume is
equal to initial volume so the these two
are equal if I look at this uh relation
here it says
that if I put them equal it says that t
over p is equal to T Prime over P
Prime so that means that if we just
prove that t Prime is equal to T so the
final temperature is equal to the
initial the the volume balance implies
that also the final pressure is equal to
the
initial so spontaneous mixing
with these conditions is isotherm
baric different story is for the entropy
balance
the entropy
balance is written here with another
little mistake because this should be a
capital S so the final entropy minus the
initial
entropy there are no interaction so
there is no entropy transfer yeah no
heat
interactions uh but there can be entropy
produced by irreversibility
so we rewrite this so s here is equal SB
minus sa a and I have the terms
here so I
substitute now I realize that
um this we can also
write well actually it's this expression
here I have
to I don't have to re uh prove it it's
written here this difference is equal to
minus r log Y which is also is
interpreted as the entropy of isomar
baric
mixing and therefore the if I take
um R the minus sign outside of a
summation I take also the total amount
out of the summation then I'm left in
side with the mole fraction times the
log of the mole
fraction now at first first site one
would be worried about the minus sign
because uh we know that the
entropy produced by reversibility cannot
be negative must be positive but if you
look at this uh function
y log
y the
function in the interval between zero
and
one the function y y log y does
something like
that versus
y so it's
negative so minus y log Y is
positive and we are safe that means for
[Music]
um reasonable in other words um possible
values of the mole
fractions which of course can go only
between zero and one that function is
non-
negative but it also says that there
is entropy production so the process is
irreversible as we have uh anticipated
by looking at the
energy versus entropy
graphs and this is called the entropy of
mixing
now so if I look at that graph
immediately I also realize
that I have could that I could have done
better in other words we could have done
the mixing
reversibly because if I If instead of
going this way I go this
way I do not generate enthropy and I
extract some
work so this this is what we called the
adiabatic availability of the state that
is achieved the moment I remove the
partition that non equilibrium State as
adiabatic availability if I am quick
enough or smart enough to do whatever
needs to be
done and we'll see how we could do it in
a moment uh you we could extract some
work so here is the
calculation of that adiabatic
availability so now the final
State
okay what we just uh U
derived is that if you if we mix This
Way the final state is the same
temperature and
pressure clearly if we we go down and we
have extracted some
energy the final State here we have a
smaller
temperature which we call it touble
Prime and how do we measure it how do we
uh do the computation well we
start the previous computation we
started from the energy balance setting
that final energy equal to initial
energy that determines the temperature
now we start from the entropy balance
because for a reversible process because
we want to extract the adiabatic
availability so that's a reversible
weight process the entropy stays
constant we apply equality of final
initial entropy and so we start from the
entropy balance
uh yeah here is the entropy balance s
final minus s initial equals
z so we write
it this way with the double
primes and then this difference uh here
we can
uh yeah it's evaluated it's
evaluated in this
line
because okay tble Prime is the final
temperature that we
have p double Prime double I is the
partial pressure that the components
will have in that new Final
state so that partial pressure is going
to be equal
to the mole
fraction so that partial pressure will
be be equal to the mole fraction
times the final pressure pble
Prime
but if we
remember if we remember the equation of
uh if we look at the volume balance
which is written here pble Prime over
tble Prime is equal to P over
T so I can uh think of pble
prime pble
prime as um what is it P over
T at as P
times T Prime over t
okay and that's why I am writing
this
here then I
apply the relation for
um for how the entropy depends on on on
temperature and
pressure here we also have a temperature
dependence so we also have the CP log
contribution of the ratio of
temperatures minus r the log of the
ratio of the
pressures
okay then I I can split this logarithm
as being this logarithm of the product
is going to be the sum of the logarithms
so I take the minus r log y here and
then I combine the log of tble prime
that appears from this part and with
that part it gets multiplied by CV minus
r but by the my relation that's C
CV okay so we finally have this
expression we can put it in the entropy
balance now I see here that I could
Define
a an average aage
specific heat at constant
volume of the mixture as being the
weighted uh as being the sum this
summation here
okay and then I
recognize this final term which is um
very close I mean what is exactly what
we call the entropy of mixing
well in any case by setting since this
has to be equal to zero by the entropy
balance this gives me an an expression
way to calculate dble Prime the final
temperature and this is the
result now the fact that these functions
are negative so e to a negative number
is is less than one
shows that of course as we
expected the final temperature will be
less than the initial
temperature and now that we have the
final temperature we can perform the
energy balance now the energy balance
here since the system is not any
isolated anymore because we have lifted
the weight in the weight
process we have extracted the thetic
availability so uh the
the energy given to the weight is equal
to the difference between the initial
and the final uh
energy so by substituting these
ingredients that we calculated up there
and
using uh the same the specific heat as
constant volume then the fact that the
ammation we defined as sort of an
average uh mixing uh
mixture uh specific heat constant
volume and we substitute tble Prime and
you compute the value for the adiabatic
availability so we
see that
this represents this
work
just to show you how we we could
actually do it with a picture so we
conclude we have 1 minute
how can you do that can we actually
separate the mixture
uh
remember
this problem here with the single
particle if I have a single particle
there and I have
vacuum I and I have this and instead of
removing the Piston I can just have it
uh
uh move uh
rightward while connected through a
pulet to a weight and the pressure of
the particle will push it to the right
that that therefore the particul do work
and
lift and similarly if I have this other
particle on the other different particle
on the other side
say suppose I have a particle of
different
kind that is confined that's separated
and it's on the other side also
here I can do the same and have the
pressure of the particle or the
particles doesn't really matter because
each one acts by itself uh so that pulls
is this
way and when the when we you have the
presence of both parts particles you
have to do it more carefully instead of
having
like an imperal P piston you have to use
semi- perable
membranes so that when this one moves to
the
right it will uh
uh so this one is
allows uh the the the black particles to
freely move in and out uh and then it
fills on on only the pressure of the
gray particles until you move to the
right and this other membrane instead
is allows the gray particles through and
instead feels the pressure of the black
particles okay so when you're done and
if you done it uh reversibly you have
extracted this adiabatic
availability okay so I think we have to
stop here today