- Hi everybody. I'm Andrew Lo,
a professor of finance at the
MIT Sloan School of Management
and a principal investigator
at the MIT Computer Science and AI Lab,
and I'm looking forward to
answering your questions.
Let's take the first one.
How can large language models
efficiently analyze financial reports
to extract key insights
such as identifying risks,
opportunities, and emerging trends?
Large language models
are actually designed
to be able to read plain text
and be able to digest and summarize them.
Earnings reports, financial statements.
These are the kind of things
that large language models can now read
and be able to generate very,
very short and pithy summaries
to be able to focus on things
like risks, opportunities,
and other issues.
In the financial sector,
we use certain keywords
to be able to highlight
risks and opportunities so
that there are automatic tags
that large language models
can figure out very, very quickly.
Large language models
will have a huge impact
on the life of financial analysts
because their job day in and day out
is to be able to read these reports,
and they can now do that
using these tools in a much
faster and more accurate way.
Can LLMs identify subtle market patterns
and anomalies that may
elude human analysts?
The answer is yes, they can,
but they can also identify
anomalies that don't exist,
in other words, hallucinate.
And this is one of the challenges
that we have to deal with with LLMs.
Right now, we know that
they're very capable
of being able to identify some
really interesting patterns,
but at the same time, they
can also identify things
that aren't there and require humans
to engage in additional oversight.
Now, by the way, humans
are not perfect either,
and we are prone to
hallucinate on occasion.
Paul Samuelson famously said,
"economists have predicted five out
of the last three recessions,"
and I think that's part
of what he was getting at.
We need to think about
how we can make ourselves more accurate.
So the combination of humans and LLMs
could actually be the sweet
spot of being able to produce
really accurate forecasts
for all sorts of economic phenomenon.
How can we build trust in financial advice
and decisions provided by LLMs?
And what strategies can be employed
to maintain human oversight and control?
Now, this is a really interesting one
because it gets at an
issue that my collaborators
and I have been working on
for the last several months,
and we think we have an approach,
but it'll be several years
before we come to it.
And the problem that we're
studying is the issue of trust.
How do we get LLMs to be trusted
and specifically in the
context of financial advice?
So in that domain, we
actually have a concept
that is known as fiduciary duty,
and this really gets
at the heart of trust.
In the financial sector,
a fiduciary is somebody
who puts your interests
ahead of his or her own.
So for example, if you
have a financial advisor,
that financial advisor
owes you a fiduciary duty,
meaning that when they give you advice
about how to manage your money,
they have to be thinking
first and foremost
about your welfare as opposed
to lining their own
pockets with commissions
that might come out of the kind of trades
that they would do on your behalf.
How do we get an LLM
to become a fiduciary?
How do we get it to be a trusted
financial advisor to you?
Our approach is to think about
how this happens in the industry
with human financial advisors.
How do human advisors become fiduciaries?
Well, for one thing, they
have a code of ethics,
so they have to follow certain rules,
but more importantly,
they have to follow a large
number of financial regulations,
laws that we put in place in
order to protect consumers.
And at one point, I
remember studying these laws
because I had to take a securities exam
in order to be involved
in a particular kind of
a financial institution.
And this exam called the Series 65
test you on your knowledge not
only of financial analysis,
but also of the regulatory infrastructure
that guides all of us in the industry.
And so after spending hours and hours
reading all of these rules
and being frustrated that I was forced
to memorize these things,
it finally dawned on me
where these things were coming from.
The historical body of case law
that has been used to
guide lawyers, regulators,
and consumers as to what
they can and cannot do,
that is a fossil record of all of the ways
that one human has decided
to be able to try to take
advantage of another human
and ultimately got caught
and prosecuted successfully for it.
So if we trained LLMs,
not just with the body
of financial knowledge,
but the full case law history
of all of the various different lawsuits
that have been filed
against certain bad actors
in the financial system,
if we do all of that,
we then can train LLMs
to become fiduciaries.
We believe that we're
still a few years away
from something that the SEC
and lawyers would agree
would be a fiduciary,
but we at least know the
direction that we're going,
and we're very excited to
be able to go that route
and ultimately produce a piece of software
that can be fully trusted by humans.
What role could LLMs play in automating
and streamlining risk assessment processes
for banks and financial institutions,
and how should these systems be governed?
So this is also a great question because
that's one of the most important features
that financial institutions
have to carry out
is risk management.
Risk management has two parts, in my view.
The first part is a quantitative part,
and that's actually
relatively easy to automate.
Computing things like value
at risk and scenario analysis
and worst loss scenarios,
all of those things can
now be done pretty much
at a push of a button
and and are being done
by all the big financial institutions.
What is much more difficult
is the second set of tasks,
and that is taking all of those numbers
and putting that into a
narrative that can be given
to a risk manager,
to a policymaker,
to a customer,
so that they understand
what the implications
of those numbers are for their
own personal circumstances.
Imagine that the stock
market just went down
by 15% today,
and that means that your portfolio of
bonds are now in trouble
because the stock market has gone down
and there's a concern that the
Fed is gonna have to step in,
and everybody is worried about
defaults across various
different kinds of scenarios,
and you're holding a
bunch of corporate bonds
that are risky to begin with,
but in the today's
scenario, it's a lot worse.
What do you do about it?
An LLM could analyze the
numerical data instantaneously
and then weave that into a
narrative which says, perhaps
today equity markets
are down by quite a bit.
That means the Fed's gonna step in,
there's gonna be panic
among a bunch of investors,
and that means that certain
assets will sell off
and other assets will
become much more valuable.
If you're holding corporate bonds,
that is likely to get hit hard,
treasury bills are gonna do really well,
but I would wait for
another three to five weeks
before you do anything dramatic
because over the course of history,
if you looked at similar situations,
these kinds of moves are temporary
and things will normalize.
That's the kind of narrative
that an LLM can provide
that is not available
when you're just looking at
a whole table of numbers.
So over time, I suspect that
LLMs will get much better
at weaving those narratives
and also being able to describe
some of the weaknesses in their narratives
and where you might wanna use
your own personal judgment
to make a call for your own portfolio.
So I think we're not that far away
from the use of LLMs for risk management,
and I'm hoping that
that will get everybody
to focus on the right kind of risks
that are relevant to them.
How can the natural language
processing capabilities
of LLMs be used to
perform sentiment analysis
on financial news,
social media, and other
textural data to inform trading
and investment decisions?
So typically, we believe
that financial markets
are moved by two things, fear and greed.
Now, that's the Wall Street
trader's perspective.
If you're asking an economist,
it's all about the numbers, right?
The bottom line is it's both.
It's the numbers, but it's
how we interpret the numbers,
and that's where sentiment comes in.
So the idea behind sentiment analysis
is to try to understand
how human emotion is gonna
react to the numbers.
And over the course of
the last several decades,
there's been a lot
written on human behavior,
psychology and the ability for us
to manage our emotions
in very, very difficult
financial circumstances.
Obviously, most of us
have trouble doing so
because we are all hardwired
to engage in the fight or flight response.
When we are threatened,
we will react in a very
predictable way physiologically,
which is great if you're being chased
by a saber tooth tiger
on the plains of the African savanna
a hundred thousand years ago,
doesn't work so well on the floor
of the New York Stock Exchange today.
So sentiment analysis is an attempt
to try to look at the various
different financial indicators
to get a sense of
whether or not the market
is overreacting or underreacting.
And I think this is where
LLMs will have a field day
because they're gonna be
able to look at the numbers,
but more importantly,
they're gonna be able
to read the literature
of what's being written at that
very moment by news sources
that are freaking the rest of us out.
When the news stations tell
us, is there something in milk
that could be hurting your infants?
More at 11.
You're gonna feel compelled to watch
that news story at 11 o'clock.
So we are very easily moved
by those kinds of threats.
And so LLMs will be
very good at picking up
those kinds of threats
and coordinating the
analysis of the language
with the numbers to be able
to produce sentiment analysis.
In fact, I wouldn't be
surprised if certain hedge funds
were already using LLMs
to be able to detect
these kinds of patterns
and start making use of them.
The hope is that the
typical retail investor,
the rest of us consumers
will have access to those tools soon.
Okay, next question.
How can we mitigate bias in
LLMs for financial applications,
and what other ethical considerations,
like algorithmic transparency
and accountability,
should be prioritized?
So the first thing to note
is that LMS absolutely do have biases.
And I know this because my students
and I documented that in a paper
that we wrote recently
looking at hiring decisions
that an LLM might make
when confronted with a variety
of different candidates.
So it definitely suffers from gender bias
in a variety of different contexts.
And it's not surprising because
what are LLMs reflecting?
They're reflecting the sum
total of the literature
that they're using as
inputs to be trained.
The first step in dealing
with bias is to document it.
We need to understand, depending
on the nature of the LLM,
how it's trained, other
supplements that we use with it,
we have to understand exactly
what those biases are.
We have to quantify them.
Once we quantify them,
then we can start asking the question,
how do we decide to change the biases
to make it more appropriate
for the purpose at hand?
So that's a question
that requires domain specific knowledge.
In certain areas, the
biases may be very small.
In other areas, the biases may be huge.
So for every single application,
I believe that we need to think carefully
about the implicit biases
in the LLM that we're using.
And once we document that,
to be able to then start
engaging in recoding
or adding various different supplements,
retrieval, augmented guides, rags,
that would actually lean
against those kinds of biases
to the degree that we wish.
Over time, we need to understand
how these biases are changing.
They change across time,
across culture, across country.
So understanding just exactly
what these LLMs are doing
is something that is
gonna be a prerequisite
to us being able to put any
of these things into practice.
You have to measure before you can manage.
Can LLMs be used to enhance the detection
and prevention of financial fraud?
I think the answer to this is
unambiguously absolutely yes.
Right now, there are a number
of machine learning tools
that are already being used by the SEC
and other agencies to
identify potential fraud.
A long time ago, it was
suggested by a mathematician
that there are certain
statistical properties
that have to exist among
a table of numbers.
And so if you see a departure
from that statistical regularity,
that's an example of fraud.
So using these kinds of distributions,
already we can detect
certain types of fraud,
but now with LLMs, with
more sophisticated ways
of processing natural
language and numbers together,
we can actually do even better.
So there, there's no doubt in my mind
that this is gonna be a
tremendously powerful tool.
The dark side of this
is that with these LLMs,
we can also create fraud
that is harder to detect.
For example, imagine prompting
your LLM by asking it
to take a look at your tax returns
and suggest ways of putting
in certain kinds of deductions
that will give you a much lower tax bill.
And even if they break the rules,
to do so in a way that makes
it virtually impossible
to detect by a typical IRS auditor.
Now imagine if you gave
that prompt to an LLM
and imagine if it could actually
deliver on that request.
That's the danger.
And one of the reasons why I
think we're in an arms race
between the regulators
and the perpetrators,
and one of the reasons why I believe
that we ought to increase the budgets
of regulatory authorities
because they need to have
the same type of equipment
and sophistication to be able
to address these concerns
so that they can stay
ahead of the fraudsters.
In what ways can LMS
assist in the development
and testing of more
sophisticated trading algorithms?
I believe that they're
actually already being used
for just that purpose.
So it used to be the case
that machine learning algorithms
really had to be focused
on the specific feature
that you were giving it
to be able to detect
patterns in financial data.
And that's really what
trading algorithms are.
It's really just pattern matching
so that you can predict
what's gonna happen tomorrow
and trade today to take
advantage of that prediction.
But now imagine being able to
make those predictions based,
not just on numerical
data, but on textual data.
And to be able to combine the two,
to be able to create this kind
of a sentiment analysis score
and be able to understand how it is
that certain kinds of
language yield predictions
that will ultimately come to pass
in financial stock prices, bond prices,
and other instruments.
So large language models now can analyze
lots of different sources
of text, including news.
News is one of the really key
aspects of financial markets.
Markets are always reacting
to current information,
and the information does not
necessarily have to be accurate
for financial markets to react.
They will react to rumor in many cases
just as quickly as they'll react to
substantive true information.
And so large language models can combine
the kind of information
across various different news sources
and distill it into a
single prediction, which is,
will the asset go up or
down in price tomorrow?
I believe that more sophisticated methods
of prediction are possible,
but the challenge is to come
up with the correct prompts
to make those predictions,
and then to be able to deal
with the issue of hallucination.
So that's one of the
reasons why hedge funds now
are experimenting with
these large language models
and why those of you who are
interested in having a career
in financial analysis,
I would urge you to start
playing around with LLMs
for exactly this purpose.
What regulatory and
compliance considerations
should be addressed when
deploying LLMs in this field?
Well, I mentioned that
there's an arms race going on
between the regulators and the fraudsters,
and I think that that's
something that we really need
to consider over the course
of the next few years
as the pace of innovation
gets faster and faster
on the side of the practitioners.
We need to give regulators the tools
to be able to fight this kind of a battle.
And unless we pass
legislation to help them,
I think it's gonna be
a very one-sided race.
Let me give you an example
of one piece of legislation
that I think we have to consider.
Data is an incredibly powerful currency
in this business.
And so who controls the data?
If I'm a consumer
and I put my data at the disposal
of a particular vendor that's
providing a service for me,
does that vendor have
the right to use that
for any purpose whatsoever,
including purposes that
are detrimental to me?
So this legislation that
needs to be formulated
as to who has the rights to the data,
and if vendors are making
use of customer data,
what can and what can they
not do with that data?
We need to pass legislation
to make this clear
so that we can allow the
data to be used in broader
and more effective ways,
while at the same time
protecting the interests
of those who need protection.
So I think that's the biggest
set of issues right now,
is that the regulators
don't have all of the tools
that they need and they don't
have the budget that they need
to be able to deal with
these kind of issues.
We need to to bite the bullet
and make an investment in
our regulatory infrastructure
to deal with this brave new
world that we're entering.