Uh it is my pleasure to introduce our
next speaker is Kristoff Reinhardt who
is a professor in the MIT department of
architecture. So give a warm welcome for
Kristoff.
>> Thank you Jen for having me here. Good
morning everybody. Thanks a lot for
joining us for this day. I just looked
through the agenda. It's really
spectacular. you're going to know so
much about data center. So much more
than I know about data center. So as Jim
said I'm from the department of
architecture. So hopefully I can give
you a little bit of insight on data
center and given the department that I'm
from uh I going to talk about data
centers as buildings and uh what the
opportunities and just the challenges of
many these build very special buildings
are. Maybe just a word about our
program. We are within the uh
architecture department but the program
is called the building technology
program. So you can think about it as as
hybrids between engineers, computer
scientists and uh and designers. And I
guess this perspective is what I also
bring to the presentation here. So uh
some key takeaways you can pay attention
now and then you can leave or fall
asleep. This is really the main
conclusions of what I'm going to talk
about. Um, a lot of these things, you
know, you write them down and you think
this is so self-evident. Hope they're
not going to laugh me out of the room,
but I try to undermine or substantiate
what I'm saying here with some extra
data and give you a sense what that
means. So, data centers are obviously
internal load dominated and they are
constantly cooling and so there's some
kind of intuitively every child could
tell you there's some benefit if you
have a cold climate in the surroundings.
So I going to talk a little more what
that actually means. So this is
basically then related to how do you
strategically place if you have the
flexibility your data center and then
the next point is really that we need a
lot of electric load but data centers
are not the only ones that use
electricity a lot of changes from heat
electrification and electric vehicle
adoption. So how do these topics blend
into your choices here? And then
finally, this is also not new, but I
think it has specific relevance right
now. The great opportunities that data
centers can provide when it comes to
thermal district systems. Basically,
some interesting synergies there. So,
let's get right into it. Uh, so how does
a data center compare to different
building types? And if we look at them
from the outside, it's just a building.
There's like the small single family
home, there's an office building and
there is this windowless monstrosity of
a data center that we are seeing in the
world. So the main difference of course
between these buildings uh to just give
you a sense is what happens on the
inside. So within the architectural
design planning world we're basically
talking about this equipment loads.
That's everything except for heating,
cooling, conditioning and lighting a
building. And so when I typically give
you a sense, a typical family home has
about two watts per square meter and the
net operation is about half of the year
of this equipment in the building. If we
go into an office building, there's a
light a large variety, but according to
the Department of Energy, we have about
five times more watt per square meter of
stuff installed, but we're only using it
a quarter of the year. And then I had to
look at that a couple of times, these
fightful numbers basically. So 10 watt
per square meter for an office building.
You can have a,000 to 4,000 watt per
square meter with the equipment being
constantly on in a zeta center which is
pretty mind-blowing. It used to be a
thousand and now they're basically the
sky's the limit in this case. So I want
to give us more all of a sense what does
this actually mean. So, uh, for those of
you who own a barbecue, to give you a
sense, what is the heat coming from an
Nvidia card, like a brand new nice
server rack that creates about 20,000
BTUs? Nobody knows what this means, but
then if you compare that, that's
basically the equivalent heating output
of a burner. So, if you have a nice
Weber grill in your backyard, that
creates 60,000 BTUs. So, if we now take
this on to the mental image you should
have of a data center, it's like a giant
Home Depot with that is filled to the
brim with these uh grills that are
constantly turned on all the time. And
what you see here is the grills at a
1000 watt per square meter. If we're now
switching over to the modern data
center, you don't even have space for
your guests anymore. It's basically it's
so packed. Every grill has 50 square
feet. That's the amount of heat that is
generated in a data center. It's just
mind-blowing. And obviously then to say
well cooling is an issue is probably not
very surprising. So then how you look at
it if we typically in the architecture
or design world look at a building like
an office building or a single family
home I show you here basically always
pairs how was it would a building like
this perform in Minneapolis and Phoenix.
So cold climate, hot climate, and then
completely intuitive. In the cold
climate, you have a lot of red that
means you have heating energy. And then
if you get into a colder climate, you
have more cooling energy. Now, if we're
switching the scale, this is how this
looks in a data center. So the other
buildings disappear. These loads are
just enormous. And now we are basically
seeing the IT load. That's the stuff,
the equipment. That's why you have a
data center. And then on top of it to
maintain uh temperatures within the
buildings cool enough you basically have
a lot of air or liquids that you have to
move and you have to move uh generate
cooling uh loads me cooling loads as
well. And I'm using a dry climate here
if we I should have actually used a
thought about it last night also like a
humid climate then you probably can
easily double the blue just because you
have to get rid of all of this humanity
as well. So a real uh technology battle.
Now if we want to um evaluate something
like this and I'm sure this is the
metric people will be tell talking to
you on and on and on. This power use
effectiveness is since data centers are
in such a different class of buildings
overall. Usually the way we think about
them is to say okay what's the total
energy that the building is using and we
are dividing this through the energy
that is actually being used to run the
IT equipment. So ideally you have a PUI
of one because that means you have the
perfect uh situation where all the
electricity goes into the goodies while
you actually have the data center. The
average right now is about 1.5 globally.
I should say one thing what a part of
probably a lot of my colleagues talked
about. This just looks at the
electricity use. This doesn't look at
the efficiency. How good is the
equipment that you have in the data
center? That's kind of separately. So we
are just looking at the electricity use
and the heat that is being generated.
So uh just to give you a sense then
because Minneapolis and Phoenix that I
the two examples that I showed you on
the two left and center bar they
basically would have in this very simple
model 1.59 1.64. So typical POE
efficiency. Now if you are moving
actually and you do the obvious thing
you use free cooling you use the air in
Minneapolis which if you've been in the
winter is really cold and you cleverly
move that naturally adabatic cooling
through the building you can basically
kind of half the distance between 1.5
and one. So obviously there's a lot of
potential uh to be had here. Hence the
obser observation being in a cool
climate has a lot of benefits. So then
there is this interesting relationship
as we are building in different parts of
the world this data center. How does
this interact with all the other loads
that are going to change? And if you
lived in the northeast, practically
anywhere within the US, there has been a
strong push towards convincing people in
different parts of the country to adopt
heat pumps. And part of that is concerns
for carbon emission. Other concerns are
very simply because it's getting warmer
everywhere. So people like to have a
system that delivers heating and cooling
at the same time. So if you just look at
the bare numbers, heat pumps are being
adopted all over new construction
existing buildings. If we are now
zooming in a little into Massachusetts,
how something like this could play out
if we got more data centers, then let's
first look at the economics of the
owner. It's actually economically in
many parts of Massachusetts a bad idea
to put in a heat pump because natural
gas is so cheap. And so there is a
strong chance that people unless we do
dramatic changes to this pricing
structure in Boston and other way where
there's a lot of natural gas will not
adopt a heat pump. In other parts when
you're in western mass where you heat
with heating oil that's more expensive
you do a little bit of weatherization
because the building stock is not there
very good there we will see a lot of
uptake of heat pumps over the coming
years. Another uh issue is of course the
moment when you introduce a heat pump
then you introduce the peak of the
building. So the heat pump will be
larger than the current air conditioning
system. So in the winter we have this
extra peak. That's super important. The
electric grid will need more electricity
than it does right now but only for a
few days. And so this is of course where
then the collaboration with the uh data
center can come into place. So what I'm
showing you here is uh Massachusetts on
the right hand side. On the left hand
side you see kind of the carbon emission
reductions that are possible in
different parts of the state if we al
change to a heat pump, electrify or
heating. On the left hand side you see
the same thing but taking into account
that an owner will only do that if they
save money. And there basically you see
it's basically in the middle part
western part of the state. This is where
a lot of changes are going to happen.
And so if we now start ramping up our
heat pumps, there will be uh upgrades to
the grid necessary. That is probably a
lot of kind of uh thinking going on that
basically ideally the data center sets
at the point where a lot of the
electricity is coming into the state.
And then ideally we managed to get power
purchase agreement ways so that on these
five days the critical hours in the year
when the heat pumps need extra power
this is basically absorbed and this
means that and I think my colleague uh
Morgan Andre is going to talk about that
from mighty a little a lot more having
very good integration of your heat pumps
with the rest of what's going on.
There's a lot of dangers and
opportunities.
So we've talked about a heat pump
basically as this thing that uses a lot
of electricity. But I mean the better
way think about it. Electricity comes
into into the data center. Out comes a
lot of hot air. And that air is
typically at about 50° C
degree Fahrenheit. So you have basically
this new thing in the world that creates
a lot of low process heat. Now the this
is nice if we can use it. The
disadvantage of low process heat you
cannot really move it very long
distances right because uh I mean air
doesn't hold a lot of energy density and
the delta t isn't high enough but what
can we actually do with that? Well
people I mean what I'm telling you is
older than some people in the room maybe
uh because basically we've been doing
this type of work maybe not uh since
2009.
So this uh pedestrian swimming pool here
in Zurich is allegedly the first
application where there was an IBM data
center in 2009. They had the hot air
heat exchanger, warm water under the
street, heat the swimming pool, a lot of
happy Swiss people. So this kind of
synergies work well. A big application
or like a symbolically architecturally
nice application is to use the hot air
in green houses. This is pretty famous
the Teles city condor set data center.
These are pretty small data center. This
is located in Paris. The idea here was
to heat an arboritum and create the
conditions of 2050. How the weather in
France is going to be at that point. I
mean it's a nice exhibition. Everybody
likes bopilic design. So these are very
obvious way of using the heat. Uh it's
maybe not enough to change the world. So
if we want to change the world, let's go
go back home. If we go to the east to
Helsinki, next to Helsinki is a place
called Mansel, Finland. And there's an
interesting case study there to be
talked about. So typical climate, you
won't be surprised to hear Finland is
cold. Uh in Scandinavia, usually the
buildings are individual midsized
buildings that are all connected through
a district system. So it's pretty
uncommon in Scandinavia for people to
own their own boiler or furnace. It's
basically a communal effort. You have a
district system and when this system was
first designed, it was gas fired. And
then come 2014, Yandex, now called
Nibios outside of Russia basically
constructed this data center 50 40
megawatt. And we will talk about it.
It's a clever data center in terms of
the use. It has no mechanical cooling.
It also recovers heat for 2500 homes.
And so right away there was some
efficiencies to be made. Even 10 years
ago, they saved about 11% on the heating
bill of the people uh in the nearby
village. Now if you look at the top left
side, it's maybe a little hard to see in
that this whole building looks like an
airplane wing. And here you see in
section how that building works. This is
basically one example where the building
faces the predominant wind direction.
the cold air moves to the building and
so it saves a lot on fans on cooling
energy. So these are just clever ways
and even then uh 10 years ago they
managed to get a POE of 1.1. So again
synergies with the cold climate uh just
as a caveat because that's when you read
about the building now you also find out
that when you are investing in these
type of partnerships that the long-term
viability of both partners is really
important. So in this case basically
when the invasion of Ukraine started the
data center uh lost its uh electric
license. So the electric center stopped
no heat to the people and so they had to
use for a couple of months diesel backup
generators. That's just to give you a
sense there are risk obviously
associated with these type of
enterprises.
And then you might say who cares about
Helsinki? How does this compare to the
US? This is just a very high level
comparison. Helen Keyi versus
Minneapolis. And I picked Minneapolis
because it's still the continental US.
It's very well connected. Um I'm sad and
happy to report that Minneapolis is
colder than Helsinki. So, uh there are
opportunities there. At the same time,
since it's continental, it also gets a
little warmer. But the main point is
here. If you want to basically use
climate in the same way as what you saw
in this example, we have climates like
this here in the US as well.
So now I wanted to switch onto something
which I think has a lot of potential and
that's architectural building science
all these things together which is
basically the uh the kind of potential
between data center and thermal district
systems and I thought what I going to do
since right now over the last two years
we had a lot of debates at MIT on our
campus what to do with our building
similar to a lot of other universities
and portfolio owners have. So this is
like a little crash course on how can
you decarbonize or electrify your campus
and basically when you look at this is a
section of the campus. What comes in on
the left hand side is natural gas and
electricity. We have like many many of
our peers a central utility plant trigen
system that creates electricity. So we
buy natural gas and make our own
electricity and at the same time we
create chilled water and steam. So steam
has at about 250 to 350 degree
Fahrenheit. So this is really really
hot. Now that's not surprising if you
move steam and then we distribute that
through through loops and then have heat
exchangers in each building and that's
how the buildings are heated. Same for
MGH, same for Harvard. That's a pretty
common uh way of operating. And now all
of these systems have the trouble that
you have old infrastructure buried in
the ground that's at 450 degree
Fahrenheit. So there are a lot of heat
losses. not a great thermodynamic
concept and so basically there's this
move to fourth and fifth generation
thermal networks and there's a lot of
thinking right now so basically thinking
of midsize data centers that can be part
of that I think is very interesting so
the fourth generation system on our
campus how would that look like we keep
the chilled water we replace the steam
with a hot water system and so now we
are switching from 350° Fahrenheit to
170° Fahrenheit. So that's a lot better
overall. That requires a good amount of
work because we have to basically change
the heat exchangers. Buildings cannot
necessarily switch from steam to hot
water. And we probably have to do
finally some upgrades to the single pane
glass that we have in the main boob and
make our envelopes a little better. Um
and then typically what you will see at
many compasses on the right hand side in
order to store access heat sink heat
source thermal storage we will have a
ball hold field under the MIT football
field which we do have and uh that
basically charges and discharges uh
helps us to seasonally store some
energy. Now if we think about what else
could we be doing we want 80° C hot
water. So can we actually get that from
a data center and of course nowadays we
can do so if I
expand my diagram I have the 50°ree hot
air that's not warm enough for the hot
water loop but if I then also run an
industrial size heat pump then I can
take this air up this air upgrade it to
80° C and so basically now I have the
hot water that I can feed into my loop.
So what is nice about that is basically
my cup, my central utility plant, if you
look on the left, is not dependent on
natural gas anymore. So it's basically
fully electrified. And what we're doing,
we're feeding some of the electricity
that we're generating in a data center
that creates the hot air back that's uh
basically the source for a heat pump
that very effectively can then operate
the campus. So um again advantage this
is fully electrified future proof as a
concept.
What would be the holy grail? Well
ideally what a lot of us would like to
do is basically do a fifth generation
thermal network which in new
construction this is and this is a great
opportunity for a data center and if
you're building a new campus in a cold
climate this I think has a lot of
potential. So effectively what would we
first do when we have a fifth generation
system then we have only one loop that's
called the amient loop and the
temperature is really you can touch it
safely at any time it's from 45°
Fahrenheit to 85° Fahrenheit so it's
this thing of water that circulates in
the ground you can put it in PVC piping
it's very friendly and then basically
what we do we need to have distributed
heat pumps in all the buildings that
deposit and withdraw draw heat from this
loop and uh that is a good amount of
effort doing upgrades to our buildings.
But it basically means that when
buildings heat and cool at the same
time, we take advantage of this right
away. We can again have a ball field to
store some extra energy. Now we are in a
cold climate here, not as bad as some of
the others I showed you, but it is cold.
And so net we need some extra heat. So
the if we had a fifth generation system,
the only heat that we still need
probably will come from either getting
clean steam from somewhere or if we
provide this on campus, we are burning
still natural gas just for the heat. But
there again, I think the real beauty if
you're a physicist and you like just
nice heat flows moving around. If we now
instead of a cup had a data center, the
data center naturally provides you the
heat that you need to keep the ambient
loop afloat. So basically you
dramatically simplify really the whole
supply system on campus and all you have
is the data center that provides heat
directly that can be used for the
ambient loop to keep it happy and then
you have basically the standard heat
pumps in all the buildings to distribute
and work with. So lots of opportunities
here. Uh now the moment of truth. I told
you how great it is to have some heat
pumps locally here. Who would be really
excited to move in a neighborhood with a
data set?
I cannot blame you. I mean, uh, there is
this great website if you want to get
entertained. The top 10 ugliest data
centers in the world. And the top of the
top is the long lines building. Who
wants to be next to a building in
Manhattan where you pay premium and
you're looking at this monstrosity of a
building without any windows? So when
you look at this obviously there has to
be some thought of what are we actually
doing to make this like socially uh
acceptable and there are some different
approaches most of them are smaller most
of them no surprise are in Europe uh so
uh kind of does a data center need to
look like a data center that's a fun not
that small data center in Gladfeldon 20
megawatt and basically what it did is
they put this right next to a hotel and
the local river and so they basically
have fake wood on the outside and they
made it very quiet. These are just kind
of ways to make it more acceptable to
have the systems in place. I like this
because I like the image hasn't been
built. Will it ever be built? I don't
know. Uh but uh basically the city of uh
Frankfurt uh tries to push now everybody
for all the new data center to have them
aesthetically pleasing. So what does a
green planned facade do to a data
center? I would say absolutely nothing
in given that on the inside we have all
these grills burning. Uh but if you look
at like the the quality of the
neighborhood there are of course uh real
advantages to be make such as do we
control the temperature in the urban
canyon urban heat island effect only if
we reject the heat really effectively
outside and it just helps us to kind of
end with these systems being located
wherever we want them located.
So this takes me to the uh uh key
takeaways. I told you you could have
left uh but uh uh it's basically uh when
it thinks of locating the building.
There are some real opportunities. I
think don't just buy a standard uh heat
pump without some clever thinking about
how to use uh advantages of nature
around you to reduce uh the energy use
of these buildings. Um also you can't
turn off the cold wind in Minneapolis.
So you have it all the time. So
questions of uh of energy security are
also in your favor. Uh heat
electrification is upon us. It's
happening everywhere. So I think it's
really important that heat pump
operators since they will present this
kind of enormous extra load on the grids
everywhere that there are some clever
synergies there and again we are only
talking about peaks heating peaks
electric vehicles I didn't talk about
because I have only a minute and 9
seconds left but this is really these
are kind of opportunities to still
balance this out uh it's mostly about
how do we keep our electricity
affordable in the end. And then I think
for the district thermal systems there
depending on who your clients are and uh
if you are campuses portfolio owners
there are definitely some economically
advantageous kind of things to explore
and with that I thank you
>> questions for Kristoff.
>> Yes.
>> Hi Tafi Arabi from AMD. A lot of data
centers actually pay for provisional
power, not necessarily power used and
their power usage fluctuate a lot during
the day.
>> Mhm.
>> Have you thought of ways actually you
can also leverage maybe that electricity
when it's not in peak demand or
>> I mean if you if you do that uh then of
course it's like a negative it's nearly
like a battery. So if you uh if you are
in a data center willing to fluctuate
your electricity by the demands of your
local utility, I think the stability
that you can add to the local grid is
enormous. The only real advantages that
I've seen Google made a lot of uh splash
about their data centers, but of course
they are located all over the world and
they're basically moving now when do the
YouTube videos compiled from one data
center to another. that doesn't cost
them anything because I don't think
they're at full capacity. I think uh um
and so these are very clever ways of
doing this if you run your data center
depending I think on who your clients
are probably my colleagues can comment
better on this if you can wait for uh
even if it's just an hour the value
generation is enormous and I think the
the earlier you talk with the local
utilities and do a future demand profile
model the better. So I showed you a
little bit in Massachusetts. We actually
built an energy model of every building
in the state. We want to build an energy
model of every building in the world. Uh
so basically this is being used for us
to see what's the current load. If we do
certain changes to the building, how are
the load curves going to evolve and how
likely for different energy policies is
it that they are going to evolve. I
think having a data center in there is
an enormous asset.
>> Thank you.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Amazing. Uh a way of using
the waste heat uh for district heating.
What's your view on? So people have been
also thinking about using uh waste heat
for u uh data centers to in tandem with
absorption chillers. Uh you know there
are maybe some mixed result in terms of
how you know the grade of heat is and
how effective that the the cooling
system would look like. So what's your
what's your view on on that one?
>> It's funny. I looked at that also two
days ago and thought, "Oh, wouldn't that
also be uh great?" I mean, I think the
50 degrees is if you want to have an
entropy wheel and you want to discharge
it, right? Then I think the 50° are not
hot enough. I think they need 80 90. So
it's always the big thing is always do
we have low or high process heat and
unfortunately paints me uh the data
centers have the low process heat. If we
had some uh if we could go 30 degrees C
higher that would be hugely unatious. So
I mean you could do the same hocus pocus
that I showed you before that you
basically combine that with the heat
pump. You upgrade the heat and then use
it for that but it's an extra step.
>> Now the big thing about data centers is
that they're big and so there is one
point of source of heat. So even
thinking of distributing to go like
upgrading to a higher heat and then
moving at longer distances. I think this
is all on the table. But the the synergy
is not as clear as for the fifth
generation network. It needs 50° C.
Voila. Here's 50° C for free. So I think
that's kind of the trade-off here. But
there's a whole field of process
engineers that will can have a field day
with you on figuring that out. Sounds
>> good. Thank you. Anyone
else?
Hey,
but
>> the kind person who gave me water.
>> No problem. Uh, you mentioned kind of
wood as a facade, but any comments on
kind of actual construction materials
that maybe are more sustainable. We've
seen kind of wood construction in some
data centers just because also I think
there's a speed to deploy as well as
I'll call them tents, but we have seen
glorified tents be used. um but green
steel as well. But where do you see kind
of the most um return on investment in
focusing on the actual construction of
the of the buildings?
>> No, this is a really uh great question.
I mean the wood cladding is really to
appease the good people of Switzerland
in that neighborhood that it looks like
the forest, right? I think that has more
aesthetic value and this is not even
real wood. Okay. Uh but uh so I mean you
said it yourself um like the the
building structure the embodied energy
is relatively small for a data center.
Everywhere else net zero buildings this
is gaining more traction. I mean I think
it's probably a question of structural
integrity. Maybe you can use CLT wood if
you want to. Uh but that depends on
where in the world you are. A lot of
growth you see in areas where people use
concrete and they're using concrete
because there is concrete right and of
course uh I mean it's just frightful to
me up until a day I thought we are at a
thousand watt and then when I had to
move these grills together I I think it
got really in frightful and I think the
4,000 watt is not the end of the game.
So I mean thinking carefully about the
structure of your building is probably a
really good idea because you don't want
to have a stranded asset when people say
oh I have 10,000 10k per watch right I
want to be the one known to have the
highest load in the world kind of thing
right
>> thank you
>> okay we want to give a little bit of
love for our online audience today so
here's a question that came in it starts
off with sir so they're definitely not
talking to me uh they want to know why
data centers are typically developed on
farmland rather than high-rise
buildings. Uh are there other issues
like due to energy efficiency, cooling
and scalability considerations or there
are there broader resilience and
sustainability factors involved?
>> Uh well short answer I don't know. If I
were to guess most home depots uh are
basically I mean it's a kind of building
uh go big or go home. I think the
economics for a data center that really
helps. So you want large spaces and they
just plus uh I mean on one way
urbanistically there are 20 people in
this big home depot and uh why should
they replace all these people that could
live downtown for all the uh livability
and just uh uh productivity that urban
centers can offer. So I think there are
economic uh reasons and not all of them
are necessarily bad and I think these
data center placement that I'm talking
here about are relatively modestsiz data
centers because again you cannot move
that heat enormous distances. I think
these type of data sensors make really
sense. If you are really finicky and you
want to have this is your data and you
want to keep your data, this is only
you. Then of course you want to have it
with you and then I think then it makes
a lot of sense. Once you made the
decision this is our data center, nobody
plucks in then all of these things
become like good ways to help you with
the economics.
>> Wonderful. Okay. Oh, one more.
>> So
>> sitting closest to me and I wanted to
cut you off. That's like unbelievable.
>> Yeah, I know. So why do you think that
that that long line long line buildings
the old AT&T building? So So why why and
and I've been inside that building and
so why why Yeah. No, it's it's a
beautiful lobby, by the way. So why why
don't you like the the the the
aesthetics of that building?
>> Oh, wow. Now we are now we're getting
hardcore here. Uh I mean I just try to
project. I'm a big projector and if I
had paid for this apartment right next
to it and everybody says I'm living in
Manhattan and you're looking at that
wall that's less than inspiring. So if
we if I actually go into view research
we know that people like seeing other
people or activity or whatever it's
going on. So this is just a less
attractive view I would overall it also
I would say without having done a survey
it's well I've done a survey with all of
you. Nobody wants to have the data
center right next to them. I think
there's a like an a natural tendency and
then these tricks with the green facads
help us overcome that.
>> Yep.
But maybe there's an apartment just
waiting for you with that.
>> It It could be the engineer versus the
architect kind of thing going.
>> Other data centers are ugly.
I'd rather see that.
It's a race to the bottom. Maybe the
next year is the 2025 uh ugliest data
centers in the world.
>> Okay. All right. One quick question.
>> So, this is about something I just saw
on YouTube yesterday, you know, like
just browsing. Me too.
>> What is the research and what are the
what are the opportunities in noise
reduction? Because as they build these
data centers closest to residential
areas all over the country, people are
starting to be impacted by this humming
that's constantly comes out of this
centers. So what's going on there?
>> It's a good question. I don't know. Uh I
mean I try to uh figure that out better.
I mean what I would probably see
generally if you manage same for fume
hoods get the get the noise and the
movement up across the urban boundary
layer that's a good move generally I
would be saying and then this last image
that I showed you is basically a clever
facade system that basically has the
green roofs and openings it's basically
an acoustically active facads actually
plants are pretty good at dampening uh
uh noise that comes out of it. I I doubt
you will really overcome it. Probably a
data center, especially if you add more
and more fans and like to it
going to make noise. I think I I can't
give you like a a silver bullet answer
here.
>> Great.
>> Oh yeah, this is like kind of fun to
look at. Not as ugly as the other
building. Our friend here won't agree,
but maybe some of
>> we we have to move on to our next
speaker. Um, sorry. At at at some point
at some point I have to bring down the
hammer on these things. Great. Let's
hear it for Christo. Great job.