I'm Katharina Ribbeck.
And I'm Amy Keating.
And it was our pleasure to chair
the program planning committee
for today's symposium.
It's incredibly exciting
to see it coming to life.
The hardest part of
this job, by far,
was putting together
just a single-day program
from the wealth of
ideas and innovation
that surround us at MIT.
It is, yeah, really this wealth
of discoveries and innovation
that makes MIT so exceptional.
Here we are not just
exploring new frontiers,
we are actively creating them.
Now we have the
privilege of hearing
from four remarkable
early-career-stage faculty who
exactly embody this spirit.
These rising stars
from chemistry,
biological engineering
and neuroscience,
are not only expanding
our understanding.
They're taking discoveries
in bold new directions
and really influencing the way
we think, the way we innovate,
and the way we collaborate.
So professors Oleta Johnson,
Bryan Bryson, Sara Prescott,
and Sinisa Hrvatin
will share with you
their visions for the
future in four short talks.
Please join us in
welcoming them.
[APPLAUSE]
Good morning.
I am excited to be here today.
I'm an assistant professor.
This is my second
year here at MIT,
and my lab is broadly
interested in using chemistry
to direct protein
traffic in cells.
Before I tell you
what that means,
I want to start by
asking you a question.
What do these five
people have in common?
I'll give you three
seconds to think about it.
All right, if you thought
that these people are
leaders, innovators, or icons,
I'd totally agree with you.
As it pertains to my research,
they share, unfortunately,
another commonality.
All five of these
people were diagnosed
with a devastating
class of disorders
known as neurodegenerative
diseases, that ultimately robbed
them of the physical and
cognitive faculties that
enabled them to have such
a huge impact on the world.
With that in mind, I invite
you to imagine a world
where a diagnosis with
one of these diseases
is not a timer, counting down
to some inevitable decline
in the way that you engage
with those around you.
My lab is working right now to
turn that world into a reality,
and I'll give you an overview
of how we plan to do this,
but first, I want to
be specific about what
these five different diseases
actually have in common.
If you look at the photos
at the bottom of the slide,
these are all photos of tissues
from patients that are diagnosed
with these diseases.
And you'll notice
these dark spots
that are on the
slide in these cells.
Those are proteins
that are aggregated,
a common feature of
all five diseases.
What that means at
the molecular level
is that proteins
that are normally
pretty flexible in a cell
to do their normal function,
they are somehow--
they somehow get
clumped together
in what we call these
protein aggregates.
We don't always know how they
happen or why they happen,
but I like to think of some
cellular protein highway
where one path gets cut off,
leading to this cellular protein
traffic jam.
Similar to if you were to say
shut down the Sumner Tunnel.
And now there's
a giant aggregate
of cars on the way
to the airport.
With that in mind, it's
important to consider
ways to prevent these
cellular protein traffic
jams from happening
in the first place.
Luckily, there's a protein
that I care about called DNAJB6
that is already very good
at directing protein traffic
and preventing these aggregates.
But as you've seen, it doesn't
always work in these diseases.
Based on what we
know about DNAJB6,
my lab has three
big-picture goals.
We want to develop
new chemical tools
that we can use to detect
these aggregates earlier
than we can right now.
We want to learn more
about the mechanisms
that DNAJB uses to direct
protein traffic to see
if there's any clues there on
what we could do as chemists.
And we want to discover
chemicals, small molecules that
can work with DNAJB6 to either
activate or mimic its activity
and prevent aggregates
from happening.
And I was really lucky to
recruit three fabulous graduate
students in my first year
to work on these problems.
Cordiana is working on a
fluorescence-based platform
for early detection
of protein aggregates.
Aaron is taking really
complicated DNAJB6 structures
and using chemistry to
make them more simple,
to make it easier
for them to study,
for us to study how they work.
And Isha is looking for chemical
detectors that activate DNAJB6
by acting as glues, recruiting
it to a protein of interest
in a disease of interest.
And that's just the beginning,
because last month I
recruited three more
fantastic graduate students
in my group who
are going to work
on three new projects
towards our goals,
and together we hope
that that will result
in better diagnostics and better
therapeutics that, had they
existed 20 or 30 years ago,
would give us more time
to learn from the
wisdom of experience
of people like Rosa Parks,
Muhammad Ali, or Stephen
Hawking.
But most importantly, we hope
that the tools that we develop
in my lab could be used to
improve the quality of life
for people who are diagnosed
with these diseases.
Ordinary everyday
people like you and me.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Good morning, everyone.
I'd like us to imagine a
world without tuberculosis.
This is the Granville mummy,
estimated to be found in 600 BC.
At the time when they
unearthed this mummy,
they thought that the cause
of death for this mummy
was ovarian cancer.
However, in the early 2000s,
researchers found that this
mummy had had tuberculosis.
Fast forward to
the 19th century,
where it's estimated that one in
seven individuals was dying from
tuberculosis.
This is an ad from the Christmas
Seals asking you to donate money
to stamp out tuberculosis.
But unfortunately, I'm here to
report that the Christmas Seals
were unsuccessful in this
campaign because today alone,
4,000 people will die from TB.
OK, so what would
be transformative?
What would be transformative
for TB is a protective vaccine.
And this is something
that we do not yet have.
We have one vaccine for TB.
It is over 100 years old, and it
doesn't meet the product profile
needed to end this pandemic.
However, if we did, it
would change history.
So looking at this graph, this
is TB incidence per million
on the y-axis and
time on the x-axis.
If we do nothing and we
just keep standard of care,
that's the red line.
If we had a 60% protective
vaccine and a mass vaccination
campaign, look at
what could happen.
All right, so the question
becomes, how do we get there?
How do we make a
protective TB vaccine?
All right, so
that's the question
that my lab decided to tackle.
So why aren't we there yet?
We heard about measurement.
I would like to submit to you
that this is a measurement
problem.
So the question
becomes, how do you
design a vaccine
in the first place?
We might all be experts
about designing vaccines
for viral pathogens,
but tuberculosis
is caused by a bacterium.
So when I think about this
problem as an engineer,
I think about the
following question, what
proteins from the bacterium
does the immune system see?
All right, this is an
especially hard problem
in the context of
infection with bacteria
because viruses have
tens of proteins.
TB has 4,000.
So it's not that simple just
to say which protein do I pick.
It's actually a
really hard problem.
And to make that problem even
just a smidge more difficult,
we have to do this
in a biosafety level
three environment, which
means that everything just
goes much slower, much more
complicated, and much more
arduous, because this isn't some
place where you can just say,
I want to try something
new and do it tomorrow.
This takes a lot of
effort and energy.
So despite those roadblocks, I'm
really excited to share with you
that we've made significant
inroads to this problem.
OK, so how do we do this?
So work led by an
incredibly talented graduate
student in collaboration
with Forrest White.
We set out to address
the measurement problem,
asking specifically
in human cells
across diverse human
genotypes, if we
infect with TB, what
proteins from the bacterium
are seen by the immune system?
So I'm going to call
this problem solved.
We can do it.
We can do it within days now.
OK, So now the next
question becomes,
if you can make
these measurements
and ask what the immune
system sees with bacteria,
can we ask what does
the immune system see
when you give a vaccine,
including those proteins
from the bacterium?
And that's what we've
been able to do now.
So now we can design
vaccines as mRNAs
and within weeks get an answer
about a particular design
that we've made.
And to give you an example
of what we've done just
in the last few years, is we've
made all these different vaccine
prototypes, and I don't have
the time to go through all
the details, but what we can
do now with these measurement
technologies and say, what if
we change just one parameter
about this mRNA vaccine?
How does it change
immune output?
So that's what you're looking at
here on the right graph, where
I'm just showing two vaccine
designs where we just
made a small 100 amino acid
change to the mRNA vaccine,
and we can change immune
output by orders of magnitude.
So while this has seemed like a
millennia-old problem for a very
long time, I'm very optimistic.
I'm incredibly optimistic
because I think we can do this.
So I'll leave you with
a provocative question,
which is, will the
next TB vaccine come
from Kendall Square?
And I think it will.
I'm very encouraged by this
because in the last six years
I think we've done so
much to answer really
a millennia-old problem.
But I think we can
do so much more.
And I think the
momentum is on our side.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Imagine a world where we
understood how our daily stress
was damaging our health.
We could track it
with simple tests
and intervene to prevent or
reverse its harmful effects.
In this world, stress
would no longer
silently fuel chronic
disease, wreak havoc
on our mental health, and
reinforce social inequities.
We all face stress
in daily life,
but globally, stress levels
are now at an all-time high.
This Gallup poll asked
people around the world
to self-report
their daily stress
levels as part of a
Negative Experience Index,
and for over a
decade, stress levels
have been consistently
rising, driven
by factors like financial
insecurity, social isolation,
and workplace burnout.
These same studies show that
stress levels are unequally
distributed across different
countries and demographics.
Within the US, stress
levels are highest
in college-age adolescents,
in women, and low-income
and minority groups.
Looking at these
statistics, it's
hard not to feel that we are
living in a pandemic of stress
with marginalized
communities and our youth,
the very future of our nation,
bearing the heaviest burden.
The consequences
of this on society
are massive, damaging not
just our mental health
but our physical health as well.
Children, for example,
who experience
severe early life stress as
measured by high ACE scores,
lose over a decade
of life expectancy
and are at higher
risk for conditions
like cardiovascular disease,
infertility, and cancer.
This association between stress
and worse health outcomes
is also seen in animal models.
For example, early life stress
reduces survival in wild baboons
and cause mice that are
raised in lab environments
to develop predictable
pathologies,
like making their
very hair turn gray.
These observations tell us
that these associations between
stress and worse health outcomes
cannot be explained entirely
by diet, smoking, and access
to health care services.
And it begs the question of what
biological processes link stress
to increased disease
and mortality risk.
I'm a neuroscientist,
and my lab studies
how the brain controls essential
functions like breathing
and heart rate.
And we see stress not
just as a feeling,
but as a biological program with
specific purpose and patterns.
When we face a threat, the
brain primes the body for action
by triggering the
sympathetic nervous system
to release norepinephrine,
causing rapid breathing,
a racing heart, and sweating.
These circuits also
signal endocrine centers
like the adrenal
glands to produce
cortisol and other hormones,
keeping the body on high alert.
Cells throughout the body
receive these signals
and are forever changed.
With new tools, we can
now monitor and target
these pathways with
unprecedented precision
to ask which precise
circuits are disrupted
by chronic and severe stress.
How do stress signals
affect different cell types
throughout the body, and how
are these changes remembered
at the molecular scale?
Through this lens,
we can view stress
as a predictable program that
can be tracked and treated.
To understand this, we're
collaborating with other Boston
area labs, using animal models
to control stress exposures,
and then using advanced
imaging and molecular tools
to track within
individual animals
how this rewires brain
activity and disrupts
physiological systems.
These comprehensive data sets
capture a more holistic view
of stress and are helping
us predict causal brain
changes that alter
bodily states and lead
to stress-related disease.
Looking ahead, addressing
this health crisis
requires new perspectives
and solutions.
As for cancer research, we
must both learn core principles
while also embracing
stress' complexity,
and endotypes if we want to
advance precision treatments.
This effort will rest on
pillars of collaboration
across disciplines to better
understand the molecular scars
of stress and to build
evidence-based diagnostics
and interventions
within our community.
And I for one am looking
forward to this bright future.
Thank you all for
your attention.
[APPLAUSE]
Good morning.
My name is Sinisa Hrvatin.
I'm honored to be here.
I want you this
morning to imagine
a world in which suspended
animation were possible.
A world in which a 10-year-old
girl suffering an incurable
disease, like
maybe glioblastoma,
instead of imminently dying,
has the choice to enter a state
of suspended animation for
a few years, maybe a decade,
and then wake up at a time
in which there is a treatment
or perhaps even a
cure to that disease.
I know this is currently
science fiction, pretty much
complete science
fiction, but what
I want to share with you today
is that there are animals
in nature that have the
ability to enter similar states
and that have the ability
to enter something
like suspended animation that I
think we can learn so much from.
And then learn how
to eventually develop
suspended animation for humans.
So I'll share with you examples
of a few of these animals.
This is the Arctic
ground squirrel.
This animal lives
above the Arctic Circle
at very low temperatures,
and during most of the year
it has a normal
body temperature,
just like you and me,
around 37 degrees Celsius.
But during the winter, it can
survive by entering hibernation,
and it can lower its body
temperature all the way down
to around 0 degrees Celsius,
entering a sleep-like state
that we call torpor.
My laboratory studies
how animals enter torpor
and also how do
their cells survive
at these very low temperatures.
And I want to share with
you a couple of things
that we've recently found.
We identified a
population of neurons
in the brain that
controls torpor.
And remarkably, we can actually
initiate a torpor-like state
even in animals that
don't naturally hibernate,
just by stimulating
these neurons.
So here you can see an
example of a laboratory mouse.
This is a thermal camera image.
It has a body temperature
around 37 degrees Celsius.
But when you stimulate
these neurons,
you can lower the
body temperature
of this animal all the way down
to around 25 degrees Celsius.
Now, this is not as low
as a natural hibernator,
but it's actually
really cold for a mouse.
And we can do this not
only for minutes or hours,
but actually for days to weeks,
showing for the first time
that we can induce a
long-term torpor-like state
in an animal that doesn't
naturally hibernate.
We've also, in a
parallel study, started
looking at how do
hibernator cells survive
at these low
temperatures and seeing
whether we can learn from their
mechanisms to improve human cell
cold survival.
And here you can see an example
of a handful of human cell lines
that don't fare very well
at 4 degrees Celsius.
But then when we take
small molecules that
mimic some of the adaptations
that hibernators have
during hibernation and
treat those cells with them,
we can dramatically improve
their cold tolerance.
And you can
immediately imagine how
this could be useful for organ
storage or organ transplantation
and also how
eventually we could use
this to learn how to lower the
temperature of the human body
to lower and lower temperatures.
And finally, perhaps
the greatest example
of suspended animation in nature
are these tardigrades, cute
little organisms that actually
live all over our globe,
from the Arctic
to the Antarctic,
and they have an
incredible ability
to survive being
frozen all the way down
to -150 degrees Celsius.
And they can stay in that
state for months to years
and then come out of it
essentially unharmed.
We're trying to understand
how tardigrades survive this
and whether we can transfer
some of those adaptations
to human cells.
Now life on Earth has evolved
incredible adaptations
to survive in
extreme environments,
and I believe that by
studying these animals,
we'll learn to harness
some of the mechanisms
behind these adaptations
to advance medicine,
perhaps even one day open
the door to fantastic
possibilities of space travel.
Now, this work needs to start
with fundamental biological
discoveries.
But in order to develop
this as a technology,
we also need to collaborate with
engineers, chemists, physicists,
physicians.
And this is precisely why
there is no place like MIT
to pursue this dream.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]