Do we have any Canadians in the room?
Anybody from Canada?
Not a one. Usually they're loud and
proud, but somebody surely knows who
this is.
Who is it?
>> Wayne Gretzky. That's exactly right.
Now, Wayne Gretzky is known for a number
of sayings, but there's one in
particular that I want to highlight
today that will be the through line for
the rest of our session together.
He talks a lot about the direction in
which he skates. Does anybody know this
famous Wayne Gretzky quote?
No hockey fans, huh?
>> Yes, that's it. He says, "I skate to
where the puck is going to be, not where
it has been." And I think this is
extremely important when we think about
the ways in which artificial
intelligence is changing the way that
companies start and scale. This is
something that we'll talk about, but my
core belief is that we as society are
creating more problems than we are
solutions on a daily basis. And the best
way to address this fundamental
challenge is through AIdriven
entrepreneurship. This gives us all
sorts of benefits as we go to create the
companies that will help to address
these problems.
My background is as a software engineer
and I believe that there is so much from
the software world that can be applied
in the creation of companies
systematically programmatically bringing
companies to life.
I've spent years teaching
entrepreneurship here at MIT.
We've taught two forms of
entrepreneurship primarily. First, small
medium enterprise. Those companies that
scale linearly, they have capped growth.
They serve local markets, but they
require very little upfront investment.
They can get off the ground without much
investment at all. And innovationdriven
enterprises, companies that scale, these
companies scale globally, have global
impact, but require significant upfront
investment to get off the ground. That's
the area that you see shaded below the X
axis. Innovation driven enterprises have
phenomenal impact all around the world.
These two forms of entrepreneurship have
long been what has enabled entrepreneurs
to get off the ground. And we've helped
many entrepreneurs here at MIT through
our methodologies take their ideas,
their research, their technology and
turn that into business plans.
We've helped entrepreneurs take those
business plans and turn them into
businesses. businesses that are out in
the world that have that phenomenal
impact.
And we talk a lot about tactics, how to
actually do things. MIT is such an
applied place. Coming back to the men's
modest mindset and tactic, this is
something that we talk about, but we
have to define our terms. What is a
tactic? It's an action or strategy
carefully planned to achieve a specific
end. But the key word here is action.
Action. So, how do entrepreneurs get off
the ground? Well, they have to not only
know what to do and why to do it, but
how to do it. And that's something that
we spend a lot of time looking at. To
really understand this, we have to go
back 2500 years. There's a book that was
written 2500 years ago. Does anybody
know what that book might be?
I see a smile.
I love that smile, by the way. and sir
over here in the in the white shirt. I
got to say I was so excited getting up
here today because he was like at the
beginning of the talk he was like
sitting there in his seat like like
leaning forward. He was so ready to go
and I love that. That gives me all the
energy in the world. But what book was
written 2500 years ago? It was written
by a Chinese military strategist.
Sunsu. The art of war. Yes. And in the
art of war, Sun Sue says, "Strategy
without tactics is the slowest route to
victory. Tactics without strategy is the
noise before defeat." And I think this
is extremely important in what we're
seeing happening with artificial
intelligence and the creation and
scaling of ventures today. Far too many
people are thinking about business
fundamentals here and artificial
intelligence over here. But it is truly
the integration of these two things, the
strategy and the tactics that is
enabling businesses to successfully get
off the ground. Entrepreneurship and the
ways in which we create companies is
changing rapidly. We're seeing more
people pursue entrepreneurship which is
phenomenal and it's one of the ways in
which we can address that fundamental
challenge that I started with creating
more problems than solutions on a daily
basis. Now I found this ridiculous and
hilarious at the same time. Many of you
will be familiar with the age-old sell
me this pen exercise. And I brought
everybody a gift that I I scooped off
the back table. [laughter]
I got everybody here a pen.
You're welcome to take one and then I'll
ask you to pass it.
Can you just take the bin? Cuz if we sit
and wait for me to pass them all around,
we'll be in big trouble. So sell me this
pen. Can you sell me the pen? Yeah.
What do you have to do to sell somebody
a pen these days?
It's very simple. Very, very simple.
THAT'S IT. RIGHT. THAT'S IT. THAT'S ALL
YOU HAVE TO DO THESE days to sell
somebody a pen. Now, the challenge that
this presents is that we see people
buying AI, this AI, that for no reason,
creating no real value. And I think
that's where the strategy and the
tactics really come into play and become
even more important. How do we make sure
that uh these companies that are coming
out emerging with AI uh products are
actually creating real value out in the
world. This is something that we'll talk
about, but anybody now can create a
company which is phenomenal. We just
have to make sure that we don't wind up
back in that position where they're
selling things that don't create real
impact. Anybody can create a business
plan and that's a phenomenal thing.
Previously, the most experienced
entrepreneurs were those who started
with a really concrete business plan,
something that was really solid. Now,
when we think about those entrepreneurs,
they're either experienced, educated, or
trained in starting companies. But not
everybody is necessarily experienced,
educated, or trained. But now with AI,
anybody can create a business plan
that's high quality, comprehensive, and
rigorous that gives them the same
starting point as any EXPERIENCED
ENTREPRENEUR. THAT'S SO POWERFUL. WHAT
THAT means that anybody in this room can
go and start a company. Now, I'm not
telling you to go leave your jobs and
start a company. But what I am telling
you is that in your companies, you have
the potential to move the needle for the
organization at large by leveraging this
AIdriven entrepreneurship uh
methodology. But to really understand
this, we have to just recognize where we
are in the broad strokes. Where are we
in the global adoption of AI? I think
back often to
downloading music online. Some folks in
this room will remember Limewire where
you'd go and probably illegally download
a song. You'd press download, you'd go
eat dinner, you'd come back and it would
still be only like 37% downloaded.
And when I go and I prompt some of the
AI tools that are out there today, like
um some of the code generation tools, I
press go and then I sit there and I
wait. And I call this the
dialup era of AI.
You press a button and you have to wait
for it to produce a response. We're
still in the very early days here. What
that means is that for entrepreneurs,
there's phenomenal opportunity in front
of us. That opportunity is to leverage
this in the process of starting and
scaling companies.
I found this investor update to be
phenomenal. I think this uh should
really open your eyes to what's
happening and what's changing out in the
world. This is an investor update that I
received. It says, "We spent the last 28
months reducing the workforce from 218
to 29 members, reducing burn, the amount
of money that they spend every single
month from $2.1 million to $300,000 and
made progress improving the core
metrics." You can read on, but the long
and short of this is that revenue is up,
renewals are up, and burn is down
significantly.
Companies are becoming more efficient
and they are emerging into the
marketplace and stealing market share
from incumbent organizations faster than
ever before.
So if we come back to these two forms of
entrepreneurship, what does this mean?
How what if we could have the best of
both worlds of small medium enterprises
and these innovationdriven enterprises?
That's what I'd like to introduce you to
today. AIdriven enterprises, AIDes.
AIDES bring the best of both worlds from
theme entrepreneurship and
innovationdriven entrepreneurship to
create companies that start and scale
and achieve phenomenal impact with far
fewer resources in far less time.
The orange line that you see here,
this is an example of one of those
AIdriven enterprises. I will give you
concrete examples as well, but I want
you to think about what happens when
with very limited upfront investment and
very short time to market, we can get a
company off the ground that scales that
has phenomenal impact in the world. What
if
in any of the regions that you all are
from around the world, we created
thousands of orange lines like you see
on the slide?
Think about the economic impact
potential that would have. Many regions
are constrained by access to risk
capital. But with this model, we need
far less risk capital. And many regions
suffer when one big innovationdriven
enterprise, one large organization goes
out of business or starts to lose market
share. What happens? Jobs are lost. We
always think of innovation-driven
enterprises as being beneficial to the
economy because they create jobs. They
create a lot of jobs. But the reality is
that also creates risk in the economy.
So aides serve entrepreneurs, serve risk
capital, serve government. They serve
truly everybody. And ultimately for each
and every one of us in this room, they
help us to solve many of our pressing
problems.
So a lot of people say, "Well, Paul, AI
is just for AI companies." And one of
the things I would say to that is that
AI is for every single company and every
single sector in every organization.
An AIdriven enterprise is not an AI
company. It is a company that leverages
artificial intelligence regardless of
what sector they're in in every
functional area. business planning and
strategy, operations, go to market,
sales and marketing, uh, finance,
operations, HR, every single functional
area. And that is what enables these
companies to get off the ground and
scale so rapidly. There's far more that
you can read on the AID methodology on
this form of entrepreneurship online.
But I want to get a quick read of the
room. How comfortable are folks with AI
today? We're going to do like one to
five, but I don't think the uh slide is
working. But let me ask you
on a scale of 1 to five where one is I
use chat GPT
and three is I use other AI tools
besides chat GPT co-pilot Gemini etc.
And five is I have 37 AI agents running
my life right now. Where are you? Who's
a one?
Who's a two?
Who's a three?
Who's a four? Who's a five? Yeah. Oh,
>> more or less. That's wild.
I have questions.
A lot of them.
That gives us a sense of where people
are in their understanding and their
comfort level with these tools. But I
want to talk about the trends that we're
seeing in these AIdriven enterprises. We
are seeing the product development life
cycle shrink significantly. What used to
take years to develop a product. If we
look back 50 years ago has decreased to
days, hours, minutes, and in some cases
actually milliseconds.
Just yesterday, Google released an
update that uh their search now produces
personalized uh user interfaces based on
what you're searching, based on your
personalized account. In many cases, now
products products interfaces are being
developed on the fly. When you click a
button, that interface is being
generated just for you, right before
your eyes. Product development life
cycles have shrunk significantly. Many
of it is thanks to these just to get a
sense around the room. Who's used one of
these tools or something like it?
Wow. Look around the room for a second.
Can you put your hands back up?
Everybody look around the room for just
a second. That's wild. Now, for those
raising their hands, I have bad news for
you, which is that for everybody else, I
am granting you one day off next week.
Anybody who hasn't tried one of these
tools, you get one day off of work next
week. I don't know that it's really in
my purview to grant that day off to you,
but screw it. You can tell your boss to
come talk to me. I think you need to go
spend just one day and you need to go
invest in what I call tinker time.
Tinker time is taking one big step back.
The reason why many people probably
haven't tried these tools is because
your day job has going concerns. You
have deadlines, you have timelines, you
have so many things that you need to
accomplish, which means you can't take a
step back to experiment. So, one day
next week, that's your opportunity to
experiment. There's plenty of these
tools and I'd encourage you to go try
them. Now, who here uh knows what vibe
coding is?
Okay, if you don't know what VIC coding
is, it's not too late to ask. In a month
or a year, it will be too late. So, for
now, go invest in playing with these
tools and prompting one of these LLMs to
go create a new software product with
plain text and it will produce that code
for you.
But it's not just about development life
cycles. If we talk about the trends that
we're seeing, the amount of time that it
takes to get users is decreasing
significantly as well. What took Netflix
years to get to 1 million users took
Chat GBT 5 days and threads just 24
hours. I don't use um X much, but there
is one post on X that I absolutely love
from March of this year. It's a post
from Sam Alman and he says, "The chat
GBT launch 26 months ago was one of the
craziest viral moments I had ever seen
and we added 1 million users in 5 days."
If you've seen this post, then you know
he goes on to say we added 1 million
users in the last hour. So the question
I would pose to you is when was the last
time your company added 1 million users
in an hour or whatever that equates to
that level of scale in your
organization.
This is what's happening and this is how
companies are entering the market today.
But it's not just about product
development life cycles and it's not
just about user acquisition. It's about
revenue. This is one of the things that
separates the dot boom and bust from
what's happening today.
The vanity metrics that people were
tracking and investing in back in the
dot bubble days. Here we have companies
actually generating revenue creating
real value out in the world. So what
took docuign 9 years to hit $100 million
in annual recurring revenue took cursor
under a year.
And it's not just about how much money
they can bring in. And it's not just
about how many users they can attract.
And it's not just about the product
development life cycle. It's about how
much human capital they need to get
things off the ground, how much time,
how many human hours. What took Airbnb
and LinkedIn over 500 people to hit that
same $100 million in a annual recurring
revenue benchmark took Cursor just 20
people. So think about this. 20 people
in under a year to go from zero to $100
million in annual recurring revenue.
That's pretty phenomenal.
And the old startup scale up model is
not necessarily the case anymore. With
these companies with smaller teams, we
don't see them moving into big office
buildings. We don't see these
entrepreneurs giving up quite as much
equity in their companies. They're
retaining more ownership, which is
really exciting and a good thing for
entrepreneurs. Most things that are good
for entrepreneurs is good for society at
large.
And we won't go through this in too much
detail, but again, I want to come back
to the idea that if you had thousands of
these AIdriven enterprises, oh, and I
guess the video doesn't even work. BUT
IF YOU HAD THOUSANDS of these AIdriven
enterprises, you would have a much more
distributed economy that has less risk.
And that's something that again is good
for all of us.
All of this comes back to the metrics
that we track. The metrics that we track
for these companies. What's happening is
we're seeing a lot of entrepreneurs, a
lot of startups who raised a preede
round of funding, a seed round of
funding, a series A round of funding,
who are blowing it out of the water by
all accounts. If you look at most
traditional metrics, but when they go to
raise their next round of funding,
they're finding out that they're
actually way behind. Despite having
phenomenal metrics in their last few
rounds, the goalpost has moved since
they brought the last round of funding
into the company because investors are
seeing far more efficient companies out
in the marketplace that they would
rather put their capital into.
So, what does that mean for these
entrepreneurs? It means that they're a
little bit out of luck.
These AIdriven enterprises are being
measured on annual recurring revenue per
FTE or full-time equivalent.
What is your company's ARR to FTE
metric? Does anybody know? I want you to
think about that one for just a second.
And I don't need you to tell me. I don't
need you to tell other people in the
room, but it's very important to me that
you know what this metric is for your
company.
If we compare that to some of the
bloated unicorns of yesterday
and some of the autonomous businesses
that are emerging now, we see very
different numbers. Very different
numbers here. If we look and we see
companies like Bench at $23,000 ARR to
FTE and then we look and we see these
autonomous businesses like Lovable at
$600,000 per FTE or Bolt.new at $1.3
million per FTE. That's phenomenal.
That's an efficient business. That's a
business that is growing at a rapid clip
and bringing in significant revenue per
FTE.
Now, we think about what an organization
is. When you hear the word organization,
what comes to mind? What do you think
about
organization? What do you think?
>> Industry connections. Okay, great.
Somebody else. What do you think when
you hear the word organization?
>> A group of people. Who said that?
Do you do you like study the dictionary?
>> Cuz you're like right on. A group of
people who work together in an organized
way with a shared purpose.
Now, I believe that this definition
is outdated. If anybody has a contact at
Miriam Webster, I would love to chat
with them. I believe that this
definition is outdated. Why? Because the
keyword people, what is the most
inefficient part of every organization?
Think about your organization. What's
the most inefficient part?
It's the people. It's all of us.
We're all irrational in some ways. We
have, beliefs, thoughts, feelings. And
the reality is that organizations are no
longer just about people. organizations.
I'm not saying we should get rid of
people, just to be clear.
But what I am saying is that we should
be redefining
this word to reflect what organizations
really are today, which are a group of
nodes where some nodes might be humans
and some nodes might be AI agents.
They're still working together in an
organized way with that shared purpose,
but they're far more efficient because
of it.
And we're seeing the emergence of many
many companies that are run by one
person but that have phenomenal revenue
metrics and phenomenal value valuations.
Now I still believe that in any one
person unicorn company the most
inefficient part of that company will be
the one person.
And this is because of founder
everything. A lot of people talk about
founder sales. Founder-led sales is the
founder going out and selling on an
ongoing basis, but founder-ledd
everything is founders going out and
doing every functional role within the
organization and leveraging AI to be
more efficient in doing that. That's the
key thesis behind my book, Startup
Tactics.
What I've done recently is I've begun
going down the path of building
companies in just 30 minutes. Can you
build a company and get it off the
ground in 30 minutes? Well, we put that
to the test. And the reality is you
absolutely can. These are the tools that
I've used to do it and make it happen.
The process of starting a company used
to take months if not years, but now it
can be shrunk down to 30 minutes, a day,
a week, what have you. These are the
tools and not to say these are the only
tools, but this is a very powerful uh
mixture of tools that you can use to get
a company off the ground.
Why does this matter? Why does this
matter for everybody here? If we look at
the data, 52% of the companies from the
Fortune 500 from 20 years ago are not on
the list today. Somebody asked me, Paul,
like what did this look like over the
course of time? What was the trend? And
if we go back from 63 to 83, there was a
35% drop off on the Fortune 500. From 83
to 2003, that drop off was 40%. And I
just told you that in the past 20 years,
it was 52%. So the question that I will
pose to you all is what will this drop
off rate be in the next 20 years? What
do you think it'll be?
>> What was that?
>> 80%.
99. Where where's the pessimist in the
room?
I I don't know. None of us know. We
can't see the future. But I feel
confident with my estimate that it's
going to be 70% or more. That's
extremely important for the folks in
this room because we need to find the
ways to move the needle for our
organizations to ensure that they do
still exist and they are still
prominent.
But it's also a question of what will
the startups that are emerging into the
marketplace today and eating away at our
market share, what will they look like.
I also believe that AI is going to put
entrepreneurs out of business.
The entrepreneurs in the room are
sweating now.
I believe that AI will start and run
companies
with humans behind the scenes.
Maybe
I believe there's a world in which we
could have a company that is start
started and run by AI.
People thought I was crazy. So I said,
"Well, there's only one way to find out.
Let's go ask Chhat GBT." This is a yes
or no question. Will there be businesses
in the future that are created and
managed by AI without any humans in the
loop?
If you had to place a bet on a human CEO
who wakes up every morning, takes in
data, reports from the day before, rep
prioritizes what's going to advance the
organization, and then delegates to
their team, or an AI CEO that's been up
all night long taking in data, rep
prioritizing, delegating to other AI
agents. all night,
every hour, every minute, every 30
milliseconds. Who would you place a bet
on? I want to get a read of the room.
Who would bet on the human CEO?
>> What's that?
>> You're betting on one or the other.
>> It's a phenomenal question. We're
betting on revenue.
Who's betting on the human CEO
and who's betting on the AI CEO?
Wow. Over the course of the past 18
months, I've asked this question of many
many people and I've slowly slowly seen
a progression of people betting on the
human CEO to betting on the AI CEO. In
this room, I think maybe uh is the most
forward-looking and the most willing to
bet on the AI CEO. And I think that's
phenomenal. One of the things that we've
done is we've taken this hypothesis that
we can have AI run companies and we
started building just that a software
platform upon which AI agents can create
their own companies. And it is one of
the most fascinating things I have ever
seen in my entire life. The first thing
the AI agents that were running this
company wanted to do, they wanted to go
have meetings with each other. And I
promise you, they learned that from us.
But the reality is is that we now have
AI agents that are out there running
companies that have sold real products
to real people out in the real world.
Real people have paid AI agents money
for products.
We've now had the first unit profitable
sale of a product from an AI agent to a
human. And this I think is really
important as we look at what happens
next as enterprises continue to scale
and how AI companies emerge into the
marketplace. But at the end of the day,
this is the technology is not what's
important. It's about leadership's
understanding of how best to leverage
the technology. And that's what our
research has shown is one of the biggest
threats to established organizations
today.
In many conversations with board members
of Fortune 500 companies, I've asked,
"Tell me, how often does AI come up in
your board meetings?"
And the response to that is, as you
would expect, several times every
meeting.
But what I didn't anticipate was that
nobody on the board actually understands
AI.
They're talking about it, but there's a
lack of literacy. And so we went out and
we collected data from the S&P 500 over
5,000 bless you board members uh over
6,000 uh uh seuite executives and we
analyze all of their earnings calls all
of their social media posts. We analyzed
all of their patent filings. We analyzed
all of their uh uh websites and job
postings. And what we found is that
there is a very clear link from AI
literacy leads to AI advocacy leads to
AI orientation for the company overall
and ultimately leads to AI
implementation. But without that AI
literacy upfront, those large
established organizations are at
significant risk from a leadership
perspective. This data that we've
collected uh led to a variety of key
insights. But the thing that I really
want to emphasize for this group here is
that leadership literacy
is what's driving AI implementation in
these organizations and giving them a
fighting chance at standing up against
these AIdriven entrepreneurial ventures.
Those new companies that are starting
and scaling rapidly. This data this data
is something that we're publishing that
will come out next year. But it's very
clear that there is a need for
leadership teams in established
companies to invest in AI executive
education to upskill their people to
establish the AI advocacy roles and to
align AI and innovation strategy
together because that's where we're
seeing companies make the biggest moves
steps forward. Um as we go through that
these are the questions that I'll leave
with you for reflection. But the number
one thing that I would say because our
companies don't give us tinker time, you
have to start with yourselves to give
our organizations a fighting chance
against these AIdriven entrepreneurial
ventures that are starting and scaling
rapidly. You have to start with
yourself. These are the tools that I'm
using every day to start companies and
to run companies. Um, what I would say
though is there's a definite risk of
what I call tool trial trauma. And
actually, I signed up for a tool, a free
trial, months and months ago, and
apparently that tool created an AI
version of me that's been talking to
people online, and I was just notified
of it by email. And it's super
dystopian, but it is the reality. Um,
there's tons of stuff that you all can
leverage and take with you afterwards.
We have all of the workbooks for startup
tactics, getting businesses off the
ground, or entrepreneurial ventures off
the ground quickly. We also have the AID
opportunity workbook for established
organizations. This workbook helps you
answer the most common question I get,
which is WTF, do I do with AI? There's a
million things we could do, but what
should we do? And a new book that will
be coming out next year called No One
Works Here. This book will uh look at
what it means for an AIdriven
organization to continue to exist. To
wrap up, I want to leave you with one
key takeaway. that is that the global
economy is changing rapidly with
AIdriven enterprises, but we're still in
this dialup era of AI. For us as leaders
at established organizations to make
sure that we have a fighting chance
against these new entrepreneurial
ventures that are starting and scaling
rapidly, we have to make sure that we're
taking one big step back and skating
where the puck is going. Thank you.
[applause]
>> [applause]
>> questions for Paul.
>> Oh, nice.
>> Oh, two arms. Set up. Thank you.
>> Thank Thank you. That was really
interesting. As
>> what's your name?
>> Jill Jones. And wonderful here from
Wales with my colleague Annie. Lots of
other people. Um, super interesting.
We're both business angel investors and
we are overwhelmed with what we should
look for when a company presents to us
and says that they are using AI.
Any
>> if I may, it's probably
>> You're just overwhelmed and you don't
know how to evaluate it.
>> Yes. Yeah, that that's it. I mean,
everybody's saying that they're using
AI, but what should we be looking for?
We're sector agnostic so we're get
seeing so much coming through and we
just don't know what we should be
looking for.
>> Yeah. The thing that I would say is it's
really important that that line of
questioning that you present them with
your your diligence process looks at
where within the organization are they
using it. Are they using it surface
level and they ask chat GPT some things?
Sometimes you remember the scale of one
to five that I presented you with. I
would dig deeper into that and
understand how they're using it and
where they're using it where within the
business which functional areas and the
level of depth to which they are using
it for internal operations. I would also
uh recommend that you think about the
different levels of AI adoption in these
uh emerging companies which is an
individual could be using it or they
could be collaborating in the same tools
together and that drives far better
efficiencies. So I would be looking at
that as well. Where are they using it in
the organization? At what level of depth
and are they using it as a team or are
they using it kind of solo individually?
Thank you, Jill.
>> Hey Paul, Mario here. It traditional
[clears throat] SAS companies build
average solutions for a common problem
that averages out between a a bulk of
people, right? With these solutions
going this fast in two to five years, I
could foresee a a solution that a system
that that creates solutions for the
individual. How do you see the impact of
company building for that? Because at
some point it won't make sense to build
companies to build solutions, right?
Because everyone will have the
capability to do that. How do you
foresee that future?
Uh I think that's a phenomenal question
and one of the things that I would say
on that is it's becoming easier for
people to start companies. It's
requiring far less risk capital and what
that means is we will see more companies
emerging into the marketplace and
competing with each other. That I
believe is a good thing. Why? Because we
will have entrepreneurs who are able to
build products and services solutions to
each of our own personalized problems.
But I don't believe that we will each
build the complex solutions that we need
personally. Some of the things we might,
but there's so many things that are far
more uh uh complex that any one person's
going to sit down and build for
themselves. There's still going to be a
need to create value for others because
you could also look at it and say, well,
we could all still be like, you know,
growing our own um fruits and
vegetables, but that's not the case. Um,
and so I think we're going to have more
personalized solutions built and
delivered to us which will be wonderful
and improve like overall quality of
life.
>> Yeah. Hi Paul, my name is Dan. Um, I
work in the financial services industry
and like one of the immediate questions
that always comes up with any sort of
like proposed AI solution is essentially
customer data privacy and and then you
know immediately there's 20 barriers
thrown up to to whatever that solution
is. Um, how do you think that how do you
think this will be addressed uh in the
future or in the present?
>> A few things. First, I think there's
going to be a growing need for cyber
security professionals, which is why I'm
very excited about the investment that's
being made in the United States to
educate folks at the high school level
in cyber security. I think that's
phenomenal and we need more of that. Um,
one of the other things that I would say
is there's uh a need to have walled kind
of like a walled sandbox, right? where
companies can experiment especially in
the financial services sector. What I
always tell people who work in um you
know financial services, banks, uh all
those sorts of organizations is you
should go buy a little bank and use that
as your sandbox. Why? I think that's
really important so that you know you
can experiment. It's very hard to
experiment in a large organization. Um,
more tactically, one of the things that
I would say is, uh, go use the tools
that are purpose-built for financial
services institutions. One of the
companies that I advise is called Lizer.
Lizer is an AI agent orchestration
platform that is purpose-built for
financial services and insurance
companies, knowing the unique risks that
are presented. And this comes back to
the last question. It's like all right
well if anybody can build products and
start companies we are going to have
more purpose-built products and
solutions for our organizations. I also
think um a lot of financial services
organizations those large organizations
will need to invest in in-house models
in or leveraging open source models on
in-house compute to make sure that that
data doesn't ever leave the
organization.
>> Thank you Paul and always thanks
everybody. [applause]