All right, good morning everybody.
Welcome to the MPG primer. So glad to
see you here so early. Even though it's
disgusting and gloomy outside, it's
going to be bright and fun here today.
Um, it is my pleasure to introduce Kenny
Westerman who's going to be talking
about gene environment interactions, a
genomewide perspective.
Dr. Westerman is a computational
scientist with interest in precision
lifestyle recommendations for the
prevention of cardiomatabolic diseases.
He's an assistant professor at
Massachusetts General Hospital and
Harvard Medical School where he develops
methods and workflows to improve the
discovery and understanding of gene
environment interactions.
His applied projects use these tools in
bioanks and cohort data sets to develop
molecular predictors of personalized
response to diet and other lifestyle
factors. Um, so please ask your
questions throughout. Again, the two
microphones are there. And thank you,
Kenny.
>> Thanks, Michelle.
>> Uh, so yeah, good morning everybody. Uh,
thanks for coming here early earlyish in
the morning to come talk about gene
environment interactions. Uh, as
Michelle mentioned, definitely feel free
to interrupt. This can be super
informal. um as so if you have questions
as I go through uh just I guess raise
your hand or should people use the mics
presumably.
>> Great. Uh so I uh had the pleasure of
giving an MPG primer on gene environment
interactions maybe three years ago or
so. So I pro probably most of you are
non-over overlapping with that audience.
So I'll give a some chunk of that will
be a similar type of introduction and
then I'll go in a different maybe
genomewide perspective as as per the
title rather than thinking about single
variant G bye discovery.
Uh so to start off just as a motivating
example uh actually first raise of hands
who who of you have done any gene
environment interaction analysis or are
are familiar with the the concept?
All right we have like half or so. So
that's that's good. So we'll start off
just to make sure everyone's on the on
the same page here. So phenyl keto is an
example uh of an inborn error of
metabolism particularly it has to do
with mutations in the phenol alanine
hydroxilase gene that convert phenol
alanine amino acid to tyrrosine. Uh and
in uh in the presence of this mutation
this buildup of phenol alanine can lead
to intellectual disability and
developmental problems early in life. Um
this manifests though as a gene diet
interaction or a gene environment
interaction in some senses because uh
the effect of a low phenol alanine diet
or the effect of this genetic mutation
only matter when two things are present.
You need both the mutation and the
presence of a standard not low phenol
alanine diet. And the fact that the
these two effects of the diet and the
genotype are dependent on each other is
kind of what we mean by the gene
environment interaction here and these
can be important. This is part of
newborn screening panels etc.
Uh so to broaden that perspective let me
just get my mouse out here. Uh to
broaden that perspective we can think
about a gene environment interaction
from one of two perspectives. uh one is
a genotype ccentric perspective where
we're thinking about the effect of a
genotype like we typically are maybe
more often at the broad uh what is the
effect of a genotype and then we're
adding in the exposure by saying how
does that effect change depending on
what the exposure level is uh likewise
we can think of it from an exposure
centric perspective what is the effect
of an exposure um and does it depend on
some genotype usually when we test these
in practice these questions
statistically will be an identical
questions in terms of finding an effect
size or a p value but nonetheless it
might change how we think about it
depending on which which of these is
your angle. Uh so and then one more way
to visualize this just to drive this
home
in the left panel here we see that there
are two genotypes here on the x- axis
and uh two environments are the
different colors and we can see that
there's an effect in the left panel of
both genotype and environment but
there's no interaction because these
lines are parallel but the moment these
lines become not parallel that's what
we're looking to detect often in tests
of gene environment interaction uh where
the slope of one depends on the value of
the
uh and this shows up in real data as
well. So this was a a study from 2022
looking at the UK bio bank and
interested in interactions with
polygenic scores. Uh so the x-axis here
is a polygenic score for body mass index
and the prevalence of obesity is on the
y- axis and you see here there's an
effect of the polygenic score on obesity
perhaps not surprising u but there is no
impact of what they used as sort of a
negative control exposure left to
right-handedness as you might expect
that genetic effect is similar and
handedness has no impact on obesity
we can also have an environmental
exposure this is diet related exposure
that has some impact but is not
interacting. So you know obesity tends
to be higher for people who tend to have
high rather than low beef intake in this
example. But again no interaction
because even though these aren't
straight lines they are not in a sense
parallel. I mean they are in a sense
parallel. Uh and then finally they they
show things like here walk pace where
you see that here not only are there
effects of the polygenic score and uh
walking pace but also the slopes of
these two lines are different such that
the genetic effect actually depends on
um the uh people who typically walk more
slowly or more briskly this type of
thing.
So other common concepts in genetics
that we often talk about without
referencing G bye are or can represent G
bye. So we'll often make reference to
variable penetrance of genetic effects.
Of course this can depend on a lot of
factors. It could be other genetic
impacts. It could be a number of things
but one of them would be environmental
factors that are changing whether a
genotype is expressed as a notable
disease. Uh we also think about
stratifying genetic effects. So maybe
you conduct a genomide association study
and then you conduct two more uh
separately in males and females. If you
are then following that up by looking to
see how these effect sizes are different
that would be an example of G bye angle.
And then finally pharmaccogenetics. If
you expand your idea of an environment
to potentially include pharmaceutical
drugs, um the very the fact that a drug
response might be different across
genotypes is yet another example of a
kind of G bye.
Uh so why do we care about finding these
in the first place? Uh first is that if
you find that you might better
understand biology. Uh you might think
you understand the function of a genetic
variant and then if a certain
environment turns that effect on or
turns it off, you might understand that
better. Uh we also have uh from the
genotype perspective, we're interested
in genetic effects. Knowing that that
effect changes by environment could be
quite helpful in uh explaining missing
heritability uh or it might help you
improve the detection of genetic
associations if you can model that
genetic effect more appropriately. And
then from an exposure centrics
perspective, this is more of the
precision medicine angle that says I
have an intervention. It's a behavior, a
lifestyle, a drug and I want to be able
to better predict how a specific
individual is going to respond
differently than just the mean of the
whole population.
Uh and that again that would be this
exposure centric perspective.
So how do we test for these then from a
sort of statistical or analytical sense?
Um in a standard G-W was which some of
many of you are probably familiar with
we're thinking about some you have some
outcome it could be binary continuous
this could be a fairly generalizable uh
approach uh and we'll essentially have
some effect of a genotype term which you
can test variants one by one across the
whole genome and then we add any number
of coariants that you might be
interested in and ultimately we're
scanning across the genome estimating
and testing the significance of that
beta G uh marginal effect term.
So in G bye we essentially take that
same model and we're going to add two
terms. One is the main effect of an
environment that you could soak that up
into the coariantss. Uh and then the the
other the most important one is this
product term where we have a product
between the same genetic variant and the
exposure. And then ultimately we're
typically going to be looking for the
beta G bye in terms of estimating and
testing uh for these models.
So going back to the reasons that we're
doing this in the first place, if we're
trying to understand biology better,
often it's going to be this G bye term.
You know, if we understand this and we
see that interaction, that's going to
help us understand um the ways that the
genetic and exposure effects are
modifying each other teach us about
biology.
From a genotype perspective, we're
thinking kind of together of what the
genetic main effect and the inter
interaction are effect. For example, if
we're trying to map genetic variance and
say we're still just trying to find LOSI
for the interesting trait, but we want
to do so in a more powerful way, it
might in some cases be more powerful to
think about both the genetic main effect
beta G and beta G by E together. Uh and
then likewise from an exposure centric
perspective, although there are fewer
statistical tests that jointly test
these two things together, nonetheless
often we want to be thinking about
exposure effects in a model like this in
a way that says, okay, what's the
standard effect of the exposure and then
how is that modified by genotypes?
Uh we often define environment kind of
broadly in the G bye world. Uh there's a
lot of different terminology that's
thrown around. Some people like
specifically to use gene coariant
interactions because of the fact that
environments can imply specific things.
Uh but often some version of this
whether we call it gene environment,
gene coariant etc. We could be looking
at anything from a sort of proper
environmental variable pollution social
factors uh to lifestyle behavioral kind
of variables, demographic variables and
even physiological traits like BMI. This
can be a little bit of a tricky one
because you can imagine using BMI both
as an outcome as it often is uh as the
actual health trait of interest, but you
can also imagine uh BMI modifying the
the relationship between genetics and
some outcome traits. Uh so that's that's
one to just pay attention to.
So in terms of challenges, we won't uh
talk about addressing all of these here,
but just to kind of get your mind going
as to why even though there's a strong
motivation for why we might be
interested in GIE, um there are some
challenges that are faced in in that we
have to get over in order to analyze
these. One is that there's a even larger
space for exploration than for typical
genetic effects. So it's not just
genomewide genetic variance. Not just
the fact that we could explore any
number of outcomes as we might in G-W
was but we also have an you know
depending on how you define it almost
infinite number of exposures uh that you
might be interested in testing uh in
practice if you you know look at these
numbers in the UK bio bank for example
you might have a thousand plus exposures
that are sort of meaningfully distinct
in some way and might be interesting to
test. So that really raises your
dimensionality your multiple hypothesis
testing etc.
Uh there is also added statistical and
computational complexity in modeling. We
won't talk much about that today, but
there are all sorts of additional
considerations that uh you don't
necessarily have to think about for
standard genetic tests that become
relevant. I'm just listing a couple
here. Do we want to use robust standard
errors? Do we center the exposures? And
if so, how does that change the
interpretation of the different
estimates from this model?
Uh there is a big question of how much G
bye signal there is to find in general.
I think that's one you know that's
motivating because G bye tests can tend
to be lower in power. Uh we think okay
well is it a problem of just needing to
increase and increase the sample size or
you know do we at some point say well
there's nothing to find here etc. So
getting a handle on how much signal
there is in general how much impact it
could have if methods and data sets
improve is an important question.
And then finally, there are some of my
favorite uh G bye discussions are almost
more philosophical. They're the
questions like when is a G bye real.
I'll touch on this like a little bit at
the end, but uh when you the more you
think about the mechanisms that lead to
uh this interaction or this effect
modification. Some of them you might
learn to be able to explain it by
certain nonlinear relationships between
variables, sealing and threshold
effects, this kind of thing. And whether
those are explaining away your G bye or
simply explaining it kind of depends on
your goal and what what you're thinking
about with the analysis.
Uh so as I mentioned a couple years ago
I focused a Juba related primer on
single variant tests. Why are they lower
power often than genetic main effects
and what can we do to improve that
power? And this time I want to focus a
little bit more on this whole genome
kind of approach and the idea of what
variance is explained by G bye. How much
is it? How do we think about that
question?
Uh so specifically I'll we'll have kind
of three subsets to this uh talk related
to that. One is how we quantify the
genome G by contribution to complex
traits in general. Just how do we think
about doing that? Two would be well what
do we find? How much signal is there?
And then a third angle would be how do
polygenic scores tie into this story.
Uh so to tackle the first one here uh
some of you might be familiar with
variance components type methods. This
is a you know a class of statistical
methods where our goal is uh to estimate
basically based on some matrix of
similarity uh between a bunch of
individuals in a data set. uh how does
that type of similarity, whatever it is,
contribute to similarities in the actual
trait of interest. Uh in this case, when
we're looking at something like
heritability or genetics based
explanations based on genetic main
effects of how people are similar, uh
we'll often be constructing this matrix
as a genetic relationship matrix. So
basically, uh each box in this
relatedness matrix is saying how similar
are the genetics, genomewide genetics of
person one and person two. at each point
in that matrix. And then the statistical
sort of inference algorithm there will
ask is basically is this trait y more
similar in people who are more similar
in this matrix. Uh if it's entirely
noise then we'd estimate this
heritability or this h squ term as
approximately zero. And if genetics
perfectly determines the trait then
people will be similar exactly in
proportion to how similar their
genomewide genotypes are. and they'll
that will be detectable uh and we'll
estimate a sort of perfect let's say
100% heritability something like that.
So if we expand this model uh to include
two types of matrices now we can build
this out into something that allows us
to make a similar type of conclusion
about G bye. Uh so here we have this we
introduce this notion of the variance
explained in the presence of that same
main effect heritability type term. uh
we add an additional term for this uh
what we might call the g bye
heritability or I'll I'll refer to it
that way um and here essentially we're
asking the question when we estimate
this h squ the het here in this
particular paper they were using het for
heterogeneity
um and the question here is is the trait
more similar in people whose genomewide
not their genotypes but their gby
product terms are more similar overall
uh conditional on this matrix of how
similar their their genotypes are in
general. Uh but ultimately we kind of
estimate these two things together and
we can get estimates of how much the G
bye contributes to heritability in the
same way that we can do for genetics uh
in a way that's much more standard.
Uh so definitely no need to memorize
this table here but just giving you an
idea that there are a whole bunch of
methods that people have produced in uh
especially the last 10 years but even
before that for thinking about
estimating these things. Um some of them
come from individual level data which
are going to allow maybe slightly more
precise uh and accurate estimates but
they are uh going to be a lot more
computationally intensive typically and
the G bye piece makes it even ratchets
up further the the computational
complexity of these uh and then we have
summary statistics based methods that
are kind of relatives of LD score
regression which some of you might have
heard of uh that you can con uh conduct
a variant by variant genomewide
interaction study and then perform some
imprints afterwards. Yeah,
>> oh yeah. Okay, [laughter] now I can feel
it. [snorts] Uh no actually I I know you
said that you were not going to talk
about you know some complex as aspects
of these gene environment interactions.
Uh it's just out of curiosity actually
for among these different tests if there
is some um some analysis on the scaling
of the exposure. So I know that you know
there could be and actually you were
showing this paper from the group of
andidal before and I know that there was
a poster in a in ASA a couple of weeks
ago where a person from his group was
actually saying that well you know
anything can be a gene by interaction we
just need to find the right scale for it
>> and so I'm just wondering if these
methods account for that to some extent
>> yeah so there are a couple things uh
related to that one is uh this is in the
category of those philosophical things
that I was talking about which I think
are kind of fun and frustrating to think
about. You know, if you can get rid of a
G bye by doing some complex
transformation, you know, have have you
invalidated
the G by is it still a G by is it still
useful etc. So those are kind of
interesting questions in general. Um in
terms of these specific methods, um one
of the very things that differs between
them are things like these assumptions.
Um so you know and one of Andy's at
least one of these is from these
softwares are from Andy's group and you
know they're thinking about uh for
example something that gets a little bit
towards that is the heteroscadasticity
thing and so if you have a trait that uh
for which the environment is associating
with greater variance the higher the
environment gets of course in your trait
that'll relate slightly. Um, a lot of
these I don't know that they're dealing
explicitly with the transformation
itself in the method, but definitely
some of them like Andes are aware of
that issue and will show comparisons.
There'll be at least one slide in a
couple slides away that I have uh
there's a heritability estimate with and
without log transformation of BMI, for
example, and you can see they often they
don't change as much as I would expect,
but uh yeah. Yeah.
And so in addition to these variance
components methods, I wanted to just
briefly give a shout out to a couple of
other ways we can think about it. Even
though I won't talk much about these.
One is the idea uh I mentioned before
that things like a stratified analysis
uh if you are following them up by
comparing the two strata is in essence
an interaction test. Uh just maybe not
done formally.
Um but in and in that respect if you
have an exposure that is either in
discreet discrete buckets or binary then
we can for example calculate the
heritability in two different strata in
males and females compare them that will
get you at least an approximation of an
answer is the heritability different and
that you know that tells you something
about the genomewide uh contribution of
genetic variance to whatever trait
you're interested in. We could look at
genetic correlation uh which actually
this this kind of concept applies a lot
if we think about cross ancestry
portability of polygenic scores things
like that you know the question of
whether effect sizes for genetic
variants are different systematically
between different groups.
So those sort of stratified analyses are
one way we can also think about these
genomide contributions. Another is to
test polygenic scores for PGS bye. uh I
will talk substantially more about this
a little bit later.
So uh based on hopefully that gets some
idea of this question of how we think
about the G by contribution to variance.
So then what do we end up finding in
practice and so here are just a couple
for a couple of those software programs
uh that I mentioned in the in the last
slide or or algorithms I'm just listing
showing some results from their real
data analysis. Um, a lot of these
disclaimer end up being in UK bioank. So
we're a some of these inferences may be
limited to UK bioank but for example
here do I have a how about that? Um, so
to orient us for example okay one of
these papers from 2020 that was
introducing one that was introducing one
of these methods that happens to look at
many environments together. So we're
kind of combining the G bye contribution
not just genomewide but from multiple
environments. um to orient us.
Basically, we have two types of traits
here. The first three rows are our body
mass index. The last three rows are some
version of blood pressure. Uh and sort
of consistent with what we know, these
are showing standard sort of genetic
main effect heritabilities in the realm
of something like 25%.
Uh when we look at the G bye
contributions to heritability, these are
actually a little bit higher than we
maybe tend to find, but they were
reporting across multiple exposures
things in the realm of something like
10% additional variance explained beyond
that 25. Um so this is closer to the
upper bound of often what's reported.
Still substantially lower than genetic
main effects, but uh meaningful
contribution to the trade itself. Uh if
you look in the bottom left here, this
was another paper from a couple years
ago. Uh this monster LM, the names of
these are great. Uh this one is looking
at specifically wasted ratio as an
exposure. As I mentioned, these
atyposity traits can sometimes be used
as exposures, not just outcomes. Uh and
you see they're showing for a whole
bunch of different types of bloodbased
traits here. A lot of these red are the
G genetic heritabilities. These are
again in the realm kind of 20 30% 40% as
we might be familiar with for a lot of
complex trait heritabilities. Uh and
then the blue here are the interactions.
So a lot of them are significantly
nonzero but we're more in the realm of
something like 3% 5% etc. Um this was a
paper from just last year that was
looking specifically at smoking
interactions. uh and they had an an
interesting way although they did report
sort of raw heritabilities if you will
they also thought it would be
interesting to report a ratio of
variance explained by G by smoking
interactions for each of these outcomes
as a uh fraction of the overall variance
explained uh this sort of H squared in
general. So interestingly here when we
quantify it in that way uh you can see
that we're looking at
uh fairly small contributions to
variance explained relative to the
overall heritability. These are
something between I don't know you know
2% 5% 10% of the standard heritability
uh not of the overall trait variance.
Uh does that make sense that
distinction?
Yeah,
>> that one. Yeah, we c we could talk about
that after. This is kind of an artifact
that sometimes shows up in some subset
of variance estimation traits, but uh
yes, it is it is odd. I agree, but we
can talk about that later. Yeah.
>> Oh, yeah.
um some of those measurements that are
might not be stable and they're only
measured once, you know, how do how do
they correct for that or try to deal
with that?
>> So, one way to answer this without
calling out any of these particular
papers. I truly have I'm I'm not
thinking about any of them in
particular. often these are genetics
people doing these studies and they
don't care that much about the exposure
because they're trying to introduce a
method not necessarily
uh you know find the definitive genetic
architecture of smoking interactions
whatever it might be. So um part of the
answer is they sometimes don't we'll
well you know do you this will be one
final part of the analysis in a paper
and they do sort of some cursory okay
this is how we're going to define
smoking go I'm guilty of doing this
myself for sure uh but I think what
you're pointing to is definitely right
and it is contributing to maybe why some
of these look like they're smaller
contributions to variance than there
might be in reality there are a couple
reasons for that but um The exposure
measurement is a huge one that I focused
a little more than the last time I gave
a primer on this, but it's it's a super
important thing. Essentially, in G bye
work, we have all the same
traditional epidemiology
limitations for these exposure
definitions, how we think about them,
whether there's reverse causation, etc.
on top of then the complexity of the
genetics and their the interaction
modeling. But so I they'll vary
obviously in how they process but that's
it's a great point.
Uh okay and this one sorry I wasn't able
to find a non grainy image and took too
long trying to find one but uh this was
one of the summary statistics based
papers and this this is another one that
did look at variance explained by G bye
in a way that aggregated over multiple
exposures. Um so you know whereas these
when we were looking for smoking again
uh something like 5% of an already you
know maybe 20 or 25%
heritability that's a pretty these are
pretty small numbers in this paper on
the right for example but that's only
one exposure. So we expect a little bit
higher contributions to variance when we
uh look at the sort of overall burden
over multiple exposures. Um here uh the
way they're being depicted is in the
blue are this narrow sort of narrow
sense uh main effect genetic
heritability and in the red are the
interaction contributions on top of
that. And then we can see for this paper
for example for type two diabetes these
six exposures together uh explained in
their estimation almost in this case
almost as much variability in the
interaction as the main effect. Most of
these the interaction is quite a bit
smaller but we're dealing with uh
contributions to variance of uh you know
things in the realm of maybe two 2% 4%
5% things like that.
Uh so one important caveat for all of
this as we're thinking about the
relative contribution of genetic main
effects and interaction effects is that
I titled it here interactions may
masquerade as genetic effects. Another
way to think about that is we've already
found a lot of the interactions without
knowing it by doing genetic main effect
tests. Um so this is some uh some
simulations that were done from a a 2016
paper. The idea was they again this is a
purely simulation. So we know the right
answer. Uh they they simulated some
exposure with a mean that's not zero
which is kind of a key nuance of this.
Uh but if you simulate some exposure and
then you simulate an outcome that has an
effect that's purely driven by G bye
there's no exposure main effect there's
no genetic effect independent of the
exposure it's just a G bye
and then uh depending on the riskil
frequency you sort of test genetic
variance then for uh kind of decomposing
how much variance is explained by G by V
and G by Even
though this again the ground truth is
that G by E is what this trait is
determined by. Uh the dark blue here is
the G bye. We're going to attribute very
very little. The model in practice is
going to attribute almost none of this
variance to G by E and it's going to
attribute most of it to G, some of it
depending on the risk frequency to E. Um
this can take a little bit to wrap one's
head around. I know it took me a long
time initially to sort of think through
some of this, but the main takeaway at
the moment is that
by being aware of this fact, we can kind
of acknowledge that some G bye effects
or effects that really are G bye in in
the sort of underlying truth of how
biology works or the data gener
generating mechanism will show up as
genetic main effects or they'll show up
in a way that
makes us underestimate how much
contribution G bye interactions in the
sort of causal truth have to uh the the
production of these traits. And this
does ultimately matter to try to step
towards disentangling this because uh
again it has implications for example in
a precision medicine context. How much
do you expect to be able to change
someone's genetic predisposition by
changing an environmental exposure? If
we have vastly underestimated we might
think that potential impact is tiny when
it might actually be quite quite large.
>> Yeah.
>> Is it true that thinking about the last
slide where you have the T2 and the
contribution of all exposures to gen uh
G bye expos right where you have
basically half and half for you know
just genetics and and G bye. Uh do you
think that if we have infinite sample
size and infinite exposures measures
that that would be all real?
>> Um I don't think it would be. I think it
there's some contribution that you just
expect to be largely genetic and there
are some arguments that I don't fully
understand to be honest uh that
arguments that nature or selection will
tend to want linearity.
I don't again I I will have to get back
to you or we can discuss this later in
terms of thinking about that question
but there are some sort of theoretical
arguments like that that suggest um that
there's going to be some basis where
just there will be some genetic effects
that are that are not going to be uh
fully modifiable but it's a good point
and it is the way the the seed that I'm
trying to plant and how we're thinking
you know that both um with better not
just more exposures but also better
measured exposures
that not only does the red bar go
higher, but maybe it even invades, if
we've measured it better, maybe it
invades a little of the blue space here,
that kind of thing.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, sorry. So, I'm like here. Thanks.
>> So, about the gene bye part. So uh I'm
wondering did you further I don't know
classify the G bye facts about their I
don't know categories for example uh
most uh proportion of the G by effect
may be uh attributed to those um
genotypes that resid in I don't know
lower heritable genes compared to those
highly heritable genes I don't know
>> and by heritable there do you in um the
genes that are contributing to the main
effect the standard heritability.
>> Yeah. For example, probably for some
highly heritable genes is uh uh less
impossible to identify gene by effect
that could contribute to I don't know
variance explanation. But for those uh
genotype that resid in lower habitable
bore genes that may be more impossible
or highly probable to identify effects
for the target trait things like that.
>> So just confirming you're you're
invoking the idea that if there's a
genetic main effect at a gene level or a
variant level we're more likely to find
that that participates in a GE. Is that
what Yeah. Um that that is something
that we find. Um I'll have a kind of one
slide on it in a little bit, but yes, uh
that more tends to be the case rather
than not. Yeah.
Um okay so to sort of t summarize some
of this some of these empirical results
from these variance components
approaches um as some of you are
probably already familiar standard snip
heritabilities uh just genetic main
effect prediction are often very
consistently for complex traits in the
realm of something like 20 to 30 plus
percent for traits like anthropometric
things height easily more
straightforwardly measured highly
genetic they can reach greater than much
greater than 50% sometimes
um when we compare that to G by
heritabilities as currently measured
using currently methods current methods
etc. In terms of overall variance
explained we tend to be finding things
when they are significant in the realm
of something like 1 to 10% uh and also
another way of thinking about that would
be up to uh maybe 10% or so of standard
sniper heritability.
We also, as we've been discussing a
little bit, you might expect more signal
uh when combining G by contributions
from multiple exposures and we could uh
to the question from before, we could
imagine stacking more and more and
potentially accumulating additional
variants explained. Um so some caveats
to this. First, these upper limits are
not as hard as those for genetic main
effects. This is basically I won't spend
more time on this because we were just
uh discussing it but uh there is sort of
more hope for increasing this than with
just uh more targeted analysis than
improved methods might be expected to
incre increase something like a genetic
main effect heritability. Um true G by
effects might be disguised as a genetic
main effect. That's what we were just
talking about where uh maybe there are
true underlying G by effects that look
like their genetic main effects when we
do the actual analysis. Uh and then
finally just a reinforcement this is
true uh also in uh most genetics work
but variance explained is not the same
as biomedical value. Uh when there is
high variance explained it matters both
how strong the effects of genetic
variants are but also how prevalent they
are. We're thinking about evolution,
selection, uh, and the fact that, uh,
ability to intervene on something, uh,
might be different depending on the
biological mechanisms underlying any
given locus's action, that sort of
thing.
Uh, so then finally to wrap up this
final point here, what is the role of
polygenic scores? So when we're talking
about genomewide approaches, obviously
polygenic scores are something that come
to a lot of people's minds and they're
something that we've worked on a little
bit. So polygenic scores, just to make
sure everyone's on the same page, these
are maximizing signal by aggregating
across genetic variant effects
genomewide.
Um the concept here is that we could
imagine developing a polygenic score as
we otherwise might that's meant for
prediction but then test it for PGS by
environment interaction. And unlike a
variance component approaches, these can
these are valuable beyond those because
they don't just allow us to quantify
okay this is how much it matters but you
also get an individual level estimate of
what is this polygenic score and if that
predicts if that modifies the expected
response to an exposure and environment.
you could tell that individual here's
how much you know in in a personalized
way here's how much that your outcome is
expected to change upon modifying the
exposure.
Uh so a basic approach would be to
create a standard polygenic score test
it for interaction. Um this was a paper
from uh 2012 that made a little bit of a
splash and they were looking at these
different quartiles of a body mass index
polygenic score and these are then the
different colors. uh for example in the
nurse's health study on the the left set
of bars and what they're showing on the
y- axis axis is not BMI itself or not a
mean but rather the effect size of sugar
sweetened beverage intake on BMI and so
what they were seeing is that depending
the higher one's standard genetic
predisposition to higher BMI was the
greater impact a BMI increasing exposure
like sugar sweetened beverages had on
that outcome. Uh and so there was some
initial excitement from approaches like
this as to whether this could apply in a
lot of cases, whether polygenic scores
can just allow us to much more
powerfully and strongly detect G bye. Um
but not only does that not work as well
in many cases, but it's maybe
theoretically not the best way. If we're
trying to find a polygenic score that
interacts with an environment, we might
want to build that polygenic score in a
way that's slightly different if your
ultimate goal is interaction than if
your ultimate goal is prediction. Um, I
won't spend too much time on this here
just for overall time reasons, but this
was a a paper of ours recently that was
looking at if you
run different types of genomewide
studies, you can run a standard GWAS or
you can run an interaction focused G-W
was or a variance focused G-W was etc.
You have different types of betas that
you can aggregate over when building
your polygenic score. And these
different approaches might get you an
ultimate score that's more effective at
detecting interruption, something like
that.
And so this is getting a little bit to
the question from before which was uh
the question was something like well you
know are in genes or lossi that have
main effects are we expecting to find
interactions? Um, another way to put
that here are are G byes likely to be
found in novel LOSI or are they in
established LOSI for the trait in
question? Um, this was something that we
at least poked into a little bit in our
uh paper and at least in a preliminary
sense, what we tended to find just as an
overall takeaway was that
[clears throat] often it seems like this
genomewide signature of G bye is a is
not distinct. we're not necessarily
discovering new lossi that are
interacting but it seems to be some
targeted subset of the overall genetic
architecture. Um so if you know if there
are 20 lossi that affect here in this
particular study that affect the liver
stress biioarker alt um then maybe 10 of
those are are particularly interesting
for interaction with BMI. uh and that so
a lot of these genomewide discovery of
what LOSI are are participating
interaction consists of you could
conceive of that process as more like
we're trying to find the right subset of
the in this case alt genetic
architecture
um and then one final way we can think
about uh increasing or adding
sophistication to some of these
polygenic scores for approaches if we
want to creep back from a full only
genomewide approach but get a little bit
more mechanism involved. uh this was an
approach that's been taken by a couple
of studies but I'm I'm highlighting here
from this Godderman 2025 paper uh where
they started with a genomwide set of
genomewide significant snips uh 204
snips from a colorectile cancer GWAS and
said instead of testing that for
interaction we're going to test or in
addition to testing that for interaction
we're going to find a pathway database
this panther pathway database that has
lists of genes that belong to certain
pathways um if you map the pathway to
genes and then genes to a bunch of
variants kind of physically near them in
genomic position. Uh you can then create
new polygenic scores from subsets of
these 204 snips. Uh and then you create
a whole bunch of those maybe it's 50 100
plus test each of them for interaction
and that might be a more powerful way
and a more biologically specific way to
find interactions. uh in this particular
case uh they were able to find for
example that in the blue line here uh
this was one particular pathway specific
polygenic score this related to TGF beta
um pathway activity and they found that
genetic variance in this pathway a sort
of a polygenic score focused on that was
able to associate with a steady decrease
in the effect size of non non-steroidal
and anti-inflammatory drug use on
colorectal cancer risk
uh in a sort of step-wise way, the
higher this genetic predisposition.
Again, the y-axis here is an effect, not
a mean or a proportion. Um, and this was
a stronger interaction, a stronger
effect modification in blue in that
pathway specific effect than the
genomewide score was in green there.
Uh, and I had a couple pieces of bonus
material. I'll show one of them just for
for time reasons. This was an
interesting uh this is coming back then
to what I mentioned about the little bit
of philosophy uh that's that's involved
here. So, uh, I was talking with a
colleague a couple years ago, uh, and I
think she made some provocative
statements like, uh, do G byes really
exist or something something of that
nature. And as we were talking through
this, it kind of a a review was born.
Uh, and so we were kind of cataloging a
series of what we ended up calling
phenomena where, you know, what are sort
of mechanisms that can lead to the
ability to detect a statistical G bye.
And this was one of just to give you a
flavor of one of them here. If we have
correlation between a gene and an
environment or genetic variant in an
environment shown here combined with
nonlinearity and a relationship between
that environment and some continuous
risk factor or nonlinearity even kind of
comes baked into binary outcomes. Um but
you can see that this is sort of a a
subtly nonstraight line here in this ey
slope. um that can actually produce the
appearance of a G bye where now we're
saying if you actually now stratify by
genotype and you look at the
relationship between this simulated
exposure and outcome these lines are
subtly not parallel you could imagine
more extreme versions of this um but
this was one example of how okay if gene
is correlated with environment and
environment is nonlinearly correlated
with the outcome we can detect G by is
that is it a real
you know, depending on how you're
thinking about it and what you're trying
to discover, it might be real. This
might have the same level of medical
implications
as something else, but it might not
teach us about the effect of this
genetic variant as much as we thought.
So, this is kind of just getting your
mind jogged about that that issue a
little bit. I'm
>> going to skip this here for time and
just summarize. Uh so G by E analysis uh
as I've mentioned can be a critical
building block for not just biological
understanding when we're trying to just
nail down where are these interactions
and what are the lossi uh but also
informing personalized medicine if we
take a sort of overall genetic
prediction of how someone is going to
respond to an environment. Um, these
genomewide approaches that I've been
talking about can allow us to both
understand where there is locus or
pathway specific signal to pursue, what
environments are more interesting than
others because they explain more
variance. This is a good place to start
to look to improve exposure definitions
etc. Um, they also allow us to maximize
power to detect this heterogeneity in
the exposure outcome relationship in the
same way that polygenic scores and
genomwide approaches do for genetic main
effects. Um, progress continues to be
made. uh I'm trying to do my part in
contributing to it, but a lot of people
are are working on things like GIE
specific polygenic scores, pathway
specific approaches uh and creative
approaches to exposure definition. So
happy to talk through any more of this.
Uh thanks for your attention.
>> Thank you. Questions? Great.
>> Thanks for the beautiful talk. Yeah. On
this philosophical stuff, I mean, it
seems like like you know the old adage
of all models are wrong and some are
useful and all we're doing here is like
making models and seeing what the
outputs are. So, I don't know. I just I
just feel like in this field there's a
like there's a ground truth that we're
trying to get to is like the philosophy.
Whereas it seems like there maybe there
are some useful models we can build and
then everything that we are going to be
able to say is going to relate to those
models. So let's get very specific about
like what models are we building and why
type thing. I wonder what your reactions
are to that. I I totally agree and I
think that's that's one of the things in
that uh in that review where we were
talking about these different phenomena
you know there's a section at the end
where uh a couple people had read an
initial draft of the manuscript and had
said
okay can you we want a final section
that says which of these phenomena are
mean it's a real GIE versus a spurious
and as we tried to think like we can't
answer it's not a question you can
answer because some of these truly
depend on your uh your scientific
question. And so would one of the the
calls there in that paper was basically
just to say um to call for more clarity
in the in at the outset of a G bye
containing study to say we're looking
for precision medicine application if we
detect you know if our outcome of
interest is LDL cholesterol and this is
measured and clinically relevant on the
raw scale on which it is measured in
milligrams per deciliter uh and we're
thinking about it in term we're always
thinking about it in terms of percentage
changes or we're always thinking about
in terms of um when you take a statin, a
doctor is going to think that you'll go
down by 20 milligrams per deciliter.
Will that be different by people? And if
there's nonlinearity or nonhomogeneity
in that, okay, maybe that's a clinical
example where we care whether we care if
that's going to happen somewhat
regardless of the actual mechanism.
Which of these phenomena are at play
versus, you know, sometimes we might
actually be thinking, well, we need
better genetic discovery. We're doing a
G-W was, but we want to incorporate
interaction effects because we think
there might be effect modification
there. You really want to make sure
If the mechanism is genetic variant
correlating with exposure and that
nonlinearity impacting the outcome,
you haven't found what you're looking
for if you're trying to map genetic
lossi related to some trait because
there's no causal relationship between
the genotype and the the trait of
interest. So if if that makes a little
sense and at least how I'd start to
approach thinking about it.
>> Yeah. And I'd wonder what you mean by
causal. But but another thought I guess
um this way of thinking might suggest
that some of the interesting like new
biology would come by working with
different types of people who might have
different use cases and different things
that they're interested in modeling. And
I wonder if if you've experienced that
like working with different people
coming from a different disciplinary
background or something might spur new
directions or something. I I I mean I
definitely this is a very broad sense
but I think even working with clinicians
for example is it was a big eye openener
for me to then you know think about okay
how are they thinking about the value of
effect heterogeneity like this I'm
excited because I have a p value of you
know 0.006 O6 or something and they're
saying well okay am I going to treat
someone differently uh and so that you
know the effect sizes etc are different.
Yeah, thanks.
>> Okay, I think we have time for one or
two more questions. Go ahead.
>> Just on on the same on the same note, I
I was just thinking actually, so I know
you say that biomedical is not the same
than heritability. you know that we
cannot say that more heritability
necessarily is more beneficial for the
clinics
>> but if you can I don't know if the paper
that you were talking about this
partition uh polygenic scores by
pathways actually are able to show that
by aggregating all of those you can
explain more heritability than just
using the classic uh state-of-the-art
polygenic risk score uh but I mean I
guess that if you can say that you can
globally explain more heritability by
using this uh PRS S times E um
uh components then I guess that there
could be you know big value even for the
clinics uh in that regard.
>> Yeah. Um I think so a couple things one
uh we have a similar I was showing a
paper from another group but we we have
also done a similar study to that create
pathway specific polygenic scores and
then test them for interaction. In that
one, we did do a sort of likelihood
ratio test to say if you put all these
interactions in, do they explain more
variance than just a polygenic score by
E and they do quite substantially so
when you combine them all together at
least in our hands with one particular
empirical example.
So that was part of it and I'm already
forgetting the second half of the
question. No, I guess it's more about,
you know, the variance explain versus
biomedical utility uh of it. But I guess
you know like you could totally say that
uh if you can explain more variance then
to some degree if there is the right
route it's going to have some some
utility at the at the clinic level. Uh
yes and oh that's the last thing I was
going to say is I think I definitely
agree and I think there are some people
thinking about this and even if we can
squeeze out you know an extra
performance improves by 10% 20% of
standard polygenic scores that could be
good I think the one tricky thing comes
exposure measurement becomes a whole
bigger whole much bigger thing there of
course standardization of genotypes is
one thing standardization of uh the you
know what people are eating that what
environment they're exposed to could
become tricky there but not an
unsurmountable insurmountable obstacle.
Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. Thanks um so much for your talk. I
think we had a great discussion and so
everyone can move to the seminar at
9:30. But thank you.