okay our next speaker we're very excited
to have Alexandra hi yeah so thank you
so much hi everyone I'm Alexandra I'm a
grad student here in the department and
I'm going to talk to you today about new
constructions of somewhat homomorphic
encryption uh and this is Joint work
with my adviser Henry and with Yale and
venod okay so the classic problem solved
by cryptography is that of secure
communication so in this problem my
friend and I want to communicate but we
can only talk over some public or
insecure Network and the way
cryptography solves this problem is by
letting me sample an encryption key that
I can share with my friend and now we
can send encrypted pieces of information
over this network so that each of us can
decrypt the packets and see what the
information is but to anyone who's just
e dropping on our messages they have no
idea what we're saying a downside here
though is that F this fundamentally
requires trusting the recipient so here
for example I trust my friend but this
isn't always want what we want to do in
the real world so in the real world
today we're sending our personal data
all over the place to many many
recipients and it really only takes one
of them to be breached compromised or
malicious for our data to fall into the
wrong
hands and so what we can do is we can
ask whether we can ask for more from
cryptography and specifically whether we
can protect our data not just during
communication but even during
computation uh and so cryptographers
have formalized this notion of that as
that of homomorphic encryption so the
idea here is that in a homomorphic
encryption scheme anyone can compute
directly on encrypted data without ever
decrypting it and without ever learning
what the underlying data is so to be a
little bit more precise here again I'm
going to sample a secret encryption key
and now I can encrypt any values of my
choosing so here I'm encrypting these
values X1 through XM and I can publish
them in a way that any recipient so here
for example This Server can apply a
function directly to the encrypted data
without ever decrypting and without ever
learning my messages so here for example
the server is going to produce the
encryption of f applied to X1 through
XM so to be just a little more formal uh
we say an encryption scheme is
homomorphic if it satisfies three
properties so first of all if our
encryption scheme is correct which
really just means that given the secret
key I can decrypt the server's message
here and I'm correctly going to recover
F apply to X1 through XM with good
probability so second we need our
encryption scheme to be secure which
means that anyone who does not have my
secret key has no idea what the messages
are that these Cipher texts encrypt and
finally we want our encryption scheme to
be compact which really just means that
the bit length of all of our Cipher
texts here should be a fixed parameter
and really should not grow with the
function f that we're applying to them
uh and really the intuition for this
last requirement here is that what this
protocol here is doing is it's sort of
Outsourcing the computation of f to the
server so it had better be that the
communication that we're incurring is
smaller than if the server were just to
send us F in the first place so really
this compactness here captures what we
mean to actually compute on the
encrypted
data okay uh and so a long and very
fruitful line of work has shown that if
we have homomorphic encryption then we
can use this to build a whole Suite of
privacy preserving applications so for
example you could imagine that the
function f here is a machine learning
model uh and so we can have our user
Make private queries to the machine
learning model without revealing what
she's querying the model on or similarly
you could imagine F here to be web
search or like the Google functionality
and then in that setting you can use
this to build a private search engine
that never actually learns what its
users are searching
for okay so this is homomorphic
encryption uh and so sort of as the
definition implies homomorphic
encryption exists along a gradient
depending on what types of functions we
can actually apply to encrypted data so
at the very bottom here I have classic
private key encryption which is not
homomorphic so we can't perform any
computations on encrypted data then
above this we have linearly homomorphic
encryption which can evaluate only
linear functions so perform only
additions on encrypted data and then at
the very top here most powerful we have
fully homomorphic encryption uh which
can evaluate any function on encrypted
data so really uh for the point of this
for the purposes of this talk you should
think of this as evaluating any number
of additions and any number of
multiplications on Cipher texts and so
really in between linearly homomorphic
encryption and fully homomorphic
encryption there's a huge range uh
depending on how many multiplications
your scheme can support so really how
expressive the function classes that it
can handle uh and we generally refer to
this as somewhat homomorphic
encryption okay so what do we have today
well the classic encryption schemes that
we use every day to protect our
communication on the internet are not
homomorphic but fortunately we can do
better uh and so specifically the number
theoretic cryptography of the 1980s
gives us a whole Suite of linearly
homomorphic in Crypt schemes and a
really beautiful line of work showed
that you can actually boost these
schemes to compute some nonlinear
functions so specifically to compute
branching programs of a certain type on
encrypted
data then in 2005 we learned that using
cryptographic pairings you can compute
any number of additions and one
multiplication on encrypted data so this
here is really degree 2
polinomial and then in 2009 there was a
huge breakthrough in cryptography that
showed that using lates we can actually
get all the way to fully homomorphic
encryption and today we also know how to
get there using the Machinery of
indistinguishability
obfuscation so really this is the
landscape of homomorphic encryption
today so if we want to compute somewhat
complex functions uh and nonlinear
functions on encrypted data we really
only have a few ways of getting there
and for the schemes on the right here
you should think of them as relatively
heavy cryptographic machinery that you
know like rockets can be somewhat
expensive and so this talk is going to
be about uh new construction of somewhat
homomorphic encryption uh and
specifically we're going to build an
encryption scheme that lets us compute a
fixed and bounded number of
multiplications followed by many
additions on encrypted data and so to
build this scheme we're going to combine
two tools so first we're going to take a
linearly homomorphic encryption scheme
so this is the balloon here given to us
by number theoretic cryptography and
we're going to show how to lift a
linearly homomorphic encryption scheme
into a somewhat homomorphic one by using
just one additional assumption and this
assumption here on its own uh just gives
us private key encryption so on its own
it has no homomorphism but when we put
these two relatively simple tools
together we get something that's much
more
powerful and so that's exactly what this
talk is going to be about so we're going
to see how we can combine this sparse
learning pars with noise assumption
which is is the assumption that only
gives us private key encryption with a
linearly homomorphic encryption scheme
to build somewhat homomorphic encryption
uh and so specifically the somewhat
homomorphic encryption that we'll build
today is such that for any a priori
fixed parameter L that's at most
polinomial in our security parameter
we're going to be able to perform just
slightly less than logl multiplications
followed by logl additions on encrypted
data okay and so let's begin by
discussing this sparse LPN
assumption so the sparse learning
parities with noise assumption is based
on the following problem so say I sample
some random Matrix a that's sparse so
specifically every row is just going to
have very few nonzero entries and then I
sample some dense and random Vector s
say have Dimension n and some error
Vector e and specifically I'm going to
sample these errors so that most of them
are zero but with some very small
probability so here 1 over root n each
error is going to be completely random
and so now what I'm going to do is I'm
going to publish a and I'm going to
publish a * S Plus e and I'm going to
ask you can you distinguish this from
just a random a and a truly random
Vector
B and it turns out to the best of our
knowledge the answer here is actually no
so this is a hard problem we don't have
any efficient algorithms for
distinguishing between these two
distributions uh and in fact this is to
the hardness of random constraint
satisfaction problems and other problems
in average case
complexity okay so first of all as
scientists here we might be sad right
this is a hard problem that we don't
know how to solve but as cryptographers
we can be happy because we're going to
use this encryption scheme to build or
we're going to use the hardness of this
problem to build encryption schemes uh
and specifically today we're going to
use it to build a somewhat homomorphic
encryption scheme and so the way we're
going to build this scheme is using two
key design steps so in a first step
we're going to use this sparse alpan
assumption to construct an encryption
scheme that's going to let us perform a
bounded number of homomorphic additions
and
multiplications so this this already
sounds great right this is what we
wanted to construct but this is going to
have a huge caveat which is that our
Cipher texts are going to be huge so
really our scheme is not going to be
Compact and it's not going to meet our
definition of homomorphic
encryption but it's still going to have
one nice property which is that to
decrypt these Cipher text we're only
going to need to apply a linear function
so decryption here is only going to
require
additions uh and so then in a second
step what we're going to do is we're
going to use a linearly homomorphic
encryption scheme so this is one that
can perform only additions in a compact
way on encrypted data to shrink down the
cipher text in our original scheme and
so now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to step through each of these two ideas
in much more
detail so specifically our goal in this
work is going to be to build an
encryption scheme that meets the
following properties so what we would
like is for our Cipher texts to be
matrices and for our server who here is
going to apply some function f to the
cipher text to operate as follows so if
our server wants to uh add two encrypted
values it should just have to add the
corresponding Cipher text matrices and
if our server wants to multiply two
encrypted values it should just have to
multiply the corresponding Cipher text
matrices so for the cryptographers in
the audience this should really remind
you of the Gentry sah High waters's
fully homomorphic encryption scheme from
lates which here we're trying to port to
the setting of code-based encryption
with the sparse LPN
assumption uh and I'll introduce one
more requirement which is that we'd like
our decryption function to be linear so
what this means is that when our user
gets back this big Cipher Tech CF here
it should just need to apply a linear
function to it so do some additions in
order to get back the underlying
encrypted
message okay so how are we going to do
this well the key idea is going to be
the following so as our secret key we're
going to sample a random Vector s and
this should sort of remind you of the S
Vector in the sparse alpan
assumption and then to encrypt any value
x what we're going to do is we're going
to build a cipher text that's a sparse
Matrix and that has the following
special special structure so we're going
to have our encrypted value X be sort of
a noisy igen value of this Matrix where
the corresponding IG Vector just depends
on the secret key so let me be a little
more precise what I mean here is that if
I have my Cipher text Matrix C and I'm
going to multiply by this igen Vector
which here will be minus s and then a
one what I'd like is to get back roughly
the underlying encrypted value X again
multiplied by the same igen Vector so
this is what it means for X to be an IG
value of the Matrix C and when I say
noisy here is uh I just mean that I'll
be okay with this equation here being
corrupted in a couple of locations as
long as it holds like
mostly okay so first of all you might
ask how are we going to do this how can
we H inject this noisy igen value into a
matrix and the idea is going to be
roughly to do the following so to build
the cipher text Matrix what we're going
to do is we're going to sample a random
a matrix uh we're going to sample a
random error vector and then as our
Cipher text we're just going to publish
the a matrix concatenated with one more
column which is going to be a * S Plus
the errors plus our message times some
function of the secret key so really
here we see that what the sparse LPN
assumption tells us is that a * S Plus e
looks random so this Cipher text here
really is hiding the message that we
embedded into it but if you stare at it
for a while you can see that it actually
satisfies this noisy igen value
equation okay so what I argued so far is
that we can actually build Cipher Tex of
this form and now you might wonder why
is this useful why do we want this
special structure and the reason really
is because it's going to let us perform
these homomorphic
operations so specifically to add two
encrypted values what we're going to do
is we're just going to add the
corresponding Cipher Tex matrices and
what we see is that we if we add two
matrices that have the same igen Vector
this has the effect of just adding their
igen values so really what we get out of
here is an encryption of the sum of the
underlying
messages and in exactly the same way we
can multiply Cipher texts so
specifically if we multiply two matrices
what we get out here is a matrix whose
igen value is the product of the
underlying I values so really by
multiplying two matrices we get out a
cipher text that encrypts the product of
their two
messages uh and last but not least I
said we wanted decryption to be linear
and again this here follows by this same
uh blue equation so specifically to
decrypt a cipher text all we need to do
is to multiply by this secret Vector
which has the negative s in a one and
what this gives us is the message
multiplied by the same Vector so we can
then check whether the underlying
encrypted value was a zero or a
one okay so that
yeah linear right it's linear with noise
linear with
noise exactly well so for our purposes
it's going to be linear because we're
just going to look at one location in
this equation and we're going to just
guess that it has no noise but you're
totally right you could do some error
correction here like you could compute
some majority function but what we just
won't do that for our purposes so
far great okay so now zooming out again
we have this scheme our Cipher Tex are
these sparse matrices our server can
compute on them by just adding these
matrices and multiplying these mat icies
and when we do this they get somewhat
less sparse and the errors in the
underlying equation are going to
propagate somewhat but if we sit down
and analyze this we see that if we have
our initial Matrix Dimension be n byn
and if we have our initial error rate be
something like 1/ root n then we get a
scheme that actually can perform just
slightly less than login multiplications
and just slightly less than root and
additions and we'll still be able to
decrypt correctly
okay so so far this seems great right we
can just pick our parameter n to be as
big as we would like to support as many
operations as we would like on these
Cipher
texts unfortunately though what I just
said should be a huge red flag to you
because and here is also the dimension
of our Cipher texts so what I said is
that we have to make our Cipher texts
bigger if we want to compute on them
more and so in fact we have a scheme
that's not at all compact uh and it
turns out our server would always be
better off just sending a description of
the function f to the user instead of
operating on these big Cipher texts
whose uh whose size must be bigger than
the description of F and then sending
back another big Cipher deex again whose
size is bigger than just the description
of
f okay uh so that's the bad news but the
good news is we've only used one of our
two ingredients here and we're going to
try and save this using linearly
homomorphic
encryption and so specifically what we
have right now is a scheme where we have
these big bulky sparse LPN Cipher texts
that our server can compute on right so
our server can go from an input Cipher
text evaluate some function on it to get
an output Cipher text that now encrypts
the function applied to the data and
really what we would like is a way for
our server to translate this bulky
output Cipher text into a new Cipher
text from a compact and small encryption
scheme that encrypts the same message
right this would be great if we could
just shrink our big Cipher texts into a
much smaller one from a different scheme
and the way we're going to do this is
taking advantage of
homomorphism so specifically what we
know is that our green sparse LPN Cipher
text here has a linear decryption
function and really decryption is just a
function so we can homomorphically apply
this function to this Cipher text and
since it's a linear function we know
that this only requires performing
additions so what we could do here is we
can take the secret key of our sparse
LPN scheme and we can encrypt it under a
linearly homomorphic scheme and then
under this scheme we can homomorphically
run our decryption function and so what
this is going to give us uh so what the
decryption function does is it takes
this big Cipher text and outputs the
underlying encrypted message so if we
run this under encryption what we get
out is an encryption of the underlying
encrypted message so really we've
managed to translate from this scheme
with the bulky Cipher text to the scheme
with the small Cipher text just taking
advantage of
homomorphism and I should say this idea
of sort of decrypting under encryption
goes all the way back to the very first
encryption schemes uh or fully
homomorphic encryption schemes of gentry
in
2009 okay so now we've partially fixed
our problem right we no longer have this
big output Cipher text instead we can
have our server shrink it down into a
small and compact Cipher text of a
linearly homomorphic encryption scheme
but we're still not quite happy because
we still have this big input Cipher text
the good news though is that we can play
this exact same trick again so
specifically what we would like our
server to do is to start with a compact
Cipher text from some uh small
encryption scheme and then have a way to
translate this into a big Cipher text
from our sparse LPN scheme and what we
see is that our sparse LPN scheme by
construction we built it to be
homomorphic right so if our sparse LPN
scheme can evaluate the decryption
function of this orange encryption
scheme then we're in business and then
we can indeed perform this translation
in exactly the same way so specifically
we can take the orange secret key we can
encrypt it under our somewhat
homomorphic scheme and then whenever our
server gets this orange Cipher text
encrypting the input value it can
homomorphically run the decryption
function to get a big green so sparse
LPN Cipher text that encrypts the exact
same
message okay so now what we can do is we
can put all of these steps together and
we get a final construction that looks
roughly as follows so first we're going
to have our user send a one-time
evaluation key to the server so you can
think of this as just like an identity
card that the user publishes to the
server that it can later reuse as many
times as it would like and what this
evaluation key is going to hold is going
to be a chain of encryptions of one
schemes key under the previous one so
specifically what I'm going to do here
is I'm going to publish a a sparle PN so
a green encryption of the orange key and
then I'm going to publish a linearly
homomorphic so a pink encryption of the
green secret
key and so now uh when our our user
wants to send Cipher text to our server
what our user can do is it can send just
these small in compact orange Cipher
text to the server it can have the
server locally expand them into the big
Spar alpan Cipher Tex then use the
homomorphism of these Cipher Texs to
compute on them and then finally squish
them back down into a small Cipher text
from a linearly homomorphic encryption
scheme and so this is what our server
can send back so really what we've built
here is a scheme where all of the
communication that's sent on The Wire so
all of these Cipher texts that are
actually being sent here are tiny and
all of the computation with the big
blowup that happens from using sparse
LPN just happen sort of in the server's
head okay so uh this was this was it we
just constructed a whole somewhat
homomorphic encryption scheme and so
really the takeaway from this talk is
that we can combine these two relatively
you know simple and in some sense weak
Primitives so specifically The Spar
alpan assumption and a linearly
homomorphic encryption scheme which is
given to us by a whole Suite of number
theoretic uh Primitives and when we
combine them we can build something
that's much more powerful so
specifically we built a somewhat
homomorphic encryption scheme where we
can compute a fixed but and bounded
number of multiplications followed by
many additions on encrypted data so what
I wanted to do now is just leave you
with a couple open questions in this
area of research so the first question
is whether we can actually make our
schemes concretely efficient and
practical and really the barrier here is
this big evaluation key that we had our
user send to the server even though it's
reusable so so you only need to send it
once but it would be really nice to get
rid of this key and if we were able to
do this then our scheme would already
have a couple appealing properties and
so specifically most of our servers work
here was really doing these sparse
Matrix operations which on their own are
already a heavily optimized
workload the second question I wanted to
ask is with this homomorphism so given
that we can evaluate this class of
functions what can we build uh and so
here at first glance you might be kind
of skeptical right this seems like a
quite simple class of functions that
we're evaluating here but in fact
there's some hope uh and specifically in
Prior work my collaborators and I showed
that if you can homomorphically evaluate
this class of functions so many
additions and maybe just a couple
multiplications and if you combine this
with modern machine learning and
specifically semantic embeddings then
you can build things like private web
search so I think it's a fun time to
think about what else we can build with
these types of
techniques uh and last but not least
sort of the moonshot question here is
whether we can fly even higher so
whether we can get even more
homomorphism from these schemes uh and
perhaps even get all the way to fully
homomorphic
encryption cool yeah so thank you so
much and I'm happy to take any questions
uh thanks for your talk and and for the
work that you put into the presentation
also is really uh I appreciate it so
thank you for that um I wanted to ask
you you seem to be careful to say that
you can do multiplications followed by
additions yeah is it just because if you
do some additions first then the noise
from the additions grows too much like
could you do one addition first if you
wanted yeah so you totally can you
totally have can inter leave additions
and multiplications as you want and
you're exactly right the only thing that
changes is sort of the error analysis so
both the sparsity of your Cipher text
would grow differently and the errors
would grow differently and so then you
sort of need to perform some accounting
of like how many operations can you
still do before the errors become too
large but you're totally right in in
principle you can operate however you
would like uh I just gave this
presentation because it's sort of a
simple
overview okay perfect