Thank you everyone for joining us um
this afternoon. Uh welcome to our next
installment of the equity and biio
medicine seminar or EBM. Uh the EBM
series is an interactive meeting that
focuses on critical issues related to
equity and representation in biomedical
research especially as it applies to
genomics and research genomics research
and uh precision medicine. Speakers dive
into the equal or unequal social
implications of their work. uh really
thinking about who's affected, how are
they affected, and why. The overall goal
of this series is to foster discussions
about equity and inspire scientists and
trainees and others in our community to
reflect on the social impact of our own
research. Uh the EBM series is sponsored
by the idea office here at the Broad
Institute of MIT in Harvard. Um, and for
more information about the series or to
make suggestions for future sessions,
please reach out to our office. Uh, Lois
will will be putting information into
the chat there. Please note that EBM
seminars are recorded and will be shared
on Broad's YouTube site. to to ground
our conversation, I just want to start
what by presenting um kind of uh some
data that can um lead us into what I
think would be uh an interesting way to
think about um uh um this topic thinking
about building trust and understanding
through accessible science
communication. uh post pandemic there
have been measurable declines in public
trust in scientists as you can see here
evidenced by the pe research study here
in this slide um there have been
reductions of about 10% between the
years of 2020 and 2024 in response many
have been thinking about ways to
understand and address the public's
waning confidence with numerous
organizations um like ours making
efforts to foster trust in science and
enhance outreach to broader audiences is
in today's session. We will focus on the
role that accessible and inclusive
science communication can play in this
work. And now it's my honor to introduce
our panelists for the
discussion. Uh first we have Brian
Southwell. Uh Brian is a distinguished
fellow at um RTI International where he
oversees research to assess risk
perceptions, mental models of scientific
concepts and public trust in science and
scientists. Um, Brian also is an adject
professor of internal medicine with Duke
University where he co-founded the Duke
program on medical misinformation and is
a faculty affiliate with the Duke
Initiative for Science and Society. In
addition, Brian is an adject associate
professor um with at UNC Chapel Hills
Gilling School of Global Public Health
and an adject faculty uh member at the
University of Delaware. Uh at RTI, Brian
co-leads um the All of Us Researcher
Academy to improve equity and scholarly
publishing to the National Institutes of
Health. He's an um active participating
in uh several efforts to address public
understanding of science through peer
reviewed publications as well as public
commentary talks and venues such as the
Aspen Ideas Festival. Um he advises for
projects such as NOVA science studio and
as um and a consensus study for the
nationalmies of science and engineering
and medicine. His research appears in
more than 150 journal articles and a
chapters in um in in several books
including measuring everyday life
talking about research and why it
matters. Um thanks so much Brian for
joining us today. Uh our next panelist
will be Sheniqua Collier um is uh who's
an associate professor with tenure in
the department of clinical research and
leadership at the George Washington
University of medicine and health
sciences. She has also served as a
special volunteer at the center for
research on genomics and global health
at the national human um genome research
institute NI at the NIH for over 13
years. She has nearly two decades of
experience analyzing the ethical, legal
and social implications of emerging
technologies which includes her time as
a post-doal scholar at the center for
genetic research ethics and law at Case
Western Reserve University School of
Medicine. She works on various projects
funded by the US National Institutes of
Health and with a focus on LC of
genomics research and data science.
Thanks so much Fenikua for joining us.
And last but not least, um our own
Namita uh Sang Gupta, uh who's an
associate director for scientific
engagement, policy, and advocacy at the
Broad Institute. Um based in Bro's
office of communication and government
relations, she develops and leads
programs and community partnerships to
advance Bro's public engagement efforts
and organizes strategic thinking and
connectivity on matters concerning
government relations and public pro
policy across the institute. Namtha
facilitates Broad's relationships with
neighboring communities, local, state,
and federal government, international
delegations, and the general public. She
is also responsible for overseeing the
Broad Discovery Center and related
public outreach and educational
efforts. Um, Narmtha holds a PhD in
environmental toxicology from Clemson
University and a mass uh uh MS in
biotechnology from Bangalore University
and a BS in chemistry from the
University of Kolkata. Thanks so much
for joining us, Namtha. And uh with
those introductions, I would like to
pass um it over to Brian. We will start
with a few grounding talks before we um
enter a panel discussion on the topic.
Um and then we'll end the last uh 15 or
so minutes. We'll um save for questions
from the audience. So please, if you
have those, share them in the chat with
us. Um with further without further ado,
I'll pass it over to Brian.
Thanks so much and I I really appreciate
the broad interest in this topic and and
willingness to have this discussion.
It's a really important one. So um I
wanted to offer just a couple of initial
remarks just to help set the stage um
you know for uh this discussion um and
then I'll pass it along to my colleagues
as well. But I'm just going to share
screen here for a moment. offer just a
few thoughts uh that might help to um
offer a foundation for our exploration
of of this larger you know discussion of
of trust. So you know there are a lot of
questions that we often will come to a
discussion like this with uh you know
related to uh you whether or not various
communities may or may not trust um you
know scientific institutions. um we
might get to a point of of asking
questions about a sense of connection
you know to those those different
institutions but I think it's also
important for us to step back um and
both look at the landscape as it exists
um in terms of the information
environment and um to also think a bit
you know historically um you know as
well and so let's just do that for just
a second um and then kind of move ahead
I I think it's important for us
conceptually to also ask questions about
you what we mean by some of these words
uh and and I think we can um you do that
in a productive
So um you with regards to our
information environment um this won't
necessarily be surprising to you but I
think it is worthwhile to just you know
take stock of this that you know we are
in a landscape right now where um you
know larger you know institutions
themselves sometimes are sources of
information. Um but in the larger
information landscape they are often
competing with smaller more nimble you
know organizations or even individuals
you know sometimes and those
organizations and individuals themselves
may or may not be professionally
trained. It may or may not be aligned
with a formal um you know news outlet or
a scientific scientific institution. And
yet um you know through social media
through the internet there are ways in
which um you know those types of
organizations also are contributing um
and sometimes complicating um you know
the landscape. We've seen in past
decades a shift from um you know
broadcast to uh you know various um you
know other you know channels different
ways. What that means for us is that we
may not at any one given point in time
know what community members are
necessarily you know watching what it is
that um you audiences see and hear and
encounter isn't necessarily always
easily um you know assessed. We've moved
away from a landscape where they're just
a handful of of network um you know
broadcast channels towards something you
know much more uh you know diffuse and
diverse um in different ways and people
are also inconstant social networks.
some of those networks are better or
less uh connected to um you know
different information sources and those
networks themselves may or may not be
particularly uh identifiable or
available to to institutions. So there's
a really complicated landscape uh there
that we've got to recognize people are
operating in. Um and we also are seeing
um you know artificial intelligence
really shape and change that landscape
in different ways both in terms of
production of content but even um in
different ways shaping people's
experiences with something like a search
engine um you know where now
increasingly you've got results that are
assisted by artificial intelligence um
and are becoming uh simultaneously
seemingly more seamless um you know and
for people and summarized but yet people
are maybe less aware of um all the
different places where information might
be being pulled
from. So that landscape um also is often
complicated and we'll and you'll hear
many people worry about you know the
extent to which it's cluttered by um
misinformation, inaccurate information
about science. And I that's uh an
important aspect of of the landscape
that people are dealing with. But it's
also important um I think to recognize
that uh it's not necessarily a new
phenomenon um that we've actually been
dealing with misinformation about health
and medicine and science for quite some
time. Uh you can you turn back a century
or so ago, we were dealing with um you
know the original um you know episode of
snake oil um sales uh you know and
promotions um that now has echoed
through our our popular language such
that a snake oil salesman or snake oil
salesperson is something that you would
not want to be called. Um but it
actually has roots in real historical
incident. Um we've been dealing with a
fraudulent promotion of claims for quite
some for quite some time. But it's not
just bad actors and and folks you know
promoting uh fraudulent claims outside
of scientific institutions. Uh
institutions that themselves have um you
know supposedly been scientific um have
often and or sometimes anyway um you
know offered um you know information and
conclusions that was really not rooted
in the best you know available evidence.
Um you we can look at you know in the
early part of the 20th century for
example the eugenics movement um you
know in the United States where um you
know formally scientific institutions
were sometimes not universally but
sometimes making claims that uh really
of course were not really rooted in um
particularly useful uh you know
evidence. So I think we can see that
this is a complicated environment. Lots
of different authors you know in our
information landscape lots of different
places that we might look to for um
remedy. Um, and it also is important for
us to ask questions about what it is
that we mean by trust. You know, we're
here today to talk about trust. And I
think trust itself is really importantly
multifaceted in the line in the minds of
um, you know, many audiences. Uh, trust
often means for people a sense of
intellectual credibility. It's our
common sense use of it. And sometimes
we'll get to a point of recognizing that
you know consistency or reliability also
matters. But something that I think gets
left out a lot of these discussions is
the idea that trust for many people is
also a matter of perceived shared
interest. You know, it may be the case
that a particular person you're hearing
talk um you has lots of letters after
their name, uh they're perceived to be
an expert in their field, but if you
don't get the sense that they care
whether or not you live or die, they may
not necessarily be deemed trustworthy by
you. And I think the same is true for
institutions as well. So generally
speaking, something that we might do is
shift our our our stance here slightly
to think about um issues of trust um
less in terms of worrying about blaming
those that don't necessarily trust us or
trust institutions and more thinking
about what could be done to build and
maintain trust. Um and that's I think a
really productive way to um you know
think about you know this this uh
discussion. Now alam noted here some of
the the slippage we've seen with regards
to trust in in science. But I also want
to put that into larger historical
context because relatively speaking we
still have a fair amount of trust
actually in many scientific institutions
when you look at it compared to other
types of institutions you know over and
if you look at it over time um here's an
example of a figure that appears in um a
new consensus study which just appeared
in December and I had the um privilege
of being a part of that committee um
that the nationalmy's um you just
released and they helped to set the
stage here as well by by noting that um
we do need to worry about you know this
issue of trust but yet it's also
important to recognize that relatively
speaking trust in institutions has been
has been high so we can ask I think
important questions though about what
ways in which people might uh ways in
which people might differ with regards
to trust what are some predictors of
trust and here's where I think we might
um you move into a really interesting
part of our discussion something that we
pointed out um another report that I had
a chance to be a part of for the
national science foundation uh their
science and engineering indicator 's um
report of spring 2024 uh noted that when
you look at um confidence in scientists,
one of the predictive factors is the
extent to which people actually
understand the process of science, the
extent to which they actually understand
what it is that is constituted um by
science rather than just thinking about
team science. What extent is there
transparency? Is there a sense that
people have an understanding of what
scientific research is all about and
what it's like? And those that have um
you know express more understanding
actually tend to express more confidence
in science. So one step forward for here
this might be for us to offer more
transparency about what it is that
actually is happening um in scientific
institutions. But another aspect of this
really builds on the earlier point that
I just raised. We've got to find ways to
think about um perhaps pointing out
those connections, those shared
interests that do exist between
different communities and different
institutions. That's a question for us
then here is not just how who who should
we blame for losses and trust but rather
what can we do to actually identify and
uplift shared interests between
organizations and people outside of
those organizations. That's something
that we often don't spend enough time
doing and I think it's something that we
could actually productively do here um
together. So I think that's something
that's going to um it be useful to keep
in mind for a lot of the um points that
we want to raise. I'm happy to raise
more um a little bit later, but I want
to pass it now to Sheniqua for some
additional thoughts.
Okay, thank you. Great. Good afternoon
everyone and thanks to the Broad
Institute and my co-panelists for the
opportunity to engage with all of you. I
don't have any conflicts of interest and
opinions expressed are my own. My short
remarks will focus on the link between
actions and messaging. Do our actions
support or undermine what we communicate
to build trust? I want to talk
specifically about how transparency
regarding the scientific process can
enhance trust in science and pick up on
threads Brian introduced about
transparency and also shared interest.
First, scientists generally acknowledge
that we should emphasize our common
interests. Uh Brian talked about shared
interests as scientists, communities and
scientists who are members of
communities. The importance of
understanding and prioritizing the
research needs of different communities
has been highlighted in the literature.
However, investment in these areas
should be monitored, assessed, and
increased to prevent operation in a
scientific va vacuum or overly top- down
approaches. Otherwise, how can we
identify our shared interests? How can
we grasp the nuances and complexity
surrounding them? Second, scientists
with abundant funding sometimes treat
community partners or researchers
working in low resource settings merely
as data collectors rather than as
partners. Here is a specific example
from Dr. Ambrose Wankam who researched
what happened to collaborations between
scientists in Cameroon and external
scientists. He found that few African
researchers and institutions were
involved in priority setting and
authorship. research topics did not
align with local health priorities.
Almost all DNA samples were stored
outside of the African continent and no
studies addressed the ethnic diversity
in
Cameroon. I'm concerned that if we
continue to see a divide between
scientists and our partners from
marginalized and underrepresented
communities, including those who are
also scientists, it will limit the
opportunity for equity in these
partnerships. So, how can we adjust our
communications and also our actions to
reduce the negative impact of power
dynamics and imbalanced resources while
also fostering trust and adhering to
important research ethics practices?
Additionally, how can we show that we
value community input about what is
ethical and equitable? Importantly,
research structures and frameworks
lacking transparency and accountability
undermine our efforts to build trust.
We have been ringing the alarm bells
about the urgent need to recruit diverse
populations and groups to research for a
long time. And we often communicate to
the populations and groups we are
targeting that we need them and their
samples and data in order for everyone
globally to benefit from the promises of
genomics medicine and genomics research.
And that's the area I'm in. So I'll be
using genomics examples. Um there's our
shared interest. And I think this is
true. I've argued for inclusion as well
with my geneticist colleagues. Um, our
field has spent less time on improving
transparency and accountability
mechanisms to ensure that the scientific
practices align with our community
messages. I there's real concern that we
treat equity as if it is in inevitable
and we neglect transparency and
accountability in our research
processes. We are all facing the
possibility of declining resources and
the United States and other countries
grapple with discrimination, power
disparities and shifting political
systems. So equity in any environment
cannot be
guaranteed. Here is a point um an
on-point example. In 2020, Ben Egan and
colleagues reported in Nature that even
when geneticists have access to diverse
data, they commonly discard these data
or use them only to replicate or confirm
findings from studies focused on
European ancestries. Usually, they found
the authors do not offer a reason or
justification why. In the few instances
when authors provide their reasons for
exclusion, the most common one is a fear
of confounding variables. The second
most frequently mentioned reason is a
lack of statistical power. Additionally,
they found one study that explicitly
stated that they follow the methods from
past publications and that contributes
to their decision to exclude data. So,
while the authors agree that these
reasons um are legitimate, they also
emphasize that they do not necessarily
prevent the analysis of data from
diverse populations and they argue that
uh authors should analyze such data. The
authors um argue that finding a genetic
association can secure publication, but
analyzing different populations may
complicate the process and delay it. My
perspective is that this dynamic between
researchers, reviewers, and editors may
be seen by the public as a preference by
scientists for studying European
cohorts. In 2020, some of the same
authors um apply the accountability for
reasonable accountability for
reasonleness framework to allow for
difficult choices and tradeoffs like the
ones I described, but also promote
procedural fairness. As part of this,
they discussed transparency,
enforcement, and revision, as well as
other factors, proposing that funders
and journals develop ways to enforce a
framework that's aligned with evidence
and principles and values, and that
assessments of transparency and
revalence. Um, they understand that
these assessments will change with
society and methodology. Um, in
conclusion, I just want to suggest that
the scientific community reward journals
that create space and opportunities for
scientists to openly share their
decision-making processes related to
equitable inclusion or dis or exclusion.
Journals are major gatekeepers of
information and communication and our
journalists pick up what's written in
these scientific um publications.
Members of the public sometimes do as
well. So um by fostering transparency
and account and accountability I believe
we can begin to eliminate some some of
these barriers to communication and
build trust. Thank you so much.
Good afternoon everyone. Uh my name is
Namita Sang Gupta and uh I am the third
panelist for today. I don't have slides
uh but I'm going to share perspectives
from another lens here as a practitioner
of science communication. um and public
engagement. Uh I'm going to share some
best practices and uh things that I
apply in my own work in my with my
colleagues I work with and uh outside of
the broad I'm also an adjun professor of
science communication at Clemson
University in South Carolina uh from
where I also graduated did my PhD from
there. So uh these are fundamental
concepts that I also teach graduate
students when they are thinking about
communicating uh complex research topics
with a broader
audience. But uh from the broad
institute context uh just for a quick
note actually what you see as my
backdrop is the broad discovery center.
It's a wallpaper here but uh I'm not
sitting at the discovery center right
now but it is a public science museum uh
which is free to the public open
Thursday through Saturday. uh and uh we
offer a lot of tours and uh you know
public engagement programming through
the broad discovery center. We are a
2-year-old uh science museum that uh
aims to demystify complex biomedical
research uh happening at Broad and our
partner institutions and collaborator
sites nationally and worldwide. Uh we
try to demystify that for the general
public. The exhibits at the discovery
center are uh centered around different
disease areas and uh I wanted to use the
discovery center as an example in
explaining some of the concepts uh that
I'll talk about through the panel today.
But uh going back to like three or four
concepts that I want to touch on. Uh I'm
assuming some of you on this panel uh
sorry some of you in the in the
participants are either scientists or
you're science communication
practitioners or you're just interested
uh you know you uh in this topic. So one
concept that uh I always uh teach my
students uh graduate students when uh we
talk about science communication best
practices and how to like help coach
them to communicate about their work. I
tell them that there is no concept as
lay audience or general public like I
know we talk about that very commonly in
everything we say what's the messaging
for the general public or how will you
say this as a scientist to a lay
audience audience uh audience is much
more nuanced so I encourage anybody I
coach uh and work with on the science
communication project is let's do an
exercise to uh reframe our audience like
so we do an audience reframing develop
audience personas and kind of see what
is some common goal in science
communication that would cater to that
audience group. A lot of scientists and
early career researchers I've worked
with uh we've often identified like five
top personas for them you know like
which are very important for them for
example experts outside their field so
they may be a biologist who's trying to
communicate and collaborate with a
mathematician uh interdisciplinary
audience so they are possibly invited to
a conference that has a larger like
group of people from across different
expertise area collaborators you know
like uh it's it ties into the
interdisciplinary audience as well. But
sometimes you may be a chemist who's
trying to develop some kind of machine
learning model with someone else or
you're working with u someone who's a
history uh you know uh expert. So it
just kind of depends how you're
communicating with your work with your
collaborators and stakeholders.
Stakeholders is anybody who benefits
from your work. Stakeholders anybody
who's like helping you with your work
and of course decision makers. Decision
makers are policy makers. decision
makers are your agency, grant agencies
or donors who will be deciding to give
you uh funding for your work maybe. So
helping develop some kind of audience
persona before any type of public
engagement work you do is really a
really helpful exercise. The other
aspect since we talked uh Brian and
Shaikica laid the foundation of trust in
science communication. I think the other
aspect or best practice that goes along
with that is balancing simplicity and
accuracy. So as a communicator, as a
science communicator, as a scientist,
there are strategies that you can employ
to break down very complex scientific
concepts in ways that can be accessible
and engaging to your audience. Uh, of
course you I know a lot of scientists
are nervous about uh making things sound
too simple, oversimplification or that
can get carried through misinformation.
So there are ways there are layered ways
that you can address this. Uh I always
encourage as a best practice uh when I'm
coaching for these projects is focus
first on the why. If you're
communicating about something, what is
that larger societal, global, public
health uh problem that your research is
addressing? And I have experienced this
that a lot of early career researchers
are hesitant. They say that no but I'm
working on a very specific pathway in
this particular organism, this disease
model. And I say okay let's zoom out.
Let's think about why even do this work.
So let's start at that level. Then the
second layer goes into what like what
are you doing about the research? Like
maybe you're uh it's not even at the
technique level. What is your larger
research question? Let's frame that for
your audience. And then we get into how.
That's your what technique you're
approaching uh with this. What method
you're implementing? What data set
you're using. And when researchers tend
to apply this in the way they
communicate like the why, the what and
then the how. And even science
communicators as science communicators
we've experienced this at the broad
discovery center we to a lot of public
tours and uh our really talented visitor
experience assistants when they engage
with the public they've applied this
framework because in our museum our
content is also displayed in this way.
We have a lot of people who just like
engaging at the why level the big
picture question. But we also get we are
located in Kendall Square, a biotech
ecosystem here in Cambridge,
Massachusetts. So we also get a lot of
people who come to our museum who are
biotech CEOs or collaborators from
Europe or uh students who are pursuing
STEM majors in undergrad and they ask a
lot of questions that are associated
with the how. So for for kind of like we
want to make sure that we're offering
content in our exhibits, in our tours,
in our discussions, and in the dialogues
that we have with the public in these
nuanced and layered ways. So I think
that framework has really helped us. Uh
and finally, anyone I'm going to close
out with like just one final tip with
again like a what and how framework is
anyone here if you're like you know as
as you saw the uh the data that Alham
presented at the beginning of the
session and Brian and Shaunie also
presented really great like uh data sets
and uh information. If any of that is
encouraging you that I need to step up
my science communication game or as a
scientist or a science communicator, I
have a role to play going into 2025. Um
I just kind of do this simple formula
that I apply to every almost science
communication initiative is let's take a
sheet of paper and write down the what,
the who and the how. That means what
every great science communication
projects begins with a great science
communication goal. That means what are
you trying to communicate? What is the
purpose of that? So let's first write a
clear goal. Then you write who who would
benefit from knowing about this. And
sometimes in some cases based on the
kind of researcher you are or the
program you're running maybe the who is
first and then goes the what. But who is
your audience? And that kind of
reframing that I talked about in the
beginning. And most important after that
is the how the medium of communicating
you know then that's where like if you
remember the first slide that Brian
showed about trust and the different
mediums of communication that has
evolved over time we really have to pay
attention to that. If you are really
communicating to teenagers who are only
on Tik Tok or Instagram reels, your
approach might be very different than if
you're communicating with community
members in a neighborhood that is
impacted by a particular environmental
health problem in their community and
you have to meet them maybe at the city
hall or wherever the convening is. So
these are different ways to think about
who your audience is, where do you meet
them and what are you going to
communicate. I hope some of these best
practices are things you can apply
immediately to your work or share with
your colleagues and uh I try to apply
this every time I'm taking on a
communication project for any
audience. I'll pass it on to Alhung.
Thanks so much Namatha Sheni and Brian.
Um so
many interesting points raised from
different perspectives and I think it's
going to make for hopefully a rich
conversation in our panel. Um, I'd love
to start with a few questions for for
our our panel. Um, the first one is
focused on combating misinformation,
something that um we've we've heard
about a little bit today. Uh, with the
rise of misinformation and
disinformation, what role do you do
science communicators and other
communicators of science play in
addressing these challenges? And what
are some practical ways to foster trust
and counter false narratives?
Yeah, I can I can jump in there. Um,
it's such an important question and one
that's I think you know bothering and
um, you know, worrying lots of folks
that are probably on the call right now.
And I think something there there's a
lot to be done. Um, there one thing to
that's important to keep in mind is that
there's a role for all of us. Um, and
there's a role for many different
institutions. Um, you know, this isn't
going to be a problem that's going to be
solved, you know, overnight you per se.
It's took us a long time to get here and
it's and it's a problem that is partly
reflective of the nature of the society
that we live in. Um the nature of our
media system, the nature of lots of
things. Um and we're not going to
necessarily change that, you know,
overnight, nor would we necessarily want
to. Uh we the openness of our media
system, for example, is is a strength.
And so we wouldn't want to be in a
situation where we were censoring or
sanitizing everything because then you
might worry about who it is that has the
reigns of of censorship. Um, so we're
going to have to live with some degree
of of um, open-endedness, I think. But
something that I think is an instinct
that many people have is to somehow um,
you know, want to go to all corners of
the internet and to vanquish, you know,
misinformation. Um, you know, because
they're worried about, you know, that I
think the bigger issue, the bigger
concern is, you know, what are you doing
to actively provide good and credible
information to, um, you know, different
communities. And I think that there's a
lot that you could be doing um, beyond
what what you currently are. And that's
something that um this goes to a lot of
the points we've had raised here
already. But I think if we get to a spot
where people um were and and dependent
upon and and relied on and turned to
different sources of information more
regularly. Right now there's a sort of
wide openen sense people are not
necessarily always paying attention to
um you know sources of of information.
Those sources of institutions and
scientific institutions aren't always
providing the answers to the questions
people have. So if we can be better
oriented towards understanding what is
it that people want uh what is it
they're interested in how can we better
provide that information in a in an
accessible way that will help um you
know rather than always chasing after
and trying to vanquish um you know the
misinformation that's out there. Um I
think that's that's a really healthy you
know starting place. Now we can't have
any illusion that somehow if you just
post something on your own uh private
blog somewhere that you know lots of
people are going to necessarily read it.
we do have to pay attention to the
landscape and to the importance of
different institutions, news outlets and
others for amplifying ideas. Um, you
know, we live in a a landscape where
it's not immediately guaranteed that you
know what you say privately on the
corner is going to make its way out
there. So, you have to think about the
systems and think strategically, but to
what extent are you um oriented to be a
good and available and credible source?
Um, you can you work in conjunction with
um, you know, journalists and and
community based organizations and others
to provide, you know, that kind of
information. All those are think are
going to be um really crucial and
important and I think there's a lot more
that could be done you know than we are
we are doing right now. Um but I do
think there is hope um this we're we're
not necessarily um you know at risk of
completely drowning in uh in
misinformation although it might seem
like that sometimes because actually
there are lots of situations where
people are um you know getting
information from others in their
community. There are there are lots of
good community level initiatives. we
what we need to do is strengthen and
build up and amplify you know some of
what's been happening you know already
and not necessarily just throw our hands
up in despair and I think that's one one
my take on it um you know anyway so
yeah thanks so much Brian um I think the
the point you raised specifically around
kind of thinking about how to prevent um
misinformation from spreading and being
kind of thinking creatively and
strategically about that and finding the
right partners to help with that I think
is is a really important on um any other
thoughts on this topic from Chini or
Nam.
I think that was just such a great
answer. I don't have much to add, but I
really do think it's every scientist's
responsibility to think about also
internally the the words they're using.
Understand sort the the debate and the
discussion about how we talk about
groups and populations.
um engaging groups to understand what
they need you to communicate about as
Brian said is just so so critical and
then just recognizing that people have
individuals and institutions that they
trust on the ground where they go to for
trust and information. I you know I
couldn't agree more with that point.
Thanks
Shenqua. I'm I don't want to take away I
I have one other point to to raise and
add there but go ahead if you had other
thoughts. Uh I was just going to build
on uh some of the things that have
already been said but you know since
give a call to action to our scientists
that it is also your responsibility. I
as a as someone who practices science
communication I just thought like I
could share some tips or on of course
like there's no foolproof method that
everything is going to work but uh if
just there are some approaches like for
example if you're in a situation where
you're experiencing you're in a
one-on-one dialogue situation and you're
experiencing uh misinformation uh which
is kind of important for us those who
work in community spaces or engage with
the public on a one-on-one direct basis
is uh let that be a two-way
conversation. I think it's very
important that when you're experiencing
misinformation, it's also important to
listen and I think it it can from both
sides. It can be you block you
completely shut down or block the other
person's views. But uh and addressing
the misin misinformation respectfully is
key. If you if you're hearing skepticism
about certain things, just listen to
where that person is coming from and
then have a dialogue driven approach in
the conversation. I do agree that you
know sometimes we have to take a more
community engagement approach to things
when you know like misinformation is
already spreading about a topic. Maybe
it's important to think about who are
the trusted members in that community
like maybe working with faith leaders,
educators,
um cultural organizations, uh you know,
social media influencers even for for
that uh instance and counter false
narratives with some kind of
communitybacked messages. So that could
be like another thing to think about.
And I am actually I really loved a point
that was brought up in one of by one of
our speakers earlier u was it's also
important it's becoming increasingly
important to talk about how science is
done and we've seen we've continue to
see this and I think the general public
like when you're engaging with them when
you're speaking when you're tackling
topics of misinformation it's not about
what the findings are but like breaking
down how the data was collected analyzed
revised will help demystify by the kind
of iterative nature needed for science
and how policies get made, how those
become regulations. Uh this is something
that scientists need to think about and
have patience to also talk about that
aspect of science.
Yeah. And if if I could raise just one
other point here given the audience that
we have um there is another role I think
for all of for those that that work
directly in research for those that um
you know have sometimes a spotlight put
on their own you know research and so
here this is a little bit of an
uncomfortable aspect of this but I think
it's important for us ethically to um
you think about um you know there are
many times which our university you know
press relations offices others you put
out press releases that are perhaps a
bit more sensational than really the you
know the articles you know warrant But
we're tempted to go along with that
because perhaps you know there's a
little bit of celebrity or fame that
might come to our work you know as a
result and we all sort of let that slide
a little bit. There is this is not to
lay blame on um you know researchers
solely but there are moments where you
know our own amplification of of work
sometimes leads to some of the
misunderstanding or misperceptions. We
tend to over sensationalize sometimes.
So you might think about the
relationship you have with um you know
press office and with others. It may
mean maybe it means one or two less
headlines, you know, for your work, but
if you can provide a little bit more
context and a little bit more of a
tempered view of what it is that you're
actually saying and try to have some
arrangement whereby you're happy to work
with a group to um, you know, put out a
press release, but are you getting a
final check and and a look on and can
you stand behind and sign off on that on
that press release? That might help to
temper things a bit as well. It's
actually a recommendation that comes out
of the um national academyy's consensus
study which is part of the point there
of raising that we all do have a role.
There's a lot that's complicated, a lot
we can bemoone and worry about what
happens outside of our control, but
let's also think about um how much
sometimes um you know in our own seeking
to you know glorify our own work um we
may be providing a little bit more hype
than is is warranted and that may be
contributing to the noise as well.
Thanks everyone. That was a fantastic um
kind of thinking about this from a lot
of different perspectives. And um I
think Brian, your your last point is a
really important one as well. Um as uh
as we think about kind of the the
sensationalization of of sharing of
scientific information. Um I'd love to
move on to another uh our next question
really thinking about kind of the topic
of tailoring messages for diverse
audiences. Um and the question is you
know how can um science communicators
effectively tailor their message to meet
the needs values and cultural contexts
of diverse communities again to um this
has been discussed earlier but without
compromising the accuracy or integrity
of the science like we've already talked
about some ways to do it. I would love
to hear if there's any additional
thoughts um on how to do that
effectively.
Shanica, do you want to go
first? Well, I was just thinking about
the fact that many of us are from
communities and
um you know, we bring a perspective
um from our communities to these
conversations and to this messaging. And
I think that's valuable. I think that's
why workforce diversity is so critically
important. Um, in addition to meeting
people where they are, um, I really
would I do hope that in the future there
are opportunities to increase our
investment in long-term sustainable
relationships with the groups that we
really want to be a part of our
research. because it's not just
education level, it's cultural values.
a native indigenous group, for example,
having very significant beliefs and
values around DNA and being able to
understand those values, talk about
those values, and develop a project and
then describe the results in a way that
is respectful of and integrates the
groups or nations beliefs.
Um, you just can't do that without
birectional education. We're not just
educating communities. They must educate
us.
I I want to emphasize that point a
little further to Shenika just to say,
you know, there there are all kinds of
reasons why the diversity of our
workforce matters, but it also it
matters both in terms of good science
and it matters in terms of building
these bridges. And it's just something
we have to have the courage to come out
and say that it does matter not just
that we have a range of people
participating in studies, but we have a
range of researchers conducting those
studies and that we've got um you know
folks that have and it goes back to that
sense of um of shared interest. It goes
back but it also just adds to um you
know the range of perspectives. It's
better science um you know often from
that perspective. This is something that
um I noted earlier on one of the
initiatives that we're working on with
the national institutes of health um for
the all of us you know initiative um
which I'll put the a link in the chat
here but where we are actively trying to
think about who is it that's actually
conducting research using you know
publicly available data sets who is it
that's actually contributing to research
literature and what could we do to
broaden and and extend you know that
that range of people um and geographic
areas uh demographic differences all of
those things uh you really do matter um
in really important ways. So I I think
that's one way to think about how it is
we might better um you know shape
messages for different communities is to
have a better sense and representation
from those communities in the in the
groups that are doing that work. Yeah.
Yeah. Thanks Brian and Chenika. Really
important point about kind of the
relationship between um who's delivering
the message and how it's being received.
Um yeah, thanks. uh could go on on that
topic for a little bit longer, but I
think in um I'd love to kind of move on
to our next question, which is uh
thinking about shared community spaces
um uh and and the role that they can
play in increasing access and inclusion
in science uh the the receiving of
science and um science communication. Um
what opportunities exist um kind of from
your perspectives and uh for community
spaces? So here you're thinking of
museums, libraries and other
institutions to increase access and
inclusion uh to broaden the audience for
science communication efforts and how
can these spaces help bridge gaps in
trust and understanding.
uh I can try to address that question
given you know from my firsthand
experience uh trying to uh develop a
programming that is associated with our
public engagement space uh one of the
things that really helped us from this
is even before our museum was built or
launched is uh we decided to bring
together a group uh as a community
advisory group. So we try to identify
who would be our variety of audiences
and the types of research that we do who
would that impact and uh we identified
members from a variety of uh groups like
education, patient engagement community,
uh art community, accessibility
community and brought them together and
uh had them kind of advise us on uh a
variety of our programming on we worked
very closely with uh the patient
engagement community for two of our
galleries in the museum that is based on
psychiatric research and cancer
research. So pretty much every content
that is in the museum for those two
galleries were thoroughly reviewed,
feedback was given and uh even the title
of one of the galleries was changed
because of feedback from the patient
community. So I think that's one way I
would say in a shared community space
how we thought about having community
voices represented through local
partnerships. And then the other thing I
would like to say is
um that really helps in these spaces is
doing some kind of layered
communication. That means all your
audience or visitors will not be
engaging with the same thing. So we make
sure that they have different levels of
engagement opportunities available for
them. So when we participate in the
Cambridge Science Festival or when we do
public talks or even when we are doing
tours, we are always mindful of
different learning abilities and
learning skills and uh interest levels
of our visitors and how we can try to
meet them where they are based on
different types of offerings. Uh and we
are learning of course from visitor
feedback and try to improve our
programming and offerings on a
year-to-year basis based on the feedback
we get from the community.
That's fantastic, Namartha. Um, I think
that speaks to how important it is to
engage with um with a broad uh audience
uh broad and diverse audience from kind
of thinking about this from many um
demographic points of view in in helping
you as you all did with the museum
project to to formulate um scientific
messages and things like that. So,
really wonderful example. Brian and
Sheniqua, any thoughts on how um shared
community spaces can play a role in um
increasing access? I think this is one
of the central questions of one of the
central concerns we face as a society at
the moment is the the decline of
so-called you know third spaces or
public spaces or forums different ways.
Um I've been doing a lot of work you
know thinking in the space of um
hesitancy about vaccination and lots of
different you know um explanations get
uh put forward for that but one one
important predictor um is actually um
you know living in areas that uh have
suffered from declines in in healthcare
access um you know access to and
engagement with with healthcare
facilities really matters um in really
important ways in terms of building up
trust you know over time um and I think
similarly when it comes to science um at
the end of the day uh you know
libraries, science museums, science
centers have the real potential to be a
path forward and to be just centrally
important for our society. So if you are
in a rural area that doesn't have such a
a thing, thinking about finding a way to
invest in, you know, could be a really
crucial path forward. Many of us live in
places where there's a plethora and a
luxury and we don't recognize just how
much it matters when those things are
absent. Um, and so it's incredible to
have um, you know, uh, resources like
what Namartha, you know, runs and has
available there. That's great, but what
about those communities that don't
necessarily have those physical spaces?
What could we be done to partner with
those as well? I think if we did a lot
more of that, um, we may have some of
the less we'd have to ring our hands
less about some of the other concerns
because, um, I a lot of people do show
interest and and and excitement and are
willing to bring families to to
situations like that. if you can frame
them um as being useful and relevant to
them.
And I I have limited experience in these
kinds of um spaces as an academic. I I
belong to so many places where I engage
so many third spaces, but um I've had
limited opportunities, one time at a
museum in DC and another at a church
collaboration with an
H.B.CU. And um the HB.CU BCU church
collaboration was organized by a
professor who's very active at her
H.B.CU and also at her church and there
were maybe 400 people who attended and
one of the reasons I think so many
people came was because we talked about
an area of interest to them. We talked
about genetic testing. Many of them were
using um online companies at the time or
exploring their own stories through
genetic genealogy. And so we brought in
an expert who um works in genetic
genealogy to speak and then we also
brought in a biologist to speak and then
an Elsie scholar uh two Elsie scholars
and we had this sort of mixture of
speakers who could talk about different
aspects of the technology, how it works.
People were very interested simply in
practical implications, how it works and
then also some of the social um issues.
And I think what's really great about
that is when you're bringing together
people who are members of the same
church, they're in their own space. We
were in the church auditorium.
Everyone's in their own space. They're
with people they see every single week.
Um and I felt as if the audience members
were very comfortable talking and giving
feedback among their other church
members. And the students of course um
were very vocal as well. And so there's
just something very special about being
in a community space that belongs to the
community and really letting the
community
members sort of develop the program. Uh
the professor we work
together thinking about what our
colleagues and community members might
be interested in. And I think that led
to it being you know such a success. And
for the museum event, it's it was at the
African-American Museum in in DC. And
people are on the list serve. They
follow what talks and events are
happening at the museum. And if
something's interesting, they come. It's
so special. So um if you are presenting
work and you have the opportunity to or
want to pursue um going to a local
organization that people can travel to
or going to travel to a community,
there's just really nothing like it. I I
I really think everyone should do it if
they can.
Thanks. That's lovely lovely story.
Thanks for sharing that, Sheniwen. It it
reminds me of um some really amazing
work that's happening with uh our
colleagues in Count Me In going into
community spaces and asking the
important question of what would you
like to learn about and what can we
bring that would be useful to the
community to your community in
particular. Um, so that that I love that
I love that example. Um, I'm going to we
uh as we had predicted we that we were
going to have such a rich conversation
and and run out of time. I'd love to
transition to an um question from the
audience. Uh
uh from Curtis uh who is one of your
favorite science communicators, a hero,
past or present?
I'll go first. Um, I think the larger
majority community sometimes often
forgets that we had people like web deo
in the
1800s
following and rigorously measuring the
state of black communities. And I
purchased a book recently where of
graphs he produced of um black the state
of black communities and families over
time. and he communicated so many
different ways. He had newsletters for
communities. He had the manuscripts that
he wrote. And um so I just really
appreciated his his ability
to work through these newsletters where
that are very community and public
facing and accessible and then all or
newspapers and then also continue with
his academic work and just leave us such
nuggets that are still relevant today.
as a as a no as a social scientist
myself. I love that answer like it's
just because it just in terms of
thinking about and you're absolutely
right because so much of that was
contribution to public dialogue that
wasn't framed as capital S science um
you know per se it was more like you
let's organize some of these ideas and
knowledge you know in different ways um
yeah I was thinking there's there's lots
of different examples but you know in
terms of popular culture you know folks
that have been able to tap into and and
and talk about more abstract um concepts
that maybe wouldn't have been thought to
uh you know all that you know
interesting or relevant. Carl Sean's a
good you know example of somebody that
um you know here's here's a wide and
expansive a lot to think about
philosophically you know there but that
and people have interest in those um in
those ideas that's something people that
have the courage to talk about things
that are deemed to not necessarily be
particularly interesting. there's an
awful lot of heroism um heroins and
heroes you know during the course of the
pandemic people that on a local level
were explaining things for their um
local community um and and that's
something that I um you know really
appreciated um you know as well just
seeing so much of of was happening on on
social media in a smaller scale of
people who were trying to make sense of
this really confusing time for many
families. Yeah.
Yeah. Uh my favorite science
communicator is possibly not a popular
name in the US but uh just I have a
personal association uh personal
inspiration story associated with this
person is a scientist who ba who's based
in India his name is Dr. Dr. Tupil
Bankesh and uh I when I was in college I
happened to hear him speak once in an
auditorium packed with hundreds of
students uh undergrad and mast's level
students and I was just it's just not me
most of us in the audience were just
amazed uh he talked about lead toxicity
and how that was a pretty big public
health concern in different parts of
India occupational health and some other
ways and
uh that really inspired me to be a
science communicator. I did not have the
vocabulary for the word science
communicator. This is years ago. I
thought uh I just called him a science
motivational speaker because I was just
impressed but how like widely he would
travel and talk to communities about
lead toxicity and that actually piqued
my interest in pursuing my PhD in
toxicology as well. So he will always be
uh my favorite science communicator who
got me on this path of both my
scientific training and my profession.
Fantastic. That's a lovely story. Thanks
Namita for sharing that. Uh we have just
a couple minutes away. Um and I think we
could go on for another easily for
another 30 minutes on this discussion.
Um uh but I want to first thank our our
fantastic panelists for joining us
today. Thank you to the audience for for
joining us and engaging with the this
important topic. And I'd like to end
with um just a quick um announcement for
a feature um uh EBM that is uh our next
EBM that's scheduled for February 14th.
Um and that is going to take place in
partnership with the LC Friday forum. So
this is uh the Sarah the folks at Sarah
um and the topic will be building
infrastructures
um to enhance community engagement work.
So uh keep an eye out for um kind of
links to register for that session. Uh
they'll be this this as I mentioned will
be co-hosted with uh Sarah's LChub uh
Friday forum um folks. Again, thanks
everyone for joining us uh this
afternoon for a rich discussion um and
we hope to keep the conversation going
um across kind of thinking about uh
trust and science from a lot of
different dimensions and we appreciate
you all joining us and being part of it.
Thank you.