okay
welcome so this is
243 I hope you're in the right
place
um okay my name is Johan Pao
Beretta and
um I am very very happy to teach this
course it's as you know it's the first
time
um this
spring although this course been taught
very similar in poly Technic of Milano
for
about maybe 12
years um for the first year um PhD
students in energy in the energy program
so I'm using view graphs that I've
developed over the
years in fact this is a very particular
year for thermodynamics as you know it's
the 200 uh uh
birthday and
I I like to
say that
um right
now I I am uh I reached onethird of the
age of
thermodynamics when I started studying
it uh
1978 it was
17th
so uh it's my entire uh academic career
has been around
this of course carau is only one of many
who have contributed
over the two centu term Dynamics like
carau Jew ranking elol Claus Kelvin m v
deral
Gibbs bolman van plank dhan n
sommerfield Kate odor Einstein Kenan and
I say a few words more about him FY
gugenheim onager Zigler the gr pin
mazour atopos
and
PRS and I apologize for those
who I I I haven't uh written uh down
there actually may notice that the only
person currently alive is U John
prit but he deserves I believe a place
there anyway for he deserved it for a
long time uh
now the reason I'm
U
particularly happy about teaching this
course
here it uh goes back to Kenan and
atopos
um I like to reference them I mean Kenan
atopos but also the late professor
gios
uh sorry
as the Kenan
School of of
thermodynamics
because Kenan who by the way was uh uh
using the office downstairs in 3-
339 as we also did me atopos for a few
years and me for just uh five years when
I was young uh we used the same room so
that was a privilege for
me uh as you see these are the
books uh that have characterized this uh
School of uh teaching from Dynamics you
will see it's kind of different from the
traditional
Exposition uh I like to say more General
and more uh free of uh uh vicious
logical Loops that are typical of
theistic presentations of
thermodynamics Professor
gpos has been
teaching this course or maybe the course
that now has become
242 uh it used to be called
2451 he thought that for about 20 or
maybe 25 years
and I helped him uh during those years
and then we came up with this book this
book uh uh is uh in the background of uh
what we will we will do
here uh only in the background not that
we are going to cover the book but it
helps me a lot the the fact that uh when
in class I would say you can prove or it
can be proved you can find the proofs
all in all details in that book which is
uh I mean
very good for my from my point of view
because I don't need to spend time
repeating the proofs except only very
few fundamental ones and easy
ones uh but you can find them there and
if you are uh very fond of the subject
you want to go deep you you may study it
there and you may come and discuss uh
them uh uh my office anytime you want
actually my office hours are anytime uh
uh either by a pointer or just drop by
most of the times all the time I'll will
be in the office working so um you can
come or call
anytime if you want we can set up also
more official uh uh office
hours um now the objective of this
course
uh is not
applications because I presume that the
applications have been seen already in
previous courses that you've been
exposed to or maybe in your uh doctoral
or Master's thesis
work what I want to put the emphasis on
is a broad perspective on uh the
assumptions that are uh needed to make
or that are behind certain
models standard
models little nonstandard models uh
models that uh you use
in uh physics and in
engineering because thermodynamics as
you know uh uh covers
applications in an enormous amount of
fields so no no body can really say I
know all applications of
thermodynamics they they're essentially
infinite the good thing since we are in
an engineering department is that as you
know carau was an engineer
thermodynamics started from
engineering and then it was picked up by
physicists and so it goes back and forth
so we share uh the subject we we
Engineers share the subject the subject
with the physicist and the physicist
share it with Engineers not only
engineer I mean all kinds of engineering
so including chemistry chemical
engineering is very strong in very
strong uh
history and DEP about
thermodynamics now the emphasis of of
the course is on non
equilibrium uh until when I did my PhD
studies here uh
thermodynamics in those times was
considered a dead
subject because everybody was thinking
with thermodynamics is just
equilibrium um and in fact that was a
um for a still uh few years later maybe
in the the late
90s that uh there's been
a Revival of thermodynamics because of
non equilibrium because of ir reversible
processes now and also because of
quantum
thermodynamics now it is a an enormous
field Quantum thermodynamics in those
times it was considered
useless and asopos andos
in my opinion are the true pioneers of
of that subject even though there since
their point of view was not
standard uh they're not so recognized
not everywhere as
Pioneers but if you read the recent U uh
paper in science or scientific America
uh about Quantum Dynamics I think it's
called Quantum Ste te Punk um who was
written by uh by the way the winner of a
of the of a prein price in
thermodynamics
uh which I happen to be involved with uh
uh well she wrote this book steampunk
Quantum thermodynamics and also this
science article where she does recognize
the roles of atopos and
gios uh so the course is three parts one
the first part is the review of the
basic concepts and definitions but with
this emphasis on non
equilibrium uh especially on the
definition of entropy for non
equilibrium States and in particular uh
we will see an interesting U aspect of
what uh heat interaction is and the
generalization of the concept of heat
interaction that is useful for
describing the uh non states of continum
like
fluids the second
part which is focused on U chemical
potentials or electrochemical
potentials uh so multicomponent systems
and the role that chemical potentials U
have in describing
them so I'm not reading all these typ
and the the last part the last third of
the course
is more explicitly on the standard
theories of non-equilibrium like uh
particular the role of reciprocal
relations and uh the again
the the assumptions that are needed to
describe these states which are non
equilibrium and how they evolve in time
and um how
you
relate uh the entropy production by
irreversibility to the various fluxes
and forces in
play
so yeah this is about the grading uh
policy there will be um
a everything is going to be oral the
emphasis the reason why this is very
unusual ual it May Scare some of
you if if it does scare you and you
still have to take the
qualifiers uh consider it as a practice
for for that purpose
um if you are instead
uh pass that and you are aiming to a
career in academics where you might have
a
chance that your duty among your duties
you have to teach the subject which is
typical if you go to mechanical
engineering department typically nobody
wants to teach thermodynamics so they if
you're the new one you do it until
somebody else
comes uh
Well I this is the reason why I provide
the viewrs I provide the
videos uh so I want to make it easy for
you if you want to teach it this way
because it's already done okay um
and I'm very happy uh to share uh all
this because as as I said uh this is my
uh life
subject so there will be um one homework
and uh four midterms essentially there
so five items that you have to do they
are all take
home uh as soon as as and they are all
of the kind that you are give you one or
two VI graphs of the ones that I use in
class and you have to repeat in your own
way in front of a camera no more than
five minutes uh the words that go in
between the equations that or the the
things that are written on the uh on The
View graphs so that's essentially a
short lecture uh that you give on that
subject following using the you can use
uh you can use the videos you can use
whatever you want to to to do them so I
would consider those
easy uh so you shouldn't be concerned
about grades that you get out of this
course and yes there is also a final
exam which is also oral that's oral in
presence it lasts 30 minutes
uh and also for that uh um it's the same
idea I I tell you take the view graph on
say chemical
equilibrium and talk about it so you
don't have to memorize anything you you
have the view graphs you can also take
your own U hand notes or your whatever
you want uh as long as you don't come
without anything and you waste all the
30 minutes trying to write a couple of
the formulas you remember because that's
I consider a waste of time it doesn't
allow me to uh check that you have tried
to go uh over uh all of the things that
we have covered the actually the
um the final is going to cover only the
second and third
part uh of of of the of the
course uh okay so
let's get
started
thermodynamics so what's
thermodynamics do any of you have an
idea
of what what's the definition of
thermodynamics don't be scared I
mean no you're shy
yeah okay that that's
two I
would anything anything more like
General how you use you you use
thermodynamics in your uh in your
research what do you use it for
maybe you do molecular Dynamic
simulations that's a way to compute
properties of
stuff in
fact
yeah heat and work are
certainly peculiar
um kinds of interactions that occur that
are described in thermodynamics
but in general thermodynamics is
a is a subject where you say let me use
words that I haven't defined yet but uh
it's a subject that um
um allows you to compute properties of
physical
systems and see how they change with
time and how they are maybe transferred
from one system to the other like by
means of heat and War
all right so
system
property state of the
system also the word
process okay so this is why I want to
spend some time in uh
defining these things these words
because these
words are loaded of meaning
and
therefore uh represent
restrictions uh within the theory of
thermodynamics actually thermodynamics
is
really modeling you want to model
physical
reality exactly like
physics or or mechanics uh does some
modeling of certain aspects it's also uh
similar
um so the key word is
modeling you want to describe
a a glass of water a bottle of water the
water in a bottle
and uh you make a model you typically
simplifying the situation to make it
contain enough of what you need to
describe that water but nothing
more so sometimes this system this will
be a system the water inside this
container and uh uh this system is
interacting with the air that surrounds
it so you need to consider both the
water and the
surroundings but most of the times you
don't need to consider what happens in
say the corridor of your lab or what
happens where is the moon right now so
you can simplify by
removing unnecessary aspects of your
physical reality and
concentrating on what you really want to
represent uh and also you want
to simplify
so uh as you know I can describe water
as if uh it's composed of molecules and
molecules can be considered for certain
aspects um like
U
indivisible like atoms in the democratus
sense no you cannot split them but if
you're interested in uh
chemistry well then the molecule can be
split and then the building blocks are
the
atoms or if you're interested in uh
nuclear uh
phenomena they building blocks and not
even the atoms there are the protons the
neutrons the
electrons if can even go to lower level
description it can go to quarks and the
quarks can be split into Maybe spring uh
string theories and things like that all
right so who knows uh if there is a a
bottom level of description for things
but not for every model you need to go
that deep you just use whatever is
necessary for enough for the phenomena
you want to describe so that's the let's
call it art of modeling
to get rid of the
unnecessary so usually a system uh we we
agree and we understand that is made up
physical systems made made up of
constituents that could be the molecules
the atoms the nuclei the the protons the
nucleons uh and so on depending on the
level of description you choose
then you so you set up this bunch of
molecules which are the ingredients of
your object of study that's not yet a
system you have to explain or describe
how they interact with each other for
example in a molecular Dynamic
simulation you want to describe uh what
kind of potential uh like ler Johns our
spheres uh soft spheres and things like
that okay so these are
uh um internal forces between the
constituents of your
system and then you also have to um
because most of the times your system is
confined for example the air in this
room is confined by the walls or the
water here is confined by the bottle and
uh so you want to uh describe uh also
the what I would call the external
forces as something
that puts in the model the effect of the
walls but these effect external forces
must be particularly
simple and there it's written that
you should U the those forces should not
depend on the coordinates of
constituents that are not
the constituents of your
system so what does that mean for
example the walls yes the walls are made
of molecules so when I
have a molecule of oxygen that goes and
hits the wall and it bounces back uh
what affects that
bouncing is certainly the molecules of
the W okay but you don't
need
to uh describe to include the the
molecules of the W in your model unless
you're interested in the effects also of
what happens inside the wall you could
just describe that as a like
a mirror bouncing or in elastic bouncing
or in elastic bouncing can Define rules
of how the walls behave when particles
go uh and uh go and uh hit
them uh so these
rules may depend on some control
parameters for example where the wall is
you could have a classical piston on you
can move a wall okay so and so you
control the position of the wall you
could also
control
um other with other parameters what the
worldall does to your particles okay as
long as it that effect is not um
dependent on within your model of uh
the coordinates of those uh
particles so if the external forces are
of this
kind then we can call it a
system and here is a counter example for
example suppose I have a hydrogen
atom with a proton and an electron and
we all know that
electrostatics Mak such that the the
force uh um sorry for
Interruption so the force between proton
and electron depends on the relative
distance of of of between the
two and
so if I have an electron which is bound
in an atom and I want to consider it as
my system I
cannot that cannot be a system
because the for the external Force
depends on the
coordinates of the
proton so if you want to consider that
situation you have to INE include the
proton in your
system or you have
to or you can only do it if the electron
is in a situation where the effect of
the proton is independent of the
relative
position those are very
few except if the electron is very far
away from the proton so like is a free
particle Okay so the word system is
loaded and as I said uh most of the
times you need your system which is
confined by say the walls according to
those rules and also you need another
system to be outside which is capable of
interacting with it for example uh
usually we call that the environment of
the system
which in principle is the rest of the
universe but in practice is that little
part of the rest of the universe that is
relevant to your uh
application okay so once we have defined
the word system we said well we want to
study the properties so how do we study
properties well we go to the lab and we
do
measurements those are are called in
general physical observables the things
that you can measure are physical
observables and they correspond to
measurement procedures so uh recipes
that you apply in a
lab uh that you should be able to apply
in any lab so the given recipes should
not be lab dependent otherwise it
gives something that is not um feature
of your system it's a feature of your
system in your lab so the lab is part of
your
system okay but it's that's not enough
not all physical
observables can be called
properties in order for them to be
called properties you need the result or
the outcome of the measurement to be
dependent again within your model on a
single instant of time
so take this example a point Mass
particle that moves along the
trajectory so yes if you take two
instance of time T1 and T2 and measure
with a stick the
distance uh between those two
points that's certainly a physical
observable you measure it there is a
measuring procedure take the stick and
measure it but it depends on two times
it's not a
property even if you divide it by the
time interval between those two instants
uh you get a ratio which looks like a
you would call it the average uh travel
travel distance but that's again not a
property because it depends on both T1
and
T2 instead we all know that if you take
the limit of T2 go going to T1 and
measured only for a short uh uh distance
that same ratio that one tends to a
property that we call the velocity so
that is a property and it it is assigned
to the time T1 to the single uh time
interval so this is what we mean by
properties and properties there are many
properties that you can uh uh
describe and that they are defined by
the various measurement process
procedures that you can devise in order
to stud to study your
system uh for
example if this is my system I could
count how many molecules are in there so
counting is a good maybe difficult but
it's a well defined uh measurement
procedure so I can count how many
molecules and if there is not only water
but maybe there is also carbon dioxide I
should count how many water molecules
and how many carbon dioxide maybe some
oxygen some nitrogen uh all right then I
can also measure
if my system is um variable volume not
this bottle but if if this is a variable
volume uh
container um then I can also measure the
volume at a given instant of time right
so that's another it's not really
property because it's the value of one
of those that we would call the
parameters of the external that
characterize the external
forces and these parameters yes for a
lot of um situations in which you want
to study properties of
substances volume is the main and only
parameter but
uh as you go especially for small
systems that's not true anymore so the
shape of your container
matters we will see we more about this
uh so for example if you want to
describe the geometry of this um room uh
you need many parameters this is it is
just a box it would be L1 L2 L3 but if
you consider all the detail
uh like there is a there is a there is a
corner there you got tables how many
parameters you need you need a lot of
parameters and they all count for some
properties but maybe not so these are
still just the
parameters at that instant of time and
then you can start measuring uh
properties
properties depend on um the model you
are considering for example
suppose um suppose I consider a the
simplest
uh mechanic classical mechanical uh uh
system a particle a single particle in a
box and let's make this box one
dimension so it's even simpler just it
can move back and forth between as X
goes from Zer to
L
okay okay so this is a your particle a
point
mass m you have to specify M so it's a
parameter of your uh of your system the
number of
particles uh at times T well it's equal
to one it's just one particle at any
time so it's a constant also
m is just m at any
time what else can I measure well I can
measure where the particle is so that's
X that may
change so that's a variable
property I can also uh measure x dot
the rate of change like we did there for
velocity okay so it turns out as you
know
that these two essentially or their
equivalent position and
momentum uh are the independent
properties if you measure
those with those measurement results you
can compute all other properties of that
system
uh so the list of properties this P1 P2
dot dot um is typically
infinite why well because uh even for
this simple system if I know X may I
maybe I want to compute X squar or X
cubed or x to the n and n can be
anything so uh I have an infinite number
of properties
but I could shorten the list by just
using the independent ones or a set of
independent ones okay so let's say that
these in this list are the independent
ones those that are strictly needed in
order to compute all the other
properties all right so if you know at
one instant of time T all these numbers
because each one of them is a number so
if you have that list of numbers there
is nothing else you can say or you can
measure about your system at that
instant of time there's no other
property so that thing fixes all the
properties that is what we call State so
the state of a system is a list of
numbers from which you can compute uh
all its properties at one instant of
time
the same
system let's make
it here in another theory for example
not for example another important theory
is quantum
mechanics and then you know that quantum
mechanics the story is a bit uh more
complicated
because uh for example example if you
want to measure
position um cannot really talk about or
you're not completely allowed to think
of the particle adding position until
you measure if you ask the particle
where are you so you make a measurement
uh a measurement act for position the
particle is compelled to give you an
answer so it will answer yes and here
but you cannot
um infer from that single act of
measurement that the next time you have
the same system in the same state if you
perform a measurement act the particle
give you the same answer all you can
predict is the probability all you can
represent is the probability to get an
answer so the so uh if the probability
to have the particle between X and X
Plus
DX and the probability is the this the
area here of this curve and this curve
uh is obtain like
the the it's the wave function modulus
squared something like
that times
DX okay so that's the probability
density uh
and okay
so for this
particularly
simple uh quantum mechanical
System since you need a function in
order to describe the
probabilities um a function is an
infinite set of
numbers because it has a value here
there's another value here and another
there so this is an infinite set of
numbers so this is a system which has an
infinite number of independent
properties which are though U thanks to
mathematics expressible in terms of a
single
function in more complicated situations
uh the function is not the wave function
and is called the the density
operator but uh still it's a
mathematical object that contains all
the probabilities of measurement Act of
any uh physical observable that
qualifies as a property so having raow
of
t u gives you allows you to compute the
values of all uh uh properties for a for
a Quantum system
okay so that's the word
State usually one says
in
in Easy exp exposition of thermodynamics
one says well the state of the system is
it condition at a given instant of time
okay that's what we mean by Condition
it's a list of numbers all the values of
all the properties
the next stage is that if I want if I
know the state of a system and actually
here I'm going to use the letter
A to represent um uh okay we use it for
several
purposes the Box typically represents
the idea of system and a is the name of
the
system a sub one
it's
really a at time T1 so a sub one is
defined as uh the list of all the
properties at the given instant of time
T1 that's just for short
end so if I know now the state I want to
see how the state evolves in
time and the state
namely the
properties can change in
time uh by many reasons due to many uh
uh phenomena some of them are related to
the effect of internal
forces like particles in a box that
would Collide and the effect of a
collision uh makes their positions
change uh
they are due they may be due also to the
external forces collision with the
wall or change of the position of a
wall
okay so somehow you could uh say that if
you're
not playing around with the parameters
of the system changing the walls uh or
moving the walls uh and what happens is
just due to the internal forces uh you
call that internal Dynamics you call it
a spontaneous
process within the system it happens all
within the
system if
instead the the change of your state so
the change of the properties is due to
uh either what uh to what you do to the
to the walls to the moving of the
parameters
or to what happens uh on the outside of
your system so
if I have some hot hot air that goes
around this this bottle and therefore
there's a heat exchange through the wall
that is going to heat up the bottle or
maybe cool it down you put the bottom in
the refrigerator it cools
down all right that
uh is an
interaction and
uh interactions are very several kinds
and we we will spend time in describing
and U giving models for these kind of
interactions first of all work and then
heat you will notice that uh we will
Define heat we will not we do not start
from
heat and this is very important uh if
you're fan of um logical
consistency because uh heat uh is
typically
defined uh by euristic arguments and by
a lot of hand waving even by the best
physicist so if you go uh there is a
series of lecture I'll mention another
in a moment that you may know by Fineman
that you find on YouTube he was a
wonderful
professor in the
60s and U he has this very funny
lectures was a great teacher and you
should see how uh he how much hand
waving he does in order to describe what
heat is because it has to do with molec
agitation and all that all right yes you
can do it that
way and you see here we do it in
entirely different way which is
equivalent but uh you will see where it
where it deres from it is a heat is
going to be a consequence of the laws of
thermodynamics
uh which which is the way it should
because after all heat as you correctly
mentioned is
a it's a PEC peculiar concept of of
thermodynamics so uh how could
you pretend or or or or or attempt to
describe it by just using mechanical
Concepts all right more of that uh as we
go
along um if a system under goes uh
spontaneous processes and is unable to
affect the state of the environment we
call it an isolated
system all right so we have the state
and we want to describe how the state
evolves in
time now this picture is a
trajectory but this trajectory is you
have to understand it as a a trajectory
in state space so
uh for every independent
property you should think of having
suppose you have uh just three
independent properties like XY
z uh then the state is a point here but
if I have more independent properties I
need more axis one for each independent
property so I need a multi-dimensional
space
not easy to draw on the Blackboard but
easy to well easy to imagine it's an
abstract idea so that's what we mean by
uh State space and the state that
evolves in time we call it the
trajectory
typically the description of the the
trajectory in your in our models is the
Sol
solution of a differential equation that
we call the equation of motion of the
system which says the rate of change of
the
State uh is some function of the state
itself and of the various forces
external forces or parameters of things
that you can control from outside of the
external forces like squeezing the
bottle or things like
that okay so that's the equation of
motion if your
model has the equation of motion like in
uh molecular Dynamic simulations I
believe you do have the equations of
motion and those are exactly what you
solve in order to see the system
evolve then
by analyzing that equation of motion or
maybe the results maybe the results will
suggest ideas about analyzing the
equation and finding some um
General uh features of that time uh
Evolution these features if you can
prove them that they are theorems of
equational
motion some
of these
theorems are
features of all models good models
successful models of physical
reality in other words what I'm saying
is
that if you're describing a piece of of
physical
reality with a with your
model that
model uh so it have equation of
motion it we and that equation of motion
will have a couple always have a couple
of uh theorems no matter what the what
the system is small or large complicated
or simple
um those two theorems are General
features of all modeling assumptions for
modeling um or or modeling of of
physical reality uh then
is what we call I mean they become so
important these results because they're
General that we call them
laws like law of conservation of
momentum
uh and here in particular we will be
concerned about those that have to do
with energy and entropy
but the message here is that
uh these
results if you add the equation of
motion are theorems of the equation of
motion however there is an alternative
suppose you don't have the equation of
motion or you don't want to solve the
entire equation or motion for your
system because perhaps it's too
complicated I mean can you imagine
solving the equation of motion for 10 to
the how many I mean 10 to the 23
particles uh U if you do your molecular
Dynamics
simulations the number of particles may
be I don't know million but not 10 to
the
go so not only it is Impractical to
actually do
it but
uh is actually
useless
because you can uh extract uh a lot of
information by by first of all studying
smaller systems as long as they're not
too small we will
see uh but
also you may not need all the details of
the time
Evolution however even if you
give up the description in terms of a
full dynamical description in terms of
the full equation of
motion you shouldn't forget about these
two theorems that any equation of motion
must
satisfy at that level of the scription
you call them fundamental principle you
call them laws you call them
postulates they become the starting
point something that you
know
uh must be satisfied by your
model and so instead of describing the
entire time Evolution we
use when we can or when it is
enough we use the idea of process the
idea of process is not only an initial
and a final state of your system on
which you want to check that those laws
are are
satisfied yes you do need an initial and
final state but you also need to
describe the
effects that the time evolution of your
system induced in the uh rest in the in
the environment of the system
so how do I
describe the effects on the environment
of the system well let's call B the
environment the effects on
b i describ by the change of its
state what else can I do more than just
saying how all the properties of the
change during this
process so I lose track of the details
of how it goes from A1 to A2 and how the
environment goes from B1 to
B2 uh and that's the
simplification but I need to describe
the initial and final states of my
system and of the environment
that so that's is what that's the idea
of
process the meaning of the word
process and now we get uh ready to um
this
um to introduce the first
law in order to introduce the first flaw
we need uh to
Define so a particular kind of process
that allows us to
connect this more general theory that we
are constructing to what we know from
mechanics so we consider the simplest uh
mechanical object something like
that here it's represented by a a mass
in a gravity field like
weight that's why we we're going to call
this particular kind of process a weight
process so a weight process is one in
which the external effect you remember
here this the external effect is the
change of state of your system in this
case for the weight process B is just
the weight or the only effect that
occurs outside of your system is the
change in height or El
of your
weight of a
weight so if if you have a process like
this your system changes from one state
to another and the only external effect
is the change in elevation of a weight
you call it we call it weight
process if there is no change if the not
even the the weight so if Z1 is equal to
Z2 is equal to
Z1 then there are no external
effects this could be a spontaneous
process but the idea of spontaneous
process is
really uh more demanding it requires
that at all instance of time from T1 to
T2 the weight
outside doesn't move
instead you could have a
zero uh change in elevation weight
process in which it's only the initial
and final elevation of of the weight
that are the same but during the process
it may have went have gone up or down as
long as at the end it goes back to the
initial uh height then it would be zero
okay so why is a way process uh
important
because it
[Music]
enters um the statement of the first
law I know that
usually uh especially in engineering
applications but on not only uh you say
all right I'm going to write the first
law and by first law that what what you
mean is really uh what we will call the
energy balance
equation okay but the first law in fact
the way we're introducing
here uh contains much more than just the
idea of energy conservation which and
and energy exchangeability that is
behind the the energy balance equation
as we will see in a second but uh uh it
also is what guarantees the existence of
property energy for every
system and it does
so because we have loaded the word
system if you go back to the to that
picture of the proton and the electron
okay and I said all right I cannot take
the electron and call it a system it
doesn't qualify as a system and in
fact for this thing which is not a
system I cannot apply the first law and
as you will see the consequence of the
first law will be the existence of
property energy this thing doesn't have
energy you cannot Define the energy of
the electron when Bound in a
proton why not
well yes if you have an electron without
the proton far away it has its own rest
mass and maybe you can Define its energy
as uh us using uh this famous
formula but when it is bound to a proton
and so there is
a electrostatic
interaction uh there is some energy that
is related to this interaction it's
called the interaction
energy it's a property of the
pair and there is no
way no uh logical way in which you can
assign part of this energy to the
electron and part to the
proton so that system doesn't have
energy and so I'm happy that we have
excluded it yes I'll be there in a
moment uh I'm happy that we have
excluded it by our definition of system
so that we we will be able to say that
every system as energy as a property
every system satisfies the first flow
the way we State we state
it but it has to be a system
yes the
limit uh no for by for the electron by
itself
no but if I
consider uh the atom and the atom is far
from everything else
then the
two uh I mean this Force becomes an
internal
force and that energy the interaction
energy becomes part of the energy of my
system so for example in ter ter
of hamiltonians if you familiar with
that you would write the hamiltonian of
the
electron
uh which is the thing that represents
the energy when the electron will be by
itself the the amoni of the proton and
then the interaction energy between
electron and
proton so that's well defined for this
entire system for the combin
for this actually for the only system
you can Define for this
situation but uh you cannot say ah okay
but this is the energy of the electron
no this would be the energy of the
electron if the proton were weren't
there okay
no no no it's just this is just an
example and this is the re the reason
why I need okay suppose you have this is
the moon and this is the
earth okay same
thing there is a gravitational force
okay uh
if you cannot consider just the
moon as a
system if for what you you want to
describe it is important what it's uh
interaction with the Earth
is for the moon for the Moon is simpler
in the sense that uh if you consider
short instance of time in which the
Earth is relatively fixed
so there is no change in the relative
distance then maybe for that instant of
time the move the mo the moon will move
a little bit the relative distance will
not change so within that time frame
maybe you can neglect uh the
gravitational effect from from the
Earth but it's exactly the same um uh
idea or um
or say suppose this is the air molecules
like o2 molecules that are in this room
and this is
the
cement molecules in the
wall if
I can model the cement molecules in such
a way that they are uh they imply a
fixed um effect on the molecules
outside so that this becomes an external
force that does not depend on the
position or or the movement of the of
the the cement molecules in the wall
then this is an external force and
essentially what I do is substitute
this with a an effective
potential uh uh of the out side onto my
internal molecules and that effective
potential is a way to describe external
uh
forces
okay so and this is what you need to do
uh in order to come up with something
that you can call a system and to which
you can assign an energy that's what any
model in physics is is uh is um is
about all right
I'll be happy to discuss it later more
if you
want later on any
day okay so all right so what's the
first law first law
says this important uh it's actually
made up of two
statements the first one is that you
take any
system and take any two states of your
system they can always be interconnected
via a wave
process so it's it's a matter of
existence in your
model you must allow this in order for
it to be a good
model you have to find a way to
interconnect now there is something
wrong in this slide I'll have to correct
it the
arrow because the law doesn't
say that you can always do it in this
direction it says you can interconnect
them so if if you cannot go from A1 to
A2 then you can do it from A2 to
A1
okay the second Ascension is
about how
much potential energy because we from
mechanics we know that the the weight
that goes up and down in gravity field
has a change in potential energy okay
so the potential energy uh change of
your weight here depends
only on the pair of states
not on the particular way or a
particular weight
process with which you can go from one
to the other or in other words all way
processes that interconnect those two
states have the same external
effect or equivalent at the external
effect
because sure I'm using the weight in a
gravity field build as a prototype of
mechanical effect but you could also use
um a charge in an electric
field or you could use a a point mass
that changes from one velocity to a
higher velocity so the kinetic energy
changes anything that is purely
mechanical is the right hand side of
that it's this external effect
and so um
yeah those two assertions in the first
law allow you to define a measurement
procedure for property energy because as
we said before a property is
defined by a measurement procedure and
what's the measurement procedure for
energy well you come to my love
with your system in a given uh State and
you ask me to measure uh its energy and
I take your
system and I ask you to
pay uh and then I'll tell you before you
leave that
look really yeah on the door is written
that I measure energy I actually measure
energy
differences okay
so you have to pick another state of
your system that I will consider as a
reference and then I will measure the
difference in energy between those two
states and how do I do
it well once you're gone because I don't
want to uh show you my secrets I go on
my shelves and find way processes and I
find one that fits that allows me to
change the state of your system from the
reference one that you have chosen to
the actual State you're interested
in and I measure how
much um gravitational potential energy
change uh the weight has undergone when
I did that so that's a that's a
measurement procedure and I'll give you
the
number of
course the units are already those of
potential energy so they the of energy
Jewel in
si and
uh
um and what's nice of these two
assertions is that they Val for any
system any well defined system
here and so and so you in principle can
find this uh weight process for any pair
of states
using that
definition you can prove now if you're
interested in the proof go to the
book because I want to go quickly over
these things because presumably uh these
are uh easy Concepts but uh the proofs
are not that uh obvious but you can
prove from those
statements this fact that um
energy differences are
additive so if I consider a system which
is composite of two
subsystems namely the definition of
system applies for each of them so I
consider a composite system C which for
example could be the entire mini
Universe namely my system plus the
environment or could be just two systems
so system C doesn't have to be isolated
ated
and in in either case you can
prove by applying that same measurement
procedure that defines energy that we
have just seen if you apply to
system a in state A1 you get a
number I call it e energy of system a in
state T1 or sayate state one
B in this I apply the measurement
procedure I get the value for for for
B and then I
also apply the measurement procedure to
to the composite system when uh the
state of the composite system that I
call
C11 is actually
C11 is actually A1 B1 so it means that
the it's it's the state in which
subsystem a is in state one and
subsystem B is in state
B1 all
right the theorem
says that the difference between
energy the difference in energy for
system C from with respect to the
reference is equal to the sum of the
differences uh of of energy for a and b
with respect to their respective
references
provided provided that I have chosen as
reference a compatible reference for
system C so uh I cannot choose
arbitrarily the value for the reference
uh energy for a and for B and also for
C
otherwise uh I cannot I do not get
additivity of the values I only get
additivity of the
differences all
right
another almost trivial consequence of
the definition of
energy is that when the external effect
when they when you have a a weight
process so the only external effect is
the changing height in a of a
weight and the weight doesn't change in
height so there is no external
effect then E2 is equal to E1 so that's
the principle of energy
conservation so energy is conserved in a
no net
effect uh uh weight
process the
other idea which is important is the
fact that energy
can
be uh exchanged so in other words you
U you may have energy of your system so
the energy of your
system uh may
change but if it changes or suppose it
goes down for one system it must must go
up for some other system
uh so this is a consequence of uh the
two aspects that we have just seen
conservation if system C is
isolated we've seen here no change
outside so the energy is concerned
but the energy is also additive so if
you combine these two it says that uh
whatever change of energy occurs for air
a system a is equal an opposite in sign
to the change in B so if it goes down
for a goes up for
B most of the
times our interest is in system a
and so if our focus is on system a the
effect on system
B we sometimes call it uh energy
transferred or actually in most of the
times we call it energy exchanged
between A and
B because the idea is that if if this
appears from a and appears from from B
it has been
exchanged now you
could you could argue well maybe is this
really uh a
transfer and the argument uh um is
fascinating you should uh I I I refer
you to this um wonderful lecture by fan
uh I added this just so you don't have
it in your slide but I'll post it in
today's post with the final slides for
today and there is a link to the
YouTube um lecture in which uh in a very
funny way he uh describes these U
principles of uh great conservation
principles it explains why they're
great
uh but here the reference is because he
explains also that using relativity
Concepts uh but in a simple
way
um it explains that um things cannot
just U if a property is
conserved uh it also must be um actually
transferable um how does you say um
yeah
transferable um across the interface
between one system and the other cannot
it doesn't simply disappear here and
reappear but it's it
moves across the boundary so that's what
we call uh local local
conservation uh all right so for our for
our purposes in order to obtain the
equation that we usually call the energy
balance equation we
rewrite this right hand side with
another
symbol which is this symbol here it's
energy
uh the superscript means
transferred from B to a the arrow
matters
during the time or during the process
one two so during the time interval T1
T2
okay so so that uh with this way of of
of defining uh you can rewrite this
equation as uh the energy balance like
here E2 minus E1 is equal to E
A received from here I already started
simplifying the notation so I dropped
the B but I should have written
B Because
B is the environment of
a and the
arrow on the symbol is the equivalent of
what of what you usually um you're used
to as the like the sign convention for
energy
exchanges now some people like to
say consider uh heat positive If U going
out and work positive if going in or
vice
versa this notation allows you to Define
whatever uh whatever using the
arrow and the
fact that this symbol here which we
would call
Energy exchange can have both positive
and negative
signs negative values if if it is
positive it means that the uh the flow
of energy is in the direction of the
arrow so in that case it's positive if
in but you could also Define it as
positive out in that way the energy
balance is written this
way okay so you choose the sign
convention
which allows you
to avoid having a to have a figure or
figure like here
to give meaning to properties that are
not just numbers because they have
because interactions the energy change
exchanged via an interaction between two
systems uh has not only a value but also
a Direction so it's like a vector it's a
little simpler than a vector because
it's just in or
out but it's it has two items the amount
and the
Direction all right and then sometimes
we also write the energy balance
equation in a rate form so we divide by
the the time interval that
occurs uh between 21
and if that time interval is uh
infinitesimal meaning that we can follow
the process as a function of time we can
follow we actually this is a a more
refined description that allows you not
only in finite times intervals but also
infinitesimal time intervals uh then you
can write it in the form of a
differential equation so the rate of
change of the energy is equal to the
energy the rate at which energy is
transferred into your
system okay so this is the energy
balance
equation
uh yeah I don't know if you survive but
uh I'll try to uh finish maybe a couple
of minutes before but uh I prefer not to
make a take a break because it uh uh it
makes it
um it allows you to go away that's the
problem I don't want you to go
away okay now
um so I want to give the ingredients and
maybe also the statement of the second
law so that you so that you can see that
uh in a couple of hours of uh of lecture
you can uh do
you can get almost to the second
law the second law at least in the
statement that we are going to
adopt has to do with
States and certain types of states in
particular the stable equilibrium States
will play a fundamental role in uh key
role Central role in the second law so
we need to Define what we mean by that
so we can uh classify
States uh according to uh two
criteria so that makes four four
possibilities uh the roles here are
characterized by whether the state
changes in time or does not change this
time and the columns
by what is the cause for those
changes why does it change does it
change because of something that uh
occurs outside so it's an interaction
with an external system with the
environment of the
system or does it
occur uh even if those interactions are
turned
off so for example uh in a spont is
proc and these are the various
possibilities so we call Un steady state
if it changes with time and that is
because of external interactions the
the the the typical
example just to
uh
consider um bath
tub in which you have water coming in
from the foret and you have a drain open
okay so if the flow rate and suppose
that this is a simple simple system in
which uh the
only uh proper
relevant property is the
shape and position of this interface
between Water and
Air okay
so an unsteady state would be one in
which the level changes because there is
no balance between the inflow and the
outflow If instead you have uh that the
state doesn't change in other words you
have a flat
surface that stays put at the same at
the given height all the
time it means that but this is due to
the fact that there is balance between
inflow and outflow that's a steady
state if I turn the flow off and uh
close the
drain and the surface is flat and
doesn't move that is an equilibrium
State If It Moves because maybe I shake
it and there are waves that is a
non-equilibrium
state it in the non equilibrium state
dat the moving aspect is related to the
internal Dynamics not to the um
interactions with the what what's
outside not with external interactions
okay so that's the idea of this
nomenclature that we
use now let's focus on
equilibrium right there is equilibrium
and
equilibrium the concept of equilibrium
is known from
um uh mechanics so I'm sure you've seen
it some somehow
somewhere this the stability of
equilibrium
also is important it is important in uh
mechanics it is important in uh in the
entire uh physics
now if we go back to that idea of uh
describing the change of
state in state space so that's
A1 a of
T1 and this is a of T2 with the
understanding that now the black this
point represents a point in a
multi-dimensional space in which each
axis is an independent property
okay so this is the solution of a
differential equation which is the
equation of motion of your
system all right so if the state is
changing because as time goes on it
moves from here to there this is not an
equilibrium
State okay
an equilibrium state would be one in
which the state does not change so
what's the trajectory the trajectory is
is a
point you start there and you remain
there so that's
equilibrium the question is of
stability is whether trajectories that
are nearby where do they go
okay you know let me you play it with
the with the game of mathematicians who
likes epsilons and Deltas okay uh so the
mathematician in this case the
mathematician's name is
liapunov maybe there is
a not sure about
U right sorry for the spelling maybe
it's wrong
I'm not sure about the O
there yeah I don't think there is there
is okay all right so yuno
says give me if the state this state
equilibrium state is stable give me any
small number
Epsilon then I can
find a smaller number Delta which is a
function of Epsilon
such
that if I consider uh all the states
that are within distance
Delta uh from the equilibrium State So
within this small uh hypers sphere ball
of radius
Delta any
trajectory that
goes that has a point in there
will not evolve farther
away than the bigger
sphere so it will stay closed so to
speak that's the
idea so this would
be
stable but actually this this definition
of stability is
locally locally
stable okay so then that would be a
feature of this
state and also of that
state
however and I'm not going to because I
don't remember it and doesn't matter uh
to give you the Epsilon version of the
uh meta stability but it can be done I
can give you the reference for
that there is a difference between this
locally stable uh state and equilibrium
State and these other locally stable
equilibrium State this one which we call
Meta
stable is such
that look what I can do I
can in a weight
process
take this mass or whatever it is take it
up he up to the Casp and then take it
down to this same level so that we are
at the same level
here so in order to do that I had to
spend some uh energy from the weight
outside to pull the mass
up but then that
energy uh is given back to the
weight at least if I get exactly to the
same
height at that stage I have been able to
do what I have been able to change the
state into a different an entirely
different state this
one which if I let it go it will start
bouncing back and
forth okay so definitely this situation
in which the thing bounces back and
forth is different from this one all
right so
stable equilibrium
state I'm sorry this meta stable
equilibrium State I have been able to
change it to a different state without
leaving any external
effects whereas this is not possible for
these lower U lowest uh energy
equilibrium
State because if I want to go if you
want to change it
wherever I want to go I need to spend
some energy and it will not return it
back to
me all
right so with this in mind the idea and
the actual definition of stable
equilibrium state which is important
very important for the statement for our
statement of the second law
is stay equilibrium state is an
equilibrium state that cannot be
changed uh without
leaving uh
net external
effects
without uh net external effects I cannot
change a stable equilibrium
State and why is that
important oh sorry uh right I have the
time no okay why is that important we'll
return then to the previous
slide because the second law is about
this question IT addresses and gives an
answer to this question how many stable
equum states does a system
have we all know the answer that
mechanics gives no mechanics
says one only one is the minimum
energy provided of course you have
fixed uh the number of particles and the
values of the parameters of your
external
forces okay
so that's the answer in
mechanics there is only one equilibrium
state
however the statement that we will uh
adopt which is due to atopos and
Kenan uh is
that no in
thermodynamics that's not
true uh there is a one stable
equilibrium State once you have
fixed the numbers the number of
particles and the values of the
parameters you have one equilibrium
State stable equilibrium state for every
value of the
energy which of
course appears to be a
contradiction
with uh mechanics and as you know people
have G uh on for
a cental talking about this uh
discrepancy between mechanics and
thermodynamics and how do we resolve it
and so on we'll see that there is no
discrepancy and there is no um serious
uh problem the moment we realize that
the States considered in mechanics is
just a subset of the States considered
in thermodynamics
uh and it actually we will see that this
is the subset of states for which the
entropy is equal to zero but we haven't
defined entropy yet entropy definition
will come next time uh and uh uh so for
the moment I think I would finish since
I promised five minutes earlier uh and
uh we'll uh take it uh from here
okay