Next, we will have our last speaker, Dr.
Masashi Hirose. He is the co-founder and
CEO of NanoQT, who is working on very
exciting key technologies to enable
modular quantum networks and
communications. So, it's all yours,
Masashi.
Thank you for the introduction. Um, hi
everyone. My name is Masashi Hirose. I'm
CEO of NanoQT.
Um, it's a special pleasure for me to
speak here today. I did my PhD at MIT in
quantum technologies about, um, just a
decade ago. And it's amazing to see how
far the quantum industry and also
initiative at MIT evolves, uh, in the
last, uh, decade. And it's also honor to
follow, um,
great talk by Professor, you know,
Donner and also Bill, and also Takaya
from Qera.
Because NanoQT is among the many who
deeply believe in the long-term
scalability of neutral atom system.
And our work is indeed to build to
extend their advantage into the next
phase of quantum computing.
NanoQT, um, is a Japan-based hardware,
uh, quantum quantum hardware startup
developing a key missing component in
the industry, that is a quantum
interconnect. The hardware foundation
for modular, scalable, and networked
quantum computing.
In the next few minutes, I'll cover who
we are,
the coming scalability challenge, and
our solutions, uh, the nanofiber cavity
interconnect.
Let me start from the overview of the
company. Um,
NanoQT develops a quantum interconnect
technologies and also system
architecture for quantum, uh, computing
and communication.
Our core technology, uh, is engineering
capability of an ultra-low loss
nanofiber cavity to enable the cavity
quantum electrodynamics, which is called
cavity QED.
Which has been well-known phenomena in
the physics textbook for decades, but
the commercializations of cavity QED
technologies, especially for quantum
information processing context, has been
very challenging because engineering the
ideal cavity is very, very hard.
After a decade of R&D work in here in
Japan, uh, we overcome, uh, the
challenges, and that's how we founded
the NanoQT in in a two 2022.
We are still early phase, but in the
last, uh, three years, uh, we rapidly
expand the operation, uh, including the
development of IP, and also we form the
one of the largest quantum hardware team
in Japan, consisting of, uh, 15, more
than 15, uh, PhD scientists engineer,
including, uh, three MIT alumni, and
also we have a one MIT professor as one
of the scientific advisors.
And we are supported by a venture
capitals in Japan, United States, and
United Kingdom. And we also backed by
the, uh, government support. And, uh,
technology development, uh, also
supported by a collaboration with, uh,
you know, other, uh, universities and,
um, companies, including Qera.
So, uh,
what the visions of NanoQT is to really
develop the quantum, uh, networking of
the quantum computers.
So, if we look at the, uh, current
quantum, uh, computing hardware today,
it remains fundamentally monolithic.
A single quantum, a single QPU must hold
host all qubits locally, and this
architecture will hit the limit.
For example, in the neutral atom
systems, the number of qubits, uh, per
unit is limited by, uh, laser power,
optical access, and imaging resolution,
etc., which constrain how large a single
device can become.
So, the projection is around 100,000
qubits, but we'll definitely definitely
need to change kind of architecture to
to be a, uh, large systems with more
than millions of qubits.
And the second bottleneck of this
monolithic structures is that the
today's QPUs are completely decoupled
from quantum communications, which is
another actually quantum advantage we
should capture.
What we want to achieve here from from
from here is to develop the networked
and modularized quantum, uh, like QPU.
And in this world, like multiple QPUs
linked through the interconnects, behave
as one larger logical processor,
allowing qubits scale to grow, uh,
without the constraint of a single
device.
And also entanglement distributed over,
um, long distances by optical fibers
integrate the quantum computing with
communication, enabling the multi-site
and multi-user quantum operations.
To drive these transitions, we need a
device called a quantum interconnect.
So,
what the should a quantum interconnect
actually look like? So, we think that
the
three key elements are critical to
design
the quantum interconnect. First, the
cavity QED system unlocks the
efficiency. We need a device
designed along the cavity QED to drive
the efficient
media conversion between matter qubits
and a flying qubits.
And a second,
optical fiber remains very effective in
even in a quantum context in order to
carry a flying qubits like a photons
across distances. And how we kind of
integrate into the optical fiber is is a
critical from architecture perspective.
And the thirdly, QPU-centric is very
essential.
And I want to emphasize this at the
point because most of the market
solutions claimed as a quantum
interconnect is indeed operating as off
unit.
What we believe is that direct
integration into the QPU is essential to
achieve the minimum loss and a latency
and required for the quantum computing.
So, these principles leads to our
solutions for the fiber-based quantum
interconnect, which is fully end-to-end
waveguide cavity architectures
and natively integrated into the neutral
atom-based QPUs.
And that architecture allows us to, you
know, drive the systems in high
bandwidth aligned with the QPU clock
rate of the neutral atom-based QPU.
What enabled this to realization the
technology comes from actually
proprietary device called ultra-low-loss
nanofiber cavity systems, which only
NanoQT has the capability to develop.
This unique actually the cavity systems
host consists of
nanofiber regions, which whose a
diameter is around like a few hundred
nanometers.
And that nanofiber region is sandwiched
by a pair of the fiber Bragg gratings
developed at the core of the fiber.
This actually millimeter lengths of
long,
you know, the cavity systems can host
like hundreds of neutral atoms at the
same times.
And we actually make this device
from the commercially available optical
fibers
without actually
adding
substantial loss.
And the current performance of the
cavities is characterized by a number
called finesse aligned like the 4,000.
Which actually enables us to drive the
strong coupling regimes of the matter
qubits and photons.
And this architecture allows us to
seamlessly integrate into the
neutral atom-based QPU thanks to the
actually common technologies such as
optical tweezers.
So, we can directly install this cavity
systems inside the chambers of the glass
cells of the,
you know, neutral atom-based QPU
systems.
So, lastly,
um
just let me conclude from the the
potential collaborations opportunities.
We are looking for technology partners,
strategic investment partners in
different dimensions. Um What first is a
technology co-development, especially
around development of ultra-low-loss
optical fiber, nanofabrication and
packagings.
And also,
we are looking for the partners to
generate the use case
because our device modularize the
standalone QPUs to be multi-users
QPU set you know, distant locations.
This adds the new functionality to the
QPU and a lot of like actually potential
use cases to be explored.
And lastly, we are also looking for
investment opportunity from kind of
strategic players.
And yeah, that's all. Thank you very
much and I look forward to the the
conversation.
Oh, lastly, yeah, we have a lot of
actually the technology publication
behind what I, you know, what I
presented today. And if you're
interested in, I would recommend to, you
know, access to those, you know,
literatures to understand our
technologies and application, too.
Thank Thank you. Masashi, thank you so
much. And since we are running out of
time, so we won't be able to have Q&A,
but I would encourage you our audience
to reach out to Masashi on their website
at NanoQT or you can come to us,
iop.mit.edu,
if you want to follow up.