So
next we will so we we're switching away
from metric basis and we talk about
differentiation.
So if we have a function
uh on R say
uh and then we say that
that uh that x that f is differentiable.
at x0. If the limit here
if the limit uh f ofx minus f of x0 if
the divided by x - x0 if this limit here
exist
um if this limit here exists
as x go to x0
this here This here this quotient here
is usually called the difference quotion
and it's always of course when you form
this different quotient it's always
assumed obviously that x is not equal to
x0 so that the denominator makes sense
right so if this limit here as x go to
x0 if this exists then we say that the
function f is differentiable at x0 and
the limit is called the derivative of f
at x0 and this is how it's denoted.
Okay.
So now
the simplest possible example of this
would be
uh that suppose that you're looking at a
function that is constant. of f is equal
to f for some constant
uh c
uh then if you're looking at this
difference quotient so f of x - f of x0
x - x0
well the value at any point is c so this
here is c minus c / X - Y X 0 and so the
denominator is zero. So this whole thing
is zero and so of course the limit this
is zero for each X
and also it takes zero. So in particular
of course the limit here exist. So the
limit here of the different quotient
uh exist
and it's equal to zero right because
it's zero for all x for a given x0.
So that would be like the simplest
possible example. The second simplest
example, second most simple example
would be that you're looking at a linear
function. So let's say that f ofx is
equal to x, right? In this case, the
difference quotient.
So the difference quotient here,
well this here is x.
This here is x0.
So this here is for each x and x0. This
is one. So the limit of course in this
case also exist.
The limit here exist and it's equal to
to one.
Right? So in this case, so in this case
f is differentiable
at all points and the derivative at all
points is equal to zero. In this case, f
here is also differentiable
and the derivative at all points is
equal to one.
Okay. So now in general how do we
compute the so how do we compute the
derivative of a function?
Uh how how do we
compute the derivative
and for that there are some some basic
uh laws how to compute it. So there's
these laws
um the sum rule
uh what's usually called the liess rule.
uh the quotient rule
and then uh also the chain rule.
Okay.
Now let me uh look at the first three
rules first.
So um
I have uh two functions f and g they are
defined say on r but it could have been
a subset of r
uh and uh I'm assuming that that they
are both
and both
right actually I need we'll need one
okay so both Um
f and g are differentiable
at x0.
Then we have the following. So we have
the following lema.
Uh
uh one is we have that. So one and this
is really the sum rule.
We have that the sum here f plus g. So
the sum of these two functions this is
the function that is just in x is just a
sum of f ofx and g of x. We have that
this function here
f + g is differentiable
at x0
and the derivative f + g. The derivative
of this nx0 is just a sum of the
derivative.
Okay,
let me let me prove this one here right
away. So let me
so let's prove this.
So we have the sum. So uh we we will we
are going to look at so we form the
difference. So form the difference
quotion.
So f + g
at x - f + g
at x0
x - x0
right so now what is this? So this here
is
uh this is just f of x plus g of x
minus and then f of x0 plus g of x0
and then divided by x - x0 right
and so then you can split this up into
two. You can write this difference
quotion as if you split it up. If you
collect the fs in a nominator.
So I just collect the fs
and then afterwards I collect the and I
put it on two different fractions.
Separate them out and then I collect the
G's.
And now you see that because f was
differentiable at x0 this thing here as
x go to x0 this here goes to fprime. So
this here goes to f prime of x0. This is
what this difference quotient here. And
this difference quotient goes to g prime
of zero. So you have that indeed it does
converge and this is what it converts to
right and so this prove that the sum of
these two functions is also
differentiable and their derivative is
the sum of the derivative okay the next
thing we will prove is len rule but
before that I need to kind of step back
and I want to so before proving so the
next uh maybe I'll just state it and
then we'll go back and we need something
The next is what's called liveness rule.
So it's all you know you could also call
it product rule but it's really quite
generally called the lieness rule.
And so this is when you looking at the
product of these function. So the
product function,
the product function is a function in x
that is just the product of f ofx and g
of x
[Applause]
and lightness rule.
Lightness rule it say the following
that if f and g are differentiable at x0
then the product of these two function
here
is also differentiable at x0.
And the derivative of the product is the
derivative of the first function at x0
times the value of the second function
at x0 plus the uh the symmetric in f and
g which is the value of f at x0 times
the derivative of g at x0. Right? So the
product is differentiable at x0 also.
And this is what the derivative is. And
in the notes, I just copied a little bit
of thing just for fun from Wikipedia
about lightnings. That was kind of
interesting figure and played an
important role long time ago.
Okay. So before I want to prove this,
let me step back and let me make an
observation about
um
uh what it means to be differentiable at
a point.
So So this is the next lemon.
So you have a function f
on r into r
and and you assume that um uh f so if
f here is differentiable
[Applause]
at x0. Then I claim that then f here is
also continuous
at x0. Okay. Okay. So, so in other
words, different being differentiable is
stronger than being continuous.
In a minute, we will see an example of
something that's continuous but not
differentiable.
And so
uh okay so now let's try to prove that
so right so I'm assuming that it's
differentiable so this means that
this
this difference quotient here
this here has a limit and that limit is
the derivative right as x go to x0.
So this means that um that there exist
uh there exist delta greater than zero
such that
if x here
uh minus x0
is less than delta
right of course I'm assuming that it's
not equal to x0.
If it is less than the difference to uh
between x and x0 is less than delta,
then this difference quotient here then
f of x - f
of x0
x - x0
- frime of x0. this thing here have to
be less than one right I mean this is
just using that this limit exists and
I'm sort of using in place of epsilon
I'm using one right
okay
[Applause]
now so this means just multiplying over
and And multiplying over you get that f
ofx
minus f of x0
uh minus
frime
uh of x0
this thing here
uh times I'm I'm multiplying both sides.
So I'm multiplying
both sides
uh by
uh x - x0. This is a positive thing,
right? So I'm multiplying both sync by
that. So then I get this thing here x -
x0.
Uh and then I get less less strictly
less than x - x0, right? Because this
here is strictly positive.
because x is not equal to x0. So I have
that and so I get that. So I now I just
split it up. So I have that f ofx - f of
x0
is now less than
x - x0
plus frime of x0.
time uh x - x0
right this is just the triangle
inequality that we've used many times
just on
right
and so now you see that um that if you
now
um so given
so now if you so now and this here of
course I can also write
uh like this
sorry I can just factor this out and I
can write it as 1 + frime of x0
like this fine and so now if I want this
thing here so so now you can if you were
to right so now you want to prove that f
is continuous at x0 so you want this
here to be less than some given epsilon
So given epsilon
epsilon greater than zero
you uh let
delta 1 be like the minimum
of uh if you let said
delta 1 to be the minimum of the delta
that I already chose. So then I have
this inequality
and then um and then uh epsilon
uh over 1 + frime of x0
right
so if I make delta
I choose delta like this then I have
this inequality
I fill in that so now I'm assuming that
this thing here is less than delta 1.
So again I have this inequality because
it's less than delta. So then uh when I
fill in here delta 1
for this then I see that this thing here
times this is less than epsilon.
This here
holds
when
x - x0
is less than delta 1 right again because
if it's less than delta 1 it's less than
delta so I have this inequality and then
I can use that delta 1 since is less
than this
and then I get this inequality
okay so this prove right so this is
really what we want to prove right we
want to prove that if it's
differentiable then it's also continuous
and the continuity here I I proved it
you know with you know epsilon or delta
that you really should prove it like
okay
now let's look at some examples so this
means that if a function is
differentiable
then it's continuous
[Applause]
Let me give you an example
uh of a function that is so let me give
you a few three examples.
The first example is maybe the simplest
one um that so this is the function f
ofx that is equal to the absolute value
of of x. So f here is defined on r into
r
and it's just the absolute value and so
I well the absolute value here so we've
seen before so f here is continuous
it's continuous at all points right uh
in particular of course at zero right
but if you now form the difference
quotient, right? Suppose that x here is
bigger than zero. And now look at the
difference quotient. So the difference
quotient uh
uh quotient
at uh at x0 equal to zero. If you're
looking at that difference quotient and
and you at the you first look at where x
is positive if x is positive then uh f
ofx minus f of 0 x - 0 this difference
quotient here if x is positive then this
thing here is just x. So this is x - 0
x - 0. So this here is one right this
difference quotient is one. This is when
x is positive. When x is negative
then the then f ofx
if x is negative then the absolute value
is minus x
right. So the difference quotient here f
ofx minus uh f of 0 which is zero x - 0.
This here is just - x
/ x.
But this thing here is minus one.
So for all if you are if you're looking
at the difference quotient
and you uh that comes from looking at
the derivative as zero. Then when you
approach zero from the right then the
difference quotient is one. When you
approach it from the sorry uh yeah from
the when you approach it from the left
then the difference quotient is minus
one. So it doesn't have a limit right.
It has a limit from the right from the
left but it doesn't have a limit if you
don't restrict where it's coming from.
So this function here
uh is not differentiable. Yeah.
>> So okay. So this is
right. So
so this so this is so so we did this
earlier in the class. So if you take
so
that the difference quotient here
that this thing here is converging to to
some number say a right. This here means
that for all for all epsilon greater
than zero there exist a delta greater
than zero such that
if x - x0
is less than delta
and again
x is is assumed to be different from x0.
If you have that then this difference
quotient here
minus this a
is supposed to be less than epsilon.
And so that's is
okay. And so you see again in this
example that we just looked at where uh
in the example that we just looked at
where uh so in the example
where f ofx was equal to the absolute
value of fx
the if you were graphing it then this
looks like this
right and we saw that the difference
quotion when you approach it over here,
difference quotient was one. When you
approach it over here, the difference
quotient is minus one. So if you take a
little any little interval around zero,
then there the difference quotient could
be either minus one or one, right? But
even however small you make this little
interval, it's not like that it converts
to some number because it has it it is
both you know they're both uh cases
where it's one and cases where it's
minus one.
Okay. So that's that's like the first
example
and again you know of a function that is
continuous
but it's it's not differentiable as at
zero. In this case it was a zero.
Um and maybe a little bit more
interesting example along the same line
uh is uh the following.
So
So um if I so this is again a function
on r into r
and I said f ofx = x * sin of 1 /x. This
here is not really defined at zero. So I
need to define it also at zero. So when
x is equal to zero then I just set it
equal to
to to zero and otherwise I set it equal
to x * sin 1 /x okay
and so the thing is that this function
here so f here is continuous
in particular it's continuous at x at at
when at at zero it's continuous
continuous it's actually continuous
everywhere but but it's mostly
interested in it at zero the graph of
this to remember that sine function sine
function looks like this that at zero
um at zero
at pi
at 2 pi
at 3 pi and so on at all of these
by at all integer multiples also for the
negative ones at all integer multiple of
pi sign function vanishes
and in between here it is at pi / two it
achieves its maximum which is one and so
the function looks like this
so this here is one
right that's how a sign function looks
And so now if you're looking at sine of
1 /x that's going to be a function as
you're going down. So this is so if
you're looking at this here was sine of
x but if you're looking at sine of one
of x as x go to zero this here becomes
very large. So this means that as you're
going to zero it go very rapidly through
these periods where it goes where it's
oscillates between minus1 and one the
value here is minus one
and so as you it will look like this
that uh it will again uh if you're
looking at it will again fluctu it will
fluctuate but it will fluctuate operates
uh much more rapidly. So if this here
say was one over pi
at one over pi 1 over 1 / pi is the same
as pi there it would be zero and it
would like fluctuate
um it would fluctuate so it would look
like something like this but it would
fluctuate
you know
it and then as you're going way it will
fluctuate less less often right so as
you're going down towards zero it will
fluctuate a lot right it always because
sign always is between minus1 and one
the value here will always between
minus1 and one but as you're going
towards zero from the right or from the
left it's going to fluctuate more and
more right as you're going away from
zero is fluctuating less and less.
Okay. So, so this is the function I'm
interested in. And so, but when you
multiply
when you multiply through by X
then you see when you multiply through
by X it's fluctuating but it's always
fluctuating between minus1 and one. If
you
multiply it by x then as you're going to
zero this hair will squeeze down and it
will become the fluctuation will be zero
at zero. So it's easy to see that this
function here so is indeed continuous.
Right?
But let's look at the difference
quotient. So the difference quotient.
So if we're looking at the difference
quotion, so we're looking at and we just
look at the difference quotient at zero.
So this is the difference quotient
and so it's x sin 1 /x. The value at
zero by definition was zero.
And so you see that now this here the x
this here becomes just x sin 1 /x / x.
And so you see that this here cancel
with that. So you just get sine 1 /x.
And so you see that now as x go to so
when x here goes to zero
this here fluctuates. This have
fluctuate
between
minus one and one n1
but it doesn't have a limit right
because it's fluctuated y or why not
right. So this is a this is an example
again this is another example of a
function that is continuous
at zero but not differentiable at zero.
It's actually much worse than the
previous the previous one was the
previous one the example the
previous example that was this example
is much more tame. It is not
differentiable at zero but if you were
restrict to just positive things then
from then it would be differentiable
right if you were you could also define
derivative. In general when we define
derivative we let it be defined in a
neighborhood of that point. So on either
side. But if you were considering where
you were allowing the function just to
be defined at this point and then to the
right say or to the left then this
function would be differentiable. Right?
But the in the in in in this example
here it doesn't matter if you restrict
the interval to just to the right or to
the left. It's still not differential.
Okay.
Right. So this is something about this
example is something about that it
fluctuates wildly
and that is causing it not to be
differentiable. If it wasn't again if if
you if you defined it if you didn't have
this kind of the X here is sort of
serving as some sort of it's dampening
how much it's fluctuating right so if
there wasn't a X here then this function
wouldn't it would just fluctuate
and it wouldn't even be continuous at X0
right but once I put this X on then it
becomes continuous if I put another x.
So if I'm looking at
f ofx = x^2 * sin
1 / x. Suppose I'm looking at this
function. So now I have sort of dampened
dampened the fluctuation even more. And
so if I again looking at the difference
quotient. So so I'm looking at this
function maybe I should be more careful.
So again at zero I need to define it
separately. So I define a function
that is zero at x = 0 and then it is x^2
* sin 1 /x otherwise
if I'm looking at this function then I
claim that this function is in fact uh
French at x at zero and so let's look at
Okay.
So again, I'm looking at the difference
quotient
and the value at zero is zero. So I have
this.
And so this here is now just x²
sin 1 /x. This thing here is then x. And
so you see that this difference quotient
is just this. But this here does
converge to zero as x go to zero.
Right? So this function is actually
differentiable. Right? It's fluctuates
but it's it's more mild the way it
fluctuates.
Okay. Now let me get back to the the
rules. So we proved one uh rule that was
this sum rule.
Then the second rule we're interested in
is when we're looking at the likeness
rule. So we're looking at the product of
these two functions and each function is
assumed to be differentiable
uh at x0 and then we claim that the
product function is also differentiable
at x0 and this is the formula for the
derivative. Right?
to prove this one here I need this fact
that we have now proved that if it is
defensible then it's also continuous at
that point okay so I'm going to use that
fact
and so
and now
so so now so
let's
let's prove
uh of lightness room.
So we have uh these two functions. We're
looking at f of x. We form the
difference quotient.
So this is the difference quotient x -
x0
uh I I we do this trick that we've done
a bunch of times before when we also
looked at products. We had two sequences
and we looked at the sequence that was
the product of the these two. Right? So
if you have just a reminder
that I mean it's not like
but but but
so remember that if you had a sequence a
n and a sequence bn and you knew that a
n converts to a and bn converts to b
then the product here converts to a * b.
Right? So, and when we prove that we use
this little trick with that we are uh
we're splitting the difference between
this and this. Right? And so I'm going
to do exactly the same trick here.
So I'm looking at this thing here. And
so I write this thing here as f ofx * g
ofx
minus and it doesn't really matter
you know where you're inserting it. So
this here it's like splitting the
difference and then I have to add it
again.
So this is certainly the same. I'm just
subtracting it and adding it right back.
And now I split this into two. So I
write this in here. So I So this uh
fraction I split into two. And the first
one I take this one here together. So
and you can factor out f ofx. You can
write it like this. f of x - f of x0
x - x0 right so this is just right I'm
just here I'm factoring out the g of x
and then I'm left with this this is this
and this is giving the denominator like
that this is this part here and then I
have the other part here but there you
see that f of x0 is factoring out
and then I have g of x minus g of x0 x -
x0
like that.
But now you see that as x goes to x0,
right? Well, g was continuous at x0,
right? So this thing here
as x go to x0 this thing here goes to g
of x0 right this one here that was
because g was continuous because it was
differentiable so it was also continuous
this here goes to the derivative
and the second thing here is this here
is just constant
and this here goes to the derivative
like that
right so we have so what we have proven
is this here is as x goes to x0
so you see that we have proven that the
difference this difference quotient here
for the product
has a limit and this is what the limit
is right and so this means that the
product is differentiable
and this here is the derivative and
that's exactly the this formula. Okay,
which was this over here. This formula
here.
Okay, the next thing is that we uh want
to prove the next rule is like this
quotient rule.
So let me prove the quotient rule.
[Applause]
So, Leness, right? Less and
Leness and Newton was the one that was
uh um um responsible for calculus.
Uh and so then the next thing I want to
prove is this quotion.
And so again you have these two
functions f and g
and uh they are differentiable.
at x0 and I'm also assuming that g here
at x0
is is not equal to let's just assume
that g is not equal to zero everywhere
is never is is is is different from zero
everywhere.
And then the quotient rule say that if
you're looking at the quotient here and
you take the derivative of the so it say
that if you're looking at the quotient
here maybe I should so the quotion will
say that that if you're looking at this
thing here this now makes sense because
g does not vanish
This here is differentiable
at x0. And the derivative
the derivative of this function
at x0
is given by the following formula that
it is the derivative of f at x0 time g
of x0
minus uh um f at x0 * g prime at x0
divided by G G² so G of X0 times itself
I'll write that as a square this
here again this here this here is just g
of X0 * G of X0
okay
so now let's try to prove
So we're looking at f ofx f like this at
x minus. So this is the difference
quotient
at x0 divided by x - x0, right? That's
the difference quotion. And so written
out this is f of x
g of x
minus
g uh f sorry f of x0
divided by g of x0
x - x0. So let me put this on a with on
a fraction with a common denominator. So
if I do that then this thing here is
right. So then I'm multiplying
uh by g of x0 both in the denominator
and denominator here. So I'm getting f
of x
times g of x0
and then here I'm multiplying by g of x
in both denominator and denominator. So
getting this thing here
g of x and then it becomes x - x0
and then g of x g of x0
like that.
And so now you can write this thing here
uh as right. And so now you do the same
trick uh as before.
I mean I could have I could have gotten
away uh slightly easier with looking at
a special case of this quotion rule
where f was a constant function one. So
I could do that first and then the
general case I could then from get from
this special case together with the
lens. But I chose to it's most often
they want to do it together anyway. But
if you have to do it together, you have
to use the same trick that we just did.
So we're using
uh that over here.
So uh
so f ofx
g of x0
minus uh and then uh f of uh f of x0
plus uh f of x0
g of x0
uh minus f(x)
g of x. So this is again where I'm
subtracting in the denominator something
and then I'm adding it back up
immediately.
So I have this
like that.
And so now uh if you do that then you
see that. So now you can and now you
split it up again into two fractions.
So we split it up
and so this thing here this thing here
but there you see that there's a g of x0
that factor out. So this is equal to g
of x0 and then you have f ofx minus f of
x0
and then x - x0
g of x
g of x0 like that.
And for the second one, see that there
you there you also have something that's
factor out. And this is f of x0
like that.
And you're getting g of u of x0
minus g of x
over
um x - x0.
uh g of x
g of x here like that.
And now okay so now I can make this
looks nicer. I can this one here cancel
with that.
And so I can write this thing here as 1
/ g of x
f ofx
- f of x0
/ x - x0. So this take care of this.
Here I can um here I can um I will write
it as I will take this one here out. So
I'll write it as f of x0
g of x
time g of x0.
And then I'm left with this thing here.
And what I don't love about this thing
here is it's not quite the difference
quotient because the order of these two
is wrong. So I switch the order. But if
I switch the order then I have to
pick up a minus sign. So I get minus
here. And now it is g of x
g of x0
x - x0 like that.
Okay. And now you see that as x so as x
goes to x0
so now as x
well this one here the function was
differentiable so it's also continuous.
So this goes to 1 / g of x0.
This one here just goes to the
derivative
at x0.
This one here goes to again because the
function is continuous. This goes to
minus f of x0
and then it's what I wrote before as d²
is d of x0 * itself.
And then this in here goes to the
derivative of x0 at zero.
Right? And now I can if I want to I can
rewrite this in here. If I want to put
it back on a common denominator, then I
have to multiply in the nominator and
denominator by g of x0. If I do this, I
get f prime of x0 g of x0
and then I get g^2 of x0 in the
denominator. And then here it's just
those two minus f of x0
g prime of x0.
And so you see that this here is exactly
this formula here this this quotion rule
right. So this proof that if you take
two functions the the one you have in
the denominator if that is non vanishing
so you can form the quotient and if each
of these two functions is differentiable
then the quotient is also differentiable
and this is the formula for the
derivative
right so now why is this already really
really useful
so
so We calculated
we already we calculated so we started
with the example of where f is a
constant right and we saw that it's
differentiable and the derivative is
zero. Then the second example we had was
where the function was x and we saw that
it was differentiable and the derivative
is one. Right? If you now take um if you
now take ax
times uh right so let's just take ax as
the next example
this is like a constant function times
this function so light rule sorry if f
ofx is equal to a * x where a is a
constant lightn will say that the
product of two differentiable functions
is differentiable and the derivative of
This is the derivative of that, but the
derivative of that does a constant
function. So that's zero. So I don't
really have to think about that. So it's
just the a times the derivative of the
second function, but that's one. So this
here is the derivative of that.
Right? So and the next example would be
that you're looking at a x plus say b f
of x is equal to this. Then you can use
the sum
plus you know we know what each of these
is. So you get that this one here is
also differentiable and the derivative
of this function here is also just a and
and you can continue like this that if
you take
um if you use if you now have a polomial
suppose you take a to the power n so f
of sorry uh if f of x is x to the^ n
then you can think about this thing here
as x * X * X * X
and you can use the lieness rule right
and so if you use the leness rule so you
just do it first in the case where f ofx
is equal to x^2 you can think about this
as x * x these are two differentiable
functions so the derivative here is now
the derivative of this so that's 1 times
the other function plus you keep this
one here and you take the derivative of
that. So this is this. So this is 2 * x,
right? And so if you take this function
here using lightness rule,
in this case the derivative it's
differentiable and the derivative
is uh n * x ^ nus one. Right?
So that's so so and and in fact find
even more generally
you know just using the sum and the
likeness rule if you take any
if you take any polomium a n x n + a n
-1 x n minus one
down to
the last sign is being a constant. If
you take a polinomial like this just
using the lieness rule and the sum rule
using those repeatedly
we know that this here is differentiable
and the derivative is just like the sum
of the derivative of these. So this is
going to be a n * n * x ^ n -1
+ n -1 * a n -1 x n - 2
and then the this one here the
derivative is zero. So the last one
you're getting something non-trivial for
is a one
right. So this is just using sum and
license room.
And so this is just using
the sum
plus lightness room
repeatedly.
Okay. Now likewise if you take a
rational function so meaning that if you
take something if f ofx
is equal to some polomium
a polomial
so it's called p
of x divided by uh q of x. So where this
here is a polinomial
and and and so is that right? So now you
can use the uh the quotient rule right.
So the quotient rule will tell you that
as long as you are looking at point
where this here does not vanish. So then
the quotient here is also differentiable
and it gives you a formula for the
derivative in terms of the derivative of
each of these two and each of those two
they can be calculated like that.
So you see it's already already now we
have like quite the derivative of a lot
of functions right we have of all
function and of all rational functions
rational functions again are clos
by other polinomial
okay
so now the next rule uh that we want to
talk about is the the chain rule
So what is the chain rule?
So the chain rule is a little bit
different from those three rules here
and and it is where you take the
composition of functions.
So the next is the chain rule
and again this is about
composition
of functions.
Okay. So I have a function f that goes
say from
say that it goes from some interval a to
b into another interval from c to d
and then I have a function g
that goes from this interval here
into r
because g is defined you So like
whatever the the image of of of F always
if it's in this set this is where G is
defined then you have that uh you can
form
if you take some X in here. So if X here
is in A to B then this here makes sense
and this is now an element here. So this
is where G is defined. So this here
makes sense, right? And this is now what
we call the composition. And we write it
like this. It's important to write it in
the correct order.
And so this is the composition function.
Okay. And uh and the thing is that this
so right. So now the chain rule is the
following.
So the chain rule is a following
theorem.
that if
f is differentiable
at x0
and
and uh g
is differentiable.
at y0 where y0 is equal to the value of
f at x0.
Then the composition then the
composition of these two functions is
differentiable
at x0. And the derivative is equal to
the derivative of g at y0 times the
derivative of f at x0. So this is the
chain rule, right? The chain rule say
that the composition is also
differentiable
at x0. And this is the formula for the
derivative.
Okay, let's try to prove that. Uh and so
that we in this case it's useful to
divide up to two to two cases.
Um
and the two cases to divide up to. So
let me just look at the look at the
special case first and then once we
understand that it's would be clear the
general case would be clear. So let's
make one assumption. So let's try to
prove it.
Uh and but we assume first
that the derivative
I'm going to assume that the derivative
at x0 is not equal to zero. So I'm
assuming that first. What does this
guarantee me? Well, remember that the
derivative is the limit of this
difference quotient,
right? So this is this is the limit.
If this here is not equal to zero,
this means that when x is very close to
x0, this thing here
is
very close to this thing that is not
equal to zero. But then it means that if
you are very close to x0, f ofx cannot
be equal to. So if you have this here,
this implies that f ofx
is not equal to x0
for sorry is not equal to f of x0
for
x sufficiently closed
close to x0.
I'm always assuming of course that x is
not But x is not equal to right.
So, so I'm going to first make this
assumption. And if I make this
assumption, what I get out of it is that
this thing here is not equal to that.
Why is this useful? Because now I can
actually look at this difference and I
can divide by it. Okay.
So, I'm going to
I'm going to just to make things a
little bit clearer.
So I have my function.
So this here is is this f and here I
have g.
Here I have x0.
But under f it's taken to this which is
f of x0. But this I also will denote by
y z right. So I'm denoting just to make
clear y0 is just the value here.
And then I will use uh for I will I will
f ofx
I will denote by y. Okay.
So now I'm looking at the difference
quotient. So I'm looking at f of sorry
I'm looking at g of f of x minus uh g of
f of x0
uh x - x0 that's what I'm supposed to
look at
and I'm can write this thing here
as g of y because this here I also call
y right so you can write it like this g
of y 0
and then I will write it as y - y 0 but
I didn't have this in the denominator up
here so I have to multiply it back on
and then I still have to divide by like
like that right so I can write it like
this this here I'm happy with we'll get
to this in just a taken, but I'm happy
with this expression. The other one I
really want to put it back in in terms
of f. So I'm writing this thing here.
And this thing here, I really want to
put it back in in terms of f. So if I do
that, I write it as f ofx - f of x0
x - x0.
But now you see that as um as x go to
x0, right?
Well, as x go to x0 the because the
function f was continuous at x0 it means
that if x go to x0 then the value at x
which is y will go to the value at x0.
So when when
x goes to x0
we have that y goes to y0
right
so this means that this thing here this
here converge right that's just because
the function f is differentiable so this
here will converge to the derivative so
this the the second factor here is
converging to fprime at x0. The first
factor is but now you see that we just
argued that y goes to y0. So this is
also a difference quotient, but it's a
difference quotient for g. And since y
goes to y z, this difference quotient
here goes to the derivative of g at at y
z.
Right? But that's exactly the formula
that we wanted to prove except that we
made one assumption that the derivative
of f
at x0 was not equal to zero. We made
that assumption only so that this number
here was not equal to zero. Right? And
so we could kind of divide by it.
Right? But actually otherwise
um
right if if you for some reason if y was
not equal to y z
but right then this formula here would
still hold right so it's only the the
the possibility
that uh that y could be equal to y z but
now you see that if you We're just
looking at the difference quotient g of
f
g of uh of y
minus
sorry uh g of f ofx
minus.
So this is the difference quotion that
is the one we really have to look at for
the
for the composition right and this is
what we also called this here is what we
call this thing here is what we called
y0 this thing here is what we call y
and the only case we haven't dealt with
is where f prime
of zero is equal to zero and
y
is equal to y z right this here again
was f of x and this here was equal to f
of x0 so this only this case here we
haven't dealt with right
but you see that if If you if it h if it
so happened that f ofx was equal to f of
z then this difference quotient here the
d the denominator would trivially be
zero right and so you want to prove we
have that if this here was not equal to
zero then we have that this is
converging to the to the derivative
and the only case we have to look at
where this derivative is zero. So we
want we are claiming that so the only
case we're left with that we haven't
dealt with is first of all where the
derivative
so let's see so
let me just write down here clearly the
remaining case
for the chain rule
So the main cases that the derivative at
x0 is zero. Right?
And and we have already observed that if
the derivative is zero but
but
y is not equal to y z. If this is the
case then actually g of f ofx
minus g
of f of x0.
This thing here
still converge in this case here where
this is the case. This here still
converts to zero. Right? So, so we still
have the chain rule
in that case if this here was not the
case. The only thing we have to worry
about is what if y was equal to y z. But
if y was equal to y z when we're looking
at the difference quotient, this is the
difference quotion after all. And so in
that case, this thing here is y z. This
is y z. But in that case the difference
quotion is actually zero already. So of
course it's it's going to be very close
to zero right it's actually is zero
right you see that the remaining case
that's sort of trivial
but we wanted to first exclude it
because we wanted to be able to divide
by this difference right and then once
we have seen that under that assumption
it was it was you know we got the
formula we wanted then we go back and
then we say that not only you know the
the the the the remaining issue was well
first of all
was the case where the derivative was
zero but in fact um you the only case
that was potentially a problem was when
y was equal to y zero but for that it's
the difference quotient was was actually
trivial zero okay so that's the the
chain rule
Um, and so we only have a few minutes
left. Uh, and I won't quite be able to
get through all of the stuff. Uh, but I
can get through one more lema.
And so, and then I'll pick up from from
here uh, next time.
uh the notes are already posted but but
so the last bit of the notes we'll do
next time.
So so the following lema here.
So if you have a function
say from R to R
and you have that X here X0 is a local
max
or min.
So f is a function from r to r that is
that is differentiable.
And uh x0 is a local max or local min
for f.
then uh then
the derivative
at x0
is equal to zero. Okay,
let me remind you what a local max and
local min is. So if you take a function
so a local max similar for a local min
if you have a function here you have
here x0 a local max means that in a
neighborhood of x this point then the
value at x0 is the maximum. So local max
at x0
means
that they exist
delta greater than zero such that
um that if you're looking at the
interval
um to either side of x0 this interval
and you're looking at uh at f here
restricted to this subset then uh then
uh x0 is a local max is a max. So this
means that f ofx zero is equal to the
max
of f where x here is in this little
interval here.
Oops. Like that.
Right. So it's it may not be right. So,
so the idea is that it's just the
function may look like this and this
here is x0. So, you see that in a
neighborhood like this, it looks like
that you have that this x0 is a maximum,
but there might even be somewhere else
where the value is much higher. Right?
So, that's a local maximum and similarly
for a local minimum. Okay? And so I
won't be able to to actually prove this
lema. We we'll prove that next time. Uh
and then once we have that lema, we
prove what's called roles theorem. And
then we will use it to prove the mean
battle theorem. But so but I'll do that
next time, but it's actually in the
notes that I I posted already.