so I'm Anor ala and welcome to the Deep
learning day it's going to be a little
bit more than just deep learning and uh
so we will start with an introduction
and Philip will kind of set the stage
and tell you what the day today will
consist of and you know I hope that you
enjoy okay um yeah thanks for coming so
just going to get a show of hands of who
has taken deep learning class studied
deep learning programmed deep Nets okay
and who has never touched a deep net
doesn't know what a deep net is at all
okay good so I thought we would have a
mix and we're going to try to make this
accessible to everyone but also include
some of the latest technical
content um okay but that helps so many
of you have seen this um I'm sure all of
you have heard of you know deep learning
this is the big one of the big
Technologies driving AI these days okay
so in this first like 15 minutes I'm
going to um kind of give you the
schedule for the day but also give you a
few of the basic building blocks of what
a deep net looks like that we'll then
see elaborated in the remaining
lectures okay so um here's the schedule
and it follows kind of the timeline of
deep learning from 1986 which was when
the uh back propagation algorithm was
published uh which was one of the kind
of first moments in getting an algorithm
to be able to train a neural net to do
something interesting up until
today and um the first 15 minutes is
going to be deep learning and then the
rest of the day will be everything that
you kind of build on top of that which
you could call Deep learning It's
associated with deep learning but it
really goes beyond um the 1980s version
of Deep learning okay so I will give you
the basic U idea of training a neural
network to fit data uh and then kaiming
will come in for the next lecture um on
uh the next part of this text stack
we're going to build up this text stack
which is the stack that powers modern
systems like chat GPT so the next piece
that you really need to understand is
generative modeling this is the main way
that we train our deep Nets these days
is with what we're called generative
modeling
objectives um and then on top of that we
don't just do any old type of model on
any old type of data uh for the really
powerful systems that you're seeing
today uh they're mostly large language
models so we'll have you talk about that
uh of course there are other ideas too
but this is the tech stock uh that we're
going to tell you about today which is
for the kind of modern really powerful
popular systems like language models uh
like chat GPD okay so then um generative
modeling really got to be a big Topic in
deep learning in the 2010s I put down
2014 because that's when two Landmark
papers were published VA vaes and Gans
um but you know it's fuzzy these years
could be shifted around a little bit um
and large language models started
becoming popular around 2020 that was
when gpt3 was published and we're now
currently in the large language model
era of things like chat
GPT okay but things have progressed
beyond that like that's not the latest
thing so the the even more recent thing
which started maybe around
2022 is uh the idea of not just directly
like sampling from the language model to
write random stories but doing what's
called reasoning so I'll talk about that
in the afternoon and reasoning models
are uh what are starting to make
headlines today so for example if you
heard about deep seek R1 uh this is a
reasoning model so I'll tell you what
that
means okay and then the the very last
piece on top of this stock which Antonio
will talk about uh he'll actually talk
before me because we switched the
schedule around but it's it's agents
making systems that uh do reasoning on
top of language models that are built
out of generative models that
fundamentally rest on deep neural Nets
uh but making actual agentic AI systems
out of that and Antonio will talk about
that and that's um becoming the thing
around 2023
now of course all these ideas have their
Roots much in much earlier work but this
is this is kind of the the slope that
I've seen uh and the interesting thing
if you look at the years I've drawn them
in kind of logarithmic scale so why are
we you know all trying to clamor to
learn this because this is the real
curve this is the real timeline okay
it's just exponential uh okay so so much
is going on right now and it's just a
really exciting time you can see that
we're going pretty far beyond uh kind of
traditional deep learning in this in
this course uh some people choose to
define deep learning as just the blue
part which I'll spend the first short
talk on um but you you know the whole
stack at places like open AI deep seek
Google Etc is is this current stack
okay okay so here are the the times um I
believe there's some print outs of the
schedule in the back or you might be
able to find it online um so we'll have
generative models large language models
then we'll have a lunch break uh then
we'll do agents and reasoning and then
we'll have a Q&A session at the end when
we can take your questions
okay so let me now tell you uh the basic
building blocks which many of you have
seen before but just so that we get on
the same page to start off so so what is
a deep net a deep net is roughly
inspired by how the neural Nets in our
brain work right the name is the same
it's a neural net and um in our brains
neuroscientists have a pretty good
understanding of the kind of pipeline
from raw sensory inputs data coming into
the uh into the eye into the ears uh
being processed by different layers of
the brain until at the kind of back at
the top layer of the brain uh which is
actually in the front of your brain uh
you end up having recognition and
decision- making and uh more like highle
intelligence so this is the visual
hierarchy in the brain uh you start with
photons you have Edge detectors which
get like added up into conjunctions of
edges and detected as patterns and
Spirals and triangles and eventually in
uh an area more frontal in the brain the
it cortex you get get the recognition of
cats and dogs and foxes and so
forth okay so what does that look like
when you make a machine do it it looks
very similar it's going to be a
hierarchy of going from the raw data to
a good representation that from which
you can make a decision or
classification so we start with the raw
data we might detect things about that
data we then will process these
subcomponents into higher order
structures like segments and parts and
then we'll eventually classify well
given that I see a blob of gray over a
background of dark and there's a circle
in the with a like a dot in the middle
that might be an ey then I'll recognize
as a herin okay so this uh hierarchical
kind of pipeline that you might have
coded by hand 20 years ago uh now we
simply replace all this boxes with um
kind of empty learnable parameterized
functions and we learn the mapping to go
from the input to the output but it's
still this hierarchical computational
flow okay
so in modern neural Nets we don't use
exactly the same hierarchy that Vision
scientists might have come up with in
the past we have something a little more
generic we just have these layers very
simple functions um that transform the
data layer by layer uh one by one and a
deep net is just a lot of those okay so
we neural Nets deep Nets same same
thing okay so the key thing is I'm going
to have functions that are parameterized
by weights and biases I'll tell you what
those are that map the input data to an
output uh representation of the data
like the label
Heron okay so here's how the whole
system looks uh when you're going to
train it so to train this network to
recognize images you simply provide it
an image of a heron you provide it the
label of what the target you want the
network to Output at the end the target
representation is going to be the label
herin and you provide it with what's
called a loss function which will
penalize the difference between the
output of the network and the Target
that you wanted it to Output so this is
called supervised learning and um if you
haven't seen these equations uh don't
worry if you have there to remind you of
the the basic math here uh we're going
to try to find the parameters which are
going to be the weights and biases these
are like knobs I'm going to fiddle with
these knobs to change the transformation
so that it will achieve what I want
it'll achieve a low loss low loss means
low error it's going to achieve what I
want okay so when I see the herin it
will output heren and if it doesn't I'll
get a l and I'll update the
parameters okay if I see a guitar fish
this is the training process I'll show
it more and more images next I'll show
it a guitar fish and I'll say what did
you think this is well it'll say I think
it's a you know a clown fish I'll say
well that was a little bit off I'll you
know have an error and I'll try to
update the parameters to the knobs in
order to minimize that error and then I
showed a car and I showed a million
images and once I've done done that it
will be able to um see a new image and
recognize what it is
okay and the way that it does that is uh
the basic training algorithm is gradient
descent so that simply means take that
um objective of minimizing the loss and
try to tune the parameters fiddle with
the knobs in the direction that will uh
reduce the loss uh locally and that's uh
based on the gradient of the loss with
respect to the parameters okay so that
looks like this I have some setting of
The parameters that incurs high loss
that doesn't recognize the you know the
guitar fish and the car and so forth and
I simply set it up as an optimization
problem where I'm trying to make that
loss go down via gradient descent I'm
just going to walk down the slope to
lower and lower amounts of error until I
get a good solution to the
problem okay so this is just to kind of
lay out that the the basic the basic
ideas we'll go into a lot more um
interesting detail soon okay so the way
I'd like to think about the elementary
operations so you can think about a
neural network now it's just a
parameterized function that is fit to
data to minimize the errors you may come
predicting properties of the data that's
one level of understanding it uh the
next level is well internally what are
the transformations of this
parameterized function they're achieving
that interesting mapping and the way I
like to think of it is that layer by
layer you're changing how you represent
the data you're transforming the data so
you start with the raw data and you do
something to it to make it into a better
format and you do this over and over
again until at the end you get your
decision okay so so this is going to be
um a kind of mathematical like little
abstract picture of what's going on
inside a neural net uh but I think it
helps helps us understand it so let's
just look at a neural net that's trained
to classify the red points apart from
the Blue
Points okay so you might have done some
basic linear classifiers in math classes
in the past well this is a little tricky
because it's not actually linearly
separable you can't separate that red
set of points from the blue set of
points with a line so you need a
nonlinear classifier luckily deep Nets
can do that uh so this is showing the uh
the data represented as a scatter plot
so each data point is a two-dimensional
Vector two attributes and you can draw
that in a two-dimensional plane on the
left and the whole goal of a classifier
is simply to find a way of moving the
red points all to the output
representation of a cat which we'll call
the label one so the label one will be
represented as um yal 1 and xals 0 so Y
is like catness and X is dogness and um
so I want all the red points to move to
the point 1 Z that all interpret as a
label of the data being a cat and all
the blue points should move to the label
01 it should be not at all a cat 100% a
dog so a classifier's output which is is
it what's is a cat or dog can be
represented as this kind of
two-dimensional picture of its belief to
the degree that it's a cat the y- Axis
or it's a dog the x-axis
okay so all the deepnet is doing is
finding a way of moving those data
points around and the interesting thing
is that the way it moves them around is
very very simple each layer of that
neural network is just going to make a
very simple modification to where the
data points live uh and eventually at
the very top they'll all live at the
right Point all the red points will have
moved to the cat label and all the blue
points will have moved to the the dog
label so what does that look like
there's two basic layer types and uh
then there's a lot of other traditional
fancy ones but the two basic ones that
are really the workor of deep learning
are called the linear layer and the
pointwise
nonlinearity so the linear layer is one
of those Transformations okay it's going
to be a linear transformation of the
data here a geometric linear
transformation so what does that look
like so in math it looks like this I
take my input data which is just you
know some image or some raw data I'm
processing X in I uh multiply that by
matrix W that's a linear transform
we call the Matrix W the weights of the
neural network I add a bias um so it's
an aine transformation and I get an
output which has moved the data points
to new location X
out so people in neural netland often
like to draw these as networks of
neurons but this is just a
representation of that equation I have a
vector xn of numbers I have a linear
transformation which is uh like every
output is a linear combination of all of
the input numbers okay that's just a
matrix a linear combination and then I
have a bias which I can add a kind of
constant to each of the um output
Dimensions okay so this is two different
ways of looking at the network my
favorite way is actually this so here is
a picture of that plane that represents
um the input data X in and how does that
data get transformed to become X out so
a linear transformation looks like that
it's it's actually an aine
transformation it's a geometric
transformation of that input data
distribution if the data lives on a grid
then will make this picture here if the
data is like a cloud of red points and I
have some particular linear
transformation uh it will look like this
it can rotate and it can shift and
translate and scale uh the distribution
of the data so it'll move that data
around that data is the
representation um of the neural Lance
representation of the data it's
processing on Layer
Two okay so that's the first function
that it uses to move all the red points
to one dot okay the second function it
uses called the reu this is just going
to be for each Dimension each uh each
neuron will I'll take its value and if
it's below zero I'll set it to zero and
it's above zero I won't do anything okay
so it's like a um a clipping type of
function Clips off the negative values
and here's what it looks like in terms
of how it transforms data all the data
in the negative part of that plane in
Negative X or negative y gets clamped to
the axes xal 0 or y equals 0 and the
data in the positive part is an identity
nothing changes there it just is it
doesn't do
anything okay and so if I apply that to
a cloud of red points then this will be
the effect the reu tries to kind of push
everything onto the axes um of this High
dimensional space uh this neural net
representation
space
okay so those are two very simple ways
of moving around the points and there's
a bunch of other ones I'm not going to
talk about all of these but we have the
linear the reu we have normalization
layers which kind of push everything
onto a sphere and we have softmax layers
which kind of um are another type of
normalization
effectively okay so simple geometric
Transformations that take your raw data
distribution and move it around until
you have achieved a um an arrangement of
the data you've moved the Blue Points
apart from the red points so I'm only
showing the red points here but what if
we look at the Blue Points too so here
is a uh like you know five layer uh
Network this is being trained with
gradient descent and I'm going to show
you a movie of how gradient descent will
update the transformations to move the
red points apart from the Blue Points so
the top of the network we're going to
want the blue points to all live on xal
1 yals 0 and the red points all live at
xals 0 y equals 1 that's label for cat
and dog okay or two two classes
abstractly the input the representations
are all entangled you can't separate
them and then layer by layer we're going
to achieve this transformation okay at
initialization it's basically not doing
anything interesting it's just kind of
smushing all the red and the blue points
on top of each other um and it looks
like all blue but that's just a
rendering artifact at the top okay so
here's what it looks like so this is
exact this is not hiding anything this
is really the uh the the this is a
neural network where every layer is a
two-dimensional transformation usually
they're high dimensional Transformations
this is just a two-dimensional
transformation and first the linear
transformation at the bottom the first
linear layer kind of stretches
everything out then the reu snaps
everything onto the two axes and then
another linear transformation kind of
stretches it in a different direction
it's trying to kind of stretch and pull
things such that somehow we're going to
get the red points apart from the Blue
Points you might be thinking this seems
really impoverished like how could it
possibly um you know disentangle
complicated data distributions where the
classes are all overlapping in different
uh different parts of the space and and
the interesting thing is yes a neural
network with only two dimensional you
know two neurons per layer two
dimensional Transformations is not
capable of doing everything it works in
this case but uh interestingly a neural
network in high Dimensions just using
these linear and point was nonlinear
Transformations can fit any function
it's called the universal approximation
property it can fit any any continuous
function okay so at the top of the
network we now have all the Blue Points
shifted to uh one one cluster where x
equals z meaning full belief it's a dog
and all the red points to uh y equals 1
uh which all means 100% belief it's a
cat Okay so I'll show you that one more
time this is what it looks like to train
a
network okay so this is the way I like
to think about neural nuts and the uh
the the fundamental building blocks
geometric transformations of a data
distribution that go from raw entangled
data to better organized data from which
you can make a decision a prediction or
potentially just like generate pixels
which Tim being we'll talk
about okay so um I think that that would
the Whirlwind tour of just getting you
to think about neural networks let me
take one or two questions and then King
will come on
yeah yes uh reu is rectified
nonlinearity or rectified linear unit is
is the is the
acronymic so uh linear and uh a very
broad class of pointwise nonlinearities
uh have the property that you can they
have Universal approximation property
you can fit any function with those if
you stack enough of them and you have
enough neurons per layer um but it's not
anything it's not absolutely anything
yeah you can you can have some functions
that are not Universal
yeah okay any more questions and then I
think we'll do timing yeah one
more all the faces uh is that the way
this then to the edges what does the
whole Edge represent so the the whole
Edge actually represents in this case uh
technically the belief the probability
that you think the image is a dog so
it's not saying like what type of dog or
all the different types of faces it's
just uh if the point had landed uh like
here I would be saying I have 50% Bel
it's a dog I don't know if it's a cat or
a dog uh so really what I'm showing you
is is called a Simplex but I didn't get
into the the full details here like up
and down yeah up and down is like my
belief of cat and left and right is my
belief of dog yeah get 100% c%g that's
the goal yeah so that's what I'm showing
you as the goal
yeah there is a point yeah yeah that's
yeah like because you're not just P to
point to the
edge The
Edge this whole it's it's actually this
line is going from my belief that it's a
cat to my belief it's a dog and
intermediate points mean I don't know
means 50/50 and I want all the red
points to be I'm I'm sure it's a it's a
cat and all the blue points to be I'm
sure it's a dog but during training it's
not sure so it's going to try to
gradually become morer and pull them
apart yeah that's the idea okay one more
and then we'll go yeah oh yeah go ahead
you go back a little TOS of yeah right
there how those
wirings uh the wiring graphs are just
showing like this is a vector of inputs
xn uh so it has indices I and uh this is
a vector of outputs and the the
dependencies like uh the jth index or
you know the ith index of X Out is a
function of the ith index of X of X in
plus this um Global kind of potential
here and that's what that layer is doing
so it's kind of showing the dependency
structure okay I think we should move on
to Kim Ming um and I'll be back uh in
the afternoon for
more thank you