Hello everyone. Uh my name is Praimnat
Shari and I'm a post-doal associate at
the MIT Media Lab. And today I'll talk
about something that I'm sure none of
you have ever thought talked about
before. AI agents. Uh just kidding. So
uh uh I'm going to talk to you about
this project that we're working on uh
out of the MIT media lab that we call
Nanda Na Nda. It stands for AI agents in
a decentralized architecture. And
basically the question we are trying to
ask is how can we build the next open
agentic web? Uh so next slide please. Oh
actually uh how do I
this.
>> Okay, perfect. Thank you. Uh initial
hiccups, but uh today I think uh I'm
sure like all of us have experienced the
magic and beauty that are these large AI
models. uh uh maybe worryingly so, we
are spending increasing amounts of time
trying to get Chad GPT and Claude and
Gemini to answer mundane to complicated
questions about everything in our lives
from how do I make that uh brownie to
how do I refine this uh letter for a
promotion or something like this. But uh
we are moving to a future with these big
centralized models uh that could
potentially if if sort of the status quo
reigns uh we'd likely move to a future
where there is one best model for every
particular task. One perfect model to
solve diabetes problems. One perfect
financial adviser or one perfect math
teacher. But the future we are excited
about is slightly different. that future
is decentralized and we are inspired by
what uh we as a collective experienced a
couple of decades ago when the web and
the internet developed. So on the left
side is the progression of the web and
on the right side is what we are seeing
with AI agents. So uh a couple of
decades ago uh we went from what we call
mainframes or PCs which are uh sort of
computers but that don't really talk
with each other to the intranet which is
a local trusted network of computers
that really know of each other so can
talk with each other already to the
internet and finally to the web the
amazing web that has made so much
possible. uh we see an analogy with how
AI is developing uh albeit at a much
much faster rate. uh we've gone from uh
sort of these AI models uh like chat GPD
that came up uh just a couple of years
ago uh to what we call agentic AI today
which is uh a bunch of these models
talking to sort of instances that are
already known to them uh in like other
agents other tools and collaborating
with them to what we call decentralized
AI uh which just basically means it's
becoming increasingly easy for folks to
deploy their own AI agents using the
simplest possible tools like crew AI or
lang chain uh so that anyone really can
have their own AI agent doing a specific
task but these agents don't know of each
other don't know of the existence of
each other and cannot collaborate with
each other and that's where we envision
this future of an open agentic web which
we call Nanda how can how can a large
number of agents millions billions
trillions whatever eons you're most
excited by uh how can a large number of
AI AI agents that may exist in the very
near future uh collaborate across
organizational silos, communicate
seamlessly, navigate autonomously,
socialize, learn, earn and transact on
our behalf. Uh this future is not that
far-fetched. Uh if you recall the
previous side slide, I showed you the
progression of uh the internet and the
web which took a few decades. And on the
right column, I showed you where we are
at with AI, which has taken maybe 3 four
years. So we uh this agentic web may
seem uh ambitious to you but may not be
that far-fetched. So it's important to
start thinking about what it means to uh
have this future of an agentic web.
Uh I'll talk about more of these but we
think there are three critical pieces to
think about uh as we are trying to build
this open agentic web. The first is what
we call foundational pieces. What does
it take for an agent to exist on this
agentic web? Uh infrastructure like
registries, search, discovery,
protocols. Uh I'm sure all of you are
familiar with A2A from Google, MCP from
Anthropic. Critical components like
those uh uh security, authentication,
identity, important pieces that I'm sure
a lot of you here are actively thinking
about that are very critical for agents
to exist on this agentic web. Second
piece is what we call agentic commerce.
Once these agents exist on an agentic
web, what does it take for them to
complete a transaction with each other?
So, how do we establish trust and
reputation? How do we do discovery? How
do we do routing of agents? And finally,
how do agents value each other's
knowledge? How do I ask Jim's agent a
question without knowing whether Jim's
agent can answer that question
beforehand? Because remember agents are
very different from web pages. I can
read a web page and know what the web
page contains. I cannot read an agent to
know what it knows already. So knowledge
valuation is what we call it. And
finally, agentic society. How do a lot
of the agents come together and
collaborate to become bigger than the
sum of their parts? These are sort of
the research questions that we are
thinking about uh as we are thinking
about this open agentic web. Today I'll
touch upon three uh points uh very
briefly about this open agentic web. We
can talk about this a lot but I'll touch
upon why do we think this is a viable
future. Why do we think we are heading
towards this? What are the risks uh that
prevent an open agentic web and why
should you care about it? And finally
what we are doing at uh as part of our
group to make this uh slightly more
probable
uh of happening.
So first why do we think this uh egentic
web is likely to happen. So today uh
most of us use uh rightfully so uh
centralized big models like uh GPTs or
claude or Gemini uh to do many different
tasks. Uh most agents are wrappers
around API calls to these types of
models. uh and uh that that is one train
of thought bigger and better centralized
models uh that are general purpose
learners but can also be gotten to do
specific tasks. But uh we like to think
about an alternate uh potential path
which is the uh future of what we call
small language models. So instead of
having one large model that is generally
good at doing everything, uh uh recent
research is showing uh promise uh in the
future of many small specific models.
what what are called small language
models that can do specific tasks uh
with much much fewer parameters and be
deployed on smaller devices like cell
phones and other edge devices uh to do
their specific task that they are
intended to solve. uh these small
language models have already shown uh
pretty good promise and at specific
domains like code generation uh
working at much much smaller parameter
counts much much smaller footprints
while performing well at their specific
domains. Uh they of course have narrow
functionality but they allow for better
alignment capability, better sort of
guardrails to safety and all that kind
of stuff. And so with the advent of
small language models, oops, uh, with
the advent of small language models, it
is not uh, far-fetched to think about a
network of small language models
deployed on edge devices doing specific
agentic tasks building this future of
what we call an agentic web. So uh with
this sort of contextualization of why we
think this is not that far-fetched, the
next question is what are the kinds of
risks for this for this egentic web to
remain open? Uh and I'll explain what I
mean by that. But really again we need
to look at history. So uh not too far
from here where we are sitting right now
uh uh important work was done to build
what we call today the worldwide web by
the W3C consortium led by Tim Bernersley
uh and uh they did a lot of amazing work
of course not just them uh around the
world a lot of very important
technologies were developed to make the
worldwide web possible these core
components like HTTP HTML URLs browsers
uh these foundational scaffolding pieces
that have led to all of the revolution
uh from web 1.2 to web 2.0, cloud
services, APIs, uh everything has been
made possible by these fundamental
pieces. But really maybe the most
incredible feat was that this web
remained broadly open. Uh it did not
become uh part of some sort of walled
garden. Anyone can deploy a web page
when they want and of course uh there
are a sort of uh major players doing
certain sort of tasks like search or
transactions but the web itself is
largely open. This is not the norm. This
is as we have learned uh over time, this
has turned out to be the exception
because uh if you think about all of the
revolutions that came after maybe the
mobile sort of app ecosystem or the
cloud provider ecosystem, the tendency
is for it to become sort of a few major
players uh controlling access,
controlling uh services and that
certainly has its positives uh including
doing things like security or uh uh
associated aspects but also it makes it
less open and less vibrant. So as we uh
sort of move towards this idea of an
open agentic web or an agentic web
indeed the question is what can we do to
keep the agentic web open and what will
happen if we don't think about these
efforts. So an open agentic web is one
we define it as one with sort of open
standards uh uh open sort of discovery
authentication payment protocols that
folks can build on top of uh and does
not have barrier to entry for anyone to
sort of uh come on top of this. Whereas
a closed platform which is uh also a
possibility that can happen uh likely
what will happen is somewhere in between
the two where we'll end up but a closed
platform is one where access to agents
access to services access to platforms
is controlled by uh front-end agent
store vault gardens start coming up uh
opaque algorithms start showing up that
we don't really have much control over
uh and uh sort of uh this leads to uh
things that were maybe not envisioned.
For example, if you think about the
traditional web uh aspects such as SEO,
search engine optimization. I'm sure Tim
Berners Lee did not think about it when
he was setting up the world web and the
fundamental protocols because really
this is not something they thought
about. But with the benefit of
hindsight, as we build the agentic web,
these are things we should think about
to ensure the agentic web remains as
open as possible.
So really the call to action on this
front is the the non the tendency is for
these uh technologies to become closed
and uh as part of world gardens uh and
for a few major players to show up as
opposed to it becoming open and vibrant.
But uh at least it is worth putting in
the effort and thinking about what it
means to keep these open. what are the
benefits of keeping the agentic web open
and uh the as I mentioned b earlier uh
we don't have much time because this
technology is moving very very fast and
we need to keep up with it uh if uh we
care about keeping this open agentic web
open and with that I'll come to sort of
the uh third piece which is what we are
doing here as part of our project to
build this agentic web and think about
what are the components that are nec
necessary to make it possible, make it a
viable future and what are the research
problems that we are thinking about. So
uh the first sort of problem that we are
thinking about is uh interoperability
across enterprise silos across different
kinds of data silos for agents from one
place to talk to another. Uh
uh it's it's good to think about again
uh technology from before and we like to
think about telephone exchanges and how
telephone technology developed in the
past and what it means to build a
telephone exchange for the agentic web.
Today the agentic web already exists.
There are a lot of different types of
agents and agentic players out there. uh
MCP servers, A2A agents that talk via
Google A2A, agents on other enterprise
platforms. Your enterprise may have
internal agents to do certain specific
tasks. All these agents exist on the web
on the agentic web but don't really have
a way to talk to each other to
interoperate with each other and make
this sort of worked agentic web a viable
future. So uh to to solve this problem
to make this interoperability possible
we think of Nanda the project we're
building as sort of a quilt in this post
AI world a quilt that brings together
all of these critical components that
are necessary for agents to interoperate
across silos components such as
foundational pieces like registries
protocols uh trust components
communication protocols like A2A and MCP
that you may be already aware of
transaction pieces uh if you have heard
about AP2 that Google came out with
recently. Uh and uh of course more
fundamental things like agent builders,
uh data and tools, compute, all of these
things need to come together and work
together uh and fit in together to make
sort of agents interoperable across this
open agent web. And this is where we
view our role to ensure that all of
these pieces come together and think
about the problems at the intersection.
What does it mean to build the DNS for
the internet of agents? What does it
mean to build an agent passport, a
metadata schema for agents so that they
can autonomously communicate across the
agent equip? What does it mean for
agents to interoperate across silos?
What does it mean to build an adapter
for these kinds of these are the kinds
of problems that we think about to make
this interoperability feasible? So four
critical choke points that we are most
uh interested in at this stage to make
this uh possible. The first is what we
call registry. How can agents uh
communicate across silos across reg sort
of uh organizational boundaries uh to
ensure collaboration across these kinds
of silos while maintaining privacy and
sovereignty of data and all of those
important things. Second is what we call
passports. Uh what kind of verified
credentials or metadata schemas do
agents need for them to interoperate
across these uh organization silos on
the agent equipment. Uh third is the
interoperability piece building the
telephone system or the exchange for
agents uh across enterprise silos and
fourth is at a stationation. Once agents
exist, how do you benchmark them? How do
you certify them? How do you uh verify
their capabilities to ensure they can be
good actors on the agentic web or at
least deterministic actors as much as
much as possible on the agentic web. So
we are working and focusing on all four
of these components. Uh I won't get to
talk about all of this in detail but uh
you can I'll link you to our web page.
You can head to that uh you can check
out all of these links that talk about
each of these components. But really all
of this goes back to uh those core
research problems that I talked to you
about uh up top. Foundational pieces uh
the agentic economy, how do agents
transact with each other and the agentic
society. How can agents build something
bigger than the sum of their parts and
learn collaboratively together to build
a a sort of big emerging system across
this uh network of agents.
>> [snorts]
>> So uh as part of our group we've been
working on uh a lot of these core
technologies for the for building this
internet of agents before even these AI
agents existed. Uh a decade ago we
pioneered what we call autoML. We've
been working on privacy preserving
machine learning this notion of
knowledge markets as well as
decentralized agentic system for many
years now. And uh we are most excited to
bring all of these technologies and
capabilities to this idea of an agentic
web and put it all together to uh make
this a viable future. So the research
road map uh what are the problems that
we are most excited about and focused on
working on uh as I talked to you about
already foundational infrastructure like
indexes and registries uh decentralized
compute and storage interoperability
uh adapters and teaming. How can agents
form teams and discover other agents
across organizational silos? AGI what we
call knowledge pricing uh as I touched
upon briefly before which is how can
agents uh uh value other agents
capabilities before talking to each
other some kind of benchmarking for
agents mainly collaborative learning
learning across silos and marketplaces
all of these are we think very very
important problems to solve to make this
agentic web viable and this is a massive
endeavor there is like we are in no
under no illusion that we will be the
one to solve all of these problems. In
fact, we'll be the one to solve a
minority of these problems. But the goal
is to build a broad collaboration to
ensure folks like you from industry and
uh folks like us from academia work
together to solve these problems in a
way that they fit well together and so
that all of our work moves in the same
direction.
Uh we are uh excited to work with bunch
of collaborators across uh major players
already in the space. uh and uh uh in
industry uh uh and we are thankful for
their guidance. So that again we build
together and build uh collectively to
make this a viable future. uh as part of
our project uh we run many many events
uh and are fortunate to have had uh many
important speakers uh in different sort
of aspects of this field to talk about
their thought process on what it means
to build an open agentic web and we are
very passionate about keeping this
process open and collaborative and we'd
be very happy to have all of you here
join us think about some of these
problems tell me what you agree with
more importantly tell me what you don't
agree with and uh build towards this
together. Uh we also run research groups
uh uh uh constituting of members uh
across academia and industry. We've
written a bunch of sort of uh tech
technical uh reports and papers that
help us think about some of these pieces
like what does it mean to build a
registry for the internet of agents?
What does it mean to build a sandbox to
attest agents on the agentic web? What
does an agentic passport look like? All
of these are things that we've thought
about, talked about, and uh we'd be
excited to have you uh join us to
contribute to this.
Uh before finishing, I'll just give you
a glimpse of two of the things that
we've worked about worked upon. Uh uh
first is what we call the DNS for the
Internet of AI agents, the agentic
registry, and the second is what we call
a sandbox. The first question to answer
is as I touched upon the agentic web
already exists. There are so many
different agentic entities like MCP
servers, AI agents that already exist
out there on the agentic web but don't
really talk to each other. an agent for
example within Salesforce's agent force
platform may not be talking to another
agent within HCL's uh like agent core
agent sort of their agent platform or uh
such types of interoperability platforms
problems and so the question is how do
we build discoverability for this agent
there are two broad options one is what
we call a centralized registry a
registry that is similar to DNS
a a single source of truth that is easy
to maintain that lists out all of the
agents that exist out there. Uh and this
other option on the other end of the
extreme is a decentralized discovery
platform where there is no single source
of truth. All the metadata is
distributed and discovery happens across
this distributed ecosystem. Both of
these have their strengths and both of
these have their weaknesses. And we've
come up with our own solution for this
registry architecture for the internet
of AI agents that we call the Nanda
index. The goal of the Nanda index is
not to be the one registry for the
internet of AI agents. Think of this
more as a lean central switchboard. Uh
so we uh envision and we are supportive
of all the important players having
their own agent registries uh sort of
listing out their own AI agents uh
controlling their access controlling
their capabilities. Our goal is to
ensure that these are all interoperable.
Registry A can find and discover agents
in registry B, set up that
communication, and once that handshake
has been established, these agents can
talk with each other without ever having
to come to the index or our sort of
switchboard ever again. So that's the
interoperability goal with the Nanda
index. Uh we're excited to collaborate
uh with many uh academic players. uh
just like DNS had uh 12 core registries
uh that allowed for global
interoperability, we are excited to work
with top AI universities around the
world uh to focus on hosting and
building this distributed Nanda index to
ensure AI agent registry
interoperability.
Uh we are also interested in uh ensuring
interoperability across protocols. Today
there are many different communication
protocols that exist out there. All very
important A2A, MCP, NL web, NLIP, many
many important agentto agent
communication protocols that today don't
really talk with each other. And so
we've put in some effort to build what
we call the adapter that allows agents
from protocol A to talk to agents with
protocol B and ensure interoperability
across silos in that way. So it's not
just about agents being able to discover
each other. Once they discover each
other, they should also be able to talk
in the same language and that's what the
adapter aims to do. The third is what we
call nest or nanda sandbox and test
build. This addresses the last piece
that I talked about which is
addestation. Once an agent is built and
becomes let's say a citizen of this open
agent equip. There are so many things
that need to be verified. Uh what are
the capabilities of the agent? How does
it communicate with other agents around
the world? what does it mean to host and
resolve AI agents on this agentic equip
and many many more important problems
for this we've built this sandbox which
is uh an ecosystem of live deployed
agents on this dashboard every dot that
you see is an actual agent that is
deployed in that particular part of the
world across cloud providers across
agent builder platforms and these agents
actually actively talk to each other so
today if you go to nest.pronanda.org
or the dashboard for this uh sandbox.
You can see these agents talking to each
other every few seconds building traffic
and communication on this sandbox for an
agentic web. And with this sandbox, we
are very excited because we can start
thinking about many many uh sort of
problems that we need to solve as we
build this open agentic web. Uh how what
does it mean for this agent web to
scale? How well does it scale? Uh what
what kind of protocols do we need to
build for AI agents? both communication
and coordination. How can we solve
problems at the infrastructure level to
ensure AI agent interoperability? For
example, resolving AI agents, serving AI
agents across geographies and latency
problems for orchestration across large
agentic teams. All of these problems are
ones that can be thought about and
evaluated on the live sandbox. You can
actually uh this sandbox is live today.
Code is open source. You can take your
own agent and deploy it on the sandbox
and see how it talks with other AI
agents on this open agent equip. So it's
very exciting. Uh today as I said it
hasund a few hundred AI agents. Uh these
agents can talk across communication
protocols A2A slim few others as well.
Uh it hosts different index and registry
architectures. It is distributed
globally and really it's a means for you
to uh experience the agentic web without
uh having to deploy our agent out there
in the uh real world. So uh as I
conclude my talk uh I hope uh if there's
one thing you've taken away from this uh
presentation it's that there are so many
different problems to think about as we
embark on this journey from individual
distributed agents to this idea of
aworked agentic web registries discovery
intent mapping adaptive routing
observability safety control plane and
many many more things I'm sure a lot of
you are thinking about all of these
important problems so are
And uh it is important to uh work on
this together. Work on this with uh
urgency and work on this in a manner
that retains uh sort of uh openness as
much as possible of this agentic web so
that we can uh build this next agentic
web together. Uh usually in my
presentation we also have this platform
if you're interested to build your own
AI agent quickly. So you can go to
jointhreadn.org just to experience what
it means to have your own AI agent. It's
a very simple platform. You can loging
in via Google Oath and then uh build a
quick AI agent that's a digital turn off
yourself and talk to it and see what it
means to have this magical AI agent for
if there is anyone who's not really
worked with AI agents. But really uh
that's about project number uh we are
focused on building this open agentic
web. Uh I talked to you about our
three-phase research road map. uh what
it's not is some kind of agent builder
or one registry architecture or one sort
of communication protocol or something
like that. It's more about bringing
together this agentic web bringing
together all those critical pieces and
ensuring they work together. Uh most of
the things that I've talked to you about
is open source GitHub code uh documents
and reports everything is open source.
You can go to projectna.org and check
those out. Uh we also work on many
algorithmic novelties uh uh that you can
check out from our web page. Uh we also
run uh a lot of these seminars. We have
weekly meetings every Friday. If you're
an engineer and wants to test out our uh
sandbox and registry we run weekly
technical office hours every Friday. We
run bunch of regional chapters for
people to get together and think about a
lot of these problems because really
that's the goal to get all of you
together all of us together and think
about these problems together to ensure
we uh don't miss anything because again
as I touched upon initially this
technology is moving much much faster
than the traditional web did and it's
very important to think about both the
strengths and the challenges today with
that I thank you uh for your time and
have you take questions. [applause]
>> Do we do we have any questions
right here?
>> My let me know.
>> You're audible. So given that again
presentation was phenomenal but given
that you're speaking
I'll just do a quick for our virtual
audience. uh the the question was about
regional standards for interoperability
between these agents.
>> Absolutely and this will be a challenge.
So I think it's a bit of a chicken and
egg problem right now because uh as
you're aware uh if you think about
governmental organizations or regulatory
bodies there is no real regulation as
yet for uh agent interoperability or
what uh agents can talk about how they
communicate with each other. So it's a
bit of a chicken and egg problem. We
certainly anticipate uh uh there to be
interoperability challenges or
interoperability uh aspects that need to
be considered. Today we don't face them
as you touched upon uh because actually
there is one chance even before that
even if we don't think about like
regional interoperability challenges
there is already like let's say
organizational interoperability but even
intraoperability challenges today uh
like uh big organizations uh as all of
you may already know I may be speaking
to the choir here but uh big
organizations may have their own agents
within their company but across like
verticals that don't talk to each other
at that level. So those are the sort of
challenges that we are seeing today and
trying to solve and of course there are
many aspects to solving those
challenges. first is forget about all
the security risks and uh all of those
types of problems but first enable that
discoverability and communication right
and that's what I talked about with the
uh registry switchboard and A2 uh sort
of protocol interoperability then come
the security challenges the guardrails
all at the intraorganizational level and
then we'll think about the inter and
then certainly at some point we'll have
to think about the regulatory challenges
as well but uh it's a bit of a moving
target right now and we are moving up
the levels if that makes sense.
>> Uh we have a question in the back here.
>> Quick question regarding community
alignment. How are you thinking on on
gain alignment from the community to
start using
>> I have to be quick Mario here to start
using the the
all these project the the network system
because at the you have on on one side
you could have chaos with a lot of
individual efforts creating a agents
without a particular framework or
protocol but you're you're trying to
build this network with a
[clears throat] order framework. How do
you how are you seeing to bring them on
board to to get gain adoption and make
it a standard board?
>> Yeah, I think uh it's exciting because I
think as you know a lot of the big
players are also thinking about these
problems in tech. For example, Google is
building this A2A protocol for agentto
agent communication. Cisco uh as part of
their agency project whom we collaborate
a lot with as well are also thinking
about some of these pieces like how to
build registries how to ensure agent
discovery and interoperability across
these large networks. So and we talked
to a bunch of bunch of companies as well
some of them were listed on the slides
and uh I think what we are hearing is
it's not a question of if but a question
of when. Of course there are a lot of
challenges to solve along the way. I
know a lot of uh organizations are also
currently thinking about things like
guardrails or intraorganization agent
interoperability as I was touching upon
here but really it's a question of when
not if uh if I said that the other way
around earlier but it's a question of
when not if and so uh people are sort of
excited about this uh and which is why
it's sort of important to build
collaboratively so ensure that agent
builders are working together with
people who are building communication
protocols or registry architectures and
ensure they all work together properly.
>> Okay, we're out of time, but we're going
to squeeze in one more quick question.
>> Okay. Uh how much of the architecture is
based on the assumption that the AI will
go towards a tiny agent and will it work
with with independent agents build on
bigger AIs?
>> Yeah, none of the architecture is
predicated on that assumption. uh the
only thing that is predicated on that
assumption is let's say our estimation
of scale for example let's so if you saw
my slide was very ambitious at the
beginning and it said there'll be
trillions of AI agents so if that h that
is predicated on there being edge agents
and actually that's not very farfetched
for example my phone today has it's like
a Google pixel and it has some AI model
that it runs locally I've been told so
it's not that farfetched but none of the
architecture is predicated on that
assumption for sure Great. Well, let's
hear it for Prauma.
>> Thank you so much.