so today we are going to uh talk about
where consumer decisions come from
remember last lecture we built a supply
curve and demand curve and I just sort
of made them up and I said now we're
going to start to go back and build up
where they come from and today we'll
start with the demand curve and start by
talking about consumer preferences okay
so um the first thing we're going to do
is we're going to understand how
consumers make choices now essentially
as I mentioned last time consumers make
constrained choices they essentially
make themselves as well as off as
possible subject to a limited budget
what we're going to start with today is
forget the limited budget imagine we
just all won the Mega Millions okay
there's no budget we're just going to
ask what to Consumers want and not worry
about how they're going to pay for it
okay so today we're going to talk about
preferences we're talk about what
consumers want and how we translate
those wants and desires into a
mathematical formulation that allows us
to derive demand curves okay the so
basically we're going to do this we're
going to ultimately for Consumer demand
proceed in three steps the first step is
we're going to write down our underlying
assumptions about consumer preferences
we're going to talk about how consumers
talk about a set of axioms that
determine the rules of consumer
preferences across
Goods we'll then translate those set of
a into a mathematical function we call
the utility function which is a
mathematical expression of consumer
preferences and then next time we'll
introduce the budget constraint and talk
about how consumers make choices given
this mathematical utility function and
given the budget constraint they face
okay so that's the road map of where
we're going okay so today we're going to
talk about pref es axiomatic rules of
preferences and how they translate into
the mathematical rules that govern
individual
decisions so do this let's start by
talking about
preferences and let's talk about the
key assumptions we are going to make in
modeling consumer
preferences so remember all models make
simplifying assumptions we're going to
make um inexact models make simplifying
assumptions we're going to make three
assumptions here the first assumption
we're going to make so what are the key
assumptions the first assumption we're
going to make is
completeness that is we are going to
assume that when consumers are faced
with two choices they're either going to
prefer one or prefer the other or be
indiff but they're going to have an
opinion they're not going to say I don't
know
okay consumers will have opinions over
all possible choices they'll like one by
another they'll be indifferent but
they'll have opinions over all possible
choices it's a complete set of
preferences the second thing is the same
ass subject we've been making since
kindergarten in all our math classes
which is
transitivity okay which is the classic
if you prefer a to B and B to C you must
prefer a to c I'm pretty sure all MIT
students know transitivity by now okay
um so that is uh the second key
assumption which is once again not a
great not a big deal the third
assumption is where economics gets its
power the third assumption is a new one
which we call the Assumption of nons
satiation or new to you the Assumption
of
non-satiation or basically more is
always
better okay the third assumption so
these assumptions are standard
assumptions make in math class complete
Choice sets transitivity nons satiation
is new to you that's the assumption that
basically more is always better now it
doesn't mean more makes you equally
happy it doesn't mean the 10th thing
makes you as happy is the ninth thing it
just means the 10th thing is always
better than not having it more is always
better okay so basically if you're
offered something for free you'll always
take it okay it's always better than not
having it that's because we live in a
world of goods you might be thinking to
yourself well if someone offered me for
free you know to stick me in the eye
with a needle I wouldn't take that and
you're right cuz that's a bad
for most people I guess but uh we're
going to operate in the world of goods
so as long as things are Goods we always
want
more now with those in mind we can
develop what we call indifference curves
which are
essentially preference Maps we're going
to map people's preferences into a set
of what we call indifference curves so
to do this let's start with a simple
example okay imagine at the beginning of
semester and your parents
are going to give you some money to buy
the two things you care about slice of
pizza and cookies that's all you care
about in this world once again as
someone asked last time work was
simplifying two-dimensional assumptions
in reality of course you care about
buying 20 different things but the
underlying logic won't change the math
will just get harder and the graphs will
become multi-dimensional hard to see so
we're going to start with two goods but
everything we do here works with three
four five six Etc Goods okay just harder
math and Graphics so so let's say have
two goods and let's say you're going to
face three choices choice a is you can
have two slices of pizza and one cookie
Choice B is you can have two cookies you
can have I'm sorry one slice of pizza
and two cookies or Choice C is you can
have two slices of pizza and two cookies
those are your three choices you're
facing okay and let's
assume given my preferences that I'm
indifferent between A and
B let's assume that given my preference
I'm indifferent between those two now
where does that come from well we are
going to take preferences as Primitives
we're not going to question where
preferences come from people going to
have their preferences it's genetics or
nature nurture whatever that's something
we deep delve more deeply into when we
think about deeper economics but for now
for this class preference is given so I
have a set of preferences such that I'm
indifferent between those two choices
but I prefer opt C to both okay I'm a
different between A and B but I prefer C
okay so we can now graph my preferences
Andrew can I get a copy the
handout uh so we can now graph my
preferences and the graph of my
preferences is shown in figure
21 okay everyone should have a handout
remember they'll always be in the back
when you come in please make sure you
grab them as you come in figure 2 one is
a map of my preferences okay on the x
axis okay is I believe let me just I'm
going to look at yours for a second you
can look at your neighbors on the x-
axis is cookies on the y axis is slices
of pizza okay so indiff maps are
essentially maps of how you choose
between two goods you're choosing from
okay so basically this is your
indifference map thank you um this is
your indifference map and what you see
is we have mapped the three points a b
and
c a is one uh two slice of pizza in one
cookie B is two cookies and one slice of
pizza C is two of both and we have drawn
a curve between A and B we label this an
indifference curve it's an indifference
curve because I said you're indifferent
between A and B so there's a one
indifference curve goes through both A
and B because you're indifferent between
those choices remember completeness says
you can't not care complet completeness
says you have to choose but it's okay to
be indiff okay but Point C is on a
higher indifference curve because you
prefer Point C to
both okay so there's going to be four
properties of indifference curves these
indifference curs which you're going to
work with extensively throughout the
semester are going to have four
properties properties of indifference
curves first property okay is consumers
prefer higher indifference curves
so the further out the indifference
curve is the more preferred it is okay
and that just follows from non-satiation
more is better so quantities that are
further out away from the away from the
uh uh away from the origin are better
okay the second property is indifference
curves are downward
sloping we're not say anything about the
sheet yet just the slope that
indifference curves are downward
sloping and once again this follows from
non-satiation why because if
indifference curves were upward sloping
it wouldn't sat you wouldn't satisfy
non-satiation look at figure 2 two with
an upward sloping indifference curve an
upward this is just one particular kind
of upward sloping IND difference curve
but true for all of them if the differ
curve is upward sloping that mean you'll
be a different between one cookie and
one slice of pizza and two cookies and
two slices a pizza that would violate
non-satiation you can't be indifferent
between less and more you have to always
like more better so difference cures
have to be downward sloping through
non-satiation
Okay the third is indifference curves
never
cross indifference curves never
cross and the reason because the
difference curves can't cross is because
that would violate transitivity and more
is better so let's look at figure 2
three with Crossing indifference
curves
okay in this graph figure 2 three A and
B are on the same indifference curve and
A and C are on the same indifference
curve that means you must be a different
between a and b and different between a
and C well if you're different between A
and B and A and C by transitivity you
must be IND different between B and C
but that can't be true you can't be
different B and C because B is more than
C okay B is is a dominant you get the
same amount of cookies and more pizza so
you by definition have to like B better
than C so you can't be you violates
jointly transitivity and
non-satiation okay so that's the third
property and the fourth property is
basically completeness which is which we
express as only one indifference curve
through any given point you can't have
two indifference curves that cross
through one Point okay so one I see
through any given
point per Point per precise allocation
going be one because otherwise you
wouldn't know how to feel okay there has
to be one IND difference curve through
precise
Point
okay so let's with these rules in mind
let's talk about how you can use IND
difference curves here's how I learned
about difference curves when I was
student in 1401 here's how I learned
difference curves actually a semester
later I still didn't quite understand
how I left 1401 cuz I was as smart as
you all okay but I had a year op and my
year op was with a graduate student and
this graduate student was trying to
decide on where to go for their job and
they said to me look we can express it
in difference curve this is one of a few
graphs I'll draw for you this semester
he said look there's two things I care
about I care about school quality like
how highly ranked is where I'm going to
go are my colleagues the smartest Etc
and I care about location which is how's
the weather really this is weather
okay and he had two choices his choices
were Princeton great quality mediocre
weather or Santa Cruz not as good
quality great weather to Santa Cruz I
don't know how anybody studies there you
can like walk out steps out and surf
okay and he basically said look at this
point I'm
indifferent I'm indifferent between
better job at Princeton but you know
mediocre weather and a worst job at
Santa Cruz no offense to Santa Cruz
Princeton's an amazing place Santa Cruz
is still a great place but it's not
Princeton okay a worst job at Santa Cruz
uh and awesome weather and being able to
Surf every
day so he said I'm indifferent he said
in the end what did he decide to do in
the end he decided to go to a place
called The
IMF which is not the thing from the Tom
Cruz movies but actually uh the
international monetary fund because that
was in DC which had better
weather and was so it wasn't as good a
job as Princeton this is Princeton this
is Santa Cruz
but it was better weather it wasn't as
good weather as Santa Cruz but it was a
better job and he decided that
combination made him happier is he right
no he's not right there's no sense of
right preferences or your
preferences okay you might all feel very
differently about this set of choices
does anybody's preferences are correct
or wrong okay this is just how we
thought about this job choice and how we
used an indifference map to explain
it okay questions about
that question about how these
indifference curves work yeah
speak loudly so everyone can hear
thanks that's a great question so
basically once again the the question is
how do you put quality into this
framework well essentially what you
would do is you would say then I have
two Dimensions be quality and quantity
of one good you'd have to add either a
third dimension or you say it's a
different choice so it we'll do a lot in
this course you could think of
sequential choices so let's say for
example you want to decide between uh
cook and pizza you decide and now within
cookies you want to decide you decide I
want to allocate $6 to cookies now I say
my choice is one unbelievable $6 cookie
or six terrible $1 cookies that's a new
indifference curve you've already
decided first how many you're going to
spend on cookies then you decide so
that's we can always break any monster
decision to a set of sequential
two-dimensional decisions so that's how
you do it okay good question other
questions yeah
yeah yeah I I always get that question
it's technically different but
effectively the
same okay good if I don't see your hand
by the way shout out it's a big
classroom okay so now we're going to
move on move on from preferences and go
on to talking about utility
okay point two topic two utility okay so
basically underlying where preferences
come from is a mathematical function we
call the utility function it's basically
how we mathematically represent these
graphical indifference
curves okay so it set so for example a
common form of utility function will use
a lot this semester
okay is is the log utility function
which is the which we express the form
utility is the square root in this case
of pizza slices times the number of
cookies that is a mathematical
representation of preferences it says my
utility is a square root of the number
of slices of pizza times the number of
cookies s stands for pizza because it's
slices because we use P Elsewhere for
prices I don't be confusing okay so that
says note this is consistent with what I
wrote up there about indifference
curse two slice of pizza and one cookie
gives me square root of two utility one
slice of pizza and two cookies gives me
square root of two utility so I'm
indifferent two slice pizza in two
cookies gives me two utility so I'm
happier so this is consistent with the
indifference curves
yeah that's a different IND that you
could write down like I said I'm not
judging anybody's preferences but that
would be a different mathematical
function this is one of an infinite set
of mathematical functions right down
this is not a true representation this
is an example you can write any utility
function you guys want to think of we
can write it down and we'll write down
many of them this semester but I need to
work with this one first till we
understand the rules
yeah what well no but it shows your
indiffer between s and C but it would
show that you it would show that you are
you prefer uh more of both but it's true
it shows you're indifferent between s
time C that's absolutely
right between
what same as
what oh oh that's a great Point uh
that's an excellent point the reason
we're going to need square root is
because it's going to it's it's a form
of preferences that's it's a a a rule on
preference going to help us do a lot of
things well in this semester I'll
explain that in one minute it's a good
question now I understand thank you yes
in fact that question leads to a natural
next question which is what the hell is
utility what does it mean and the answer
is utility means nothing cardinally it
only is meanings ordinally that's what I
mean is a utility of three is a
meaningless concept utility only matters
in an ordinal sense in the sense of
ranking choices so utility functions
will simply be mappings that we use to
rank choices not mappings that we used
say this choice is 50% better than that
choice it's only for ranking so the
number itself doesn't matter and by that
same question well the ranking of s time
C was the same as ranking of square s
time C so why do we write it that way
okay and the reason we write it that way
is because the utility functions of this
general form of this power form of less
than one um will deliver an important
rear World consequence and we see that
through the notion of marginal
utility okay so once again this is just
one form of preferences the question is
absolutely right this mapping would work
just fine as s time C or S2 time c s or
s to the millionth time C to the
millionth because the because the
numbers don't matter it's the ranking
that matters all those little the same
ranking but those functions deliver
something very different which would
violate the way we think about the real
world which is that basically the
fundamental driver of all consumer
decision will make this semester
remember I said everything I'm going to
tell you a hundred times things are
really important this is really
important okay the fundamental driver is
the key assumption that we make of
diminishing margin
utility that is we assume more is
better but the next unit is not quite as
good as the one before we assume
marginal utility diminishes we assume
each additional unit makes you less
happy than the one before which wouldn't
be true if we didn't have the square
root function there okay why do we
assume that because it makes sense okay
it makes sense that basically 10th slice
of pizza makes you less happy in the
ninth slice of pizza it makes sense that
the fifth cookie makes you less happy in
the fourth cookie it makes sense that
your fifth favorite movie makes you less
happy than your fourth favorite movie
now it could be tiny increments between
them but it makes sense that when you
rank things the next one is worth less
okay so for example let's go to figure
24 and let's hold the number of pizza
slices by the way Andrew we should
change that instead of holding pizza say
hold pizza slices okay let's change the
number of pizza slices constant at two
let's assume you you for sure decide you
want two slices of pizza now you're
going to ask yourself how does my
utility vary as I uh have additional
cookies the answer is if I have one
cookie
my utility is 1.4 of two if I have two
cookies my utility is two if I have
three cookies it's 2.45 and so on okay
basically what you see is that the
incremental utility from each additional
cookie is falling that's shown in figure
2-5 figure 2-5 illustrates diminishing
margin utility each additional cookie
makes you less happy holding constant
the number of
pizzas okay
so
basically this is an enormously
sensible uh assumption it's an
assumption as I said no one can tell you
what your preferences should be but it
turns out we think most in we think most
people's preferences satisfy the
principle of diminishing margin utility
and that is going to drive a lot of the
mathematics we're going to do this
semester it's not we will we will give
you examples where it's not true we'll
give you examples of increasing margin
utility and constant margin utility and
have you discuss them but we're going to
generally soon diminishing
question that's a great question that
would be that's um essentially in this
with these
preferences it would say that
essentially your preferen are such that
if you can't have a cookie you don't
care how much pizza get that doesn't
violate non-satiation because basically
that is uh non-satiation says more of
everything is better it doesn't say more
of one thing is better more of any one
thing is better non says more of
everything is better it can't be true
that you get more of everything you're
better off it can be true getting more
one thing doesn't make you better off so
think about left shoes and right shoes
okay it doesn't matter how many once you
have if you only have one left shoe it
doesn't matter how many right shoes you
have so it doesn't violate more as
better it's just but you'll be better
off with two left shoes and two right
shoes than one left shoe and one right
shoe
yeah good question good I love these
questions thank you so much okay so
basically with that in mind let's talk
about how do we can now go back and ask
well what drives the shape and slope of
indifference
curves okay so what is the slope of the
indifference curve the slope of the
indifference curve is the rate at which
we're willing to trade off just
definitionally mathematically the rate
which we're willing to trade off slices
of pizza for
cookies okay the rate which you're
willing to trade
off trade off basically one good for
another okay so we'll call that Delta s
Delta C is the slope at any point that's
the slope of the indifference curve the
rate at which you're willing to trade
the good on the Y AIS for the good on
the x-axis we're going to just Define it
this way for convenience obviously you
can invert it doesn't change anything
but for convenience we'll always think
of it this way the rate at which you're
willing to trade the good on the y- axis
for the good on the x- axis okay and
we're going to call
this the marginal rate of
substitution the mrss a key concept for
this class the mrss the marginal rate of
substitution okay that is the rate at
which you're willing to trade off the
good on the y- axis for the good on the
x-axis okay now you're not really
trading we're not in some ancient barter
system where you're trading pizza for
cookies but effectively you are because
of opportunity cost given a budget we
haven't given you a budget yet but next
time we will given a budget any money
you spend on Pizza you can't spend on
cookies and vice versa so effectively
it's a trade by buying a slice of pizza
you're essentially trading away cookies
not the only trading away but you're
trading away the money you could use to
buy cookies okay so in the world with
only two goods whenever you buy one
you're trading away the other now
doesn't operate directly operates
through the budget constraint but that's
the way to think about it so you're
substituting pizza for cookies now how
does this
relate to the utility function well
here's what's kind of cool okay think
about an incremental Move Along an
indifference
curve an incremental Move Along
indifference curve is essentially you're
giving up a little slice a little slice
of piece to get a little more cookie on
the margin so that's saying you are you
give up Delta
s times the Marg utility of slice so you
give up a little bit of slice of pizza
which you liked mu that's your margin
utility for
pizza and you're getting a little more
cookie which you value at your margin
utility for cookies okay that's the
equation of that's a Delta along that
curve okay you give up a little pizza
which cost you margin utility of pizza
you get some cookies which which gains
you marginality of cookies okay
rewriting this we get get
that Delta s Delta C which I said is the
mrss is equal to minus
mu C over muu the mrss is the ratio of
margin utilities that is the slope of
the indifference curve is the ratio of
the margin utilities and that's how we
tie the math and the graph
together that's how the math the graph
together that basically the slope of the
indifference curve is the mrss is the
negative opposite of the ratio of margin
utilities now this is very tricky here's
the one thing you need to keep in mind
which is to remember that Marg the
reason there's a negative sign is that
margin utilities are negative functions
of
quantity the more you get the lower your
margin utility is utility is a positive
function of quantity but because of
diminishing margin utility margin
utility is a negative function of
quantity got to keep embed that in your
brain okay moris better says utility is
a positive function of quantity except
of course in this important case was
pointed out there positive function of
both things going up but margin utility
is a negative function of quantity okay
you're less Happy by the next
incremental unit than you were by the
ones before okay so basically as you get
fewer slices and more cookies what is
happening well the Marg ility of slices
is
rising you're giving up pizza slices so
your Marg utility is going up the
marginality of cookies is
falling okay so what you get is
basically a decline in the value of the
mrss the margil of pizzas is slightly
Rising okay margil cookies is slightly
falling this ratio Falls so the mrss
Falls so you get this downward
sloping indifference curve okay so this
is sort of hard so let's see this
mathematically and graphically let's
start with the math okay let's start
with the
math okay we said utility is the square
root of s * C okay so what is the margin
utility of cookies well we're just going
to differentiate this with respect to C
differentiate this function with respect
to C what do you get so Delta U Delta C
you get 0.5
time the number of slices of pizza over
the square root of s *
C okay what is the margin utility of
pizza slice of pizza you get
du
DS equals 0.5 * C over Square < TK of s
* C and once again I apologize for the
handwriting please ask if it's not clear
okay so I'm just differing this function
to get the two Marge
utilities okay if I take based on these
two Marge utilities the mrss which is
the the negative of the ratio the
mrss equals minus s over C for this
particular example don't these aren't
general rules I'm deriving here for this
example the mrss is minus s over
C so basically what the Mrs is showing
you is
that the mrss for slice of cookies for
slice of pizza opposed to cookies is
rising as you get more slices and foll
as you get more cookies so let's see
this in figure
26 okay figure 26 shows the indifference
curve again but now with the mrss is
plotted remember the indifference curve
is not linear in this case so mrss
changes along the indifference curve so
I'm giving you local
approximations to the mrss at different
points to the indiference curve but it's
very important to remember this is key
because the DI Mission utility you are
going to get
yeah
right yeah yeah figure 2.5 is just
giving you local approximations those
points are solved by differentiation but
those are local
approximations okay yep so basically um
that's the thing our graphs are never
going to be as precise as our math
because we of because we essentially
want to use linear mathematics for
nonlinear for nonlinear graphs and so
we're going to end up with a lot of
local local
approximations okay so basically in
other words at Point
a okay um at Point a um you have four
slices of pizza in one cookies at point
B you have two of each and at Point C
you have four cookies and one slice of
pizza and according to this utility
function you're indifferent right all
those give two as the utility all those
combinations give utility of two you're
indifferent okay now but at Point a even
though you're different between all
three points they have very different
mrs's at Point a the mrss is minus four
you would be willing to give up four
slices of pizza to get one
cookie at Point C the mrss is minus
one4 you'd be willing to give up only
one slice of pizza to get four cooked
why what's changed between points A and
C why is the Mrs changed so radically
between points A and
C
yeah what
sorry you have you have fewer slices of
pizza exactly so basically what's
happening is as your slice of pizza
Falls and then by definition your
cookies goes up your margin utility of
pizza Rises and your Mar utility cookies
fall when you're point a you really want
pizza you're happy to give cookies to
get pizza because you get I'm sorry you
really want want cookies I'm sorry my
bad at Point a you really want cookies
you got four slices of pizza you're full
already you want a cookie okay when
you're at Point C it's like what do you
do with four cookies you're not going to
have enough protein in your dinner your
mom will be upset okay so you basically
want to trade some of those cookies back
for some pizza okay and then at point B
you see the mrss is minus one because
given this utility function at that
point you're essentially
indifferent you're indifferent between
pizza and cookies at point B Okay so so
that that is why we
graph we graph the um we graph the
indifference curves uh in this way as
concave uh as concave indifference
curves concave to the origin because
basically we want um we want to satisfy
this principle diminishing marginal rate
of substitution for those you who really
want to be
technical the real technical definition
is diminishing margin substitution you
don't always have to have diminishing
utility we generally you could write
down functions which don't have dimin
utility but do have diminishing Margate
of substitution if you are so inclined
the technical definition is is that what
drives what what drives utility theory
is diminishing margin R of substitution
but almost always we'll have diminishing
margin utility as well that's all I'll
say about it you can forget it if you
want but if it's bugging you that's why
okay
now consider what would be like I'm
sorry so it's it's convex to the origin
my bad I'm sorry convex to the origin in
difference curves convex in difference
curves consider what would be like with
a concave to the origin and difference
curve as in figure
27 consider what life would be like we
often do proes by the negative okay this
is for the utility function figure 27 is
for is drawn for the utility function
X2 plus y^2 =
65 that's utility function that's graph
there well uh I should say S2 Plus I
shouldn't say X and Y I should say
S2 S2 Plus C s equal
65 okay now once again you can't tell me
that utility function is wrong people
have different preferences but it
doesn't satisfy what we could think is a
common sense principle which is that
would say that when you have eight
slices of pizza in one
cookie you you'd be willing to give up
um when you have eight slices of pizza
uh and one cookie you would give up only
an eighth of a slice of pizza to get a
cookie so you really wouldn't give up
much pizza to get a cookie and yet when
you're down all the way of having seven
cookies and four slices of pizza then
you give up almost two slices of pizza
to have a cookie it doesn't make sense
why would you give up more pizza when
you have less Pizza when you already
have eight slices of pizza why are you
less L of a a pizza for a cookie than
when you have more slices of pizza uh
when you have fewer slices of pizza and
more cookies it doesn't make sense
that's why we gener now it doesn't make
sense let's be clear I'm not saying it's
inconsistent with reality okay like I
said we don't have strict laws like
equal MC s in this class there's someone
out there who has these preferences I
guarantee it what I'm saying is most
people do not and so we're going to try
to in this class like I said make a
series of simplifying assumptions that
explain most of reality even they
explain 100% of reality okay and
diminishing mrss is one of those
assumptions okay and that's why um
diminishing mrss makes
sense uh because it delivers the fact
that the more you have of one good the
less you care about having the next unit
of it okay let me stop there questions
about that this is really really
important for all of consumer Theory
it's actually going to be important for
production Theory too this General
notion of diminishing production the we
call it diminishing marginal product but
it's going to be the same sort of thing
so questions about how this where this
all comes
from okay
you know throughout this class you want
to ask yourself does this pass the mom
test that is could you go home and
explain this to your non-economist mom
and you should understand this well
enough that you can I don't know if
she'd be interested but it doesn't
matter she's your mom she has to listen
to you so basically make sure you
understand it that well okay now let's
go to an example yeah I'm sorry go
ahead uh the only point of a concave
disc would to represent the set of
preferences I wrot there I mean there's
no there's no point or not point it's
just simply saying that there exists
someone in the world who has that
utility function this is their
preferences but you won't generally ever
see one does that make
sense all
right okay so let's go to an example
there's actually a wonderful example of
diminishing margin utility and how it
operates in the real
world which is um different
sizes of consumer goods of consumer uh
consumption Goods so for example at
Starbucks according to Alex's detailed
research you can get a tall ice coffee
for
$455 or you can get twice as much coffee
whatever the hell they call the big one
for 90 more cents so $455 for the
smallest 90 cents more to double your
amount of coffee or McDonald's a small
Coke is
229 a large Coke which is more than
twice as big is 299
so essentially you are paying much less
to increase the quantity why is
that yeah loudly so we can here go
ahead exactly so you think about
yourself walking to McDonald's on a on a
hot day okay or Starbucks on a cold day
and you really need to be saded you're
you're you're either very very cold or
very hot you need to be SED but a small
will get you most of the way there now a
large is better buy more is better but
it's not as much better you just needed
to be Sav you need to make sure you got
your your liquids in so you're not
willing to pay as much for the
incremental quantity you're not willing
to pay as much and the key thing is that
basically um uh that companies recognize
this and this is where we start to dip
into producer
Theory companies are making their
business decision
based on what they know about consumer
preferences this is why someone asked
you know why we ever have a concave
indifference curve this is why companies
don't believe they're concave uh uh
concave indifference curves because they
price this way they know that most
people care less about the additional 16
ounces they do about the first 16 ounces
now if if maybe you all thought that was
common sense or maybe you never thought
about why that is but this is once again
an illustration of how a common
phenomenon in society that exists
everywhere
can be explained by what's an incredibly
simple model remember we came into this
class knowing nothing about utility and
all that stuff we' already got an
explained an incredibly important
phenomenon in the world and there's many
other choices and things that you'll see
that that can be explained by this model
OKAY questions about
that
yeah great question someone to answer
that how does it benefit Starbucks and
McDonald's yeah
Yeah so basically if they McDonald's if
if they price essentially the
calculation we ar going to producer
Theory yet but I'll give you a heads up
the calculation McDonald's and Starbucks
are doing are I want to you're right the
next let's say the next let's say the
first I mean the cost the inputs of
stuff is so cheap I mean you'd be
disgusted how McDonald's for their sodas
it's like probably about three three to
four cents for them to make a soda in
terms of the marginal cost of a soda
Okay so let's say it's 3 cents for a
small and 4 cents for a large okay so
basically they're if if they couldn't
get if preferences were such and you can
write preference this way where I never
want anything more than a small like
literally our stomachs can't hold more
than a small then they nobody pay a
penny more for a large and they wouldn't
make it but nobody's that way every most
people pay a penny more for a large so
then your question is how much more can
I charge before people don't want the
larges anymore and that's essentially
the calculation they're doing is there
they comput and they've got people
hundreds of people doing this all the
time saying look if we charge 69 cents
people buy the large if we buy if we
charge 70 cents people buy a couple
fewer larges but we make one cent more
but once it go about 71 no longer makes
sense and that's essentially the
business decision making we'll talk
about in a few lectures which is how to
businesses decide how to set their
prices here we're just showing this set
their prices and response to a principle
we now know is generally true which
diminishing marginal rate of
substitution
other questions good question other
questions all right well let's stop
there um we will it's a little early but
that's all I got for today so we will uh
come back on Wednesday and we'll talk
about what happens when you actually
have a limit on how much you can spend