Good afternoon. [clears throat] I
realize I'm sitting here standing here
between you and your lunch. So I'll be
quick. Five slides only. Uh so uh Zafino
um my name is Sanjay Marander uh founder
CEO and uh we started this company
literally uh last year late last year
and we saw a need a need that we felt
this generation of AI can actually help
and this is about uh managing compliance
and staying compliant right so we're uh
initially targeting highly regulated uh
dibs stands for defense industrial base
and in particular
There's one particular um um
regulation called CMMC which literally
went live a few days ago, November 11th.
So that means dibs have now one year to
be compliant and provide a cert to the
US government if the US government is
their customer whether you're small or
large you're going to have to provide
thatert and so as a result we felt
there's a cliff coming and this is a
very very large problem and primarily
it's uh a very difficult problem because
to date it has been a very manual
process it's very uh you know disjointed
fragmented
And because it's manual, a lot of
consulting hours get used and that means
it tends to be extremely expensive. And
we felt there's got to be a way to
ingest all this disperate data. Uh
yep. So yeah. So the solution that we
came up with is initially we said let's
uh target the uh defense industrial base
uh with uh a product we call integrity.
And what you're seeing here is the
dashboard. What we're doing uh generally
is that there's a uh a framework whereby
our framework can ingest any kind of
documentation policies uh that you may
have and we compare that with the rule
book and initially the rule book for
integrity is CMMC and what we're doing
is in not months which is what typically
happens if you're using consulting hours
in uh minutes we're going to give you a
view of where you stand And what you're
seeing here are 110 controls in that
dashboard top left. That's for CMMC. And
it will very quickly tell you how many
you've met, how many you partially met,
and how many you've not met instantly.
And then we'll tell you also what what
you need to do to get to the next level.
You might we might say, "Hey, uh you're
28% compliant today." And we we'll say
do these three things next. And oh, by
the way, the people responsible that
need to do these are also these various
folks. your CFO, your uh director of IT
and so forth. And we'll tell you how
many uh percentage points you'll gain.
Our goal is to get you to 100% as
quickly as possible and also to do it
reliably. We actually, you know, we all
know about hallucination by AI systems
and all that. Compliance is a
deterministic system. So that's why we
have a little bit of human in the loop,
but at the same time, we need to get you
to 100% before you present yourself to
the auditors. And of course uh uh what
what typically is happening here is the
reason you want to even do this uh is
because compliance is sitting between
you and your revenue and if uh you're a
a government contractor sometimes it's a
lot of revenue and the government now
has said it's not an episodic process.
You need to be continuously compliant
and you know people throw up their arms
because it's not going to be possible.
So here's our uh a typical uh customer.
One of our uh customers uh she's a CISO
where the government portion of the you
know business is about 100 million and
she has to be compliant by November
2026. She doesn't even know where to
start, right? And so and certainly there
and typically you're spending 400 to
500k for something like this. and she's
told us there's just no chance we're
going to uh you know uh have that kind
of budget and we don't have uh you know
a year of consulting hours. So um uh the
first project is of course uh first
product of course is in uh dibs uh but
the reason we're here is because we know
in the audience we have a lot of ILP uh
you know members who are uh in
industrial as well as insurance finance
healthcare and you all man you all uh
need different compliance requirements
from various regulatory bodies and so if
we can be of help to you because we are
looking for design partners
Uh please come uh say hello. We're next
door again. My name is Sanjay Maranda
and very happy to be here for the second
time with second company at ILP. Thank
you.
[applause]