the MIT energy initiative presents
making the case for hydrogen in a zero
carbon economy analyzing California's
power system Mighty researchers show
that hydrogen generated electricity is a
cost competitive candidate for backing
up wind and solar written by Lita
Zimmerman as the United States races to
achieve its goal of zeroc carbon
electricity Generation by 2035 energy
providers are swiftly ramping up
renewable resources such as solar in
wind but because these Technologies turn
out electrons only when the sun shines
and the wind blows they need backup from
other energy sources especially during
seasons of high electric demand
currently plants burning fossil fuels
primarily natural gas fill in the gaps
as we move to more and more renewable
penetration this intermittency will make
a greater impact on the electric power
system says m genser a research
scientist at the MIT energy initiative
or Mighty that's because grid operators
will increasingly resort to Fossil
fuel-based peer plants that compensate
for the intermittency of the variable
renewable energy or VRE sources of sun
and wind if we're to achieve zero carbon
electricity we must replace all
greenhouse gas emitting sources cancer
says low and zero carbon alternatives to
greenhouse gas emitting peer plants are
in development such as arrays of lithium
ion batteries and hydrogen power
generation but each of these evolving
Technologies comes with its own set of
advantages and constraints and it has
proven difficult to frame the debate
about these options in a way that's
useful for policy makers investors and
utilities engaged in the clean energy
transition now genser and Drake D
Hernandez
sm21 have come up with a model that
makes it possible to pin down the pros
and cons of these peer plane
Alternatives with greater Precision
their hybrid technological and economic
analysis based on a detailed inventory
of California's power system was
published in the July 6 2021 online
edition of Applied Energy with an
October 2021 print publication date
while their work focuses on the most
cost-effective solutions for replacing
peer power plants it also contains
insights intended to contribute to the
larger conversation about transforming
Energy Systems our study's essential
takeaway is that hydrogen fired power
generation can be the more economical
option when compared to lithium ion
batteries even today when the cost of
hydrogen production transmission and
storage are very high says Hernandez who
worked on the study while a graduate
research assistant for Mighty adds
genser if there is a place for hydrogen
in the cases we analyzed that suggests
there is a promising role for hydrogen
to play in the energy
transition adding up the costs
California serves as a stellar Paradigm
for a swiftly shifting power system the
state draws more than 20% of its
electricity from solar and approximately
7% from wind with more VRE coming online
rapidly this means that peer plants
already play a pivotal role coming
online each evening when the Sun goes
down or when events such as heat waves
drive up electricity used for days at a
time we looked at all the peer plants in
California recount skener we wanted to
know the cost of electricity if we
replace them with hydrogen fired
turbines or lithium ion batteries the
researchers used a core metric called
the levelized cost of electricity or
lcoe as a way of comparing ing the cost
of different Technologies to each other
lcoe measures the average total cost of
building and operating a particular
energy generating asset per unit of
total electricity generated over the
hypothetical lifetime of that asset
selecting 2019 as their base study year
the team looked at their cost of running
natural gas fired peer plants which they
defined as plants operating 15% of the
year in response to gaps in intermittent
renewable electricity in addition they
determined the amount of carbon dioxide
released by these plants and the expense
of abating these emissions much of this
information was publicly available
coming up with prices for replacing peer
plants with massive arrays of lithium
ion batteries was also relatively
straightforward there are no technical
limitations to lithium ion so you can
build as many as you want but they are
super expensive in terms of their
footprint for energy storage and the
mining required to manufacture them says
genser but then came the hard part
nailing down the cost of hydrogen fired
electricity generation the most
difficult thing is finding cost
assumptions for new technologies says
hernandes you can't do this through a
literature review so we had many
conversations with equipment
manufacturers and plant operators the
team considered two different forms of
hydrogen fuel to replace natural gas one
produced through electrolyzer facilities
that convert water and electricity to
hydrogen and another that reforms
natural gas yielding hydrogen and carbon
waste that can be captured to reduce
emissions they also ran the numbers on
retrofitting natural gas plants to burn
hydrogen as opposed to building entirely
new facilities their Model includes
identification of likely locations
throughout the state and expenses
involved in construction of these
facilities the researchers spent months
compiling a giant data set before
setting out on the task of analysis the
results from their modeling were clear
hydrogen can be a more costeffective
alternative to ion batteries for peing
operations on a power grid says
Hernandez in addition notes genser while
certain Technologies worked better in
particular locations we found that on
average reforming hydrogen rather than
electrolytic hydrogen turned out to be
the cheapest option for replacing peer
plants a tool for energy
investors when he began this project
genser admits he wasn't hopeful about
hydrogen replacing natural gas in peer
plants it was kind of shocking to see in
our different scenarios that there was a
place for hydrogen that's because the
overall price tag for converting a
fossil fuel-based plant to one based on
hydrogen is very high and such
conversations likely won't take place
until more sectors of the economy
Embrace hydrogen whether as a fuel for
transportation or for varied
manufacturing and Industrial
purposes a nent hydrogen production
infrastructure does exist mainly in the
production of ammonia for fertilizer but
in Norm investments will be necessary to
expand this framework to meet grid scale
needs driven by purposeful
incentives with any of the climate
Solutions proposed today we will need a
carbon tax or carbon pricing otherwise
nobody will shift to new technologies
says genser the researchers believe
studies like theirs could help Key
Energy stakeholders make better informed
decisions to that end they have
integrated their analysis into Sesame a
life cycle and technoeconomic assessment
tool for a range of energy system
systems that was developed by MIT
researchers users can leverage this
sophisticated modeling environment to
Compare costs of energy storage and
emissions from different Technologies
for instance or to determine whether it
is cost-efficient to replace a natural
gas powered plant with one powered by
hydrogen as utilities industry and
investors look to decarbonize and
Achieve zero emissions targets they have
to weigh the cost of investing in lowc
carbon Technologies today against the
potential impacts of climate change
moving forward says Hernandez who is
currently a senior associate in the
energy practice at Charles River
Associates hydrogen he believes will
become increasingly cost competitive as
its production costs Decline and markets
expand a study group member of mighty's
soon Tobe published future storage study
Gensler knows that hydrogen alone will
not usher in a zeroc carbon future but
he says our research shows we need to
seriously consider hydrogen and the
energy train transition start thinking
about key areas where hydrogen should be
used and start making the massive
Investments
necessary funding for This research was
provided by mighty's low carbon energy
centers and future of storage study