it's great to be here everyone I am Sid
probstein I am the Creator uh of swirl
and the CEO of swirl corporation which
uh promotes and uh is expanding it into
the Enterprise I've been lucky to work
in search a few times previously at
companies like um an tibio now better
known as service now uh but in
particular I'm focused on the scavenger
hunt and our team is obsessed with
ending the scavenger hunt you know what
the scavenger hunt is it's the less fun
version of the thing we've sometimes
done at birthdays or or at parties uh
and it's particularly impactful for
employees in the Enterprise where they
have many silos they go from tab to tab
logging in Remembering how to use the
search engine uh or query system writing
queries downloading documents and AI
seems like it should be the perfect
answer but yet there's a
problem the problem is AI Solutions
especially this first generation require
you to copy data into them they're like
databases your information goes in and
you get insight out that can be
problematic in when you have complex
security across multiple silos uh
compliance issues in regulated markets
such as sharing a departmental owned
resource with a corporate owned resource
or simply verifying that a third party
is okay to hold your data when your uh
information in landscape looks a little
bit like this uh the cost of duplicating
data becomes hugely problematic and
ultimately it requires you to have a lot
of Technical and security capability not
every organization is 100% ready to just
do those things and so that's why you
see so many articles about the adoption
of AI being slow or challenging swirl is
different swirl is software you deploy
anywhere in your environment in your
subscription on your Edge it's 100%
containerized so information never
leaves your environment or control and
that's really a key compliance issue
another one is swirl uses a zero trust
model there's no way to add documents to
swirl it doesn't accept them there's no
indexing it integrates with single sign
on and so it's able to talk to the silos
exactly the way the user does in fact it
does so on their behalf creating a very
personal view when swirl searches or
generates an AI Insight uh the way you
would sort of creating a chat GPT for
your data it's your outlook your one
drive your email your calendar your
files now sometimes people say well okay
what does that sort of end up looking
like well here's a convers a with your
data here's one that I have uh had
recently how much cyber Insurance do we
have as a company I'm the person
responsible I bought the policy and I
dropped it in one drive as one does I
don't remember exactly what's covered
now swirl turns any llm or gai that's
sufficiently capable into a powerful
Search Assistant we show it what the
user is authorized to see so when I
suggest I'm looking for a policy of our
companies it comes right back and says
that might well be in one drive or
SharePoint I confirm that and I get the
answer in less than a minute that saved
me at least five more five to 10 minutes
because it's about a 50-page policy
there's also a second document that I
would need to gather it's referenced
here actually because in addition to the
Insight I have citations I can click
those links and verify that this is all
correct and of course that's part of
building a trusted AI solution you have
to be able to verify the
information it's not just for Content
though swirls Works amazing amazingly
well and transforms that Search
Assistant into someone who can help you
navigate structured data uh ever come to
a new job flipped open your new laptop
and found 50 icons sure we can
understand what's under chat or email
but what's under powerbi or Tableau or
some other business intelligence or
reporting tool there could be anything
there thrl can generate answers to
structured data questions like how much
did we ship or how much did someone
raise what categories have been raising
recently even visualize it but
ultimately you can click the link and go
right into the
silo srl's secret secret special power
is
reranking swirl gets the results by
using search apis or query apis and then
figures out using Vector analysis and
large language models what's the best
result for the user's query it's
contextual and has that uncanny human
feeling that you get when you're talking
to chat GPT so here you can see swirl
reranking Google's results you search
for red hat acquires you can do this
right now most of the results will come
back about red hat being acquired by IBM
if you use swirl which by the way you
can get running with two lines and
Docker in one minute uh you'd rerank
that result set and find all of the red
hat Acquisitions or even purchases
because it knows that those words mean
the same thing it works amazingly well
on box.com and many many other search
engines uh here we find the search term
in the title and boost it up from result
two to result number
one swirl can do this kind of
conversation and search and reranking
using any of the AIS or llms in the
left-hand column and generate insights
from the data platforms Enterprise
applications and web services you see
here leaders like mongodb Google big
query or snowflake uh Enterprise
applications obviously M365 but also
other popular ones like Salesforce
service now slack and
atlassian and what are the benefits of
deploying swirl while a global life
sciences firm studied their supply chain
team they were um struggling with
information overload too many reports
and different dashboards to use they had
a data science team on call effectively
through a ticket system with a two week
SLA and they had the highest cost to
answer questions and significant burnout
in the team due to the problem of having
to ask over and over again with swil
they s switched 100% to a self-service
model and they saved 7 and a half hours
per employee per week that's their own
study in particular 4 hours with the
navigation problem you can see in the
lower right hand corner we've also help
solve these kinds of problems for secure
Services firms where critical help desk
information needs to be brought together
without actually merging the data and a
national technology service provider
that's um solving uh incoming requests
from prospects uh in less than a few
minutes uh with very high accuracy and
ultimately taking the humans out of the
loop and letting them focus on um the
exceptional cases right when one of the
great things about swirl is when an AI
isn't confident we can flag that and uh
cue it for review human review we are
here looking for Enterprise uh proof of
value opportunities for teams of
Departments of around 50 employees
particularly if they're reporting on and
or making decisions using documents and
databases from multiple silos especially
in regulated Industries some of the use
cases you see here uh supply chain I
already mentioned uh lending is a big
one and leasing a wash in documents that
are typically not in data models with
the goal of increasing productivity
reducing decision time uh eliminating
information gaps and also increasing
customer
satisfaction so I'll just pause here
love to take some questions I hope that
uh all made
sense thanks SED um good examples um and
um I think a variety of sectors that
hopefully people can see um their
applications so um a question about
privacy which is so important tell us a
little more about that so I think it's
been it's been written about a lot that
privacy um is one of the biggest
barriers to adopting AI swirl is is
software deployed in your own
environment it's not a SAS we can host
it for you if you like for some
applications we're happy to do so but
when you're deploying it and it's going
to have access to um employee pii and
potentially other sensitive information
it stays in your own environment your
your corporate environment so it's never
leaving your firewall so to speak that
term is not totally correct these days
but anyway let's call it the perimeter
and um as a result it's under the same
controls that the current employee is uh
data is so that's really compliant and
be much more reassuring to um employees
who might otherwise worry that you know
their internal Communications are being
shared with a third
party great and um which areas within a
company um are do you tend to work with
and um what's the um process for like
user interface and um and things like
that oh great great great question uh so
ultimately we work with folks who have
documents and databases supply chain is
a very common one uh status report
analysts are very common research teams
um R&D teams particularly uh both on the
dev side we have lots of folks who use
us to look across multiple
githubsign with the apis first you can
uh assemble a variety of different
widgets and interfaces you can deploy on
your existing
applications okay thank you