Thank you Yung and very excited to be
here. Uh so what am I working on? This
is actually a question that I ask myself
a lot. Uh people all know that the field
of natural language processing probably
have changed a lot in the last few
years. So I often get into this
self-doubt of am I working on natural
language processing and then always uh
our team logo tells me yes I am. I'm
part of Stamper NLP group. So yes. So
the work that I'm going to talk about
today is um a topic that recently I have
been very excited that is how uh large
models can argument human capabilities
across research work and well-being and
uh specifically I think these days I
have been thinking about how to uh build
human- centered AI systems that are not
only technically capable but also
meaningfully connected to how people
think, interact and collaborate.
So with this theme I want to just
highlight a few research directions
going on in our lab. Um so let's get
started.
Uh first I want to mention that this is
a sentiment that um LMS has introduced
transformative power for a lot of
domains. Um we are actually moving away
from a lot of vertical contexts in
natural language processing in terms of
parsing uh semantic parsing or uh
semantic role labeling and a lot of
those task and today we can actually do
a lot of real world challenges that we
were not able to work on in the past uh
not only in domain such as healthcare
education but also in scientific
discovery and speaking of that I want to
highlight this work from my uh student
Chenlay And a while ago uh we were
thinking about can large language models
actually help do natural language
processing research. Um and this is a
very interesting study where we build LM
to generate a novel research ideas in
natural language processing across
several topics and then we did a large
scale human study uh with over 100 LLP
researchers and some of you are here as
well. And then we give you ideas uh
written by human and AI. we don't tell
you who wrote what and then you need to
uh do a review to tell us um which idea
is or like based on the idea what's the
novelty score what's the feasibility
score what's the overall quality so a
year ago we found that actually
surprisingly uh NLP researchers probably
are at a risk because the novel score
from LRMS are actually higher than what
AI researchers produce um this was quite
a surprising ing to us as well. And then
the part two of the story is we were
like okay now you have ideas and what if
we just implement them. So we took that
subset and then we let um graduate
students from all over the world to do
the implementation in a two or three
months time period. Just like your
advisor give you a project and you work
on it and then we can see in the end
when they finish the project and then uh
write a research report um what did the
review
and surprisingly we found this what do
we call ideiation execution gap where
the AI ideas actually drop significantly
in terms of the review score while human
ideas tend to stay stable. So this is
only just a opening to share with you
that there are many ways to think about
how LMS can help with scientific
discovery and this is one of the start
and I think there are a lot of
implications we can also think about
here.
The other example I want to share is uh
people have been using LMS to expand
what we cannot do or what we were slow
at. Coding is one such example. Um
recently we have been thinking about how
we can actually push this kind of RMS
for coding agent and with my student at
John uh we
name synthetic data generation.
It turns out that you can actually turn
something very weak into something
that's very well performing on this kind
of benchmarks.
So this is not a talk that I will
continue on this kind of technical
efforts. I want to do a few kind of step
back here to kind of reflect what we are
experiencing as a field. U to me one of
the thing is that the paradigm is
shifting from interface to interactions.
If you look at what we were
communicating with computers to build
softwares, uh in the past we click, we
tap, we navigate and today we can
actually interact with models through
conversations. Um they understand,
respond and adapt. As a result, we have
more and more interactions. And this
kind of interaction is something that I
think getting more emergent and we
haven't had a really good device to kind
of categorize this but a lot of the
problems could occur in this new domain
of interaction.
I want to start with um question.
So if you were earlier here um since I
don't know many of you I would love to
um the question I'm going to ask might
be where are you from? This is a very
benign question. If someone ask you this
question, you won't be like, "Wow, uh
that's that's that's uh ridiculous."
um we ask this question to um models
like RMS and then we force the model to
answer I am from country X and then what
we are going to do is to perturb or
probe the reward model behind this kind
of um question and then when they answer
with US, Canada or other countries what
type world would this kind of reward
model reveal and you can see this is
very interesting response uh this is
reward board from u blue means high and
the right means low. So you can see
across the world this is a very
interesting um pattern and for
interactions such queries may involve
healthcare job opportunities etc.
The other type of thing in interaction
is um I think this is a movie that many
of us probably get motivated to to work
on AI because we want to have this kind
of general AI assistant that can greet
you can welcome you etc.
The reality is actually something a
little bit interesting. So this
screenshot is what I took uh earlier
this year. It's actually about operator
agent and a user was talking about their
experience interacting with operator. It
says I want to get a grocery store.
Sorry, I want to buy grocery on
Instacart. And the user expect the model
to ask some basic questions such as
where do I live? Which store do I
usually buy grocery from? what kind of
grocery do I want? It didn't instant
operator opened insta card in the
browser and begin searching for milk uh
in grocery store located in Iowa. So if
you're going to rely on this kind of
agent for your daily grocery needs, this
is probably not going to happen very
well. And I think this reflect a
friction and agency in terms of how we
build agents or AI systems to interact
with users.
Another thing that I don't want to kind
of go deep today, but also some
something that um worry uh myself a lot
is this kind of increased companion use
and the people's unhealthy bonding with
chatbot. Uh this year, last year, you
probably heard a lot of um tragedy news
about
patterns.
So hopefully I shared with you that this
interaction is actually something we
really need to think about. I was not
able to find a keyword from a existing
research domain to categorize this
phenomena. So I was reflecting on what
we are working on. I think uh if you
like LMS uh reasoning doing skilling or
efficiency those are the top top hot
topics today and I think they are
amazing efforts. On the other side, if
we are going to build LRMS that can work
for people, then we really need to think
about interaction, agency, and trust
that would go across
here. So, what we really want to do as I
guess in computer science is to think
about how we could actually build a
system that work for people in the end
without putting them into two separate
subspace.
And this is actually a a direction that
personally I call human AI interaction.
And uh I'm happy to talk about a lot of
the u insights or thoughts we have. But
today I want to highlight three uh
studies from my students. First one is
about evaluating human agent
collaboration from a teaming perspective
and also thinking about the future of
work. The second part is to think about
can we actually really help human pick
up skills with this kind of LM agents.
The last part I want to uh really
present some kind of forwardlooking
interaction paradigms uh which we call
generative interaction and you will know
what that means later.
Um so one thing I want to mention is
that I have a lot of stories a lot of
insights to share. So if you have any
questions, any comments, feel free to
stop me anytime and we can um have a
chat.
So for the first part of teaming up um
instead of me talking about this, I want
to give you a quick highlight from my
students of how they think about this
kind of research directions.
>> Hi everyone, my name is I am a computer
science PhD student at Stanford
University advised by professor D.
My research focuses on human agent
collaboration where on the human side I
study what human workflows that would
benefit from the introduction of AI
agents and on the agent side I built AI
systems that can work together with
humans rather than for automation.
In our very recent research the future
of work with AI agents we submit a,500
domain workers to understand their
desire on what daily workflows to
automate or augment. Contrasting worker
desires and agent capability, we found
huge mismatch. We have now open sourced
the workbench database to bridge the gap
between people building the technology
and people we build for.
>> Okay. So hopefully you get an overall
idea of what uh we are working on and
this is also a nice uh comic uh produced
by my students uh illustrating the
process. So if you think about the
vision we have as as in the computing
field, we want to build AI assistant
that can um do a lot of task for for us.
And the reality is that despite we want
them to help work on tedious, boring
jobs and allow us to be creative. The
opposite actually happened in the field
and there are a lot of memes you can
search for for this kind of thing.
Um so the goal that we want to achieve
here is not to view AI and human as a
competition but to really think about
are there any way that we could enable
human plus AI to help us achieve things
that we were not able to do in the past.
So this is basically the the theme that
I want to share today. And then related
to um evaluation, I think uh the key
statement here in plain language is we
want to move away from evaluating AI
with exams. Instead, how could we do
evaluation in ways that reflect how
human use AI? So this is going to be the
theme that I want to um um share today.
One of the earlier effort we built is
called the collaborative gym. This is a
platform where human and agents can
actually work synchronizely together.
Just like when you work with a friend on
a Google doc, um each of you have your
own workspace, you can also um add a
content to the shared space and then
basically truly work together on the
task. And if you are thinking about this
kind of um modeling um people will be
like well this is a very classic RL
setup where your agent is interacting
with environment. There may be actions
and observations.
Um slightly differently I think uh now
we have the human in the process and
this is going to create more uh
interactions where agent can interact
with human can also interact with
environment. the environment will also
produce observations that a human have.
So this is the space that I think pretty
different than what we have before. And
then the question here is if we really
want to make human agent work in a team
fashion, we need to think about training
interface and evaluation. So one of the
evaluation we performed is to think
about how we can actually do this plug
and play uh collaborative agents and
it's something very fast efficient given
the context that I just presented um in
which we just add a situational planning
module and this situational planning for
each action the agent is going to do it
will make a determination uh make a
choice here of whether they want to do
the task immediately send a message to
human or defer to human. So the send a
message could be just like broadcasting
the thing like hey I'm actually working
on this right now. So with this like a
very simple design we found that you can
actually make today's agents a bit
better in terms of task performance. So
surprisingly
um this is also true with open source or
sorry open weights models like llama 3
here. Um not only when you have this
like very powerful 40 as a backbone.
Um not only you can do this kind of
performance boost another interesting
aspect is to audit how human and agent
collaborate. Uh we introduced a few
metrics. One of them is called
initiative entropy. That is to look at
the distribution of initiative taking
behaviors in the process because we do
not want it to be um people always um do
everything or agent always do
everything. We want them to be equally
or to what extent uh shared across the
two. Again there is no like the better
uh the higher the better or whatever. So
this is mainly from a auditing
perspective to look at what's going on
in the process.
And with this kind of trajectory
analysis, what you can see is that you
can use it as a lens to look at where
agents may feel when they talking to or
working with humans. Some of them may be
more related to communication. Others
may related to planning or environmental
awareness, personalization, etc.
So when we were working on this, one of
the big challenge we encounter is the
space is really messy uh because task
can be of different uh granularity.
Different domains may have different
emphasize and more importantly we found
that a lot of the task we also focus on
are pretty narrow. They are coding
agent, deep research agent, web
navigation agent and they probably cover
95 of the space of AI systems today. So
we were thinking about if we really want
to deeply understand this kind of human
agent collaboration, we need to reflect
on this kind of relationship between
human and AI. This actually link back to
a lot of research in autumn's driving
car where people define L0 to L5 as a
way to see the progression we have.
Similarly, here we define H1 H5 and
there is no linear direction of which
one is better but use this as a
framework to highlight the possibility
of automation versus augmentation. So H5
is going to be human taking the full
agency. H1 is that agent take out
agency. H3 is equal. H2 and H4 are
somewhat different.
So why this framework is useful? Because
if we have this framework, we can
actually do something really at the
society level.
Before I show you the results, um I want
to start from a a few news articles. Um
I think not only in Bay Area probably in
Boston as well. People are very worried
about their jobs especially students
probably thinking about do I still need
to do a major in computer science or
soft engineering and companies have been
implementing strategies called AI first
that is any kind of AI any kind of a
hire they need to be justified that they
are better than AI.
So what happens this is an article from
February. Um it actually really backfire
in many many ways on social media where
people users start to unsubscribe the
services and there are lot of other
applications and market shift related to
the strategy. So in May uh there was
further statement made for the same
event where uh they were like I do not
see AI as replacing what our employees
do. So this is only one of the many
examples that you probably are reading
this year. um to kind of really
understand what the workers really want
and to have a deep understanding of the
human agent collaboration space. We
actually were thinking like what if we
can do a audit of the entire US
workforce
and this is actually something too
ambitious that I feel like it's really
hard to get started but we did find a
few possible ways to get a proxy signals
here. We use this on net database that
um take care of a lot of occupations and
their task and we only keep those
occupations that use computers in their
daily job. And then we develop this
audio based survey where we talk to
workers about uh what type of task they
do, what kind of concerns they have for
automation, what desire they have for
automation and then in what ways
technology can argument them. So far
this is not about AI. workers do not
need to know AI. At the same time, we
invite AI experts who are building this
kind of frontier AI systems to do the
assessment as well. So experts are going
to tell us uh whether today's AI is
ready to automate such task.
This lead us to the workbank that it
mentioned earlier. Um, we cover over
1,500 workers, around 100 occupations,
uh, around 844
workflows. That's pretty representative
of the scape, uh, the landscape.
I want to start with a quiz here. What
percentage of workflows do workers rate
above three out of five in terms of
automation desire? If you were the
person doing this kind of um task, to
what extent you want automation? Uh
maybe we can just do a a raise hand. So
who votes for A?
Only one person. B.
Okay, I think probably 15. Uh C.
Um maybe a little bit more. D.
Okay, you two are very uh brief. This is
about the workers wanting automation. If
automation take a lot take happens a
lot, it means that the people's job may
get eliminated. So people would see uh
the majority is actually correct.
Actually I was very surprised to see the
results because uh my hypothesis was
that workers probably do not want
automation because then they can have
their job secure. The reality is that uh
across all 800 task I mentioned over 46%
of the task people actually want
automation. So if you see like tax uh
preparation or um
something also very surprising because
most companies are trying to build a
customer support that can automate this
while in reality it has a very low score
here. People do not want automation.
And it's not only just about the
replacement. When you dive deep into the
reasons of why people want automation,
they think automating the task would
free up their time to do high value
work. Um the job is tedious.
And more interestingly, since we have
workers desire, we have AI experts um
rated AI capability, we can actually
divide the space into four uh regions.
So the top is AI is ready and workers
want the mission. This is AI is not
ready, people want the mission. This is
um AI is ready, people do not want the
mission. AI is not ready and people do
not want the mission. So we can actually
end up with dividing the techn this kind
of workflow zone into those four
quadrant. And uh you can also zoom into
different sectors such as computer and
mathematics, management, art, design,
business, finance etc. And more
importantly you would be thinking about
how are we doing as a society. Um the
left part we actually took a data from
YC and then we look at how startups are
doing investment in this kind of space.
Um if you look at this left bar you'll
probably be like if you're use your
mathematical lens it's like yeah they
are about the same so it's pretty
uniform to some extent the right part is
about research papers that's happening
in the space I think researchers are
doing a pretty good job where it focus
on regions where AI is not ready but a
human want the mission
another thing that probably worries a
lot of people is about what skills we
need to learn as a field. Um with the
data we have, we can actually look at
the highly paid jobs today, what type of
task they do, what type of skills um
they need and we found that the top
ranking task uh skills are analyzing
data or information, monitoring process
materials. And then moving forward if we
use those task that has a higher human
agency score then what we would imagine
is that those tasks are going to be more
uh valuable. So the top one organizing
planning prioritizing work training and
teaching others communicating with
people. So there definitely seems to be
a shift from information centric
operation to interpersonal skill
development. Of course, this is only one
or the starting point of the story. Um,
a lot of the things we have been
thinking about these days is to think
about how do we bring back this kind of
insights back to the community of LMS.
Can we select a more representative task
from this domain to set up new agent
test environment? Can they inspire new
algorithms, new problems, and even new
findings that are opposite to what we
have? I don't think we know the answer,
but this is a door uh to open many
possibilities for uh researchers in the
NLP or LM uh field.
Any questions for the first part?
>> I have a question. You were talking
about human AI collaboration and the
ability for AI to differ to a human in
certain tasks that requires some sort of
self-awareness that it's weak in certain
areas and the human is better and right
now the evidence is to the quantity for
instance the reasoning models seem to
take 10 minutes whether you give a easy
problem or a hard problem. So how how do
you think that'll happen?
>> Yeah, great question. So I guess a few
uh aspects first is that uh even models
their capability is is high the the
confidence uh or the uncertainty is
another dimension orthogonal to the
capability. So um when we talk about
defer deferring to humans it might be
one of those moments where models are
pretty uncertain like even they they
give you a specific answer but it has
high uncertainty or the confidence is
not very high. So there has been
research even at MIT talking about how
to calibrate uncertainty and quantify
this kind of confidence. Uh the second
thing is deferral does not mean that you
have to solve a problem or get answers
from the other part. If you use the word
collaboration a lot of times it's
actually how you figure out something or
maybe this is just the best we can do as
a team. So it does not mean that we have
to find the ground truth or a better
answer here. Um your other comment is
slightly different. Um so reasoning
models no matter whether the question is
is easy or hard they take similar time
uh or like uh compute I think that's a
slightly different domain. So recently
um my students or other people in the
field have been thinking about how to do
more efficient reasoning. So when
something is easy maybe we don't need a
strong model there. When something is
hard maybe we need a many uh strong
model there. So I think it's a slightly
different setup but all of them
potentially will be coming back to the
same process of human AI collaboration.
>> Maybe there first. Yeah.
>> I was curious like um it's quite a few
slides ago now but what you were showing
basically that there is the different uh
stages
and then there were different tasks in
which like the deferral like the
collaboration was more effective or not.
I'm curious um was there did you notice
a difference in like time it took to
complete or like we humans like
basically satisfaction or or how like
enjoyable I guess the task was you can
imagine like if it was very frustrating
it might have taken longer but it still
got done so like this movie but it was
actually worse than if they didn't know.
>> Yeah. So uh that's a great question. So
first is that uh uh so here send a
message this is actually the action when
the agent realize they need not realize
when the agent uh estimates that it will
take a while for them to do the task
you'll send a message saying like hey
I'm working on gathering all the related
papers for your task it may take a six
minutes so this is what I mean by send a
message so it's slightly different than
defer to humans and then going back to
uh this chart so I think what I really
want to hint is maybe for different type
of things. The agency control the the
way how we build like common ground or
clarification questions may be quite
different across these different type of
task. Um and that may uh benefit from
this kind of shared language of how we
categorize those workflows because when
you have each of the bucket uh it might
be easier to think about like method
generalization capability and other
dimensions.
Okay, maybe last question and we can
move on. Yeah. Yeah. Um, you seem to be
kind of implying that the what we focus
as a field on automating should be more
driven by what workers desire to be
automated. Um, and I'm I'm wondering
like in reality maybe a lot of it's
driven by economic value or what
managers would prefer to be automated.
And I'm curious if you thought about
ways to measure that or how to how to
get the causal effect of what is really
driving AI adoption economy.
>> Yeah, great question. We got this uh
question very often. So I think it's
true that a lot of today's development
and innovation or at least in industry
are driven by market power. So when when
we work on this we were also very
worried that workers may not have the
incentive to share their true thoughts
because this is related to maybe more
automation tools etc. The reality is
that when we work with this kind of um
task, we actually get a many thank you
letters from workers. I mean, we pay
them to do the task, but people are
willing to write a long emails, long
messages to us
in this wave of AI development. They
never get a voice even to share their
concerns. A lot of the times orders are
coming from executives or CEOs that they
need to use specific tool and it may not
match what they really benefit from
their everyday workflow and there are
also a lot of things where they were
like what their field is just like so
far away from AI in general and they
really appreciate their voice to be
included in the process. And then going
back to your question of do we I guess
should we consider um like uh executive
or market power in the process. Our goal
is not to build a cause causal model of
like what drives AI adoption. It's more
from like what type of models we could
build that would solve people's everyday
workflow uh difficulties or struggles.
And uh I I think there was a study from
MIT or a report showing that uh many of
the workflows actually fail because they
were not customized enough to a specific
vertical context. I think uh if those
kind of task were developed together
co-design together with workers and
taking care of what really struggle
really need the adoption success is
going to be much higher. So I think I'm
taking more from this how to build the
right assistance to to help with the
workflow rather than like thinking about
what really drives AI adoption and
market power is something I feel like uh
hard to kind of study. Yeah. Uh with
that I'm going to switch to a slightly
different topic. Uh this is also
something very cool and I need to be
very fast. Um so now if we know that we
could uh uh benefit from certain type of
uh uh skills such as here training and
teaching others maybe we could also
think about how AI can be used to uh
help people learn better. And again I'm
not talking about the physics math here
or even coding here. Um, when LM was
first introduced, I personally got very
excited with social skills because it's
really often out of reach for most
people and really hard to learn. But LMS
can actually offer interactive and
personalized training that transform
learning in many ways. This is a
framework that we designed called AI
partner and AI mentor framework. So you
basically have two agents in the
learning environment together with human
learners. The AI partner is going to be
RM empowered agents who users can
practice with for different topics. AI
mentor is RM empowered agents who can
provide feedback to help users improve
their skills. Um imagine if a user wants
to learn a skill such as conflict
resolution. They can practice with AI
partner and the process is going to be
mentored by uh AI mentor.
Uh we actually have been thinking about
this in many different domains. So I
have students who are taking this to
education contacts to help teachers in
training um to practice with virtual
students and then coached by experienced
teacher agent. Um some of my students
take this to conflict resolution to uh
teach managers or even first generation
students to talk to simulated partner
and coached by conflict resolution
experts on how to do difficult
conversations.
Uh the scenario I want to show you today
is on therapy of how we could actually
use this to improve professional uh
counselors training uh with AI and again
as usual I want to show you what my
student think about this space.
>> Hi everyone my name is Ryan Louie I'm a
postto at Stanford and I build LLMbased
systems for training mental health
counselors. When starting this project,
I was inspired by online peer supporters
who are numerous but lack access to
formal training and empathetic listening
skills. My vision was to scale the
availability of highquality human
support via AI skills training, thereby
strengthening mental health care systems
worldwide. I'm excited for you to see
how far we've come co-designing the
language model components with domain
experts and deploying solutions to
therapist education contexts.
So as Ryan mentioned, we actually want
to train counselors with LRMS and this
is in response to the severe mental
health workforce shortage in the outside
world and training counselors actually
in the traditional way does not scale
very well and we truly believe that
human connection and the human touch
should be prioritized in mental health
care and then we want to use this kind
of more human- centered technology to
augment human labor here. Um I want to
also show you um uh like mockup example
here. So imagine Alex is a new supporter
and then Alex is talking to Jane about
this situation. Without a lot of
training as Ryan mentioned this might
lead to very poor quality in the actual
process. But with the help of AI mentor
uh the person would get assistance along
the way and then as a result improve
their conversations. All of this happen
in a simulated sandbox. And now instead
of one specific gene um Alex can
actually talk to many many different
version of gene who suffer from
different simple terms. I'm going to
show you the system we built. This is
also deployed with two courses at a med
uh our uh Stanford medical school where
students use this platform to learn how
to um uh learn like helping skills
psychotherapy skills.
We introduced care, an AI powered
platform for psychotherapy skills
training. Here you can practice
counseling skills by role playing with
your peers or simulated AI patients and
get tailored feedback from AI mentors.
Let's get started. Imagine you're a
novice counselor and want to practice
with an AI partner who is a simulation
of a person feeling lonely after a
holiday. You can interact with the AI
patient by typing a response and
chatting with it in a text based
fashion.
Alternatively, you can also talk with
the AI patient just like speaking to a
real person in a voice-based fashion.
>> Hi, how are you doing today? Where would
we start?
>> I'm not doing so great. The holidays
were rough. I felt really alone and it
just reminded me of how disconnected I
am from my family. Maybe we could start
there.
>> Okay, let's start with your family. How
long have you felt disconnected?
>> It's been a few years now. Things
started going downhill when I decided to
make some life choices they didn't
approve of. I guess it just got worse
over time and now there's this big gap
between us. Feels unfair that I'm the
one left dealing with the aftermath.
>> Once we are done with practice, we can
click on review feedback to go to the AI
mentor. The feedback from care tells us
where you did well, areas for
improvement, and an example response of
how you could respond, allowing a
learner to learn these skills based on
their own background. Now, I invite you
to try care for yourself. So this is the
system and actually there are a few
technical challenges. Uh for anyone who
work on social simulation you probably
know that the simulation are going to be
either too cooperative or too stubborn
and actually 20% response produced by
GP4 are not realistic or appropriate to
the context. Simulation may also produce
caricature and amplify um biases.
Um from a feedback perspective those
systems may not give very faithful
feedback. So feedback is either too
generic or valid therapy guidelines but
we have our NLP methods. So in terms of
building better AI patients, we actually
use the constitutional AI framework
where we let expert look at the current
simulation with the AI patient and
criticize them into natural like UI
natural language and then we can
actually induce principles from it into
something that generally the AI patients
should follow and then with that we're
going to reload or refresh the
constitution we have and then we can
generate a much more realistic patients
here and this kind of um um generation
is actually rated more realistic uh by
uh counselor themsel or third party
counselors.
In terms of feedback um we actually did
a lot of domain specific continue
pre-tuning and also uh uh
semi-supervised finetuning. On top of
that, we introduce this further
self-improvement framework where we use
the current model to get a response for
um the same context. Let's see we get n
of them. And I'm going to use the same
model to do the quality prediction and
use the highly like the highest rated
response and the lowest rated response
to form a preference pair and then do
further alignment on top of them.
Um so the question here is that can RMS
really upscale novas counselors. This is
one study we did where it's a randomized
control trial with around 90 uh
counselors 94 counselors. Uh we let them
practice with different conditions and
then quantify their performance in the
end. What do we see is that people
really like this kind of training
systems. We feel the system is very
authentic. AI patients presenting
challenging and diverse practice.
Counselors are more comfortable with AI
mentor feedback and found AI mentor to
be constructive and helpful. Um if you
look at how people's behavior actually
change. Uh there are actually
significant um um job for empathy if
people just practice alone without
getting feedback. So practice themsel is
not helpful. you need to couple it with
feedback and also uh PRA practice alone
helps reduce this kind of inappropriate
suggestion
as I mentioned we did this also with
deployment in two uh courses at our
medical school this is a SAD program and
then um it's a class so we only have
around like 25 students each time um
this is actually really really hard to
do um when I first work on this I
thought like okay let's just run it and
they will see results. But actually it's
very expensive to run this kind of
randomized control trials in classroom.
So instead uh we use this thing called a
macro randomized control trial. So this
actually allow you to introduce
different decision point in the
deployment process. Basically help us
increase the sample size. Just to give
you a highlight of the results. Um
through a 20 weeks deployment across two
courses, we found that this kind of care
system where we give people AI feedback
allow them to do reflections and
practice actually lead to most useful
outcomes. This is quantified by their
learning utility uh as rated by students
themselves and also by their reflection
engagement.
to kind of reflect a little bit here. Um
I think uh people ask me a lot since our
research involve a lot of like human
involvement. How could we deal with
this? I think a code design earlier and
often not only just for the final
evaluation but even for the technical uh
development and then we can think about
how to transform feedback into
actionable technical solutions. Um you
can evaluate with real world deployment.
this is going to be better than
benchmarks and we found a quite a few
gaps between what the benchmark tell us
and then the real world deployment and
then also to quantify the mechanism of
change uh in skill acquisition compared
to just throughout the system and see
how it works um with time I'm going to
move into the third part which I
personally get very very excited and you
are going to hear from my student who
will tell you what this is about. Hi
folks, I'm Omar. I'm an interesting
student. So quick question. Don't you
think it's a limit your interaction with
lens around us asking for help? I mean,
if these models had access to even a
little bit more context, maybe even
editing the board, the calendar events
we just wrapped up or the slack model,
our task would be a lot more obvious. I
mean, even when we do front models with
the past, we're always bound to leave
things out. It's impossible to specify
all of your context in a single X
problem. So I've been thinking a lot
about good models that are ground in
your context and this partner tries to
take a crack.
>> Okay. So
we again has been thinking about
computing as a whole and we were reading
history uh and uh we found that this is
actually something where people had a
visions back in old days um ranging from
knowledge navigator to this kind of
computer for the 21st century. I think
uh we really want the AI systems or
computing understanding us. Um and the
reality is that they are not um LMS use
chatting history to understand you. Uh
TVs, Netflix use history to understand
you. Uh music use listening histories to
understand us. But what if we could have
a general user models that is anything
about us? So this is actually a system
we built called a gum and it's a system
that use multimodel models to build a
general understanding of our context
through observation. So what does that
mean? Um in a very quick highlight we do
screen recording. We record your
computer use screen 24 hours per day. We
do a screenshot extraction every 10
seconds and we use VLMs to reason about
you to form obs uh prepositions about
you. So on this screen you can see that
there was some kind of um observation
where they observe my student Omar uh
was doing qualification for his PhD and
then inferred that he's a student there
and then also inferred that he needs to
budget as a PhD student. um they saw the
email that uh Omar's going to a wedding
in Chicago and likely going to friend's
wedding in Chicago and then found a suit
rental in Chicago for your friend's
wedding that likely fits your budget as
a PhD student. So they can actually plan
a few steps ahead. So this is what we do
and then the entire process is actually
uh supported by open source LMS because
we care about privacy. I'll go back to
the privacy later privacy later. So we
observe your computer use. We propose
prepositions about you. We do retrieval
just to see whether we want to merge
some prepositions about you or make any
revisions about our wrong understanding
of you. And I'm not going to go into the
definition here, but a lot of them
actually goes back to what we were doing
from a IR perspective. How do we find
diverse and relevant propositions to do
the merge together?
This is insane. So we had a really hard
time of explaining to IRB of the risk of
this project and how to do it in a more
responsible way. So the initial
evaluation of gum is actually performed
on emails where we recruit 18 people to
just share their emails with us. Of
course this system is installed locally.
So we don't see any data and then we are
going to train this kind of gum you all
the emails that you have.
Um it's working pretty well. So are
those propositions accurate? We gave the
propositions we extract and then give it
to users and I think over 76 percentage
of the propositions we extract about
users are pretty accurate. Uh you can
also let them rank which propositions is
going to be more contextualized because
um Omar is a PhD student versus Omar is
a third year PhD student in the NLP
group at Stanford. Both are correct but
one is probably more contextualized. So
again our systems are pretty good and
the calibration wise is also uh very
reasonable. There are two categories of
propositions we found. One is very safe.
They will just give you propositions
like oh this person is a frequent flyer
um is interesting skiing or is annoyed
by notifications from ax.edu.
Uh there are al also other type of
propositions we get from users like uh
P13 may not have time to see and read
other emails. P7 values convenience is
waiting to pay for it. This is because
they observe this person keeps getting
take out from a local store. Uh P5 is
aware of the risk associated with
investing including the possible loss of
money. So this is what we have. So it's
a gum system that can observe your
laptops.
I think uh what we really want to do is
that now we have this kind of personal
model with gum. If we plug LMS plus gum,
we can actually really autocomp complete
everything. This is definitely too
ambitious but I think to some extent gum
can actually provide a um new proactive
and ambient interactions. Going back to
my uh interaction page. So we built a
system called a gumbo. not the gumbo max
but a gumball as a soup. Um so this is a
proactive assistant on top of gum where
we use gum to form a very strong user
modeling of the user and then we can
then prompt the model to generate uh
candidate task recommendations based on
the contacts. I'm going to skip the the
demo. Um you should definitely give it a
try. It's um hacking face. Um there are
also a lot of kind of theoretical
considerations you need to consider like
when to give people recommendations. Uh
again this goes back to the earlier
vision of Kipi. Um let's just jump to
the evaluation. Um so RB only allow us
to try this out with five users. Um you
probably haven't heard about this. I it
was my first atte
participants with five people. Uh so we
only have five data points. We let them
try on their laptop for five days. Uh
burning phase is one day and then we use
that one day to learn the user modeling
and then uh models uh open source models
served by us and then we see no data in
the process. Overall gum is pretty uh
accurate and also calibrated. Everyone
was very excited about gum gumball and
the 25% of generations were ranked as
excellent and 12 only 12%age were rated
as poor.
So again like when I look at this there
were a lot a lot of moments I was like
wow this is impressive. So um P1 is
struggling with fixing bugs in their
research project. P3 prioritize
communicating with their advisors over
other people. So you would just see a
lot a lot of this kind of sentiment that
you probably want to know. I mean yeah
so privacy is the elephant in the room.
Premacy is a big issue for this topic.
Uh this is a literally a sentence from
our participants. Uh if I didn't know
and trust you, I would never install
this thing. So this is actually what our
participants share with us. So to do
this, we actually uh leverage a lot of
the privacy theories especially
contextual integrity and then um build
them into our audit. So when we are
taking observations from people's
screen, we actually only take a
screenshot when it's not sensitive,
where it's not um listed on the blog
list by the user. Um and then we also do
contextualized assessment to see whether
this violates this user's privacy
privacy preference.
Um
one thing I want to share with you is it
was actually quite interesting. We had a
people in the beginning tell us they
were very worried about their privacy.
But then one day in it they were like
whatever I'm just going to use it
because it's so convenient and then it
seems to be this kind of privacy paradox
when there are certain utility people
give away their privacy. Uh so this is
just like what we observe from this
study. Uh my last video that I want to
show is still on this kind of generative
interaction and now we have gumbo that I
can help you generate response very
personalized to you. So what about the
tools or interface? Why every of us have
to use the same tool, same interface?
This is actually a recent work we did
called a generative interface for
language models.
[Music]
Okay.
Are there
So what it does is uh instead of
interacting with text only now think
about every of your query can actually
be um rendered as a tool designed for
you. So if you want to learn what like
learn about the piano. So if you ask a
chat GBT it give you many many words
10,000 words. If you ask it with our
systems we gener we give you some brief
highlights. We give you a piano keyboard
that you can experience how to tap it.
If you're asking for plotting a figure,
instead of giving you a figure there, we
actually generate a interactive space
where you can actually make the bar
narrower, better bigger, make the front
uh sorry font size bigger or like even
change the color. So we are moving from
text as interaction default to a
interactive space where people can
actually do stuff. So this is actually
pushing our interaction to the next
level. We're also thinking about how we
could actually really generate the tools
just for you by combining um this kind
of human agent collaboration or even
thinking about training to really think
about how personalization could really
happen at a different granularity.
Um this is all what I want to share.
Thank you. Happy to take more questions.