Well, Thanks to Governor Healey.
I so appreciated her remarks.
So let me start my own remarks
with a few essential thank yous.
First, I have to say, in
reading through today's program,
I expect that we all
had the same experience.
Holy Toledo, this
lineup is spectacular.
The caliber of the speakers,
the boldness of their thinking,
the scale of their
accomplishments,
the range of frontier
subjects being covered
is just astounding, sort of
like a fantasy football team
if biologists played football.
In any case, I want to start
by thanking the incredible team
that persuaded all of
these brilliant people
to bend their calendars
to make this day possible.
Special shoutout to our Dean
of Science, Nergis Mavalvala,
to Dean of Engineering
and Chief Innovation
and Strategy Officer,
Anantha Chandrakasan,
to the entire Faculty Program
Planning Committee co-chaired
by Professors Amy Keating
and Katharina Ribbeck,
and especially to Marsha
Warren and the events team,
who orchestrated every detail.
We're all in your debt for
creating this extraordinary day.
And of course, I want to thank
all of our speakers from inside
and outside of MIT for
offering this amazing 14-course
intellectual banquet.
The talent assembled here--
from those who will
speak, to every one of
you-- has produced some truly
towering accomplishments.
But also, and I believe
more importantly,
you represent a deep well
of creative potential
for even greater impact, which
brings me to the insights that
inspired MIT HEALS.
Since I still have
fairly fresh eyes
on the wonders of this
multi-institutional community,
let me start with a
little perspective.
So I started my career as a
cell biologist and then a cancer
biologist.
And my husband, Danny Lew,
also leads a research group
here focused on pure
curiosity-driven science.
Well, we both had
long, happy careers
at another fine university.
But I will never
forget the expression
on Danny's face the day I
mentioned that I might interview
for the president's job at MIT.
MIT?
It was like those cartoon
dogs, where the eyes spin.
He was thrilled-- we
both were-- to think
we might join a place
with such a wall
to wall appreciation
for fundamental science.
And you can imagine
when we got here--
like kids in a candy store.
But pretty quickly, you
realize it's not a candy store.
It's a candy factory--
not only MIT, but the whole bio
ecosystem, from Kendall Square
to the seaport, to the
legendary hospitals
and the countless corporations,
startups, universities,
venture capitalists,
incubators, and philanthropists
across the region.
You see it any time you meet a
clinician or a faculty member.
Even students, they're exploring
techniques or technologies
right at the frontier
of their fields.
And then they casually
tell you, oh, yeah, I also
started a company
or two or more.
As a source of new knowledge
and new tools and new cures,
and of the innovators
and innovations that
will shape the future of
biomedicine and health,
there is just no place like it.
And today, we're here
to talk about how
we can make it even better.
That is the ambition
behind MIT HEALS.
Our goal with MIT HEALS is to
inspire, accelerate, and deliver
solutions at scale to
some of society's most
urgent and intractable
health challenges.
So with that goal in mind
and with expert guidance
and leadership from
many of you here today,
including Anantha and Nergis
and many other faculty leaders,
we've identified
three priority areas
where we have a
vital opportunity
to make a real difference.
In shorthand, these
three priorities
are talent, collaborations,
and bridges.
First, talent-- the caliber
of talent in this room today
is the caliber of talent that
this ecosystem needs every day
forever.
If we want to be the biotech
capital of the world,
to spawn the next
biotech revolution too,
we can't take this concentration
of talent for granted.
But nothing attracts
talent like talent.
So a crucial part of MIT
HEALS will be finding ways
to support, mentor, connect,
and foster community
for the very best minds at
every stage of their careers.
The second priority
of MIT HEALS is
to spark new cross-cutting
collaborations
between individuals, both
within MIT and with allies
in the hospitals and industry.
To encourage faculty to pursue
high-risk, high-impact ideas,
were going to be providing
substantial MIT funding.
So why is this?
Now, certainly because
daring, unproven ideas
can often be the
most transformative,
but also because federal
dollars are only shrinking.
Federal funding seems to
get more and more cautious
all the time.
I mean, I remember
this frustration--
and I'm sure many of you
experienced this frustration
firsthand-- to get a grant.
Sometimes people prefer you've
actually finished or almost
finished the work that
you're proposing to do.
This doesn't lead to
transformative discoveries
necessarily.
I also want to emphasize that
this internal funding will
support not only translation,
but deep, fundamental,
curiosity-driven research.
For people outside
academia, it's
very easy to see the
value of translation.
They see the cures that
make it to the bedside.
Yet for some outside of
the scientific community,
it can be a mystery why we care
so much about basic research.
But it is fundamental
curiosity that
has driven the discovery
of so much of what we know
and now take for granted
in the life sciences.
And I have to say--
I always say this-- even for
those focused on translation,
you can't translate nothing.
You have to think about the
fact that today's cutting-edge
approaches-- immunotherapy,
AIDS therapy, the mRNA vaccines,
the new sickle cell cure,
thanks to things like CRISPR,
things discoveries made based
on just fundamental curiosity--
all of them sprang
from a robust pipeline
of breakthrough knowledge.
So we're investing
enthusiastically
to keep that pipeline strong.
And of course, in
terms of translation,
we're eager to empower
MIT's unique community
at the juncture of
engineering and bioscience
in an era powered by
incredible new tools.
We want to give these faculty
members the confidence
to collaborate freely
with colleagues
from across disciplines-- from
AI, policy, and economics,
to the humanities, to design.
We want them to take
on the hardest problems
and pursue their biggest ideas.
We see great potential
for producing
practical, scalable solutions
in a wide variety of fields
such as AI and life science,
low-cost diagnostics,
neuroscience and mental health,
environmental life science, food
and agriculture, the future of
public health and health care,
and women's health.
Third and finally, MIT HEALS
will prioritize building bridges
between institutions, developing
even stronger, more effective
relationships with the
region's world-class hospitals
and biotech and
pharma industries.
Several of our
faculty, many faculty,
have established very
fruitful research programs
with hospitals
across the Charles.
I think about the work of
Regina Barzilay and J-Clinic
as standout examples.
But we want to
make it much easier
to make these relationships
spring up and flourish.
We want them to be
in reach for everyone
so that each PI doesn't
have to reinvent the process
and re-navigate the same
barriers around data sharing,
computing power, and more.
And at the same time,
while MIT has always
had a distinctive openness
to working with industry,
we believe that
there is much more
we can do to connect
our researchers
with the full power
of the ecosystem,
from biotech to pharma.
I have to say, I can speak
from my own experience--
even though it's receding
into the distant past--
working on basic science of a
particular drug-resistant breast
cancer.
We published a paper in
Science Translational Medicine.
We even patented our findings.
But it felt absolutely
impossible to take it further.
We didn't have an
ecosystem to plug into.
Here we definitely
have the ecosystem.
And MIT HEALS will help to very
deliberately improve and deepen
those connections, too.
Overall, MIT HEALS
is an opportunity
to make our work as individuals
and institutions collectively
add up to more than
the sum of our parts.
And I believe this
effort could not be
more timely or more important.
A key next step will be
selecting a faculty member
to serve as a director.
And a team of faculty
from across the institute
are conducting the
search right now.
In each of the
areas I described--
talent, collaboration
between individuals,
and bridges between
institutions,
we feel that action
is imperative.
And it gives me
great pleasure to let
you know that MIT
HEALS has already
attracted major support from
several sources, for instance,
in the area of talent.
An important aspect
of MIT HEALS is
supporting our graduate students
to explore new directions
in life science, particularly
interdisciplinary research.
I'm pleased that MIT
will be able to provide
new internal support
for an initial cohort
of graduate fellows
for MIT HEALS.
And we're delighted
that the founder
and CEO of Flagship Pioneering,
Noubar Afeyan, who's
here today--
one of our long-time
collaborators,
a member of the Executive
Committee of the MIT
Corporation, and a former MIT
Course X PhD student himself--
has committed to supporting
additional graduate fellowships
as part of MIT HEALS
So thank you, Noubar.
[APPLAUSE]
In the same spirit of
supporting great talent and as
another key part
of MIT HEALS, we
will launch the MIT Health and
Life Sciences Collaborative
Fellows Program, a
world-class program
for postdoctoral scholars.
This highly competitive program
will give fellows the freedom
to explore some of the
most pressing issues
in life science
and human health.
Fellows will receive a four-year
fully funded appointment at MIT
and benefit from faculty
mentorship, as well
as participation in
community events focused
on careers in academia,
industry, and entrepreneurship.
We are delighted to announce
a gift from the Biswas Family
Foundation to establish
the inaugural cohort
of postdoctoral fellows.
The Biswas Fellows will
conduct cross-cutting research
in areas such as AI
computation and health,
low-cost diagnostics, nanoscale
therapeutics, neuroscience,
women's health, and
curiosity-driven life sciences.
Thank you so much to the
Biswas Family Foundation.
[APPLAUSE]
As an example of sparking
new collaborations,
I'm also thrilled to announce
another integral piece of MIT
HEALS--
the new Hood Pediatric
Innovation Hub.
It was established
through a catalytic gift
from the Charles
H. Hood Foundation,
a leader in supporting
groundbreaking and innovative
pediatric research.
Led by Professor
Elazer Edelman--
the Edward J. Poitras Professor
in Medical Engineering
and Science and a world-renowned
cardiologist-- the hub
will bridge the
translational gap
for innovations in pediatrics.
Currently, the major
market incentives
are medical innovations
intended for adults.
As one example,
children are often
treated with medical
devices and therapies that
don't meet their needs because
they're simply scaled down
versions of the adult models.
The Hood Pediatric Innovation
Hub aims to overcome such
persistent barriers to bringing
life-saving technologies
to market by leveraging MIT's
state-of-the-art technological
expertise and a network of
health care stakeholders across
the country.
It will also strengthen
collaborations
with many hospitals, including
with an important partner
in Boston Children's Hospital.
So huge thanks to
the Hood Foundation.
[APPLAUSE]
And finally, I'm
excited to share
that one of the flagship
components of MIT HEALS
will be a collaboration
framework between MIT and Mass
General Brigham.
It will bring together these
two world-class research
institutions to advance
technology and clinical research
for transformative
changes in patient care.
Through the MIT-MGB
Seed Program,
we are garnering
and will continue
to seek philanthropic
funding to establish
seed grants for joint research
projects led by MIT and MGB
researchers in mutual
areas of interest.
And I'm extremely
pleased to announce
that Analog Devices will
help launch the MIT-MGB Seed
program with gifts
to both MIT and MGB
to establish the Analog Devices,
Inc. Fund for Health and Life
Sciences.
This visionary gift, which has
been described by Analog CEO
Vince Roche as a
once-in-a-generation
opportunity, will help
accelerate the adoption
of critical sensing, digital,
and AI technologies in clinical
settings.
And the new framework
overall will
be a model for how we can
all work together more
effectively in the future.
So thank you to MGB, and
thank you to analog devices.
[APPLAUSE]
So this is fantastic.
I mean, you can see there's
fuel, energy, power behind this.
We have very high
hopes for MIT HEALS.
And the momentum is
already beginning
to make these aspirations real.
Now, before I close, I have
to particularly call out
the Dean of Engineering
and Chief Innovation
and Strategy Officer,
Anantha Chandrakasan, who
has had the vision and
drive behind bringing
this initiative to life.
So I really want to
thank you again, Anantha.
[APPLAUSE]
And to all of you, I'm
so grateful that you've
joined us for this
important moment,
for this outstanding program.
Look forward to
working with all of you
as we work to seek new
knowledge, bold new solutions
to real problems in human
health in fields from cancer
to climate change.
So thank you all, and I hope
everyone enjoys the day.
[APPLAUSE]