so at vivc what we do is we take drugs
that normally cannot be absorbed by the
GI tract and get into the systemic
circulation and we take these drugs they
normally have to be given by IV and we
transform them into a tablet into a
simple pill and when the slides are up I
can jump to um the main part and show
you that how can we do this um well
first of all the reason why we do it is
that currently over 40% of the drugs on
the market um are large molecules and
Maria's presentation touched on this
earlier and so basically the size limits
them getting across the GI tract so with
the market um expanding in these areas
it's very very important to give
patients the choice to be able to take
the medicine orally and that's our
vision at vivc so we work with different
biotech and Pharma companies who have
new drugs that cannot get across the GI
tract okay so we work with biotech and
Pharma companies who have and drugs that
cannot get across the GI tract to make
them into oral pills so the challenge as
I said is that it's a large number of
drugs and our vision is to H give
patients the choice and the benefit for
the patients also touched by media
earlier is that you avoid needle pain
safety issu issues there is a higher
patient adherence but also the ability
to take a tablet at home really has a
positive impact on the Health Care
system and also there are advantages for
Pharma there's a larger patient
population a market that they can tap
into it also expands the IP uh
protection for that molecule and often
it gives competitive Advantage for a
particular Pharma company in a
particular therapeutic area
so the vivx engine is depicted in this
slide and it's there are three main
components so if you focus on the top
left hand corner we have a high
throughput GI ass system physiologically
relevant called the GI orus and we have
multiple nature Publications that show
validation and what we essentially do is
we can test the ability of thousands of
compounds per day their ability to get
across the GI tract so we use Pig GI
tract and we also have access to human
GI tract
tissue moving to the right hand side
we've now got over 130,000 data points
and so what we can do then is
interrogate the data use AI models and
in-house expertise to look at a
particular compound and predict what
type of chemicals that we can add as a
combination and a formulation to help
that compound get across the GI track
tract and then H down at the bottom what
we also have is we have our own IP on a
range of different formulations that
we've identified and it's the
combination of all three that enable us
if you look at the Orange Box we're
primarily working on peptides we can
also work on algon nucleotides and
smaller proteins but this system enables
us to take something that has to be
given to a patient needle to make it
orally bioavailable so why can we do
this and other people can't because we
have the GI Odis platform the high
throughput system we can test thousands
of compounds a day normally other
companies have to do that in Vivo
studies and that can take years to to
test this number of compounds again we
I've said we've got the rapidly growing
database which is an advantage other
companies don't have that or
organizations and also we've got our own
drug delivery IP that we can use and
other people are limited to what's out
there in the public domain
so now I wanted to share H quickly a
couple of case studies of data that
we've um produced using our platform so
here I've got four different molecules
and that we're looking at the aoi
availability of liquid H formulations in
a rat PK model the Y AIS is the oral
bioavailability and the x is the
different compounds with different
formulations so on the left hand side if
we look at the vancom an antibiotic and
normally it has got a really low oral
bioavailability we use a benchmark
formulation that everyone can use out
there and it's called sodium caprate and
what you can see here is that with that
Benchmark formulation you get very low
Auto bioavailability of vancom is with
our formulation identified we can
produce a 15-fold increase one of our
partner compounds for recycl peptide
looking at the second graph you can see
that we actually increased from
Benchmark and with our formulation we've
got a fourfold increase for the second
partner compound we've actually had a
40-fold increase and then I included the
semaglutide data here because I'm sure
everyone in the room knows about glp1
Agonist is reading all the information
out there at the moment and what we
managed to do is taking novan nordis
semaglutide if we add a benchmark
formulation the C10 versus what we have
in house with um our vivx formulation
we've got a 10-fold increase in oral
bioavailability so I'm sure that the
data that I'm showing to you just now
has convinced you that our vivx engine
does work and so the ask today is we
have some Partnerships already
established we've already got seven
Partnerships and the Partnerships can be
either a formulation partnership whereby
a partner comes to us and says I've got
this really interesting compound it
shows efficacy but it has to be given as
IV at the moment can you work with us to
give us an oral
and um today this year in 2024 we've got
multiple um Partnerships only some of
them are in the public domain we
announced earlier this year that we had
a partnership with est stellis for such
a program and last week a press release
out that we're working with ailum a
company on the west coast developing um
immune related disease molecules and
then the second type of Technology uh
sorry partnership we look for is a
strategic technology partnership so what
we can do is if a comp has a particular
type of molecule so for example last
week again a press release out about
orbis medicines who are funded by Novo
seeds they have um cyclic peptides and
they want to work with us so that we can
help them develop or bioavailable and AI
proteins is an another company in this
area a a Boston based company who have
many proteins which are Sur antibodies
so we're also working with them so I'm
interested if anyone in the rooms got
any H potential projects whether it's
formulation or strategic technology I'd
be happy to speak to you and why should
you partner with us because we have a
very experienced team spearheaded by
myself uh a solid board of directors and
Global experts as scientific advisors so
again apologies for the technical
difficulty um hopefully um you
understand what we're doing and if
anyone wants to speak to me at lunch
break or reach out to me after after I'd
be happy to discuss with you
[Applause]