good morning everyone uh welcome to Nano
exploration webinar this is our first
webinar of this year and uh today it's
my great pleasure to host uh Dr Zack
hwen uh from our group to talk about
present his research and uh Zach uh um
joined our group in 200 uh uh
2023 and uh um he received his PhD uh in
2019 uh from uh North Eastern University
and um he also did a post
do at a uh nebal research lab before he
uh comes here and it is such a wonderful
pleasure to work with Zach uh he uh is
so uh uh energetic and uh motivated and
his uh enthusiasm is so contagious and
uh he's such a a great leader and man
Mentor uh in the group and also connect
us with a lot of collaborators uh to ciz
our materials I'm so thankful to work
with deck and um yeah I hope you enjoy
uh his talk today and uh before we uh
start a z seminar uh I would like to
mention some uh um housekeeping uh uh
things uh in uh if you have a question
during the seminar uh please uh you can
write it in the chat or uh you can wait
until um uh after the seminar the Q&A
time uh you can read your virtual hand
and we can uh ask the question there um
I think with that I will uh give the
time to
Zach thank you
Zach awesome um Okay cool so I guess
people can see me um hopefully see the
research so thank you Jing for the
introduction that's very kind and thank
you so much MIT
for giving me the opportunity to present
the work so this work it is a
conglomeration it's really a combination
of many bushels of people coming
together each solving a unique and
complex challenge to make it possible so
this is um extraordinary
interdisciplinary I don't know how it
would have come together without the
help of so many people um so 2D
materials let's Dive Right In um 2D
materials they are sort of surprising
and they continue to surprise actually
for decades for decades people predicted
2D materials could not exist in the Free
State they would need a special
environment but it surprised everyone in
2004 when they started to come on the
scene and they continue to surprise in
part because I believe once you stack
them so one 2D material stacked on
another that they um will then form new
properties and this formation happens
because where the 2D materials overlap
their crystals have an effective
multiplication and they form this Moray
pattern you can see this Moray pattern
this Moray pattern is a new crystal
lattice and as we twist the materials
does it
um um oh is it working or I don't see
the slides
moving um oh oh sorry I was uh there we
go perfect now we got it but as you as
it twists um you can see new Moray
patterns form and so new lates and this
is um you know how can a lattice make
such a difference well think of diamond
versus graphite both are chemically
identical both only have carbon yet they
have different lates and they have
dramatically different properties and
the same thing sort of happens with the
2D materials when we stack them when we
twist them we can sus out very
surprising
properties um so as a quick so I can
prime my audience um stacking involves
bringing a stamp to the surface and then
when it's released it can pick a
material up and then you can stack the
materials one on each other Okay cool so
think that in your mind so now going on
I'm going to give a quick background of
some of my favorite uh works that show
really the impact of this field so the
first one this is a classic right this
is a classic magic angle graphing back
in 2018 it bursts on the scene and
everyone was excited it blew the world
away actually you can still find the aps
American physical Society talk on
YouTube by Professor Yar herero and um
it's like a standing room only packed
room and um they display other places in
the conference room but it's sort of
simple you know they took two graphine
sheets I mean it wasn't simple at the
time and it's still not simple but in uh
conceptually it's two graphine sheets
Twisted to a magic angle roughly you
know 1.1 and you then can get
superconducting activity and you can
even gate it so change your carrier
density and go from M insulator back to
superconductor and this is a stunning
result right so you can stack these 2D
materials and now you can get super
conductivity out all right let's talk
about the next one let me start my timer
Jing I'm just starting my timer so let
me know if I go over um and so um yeah
2D magnetics people also weren't sure if
a magnet could exist within 2D materials
but they did find one it's chromium I3
and it monolayer it's pherom magnetic
then if you have by layer pristine so
the stacking order is perfect I believe
then you get antier magn but if you
twist those two layers you get do
domains of pherom magnetic and domains
of antiferromagnetic so we can see as we
stack materials we can get not just
different super connectivity but we can
also get um unique uh magnet magnetic
behavior all right let's move on um
bisco Twisted bisco so this work is done
by Dr Frank Xiao he's at MIT but now but
uh was previously at Harvard and
Professor Philip Kim's group and they
took bisco which is a well-known uh
cprit um superconductor and they twist
it to different angles zero 31 degrees
you know nearly 45 degrees and they
found out at 45 degrees they got this
like really stunning result they also
found they could make a jome diode
without a magnetic field pretty pretty
stunning and they got these fractional
Shapiro steps and so this seemingly well
understood material simply Twisted
produced a very unexpected or a pretty
amazing result um okay now we're going
to move on sliding ferel electric so
these are quick updates on the amazing
stuff that the stacking can do and it's
all sort of in the recent history um
sliding Fair electrics you can take
certain two-dimensional materials and
you stack them in the AA configuration
and nothing really happens but if you go
to the ab stack configuration the ba you
can get electric fields that form within
the material depending on the direction
and and what's neat about this is now
let's stack it let's put graphine with
two hbn sheets and now we have an hbn as
an insulator now we can gate it so we're
going to apply voltage we have electric
field going through here and as you
apply an electric field you switch
between ba and ab and very very cleverly
this graphing right here acts as a
sensor so we're going to look at some
data right here and you can see the
graphing resistance and you can see two
states two very distinct States you can
almost write one as the onate
you know or off State so zero and one
and they actually then showed it has
some uh major implications for advanced
Computing I think it was um insanely
fast switching speeds like nanc uh you
know equipment limitations that allow
him to go to check even faster and they
also um like 10 to the 11 or something
like that um uh switching cycles and it
still had some pretty good performance
um so I encourage everyone to read that
paper it's pretty recent but it's a a
stunning finding and very application
for industry friendly um okay so we just
talked about super connectivity then we
talked about magnetism a Jose diode
without magic field and then sliding fer
electrics um the next stuff so all the
previous stuff was stacked um in this
case just so my previous research from
Naval research laboratory but I grew
bismo selenide on top of different
transition metal dialon aide monolayers
so TMD monolayers and bisma selenide is
known for being a topological insulator
and it has these spin protected States
so it uh you know thinks spintronics and
advanced and very very low power
Computing and then the tmds they have a
strong light matter interaction among
many other properties and so the idea is
can you couple them together and we we
found sort of like two um two exciting
results so this one this result here is
a bound Exon phonon quasi particle um
which are rare quasi particles but it's
Unique is it's across the inter layer
region and then on the other side uh
this work was done at nor Eastern when I
was a graduate student but we found uh
some indications of a possible
electronic purely electronic lattice at
the interface and I believe other 2D
materials have also found some
indications um so it shows as you
combine the materials in this case
growing them we can get some unexpected
results um okay finally um so uh I
combined an oxygen transport membrane on
top of 2D materials so oxygen transport
membranes they're very simple they
here's a membrane you have a mixed gas
on one side and it only allows oxygen to
pass through so the oxygen molecule will
break up at the surface pass through as
atoms and then recombine on the other
side and this allows you to make fuel
cells so think clean energy think
hydrogen economy a lot of promise right
there but in this case we combined it on
2D materials and what we can do is we
can stuff oxygen into this interlayer
region
and within the actual oxygen transport
membrane and we can intercalate it and
also deintercalate and through this
process we can modify the 2D materials
properties so I did it once again with
these transition metal like calcog these
tmds which have a strong light matter
interaction and I could modify the
photoluminescence with high Precision
this using a laser and we can do it with
high spatial precis too so I tried to
write NRL so go Navy NRL right there um
and how high can we make the Precision
so each data point you see in this curve
and there are hundreds um is actually
one whole Spectra we extracted it using
fitting so the air bars are pretty low
so this is the Bal inessence intensity
going up in air in oxygen and then it's
going back down in vacuum as we de
intercalate and it's going back up in
air and you can see we can go up and
down um by intercalating and de
intercalating and we can do it with
really high Precision so this shows that
we have um if you combine oxygen
transport membranes we grew it in this
case but you could stack them um you can
then really modify with high Precision
your 2D materials so okay so we have
shown I believe some pretty cool stuff
right here you know we have some super
connectivity magnetism um ajose some
diode and some fer electrics as well as
Exon phoneon bound State a pure possible
pure charge 2D Crystal and also this
precision tunability and so stacking is
pretty cool but there's some issues here
you see these amazing results over here
were done uh using exfoliate primary
exfoliate materials which is not super
duper industry friendly they're not like
uh they're not crazy about it and then
um in this case I grew bisma saline top
and that was labor intensive labor time
intensive so industry likes it but again
from a research perspective it's labor
and time intensive and it doesn't work
for every material maybe I can grow on
the tmds but can I grow on graphine can
I grow on hexagonal Boron nitrite or a
random one someone would like to try out
so this begs the question can we go
beyond exfoliate can we make these
results with non-exfoliated materials
and can we stack nearly any material
well let me tell you about a hero of
mine Professor Andrew manx who did have
this dream and did try to go beyond and
they made this very novel polymer stamp
design then they built this exciting
machine right here it's all in vacuum
has a nice turbo pump and it's all
automated and they were able to pick up
and stack Mo cvd materials and what's
excited about that isvd metal oxide
chemical vapor deposition is very
industry-friendly so here you have tsmc
saying well that's cool and then they
also stacked from The Grow substrate so
no prior treatment needed that's again
tsmc is saying well that's cool and he
also showed it can run very fast so uh
30 layers per hour which is insane
compared to many exfoliated efforts and
stacked um 80 layers uh pretty rapidly
which is also an insane number of um
layers to stack right all
monolayer or you know near two but I
think monolayer and um and so what about
the results well this Atomic
reconstruction of the tmds I believe is
understated result is incredible so you
have all these extra spots here so this
is a defraction pattern electrons are
diffracting off but you have all these
like tiny little spots and those are
because the electrons are diffracting
off of the atoms moving so his interface
cleanliness and quality was so good that
the atoms readjust themselves to form
these more stable Moray patterns and
then the electrons defract over those
new moay
patterns um same wise the Precision of
the setup was impressive as well and you
can see through these um STM images I
guess but cross-sectional that it's a
very clean interface so 30 layers per
hour uh 80 layers very clean um again
our hero and so we said can we do this
as well but can we do it also for more
materials um so this is sort of where
the top comes in we have our setup right
here um there's the chamber we have our
camera we have a pressure gauge we do
things a little different we put in
argon atmosphere and we don't use a
turbo pump we use a roughing pump so we
only go to like 70 milor um but we
hopefully the Argon atmosphere gives a
level of cleanliness um we also have two
heaters a stamp heater and a stage
heater so both sides um and let's see
what we can oh I guess I can tell you a
little bit more at the machines yeah so
stamp pater is up here um and everything
is for the most part like homebuilt uh
wouldn't have been possible without all
the labmates in my team providing ideas
along the way I could point to any
little part of the machine and say this
person help with this this person's idea
was this um so very appreciative and
even small conversations in the hallway
where someone said oh you could try
heating it and that was the thing that
made it work you know it wouldn't have
worked otherwise um and so we one thing
we do is we repeated Professor mx's uh
stamp design um we don't have four
layers we don't have three but we're
working on getting a fourth layer there
and um we don't have quite the same uh
you know Precision some other stuff but
we are able to stack uh more material so
we're happy with the progress in that
area but we're working on making a
cleaner interface um cool cool so this
is the machine we have let's see what it
can do oh actually before we tell you
about the machine let me tell you about
these Shipmates that I work with this
incredible group um so this group I work
with they grow an absolutely insane
number of materials in the group so um
the group that Jing leads so we have a
single Crystal graphine um it's grown on
these like single Crystal copper foils
um and so um so the graphine is single
Crystal for these giant domains um we
also make nanoporous graphine which is
very exciting for filtering um very
exciting papers published maybe I think
about a year ago um here are all the
various tmds that are grown within the
group um we hexagonal boron nitride we
grow monolayer and very thin but we also
grow thicker 3 to 20 nmet again this is
all for very large area growth carbon
nanot tubes oh Janice material this is
one of my uh my my fades in the group so
we can take these tmds and convert this
some Janis so you make the top layer a
different calogen atom and that creates
an intrinsic dipole and these are um
they have a lot of Promise they have a
lot of Promise um so cool cool so we
grow all these interesting materials and
how is the group so productive well one
of the group members uh Dr Juna Wong um
brilliant researcher he actually made
some software and connected it some
hardware and things are automating the
lab so you can see here the fans are
starting up and that's how the furnaces
are cooled but the lids also open
themselves and close themselves and the
gas flow rates are also um automated so
because the whole process is automated I
believe has led to a significant
increase in productivity and efficiency
um also the growths are in my opinion
more repeatable so if I were to start a
lab I'm going to use lab o that's what I
say
um and so cool cool okay so we have all
these different materials uh which
materials have we stacked so up until
now I've been able to stack single
Crystal graphine mc2 mos2 wc2 WS2 naob
diselenide actually technically I guess
it was oxidized at the time um but it
used to be nide hexagonal Bor nitri
different layers um mos2 from the MOs
cvd front mos2 and a Janice variation of
mos2
mon fery networks and exfoliate
materials so so far even though we need
to improve our cleanliness we need to
improve our stamps and improve our
Precision we are able to pick up these
materials and we're hoping to iron out
some of the cleanliness and other things
and start uh churning out results and
churning out headro structures and
hopefully collaborate with people who
can do some of the
characterization um let me quickly show
you guys um stamping what it looks like
from the camera viewpoint and it will
make some of the images more clear later
um or the explanations so here's the
stamp this round thing we're looking
through the stamps so the stamps are
translucent made out of translucent
polymers and here's some nice gold
that's been deposited on an si2 surface
and then I I treated it um to get it to
release a little bit but the gold was
generously given by Peter S I can't
pronounce the last names but he's in
freser Far group great person encourage
you to reach out to him and um so here's
a stamp before it makes a contact with
the surface then it makes contact and
you can see um that there's a color
change it's due to the thin film effect
so we in contact the the polymer makes a
color change and then I picked it up and
you can see the gold picked up from the
surface and so that's how the stamping
process works we align things we make
contact and we pick up and we see if it
picked up okay cool cool so I showed you
guys earlier we have this machine it can
pick up the 2D materials here's a stamp
it's cut into a square by hand but it
only makes contact where these pillars
are that are fabricated using a mold and
I'll explain it all
later um and then let me show you so
this is real time this movie so here
we're going to be picking up different
graphing sheets um and um you'll see it
goes into contact so now it's in contact
right there so it will only pick up
graphine right there now we just lifted
up the graphine shifting location and
now we're going to go back down and pick
up a second layer and so this is all
done real time and this is the speed at
which we can pick up materials um this
was a pretty clean pick up but it could
have been better but if you wait a
little bit longer maybe give it 30
seconds or a minute or two minutes it
can it will become what appears to be a
nearly perfect pickup if not perfect um
cool cool and this is where I've tried
to do some Automation and it worked out
good but it could be better and so here
we're going to make contact with the
surface and I've automated it by by
simply telling the motors to go certain
distances down and up this is in
contrast to Professor mx's research
where there was some Optical detection
to see when the color change would
happen and then that's when the motor
would know when to stop and um so that's
what we would like we would like to go
where Professor manx did in um having uh
an optical detection it will improve the
result we believe but we've gotten
partial automation so far cool cool
um so let's show you a quick snapshot of
some of the results so you can see each
of the circles have been uh picked up
and so was 10 layers of graphine picked
up in two and a half minutes this
particular graphine um is grown on a
single Crystal copper foil and the
grains are pretty huge so at least
portions of it I'm sure were uh lined up
or Twisted to the desired twist angle so
hopefully we can repeat some of these
incredible Twisted graphing results um
but use cvd materials and more Stacks um
the next one is I stacked a multi-layer
hbn that we grew from uh Dr kunan CH and
also some monolayer WS2 and some
graphine and this was just to sort of
see how good the interface would look
and test it out um and you can see the
pl is quenched as predicted likely due
to charge transfer into the graphine and
we see all the various Ramen signals
from uh our WS2 our graphine and our HP
end so cool so this is just two quick
snapshots um but I do want to show you
um a more exciting one that we recently
got um so
beforehand so we had to cut our 2D
material into different shapes so we use
this scratch method right here and we
wanted to cut into shapes so we could
have electrodes be more rectangles and
then we could have squares be where the
device would be and stuff like that and
we're trying to reduce the amount of
polymer um um in the process I guess for
starters and then two we noticed that
there was gluing from previous
experience when a polymer was used so
we're trying to prevent this gluing so
we could pick it up from the
substrates um so we have noticed some
issues with this tactic and recently
it's not the uh uh save all but it has
worked so far for making some devices um
and so I'm going to show you guys an
mos2 and Janice hetero structure that we
made so to make a and Junction and so
here's a diagram of our stamp and the
stamp will move to the desired location
we'll go down and we'll pick up and so
here's our first pickup and we've just
picked up a strip of MVD mos2 now our
stamp will move to the Janice side I'm
going to overlap it very carefully and I
will pick up the Janice that's the
second pickup right over here you can
see and now we're going to do a third
pickup and so you can see how you can
quickly move between the materials and
deterministically choose where you want
to place your 2D material on the stamp
and then pick everything up and then
drop things off later so let's see how
things worked out so here's step one
here's our mos2 um I'm looking at the
strip this is what I want to pick up I
made contact I picked it up and I don't
know if you can see it but there's a
rectangle here so now I know I picked it
up unfortunately my stamp broke so we
still need to make our stamps more
reliable um but that's the next step um
so we picked up our
mos2 um and now I'm going to go over the
Janice and this is me looking over the
Janice me aligning everything and then I
made contact and I was able to pick it
up and in the end I was able to stack
three stacks of mos2 three stacks of
umvd Mo Janice moss and to the best of
my knowledge picking up Janice materials
is very very challenging and I don't
think very many groups have done this um
we might be we might be the first and so
um so this an exciting heterostructure
we made and I'm working with uh some
students um Morgan from Professor
boros's group who's going to be testing
some of the PN Junction behavior and I'm
hoping to repeat this and make it
cleaner um but nonetheless we're
exciting as a first try and it worked
out pretty quickly um one thing I'll
note the Janice materials they have this
intrinsic di pole and there's a symmetry
breaking so the top layer has been
changed and this symmetry breaking has
suggested some uh really nice properties
some incredible properties so we're
hoping to also do this with single
crystals and try them at Different Twist
angles try Optics and devices and
gating um okay cool cool so that's where
we are from stacking we can pick the
materials up but the interface isn't as
clean as we would like but at least we
can pick them up um we can pick up a
whole variety of materials and so now
we're looking to characterize um in the
meantime I'm doing I'm also working on
some stamp engineering not just to
improve the stamps which I believe will
decrease the amount of polymer out
gassing and improve the interface but
also because we can choose smaller
pickup areas and I believe it's um it
can reduce the number of wrinkles
probably in the final structure so I'm
going to give you a quick overview how
the stamp is created we have this mold
um and it's made using su8 and then we
pour pedms inside um and then you can
pull the pdms out and you can
functionalize the surface and you can
spin coat a polymer on top and you bake
it and you repeat it for as many layers
as you want and the top layer is going
to be your active layer that's the
sticky layer that's the one that you
want so pick the different things up and
so what we can do is by changing the
functionalization by changing the
polymer spin coat speed and changing the
um ratio of solvent in the polymer we
can uh make the active area smaller or
larger and you can see it by the
rainbows here so here we have a circle
of an inner circle and sort of these
like outer rainbows so two rainbows
double rainbow and so this inner rainbow
outer rainbow and the inner rainbow is
where the active area is and you can see
from graph it only picked up where the
graphing was and this mistake down here
um so here's a bad stamp there was a
crack that formed and when I spin coded
my final polymer layer on top it Formed
these two bubbles but it was a blessing
in disguise because when we picked it up
we only could pick up where the active
layer was and that sort of Hit Upon This
idea that we could um engineer the stamp
um so um this is the team and they are
absolute rock stars I'm going to find a
Growers problem solvers and labmates
east of the Mississippi probably more um
and so we're going to work on cleaning
up the interface making a lot of
heterostructures folks are helping us
characterize them we can see how far we
can push it I don't know if it's going
to replace exfoliated definitely not in
the short term but hopefully it moves
the um the community further along and
makes it more industry friendly um and I
think I'm looking at the time I guess
like that probably seems good we have
some time for questions um yeah any
questions guess I go to quick yeah thank
you thank you very much Z we have
learned so much during the past year
through de effort now uh it's question
and answers time uh you can put your
questions in the chat or uh raise your
hand um vir your hand so the uh now
there is a question uh um yeah maybe let
me read it hi Zach thanks for the great
talk how big is the active area of the
stamp and why did you pick the
polymers oh that's
St such a such a good question such a
good question um so the um maybe I can
show it best with this slide so um okay
so for the active
area um okay so
you okay so we have this mold and the
mold will determine how big our p uh
pdms pillar is going to be and that's
going to be sort of our Max size but we
want to keep making the active area
smaller so we want to make our pillars
constantly smaller in diameter however
you know as you can imagine the smaller
you make these molds and then you're
asking this gooey polymer to now fill
the mold and eventually you have to pull
it out you literally pull out the pdms
um and this Um this can tear the pillars
If the ratio is incorrect you know um
height to width and the natural thing is
well why don't you just make the pillars
smaller well the smaller you make it the
more it will crash into the surface so
you put your whole pdms thing on your
glass slide and then it only makes
contact where the pillar is but if this
pillar is not tall enough then you might
touch at the edges if you're not 100%
flat which is hard to do so there's this
tradeoff where it's challenging to make
the um Kil too skinny um but I think
we've gotten it down to 80 microns um
but we do as large as 2 millimet and
we're trying to you know depending on
the application maybe someone wants
large area transfers and they want many
devices in one versus very targeted
where 80 microns might be the diameter
here um also I think the larger the
pillar is the more uh reliable the
pickup can be especially in the center
region so at the edges it sort of can
break down and stuff like that and so so
I guess to answer your question 80
microns is so far the skinniest we've
tried but I believe we get it a little
bit skinnier however I don't think we
get it much based on gut intuition based
on the size of the molds which is why I
believe the active area uh engineering
is um promising because maybe we could
engineer something so the drop of active
area is only five or 10 microns and then
we're being uh yeah then we can really
Target things um okay and then the type
of polymers we chose um let's see where
do I have my Polymer slides not here so
actually maybe I should go to Ander manx
slide well let's do H okay actually
let's go to Ander manx slide it's better
um oops sorry
right um here okay so pdms because it
sticks to glass you can spin things on
ad manics has a support layer um we use
his um L lift off resist 10 I believe
and that was sort of stabilize the stamp
smart idea um I I think it also allows
better spin coating um he also has a
release layer where the polymer breaks
down when heated um and then there's
adhesion layer the adhesion layer is the
really important one so uses a polymer
called pbzma feel free to email I can
give you the exact uh stuff but it um
it's just known for being sort of a
sticky polymer and there's like some um
arguments that can be made of why it's a
good one to pick um but I'm following
Professor mx's research in this case but
pbzma is a good choice and it's spin
coats like you could try using
polycarbonate Bisal a PC which is what
almost every um group uses for uh
exfoliated however it doesn't spin coat
it only dissolves in Chlor form it's too
volatile uh whereas the pbzma devolves
in um anyo and so it can spin code so
spin coding which I pointed out one of
the later stuff is the uh trick to doing
the engineering of the stamps um this
spin coding so you need something that
spin codes thank you for the question
very good
question yeah thank you very much uh and
then the next question is how do you let
go of the monol layer sheet from the
stamp is it that uh when the monol layer
is brought close to the substrate it
bonds more strongly to that as compared
to the
step uh okay really good question um so
I would like to make a stamp similar to
Presser manic is where we have this
release layer but um I have't another
time to sort of look into that we've
been doing things in pil however we have
this uh interim solution which has
worked out actually pretty good we
hydroxate the sio2 so uh shout out to my
peeps over in Professor n's group who
really gave me the idea and helped me
along with it but if you
hydroxate um the surface you make the
sio2 very sticky and then the 2D
material just wants to leave and it sort
of pulls off the polymer and then you
rinse the polymer very quickly and it it
seems to produce a clean surface um but
we have to look into that more um so
yeah so I'm sort of trying to engineer
different surfaces so I drop off
currently by functionalizing the S2 and
making it very sticky and then it pulls
off um and that's reliable but I don't
have to do that but that's a very very
reliable
method oh um yeah thank you thank you
very much and the next question is uh uh
from Professor Pao Herrero Herrero thank
you for the nice talk Zach Have You
cized by AFM your twisty structures how
uniform is the twist
angle oh such a great it's an honor
Professor um to have you ask me a
question I remember seeing you down the
hallway I first came to MIT and I only
recognized you from your talks online so
you felt like a rock star I was like too
shy to even say anything but um anyways
um that's a very good question negative
we have not but it's like on the work
list that we're trying to do and I know
your group is actually um in many ways
leading uh that uh you know the efforts
to how to characterize these Mor
patterns and so we're actually trying to
follow in your group's lead and I've
been reaching out casually to get advice
on different stuff but it's we
definitely want to make a stack and
start the characterization um to see how
even things are thank you good
question yeah thank you very much and
the next one is uh thank you so much
Zach for the Fantastic talk I uh sorry
I'm not reading everyone's names I'm
sorry I might have missed it during your
talk but how did you exactly align the m
to and jice had her structures was it
act
optically yeah affirmative everything is
is just optically um and so yeah I I
literally just sort of like looked uh
over top how it how it looks um
affirmative I will say um so shout out
to Eden in our group who has made
software that can do twist angle
detection so it's all sort of um using
image recognition to sort of see how
we've much we've Twisted the substrate
and that does allow us to cut down on
costs because we don't have to get um a
calibrated um I guess rotational stage
um but with that in mind um we're hoping
in the future to maybe build upon some
of that image detection to have it be
done more Precision um but yeah good
question only optically right now and by
yeah and then the next one is hey Zach
thanks for the talk how is the sticking
working for such a variety of materials
is it always flat means uh parallel to
the stamp or is there some
tilt um the only tilt has been
accidental um because my problem for a
long time was I would crash the sides
and so I've been trying to make things
as like uh non- tilty as possible and
for those who don't know that's in
contrast to exfoliate materials where
they do put an intentional tilt and the
idea is to sort of squeeze out and push
out junk and I believe that's one reason
exfol material still can produce
possibly a better interface in my
opinion um so no I'm coming down 100% um
at zero degree but the reason it's
sticking is so I've actually left out
many details um just because of limited
talk time and and other stuff and
shiming shout out to shiming and our
group who's helped me with this but we
uh we sort of like detach the 2D
materials like they don't want to be on
the S2 we put them on and so that allows
us to sort of pick them up um very
easily and that's how we can that's how
we have such high success rates we're
we're like making it so they don't want
to be on the
substrate thank you very much and the
next one uh Zach you are an ex great
expert on this what wise would you gave
someone building their own homebuild
setup in their lab for material transfer
or otherwise how do you balance cost
savings with time and
capabilities oh that is also such a good
question that's such a good question so
I didn't think I could ever build this
and then I got to uh Professor Kong's
group and people just like believe in
things like no no we can do it Zach no
problem we just sit down and do it and I
was like okay I guess we'll try and I
still remember the first meeting we had
where we where people are on a
whiteboard and they're figuring out how
to build it and people are being
critical of each other's IDE but no one
took offense and it was like like a
textbook case of how to be a team and in
half an hour we had charted out a design
plan and it was awful I I didn't go that
route but that was but it was perfect as
we've like iterated on that initial
design it's like slowly moved along so I
think what I've learned from this is I
100% could not have done this by myself
maybe not even with five people right
look at the drop off how I hydroxate the
si2 you know that's Professor nar's
group helping me out um Sarah and Peter
and all the different folks there know
and I think even um in pressor mx's
group I visited Stanford so I went and
visit a bunch of groups I'm very
thankful that people shared their
knowledge and um Rita one of his
students made this like off-hand comment
and it solved our pdms problem right you
know and so um I think I just talked to
many people it's 100% teamwork um but I
will say the um stuff in so the motors
that I showed you guys earlier that
automated I guess for our growth um the
software that we use for this we also
apply to our machine so we've cut down
down we've had some tremendous cost
savings because we don't we make a lot
of things ourselves and I'm thankful for
the people in the group for teaching me
how to do that thank you it was really
good question I believe in you yeah
thank you thank you very much Zach and
uh this may have been answered but uh
maybe you can uh more speci specific
again why is your machine able to pick
up more types of material than other
designs
okay really really really good question
um okay it's it's so I could have done
the talk two ways I could have either
talked about a machine or I could have
talked about this other work we're doing
I'm calling it effective exfoliation um
but I'm gonna I probably shouldn't say
too much I think we might be a get a
patent from it and I feel like this talk
is recorded the patent lers will find me
and say no it's s but um but yeah we
have a method for effectively for
removing the uh are these ASG grown mat
Cals and we're placing them on sio2 and
they they don't want to be on sio2 in my
opinion that's how I'm looking at it and
so I think there's like different stuff
like when people spin coat PMA and then
you fish the PMA out of the water and
you put it on top of a substrate and
then you rinse away
the uh the pmma with acetone I believe
there's a gluing aspect going on
somewhere there and and I think people
figure it out like you have to fish it
out of liquid maybe some residual
liquids in between Maybe maybe a 2d
layer of water is gluing it or something
like that um but there's definitely like
an adhesion of sorts and so we we sort
of solved that problem where it's not
adhered to the uh surface as much and so
you can even see some issues with see if
I oh um yeah so for example you see how
the graphine is all broken up that's
because this transfer process which
we've approved upon it didn't work that
well so the graphine picks up from the
surface but it didn't transfer the
surface that well because the sio2
didn't want the graphine um so that's
that's the trick um that that needs to
be figured out and I can totally I'm
only only just I don't want to Rob our
group of a patent or another you know
and so I'm gonna avoid saying too much
but please stop on byy or send me an
email I can definitely be more than
happy to provide more details um but
that's that's sort of the trick you have
to it's just pre-treatment that makes it
not sticky um I I'm sorry to be so vague
about it but uh yeah um but please email
me thank you for the question that's a
really good question
thank you very much Zach uh he Zach a
great presentation is the process of
finding the 2D material from the subrate
automatic or manual ah it's only manuals
right now but it's one thing we want to
automate and so I think what I've
learned from this machine is we have
great potential in many directions to go
in so not only can we clean the
substrate but I think we can automate it
so I'm hoping it can be helpful for
fundamental science but then also
industry um so so uh but if folks are
looking to program or help out we would
love to help and so um yeah we're
working on the programming
aspects thank you and and then the next
one is what happens to the bonds around
the
circumference is is it a stamped in
vacuum could you Bast the process in a
different gases to effect the resulting
electronic Properties or symmetry
breaking at the edge of the V
she I I believe so um I I was naive I
had the wrong vacuum for a long time and
then we recently changed and made some
improvements um again under Jin sort of
guidance and we we made these
improvements and I've noticed a a big
Improvement to the stacking process so I
believe the gas that's in there does
seem to affect um the stack and how much
bonding there is and other stuff um but
I 100% haven't explored it I hopefully
we can get a publication out eventually
and then this will just be like one
stepping stone on the way very good
question yeah thank you very much and
the next one is heack super interesting
do the temperature change when the stamp
releases the 2D material compared when
picking up oh such a good question that
is such a good question okay so we found
out we effectively had to heat our stamp
to get the results to work um and so
when we didn't heat the stamp the stamp
was at room temperature and it touched
the heated stage and what do polymers do
when they're heated they expand however
the machine was fixed so the polymer had
nowhere to go and it moved and it
shifted and we have tons of movies
trying to figure out what's you know
what's going on and how we can resolve
it and um and ever since we've added
this like heated stamp um it's there
seems to be no movement and um I don't
know it's it's a I believe it's a huge
increase in performance and so um so
yeah so the heated stamp and keeping
things the same has improved from that
aspect um did I answer the question
actually also yeah I'm sorry I I just
realized that we are running out of time
uh so uh so um yeah um maybe for the
other question we we still have a few
you can send email to Zach or ask uh him
in person uh thank you everyone for for
your great questions and uh for your
interest the yeah the the next um Nano
exploration seminar will be by uh also
Zach another Zack uh Jing J from uh um
uh Department of chemical engineering at
MIT and his talk is on atmospheric water
harvesting from nanoscale
metal organic framework um yeah um I
hope uh you will enjoy um yeah thank you
very much