Uh it is my pleasure to introduce our
next speaker. Uh Daniel Jackson is a
professor of electrical engineering and
computer science here at MIT and he is
also associate director of the computer
science and AI lab or CESAL. Uh and uh
Daniel is going to talk to you about the
synergy of AI and modular design. So
let's hear it for Daniel.
Thank you so much, Jim. It's such a
pleasure to be with you all today, but I
have to start off with a bit of a
disclosure. I'm afraid I have some bad
news for you. The bad news is you come
to MIT, you know, to hear from the cool
kids. Well, I'm not one of the cool
kids. Uh I basically have spent my
entire career thinking about questions
of software design and modularity, which
I think roughly speaking, it's fair to
say have become less and less popular uh
over the years. And when this whole AI
thing happened, you know, you know, with
the emergence of chat GPT in 2022, I
have to admit that I thought thought to
myself, okay, now now this is totally a
niche market. You know, now I'm really
on my own, but never mind. We'll survive
in this world. But, you know, I've come
to think that actually LLMs might have
the opposite effect for my field. And
then it might turn out that software
design and modularity matter more than
ever before and that we might actually
see a little bit of a renaissance. And I
want to tell you a little bit of that
story. So let me start by um addressing
you know the obvious question which
you've heard about no doubt from many
other people more knowledgeable than me.
Uh how good are LLMs at coding? So on
the face of it the answer is
extraordinary right partly because of
you know the phenomenon of the dancing
dog. The fact that it can be done at all
uh makes it remarkable and we don't
always ask how well it can be done. So
here are some here are some statistics
from the last few years. Um Copilot you
know they insidiously like all these
tools track you know what their users
are doing. Um, and even back in June
2023, the Copilot estimated that their
users generated almost half of their
code uh using Copilot. And I'm sure it's
much more now. And as you know, uh, and
Armando mentioned some of these, there
have been a bunch of benchmarks. One of
the most popular benchmarks has been
MBPP. Um, and it seems that these are
really great. You know, they're
basically solving some very high
proportion of problems that are
programming problems that are presented
to them. What people don't focus on is
that by and large almost all these
benchmark examples work on single
functions and they're mostly tiny often
50 lines of code or less. And if you ask
what about building whole apps, you get
a very different story. And you know,
here's the typical kind of response
you'll get, you know, to someone who
asks, you know, on a on an online forum,
can you build a whole app with with with
GPT? And this person says, if you ask
GPT to write whole apps for you, it
can't get there. But if you architect
the app in your head, you can ask it to
build out one function at a time pretty
effectively. And in fact uh Thomas
Donkey who's the CEO of GitHub has
actually sort actually back then sort of
formulated this as the future of
programming that basically the skills of
developer will be to push to the point
at which you've reduce things to small
enough pieces that you can actually
implement it in code uh using an LLM. Um
but we could ask a different question
and the different question is if we move
away from these toy examples that are
typically the subject of the benchmarks.
What if we look at more real examples
and we have some optimism that maybe
building real code bases can still be
done small fragments at a time. So what
about small code fragments in a more
realistic context? Well, there's a very
nice benchmark called SWEBench
um which um which came I believe out of
an acade academic group and has been
adopted by OpenAI. And what they
basically did was they took about 2,300
GitHub issues from some popular repos
and they posed the question, if we
simply present these issues to an
LLM, how many of these issues can get
resolved? And they've been tracking this
number. Obviously, a very interesting
question. Um, and this seems to produce
some incredibly impressive and
encouraging results. Um, by their
measure, uh, the best LLMs are now
resolving about 65% of issues. However,
um maybe the story isn't quite so
simple. There was a study done at York
University um earlier this year and they
looked very carefully at these patches
and they found out the following. First
of all,
33% of these patches that were deemed to
have been succeeded were actually
patches in which the issue included
proposed code that the person filing the
issue had included. So all that was
necessary was to actually cut and paste
the code from the
issue. Secondly, about a third of these
patches that were deemed correct
actually turned out to be wrong. They
were deemed correct because of course we
have to have means of you know checking
correctness. So they ran them against
the test cases but as Armando mentioned
test cases are often very incomplete.
And so in fact these were wrong patches
but they were deemed correct.
Furthermore, it turns out that most of
these issues were there long before the
training cutoff for tools like GPT um
came around. And as a result, if you
take all this into account, the actual
resolution rate um for GPT4 in
particular falls to less than
1%. Uh and it's higher for some other
more recent ones, but it it doesn't, I
believe, rise above 5%. And I believe
you know they're working on this paper
and we'll review it but basically this
is not nearly as inus as exciting as one
might have thought. So in short L&M
based coding assistants often suggest
code that doesn't work and worse if you
accept one of the proposals it will
often break functions that already work
in attempting to add a new function. So
what's modularity got to do with this?
So I would say that the obvious solution
to this problem is to have properly
modular software development. What does
that mean? Well, it means that you build
your software one solid module at a time
like this and then you put these
together. Okay? And and and the idea of
course is that as you build these
modules, the other modules stay the
same, preserving the good features and
the solidity that those modules brought.
So what does modularity actually mean?
Well, I would claim that it means
actually two slightly different things.
So the first is what you might call
coherence.
And what that means is that a single
module doesn't conflate unrelated
functions. So to sort of illustrate this
graphically, this might be a coherent
modularization in which we have a yellow
module containing all the yellow
function and a green module containing
the green function. And this is an
incoherent module because it mixes green
function and yellow function
together. Another requirement of
modularity is independence.
What independence means is that one
module by and large doesn't rely on
another. So this would be a case of
independence because you can see that
the green and yellow modules work by
themselves. But this is a case of
dependence because there's this rat's
nest of relationships between the
modules and the green module won't work
without the yellow module, the yellow
module without the green module and so
on. Well, why does this matter? Well,
coherence matters because if you have an
incoherent uh modularization, then you
end up with needless complexity because
you haven't teased out the different
functions, right? And so you've
basically conflated the functions and
their purposes. You're not really sure
what you're doing. Everything's sort of
messed up together. What about
dependence violations? Well, there you
have a classic failure of localization.
And it means that you can't make a
change in one module without that change
uh propagating to other modules. Um and
it means that you can't reason uh one
module at a time. Now the interesting
thing is we we've known all this. This
is not new. You know this is the point
at which you're probably thinking snore
I've heard all this before. And of
course we've been saying this for I
don't know 50 75 years maybe even
longer. But we tolerated this in
software development right? Um and I
think the reason we tolerated it was
first of all because humans are
incredibly resilient. We're able to deal
with all the complexity this produces.
But it was often the case that we
tolerated it because we thought that the
costs that these these flaws implied um
outweighed the difficulty of actually
achieving modularity and we coined fancy
terms for this like technical debt uh
and implied this was a good thing
basically to build crappy systems. Um
but of course people realize that
there's a very heavy price for that. So
let me give you an example. I want to I
want to talk concretely about a very
simple um a very simple application and
some of the modularity issues in there.
So this is hacker news. How is it that
anybody's able to use hacker news
without reading the manual? Well, of
course it's because like any other
social media app, it has all the
familiar ingredients. So it has posts,
it has comments, it has sessions, um it
has upvoting favorites, and if you click
on an user's name, you'll see there's
some number of comma points. How do they
even dare to use the word karma, right?
How's anyone supposed to understand
that? Well, the answer is it's a
familiar notion from other social media
apps basically uh points that are acred
uh you know as rewards for good behavior
to essentially allow the the
well-behaving users uh to do more
powerful things. So you might say, well,
here's all this massive functionality.
What's new here? Of course, what's new
here is that although it's fun
functionality is very familiar, how it's
put together is not necessarily
familiar. And this goes by the name of
what Margaret Bowden called
combinational creativity. Familiar
elements combined in new ways. So in the
case of hacken news, it's things like
this that a post is actually a weird
thing. It either just has a title uh and
a link or it's a question. It's not a
post like in, you know, Facebook or
Instagram. You can't comment on a post
after two weeks. You can't edit
something you've written after 2 hours.
You can't downvote a comment until your
own post has been upvoted. That's the
karma system. and so on. So what happens
is these familiar functions are made
application specific um by these
wrinkles that actually turn out to be
the very essence of hacken news that
basically make hackenuse what it is. So
let's imagine let's we we're all going
back to school. We're in programming 101
and we've had some enthusiastic lectures
about object-oriented programming and
now we're going to code this as our
first object-oriented program, right? So
how do we do it? So here's what we do.
We say well obviously the first thing is
we have users okay so users have
usernames and passwords we have a method
to register a user a me um a method to
authenticate a user we have posts okay
which have an author and a body and a
constructor and now the question is
let's start adding all our features so
what about upvoting well what gets
upvoted posts so we'll add to the post
class a set of the set of users who
upvote or down two sets one for the set
of users who upvote the post one for the
set of users who downvote the post and
we'll add methods to upvote or downvote
the post. Okay, what about comma points?
Well, comma points clearly belong to
users, right? It's users who are
rewarded with karma points. Um, so we're
going to need to um uh we're going to
need to put those in somewhere. So,
we'll put them in users. So, here they
go. Um, we add to the user class the
number of comma points and we add
methods to increase a user's comma and
to check that a user has some number of
comma points. And now notice that what
we're going to have to do if we're going
to say that you need some number of
comma points to downvote a post, we're
going to need to put a condition inside
the the um downvote method that will
actually check that for a particular
user. Um okay, all pretty good. And now
commenting and we sort of carry on with
this game, right? What about comments?
Well, we let's treat comments as posts.
We can associate the the the comments um
with a particular post and we'll have an
add comment method. it'll make it very
nice to basically add the comments to a
post and very easy to collect the the
comments associated with a post and so
on. But look at where we've got. This is
the situation we're in now, right? We're
in this uh we're in this basically
rainbow coding scenario of total
incoherence in which we have classes um
that basically conflate all these
different functions. And if we list the
functions on the right hand side, user
authentication, posting, upvoting,
commenting, and karma, you'll see that
they're completely distributed through
these classes. There's no modularity
here
whatsoever. So we have incoherence in
particular, for example, that the post
class not only contains posting, but
also contains commenting, upvoting, and
karma. And the result of that is that a
class like this isn't going to be
reusable, right? Because you know if you
if you want if you wanted for example
you know posting without karma you're
out of luck right and notice also that
we have dependencies in particular that
the post class calls the user class
which is very awkward right in order to
get the number of comma points to
determine whether the down vote is
allowed and the result of that is that
these things can't be built fully
independently of one one another because
you need to know about one in order to
code the other. So there must be a
better way. So the better way I would
propose uh is a sort of new old way. New
in the sense that I'm going to propose
it more radically, but old in the sense
that it's just our old friend
modularity. What if we actually built a
structure like this in which we cleanly
separated the functions of um user
authentication, posting, karma, and
upvoting into separate modules.
in a large system. Those could be full
stack modules um with um with their own
persistence in in their own databases
and so on. And we put these together not
by allowing them to call each other
which will compromise independence, but
rather by having a kind of mediator at
the top um that um that called one uh
and used the results from one to call
another. And so in this scenario,
there's no dependencies between
concepts. Uh and I call these concepts,
I should have said, right? And uh and
here's what it would look like. Uh and I
don't need to go into the coding
details. There are many different ways
this could be coded. But notice that now
the important thing to note is that we
have uniform colors in each of the
modules. Um so this for example is the
user module. It contains some mapping
from users to their names and users to
their passwords and it only has
registration and authentication. It
doesn't have anything else. Karma uh it
contains a mapping from users to their
karma points. Right? Right? And it
allows you to increase the karma
associated with a user and to figure out
how many karma points a user has and so
on. So each of these different concepts
is entirely coherent in containing only
the functionality um of uh that's
appropriate. So the concerns essentially
there's a lot of talk about separation
of concerns and now cleanly separated.
And notice also that the coupling is now
gone. So you might say well surely the
coupling isn't gone because for example
comments have to be on posts, right?
Well, they don't have to be on posts.
Comments just have to be on something.
So in this case, that something is
represented by a type parameter T, which
essentially says there has to be some
target for a comment. But the comment
concept doesn't need to know what that
target is because it doesn't actually
deal in the functionality of that
target. And then this thing on the right
hand side, which I'm not unfortunately
going to have much time to tell you
about, is what I call a synchronization.
And a synchronization is this mediator.
And what this mediator does uh is
essentially connect these concepts
together to account for all those
application specific properties that I
said were necessary but while preserving
the independence of the concepts. So,
for example, we might have a
synchronization that says um we're going
to need some kind of concept for web
requests that when we get a web request
for a downvote of user U for item I,
then we're going to check that this user
U has, for example, 10 comma points. And
if they do, then we will execute uh the
downvote action uh of user U on uh on
item I. And notice that this um mediator
um wow um my my computer keeps dying.
This is very strange and disturbing. I
don't know what's going on here. Um but
hopefully it will it will last. Um so
the key point here is that these
synchronizations basically describe uh
these interactions between the concepts.
So what can one do with this? You've
been wondering what does this have to do
with LLMs? Well, the idea of course is
in an LLM what you do is you give it a
prompt and you know in the case of
whatever your LLM is GPT say it
generates some code and of course what
we're going to do is we're going to make
those prompts specifications of concepts
uh and we're going to prompt entirely
separately for each of the con concepts
to generate the code for the concept and
then we're going to have some kind of
specification in in the case of a web
application it's a route but in general
it's just a synchronization between the
concepts and we're going to generate the
code that calls the concept concepts and
that of course is going to actually need
the API of the concepts. And so what
we're actually going to do is we're
going to extract that API from the
generated code. Then we're going to
generate a front end. Easier said than
done. That's a that's a a story for
another time. Uh and we're going to
produce a fully deployed app. So my
student Barish Namazov um built a
prototype tool called Codeless to do
this. Uh and uh here are some
screenshots of it. Basically, you give a
a very uh vague and minimal description.
And here's what he happened to write uh
for for karma. He said each karma should
have user generic and points number
actions should be this and that. Um and
uh and it goes ahead. This is you know
note this is application independent.
That's the important thing and pretty
brief. Uh it generates some code. That
code has all the mess in it you'd
expect, you know, with database schemas
and all the coding details that uh that
that a you know that an end user
programmer doesn't want to write. And
then what it does is it generates an API
specification from that code. That API
specification is typically much much
more detailed than the prompt, right?
Because of course what we're relying on
here is that the LLM knows things about
karma that the user didn't need to
specify because these are familiar
concepts. And now when we want to
actually create a synchronization or a
route, we just give the minimal
information. In this case, for example,
we're saying we're going to want to
route a post, an HTTP post for
registering that should register a user
and log them in. New users should start
with one comma point. Um, and notice
there's no explicit mention of the
concepts there or of their actions. And
from that, um, codeless actually
generates calls uh the the
synchronizations that actually use the
concept APIs uh, and uh, appropriately
selects actions from them. Uh and from
that um we can produce basically a clone
of the behavior of hacken news. Um this
looks much more impressive. Um then you
shouldn't be fooled by this. This is of
course just stealing all the CSS. Um but
you know these visual tricks are are
compelling aren't they? So you can make
something but I can assure you it does
actually work. Uh and we can even make
blue pages. You know the hacken news has
this weird feature. It allows you to
change the color of the bar. Who knows
why anyone would care about that but we
can do that as well. Um and um it
actually turns out that there are a lot
of intricacies um in in hacker news. Um
not only things like all these features
I told you like you know karma um
flagging posts, hiding posts, nested
comments, complicated ranking rules, uh
all kinds of weird things. Even it turns
out producing the front page relies on
some quite complicated formulas about
the age of post and number of up votes
and whatever. Um and those are very
easily uh presented as prompts. Um in
total it needed only about a 100 lines
of prompt to generate this application
and there was no code editing needed. So
basically we ran it and if it didn't
work we tweaked the prompt a little bit.
Um not so good. This is only the back
end currently. Uh I have to say you know
I've been giving talks about this for a
while and they used to say well the
front end should be easy. I don't
believe anymore that that's the case. I
think if you want a front end that
tightly integrates the concepts so that
for example the upvote button is on a
post uh it's it's a little bit harder
but I think we have we have some good
ideas about how to do that. Some of the
synchronizations I have to admit are
pretty ugly. Um especially it turns out
often what happens in a back end is you
have to package structures for the front
end and that packaging um is sort of
ugly to describe. Furthermore, um the
concept synchronizations also need to be
able to query the state of the
individual concepts. Uh and at the time
we wrote this, we didn't have a good
story about basically mixing the kind of
database queries you needed and the
calls, the actions. We have a much
better uh story about that
now. So in conclusion, I want to sort of
return to the original premise. Why is
it that modularity matters not just for
software in general but for LLM code
generation in particular? So um I told
you earlier on these two reasons that
incoherence and dependence were bad. But
now in the concept of of LLM based code
generation I would argue there are new
reasons that these notions of modularity
matter a lot. So in the case of
coherence the main importance of
coherence is that if you don't have it
your modules become very application
specific right because they contain the
particular combination of features of
that application and that means that we
have novel combinations of functions and
as we all know LLMs are not good at
novelty what LLMs excel with is being
able to produce the same old stuff and
so we want to make our software problem
as much as possible the same old stuff
and then localization which was a
problem for human reasoning becomes a
huge problem for LLMs and the problem
essentially is that the context isn't
bounded right because now in order to
write one piece of code and this is why
in swbench all those patches break
everything all over the place
essentially you need to understand the
whole code base if you don't have
localization when you make a change
um and uh or the alternative of course
is that you have very detailed
interfaces specifications of every
component uh and that you know I think
that is something that's going to
happen. We're going to see a resurgence
not only of modularity but of precise
specification. Um but in general that's
too much of a burden and it will be
easier to increase the level of
decoupling than to place higher burdens
of specification uh on the programmer.
But the main thing is that you know I
would argue that we need to move from
this idea that we can tolerate all this
modularity to recognizing that
modularity is the very key to code
generation with LLMs. And so in short
this comes down to a shift of
perspective. We used to think of uh
modularity like this in which we had all
these dependent modules that were also
incoherent. And I'm arguing that what we
should move to is a scheme like this
where I've tried to sort of indicate by
these icons that each of these modules
represents some familiar piece of
functionality. So these are familiar
modules and these modules are no longer
dependent on one another. They have
control and data that flows between
them. But that control and data is
mediated by a kind of conductor that
embodies the application specific
details. these mediators that that call
the concepts and the concepts don't call
themselves. So what we're working on now
a whole bunch of exciting things uh
improving the way these synchronizations
work in particular um first of all to
make them fully declarative and order
independent to allow them to be
extremely expressive so you can um
describe all kinds of iterative
behaviors uh and all kinds of event
patterns. um it's very important that
these be written while inventing you
know a rich language here in a style
that's familiar to LLM. So my my
graduate student Egon Mang who's working
on this is currently trying to persuade
me that using a kind of data log way of
expressing this might be the right way
to go and I think that's a very exciting
option and he's actually managed to show
that with his new uh synchronization
language he's able to factor out the
presentation issues those packaging
issues I mentioned as separate
synchronizations and even to factor out
persistence which I think is very nice.
Um, it's the kind of thing that Adam,
our next speaker, has has done
throughout his career to basically
enable you to have immutable functional
descriptions of functionality and to
separate the updating of a database,
even the choice of a database, uh, to a
separate module. Um, we're looking at
using concepts to do front-end
generation. Uh, and importantly, I
didn't emphasize this a lot, but of
course, a key idea is if you have these
familiar components, right, you can
build a library of them. uh and then you
can reuse them from the library. And the
advantage of that is not only that you
don't need to generate them, but that
you can audit those components if if
necessary by hand to make sure they're
extremely high quality and don't contain
any security vulnerabilities. So then
the LLM problem becomes only essentially
either the generation of unusual
concepts or the synchronization of this
large number of existing ones.
Now in working on this notion of
concepts you know the initial motivation
was really two things actually.
Originally it was to think about finding
u better um user experience um and um
but also to achieve modularity both in
uh the design and the code. But what I'm
coming to realize is that thinking of
software in terms of concepts brings
other advantages too. One is providing a
design language for different people in
an organization to talk to each other.
Um, so one of the things that often
happens is that user experience
architects and software architects have
no language in common because the UX
people speak wireframes, you know, and
the software architects speak box and
line diagrams and there's no way for
them to have a really deep discussion
about the nature of the functionality
that they're designing together and
concepts uh allows them to do
that. Um the other thing is that
concepts give you a place for design
meaning that they give you basically a
structure in order to say these are the
design issues and even the human issues
associated with this functionality that
we need to understand. Um and so this
idea of a concept catalog is one that
I'm working with some companies on uh to
see how uh that can be used as a way to
basically uh record the design issues
and design knowledge of a company. Uh
just as a closing bit of perspective,
you know, I have a book on this uh which
uh shameless plug here uh which you're
welcome to find out about at my website.
You know, the origins of this project
were basically 10 years spent studying a
bunch of apps and trying to understand,
you know, what what was the difference
between the ones that had great UX and
bad UX and seeking a way to analyze uh
and structure the underlying function.
And what I found was that basically
everybody for the last 50 or 100 years,
50, 75 years, has been saying conceptual
models are at the heart of usability.
But nobody really knew what the concepts
were in conceptual models. Um, and with
this notion of concepts, we're able to
explain complex designs and design and
diagnose usability flaws. Oh, my machine
keeps dying. Excuse me. Please come
back. Okay.
um we're able to bring alignment uh and
strategic clarity in large scale
developments. Alignment between not only
different roles but also between
different products because it's often
very common in a large organization to
have multiple products. It's that
essentially share functionality uh and
also to provide of course and that's
been the subject of this conversation a
strong basis for LLM based code
generation. So with that I'm done and
I'd be delighted to uh take any
questions.
Thank you so much for this, Daniel. Um,
as I was listening to you, I felt like,
is this microphone helping? Yes, it is.
Okay. Um, I I felt like I was in a
parallel universe. And that is sort of
this I'm going to bring up a dreaded
word because it's so hyped up. It's
basically the the concept of intelligent
agents, which actually started I think
the first conference on agents,
multi-agent systems, was in 1997.
But but only the AI community knew about
it and now all of a sudden it's become
hyped up as something brand new and it's
become and I think the reason for that
is that um in the AI world agents were
always sort of buried under the covers
but now that they're um at the edge
because of language use um a lot of
people that have been working on Gen AI
tools have started hearing about them
and by the time I got involved in trying
to comprehend and what was happening. It
was so closely tied with Gen AI, this
whole concept, but everything that you
said in terms of modularity, in terms of
concepts being independent and and
communicating with each other is sort of
the heart of agent-based design. So, I'm
just wondering if you can connect what
you talked about with this whole idea of
multi-agent systems working with each
other. Oh, wow. Um, I don't know a lot
about multi-agent systems. Um I think
there are probably connections there. I
will say that in terms of this sort of
new you know hype about agentic
computing and so on uh I think agents
will obviously be useful but I think
that one of the things we're going to
see is that agents if you like will take
over the lower level more routine uh
code generation um um work uh and uh
infusing work with well understood
knowledge and in some sense will leave
more room for software designers to do
do the more imaginative and creative
work of of understanding what's really
needed in the application in the
specific context. Um, and so I think
we're going to see that sort of uh
bifocation of work.
Follow a global search replace of the
word agent or
module, how would that impact because I
could make the case that well-designed
modules are in workflows and data flows
effectively agents. So, I'm just
wondering, forgive the word,
ontologically, do you think in those
terms, is that an acceptable search and
replace?
Um, gosh, it's such a that's such an
interesting question. I wasn't ready for
this question. Uh, I think, you know, to
me, um, by the way, your book is
terrific. Thank you. I mean, I think
agent in a way is a much more ambitious
word. You know, agent implies autonomy
and independence, uh, and a degree of
complexity that I think uh, is not
implied by the word module. Um but I
think uh certainly to the extent that
you know we're going to want to have
agents that will work together
effectively and won't have you know
emerging behaviors that are
unanticipated and disastrous. We will
need exactly the kind of modularity
mechanisms uh that that that are
familiar to us. Yes. Yeah. If I
piggyback on that, I think microservices
is another word like uh the
microservices architecture is kind of
the modu
modularity implementation in real world
right absolutely. So just a word about
microservices obviously this this work
that I've described has been influenced
by microservices. I will say that I
think microservices has proved
disappointing in two respects. One is
that a lot of companies who have
microservices can show you a graph of
dependencies between their microservices
that is quite intimidating. That shows
that far from actually decoupling
functionality, they've ended up with an
absolutely huge um
crossenterprise um collection of
dependencies that I think are very
costly. The second thing is that
microservices got tied up with the idea
that modularity had to imply separate
deployment often with separate platforms
and separate languages uh and separate
issue databases and so on. And that
seems to me should never have been
conflated. That's a completely separable
issue. Um it's why some people talk
about you know modular monoliths and so
on but that was a mistake I think
because it put a lot of people off the
idea of modularity because of the cost
of all those separate deployments.
Yes.
Um, does that kind of coincide with the
use of domains? So, does the
synchronization represent a module in a
different domain than the lower level
modules?
Um, you mean in the sense of like domain
driven design like like when you have a
when you have a very complex system.
Yeah. You have the the small modules
that do the very low-level things. Yeah.
You have a synchronization that ties
those modules together that provides a
functionality. You can think of that
whole block now as a module. Y but it's
now in a different domain that has
larger scope. Oh, I think that I if I
understand you correctly, I think that's
right. And I think what I'm advocating
is, and this by the way is a contrast
with Eric Evans notion of domain driven
design, you know, which has this very
productive and interesting idea of
bounded context, but almost encourages
people to develop concepts that are
different for the same functionality in
different domains. And what I'm arguing
is that what you really want is to
achieve alignment. If everybody has user
authentication and everybody has billing
and everybody has notification in every
part of the company, you surely don't
want to design and implement it
differently in every single team. So
what I'm arguing is that indeed you want
to have shared concepts for those
things. Um but as you say I think in you
know in different domains those will be
realized differently and will interact
differently to due to the different
packagings and synchronizations.
Exactly. Last question. Um the universe
is used to natural language interfaces.
Let's say the short shorthand of a
chatbot. Does application of concepts
make chat interactions better?
Quart one. Part two is what fraction of
UX do you think can be properly subsumed
by that kind of a chatbot? And part
three, if we're only
generating interfaces and you know APIs
and chat interfaces, does that make the
code generation challenge easier?
Wow. Um there there are so many
interesting observations there. Um I
think that um you know people are
rightly pointing out that chat
interfaces are very limited. Um I
actually suspect that um for code
development they're pretty powerful.
Language is a very powerful thing and
we'll be able to go a long way with
that. Um I think that one of the
important things about concepts which is
which is I think perhaps related to your
question is that concepts are
fundamentally userfacing and what that
means is that when you describe the
functionality you want to be able to
describe it in the user terms and this
is a big difference from coding
assistants um you know like you know
cursor and uh copilot and so on which
require the programmer to explain the
functionality they want in terms of the
existing implementation modules. Uh I
should have emphasized that actually
that's a very important point that in
this case everything you describe um is
essentially at the domain level and this
is also going to be a feature of of
Adam's very interesting work um that
basically you don't want to put the user
the user developer as it were in the
position of having to break the
abstraction and understand low-level
implementation details. Uh and I think
that's really the crucial point that in
whatever interaction it is, it has to be
an interaction in what uh me and my
students call the vernacular. The
vernacular of the user uh and not in the
language of of the
programmer. Okay. Thank you very much.