Okay. So, this is this is our last class
before spring break. This is sort of
like the halfway mark of the of the
semester. Um, in the beginning of it,
I'm going to continue with some product
theory. Um, and uh try to get to a good
a good place with it. Um but then in the
second half I wanted to kind of check in
with everybody about some possible
directions for the second half of the
class.
Um okay so in in some product theory
last time we introduced some fundamental
tools from additive combinotaurics the
like plunka inequality and ra inequality
and so on and the the theme of today is
like practicing using those
inequalities.
So let's call this
Lica
Raa toolbox.
All right.
Um so these are all inequalities that
connect
sums and diff different combinations of
sums and differences.
So there's the ruer triangle inequality
and it says that a * b minus c is
bounded by a minus b * a minus c
or if you you can replace b and c by
negative themselves. So you could say
this
okay's
inequality
says that um
if
a + b is at most k * a
Then
B added to it to itself M * minus B
added to itself N times is bounded by K
to the M + N.
And the main lema inside the proof of
Plunicus inequality is also useful.
that says um that there exists so that
we have the same. If if
then there exists a subset in A which
sort of has the subset that has the
additive structure that causes this to
happen.
So that for any set C,
X + C + B,
this over X + C is also at most.
Okay, cool. So one of our goals today is
to practice using this toolbox.
Um I was reflecting a little bit on
where these come from. Um
and I think
high level point of view of where these
come from is that if if say this set is
small then there are a lot of
coincidences where a1 plus b1 is the
same as a2 plus b2 and um by kind of
rearranging those coincidences can see
that there are also a lot of
coincidences over there. That's the um
uh rough uh reason for these things.
Okay. Now, I made a small mistake last
time, so I'm going to begin by
correcting it. Thanks for the person who
pointed it out to me. Um
[Applause]
and correcting it is not a bad thing.
It's it's already a good opportunity to
practice these things.
Okay, so LMA one from last time was
stated not quite right. It should have
said
if A is in Z mod P. So this is let's say
let's call this corrections.
Um then either
a minus a over a minus a is everything
or um some kind of big mess with a lot
of addition and multiplication and
subtraction of a's is a lot bigger than
a okay but the big mess uh actually
should look like this. So you have a *
a. You add that to itself a bunch of
times. You also subtract that from
itself a bunch of times. This is what we
had last time. But I also need to divide
by a minus a, which I left out last
time. Okay. So the second possibility is
if you make this giant mess, it's
significantly bigger than a.
Okay. Um
the proof of this is very clean. Um so
the point is that if a minus a over a
minus a is not everything
then you can find some b in a minus a
over a minus a so that b + one is not a
minus a minus a.
Okay. And then we can say that a squared
is at most a + ba
because if you had any coincidences in
that sum, it would cause b to be written
uh sorry b + one.
If we had any coincidences in this sum,
you could solve for b + one and you
would be able to write it in this way.
Okay. But b by hypothesis can be written
this way. So now we have a plus
a minus a over a minus a + one * a. This
is less than or equal to the size of
this thing. Okay. And then now you just
expand out this thing. And if you just
expand it out you get this.
Um, now what I did wrong before is I
said we can like
sort of multiply by a minus a and and
like move it. Um, that's that's not
right. I just want to do something very
simple. You just this is
a set of a1 + a2 - a3 over a4 - a5
+ 1
* a6.
That's just what this means. And then
take this thing and put it over a common
denominator and expand it out. And all
those things you can write this way.
Okay.
It's always good not to trust me too
much, but does it does it look okay to
people?
Okay.
All right. Um,
cool. So then
I had a lema two from last time, which
was true, but the uh because it depended
on lema one, I'm going to have to make
it a little bit weaker. Um and it says
that if a is in zp and the size of a is
p to the s z less than s less than one
then
um
can have a cubed minus a cubed
should be at least
p to the s plus a little
So last time we had a^2 minus a^2 but
but that was based on having this nicer
thing over here.
Okay.
The proof of this is an excellent
example of practicing using plunic and
ruse inequalities.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to suppose that this is not true.
So this thing is quite small.
And then we'll keep using Pluna
inversion. We'll see like many other
things are small and eventually we'll
see that this thing is small uh and this
thing is small uh and which is
impossible by lema one.
Okay.
So
let's start with a remark.
Um
all right. So that we have that that
messy thing a^ 2
+ 3 - a^ 2 + 3. Let's call this b. A
minus a call it c.
And so lema 1 tells us that the size of
b / c is at least p to the s plus a
little bit.
Um
why? Um well
uh this this B over C it contains just A
minus A over A minus A. So one
possibility is it has the full size P.
And then that would be good. That's a
little bigger than P to the S. And the
other possibility is that it's at least
a squ. So then it's at least P to the
2s. And again that's that's good.
Okay,
so this guy is actually pretty big and
we're going to to we're going to say if
we suppose that this is small then more
and more things will be small and
eventually this will be small and have a
contradiction.
Okay, so we'll do a proof by
contradiction. All right, let me just
say
a cub minus a cubed is less than k* a.
And we're going to see that try to prove
that k is big.
All right. So this has a couple of easy
corlaries. One is that a cubed itself is
bounded by k * a. And another thing is
that a cub minus a cubed is bounded by k
* a cubed.
Okay.
So I can now plug this one into plumacus
inequality into into yeah inequality.
Once this one difference is small then I
could add up many copies of a cubed and
that would be also small.
So this inequality says that I can take
a cub to one big power
minus a cubed to some other big power
and that will be bounded by k + n * a
cubed but a cubed by hypothesis is
basically n. So this is k + n + 1.
So all of these guys are
okay. Now what about
um so um that covers B. So B is
certainly small but um we need to think
about B divided by C.
Um
yeah so B divided by C is not quite
obvious how it fits in here. But if you
take B and you multiply it by C then
you'll get a sum of degree three things
which will be part of this. So that
tells us that B * C is small.
Um
and B * C and B divided by C are related
to each other. We can I we can also say
that a * b and a * c these will also be
c.
Okay. Um so then we can use ruse's
inequality to relate b / c to these
guys. And so could say a * b / c is
smaller than uh a * b a * c. So this is
the multiplicative version of uh the
rusa inequality version two.
So subtraction has been replaced by
division and addition has been replaced
by multiplication.
Okay. And then this is bounded by k to
the order of 1 * a^ 2 and cancel the a's
and we get that uh so b over c on the
one hand is big p to the s plus gamma
it's bounded by b over c but on the
other hand it's small
and if you compare these you see that k
needs to be at least a small power of p.
Okay. Um
and then our third lema
uh was that if you if you take a subset
a and you it starts off maybe small p to
the s and you'd like to get take
products and stuff and and you'd like to
get up to something much bigger some p
to the t then you can do that with a
controlled number of additions and
multiplications.
Um, okay. So, here's what it says.
So, the definition
poly k of a is a take a product of k
things take a sum of k of those and you
can also subtract similar stuff.
And then lema 3 says uh if 0 is less
than s is less than t is less than one
then there exists some k that only
depends on s and t.
So that
um if A is a subset of FP of size P to
the S
um then
the size of poly K of A
is at least P to the T.
So I sort of you start with a set A and
you're allowed to add and multiply then
in a controlled amount of time you can
spread out to cover a very large chunk
of FB.
Okay. And the proof of this is just
repeat lambda 2 many times.
All right. So this is sort of where we
left off last time with with this
mistake about the denominators correct.
Okay.
Yeah.
So um a takeaway that I have from the
Rusa and Punicus inequality is that
there's some kind of contagiousness of
structure. So if if you see that one
projection or few projections are very
small um then it implies that some other
projections are small or few if a few
subsets are small it implies that other
subsets are small.
Um,
so
that that
Okay,
so let me spell that out.
contagious
structure.
Okay. So, contagious structure lema one
says that uh so Z isn't it? So, in in
all of these things maybe I should say
These are theorems that work in any
aelion group. So Z is an aelion group
and and and they have some of them have
versions of nonabelian groups too that
are not that different although we won't
talk about that too but okay and we have
some subsets of this group
[Applause]
so same setting. So Z is a billion
group.
All right. So suppose that a + t1 * a is
not too much bigger than a
and also
a + t2 * a is not that much bigger than
a.
And remember that these are this so this
kind of thing is basic in some additive
combinator some product theory but it
also looks like a projection. We're
taking the products at a cross a and
we're projecting it in the t2 direction.
Okay. So if we have these two small
projections
then
if I project in the direction t1 plus t2
it's also small
pretty
actually let's do let's do t1 times t2
first because that's easier and this
will be a nicer
fixed.
All right. So, there's the proof. Um
All right.
Um
Okay.
So, this this is uh
actually let me also make all of these
Yeah, let's also make all of these minus
signs.
Okay. So, a minus t1 a is quite small
and a minus t2 a is quite small.
I'm going to multiply this just by a
constant t1.
So, so this here it implies that t1 a
minus t1 t2 a
is quite small.
Okay,
Russa had this funny idea
that to
sort of think of the size of this as
some kind of distance between A and T1
A. So A is kind of close to T1 A. And
also T1 A is kind of close to T1 T2 A.
And so something like the triangle
inequality would tell us that A is close
to T1 T2 A.
And you you can really use the rera
triangle inequality in this way. Okay.
So the proof is by rera triangle
inequality.
Um and um so we have to decide who's a
and who's b and who's c.
And we want b minus c. We're going to
try to bond b minus c. So this is going
to be b minus c. Um so our um so our
I'll call it b bar is a c bar is t1 t2 a
and then a bar I guess must be t1 a
okay so then the inequality says t1 a *
a minus t1 t2 a bounded by
um a bar minus b bar. So t1 a minus a
time a bar minus c bar
t1 a - t1 t2.
Okay. So a * a minus t1 t2 a is bounded
by these guys that are both small k
and then that's it. I just divide by a.
Okay. So if the d projection in the
negative t1 direction and negative t2
directions are small and same for the
negative t1 * t2 direction that's also
small.
All right.
Um
[Applause]
All right. Contagious structure lema 2.
You can replace T by minus T.
So if A + T A is less than or equal to K
a then
a minus T A is less than or equal to K.
Yeah. So we saw this last time that if
if a sum set is big then the different
set should also be sorry if a sum set is
small then the different set should also
be pretty small and vice versa.
Yeah.
Okay. So this is also uh
also pl so this is going to be a pluna
inequality proof.
So let's say that t a is b.
So a plus b is pretty small. And then
therefore we get that b minus b.
No.
Okay, let's try Ruse's inequality.
So,
I'll say this is B and this is C because
I want to have that B minus C on the
right hand side.
And then uh
uh M A I guess can be a
A minus T I
less than or equal to
um and then let's use the second
version.
A + A A + T.
So the so this one we know is small. Now
we need to check that this one is small.
Um and but by plunicus inequality
starting here um a + a is less than a 2
a.
So this is less than k.
Okay. And now the most interesting and
difficult of the contagious structure
leas says that if
a + t a is small a + t1 a is small
and a + t2 a is small
then
a + t1 + t2
is small.
This is the trickiest. So, I ended up
needing the largest exponent.
Okay.
Um,
all right. So, this is a very good
exercise in combining these things.
We're going to start with this and we're
going to relate it to some sets that are
sound even much bigger. Um, but then
those sets we can easily chop through
with these inequalities and get back to
to a.
Okay. So,
a + t1 + t2 a
I'm going to bound that. And this this
looks quite wasteful by a plus t1 a plus
t2 a.
So this is quite wasteful because I'm
allowed to have t1 * one guy plus t2 *
the other guy. Here I only had t1 plus
t2 times the same guy. But it's a true
inequality.
Okay.
Uh, and it's helpful because we know
something about adding T1A to somebody.
And actually, the nicest thing we know
about adding T1A comes from the main
LMA.
So here in the main lema, you know, we
could have this B could be T1A.
And then we'll have a very general thing
about when you add B to somebody of this
form. and it doesn't get very much
bigger.
So have the main lama.
Uh and it tells us that there is subset
x1 in a so that for every c x1 + c + t1
a is bounded by k * x1 + c.
Whenever you see a sum like this, you
can remove this plus T1A and it only
slightly increases the size of the set
or you can Yeah. Okay. And same for X2.
[Applause]
Okay. Um,
okay. So now
we want to bound this thing
and we could get rid of the T1 A and get
rid of the T2A by by using this
inequality if the rest of the stuff had
the form X1 plus somebody or X2 plus
somebody.
We don't have an X1 plus somebody here
and X2 plus somebody in here. So I'm
just going to add them in, which again
sounds extremely wasteful, but is
actually okay.
So a + t1 a + t2 a that is bounded by x1
+ x2 + a + t1 a + t2.
All right. So now this has the form x1
plus some stuff plus t1a. And I can get
rid of the T1A by main lema one.
So that's less than X1 less than I pick
up a factor of K. X1 + X2 + A plus T2 A.
And then this thing has X2 plus some
stuff plus T2A. So I can get rid of the
T2A by by main LMA one again.
So this is less than k^2 x1 + x2 + a.
Now x1 and x2 are subsets of a. So this
is less than k^ 2 a + a + a. And then by
plunicas inequality
this is less than k 5*
Yeah.
>> What do you mean that a + a is less than
k a but you can only get k^2 a from the
a + t1?
Um
[Applause]
so starting from here and applying
plunka I can say if you call this guy B
that B cubed is smaller B plus B plus B
is bounded by K cubed A and B plus B
plus B is the same as
[Applause]
>> yeah it wouldn't really matter if this
was a bigger number
Okay,
cool.
Cool. Okay, so qualitatively we have
this picture that
the small projections are organized.
They have um
algebraic structure. You can take you
can add two small projections. You can
take the negative of one of them. You
can multiply them. So they are a ring.
It's not so clear that one is in there,
but um anyway, they have they have a lot
of algebraic structure.
And that mesh is something that we saw
in in in examples, you know, when we
wrote down like here's an interesting
set that has a lot of small projections
on the first day. The interesting set
was an integer grid. So integer cross
integer
and the set of directions were rational
numbers with small small uh numerators
and denominators
and you know if you add two rational
numbers you get another rational number.
If you multiply two rational numbers you
get another rational number.
And um and the numerology here is
roughly maybe not precisely but roughly
consistent with that.
So if you took rational numbers with
very small numerators and denominators,
you get really great projections.
Then if you add two of them, you get a
new guy where the numerator and
denominator are bigger. And that is
still a pretty good projection even
though it's not quite as great as what
you started with. and and that's what we
see here. So this guy is a pretty good
projection although not quite as great
as what we started with. And same with
addition.
Okay. So that structural feature of our
first example, it was not just a
coincidence about that example. It's a
general thing and um and it follows from
these inequalities.
Okay.
Okay. Great. So now with with this
toolbox we're going to start to make
progress towards the the Borgan cats tow
projection theorem
and we will we will prove uh an
important an important inequality of
some product theorem.
So there is a theorem.
So if a is a subset of FP and it has a
certain size
P to the S A
and D is a set of directions in FP.
D is P to the S D.
Um let's say that each of these is
strictly between zero and one. Then
there exists some epsilon depends on the
dimens on the s's big greater than zero.
So that the following thing is true. The
maximum t and d of a + t a is
significantly bigger than a.
Okay. So let's make some remarks about
it. So here's an easy correlary. Um if
you just take a plus a time a that
should be bigger than a
uh why let a be d
and plug it in.
But this theorem is stronger than this
corlary in two important ways.
One point is that we're not taking the
union over d of all these sets.
We're just taking the maximum overd of
all these sets which op priori is a much
smaller thing.
And the other point is that the set of
directions is independent from A. So the
most interesting case here is when SD is
much smaller than SA. So we have a
medium-sized set
uh a but we have we consider only quite
few different projections and still
that's enough that one of those
projections will cause uh the projection
to get bigger.
Okay.
Um we're going to use one of our tools
from Yeah.
in
uh this is essay.
Okay, we're going to use one of our
tools from day one of projection theory
which was the double counting.
So at the beginning of projection
theory, we proved that if X is in FP2
and D is in FP
Then um the maximum over t and d of pi t
of x
is at least
a minimum of the size of x and the size
of d.
Okay.
So um
so if it was the case that uh SD
was bigger than S A then then this
double counter implies our our
because then this maximum would be at
least either P to the 2 SA which is the
size of our X or P to the SD which is
the size of
Okay, by itself that so that that is
worth noticing. But by itself it's not
that exciting. The hard case of our
theorem is when SD is far smaller than
S. It has to be positive.
All right.
So here's the proof of our theorem that
combines the ideas that we've seen
today.
So first of all, even though D itself is
small, if I'm allowed to add and
multiply elements of D, then I can make
that as big as I like.
So the first step is by lema 3 there
exists um some K which depends on SA and
SD. So that
poly k of d
is significantly bigger than p to the s.
And therefore
by our double counting argument there is
a u in poly k of d.
So that a + u aa is significantly bigger
than a.
So we don't yet have
a a a u that's actually in d, but we
have a u that is formed by doing a
bounded number of multiplications and
additions and so on of things in d.
And we play this against the contagious
structure.
So um
if
the maximum t and d of a + t a was less
than k a.
Then we can use contagious structure
many times
and we'll see that also this guy should
be small.
So then
here's our contagious structure and we
get that the maximum U
in poly K of D of A plus UA is smaller
than K to a power um power here. And so
this power depends on little K.
But then if you unwind, little K depends
on SA and S.
All right. So if all of these
projections had been really small then
other projections would be small where
you add or take negatives or multiply
and you would get by putting that
together you would get that these are
small.
Okay. Okay. And so the conclusion is
that K to the C is bigger than P to the
gamma. And so K is bigger than P to the
gamma over C which is our P to the
epsilon. That's the proof.
Okay. So, let me restate um the
projection theorem that was sort of this
uh that we announced on Tuesday as our
next big goal and we'll compare it to
this theorem and we'll see that it's
closely related, but there there's still
something that we need to do.
Okay. So our our goal which we won't get
to today but assume is a theorem
KT that if X contained in FP^2
and
X could be P to the SX where SX is
really between zero and two
and D is contained at FP. P
the size of D is P to the SD where SD is
bigger than zero. Um then the maximum of
the projections is bigger than the
square root of X. So the maximum T of D
of projection T of X is at least P to
the epsilon X to the 12.
Okay.
So, so this theorem although the epsilon
is small is important because it's the
first theorem in projection theory that
fundamentally distinguishes the prime
fields from not prime fields.
And that is important in many
applications and it gets kind of
bootstrapped in the strong theorems that
that recent uh you know strong theorems
like ka conjecture versus conjecture and
stuff like that.
Okay. So let's compare this goal to what
we have from some product theory. They
look almost the same if you just set x
equal to a cross a.
So
one.
[Applause]
So theorem one is equal to
theorem bkt in the special case
that x is a product set a cross a
any questions or comments.
Okay, so maybe it's worth reflecting
since this was our main goal. Um,
why in the proof of theorem one did we
need to know that X was a product set?
So proof of theorem one is over here.
It's not very long. This double counting
argument has nothing to do with product
sets.
And we start to go along. We can say um
that the
the direction self it itself might be
very small but we if we take polomials
in the direction set then we get
something big. So up to here we have not
used at all that our set is a product
set. This would have worked for any x
and then we use the contagious
structure.
So the contagious structure said that if
if if all of these guys were small then
also the projections in directions t
plus one t1 plus t2 and so on are also
small. That contagious structure step
did use the fact that this had this
particular form which allowed us to
think about everything in terms of
ruse's inequality and the pluna
inequality and so on.
So I have been asking myself if it is
possible to prove those contagious
structure things uh directly for
arbitrary sets.
Um I I believe that they're true. Um
and it sort of follow so that the the
proof of this theorem is going to be
some kind of reduction to the case of
product sets. Um, so I think that in
hindsight the contagious structure is
true in general and so it I don't know
it seems like perhaps it would be
natural that it could be proven in
general but I'm not sure.
Okay.
Now on the other hand I would like to
argue that okay so so so then then at
first you see this and you say well
product sets are extremely special
subclass of all sets. So this is not
very good. But I would like to try to
argue that if X uh is a if this if this
thing is small at all then X is quite
close to a product set.
And if I convince you of that then maybe
you'll feel like like what we've done so
far is actually pretty close to our
goal.
All right.
[Applause]
So let's talk about that.
[Music]
All right. So okay. So remember that pi
t of x1 x2 is x1 + t x2
and also pi infinity of x1 x2 is simply
x2. It's just a convention. Okay. Now we
have some set of directions
and by performing a change of variables
we can assume that two of the directions
are zero and infinity.
So without loss of generality the
direction D is zero and infinity and
then some other directions.
Okay.
Right. So now X is any set X is
contained in pi 0 of X cross pi infinity
of X.
So pi 0 of X are all the possible first
coordinates of anybody in X. Pi infinity
of X is all the possible second
coordinates of everybody in X. And so
this product contains X. So this is true
for any set.
But because these are directions in our
direction set um so okay so let's say
let's suppose
that the maximum t and d of the size of
pi t of x is at most k * the square root
of x
and imagine that k is pretty small
okay so in that case
the size of pi 0x cross p infinity
x. That's the size of p 0x * the
size of pi infinity x. That's at most k^
2 times the size of x.
So this here is an actual product set. X
is sitting inside of it and x is um
occupies a large fraction of it if this
is a scenario that we're worried about.
Okay. So in order to prove this theorem
um it suffices to prove it for sets that
are a large fraction of a product set
and on the other hand we've just proven
it for actual product sets.
Okay. So now maybe it feels like this
theorem is is in reach that we just have
to all we have to do is to take our
proof that works for honest product
sets. We have to extend it to something
that is a large fraction of a product
set.
Cool.
Okay. So, we'll do that after the break.
It does involve some significant ideas.
There are significant recurring ideas in
additive cominatorics and projection
theory and lots of stuff. Uh, and there
are ideas about going back and forth
between something that is true um a
large fraction of the time and something
that's true uh all the time.
Okay, so that's the part of the class
today about some product theory. Take a
minute and see if you have any questions
or comments and then we'll let that rest
for the break.
Yeah.
>> So is it like in the true we have our
freedom to choose like gamma?
>> Yeah that's right. We have a lot of we
have freedom to choose gamma. So lma 3
lets us put here any exponent t that we
like and then this k will depend on t.
So this gamma can be pretty big. Um this
you know we could be halfway from SA to
one.
>> Can you see there depends on
like like in the last line it's like
sort of like absolute equal to gamma
in the last.
>> Yeah. So this C
um yeah I mean we could make it maybe
it's more maybe it's helpful to say
gamma is one minus SA over two. So yes
things depend on gamma but gamma just
depends on SA. So things still only
depend on SA and S.
>> Okay. Um
would there be a like gamma that give us
a nice bump for the absolute there?
>> Yeah. So another thing you might wonder
about is you might like you know you
might want to write down the actual size
of epsilon and you might like to uh
adjust the parameters in our argument
strategically to make it as big as
possible. Um so you can do that the
actual size of epsilon is there's a
formula for it but it it is pretty small
and so people often don't write it down
that carefully. Um adjusting gamma who
knows I think something like this is
reasonable. um it's not going to help a
whole lot.
Yeah. Yeah.
>> What is kind of the complication? If you
just kind of try and sort of
straightforwardly plug this into theorem
one, you can say that this will be kind
of less than guess you can take pi 0 of
x union of pi infinity of x as a and
then apply to theorem one which seems
like it would contradict kind of the the
statement that the projections are all
less than the square root of x.
Am I missing something kind of more
subtle there?
>> Yeah. Okay. So what so what happens now
if we try to directly deduce our goal
theorem from theorem one. So let's let's
say a is defined to be pi 0 of x union
pi infinity of x and so x is indeed a
subset of a cross
and the size of a is still basically
this or this.
Okay. So now theorem one tells us that
the maximum uh t and d of the size of
pi t of a cross a is big.
Um
okay now we actually want to bound the
size of pi t of x. How are these related
to each other? Well, this is a subset of
this. So, we we know this.
Um, but that's the wrong direction for
this to be helpful.
So, we're worried about the following
scenario
that x so a cross a is a product.
So there's a cross a and inside of it is
x
which is a pretty big fraction
and then somehow we managed to find a
projection where
the projection of x
is quite small
even though the projection of a cross a
we know the projection of a cross a is
large but maybe there's significant
piece that got projected onto something
small. That's what we don't know yet.
Okay. So, um
so your next homework assignment is due
the week after the break and it's not a
regular problem set with problems. It is
a check-in and reflection about the
class. So, you'll ask people to reflect
on um you know what what we've what
we've learned so far, see what parts
seem confusing or what parts seem like
clear. Um and then to um and then to
think about what direction we'd like to
go in in the second half of the class.
Um so there are a bunch of topics that I
think is cool are cool that we could
talk about and we could talk about just
one or two of them in depth. we could do
all of them in less depth. Um, and I
wanted to get your thoughts about it.
So, I remind people what the topics are
and introduce some of them that I
haven't properly introduced before. So,
for for for context.
Okay.
Um,
okay. So, these are topics that are
connected to maybe applications of maybe
extensions of the stuff in projection
theory that we have learned.
Okay. So one topic is um mixing
or random walks on discrete groups
and some of the key names are.
Um
another topic is a part of homogeneous
dynamics
and it's also about mixing. It's like
mixing of orchids.
Um and some of the names involved in it
are Margulus
Danny
Aratner.
Um and there's some recent work of
Lynden Strauss.
Okay, there is um Fenberg which is like
the sharp sharp projection theory
estimate in two dimensions. Um and
another thing that's related to this is
the CA problem and there's a recent you
know recent proof of the CA conjecture.
Monday after break the colloquium Hong
Wong is going to come and talk about the
Ka conjecture.
Okay. Um, so I wanted to tell you a
little bit about some of these things
and um, uh, I just you can make give be
a little informed as you think about
what you'd like to study. Um, okay. So,
this one I tried to mention on the first
day, but I don't think we really talked
about it at all.
I wanted to say something about it.
Um
okay. So, so homo the word homogeneous
is a reference to homogeneous spaces and
a typical example of a homogeneous space
is slnr
modulo slnz
call this x. It's homogeneous in the
sense that slnr acts on this space on
the left and it the action is
transitive. So every point gets mapped
to every other point.
um why would you care about this space?
So you can think of X as the space
of lises
in Rn
with co one
y. So start with the unit cube lice. I
can make another lattice of co one by
applying an element of sr to my lattice.
Um, now not all of those will be
different. So if my element was in SLNZ,
it will map the lattice Z to the N to
itself. So that's the kernel of this
map. And so the space of lises is the
quotient like this.
Okay. Um, so that's a homogeneous space.
They're homogeneous dynamics. So SLNR
acts on X and it acts uh transitively.
So if you take any X and X um the orbit
SNR of X is the whole space.
However, um SLNR has many interesting
subgroups and you could take one of
those subgroups and look at that orbit
and then different things can happen. So
let's say H is a subgroup of SLNR
and you look at H * X. Um so that's so
some kind of visual.
So this space is almost a manifold and
it has finite volume and it has a little
cusp which sometimes important sometimes
not important. Um and we have a point
little x in here and we take it orbit
which wraps around this thing in a sort
of crazy way. It looks sort of looks
like this. And uh people would like to
know um is this kind of evenly
distributed on the whole space or does
it uh concentrate somewhere and if so
where might it concentrate?
So how is the orbit distributed?
Okay. So questions of this type come up
in many places. Let me mention one of
them to you.
[Applause]
Um so here is an application in number
theory called the Oenheim conjecture.
Okay. So let's say Q of X1 up to Xn is a
quadratic form
and the question is to understand how Q
behaves when you put in integers.
So question
how is Q of Z to the N distributed.
Okay.
So one observation is that if Q is
always positive for real numbers then Q
of Z to the N will be always positive.
Um and another observation is that if
the coefficients of Q are all integers,
then Q of Z to the N will be integers.
Um
and those are the main obvious reasons
why Q of Z to the N would not be
distributed evenly on the real numbers.
Um
so motivated by that, Oenheim made this
conjecture quite a while ago. So
conjecture is that if n is at least
three and the signature of q is next so
it's not always positive and not always
negative
and um the uh
u the coefficients
of q are not contained in z time alpha
for any alpha.
Um then
Q of Z to the N should be dense
and and also in fact not just dense but
kind of these conjectures said it should
be dense but later people thought you
know if you take a big ball and Z to the
N and you apply Q to it you should get a
set of points that are quite evenly
distributed in um along an interval in
the real way.
Okay.
Okay. So this conjecture was proven by
Margulus
and his proof involves connecting this
problem to this setup of an orbit in in
the space of lises.
So how does the connection go? Well, the
way I've written it right now, I have
the standard lattice Zn and I have some
obscure quadratic form. But I could make
a change of variables so that Q is a
standard quadratic form and then I would
have some obscure lattice.
So after a change of variables,
um Q could be just X1 2 plus X K. Let's
say we're just in three variables and we
have a mixed size. Q is just this.
But um Z3 is becomes maybe Q becomes
this Z3 becomes lambda a new lattice.
Okay.
So now we have a lattice which is one
point in that space
and we don't know anything about it
really. could be any point.
But why would we have a whole orbit?
Well, we have a whole orbit
because this quadratic form has a lot of
symmetries.
So remark
um the group SO21
sitting in SL3
R uh that preserves
this
that's just the definition of this group
and a somewhat non-trivial fact is that
this is a large group. It's not you know
it's not the identity.
Um, okay. And so you could use lambda,
but you could also use
any of these guys.
So you could use the the lattice lambda,
but you could also change coordinates by
anybody in so 21. So you get a lot of
other lises and you can use any of these
lises and it's equivalent to the
original problem.
Okay. So now over here this orbit h
this is going to be so one and n is
going to be three in in this particular
application
and this initial point little x is going
to be our lambda and so we can use any
lambda in this whole thing.
Okay, so now it matters like who is in
this orbit
and if the orbit was dense, so then
lambda is allowed to be basically any
lattice. Um and uh okay and then once
you're allowed once lambda could be
basically any lattice, then maybe it's
believable that um that Q of lambda
should behave in a nice way. Or on the
other hand u maybe maybe this orbit is
quite a bit smaller and there are only a
few special lambdas in the orbit and
then it's not so clear what's going to
happen.
Okay. So that is how this setting setup
in homogeneous dynamics occurs in a
natural way in this number theory
application and there are there are more
applications also in a similar sphere.
Okay. Um,
now what does it have to do with
projection theory?
Um,
[Applause]
all right. So there are lots of
different subgroups uh h there and this
problem actually behaves in really
different ways for different subgroups
and the subgroups where there are strong
theorems are uh are unipotent subgroups.
Let me just write an example of a
unipotent subgroup. So let's say we have
SL and R and our group our group H but
I'll call it U for unipotent is the
group that looks like this.
Right? So you have all ones on the
diagonal. You have one guy in the upper
right hand corner called T which is not
one and everything else is zero. So this
is a subgroup u and this is one that is
behaved particularly nicely for this
problem.
Okay. What is nice about it? Let's also
let's also just for example we work with
SL2R. So U is just this
right.
Okay. So what I'd like to do is I'd like
to take so let's say UT is one T 01.
Um, and so I'm in principle interested
in the infinite orbit, but I'm going to
I'm sort of interested in the asmtoic
behavior. So I'm going to I want to
study the set of u subt
where t goes in some range.
Okay. Um,
cool.
So what's important about this structure
is that it interplays very nicely with a
different uh matrix.
So suppose now that little a is the
diagonal matrix
um little a r maybe is e to the r 0 e to
the minus r.
So that's sub 2 r also.
And the nifty thing about this is that
little a r u t little a minus r
is u e to the r t.
And so
um
right
so I can take utx
where t just goes from zero to one and
then I can apply a to it many times and
a
a inverse to it a a1 let's say many
times and a1 inverse many times
and this thing is now
say we do this n times
that that
so in other words in order to study this
thing I start with that which is quite
innocent looking
so that's just like a nice segment that
I can draw in my manifold and then I I
do this operation of conjugating by a
and I keep conjugating by a and
eventually I get this thing. So to
understand this thing I just it's
important it's what's just important to
understand what happens when we
conjugate by a
[Applause]
Okay. So what happens when we conjugate
by a.
All right. Um
um All right. So the conjugation map
conjugation by a,
it takes our
homogeneous space to itself.
Um, but if you look at a little piece of
the homogeneous space,
take a little box here,
then some of these directions will be
stretched and some of them will be
contracted.
So
get maybe something
Okay. Um,
and now
so let's say let's say our orbit is
yellow.
So we've we've done this a few times. So
we have some piece of orbit.
Um, and now we want to see what's going
to happen to the orbit. Uh, well, some
of the some piece of it got squashed.
Um,
so okay. Um so it it depends upon this
orbit and then um if the if the if two
strands here are separated by a
direction that's the squash direction
then they'll end up closer together
here. And if they're in a direction
separated by a direction that doesn't
get squashed then they'll stay far
apart.
Um
um
so so in this box there is a direction
so this is a box is B and there's a
direction
D subB
direction in B that gets contracted.
It's not quite true but it's almost like
this box gets completely flattened. It's
almost like the box is being projected
to something lower dimensional
projection.
Okay. Um, and these guys go through a
bunch of boxes.
So here's B2,
B1, B2, and so on. And um the direction
DBJ is is changing,
right? So um so you can choose
coordinates so that the direction of
these orbits is a coordinate axis and
then the direction that's getting
squashed is changing. So it's sort of
like as you go along here there are
projections in different directions.
Okay. Um
so
right so that's let's call this
conjugation map fee. So fe restricted to
B is sort of like a projection
and changing B
is sort of like looking at different
projections.
Um so we have one set of orbits but they
pass through a bunch of boxes and so
we're applying different projections to
them.
Okay. So this is roughly how projection
theory comes into understanding how
these orbits look like which has
applications in different areas.
Okay.
Okay. So I guess I mostly talked about
about this one.
Um
uh but it was the one that we hadn't
talked about and I thought I should say
something about it.
have just a couple minutes. Should we
It's almost spring break. Maybe we
should take a break. We should just stop
early.
Yeah, let's do that. So, let's stop
there. I wish you a very nice and
restful and fun spring break and I will
see you afterwards.