great so up until now you've been doing
what I've asked you to do now it's time
to put your imagination on display
you've noticed that we've only been
working with major Tri or major scales
and Triads and all kinds of things like
this but what else could we do well we
could thinking about the other important
scale the minor
scales and we'll remember that the minor
scales have not just one form but at
least three forms the natural the
harmonic and the melodic minor I want
you to think for a second which one of
these scills is most attuned to writing
out the harmonies of Rowan
numerals that's right it's the harmonic
minor form so that's what you're going
to be most thinking about
here why do we have to restrict
ourselves to Triads why can't we do
seventh chords or ninth chords or 11th
chords or something else so we have to
think about returning Roman numerals
like 5 seven or
seven half diminish 65 or four4
two while we're at it why do we think
that all chords have to be part of the
scale that's being played so why can't
we return flat 3 in C major for the
major Triad beginning E flat GB flat for
those who have taken 302 or 303 and 304
what about secondary dominance or what
about thinking about Neapolitan chords
or augmented sixth chords can you return
a French 43
chord and why are we sticking in the
realm of Music analysts chords like
Roman numerals why not think about the
chords that people use very often like
jazz and pop chord symbols where you
might have uh CM for C minor or c sus4
for the particular sustained ACC chord
that appears there if you know how to
use Jazz symbols why not use them and if
you've taken broke music or medieval and
renaissance music you might think about
figured Bas symbols so they're A Whole
New World unto themselves
and this should just be the beginning of
what your imagination can make so for
your final part of this assignment I
want you to make an open-ended extension
you're going to write and document very
very important document an interesting
extension to the problems above
according to what you've seen in the
video so go ahead and call your
extension whatever you want and test
your extension show me that you have
really seen what your extension is
supposed to do and what what you can do
when you're going to do all this don't
spend too much time on this but spend
some time
because asking your own questions is a
great way to understand what's going to
be asked at the end of the semester
research project