Hi, nice to meet you guys. Uh, I'm Zach
Cavlac, uh, founder CEO of Aperture. I
actually spent 11 years at MIT and my
PhD research was actually with Professor
Dena Katabi who spoke about emerald
earlier. So, I built about 500 of those
radar sensors and my expertise is seeing
through things with radar. And so
Aperture rather than seeing through
walls for healthcare, Aperture is using
satellite radar to see through tree
canopy and top soil for agriculture,
climate, and defense applications.
And so one of the most important things
that being able to see through trees and
top soil allows is for the measurement
of soil moisture. If you think of water
as the fundamental variable for all life
on earth, um feeding the global
population is 4.5 billion acres of land.
Uh about a billion of that is irrigated
today uh across the world. But one of
the things that farmers don't know when
they walk out to a field is that they
don't know what's beneath the surface.
They see the weather from the last few
days. They look at the crop canopy and
how it's growing, but they have no idea
what's going on beneath the surface
today. And so most farmers will make
decisions about irrigation and soil
moisture based on what their what their
neighbor does or driving a truck their
truck down the dirt road and seeing how
much it picks up behind them. And the
same thing goes for fertilizer
application where when you apply
nitrogen fertilizer or pesticides, if
it's too dry, it might not get picked up
by the plants. If it's too wet, it runs
off into the community's water supply
leading to downstream uh Parkinson
disease and other types of uh health
conditions.
And so soil moisture is this fundamental
variable, but because it's below the
surface, nobody can see it. And so most
farmers don't do anything about it. And
those that do might plant a single
sensor at the edge of their field or the
side of their field. Um, but that only
tells them about that section. Uh, it's
hard. It's they're battery powered.
They're often collected to a cellular
back haul. They can be driven over with
tractors. Farmers hate them. There are
some satellites that take cameras and
pictures, but once the cra the canopy
grows and closes, you no longer see the
ground and the soil anymore, and so
you're left with uh just the changes in
the color of the leaves. Occasionally
there are one to two uh NASA European
Space Agency satellites that can
penetrate top soil, but they're frequent
and far few and far between. And so what
we're developing at Aperture are a
constellation of lowfrequency radar
satellites that can penetrate through
tree canopy and top soil to measure soil
moisture at high resolution directly on
the field. We pair that with uh machine
learning algorithms that let us fill in
the gaps today between satellite imagery
uh and extract additional insights and
intelligence off of this data.
And so the way we do it today, we
already are bringing a product to
farmers. Um we leverage those infrequent
satellite measurements and we pair it
with precision weather data uh
topological modeling and fuse it through
machine learning AI and hydraological
models to produce uh customer insights
and intelligence on a daily basis so
that when it rains, if there's a heat
wave coming, they know to irrigate
regardless of uh just the weather and
guessing on their own. And so we deliver
this through a cloud-based platform. uh
we offer it either as a a farmer-f
facing product or it can be a white
labeled model that ties into other types
of a tech or climate sustainability
based businesses that benefit from this
data set. Uh all of this is cloud as
cloud-based and highly scalable across
the continental US. And so our impact is
initially within agriculture, but we
have about uh $4 million in contracts
with the Space Force, Air Force, and
Navy. It turns out that the Air Force
also cares a lot about soil moisture
because when they want to model the
weather for their operations in Europe,
uh in Asia, in South America, they're
not getting weather station data to make
those decisions. And so soil moisture
acts as that boundary variable between
land and atmospheric interaction that
lets them make operational decisions. Um
with that because of our satellite and
our analytics we're interested in all
types of partnerships and collaborations
from aerospace uh defense intelligence
but also agriculture and climate
sustainability. So we have a table next
door. Feel free to come by and and share
a bit more about your company and
application. Thank you.