- Hi, everyone. Thank you
all for joining today.
For today's seminar,
we have Professor Masha
Kamenetska from BU.
She's an assistant professor joint
in the Departments of
Chemistry and Physics.
She's also a member of material
science and engineering,
as well as the Nanotechnology
Innovation Center.
Broadly speaking, her research focuses
on single molecule spectroscopy
and characterization,
and her work has been
recognized by awards,
including the Air Force
Young Investigator Award
as well as the NSF CAREER Award.
So it's a pleasure to have
you, Masha, here with us today,
and we're going to learn
more about Masha's work
on engineering quantum properties
of molecular circuits with chemistry.
So before I ask Masha to join me here,
just as a reminder, if you
have any questions in the room,
feel free to raise your hand
to ask your question directly.
For those who are listening to us online,
if you type your question
through the Q&A option,
I'll read it and can help
moderate the questions for you.
And yeah, Masha, the floor is yours.
- Thanks.
(audience applauding)
So thanks so much, Farnaz,
for organizing this visit.
I've really enjoyed my day.
Thank you all who have met with me.
I've learned a lot.
As some of you know,
I did do my undergraduate
degree here at MIT,
so it's a little bit
surreal to be back here
in this kind of different capacity.
What's more is,
so I was a Course 8 major,
so that's physics for
those of you (chuckles)
who, like me, might've forgotten.
And now as you'll see,
a lot of what I do is molecular in nature.
So we'll see how well I
do here switching fields.
So, you know, as, as Farnaz said,
my work is interdisciplinary
and my lab broadly focuses on developing
and then applying single-molecule tools
to probe matter on the nanoscale
on the single-molecule level.
Today I'll focus mostly on
these molecular metal junctions,
molecule metal junctions
where we can create circuits
out of single molecules.
So before I jump into that,
I just want to give you a broad overview
of a little bit of what my lab does.
As I said, we focus broadly
on probing single molecules,
and so that spans kind
of the nanoscale range
or regime where we have
small molecules bound
to metal electrodes,
but we're also working
on biophysical systems
using a different class
of techniques called optical
tweezers to probe kinetics
and thermodynamics of
biological materials.
And then here in between,
we're working to apply these
tools borrowed from biophysics
to more material science applications.
And I see Haneel there
in the back who's working
on this problem in my lab.
Okay, so that's kind of a
broad overview, and again,
before I jump into the specifics,
I think it's good for us all to get
on the same kind of page in terms of,
you know, the motivation.
So why go through the trouble
of isolating a single molecule
so that we can watch it in real time?
Well, it's because, you
know, molecules are dynamic.
So I think biophysics
community was the first
to kind of really articulate
this very clearly.
If you imagine some sort
of biological complex such
as this kind of monster over here,
you might realize that a lot
of the functionality here comes
from the interface
between different elements
of this complex.
So there's intramolecular
interactions between, you know,
different parts of the same molecule.
There's intermolecular interactions
between different molecules.
And so this complex is dynamic
and these interfaces
are constantly changing
and it's very hard to
synchronize a large number
of these complexes such
that they're all in phase.
And so if you put a large
number of them into a test tube
and probe it with some
kind of spectroscopy,
you're going to get a mess, right?
A blur because they're all slightly
in a different phase of their motion.
And so if you can grab a single molecule
and actually watch its dynamics,
you can really get an
understanding what is the function
and how does the structure
affect the function
and what are the dynamics?
I would argue the same set of, you know,
arguments apply to these
molecular junctions,
which are the subject of my talk today,
where you're putting together
at least two very different components
to make some sort of, you know,
functional device, if you will.
These are not yet devices.
They're still in basic research
phase of their development,
but they have some sort of functionality.
And this was actually
proposed by Aviram and Ratner
in this seminal paper in the 70s.
And what they really kind of focused on
and proposed in a revolutionary way
is that you can actually design molecules
to give you electronic functionality,
like they can act like, you know,
transistors or diodes, and so on.
But what I think was underappreciated
for many years is the fact
that the interface here,
which, by the way is
a significant fraction
of the overall size of the
system, can't be ignored,
because the interface
is on the same length scale
as the system itself and so
you can't just neglect it.
The dynamics of this interface
will influence the properties.
And so you really wanna be able
to isolate this and study it
and see how changing structures affect
the electronic properties
of the entire circuit.
What makes these systems really
unique opportunity, I think,
is that you can see quantum effects
even at room temperature.
Why is, and that's really kind of
what I will be focusing
on today, so why is that?
Well, at the nanometer scale,
if you think about the mean free path
of an electron in a metal,
it's a lot longer than a nanometer.
So what does that mean?
That means that on the
scale of the junction,
the electron crosses the
junction ballistically
without scattering off of phonons.
And so because there's no
scattering on this length scale,
the process, this transport of an electron
across the junction is coherent.
Oops. There's the arrow.
And so even at room temperature,
this coherence is preserved
and we can observe quantum phenomena,
like quantum interference
and then also use chemistry
by manipulating, synthetically,
the structure of this molecule
to control and engineer quantum phenomena.
Okay, so just another
kind of background slide.
So how do we actually
make these measurements?
So for the molecular junctions,
I just mentioned a few minutes ago,
we use a kind of a
scanning probe technique
where we isolate a molecule
between a tip and a substrate.
And then for, so let me show you,
here's a typical molecule that
we can measure, for example.
For longer molecules and softer materials,
we actually use the optical tweezer,
and these two tools are
really kind of complimentary
in that they cover, they span
different regimes of length
and also of energy.
So the scanning probe technique
is really ideal for small
molecules on the nano scale,
because it has exquisite length resolution
and it is quite a stiff probe,
which is compatible with
the covalent linkages
in these short molecules.
In contrast, if you wanna study, you know,
Van der Waals-bonded
or hydrogen-bonded softer materials,
you need a softer probe
on the piconewton scale.
This is also the scale that's ideal
for probing biological complexes.
And you can sacrifice a little
bit of your length resolution
because these are extended systems.
So these are really two nice
complimentary approaches
and we use them both in the lab.
And what I won't get to tell you today
is about our work on biological polymers,
so here's a unzipping
of a single DNA hairpin,
which is kind of cool to see.
Here's the unzipping event
at 10 piconewtons or so.
And the other story that I
won't get to show you today is,
and I learned this previously,
when I have this pointer, I
can't actually play the movies.
So if I could, what this movie would show
is that these are two gold nanoparticles
that we're holding in an
optical tweezer in solution
and we can move them
relative to each other while
at the same time measuring
the plasmonic response.
So that's another project in my lab
that I won't get to
talk to you about today.
Okay, so as I already mentioned,
what I will tell you about
are these molecular junctions
and how we can observe
and control quantum
phenomena in these systems.
So one of the very few
kind of background
theory slides I promised,
but, so I already mentioned
that transport here
is ballistic, so this is not
like in a macroscopic system
where electron gas diffuses.
That's kind of the model
of conductivity here,
the electron crosses ballistically,
and that means that
transport here is described
by the Landauer-Buttiker
model where conductance,
this G's conductance,
current divided by voltage,
so the inverse of what you're used
to reading about resistance,
that's just the convention in this field.
Conductance is going to
depend on the transmission T
of the available quantum
channels in your junction.
So if there are many quantum channels,
then you sum over them,
and you sum over this coefficient T,
the transmittance of this junction.
And so if you have a
single conducting channel
with a transmission probability of 100%,
then you expect a conductance of one G0,
which is the quantum of
conductance through this junction.
So it turns out that
molecules typically have
a transmission probability
that's lower than 100%.
And why is that?
Well, if we kind of do the
kind of the most simple model
of what this system is, we
have two metal electrodes,
which have a continuum of
energy states filled up
to this energy E fermi,
so all my carriers of charge are
at the energy called E fermi.
Of course we apply a slide bias
which is greatly exaggerated
in this cartoon to drive the
system out of equilibrium
and drive electrons across this junction,
but now as this electron
comes to this junction,
what it sees actually
are these discrete molecular
orbitals from the molecule.
The molecule's like a zero-D system,
so it has these discreet spectrum.
And so these orbitals
are typically mismatched
in energy from the fermi energy of gold
and so what you really have here is kind
of your classic tunneling problem,
which maybe you remember
from back, you know,
introductory quantum classes
where the electron's going
to tunnel across this barrier.
And so the tunneling
probability is exponentially,
decays exponentially with
the length of the molecule.
The longer the barrier,
the lower the transmission probability.
And the other thing that it depends on
is the height of the barrier.
And in this case,
the height of the barrier
is the energy mismatch
between the molecular orbital,
so I should mention, I'm
using chemistry language here.
So MO is molecular orbital.
These are just eigenstates
of the molecular system.
And then the LUMO is the lowest
unoccupied molecular orbital
and this is HOMO, highest
occupied molecular orbital.
This is just chemistry jargon,
but the mismatch is what dictates
the height of the barrier
and so your conductance will decay faster
for molecules that have a wider
HOMO-LUMO gap, for example.
So that's one way to think about this.
There's kind of another way
to think about transmission in the system
and that's by realizing that
these discreet resonances
will broaden when the molecule interacts
with the metal, right?
So the molecular orbitals
will hybridize with the metal
and so the lifetime will shorten
and so these resonances will
broaden and it's the broadening
and the resulting overlap of this resonant
of this kind of molecular
orbital resonance,
the orbital overlap at fermi
will dictate transmission.
So energy level alignment is important
and broadening is also important
for determining transmission.
And this spectrum on
the right we often get
from calculations, for example,
density functional theory calculations
and we will often calculate
this and then compare
to our experimental
measurements of conductance.
Okay, so how do we do these measurements?
I will go through this rather quickly.
It's a modified scanning tunneling
microscope except instead
of imaging to get a image in 2D,
we're going to operate this
in the I of Z kind of mode
where Z is the axis
perpendicular to the surface
and so we're just gonna smash
and then pull out this tip
relative to the substrate
and we're going to do
that thousands of times.
And if we do this in a solution
of molecules occasionally,
we trap a molecule in this junction
and we measure the current.
Okay, we can do this at
room temperature, as I said.
We also do this at times at four kelvin
and we collect many measurements
to get statistically meaningful results.
Okay, am I doing okay with the microphone?
Yes. Okay, good.
So how do, you know,
how do you know that what
I'm telling you is correct?
We'll just look at the data.
So here's a single pullout
trace measured on clean gold.
And so immediately what you see
is you have these discreet
jumps in conductance.
This is very kind of not classical.
Why are there discreet jumps?
Because a single gold atom
has one nearly perfectly
transmitting conductance channel.
So as you pull this junction
apart, you thin out the number
of gold atoms in the cross section
and you're removing conducting channels
and so your conductance
drops in these jumps
of integer multiples of G0.
This is very nice because at the very end,
you have this plateau at one G0
and when it ruptures, you open up this gap
and you know it's pristine,
because you just had a signature
of a single quantum point contact,
a single gold atom at the junction.
Okay, I'm just going to zoom in
and show this to you
on a logarithmic scale
so that you can see that after you rupture
that final plateau, conductance drops,
and then you have this kind of tunneling
through the vacuum gap
that you might expect.
Okay, we do this, as I said,
thousands of times to get
statistically meaningful results
and we analyze the data by
constructing histograms.
Okay, there we go.
This is a histogram
of 1,000 traces measured on
clean gold at room temperature.
And so, you know, we don't
select any of our data.
We bin every single trace we measure,
we put into this histogram.
And so the fact that we have peaks
at integer multiples of G0 means
that I didn't just select
a very pretty-looking
trace for you on the left.
I do in fact, very often, in fact,
in every single trace measure plateaus
at those integer multiples of G0
and this is my tunneling signature.
Okay, so now we're ready
to introduce molecules.
And so we're going to put molecules
that have been terminated, I apologize,
there's a little bit of a lag here.
There we go,
that have been functionalized
by some sort of linker group
that we know binds to gold.
Okay, so in this case it's the nitrogen
and the mean linker group.
And so what we see now is that
following the one G0 plateau,
we very often start
to see additional plateaus at
lower values of conductance.
And if we bin every
single trace we measure,
this is 10,000 traces, I believe,
we start to see peaks
at molecule-specific conductance values.
You know, to give you a
little bit more evidence
that these are really
single molecule signatures,
I will point out that
there's a shoulder here
and if you fit the
position of this shoulder,
its conductance is exactly
double the conductance
of the main peak.
I should say that actually this question
of is this a single molecule or not
has largely been settled
over the last 20 years or so.
This field is kind of reaching maturity.
Okay, so there's one more
piece of kind of tool set
that I have to show you,
which is another way
that we analyze this
data is by constructing
what we call 2D histograms where we now,
instead of just looking at the conductance
and bending the conductance axis,
we're going to align all our
traces along the sharp rupture
and kind of add them
all on top of each other
to create a sort of heat map.
So now we've bend both the conductance
as well as the displacement axis.
So this tells us on average,
as you pull the junction apart,
not only what is the average conductance,
but also how long on average
does this molecule stay
in the junction before the
whole junction falls apart.
Okay, so these are 2D histograms.
And then here on the right you can see,
I don't think you can see my pointer,
but a 1D histogram turned on its side.
Okay, I hope that's clear enough.
And so now we can do
some interesting stuff.
So this technique is very sensitive
to the structure of the molecule.
So for example, if I measure
conductance of molecules
of different lengths,
here measuring conductance
of alkanes all terminated
with the nitrogen,
you see that the conductance
decays with length.
Of course we make histograms
and we look at the average.
And indeed once this appears,
you will see that the conductance decays,
as we predicted,
exponentially with length.
I see it on my computer.
I think it just needs a moment.
So it decays exponentially
with length. There you go.
(chuckles) There it is.
And, you know,
as expected, so this is tunneling, right?
Quantum tunneling, and it went too far.
And the other kind of interesting thing
is that the decay depends
on which molecular family you probe.
So oligophenylling, so oligophenyls,
which I don't know who the audience is,
so I think it's kind of
obvious for a chemist.
But, you know, I think we
all kinda have intuition
that this little benzene ring,
which is kind of the basic
building block of graphene,
has the localized pi system,
which in graphene results in,
you know, a lot of the
properties of graphene.
And in this case, this
delocalized pi system means
that this set of molecules
is more conductive than
the saturated set of molecules
and so the conductance decays more slowly.
And so this is kind of interesting,
this is signature of pi transport,
whereas this sharper decay is signature
of sigma transport.
And so you can kind of
understand which one
is which by looking at these trends.
Okay, so this is quantum tunneling
and this is so sensitive
to the molecular structure
that something that we're
working on in my lab,
I won't tell you about it in detail today,
but using this technique for biosensing.
So, for example, we've shown
that we can distinguish signals
from adenine and adenosine, for example.
And so we're working to see
whether we can apply this
to other bio-sensing applications.
It's a sort of new spectroscopy, okay.
So the main subject of my talk
is engineering quantum properties
in these molecular
circuits with chemistry.
And I first will tell you a story about
how we can create a single molecule switch
or a single molecule sensor,
depending on your perspective,
by manipulating quantum
interference in these junctions.
So to do this, I actually have
to tell you that, you know,
I held something back and I
didn't tell you another thing
that's important in determining transport
in these junctions.
So I told you about energy level alignment
and level broadening that
results in this broadening here,
but if my claim is correct,
the transport here is coherent,
then symmetry will be important,
because this electron wave incident
on the junction can tunnel across both
or more than two molecular orbitals
as long as they're nearby in energy.
And whether or not the transmitted wave
will interfere constructively
with itself after it crosses
these two available kind of,
you know, channels or destructively,
that depends on the symmetry
of these molecular orbitals.
So, really, if this seems mysterious,
it's actually just a property
of the fact that this is,
you know, a quantum phenomenon.
And so if we wanna look at
the transmission probability,
we have to square the amplitude.
And in this case, the
amplitude is actually a sum
of two amplitudes and so
if you square them here,
you're going to always
get an interference term.
And the symmetry of these two
will determine whether this is positive,
in which case, it's
constructive interference,
or whether this term is negative,
which just means it's
destructively interfering.
Okay, and this has been shown before.
We're definitely not the first
to find quantum interference
effects in molecular junctions.
There's been evidence
of pi-pi interference
where all the channels,
the HOMO, the LUMO,
and other frontier orbitals
are pi in character.
And so when the electron
crosses this junction,
there's interference between
the different pi channels.
There's also evidence
between different sigma
channels interfering.
But what we showed is that
actually you don't need there
to be, you know, only sigma,
only pi in certain cases,
sigma and pi type channels can
interfere with it themselves,
and this gives you a little
bit more kind of tunability
and you can kind of
synthetically modify this
a little bit more easily.
So the specific system we're going
to be looking at is this
pyrazine molecule over here,
which, again, it's very well known
that if you bind linker groups
to a benzene in the para position, again,
that's kind of chemistry jargon,
you bind a linker group
at one and at four,
and so this molecule
binds to gold through one
and four positions,
you're going to get
constructive interference.
Whereas if you put a linker group at one
and three, then you get
destructive interference,
because of the symmetry of
the HOMO and LUMA pi orbitals.
And what we show is that in pyrazine,
we can actually flip this and
reverse this trend and
then further engineer it.
So how does this work?
So this is the work of
my student Hannah Skipper
who actually graduated.
I should say PhD here.
She graduated a few months ago.
So she realized that this
trend of constructive
and destructive interferences
in benzene, again,
it results from the fact
that the LUMO has a symmetric
with respect to where
the gold electrodes bind,
whereas the HOMO is antisymmetric.
And there's actually an extra phase change
that you have to account for,
because one is HOMO, one is LUMO,
just take my word for it for now.
And so this one is symmetric,
this one is antisymmetric,
and then another extra phase change,
you actually get
constructive interference,
electron waves add in phase.
And again, if you look through
and see how it all works out
on the one-three positions,
you see that you will get
out-of-phase addition.
And so what's interesting,
again, this is very well known.
By the way, destructive
interference looks like a dip
in the transmission spectrum.
That means conductance is very low,
whereas constructive interference
looks like this no dip.
So that's the heuristic. Okay,
so what happens in pyrazine?
So in pyrazine, the introduction
of these two nitrogen atoms
actually rearranges the
electronic structure, right?
So now our HOMO is
actually a sigma orbital,
but what's important is
that the symmetry of the
sigma orbital reversed compared
to what we had in benzene.
And so now if you do the
same kind of analysis
and you compare the symmetry
of the LUMO and the HOMO,
you find that you actually
expect destructive interference
when you connect the molecule
in the para orientation
and then constructive interference
in the meta orientation.
And again, if this seems
mysterious, really,
all you need to do is you need
to put two Lorentzian line shapes
in the HOMO and LUMO position
and then you need to encode this symmetry
that we observe here in
the gas phase molecules.
And if you just do that
and then square the added amplitude,
you get a sharp dip at fermi
which predicts no conductance.
Okay, so does this work in experiments?
I'm going to show you histograms
measured from thousands
of traces at room temperature.
And so I'm going to compare
the conductance of pyrazine,
which can only bind
to the two nitrogens in the para position,
to these two other molecules which
this one has combined in the
para and the meta position.
So the one-three pathway is available,
because this thiomethyl
linker is a known linker.
It binds to gold.
And this one only has
the meta pathway open to it.
And so if you measure conductance,
indeed you see no signal,
no discernible molecular signal
for the pyrazine situation,
whereas these two have a
sharp a molecular feature.
And what's more,
the feature is very
similar between the two,
suggesting that in both cases,
these molecules bind through
the one-three pathway
and conduct through the one-three pathway.
So again, we know that
the nitrogen can bind,
because this molecule binds,
but somehow when only the
para pathway is available,
we get no signal.
So it's binding, but there's no signal,
as if this doesn't conduct, it's off.
Okay, this is interesting.
We can look at it with a little,
in a little bit more detail using DFT.
All I really want to say
here is that the model
that I've used that I've
shown you here in green,
and it will show it to
you again in a minute,
is a very simple model I just
add to complex line shapes
and I see that I get
destructive interference.
DFT has a lot more details.
It's a full abend issue of calculation
with all the details of the
junction and the electrodes
and the electronic structure of gold.
And yet if you focus on this black trace,
which is predicting the transmission
of the vertical geometry
and you compare it to what
I showed you before here
in green, you see a very similar result.
So that suggests
that this very simple model
captures all the salient features
of the junction,
that you get destructive
interference when the molecule
is fully stretched out in the junction,
which is how we're probing it.
This also confirms that
the LUMO has pi character
and the HOMO has sigma character,
so it kind of validates
our experimental result.
But the reason I think this is exciting is
because this is just the beginning, right?
Now you can start to do chemistry
and you can synthetically
tune this molecule
to tune this effect.
So for example, if you add
a hydroxy subsistent now,
DFT predicts now this
gray transmission trace,
which predicts, you know,
a much better conductance
at the fermi energy.
Why is that?
Well, that's because actually
by just introducing that substituent,
you've, again, reorganized
the molecular orbitals.
Now you've pushed the sigma
orbital further in energy,
you've brought back the pi.
Now all three of these
are fairly somewhat degenerate in energy.
They all contribute to transmission.
And if you now predict
transmission based on the addition
of three components
with the symmetry we observe
here, you get this green trace,
which again matches very
well with a DFT calculation,
suggesting that now we've kind of,
you know, tuned the conductance just
by tuning the structure of the molecule.
What's even more exciting is now
what happens if you deprotonate
that hydroxy substituent?
Well, now you've totally
shipped your spectrum
and you predict a sharp
turn on of conductance,
you've kind of, you know,
made destructive interference go away.
So does this work?
Well, I probably wouldn't
be telling you about it
if it didn't.
So (chuckles) here's the measurement
of this hydroxypyrazine
in neutral pH conditions.
This broad feature over
here is well known to be due
to this pi-pi stacking
of multiple molecules
in the junction.
It's not what we're looking for.
If you now just add a drop of base,
literally on your junction,
you see a sharp turn on of conductance
and you can see it here in
the two dimensional histogram,
these very flat plateaus.
And, you know,
the unexpected thing is
that there were two peaks.
Why are there are two peaks?
Well, here's the para conductance we think
from DFT calculations
and it just so turns out
that this molecule can also bind
through this deprotonated
phenol or the oxygen,
which we later on kind of
looked into more detail
and found that indeed
phenols bind to gold.
So bottom line is by
engineering these molecules
or synthetically tuning them,
we've turned off destructive interference.
And so now we have this
sort of, again, either from,
depending on your point of view,
either a pH sensor or a
switch where, you know,
conductance is off in the state
and then once you remove the proton,
you turn conductance on.
So, you know, so hopefully I convinced you
that quantum effects are
relevant in these systems.
And so the next story I will tell you,
and maybe I'll pause and see
if there are any questions
before I move on to the next
story, yeah, in the back?
(indistinct)
Oscillation, so everything
here is DC. It's DC current.
So I don't know exactly
what oscillation you have in mind.
- [Participant] One second (indistinct).
- Oh, sorry.
- [Farnaz] I think they're
done with the question.
- All right, okay, so I'll continue,
and then if there's
questions, just stop me.
So the next story I'll tell you
is how we can use
actually radical character
to engineer conductors
or single-molecule
conductors in these systems.
And so in the very beginning, I told you,
that can conductance decays exponentially,
which makes this a very sensitive,
it's a very sensitive system
for kind of, you know,
sensing different molecular structures.
But if you are trying to think
of how can we use molecules
for some sort of real-world
application down the line
or just how can we simplify
studying these systems,
it's actually not trivial,
because it means that beyond about
a nanometer or so, your
conductance is zero.
And so a molecule longer
than an nanometer,
you can't study it, because
you can't detect it.
So it would be great
if we could find a way
to reverse conductance decay.
And so I'll tell you a story that shows
that we actually can,
and so it's a recent development
that's kind of turning by us and others,
but turning this whole field
on its head a little bit.
So, you know, topological
phase transition,
kind of a loud buzzword, but
bear with me, if you will.
So this was suggestion by
Hoffman as well as Jelinek,
showing that, you know,
a single polymer and this will
be demystified in a second,
can actually have two distinct
or more topological phases.
And, you know, if you
can switch this phase,
you can go from something
that's rather boring
and has a wide band gap and
doesn't conduct very well,
to something that has
a very narrow band gap
and is a good conductor.
So what are these topological phases?
So it turns out that you
can actually think of them
or they're actually synonymous
with resonance structures.
So a typical, you know,
prototypical system like polyacetylene,
of course, is really
only stable in this form.
It's not possible to get
it to this structure,
but nothing keeps you from
drawing that structure.
And if you kind of draw the analogy
to topological states, you
realize that in this case,
you generate this electron
density at the edges
and these electrons are radicals, right?
They're unpaired, and it's constraint.
There's just not enough electrons
to pair them up if you
move your double bonds
to these positions.
And so this
is our topologically
trivial closed shell system.
And with the same number of electrons,
we have this topologically,
non-trivial phase,
this topological insulator.
And you can actually see it in SDM,
so this is, again, is the
work by Jelinek showing that
by synthetically tuning this polymer,
you go from the kind of typical
delocalized HOMO orbital
to this HOMO orbital
where there's increased density
of electrons on the edges,
and so that's your
topological insulator phase.
And so a few years ago,
the group of Latha
Venkataraman at Columbia showed
that these topologically
non-trivial phases actually result
in this inverse conductance decay.
So for example, cumulene,
which I'll talk more about why it relates
to topological insulators,
if it's not obvious to you already.
But if you measure cumulene
as a function of their length,
instead of the typical decay in red,
you now see that the conductance
of these molecules actually grows
as you make the molecule longer.
And this is a cartoon, the
actual data is shown here.
It's a little hard to see.
I'll zoom it in for you later,
but there's a slight growth of conductance
as the molecules get longer.
And a similar situation also happens
if you make these charged diradicals,
so these are
dication on diradicals.
And if you look at this top line here,
which is the relevant
experimental line, again,
the conductance stays mostly flat
as you add extra benzene rings here.
So B1 is just one benzene ring
and B3 is three benzene rings, and so on.
And conductance stays, you
know, at least doesn't decay.
And then as you make the
molecule even longer, at some,
you revert to this traditional
decay of conductance.
And so we were interested
in seeing whether we can
push this trend further.
Can we make molecules that,
as you make them longer, the
conductance keeps going up?
And of course we had to pair
up with some synthetic chemists
or magicians, as I call them,
because they make these
wonderful materials.
So Mike Haley at University of Oregon
and my student, Brent,
kind of realized that these sets
of benzoquinone derivatives
that they make are good
candidates for this study,
because they have intermediate
diradical character.
So I have to apologize.
There's multiple notations
with how you denote diradical character.
So in this talk, I'll mostly
use this convention delta.
And so I don't know if you remember,
I had the slide where negative
one means fully diradical
and positive one is boring
closed shell system.
And so the fact that these are closed
to zero means they have
significant diradical character
kind of in, you know, just
in neutral conditions.
So where's the Dirac
character coming from?
Again, it's probably,
well, it wasn't obvious to me (chuckles)
because I'm not, I'm trained in physics.
But it turns out that this
benzoquinone structure is,
there's stability conferred by
making this benzene aromatic.
And so the penalty,
energetic penalty paid for
splitting up this loan pair
is made up for the aromaticity benefit.
And so as a result, you get
this resonance structure
between the two and both
of these resonance structures are present
and contribute in solution.
Okay, so one more thing
is that they've engineered
these thioanisole linker groups,
which have a thiomethyl in the ends
and that allows for this
molecule to bind to gold
and allows us to trap it in the junction.
So what do we see, okay?
So I'm going to show you
conductance histograms
of a series of these
benzoquinone derivatives,
so this is BQ1 to BQ3.
And if you make a conductance histogram
of measurement made at low bias,
you immediately see
this very drastic
inverse conductance decay
or anti-omic conductance as we call it,
where the longest molecule has
by far the highest conductance
by a few orders of magnitude.
You can make a two-dimensional
histogram just to make sure
that you're not just somehow,
I don't know, you know,
reacting these molecules.
And this gives you a nice check,
because you see that as
the molecule gets longer,
the plateau the
kind of length that this molecule persists
in the junction also gets longer.
So that's a nice test that, for example,
this one is the longest,
that we're measuring what
we think we're measuring.
If you go to higher bias, this
is about 200, 300 millivolts.
This effect gets even more
exaggerated where, again,
the conductance of the longest
molecule is a few orders
of magnitude higher than that
of the shortest molecule.
So I can just kind of
simply summarize this
by plotting the average
conductance as a function
of molecule length.
It's, oh...
Suspense.
(audience laughs)
And you're gonna see, you know,
basically conductance goes up
as the molecule gets longer.
And again, ta-da, to emphasize now,
instead of DK, right,
beta is now negative,
so we have growth.
So this is inverse
conductance decay, okay?
The really neat thing about the system
is that unlike previously
measured diradicals,
these are neutral and quite stable.
And so we can actually ramp the bias
and collect IV curves to
characterize the conductance
of a variety of bias voltages.
So we can collect IV curves on thousands
of such measurements.
So that's what I'm showing you here.
This is now
a 2D histogram of IV curves
that I've added up on top of each other
and I've plotted the average
behavior with this white line.
And, you know, don't ask
me why, but in this field,
it's very common to plot IV
curves on a semi-log scale.
So it's hard to tell whether
something's linear or not.
So for that purpose,
I've plotted these dashed
or rather Brent, my student,
plotted dashed curves which
are actually linear IV curves.
And so right away, you see
that these IVs are not linear
and that indicates
that you have a molecular
resonance within range.
So as you open the bias gap,
you're starting to hit
these resonance peaks
and that indicates a small
HOMO-LUMO gap in these systems.
Okay, so plotting this
all on top of each other,
so you can compare the conductance
of these series of molecules.
And I've also converted
current to conductance
by dividing by the voltage.
You see, clearly, first of
all, that the HOMO-LUMO gap,
which you can kind of,
is this kind of width between the turn on
of current is a proxy for HOMO-LUMO gap,
decreases with molecule length.
And that's what you expect
for really any molecule.
Like your particle in a box,
you make the box bigger,
the HOMO-LUMO gap shrinks.
But what's really
remarkable in this system
is that the zero bias
conductance increases.
And it increases by two
orders of magnitude,
which is not something
that's been observed to date.
And so why is this happening?
So if you allow me, I know
I'm running a little bit long,
but I'll try to go through this fast,
because it's kind of, I
think this is exciting,
but to understand what's going on,
you have to kind of go back
to your tight binding model,
which is synonymous with 1D-SSH
and parameterize the system
to understand why we have
these closing HOMO-LUMO gaps
and why we have this
increasing conductance.
So polyacetylene has
been worked out years ago
and, you know, one way
to kind of understand
the different topological structures
is to realize that the
double bond is just really
a hopping parameter.
Where there's a double bond,
the hopping probability is higher.
And so if you describe
the hopping probability
in terms of delta like this,
then all you have to
know is that when delta
is greater than one,
you have this kind of structure where this
is higher hopping probability,
so you have a double bond there.
And when delta is less than one,
then you have this other topological state
where now you've moved
your double bond over.
And so by parameterizing
like this, you can now
just write your simple
tight-binding Hamiltonian,
for those of you who are interested,
and now you can solve it
as a function of delta,
because t1 and t2 depend on delta.
So when you solve it for
different values of delta,
you get the following.
You get your boring wide band gap molecule
when delta is equal to one.
You get narrowing HOMO-LUMO
gap when delta decreases.
And finally in the topological
state, you get no gap.
You get a gapless semiconductor, okay?
So this is just extrapolated
for all values of delta.
And now we can take this spectrum,
these are just eigenstate solutions
to this tight-binding Hamiltonian
and we can use non-equilibrium
Green's function
to calculate transmission.
So all you have to do is,
I'm just gonna take these resonances
and now I'm going to
predict transmission, okay?
So for this
boring wide band gap
molecule, you get wide bang gap,
and so you have low conductance
at the fermi energy.
For the intermediate case,
you have a narrower HOMO-LUMO gap
and so you have higher conductance,
and for this topological
system, you get no gap.
But of course it's impossible
to stabilize the system,
and so I'm going to look at
this delta equal to 0 case,
the intermediate case,
because there's actually
a physical analog to this,
and we can see whether this model agrees
with experimental results.
So the physical model I'm
going to use is cumulene.
I know it's not the same exactly,
but it's a system where you
have perfect delocalization,
because you have these
double bonds at every site.
And so, you know, I think this
is a reasonable approximation
to the cumulene case.
And the cumulene case has
been measured experimentally.
And I already mentioned to
you that what they measured
is a very kind of gradual
slight increase in conductance.
So if you look here, it's, you know,
it's all within one order of magnitude.
It's within actually half
an order of magnitude.
So it's basically flat.
You make the molecules longer
and the conductance stays flat.
And if you look here,
that's exactly what our model predicts.
So this 1D-SSH predicts that
you make the molecules longer,
but the conductance here at fermi,
which is where we measure
it, stays the same.
So how can this be?
So the only way that you can
have a closing HOMO-LUMO gap,
but a conductance that doesn't
increase is if you have some
sort of destructive quantum
interference canceling the fact
that the gap is closing.
So this is really a signature
that there's destructive
quantum interference effects
at play here that keep
your conductance low.
And this is just showing that if you look
at delta equal to 0,
the CQI terms, the
constructive interference
really cancel out the
destructive interference,
and so you just get flat
conductance, no enhancement.
Okay, what about these molecules?
And now we'll just, you know,
reveal the result that there
is no such destructive
quantum interference
in these molecules and
that's why you have this
dramatic increase in conductance.
So just briefly, how do we see this?
We have to remake our 1D-SSH
model for the cyclic system.
Again, these are a bunch of details,
but we have to introduce
two more hopping parameters
and then make sure that
the delta equal to 0,
all the hopping parameters are the same
so that you really have this
fully delocalized system,
like you expect.
So if you do this parameterization,
you can solve for the eigenvalue
spectrum of the system.
Here it is. And now you can
predict transport, okay?
You can predict conductance.
So I'm going to show you
transmission curves for this...
Lemme just go, for this BQ
series that you measure.
And so if you zoom in at zero,
you see that indeed in this case,
this model predicts that
as you make the molecules longer,
the conductance increases.
And this is consistent with
what we see in experiments,
so that's always a good
when that works out.
And if you look at the
contribution of constructive
and destructive quantum interference,
you see that in this case,
constructive interference dominates
destructive interference effects, again,
in contrast to the cumulene case.
So, you know, the really
exciting thing here, I think,
is that these,
not just that we have this
dramatic increase in
conductance anti-omic behavior,
but that this is just the beginning.
So, you know, maybe I'll
just skip this term.
Basically these systems
are highly tuneable.
And the model predicts,
so this is the BQ1 series
that we've measured,
plotted on the scale
of diradical character.
And I apologize here.
I'm using the diradical
character measurement
that's more common in
synthetic organic literature.
But the point is that using this scaffold,
the BQ scaffold,
which looks a little bit
like flakes of graphene here,
and by adding substituents on the side,
you can further tune diradical character.
And if you can tune diradical character,
you can tune the conductance enhancement.
And that's indeed what we see.
So we've measured the conductance
of these kind of derivatives,
which have these extra thiophene linkers,
which they don't bind to gold.
All they do is they
stabilize the diradical
and so they increase
the diradical character.
I realize there's a little,
this actually is, again, a thioanisole,
so the molecule binds
in exactly the same way
as the previous set of molecules,
but the key here is now
the conductance enhancement
is further enhanced, right?
So this is analogous to BQ1.
It has higher conductance than BQ1.
This is analogous to BQ2.
And it has at least an
order of magnitude increase
in conductance relative to BQ2.
And so, you know,
if you can synthetically
tune these molecules,
you can tune your conductance enhancement.
Okay, so that's the end
of this kind of section.
Again, hopefully I've convinced you
that these graphene flake molecules
have significant diradical character.
And if you can synthetically tune them,
then you can manipulate
this quantum effect
to create your functional,
highly conducting molecular junctions
or other things that
maybe you can imagine.
Okay, so I'm out of time,
so I won't get to tell you about formation
of 1D metal organic molecular wires.
I'll just, you know,
put this, hopefully exciting,
picture up on the screen,
and I'm happy to talk to you about
why it might be exciting to try
to incorporate metal
atoms into the junction
and why that's an
interesting thing to pursue.
And with that, I just
have to thank my group.
This somehow doesn't work the
way it's supposed to work.
I just wanna find the picture of my group
and I want to thank them.
I really have a fantastic
group of students.
I'm very grateful to be
working with all of them
and I have great collaborators
and funding sources
and I wanna thank you
again for your attention
and I'm happy to take any questions.
(audience applauding)
- Thanks for a wonderful talk.
So we have time for a few questions.
- Hi, thank you.
I'm curious what's the smallest molecule,
or in that last part we didn't get to,
the fewest number of atoms
you can pinch between the gold
or get between the gold,
in terms of like nucleons?
- Yeah, so you always
have the linker group,
which let's count that as one atom,
like a nitrogen in an amine case.
So you need that to anchor to gold.
And then between that,
the smallest reliably you can catch
is two carbons or two nucleons
So that's, so half an nanometer roughly.
- Thank you for the great talk.
So when you were showing your
IV curves for the BQn series,
it seemed like going from BQ1 to BQ2,
there was a very strong enhancement of
the conductance value that you saw,
but then from two to three,
there seemed to be very
insignificant enhancement.
Do you have any explanation for this?
- Yeah, so it's definitely non-linear.
I mean, basically you can
never exceed a conductance
of one G0 here.
So, you know, as you
make something longer,
in the best case,
it's just going to
asymptotically approach one,
and that's kind of your limit here.
Because you only have the, you know,
it's just the one channel.
So that's basically why.
So you get a large enhancement initially,
but then it starts to
asymptotically approach.
But, you know, actually
there's probably more to it.
So, you know, at some point,
you know, this has to break down, right?
There's going to be localization
and your conductance
that's going to break your coherent,
the coherence in the molecule
and the conductance is
going to start decaying.
So is that partly what we're
already seeing? Perhaps, yeah.
- Hi, so in these diradical systems,
you have an even number of electrons,
but they're kinda
separated from each other.
Do you open up any cool
spin physics with that?
Or is the fact that they're still like all
paired, kinda watch that out?
- Well, certainly, so, you know,
part of why these molecules got
attention in the literature,
not in our work, but previously,
is because actually there's
the exchange energies
is fairly, is,
you know, is fairly small.
So certainly people are interested
in studying the triplet state
and I think you can access that at like
as little as 50 degrees Celsius,
or no, 50 degrees above room temperature.
So, you know, that was always
in the back of our mind.
So we don't see anything yet.
Based on what we've done,
my intuition is the triplet
or singlet doesn't actually
matter for conductance.
I don't have solid evidence for that.
So there might be, we
just haven't found it yet,
and of course creating
different spin multiplicities
is one of the motivations
for incorporating metal atoms
into your junction, right?
You can have all sorts
of open shell character
and you can have different
spin quantum number depending
on the metal you incorporate.
So we haven't seen anything yet,
but, yes, that's certainly
something we're interested in.
- (indistinct) Loud enough a little bit.
- Thank you, Farnaz.
Hey, so the Haley molecules,
they're required to have
dispersed stability,
they have these big bulky groups
and so the phenols are exactly-
- Yes, perpendicular.
- There's no overlap there.
- Yep. No.
- And so you have this
intervening little, you know,
junction between in each side.
And so I'm just wondering
how that, you know,
earlier, you had direct bonding-
- Exactly. Yeah.
- And so your gold
is separated, how does
that figure into all your
calculations and-
- Yeah.
So I forget who I was talking to today,
and we were saying that, you know,
10 years or so, the thought
was that you actually wanted
as direct a contact to the
molecule from the metal
as possible, 'cause that's
how you maximized conductance.
So that's kind of to your point,
but in these molecules, we have
decoupled them from the gold
and it turns out that when
you have these radicals,
this decoupling linker
is actually essential
to seeing this effect,
because if you couple it
too strongly to the metal,
the diradical will just
escape into the metal
and you will not see this enhancement.
So actually that perpendicular,
as you were pointing out,
the pi system is perpendicular,
so the diradical is really kind
of decoupled from the metal,
seems to be key to getting
this functionality.
- Yeah, I guess,
I was thinking it almost
looks like you have
a little quantum well between the two.
- I see.
- And, you know,
you have a barrier.
That's how I would've like
thought about it is a quantum,
two little barriers on either side, but...
- You know, the wild thing,
and the reason why it took
me a while to get my mind
around this is that the conductance
of that whole entire huge
molecule, for me that's huge,
with the thioanisole, the
kinda graphene flake core,
another thioanisole, the
conductance of that whole thing
is higher than the conductance
of a single thioanisole.
So the linker, so somehow the...
So I don't know if you can describe it
by this double barrier model.
My instinct right now is, no,
there's this fundamental
kind of transport,
different transport
mechanism happening here.
Yeah, but maybe we can discuss more, yeah.
- So I'm going to ask one
of the questions from our online audience.
So the question is asking,
how can we make functional
practical electronic devices
with these molecular junctions
and what are some of the applications?
- That's a great question.
Functional, yeah, I don't know,
but maybe you know, Farnaz.
Maybe that's a question for you.
(audience chattering)
(Masha chuckling)
- Can you comment on
some of the applications?
- [Farnaz] Well, I mean, you know,
I guess I would say that,
you know, the fundamental
limit to Moore's law,
why can't we shrink down our
electronics even further?
I mean, one way to kind of
restate that problem is that
as you keep shrinking
your electronics past
the 10 nanometer size scale,
you no longer have bulk material,
which is what you're relying
on to create the functionality.
You have some sort of
zero D, right, object.
These are quantum dot, if you
wanna think about it that way,
or a molecule.
These are all zero D materials.
And so if we want to push our
electronics to smaller sizes,
we need to understand the kind
of fundamental charge transport
processes taking place
on this size scale.
So that's kind of the motivation.
How to make a functional device?
- Yes, (chuckles) I don't know-
- A lot of work in that area.
- Yes.
- Any other questions?
- Thank you. Really
fascinating, thank you.
I have a related question to the one
that was just asked about
any immediate application
to improving quantum
coherence and computing?
- Yeah, the tricky thing
here, it's kind of misleading.
I probably can't answer,
well, I definitely can't answer this fully
in a short time period.
So what the effects we
observe are due to coherence,
but the molecule crosses this junction in,
I dunno, a femtosecond timescale.
And, you know, on a much slower timescale,
this is all at room temperature,
everything's wiggling.
And so in this tiny moment
of time when the electron is crossing,
it's not scattering,
everything's coherent,
but the next time another one crosses,
the system has fluctuated.
So, yes, we're studying
coherent phenomena,
but they're very short lived.
And how we connect this
to a quantum computing,
you know, is not clear to me.
But certainly people do make
qubits out of molecules,
but to do that, they have
to cool the system down
to the millikelvin temperature.
So yeah, we're certainly
thinking along those lines,
but I'm not sure I have
a good answer for you.
(indistinct)
- I asked.
- Right, right.
I'm glad I sold you. (chuckling)
It's true, but how do you
use it for quantum computing?
Yeah, it's not obvious, but
at least we can probe these,
I mean, the nice thing
is that we can probe these
fundamental phenomena
without having to cool to
millikelvin temperature.
And I think that gives
us a lot of benefits.
We can repeat the
experiments many, many times.
We can easily modify things
without spending weeks,
you know, creating these,
these systems, so yeah.
- So we have ran out of time.
So help me thank Masha again.
(audience applauding)
Thanks, Masha.
- Thanks.
- So we are going to have
a reception until 04:30.
So Masha will be here.
You can still have a
chance to talk to her.
There's also food, so,
please, help yourself.
(graphic whoops)
(graphic taps)
(graphic hisses)
(graphic clicks)
(graphic taps)
(graphic rattling)
(graphic hisses)
(graphic clicks)