So, I'm Khalisa Stevens. I'm the chief
operating officer at the Surplus. We are
a certified BC Corp Deep deep tech
company operating across three
continents. Um, we specialize in
circular intelligence that enables
resource security and our mission is to
build the universal digital
infrastructure that makes secondary
resources instantly discoverable and
tradable across uh global markets. We're
also graduates of the MIT Design X
program and we're honored to be here.
So our founder Rana Rasuli is a
University of Cambridge PhD researcher
um in engineering with 13 years industry
experience. Our team is made up of um
tech in bleeding edge technology a
commercial excellence team and we're
female majority from mostly
underrepresented backgrounds.
We're also backed by a world-class
international advisory board and we
founded the surplus because we
identified that two trillion dollars
worth of excess resources go untraded
every year. Um meanwhile companies face
supply shocks, trade wars and resource
nationalism.
So, we developed an intelligent platform
that thousands of businesses have been
using in the past few years to generate
over $6 million in trading surplus
resources while diverting millions of
kilos from landfill at the same time.
Uh, but for every successful match, we
found that there were 10 more
opportunities that weren't being
realized.
uh circular uh sorry industrial
symbiosis a subset of the circular
economy could be one way to unlock that
value but we saw that today's current
approaches are manual fragmented and far
too slow. Um the solution is not another
circular marketplace but really the
digital infrastructure to support
secondary material markets so that they
can be traded as easily as primary um
commodities.
So building on our existing product,
we've developed an additional feature um
that we're calling cluster X. This is
the first universal protocol for
secondary material markets. Um we use
opensource intelligence for speed, but
our differentiator is our proprietary AI
uh graph. It connects messy disconnected
signals into a clear graph. Um,
essentially
this allows businesses to identify um
secondary material resources in seconds
versus in months.
So we already have contracts with
worldleading banks, conglomerates and
economic free zones across three
continents. Um they act as distribution
partners which is giving us a confirmed
pipeline of over a million businesses.
um for our partners is not just about
sustainability but it's about resource
security and with supply shocks and
trade nationalis trade wars and uh
resource nationalism
resource security is a geopolitical
priority.
Uh Dubai Holding is one of the leading
diversified investment firms uh uh
portfolios in the Middle East. They
cover verticals from hospitality, FnB,
retail and real estate. And so they
brought us on as their tech tech
partners for their gift it forward
initiative last year. Um this is the
impact of some of the work that we've
done with them. We've managed to
transform over 300,000 surplus items
that are valued to nearly $4 million um
and redistributed them successfully to
over 16,000 beneficiaries. I'm pleased
to say that they were so happy with our
work that they invited us back for a
second year. And so we've built
additional features onto our product um
including uh logistics tracking for
supply chain and accounting for carbon
emissions from logistics to the embodied
carbon of the items as well. And so
we're hoping to make a larger impact
this year.
Um for partnerships, we are sector
agnostic. We work with all kinds of um
sectors and resources. But for
partnerships, we're looking specifically
at banks and financial institutions,
conglomerates and free trade zones,
logistics and port terminal operations.
Um, so please join us because we are
building the digital infrastructure to
map, price and trade secondary
materials. Thank you so much.
>> [applause]