All right, with that,
I'm going to get started.
Welcome to the immunology
breakout session.
My name is Stephanie
Springer, and it's
my pleasure to chair
this session here
on immunology at MIT.
What is immunology and
why do we care about it
in health and disease?
So with that, I would like to
give a very brief introduction
on what the immune system
is and why we care about it
when we think about physiology
as well as disease states.
The immune system, and
this is a slide from class,
can be very simply
depicted as a seesaw.
And this is a very
simple oversimplification
where the immune
system is trying
to balance fighting
pathogens, but also avoiding
to attack the body itself.
However, as I just said,
this is a very drastic
oversimplification of what our
immune system is actually doing.
So this seesaw is
probably more accurate
because we are not
living in isolation
and our immune system is
not acting in isolation.
Lifestyle, diet, stress,
all of these factors
affect how our immune
system is working,
and diseases push our immune
system every day to react,
and our immune system
still has to keep
at bay not attacking ourselves.
And an imbalance within
the immune system
can cause diseases,
but likewise,
allow the resolution of diseases
like pathogenic infections.
And it can also affect our
health and our well-being,
and likewise, our
well-being, being happy,
will affect our immune system.
Now, this is a human
body depicted as dots.
One dot is 10 to the
power of 9 cells,
and one large square
is 1,000 dots.
Now, how big is
our immune system
if this is our entire body?
You see here in red
and in dark red,
the two major subtypes of
cells that make up our body.
The light red cells
are erythrocytes.
These are bone
marrow-derived cells
that carry around our
oxygen. They also have
some level of immune function.
The dark colored cells
are all bone marrow
derived immune cells.
So these are the cells that
fight pathogens, fight cancer,
but also are responsible for
inducing autoimmune diseases.
And as you can see here, in
contrast to the other organs,
our immune system
is, by and large,
the largest organ in our body.
It is likewise not a
single solid organ.
It is disseminated
throughout our body.
It has a network of nodes,
hubs, meeting points
called lymph nodes that
are spread throughout,
and this is where our
immune cells actually
communicate with one another.
And our immune system can
be very broadly subdivided
into different elements.
We have the innate
immune system,
and this is the part of the
immune system that senses
if there's danger somewhere.
And then, we have the adaptive
immune system in, specifically,
two arms, the cellular
arm of the immune system
and the humoral arm of the
immune system mediated by T
cells and B cells respectively.
And these are the cells
that instill memory
in our immune system.
Meaning, if you get a
prophylactic vaccine
against flu, these
are the cells that
memorize that they've
seen flu before
and are better at eliminating
the virus once you see it.
These two arms of the
adaptive immune system
act slightly differently.
The T cells recognize
specific patterns on cells
and eliminate those cells
versus the humoral arm
is mediated mostly
by antibodies.
And throughout this
session, we will
hear from experts across
all of these areas
of our immune system.
Specifically, Facundo
will talk to us
about the humoral immune system.
Aroup, later on, will talk
about B cell responses.
Jessica will talk about
the innate immune system
and how patterns are hardwired.
Hari will put many
of these contexts
into, one, how cells
interact with one another.
And Michael, at the
very end of the session,
will talk to us how we can
use those basic principles
and use it to engineer
our immune system.
This is the summary of
these five professors
titles, which I won't
repeat for time constraints.
And I'm really excited
about this session.
And with that, I
would like to welcome
Facundo Batista as our
first speaker to the stage.
[APPLAUSE]
Yes, good morning, everyone.
And as Stephanie said, my
name is Facundo and yeah,
there we go.
And that is a typical
Argentinian name.
And that is why I am going to be
speaking with his strange accent
all the way.
So when people is
asked about what
has been the best biotechnology
discovery in history,
many will argue that it
will be wine or beer.
I, and many others, will argue
that it is going to be vaccines.
And essentially, vaccines
has been the source
of protection over the
last just five decades
and saving lives for about
150 million human beings.
And although we know
that vaccines work,
we don't know how they work.
But we know that these
molecules, the antibodies that
are able to bind pathogens
and trigger function,
they are the main
responsibilities
of active protection or
a correlation with them.
And antibodies are
not responsible
of active protection,
but they are also
critical in terms
of treating disease.
And I am using this example in--
just to point out that
in giving an antibody
to a person, an antibody that
recognizes a malaria parasite,
it will protect
that person for one
year just by injecting
the antibody into them.
And these antibodies
have been the basis
of many therapeutic cures to
cancer and infectious disease,
and as such, it makes them a
key target for bioindustry.
And the industry of
antibodies is, at the moment,
in the order of
$300 million a year
and is estimated
to be in one dollar
billion in about 10 years.
That is why we are particularly
interested in trying
to understand how these
antibodies are generated.
And in these regards,
antibodies are
produced by a particular type
of cells that are plasma cells.
And these cells are
really antibody factories
that they produce
millions of molecules
per hour every single day.
But plasma cells are the
result of a particular pattern
of differentiation of B cells,
and antibodies initially
are produced on the
surface of naive B cells.
And those cells are
able to recognize
either viruses or either
antigens that they
are given through vaccination.
And once they do that, they
will do something rather unique.
They will get together
and start to divide
and they will form these
that are in structures that
are known as germinal centers.
And here, they will
do something magic.
What they are going
to be doing is
they are going to mutate
the original gene that
carries that protein in order
to make that antibody much more
potent over time.
And this antibody will
become much more specific
for a particular
antigen or a tumor.
And the way that this
happens is that, initially,
when we get vaccinated
or infection,
we produce very low affinity
or not high quality antibodies.
But then, because of the
germinal center formation
and this specific
maturation that I mentioned,
the antibodies gain high
affinity and specificity
over the differentiation
of the cells that
then relies into the long-term
survival of this antibody
production.
And just to give you
an idea, we are all
being vaccinated
for measles here.
And those antibodies that
are-- those plasma cells that
are generated in the very
early stage of our life,
they will live with us for about
80 years until we pass away.
So my lab, what we do is we
ask fundamental questions
about how B cells, biology,
and antibody responses happen.
And indeed, I will
show some examples
on one particular
discovery that we
did that really kind of
enabled us to do really
absolutely cutting edge.
What we have been
doing over the years
is to manipulate or try to
create a humanized mouse.
In this mouse, what
we do is we change
the genetic code in
different chromosomes
to now express B-cell
receptors, or antibody
on the surface of naive cells,
that are not any longer mouse,
but they are humanized.
And as such, we can study the
immune resposne of these mice
as these B cells will
be practically human.
So we use this technology
to develop and unravel
several key questions in
terms of B-cell maturation
and biology.
And one of them was,
for example, this
is how a plasma cell looks.
And as I told you,
this plasma cell
lived with a very long
time in our models.
And these plasma cells
are able to produce
about 100 million molecules
of antibody per cell per hour.
And they need to produce
that over the course
of many, many years.
And in order to do this, what
we show, in particular, a PhD
student in the lab,
Stephanie, what is--
Sophie, what she has done
is she has particularly
looked into the code of
translation of that protein.
For those of you that
are not familiar,
proteins are
expressed as an RNA.
They are translated
by this adapter that
constitutes the amino acid, or
bring the amino acids to this
that they are the
shape of the protein.
And what Sophie found
was that these tRNAs
are critical in
programming the plasma
cell to produce this large
level of antibodies there.
We are not only look
into plasma cells,
we also look very much into what
antibodies do into our response.
And I know Arup is going to
talk a little more about this.
But essentially, what
we show is that we try
to represent this as a castle.
Germinal centers, that
I mentioned to you
before, they exist in the body.
And antibodies that
we produce, they
are able to block the
entrance of particular cells
or to facilitate the
entrance of others.
But we don't do
only B cell biology,
but we try to understand how
we can translate this B cell
biology and knowing
in antibody responses
to try to inform
vaccine design and offer
novel therapeutic development.
And in this, I will give
two examples of those.
We have used this-- what we
call this mouse machine that I
mentioned to you, mouse
that produce antibodies
that look like humans.
And what we have shown through
immunizing or vaccinating
those mice that we can produce
much more potent antibodies
that they can now
protect us to malaria.
And this is of
particular function
because-- a particularly
important one
because if we have
an antibody that
works much better
than another, that
decrease the cost of the drug
by several orders of magnitude.
Similarly, we have been
involved in a large consortia
to try to use this humanized
mouse model to characterize
different antigens.
And this is the
surface of the HIV.
And these are different
antibodies bind
to different portions of HIV.
And in our collaboration,
what we have been using
is our humanized mouse models
to enable clinical trials
for the production
on an HIV vaccine.
And in that regards,
in particular,
we have taken these
immunogens to the clinic.
One clinical trial is going
to start in next January,
and this relates, in particular,
to this portion of the protein
and the production of
antibodies against that protein
or another ongoing clinical
trial together in collaboration
with Moderna that
is particularly
focusing in how we
can develop antibodies
that recognize this part of
the protein of the virus.
So with that in
mind, actually, I
would like to introduce
the next speaker that
is Arup Chakraborty, and
he will be digging more
into the B-cell response
and the biology of it.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you, Facundo.
So as Facundo mentioned,
it is estimated
that vaccination has saved about
150 million lives in the past 50
years.
But we don't have
effective vaccines
against highly mutable viruses.
For example, we don't have a
universal vaccine for the flu.
So every year we guess which
strains may evolve and design
a new vaccine.
And the situation is similar
now for SARS-COV-2, which
causes the COVID-19 disease.
The way to better confront
these scourges this
is to design universal or
variant proof vaccines.
And a part of our
work is focused
on trying to address fundamental
scientific questions which,
if answered, would aid
the pursuit of this quest.
And toward this end,
we bring together
physics-based
computations and machine
learning along with trust
tests of predictions in animal
models and clinical data.
These latter efforts are
carried out in collaboration
with basic and
clinical immunologists.
And for the vignettes that
I shall highlight today,
the labs--
the collaborating labs were
led by these individuals.
Now, as Facundo mentioned,
upon infection or vaccination,
antibodies are generated by a
Darwinian evolutionary process
that occurs in germinal
centers, or GCs.
Herein, B cells evolve
by mutation and selection
to bind more strongly
to the antigen, which
is displayed in these GCs.
And that is why, as time ensues,
the memory cells and plasma
cells and antibodies that you
generate become more potent.
Now, upon re-exposure
to the antigen,
the existing memory cells
are first rapidly expanded
to create a wave
of antibodies that
is meant to confer protection.
But new GCs over formed--
also form, but over
much longer time
scales to generate more
memory B cells and antibodies.
Now, the first vignette
that I will describe
stemmed from our asking why
three shots of the COVID
vaccines protect better against
the highly mutated variant
like Omicron, while two shots do
not even though all three shots
encode for the Wuhan
original strain of the virus.
So this Darwinian
process is driven
by antigen displayed in GCs.
How does it get there?
Circulating antibodies
bind to the antigen
and deposit it there.
Now, when you get
your first shot,
all you have in you circulating
are generic, weakly binding
small numbers of antibodies
that bind to very little antigen
and deposit them there
before the antigen degrades.
And you can see this by
imaging lymph nodes of monkeys
after the first shot.
And here you see there's
hardly any antigen there.
So if you think of the antigen
as the prey and the B cells
as the predators in this
Darwinian process, when there's
very little prey, only the best
predators are going to survive.
And that is why,
after the first shot,
the antibodies and memory
cells that you generate
are those that
initially bind strongly
to the spike of
the virus and bind
to regions called
immunodominant.
And here I have depicted
these antibodies
binding to the
spike of SARS-COV-2.
Now, after the second shot,
the corresponding memory cells
are rapidly expanded
to generate antibodies.
Now, the regions
that are in red,
they are mutated in Omicron
compared to the Wuhan strain.
And you see they
are in the binding
footprints of these antibodies.
And so they're not very
effective against Omicron.
But after the second shot
you also form new GCs,
but now you've got
circulating antibodies
that are antigen specific.
And so they bind to and deposit
lots of antigen in the GCs,
and you can see this by
imaging the monkey lymph
nodes after the second dose.
You see there are
lots of antigen.
Now, when there's lots of
prey, they're not so good.
Predators can also
survive and evolve.
And so antibodies that bind
more weakly initially to regions
called subdominant that are not
mutated in Omicron can evolve.
And this effect is
further amplified
because these
antibodies that bind
to these immunodominant regions
can enter GCs, bind to them,
thereby masking
them and effectively
elevating the amount of these
subdominant regions that
are present.
So now the memory cells that
bind to these regions that
are not mutated in Omicron
that you've created
are rapidly expanded
and become antibodies
that are protected
against SARS-COV-2--
against the Omicron strain.
Similar mechanisms are at
play for our demonstration
that instead of giving
the vaccine, as just one
shot as a bolus, as
is normally done,
if you distribute the
same amount of antigen
over seven days in seven doses
over an escalating pattern, then
you get lots more antigen than
just the bolus, which leads
to a more potent antibody
response compared
to the bolus in mice.
And very recently, this
has been recapitulated
in a human clinical trial.
So from computational biophysics
to the clinic, if you like.
But seven days, seven
shots is not practical.
And so by better understanding
these feedback loops,
we have now designed
a two-shot regime that
puts a lot of antigen
on the surface in the GC
and you get potent responses,
just like the seven day one.
We are now trying to explore
how similar mechanisms can
be leveraged such that antibody
therapy can potentially
lead to a cure for HIV.
And finally, let me note
that we have computationally
designed nanoparticles
that display spikes
of diverse sarbecoviruses,
the virus family from which
SARS-COV-2 is derived.
And this is the potency
of the antibody response
in mice to several
sarbecoviruses
that may spill
over from animals.
And you see that our
computationally designed one
is more potent than the
state of the art nanoparticle
and much better than the
bivalent vaccine that many of us
have taken.
Thank you for listening.
And our next speaker will
be Professor Jessica Stark.
[APPLAUSE]
Thanks and good
morning, everyone.
It's a privilege to be here and
to share our group's perspective
on understanding and
engineering immune responses.
I want to start by first
affirming your choice
to come to this breakout
session because we really
are in a very exciting
time for immunology
in the midst of an immunological
revolution in medicine.
We now understand that there are
a wide variety of human diseases
and conditions that can
be effectively treated
by harnessing the immune system.
As we've heard from
Arup and Facundo,
we've been able to use
vaccination to prevent or even
eliminate infectious
disease by teaching
the immune system to recognize
and respond to pathogens.
In cancer, we've
been able to use
immunotherapies to elicit
decades long remission
from disease.
Really, the closest we've
come to a cancer cure.
And nevertheless,
we remain limited
in the kinds of conditions
that we can treat
and the number of patients that
we can help with immunotherapy.
And so we still
need new paradigms
to harness the immune
system if we're
going to realize the full
potential of immunology
for human health.
We see an opportunity to target
cell surface sugars called
glycans as an untapped axis of
regulation in the immune system.
Every cell in your body, and
in fact, every cell on Earth
is coated with a thick
layer of glycans,
and these glycans exert
influence in nearly
every immunological process.
Glycans can directly control
immune cell function.
They can activate or
inhibit immune cells
by binding to receptors
on immune cell surfaces.
They control how immune cells
move throughout the body.
They can help immune cells
exit the blood and home
to sites of inflammation
or infection in tissues,
helping your immune system
locate and eradicate disease
throughout the body.
Glycans play important
roles in innate immunity,
where they help your
immune system do
one of its most important jobs,
which is to distinguish self
and non-self, telling
the difference
between host and pathogen.
And they can further influence
adaptive immune responses,
for example, by
helping determine
whether an antibody will
elicit a pro-inflammatory
or an anti-inflammatory
immune program.
Despite all of these
examples, however,
of how glycans play important
roles in the immune system,
we have lacked the
tools to comprehensively
study this biology and to
target glycans therapeutically.
And these are the
gaps that my lab,
which opened here at MIT about
a year ago, seek to address.
We are building
platform technologies
to help us fully understand
how glycans regulate
immune responses,
and to translate
these biological
insights into the design
of new kinds of immunotherapy.
I want to share
an example of how
we've been able to target
glycans for cancer immunotherapy
that builds upon recent
fundamental and translational
advances in the field.
In order to grow and
spread throughout the body,
cancer cells upregulate
molecules on their cell surfaces
that bind to inhibitory
receptors on immune cells.
By engaging these so-called
immune checkpoints,
the cancer cells can put the
brakes on the immune response,
allowing them to evade
normal immune surveillance.
However, if you block
these immune checkpoints
with something like a
monoclonal antibody,
we can-- there's the potential
to reprogram and reactivate
the immune system to sense
and respond to cancer.
These checkpoint
blockade immunotherapies
were tested initially
in metastatic melanoma,
an incredibly aggressive
form of cancer.
And in one of these
trials, patients
who received a combination of
therapies targeting the PD1
and CTLA 4 immune
checkpoints, about 30% of them
mounted a robust immune
response to their cancer
that basically stopped
the disease in its tracks.
These patients diseases
had not progressed
in over a decade following
the start of treatment.
And in light of the
success in melanoma,
checkpoint blockade
immunotherapies
have now been tested in a
variety of other cancers
and are now approved to treat
about 50% of cancer patients.
However, across all cancer
patients, only about 20%
benefit from these therapies.
And so now the question is, why?
How are cancer cells able
to evade immune surveillance
and resist immunotherapy
in most cancer patients?
And that's where glycans
come back into the story.
It turns out that cancer cells
dramatically alter their cell
surface glycosylation.
This is a hallmark
of cancer that's
been observed in many
different tumor types
and across many different
patient cohorts.
And we now understand that
one of the reasons that cancer
cells remodel their
surfaces in this way
is to engage a class
of inhibitory receptors
on immune cells that
are called lectins.
So when lectins bind to these
glycans on cancer cell surfaces,
they trigger inhibitory
signaling pathways
that shut down immune responses
through the exact same mechanism
that occurs when the established
immune checkpoint receptor, PD1,
binds to its ligand, PL1.
And while we have a litany of
drugs that target the PD1/ PDL1
immune checkpoint, we have no
approved therapies to target
these glyco immune checkpoints.
We recently developed
a new kind of molecule
that makes it possible
to target glycans
for cancer immunotherapy.
These molecules we're calling
antibody lectin chimeras
or AbLecs, and
they're bispecific.
One half of the molecule
is an antibody domain
that can target specific
cells in the body,
for example, cancer cells.
The other half of
the molecule is
what we call a decoy receptor.
It's the binding domain
from the lectin receptor
we want to target, which
serves to bind and block
the same kinds of glycans
that would otherwise
inhibit immune responses.
And so our hypothesis
was that with AbLecs,
we could block these
glyco immune checkpoints
and elicit more potent
anti-cancer immune responses.
We tested these
therapies initially
in vitro with primary human
immune cells like macrophages
and NK cells.
These are two different
kinds of innate immune cells
that we could imagine activating
with our AbLec therapy.
And you can see that for both
macrophages and NK cells,
treatment with our AbLecs
elicited more potent cancer
cell killing compared to a
monoclonal antibody control.
And in vivo, in a humanized
model of metastatic cancer,
we observed that animals treated
with our AbLec immunotherapy
exhibited reduced tumor burden
and compared to animals treated
with the control molecule.
With this proof of concept, we
launched a new biotechnology
startup called Velora
Therapeutics that aims
to bring AbLecs to patients.
The exciting thing about
the AbLecs platform
is that it's modular.
You can imagine mixing and
matching different antibody
and lectin domains
to enable a variety
of different therapeutic
mechanisms of action.
And Velora is leveraging
this modularity
to develop therapies--
AbLec immunotherapies
for indications
in oncology and immunology.
But this is just the beginning.
Glycans play pivotal
roles in the immune system
and are really attractive
therapeutic targets.
My group is developing
the platform technologies
we'll need to explore this
emerging biological frontier
and enable both fundamental
and translational advances.
So with that, I'd like
to thank my lab who
made this work possible.
I look forward to
taking your questions,
and I'd like to invite our next
speaker, Professor Hari Wong,
to the stage.
[APPLAUSE]
It's great to be here.
I want to talk to you
a little bit about some
of the complexities
that exist in studying
the immune response,
why they exist,
and how our group has been
developing technologies
and implementing technologies
to try to overcome them.
We spend a lot of time
thinking about how
the immune system operates
in its native environment.
So not in a dish, not in
blood, but actually where it
needs to function in tissues.
And the reason we do this
is at least threefold.
One is that the immune
system is a system of cells.
It's not one cell.
It's multiple cells.
And these cells typically form
multicellular units of control.
They assemble in
space and in time
into intricate structures that
do things that no one cell
type can do on its own.
You get emergent dynamics,
emergent functions,
and it's very hard to
reconstruct these units
in vitro settings.
The second point
I want to make is
that the immune cells
within these units
are communicating dynamically.
They're engaged in physical
interactions with one another.
They secrete molecules
over short distances
and over long distances.
And the communication is always
evolving over time and in space.
And lastly, the
point I want to make
is that the most interesting
aspects of the immune response,
at least in my mind,
both in physiological and
pathophysiological
settings, are not mediated
by the bulk of the cells.
They're typically mediated
by rare outlier cells
on the ends of the distribution.
I'm not sure how to go back.
There we go.
So let me walk you
through technologies
that my lab has been
developing to try
to overcome each and every
one of these three challenges.
We typically take an
imaging-based approach
to really be able
to resolve and study
these cells in their
native environment.
So what you're looking
at here on the left
is a lymph node that lies
downstream of the kidney.
I want to direct your attention
to this inset over here.
We've developed multiplexed
imaging technologies
using antibodies that now
allow us to visualize anywhere
between 20 and 60 proteins
directly in tissues where
the immune response
is occurring.
What you're looking at
here on the zoomed in inset
is a multicellular unit that's
controlling T cell responses.
You don't have to worry about
what all the colors are.
The point I want to make is that
there are innate immune cells
here, like Stephanie introduced
earlier, that are initializing
T cell responses.
There are these
green cells here.
These are regulatory T cells.
There's not one of them,
there's many of them.
These are cells that are trying
to dampen the immune response.
And there are conventional
CD4 and CD8 T cells here.
These are cells that
are trying to promote
inflammation and promote
the immune response.
And if you try to study any
one of these cell types alone,
you can't really figure
out what's going on.
It is the integrated
behavior of all three
of these cell types
in space and in time
that is predictive of how the
immune response will behave.
So we can address this.
We can identify the
units of control.
relevant cellular players.
What about the
communication aspect?
Well, we've now developed
ways to preserve tissues
in a manner that
allows us to estimate
length scales of
communications between cells.
Let me walk you
through what I mean.
Here, outlined in white,
these are two endogenously
activated conventional T cells.
They are producing a
molecule called IL2.
This is a cytokine
that's shown in red.
This cytokine will get
secreted and diffused in space.
These surrounding
cells in magenta,
these are regulatory T cells.
Like I said earlier,
these are cells
that try to dampen
the immune response.
And in green, we're reading out
signaling downstream of the IL2
receptor by measuring the
phosphorylation of STAT5,
a transcription factor.
If we look to the right, what I
want you to take away from this
is that there is a
gradient of green,
and it's largely in the
regulatory cells here.
And by reading
out this gradient,
we can infer how
far the cytokine
must be diffusing in space.
And this is important
because cells
that are positioned here
close to the producing cells
are going to see a very
different concentration
of this cytokine than cells that
are positioned way back here.
And therefore, cells that
are positioned closest
to the producing cells are
going to adopt a different fate
than cells that are
positioned way back here.
So this is a source
of variation,
how the immune system generates
heterogeneity in its responses
during a dynamic
immune response.
This is all well and
good, but it's fixed.
These are static images, and
the immune system is not static.
It's dynamic.
As I told you earlier,
communication is dynamic.
So we've also invested in
technologies that allow us
to peer inside of living
organisms-- this is a mouse--
and actually watch the
immune system in real time.
What we've done here
is a small surgery
in a mouse under anesthetic.
And we're looking
behind the knee.
It's the popliteal lymph node.
And we're peering in and we're
watching the immune response
in real time.
It doesn't really matter
what's going on here.
But the cells in magenta, these
are the regulatory T cells
that are dampening
the immune response.
They're not fixed.
They're zipping all over
the place in real time.
And the cells in magenta,
these are conventional cells--
conventional T cells
that are trying
to initiate an immune response.
So there's a
complex choreography
that's always going on in our
bodies at any moment in time.
Now, what about the
last point I raised,
how can we identify
the rare cells
that are doing the most
interesting biology?
The technologies I showed
you so far are fantastic,
but they're limited in the depth
of tissue that we can image.
We can't look at enough
volume with those methods.
So we have to take a
different approach.
And the approach we use is
an optical clearing method
that allows us to treat
our organs of interest
with a chemical concoction
that homogenizes
its refractive index.
What that means, practically,
is that it turns our tissues
from completely opaque
to clear and transparent.
And from a microscopy
perspective,
this allows us to now
image the entire organ
in three dimensional space
without any light scattering.
Here's an example of that.
This is a mouse uterus
that's been cleared.
And we're going to
zoom in the cyan,
these are the uterine glands.
And what we can find are
these rare clusters of T cells
here in magenta that are
wrapped around the glands doing
some type of important function.
That's very distinct from
the rest of the cells
in the entire organ.
These are the rare cells in
the tail of the distribution,
and they're
functioning as a unit.
But again, it's very different
behavior than the rest--
the bulk of the distribution.
So I've shown you
the technologies that
allow us to overcome
the challenges,
But, it's not good enough
for us to just take
pretty pictures and movies.
We need to combine these
experimental methods
with computational
approaches that
allow us to extract as
much useful information
from our movies and
images as possible.
So for that, we've invested in
computational algorithms that
allow us to define the
boundaries of individual cells
and reconstruct our
organs of interest
with all of their features
and protein expressions.
We can do this in the computer.
So what you're
looking at here is
a computational
reconstruction of a lymph node
where every dot represents
an individual cell.
And we can analyze
specific regions
of space, which is important
because different reactions
occur in different places.
We can use these
measurements to then conduct
a variety of quantitative types
of analyses, similar to what
you would do in data science.
We can take these
measurements and parameterize
mechanistic models using
systems of equations
to simulate how different
aspects of the immune response
will proceed.
We can make predictions.
And then, we can go back
in to model organisms
and test those predictions
using genetic or environmental
manipulations.
And through these
types of technologies,
I think, this is how we'll
get a better understanding
of fundamental operations of the
immune system and understanding
how different
therapeutics actually
work in their sites of action--
in their tissue sites
of action, that is.
So with that, thank you,
and I'm pleased to introduce
our next speaker,
Professor Michael Birnbaum.
[APPLAUSE]
All right, thanks to Hari, and
it's good to see you all today.
So in my lab, we want to know--
we want to be able to
see what T cells see.
So to give you a
graphic I pulled
from a recent review, when a T
cell is looking for cells that
are infected or otherwise
transformed by cancer,
the way that this
actually works is
that every T cell has its own
protein sensor called a T cell
receptor, which
takes recognition
of what we call an HLA,
or an MHC molecule, which
presents a short peptide.
And these MHC peptide
complexes present
a census in terms of what the
cell is expressing at any time.
So when a cell is expressing
just the normal proteins that
make a hepatocyte a hepatocyte
or a lung cell a lung cell,
then T cells leave the cell
to go about its business.
When a cell is
otherwise altered,
so whether it has an
intracellular bacteria infected
by a virus or transformed in
terms of becoming a cancer,
then the peptides are
different and the T cell
is able to recognize it
through the T cell receptor
and then kill the cell,
among other immune functions.
So for me, one of the
fascinating things about this
is that this actually serves as
numerically an interesting thing
to think about.
So in each one of
us, and my math
could be off by a factor
of 10 in any direction,
but there's roughly, say, around
50 to 100 million unique T cell
specificities floating
around in each one of you
at any given time
out of a possible 10
to the 15 possibilities for T
cells for just combinatorially
for the receptor.
And these are recognizing
these peptide MHC complexes
where in terms of what you
theoretically could have in you,
again, math is back
of the envelope,
it's something around a
trillion possibilities in terms
of peptide and MHC
combinations in any one of us.
They're not all present
at any given time,
but there's no way
for the immune system
to know which one of these you
may encounter during your life
and which ones are
purely theoretical.
This is all happening
in a system that
has to be incredibly sensitive--
because if you're infected,
you have to be able to recognize
it-- at what we would consider
incredibly low affinities.
So interactions that occur
at body temperature that
lasts for maybe about a second.
And if you do the bookkeeping,
it turns out that each one
of these T cell specificities
would have to be able
to recognize on the order of
100,000 different antigens
in order for the
books to balance here.
Otherwise, you could
have, on one hand,
for example, a pathogen, which
is able to completely evade
detection.
And somehow, on
the other hand, you
have to be able to
do this in a way
where you still have
enough specificity
that the recognition of a
virus doesn't inadvertently
lead to the recognition of any
of your own healthy tissues.
So your immune system
is doing this every day,
all day, for each of us, very
nearly perfectly all the time.
And I really want to know
how this is able to work,
and able to work in a way
that is so specific in order
to allow this to happen.
Understanding this
specificity is going
to help us understand biology.
It's going to help us create a
next generation of therapeutics.
And increasingly, especially
with the explosion
of progress in AI, the
ability to make better
computational tools.
So for all of this, though,
what we remain limited in
is the number of
examples which we've
been able to really observe.
So this is a field,
understanding
how T cell receptors
recognize peptidomimetics
that has really been in progress
as long as I've been alive.
But we've studied, really,
relatively small numbers
of examples.
So in order to be
able to make progress,
we're going to be able to--
need to be able to
look at much more data.
So in my lab, we want to
develop better tools in order
to be able to understand this.
And so we think quite
broadly about how to do this.
We use a variety of approaches.
I want to tell you just
for a couple of minutes
about one of them that
we've done in our lab.
And what we've actually done is
repurposed a common laboratory
tool, which itself is
a repurposed virus.
So we work in our lab
with lentiviruses,
which is a heavily
engineered for laboratory use
safe version of a virus
that started as HIV,
of all things, where we
re-engineered it to say, OK,
what if we take these
lentiviruses, which are commonly
engineered to infect any
cell that you might want
into in the lab, and have them
infect only T cells by putting
peptide-MHC molecules
on their surface?
So in this way, you
create a virus that
is specific for a given T cell.
And lentiviruses are
quite unique because what
they are able to do as
part of their life cycle
is leave a permanent
record of their infection
into a cell's genome by
incorporating the viral genome
into the host genome.
So our thought was, if we put
a peptide-MHC on the virus,
we could have a system where
we have infection mediated
by the molecule on the
outside with a record kept
by the molecule on the inside.
And if we're able to build
large collections or libraries
of these as a tool, which
is common in biotechnology,
we could use this as a recorder
of this peptide-MHC T cell
receptor interaction.
So we set about doing
this a few years ago.
And we were able to show
that this actually works.
So you could create a
virus with a peptide MHC.
If that virus
encounters any cell that
doesn't have the right
T cell specificity,
even one that's close
but not exactly right,
you see little to no infection,
so this is a virus encoding
cells to turn green--
very few green.
Where if you have a virus
that does have that match,
you get robust
infection of cells.
So we created a
tool, a method which
we call RAPTR, Receptor
Antigen Pairing by Targeted
Retroviruses, we were
able to create libraries
of these viruses, mix
them with T cells,
and then, allow for the
mixtures to only infect
the right combination.
So the mixture of viruses only
infecting the correct T cell.
We're able to then isolate them
and use single cell sequencing
in order to get
the information out
of what the T cell receptor
is and what the antigen
is on a many versus many basis.
So something that we
are trying to approach
the scales of how the immune
system itself would work.
And we were able to show
that this is able to work.
That you're able
to identify, even
in a complex mixture of viruses
with different peptides,
once you sequenced the viruses
that are able to infect,
you're able to get the
right answer back out.
So this is a tool we're
very excited about.
But a little
belatedly, we realized
that if you're able to
infect a cell in order
to deliver a genetic
cargo for something
like a fluorescent
protein or a barcode,
that you should
also be able to do
it to deliver some type of
therapeutic cargo as well.
And so we're in the process
of exploring this, too.
And the way that we're
thinking about this
is in terms of different
types of cell therapies.
So it turns out that
your immune system
can mount a defense against
tumors all on its own.
We call these tumor
infiltrating lymphocytes.
This is something that often
is not effective on its own,
but is something
where just recently,
in the past few
months, there's been
a clinically-approved therapy
where these cells are taken out
of the tumor, grown
back up, and reinfused.
So this is great because it's
recognizing exactly what happens
to be in your tumor.
But is torturously
complex to make.
Correspondingly, we're
able to engineer T cells
through something called
a CAR-T therapy where
we're able to point T cells
in the right direction.
But this is also complex
to make and only works
for certain cancers.
So what we've done in our lab
is created the same viral system
where now, instead of
delivering a barcode,
we're able to deliver
therapeutic cargoes to the T
cells.
So we're able to, even in
vivo, infuse a virus which
is able to find
the right T cell,
reprogram it genetically to
become more immuno activated
in one way or the other, and
then able to extend lifespan
in mice.
So we're in the process
of exploring both
of these aspects in our lab.
And this is where the
collaborative and big picture
thinking of MIT
really comes in handy.
So on one hand, we
are a part of and I'm
the leader of a team funded
through a mechanism called
a Cancer Grand
Challenge in order
to truly try to
generalize the predictions
of peptide-MHC molecules
and T cell receptors
to design these receptors.
So this is a team of
immunologists, clinicians,
engineers all working together.
So several of which
at MIT, but also
for individuals around
the world, to really try
to address one of these
large problems in immunology,
how can we make
these predictions?
And then, we're also working
to take our targeted viruses
and turned them into a
drug in a company called
Colonial Therapeutics where
we were able to show really
promising data that's
been talked about
at meetings, both in
terms of mice and monkeys,
with the hopes of starting a
clinical trial in the next year
or so.
So thanks for your attention.
I believe we're moving
to a Q&A session.
[APPLAUSE]
Please join me in thanking
the speakers again,
and I would like to invite
all the speakers on stage.
[APPLAUSE]
And this will be
an open Q&A panel.
So if you have questions,
please raise your hand
and we will call on you.
But I would like to
start off this panel
by getting each one of your
takes on why immunology at MIT
is different to normal
immunology departments that
are typically housed
in medical schools
and are very embedded
into clinical practice.
Facundo.
Well, MIT is a unique in
ecological environment where
you get direct access to
engineering and computation that
doesn't occur, generally, in a
normal immunology department.
So I always train
in institutions
that they were kind of having a
large breadth of collaboration.
And particularly
for me, I can talk,
it's rather a unique opportunity
to be close people to do things
that I am not an expert on.
Well, as Harry mentioned,
the immune system
is a stochastic dynamical
system with many participating
components in a fluctuating
environment that work together
to ultimately give you
a coherent response,
either to pathogens
or to cancer,
or sometimes, when it's
[INAUDIBLE] regulated
to yourself.
And if we have to
understand that,
we have to bring together
tools from basic biology,
from engineering, computation,
and systems design
in order to really
make that happen.
And then, translate that
into therapies and vaccines,
et cetera.
And MIT has all
these components,
from basic biology to
systems engineering.
And it's an inherently
collaborative place
and a collegial place.
And so that brings all of
these together in a mix
that I really have not
seen in other places.
And I'm the old man
here, so I can tell you
I've seen more places.
I think immunology is a field
that really needs technology.
We've seen huge advances
in our understanding
of immunobiology through the
advent of genetics, machine
learning, computational
approaches.
And these are things that
MIT is really good at.
And especially in
my field, we really
need technology development
to enable new discoveries.
So I think that's a
unique feature of doing.
Immunology immunology at MIT.
We're at the cutting
edge of technology
that we can apply to
our biological problems.
I don't have too much to add
we haven't already heard.
I'll just say, I don't know if
my lab could operate in the way
it does at many other
places in the world..
Because we need to
be able to bridge
experimental immunologists with
computationalists and hybrids
that can do both,
and having access
to those types of trainees.
That's very uncommon that want
to do all three of those things
at most other institutions.
So this, I think, is especially
helpful for immunology
because it seems to be a
property of MIT in general.
It's pretty unique to combine
fearlessness and rigor
in a combination
that actually works.
Like the ability to try
what might seem like it just
definitely isn't going
to work, or something
that might seem a
little bit crazy.
But do it in a way where
substance is never lost.
Where you make
sure that we really
are going to do this
to make the impact,
not just to make the
flash in the pan.
And I think that, in immunology,
everything my colleague
said about technology
and connections
with each other, all
of that's important.
But I think that everybody
from the sophomores and juniors
in my lab who have
started projects
through to the graduate
students, the postdocs,
and my faculty colleagues
to combine fearlessness
and rigor in one setting
is a special thing.
Question over here.
OK, I have two questions.
You will get them.
I was a cheerleader.
I can do this.
Two questions.
The first, is in
the earlier session
they spoke about how difficult
it was to move from a mouse
model to a human model.
And I'm wondering if that is
less difficult than the work
that you do, because it
appears you're translating it
faster and more readily?
So that's question one.
Question two is, I think, for
professors Wong and Birnbaum is
my understanding is
that solid tumors are
harder to treat these days.
And is your work directed
towards solid tumor treatment?
So that's my question.
OK, maybe Facundo, you can
start on the first question.
Those are excellent questions.
And there is no perfect model.
And every model helps
to address a problem.
A human clinical trial
will take tens of millions
of dollars and
several years to plan.
What we can take the
advantage is in the mouse,
for example, is
to iterate things
extremely, extremely fast.
And then, narrow them down
to be then tested in humans.
And the technologies that
we do in the lab that
is trying to make this
mouse more similar to humans
are at the tip of this because
with all the predictions,
and there is an experiment
ongoing there, all the mouse
experiments that we and
many others have done,
they have now done the
human experiment and show
that the predictions
were absolutely right.
So again.
There is no perfect model.
We will not know-- everything
will not work the same,
but at least at a very
diminished cost and time,
we can operate in the
mouse as a credible model.
And I think maybe
to add specifically
because I was in the session.
The immune system,
I think, translates
better because we're looking
at systematic changes and not
a single molecule
in a pathway that
has to be conserved
between mouse and human.
And for the second
question, Michael,.
Sorry.
So for the second question,
in terms of translation,
it's a little bit of both.
So the slide I showed
towards the end
is in models of melanoma.
And so we're interested--
which is a place where these
tumor infiltrating lymphocytes
has been clinically approved
could stand to be improved.
And so we really--
even for mouse
versus human, it's
really every tool for a job.
So some of the questions we
ask in terms of solid tumors
where immunotherapy
has been successful,
some were working in
things like glioblastoma
where progress or solid
tumors has been slower.
Some of it's in liquid
tumors because that's where
some of the clinical data is.
And so we do our best
to match depending
on what we're working on.
Question over here
and then back there.
Thank you.
Thank you for the whole panel.
Fantastic talk.
So I have two
questions, actually,
one for the whole panel.
What do you think
about mRNA technology?
What are the advantages
you see currently,
or do you see any
limitations for your work
you are doing in immunology for
vaccines or maybe therapeutics?
Second question is for Jessica.
Love the talk.
Antibody lectins.
Curious to see how
you are going to apply
this technology from oncology
to autoimmune diseases.
Thank you.
So I'll start with the
question directed at me.
Thanks for that.
Yeah, so these applications
and indications
in autoimmunity and immunology
that we are going after.
In these indications,
there's biological rationale
for why you might want to target
a glyco immune checkpoint.
So for example, in
autoimmunity, while in cancer we
block glyco immune checkpoints
to potentiate immune responses,
in the context of
autoimmunity, you
could imagine engaging those
same immune checkpoints
to elicit tolerance
in the same way
that tumors tolerize the
immune system to themselves.
In the setting of
fibrosis, there's
a glyco immune checkpoint
that allows fibrosis
to continue unchecked that we
are thinking about targeting
to help slow that process down.
But all of this builds
upon fundamental biology,
fundamental life science
research that has shed light
on these biological mechanisms.
Let's move over there.
Good afternoon, everyone.
Stepping back a little
bit, I was impressed with--
across a number of
your presentations
about just how dynamic
the immune system is.
Just the scale, the quantities
that you're dealing with
are just astronomical.
And then, on top of
it, you have people.
And so I was also impressed
by the slide showing
if you could give seven doses
days with increasing amounts
and you get a really tremendous
response, but impractical.
And I really want to target or
push on that in practicality.
I work with a state
agency that really fights
infectious disease,
and I want to push back
on that in practicality.
What can we do to make
that practical or suggest?
That's it.
No, I'm happy to address that.
I mentioned that a bit too
quickly in a brief talk
like this.
But we have now, in a
very recent publication,
which I flashed briefly,
our understanding that
is a practical challenge.
We have now, by understanding
the mechanisms better,
been able to design a system
which has only two shots, which
takes it much closer to
practicality because two shots
you can do.
And so that's now slated
to go to clinical trial.
The seven shot was already
done, as I showed in humans.
But that's where we
are going with this
is to do the two shot
regimen because that does
just as well, at least in mice.
Question over there.
Thank you for the
exciting talks.
I'd like to follow-up a little
bit on that question on probably
a more fundamental question.
In the seven doses,
I can understand
that you're saying the
subdominant epitopes
will increase, but
viruses are equally smart.
I'm just wondering what
if the previous epitope
starts dominating again
because viruses can mutate?
You're trying to
decrease one epitope
and increase the epitope.
The second question following
up with Harry's talk,
he can actually now visualize
and quantify the timelines.
Is it possible to--
I don't know how different
B cell kinetics and T cell
kinetics are, but is it even
possible to get both of them
in the same timeline so
that you can actually
get both arms to
have a good response?
So your questions are excellent.
And to the part
that I will address
is the following that I
mentioned very briefly
that we are trying to see
how to leverage this thinking
into a potential cure for HIV.
And what we are finding
there is that when
people have suppressed
virus, but some amount there,
then this may be--
this is still very
early days, but it
may be happening that one by
one, the epitopes get masked
and then you get more and more
responses and so on and so forth
while the virus is dormant.
And so you can then create a
net of antibodies that target
different regions or epitopes.
And as a consequence,
when the virus starts
to come up, the escaping that
net becomes very difficult.
And so that's the part that--
I might also slightly
comment on the second part
of your question.
In the extended
dose delivery things
that we have done, in
order to optimize it
to two doses such that it
becomes closer to practicality,
one of the things
that happens is
that you sync the
T cell and antibody
response or B-cell
responses to come more
within symphony-- asynchrony.
And if you don't give
the adjuvant also
in an extended
way, then you won't
let that to happen
because that's
how you prime the innate immune
cells, the dendritic cells,
so that later on they are
more efficient with the T cell
dynamics.
So there has to be
synchrony between those two
get the best responses.
Now, how best to image them
and understand them better,
I'll leave to Harry.
I'll just say that we and
others have definitely
shown that you can--
similar to Arup's
work with B cells.
If you manipulate the dynamics
of what the T cells are seeing,
you can get better
T cell responses.
And we know that you can't
get great B cell responses
without great T cell responses.
And I think it's just--
we need to put it together
and actually--
Facundo and Arup should probably
work on something like that.
I mean, that is an
excellent question.
Antigen or virus is the
fuel of this reaction.
If that stays for a
long time, this reaction
goes on for a long time.
And it goes on from B
and T cell together.
Arup [INAUDIBLE] show that in
these lymph nodes, when you just
give one dose, you
don't get antigen there
for a prolonged period of time.
So answering to your
T cell question, that
is very important, if
you have the fuel that
is the antigen there, you
will keep the B cells and T
cells cooperating for
a prolonged period.
I made a comment
with regards to--
we know so little
about vaccines.
All we know is empirical.
And even when we are giving a
prime and a boost in humans,
that has never been
experimentally proved.
The time between the
prime and the boost
is something that has been
determined empirically.
What we are trying to
do and what people do
is really understand the
mechanisms for this in a way
that we may alter this
prime and boost to get
a more effective response.
Exactly.
Perfect.
I would have one
last question I'm
going to ask you guys
to answer really,
really quickly in
the interest of time
is, what is the next
big frontier each of you
want to tackle?
I'm going to start with
Michael for fairness.
[LAUGHTER]
It's going to be the
integration with AI.
Can you elaborate a little bit?
Yeah.
Stephanie said quick, and
there's a timer counting down.
We can mingle after [INAUDIBLE].
So in my world, it's being able
to make general predictions
and general designs
in the same way
that you can go to ChatGPT and
make a picture of anything.
Right now, the predictions
are good, but very narrow,
very, very narrow.
So would be the equivalent
of having a ChatGPT that's
really great at making
pictures of ducks,
and you ask it to make
you a picture of a tiger
and it gives you a duck.
So I think that getting to the
point where some of these tools
are going to be generally useful
is something that we're really
excited to work towards.
On my end, I think there are
certainly biological questions
we're very interested in.
But on the
technological side, you
might have noticed that a lot
of the dynamic live imaging
that we're able to
do, we're limited
in how many cell types
or readouts of function
that we can look at.
And there are
practical limitations.
So I think something we're
really excited about and trying
to think about is how can we
visualize many, many more cell
types and their states in
real time in living organisms?
And that's not a
trivial challenge,
but we have some ideas.
We are really focused on
developing technologies that
will allow us to fit
glycans into the broader
picture of immunology
and immune responses.
And we need to understand this
biology at a systems level
and how it connects to
all of the other aspects
of molecular and cellular
immunology that we understand.
I think those kinds of
fundamental advances
are going to be necessary
to translate this biology
and to get to clinical advances.
In addition to the
things I talked about,
one of the things that we are
launching in our group right
now is a program to
really understand
how the innate and adaptive
immune systems are integrated
because very little or much
less is understood about that
than anyone by themselves.
And I believe that will
get us to really start
understanding
questions like what
determines the memory
of an immune response.
Why is it longer for one
pathogen versus another?
Why is it longer, perhaps,
in protein antigens
versus mRNA vaccines?
And so that's one of the
new frontiers that in our--
new frontiers and our
group is to bring that
into innate and adaptive
immunity together.
Yeah, I think the connection
between quantitative immunology
that is very recent, and
then translating that
into computational
or AI models is
something that is
extremely exciting
and is going to be
transformational
over the next 10 to 20 years.
I mean, we still
know very little.
We know we can
generate antigens.
generate antibodies.
We can produce structures, but
we cannot predict for better
molecule binding.
I think that the
next 10 to 20 years
are going to be transformational
in that respect.
Awesome.
With that, I would like to thank
the speakers and the panelists,
and particularly you
for your attention.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]