So welcome, everyone, to the
MIT Energy Initiatives Fall
Colloquium.
My name is Bill Green.
I'm the director of the
MIT Energy Initiative.
And this is our biggest
talk of the fall,
and it's part of
our ongoing series,
Advancing the Energy Transition.
Today, we're going to hear from
Joseph DeCarolis from the US
Energy Information
Administration.
He's the leader of that
important administration.
Maybe I'll just
talk for a minute,
though, about the MIT
Energy Initiative.
MIT Energy Initiative is the
longest established energy
hub at MIT, and we support
a lot of the energy
research on campus.
Also, quite a lot of
the policy research
on campus and economic
research related to energy.
We also run the energy
minor for undergraduates
and a variety of other
educational programs related
to energy.
And with the help
from our sponsors,
we fund quite a lot of
important energy research
throughout the campus.
In addition, we
convene discussions
like this one, where
we bring in speakers
who can address different
aspects of the energy transition
and ultimately help to convene
the conversations that will help
to build consensus for solutions
so we can work together to try
to solve the climate problem.
Today's speaker, Dr.
DeCarolis, was formerly
a professor at North
Carolina State University,
and I guess probably
he'll return there
after he leaves the EIA.
He's doing his
public service now
as leading the nation's
foremost agency
for collecting and distributing
high quality data related
to energy and one of the
best data sets in the world.
In his own research,
he also works
a lot on software
and modeling methods,
since a key part of
the energy transition
is trying to figure
out where we're going
and what the options
are for the roads ahead.
And as I think he'll
probably talk about today,
that can be a challenging task.
And hence his title, stay humble
and prepare for surprises.
No matter what we
project in the computer,
it's probably not going
to go exactly that way.
So without further
ado, Dr. DeCarolis.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
Well, Bill, thanks very
much for the introduction.
And yes, it's quite
an honor to be here.
And yes, I did put
the bottom line up
front right there in the
title, that as we think
about the energy
transition, we do
need to stay humble and
prepare for surprises.
So this talk
combines my insights
as a longtime energy
modeler in academia,
as well as my experience as
an administrator at the Energy
Information Administration.
So in this talk, I'm not
going to tell you what I think
or what EIA thinks is going to
happen with regard to the energy
transition.
Instead, I want to focus a level
higher and talk about the models
that we rely on to
make these projections.
So I'm going to start
by setting the stage
and we're going to look
at some historical data
to understand the current
state of the transition.
And then I want to talk about
the practice of modeling.
And there's three components
to this I want to talk about.
One is just the fact that these
models are not crystal balls,
but they do-- they
can serve a purpose.
And I want to talk about what
I think the utility of using
these models are.
Second, using EIA an example,
I want to talk about some
of the developments over
the last couple of decades
that took us by surprise and
how our projections tracked
those developments over time.
And third is I want to outline
some of the efforts we're
undertaking in our
long-term modeling program
to better prepare us for
uncertainty about the future.
And we want to
develop the ability
to analyze a wider range
of future scenarios.
There's a lot of
analyzes out there
that explore different aspects
of the energy transition.
Whether you're a modeler
or not, though, I
hope that this talk gives
you some perspective
on how to interpret
some of those studies.
So before I get
into all of that,
though, I did want to give
just a very brief introduction
to EIA.
We are the statistical
and analytic agency
within the Department of Energy.
So there's 13 principal
statistical agencies
across the federal government.
Again, we're a statistical
agency embedded in DOE.
Our mission is to collect,
analyze, and disseminate
independent and impartial energy
information for our stakeholders
so that they can make
better decisions.
You see the word independence
here a couple times.
That's very important to us.
So when we publish
data or a report,
we don't have to seek the
formal approval of anyone
else in the federal government.
And that independence
is very important to us,
because it means that we
can focus on doing our work
and providing the best
information we possibly can.
The other thing I
wanted to mention
is that we're also
policy neutral.
So we're not in the business
of developing policy, advising
on policy, but we
do analyze policy.
Policy is part of
the energy system.
And so we do want
to be in a position
to be able to analyze policy.
So when I talk about
the energy transition
or reducing carbon
emissions, as administrator,
I'm not advocating for
any particular position.
But again, I'm looking at it
from an analytic perspective
and what we need to do to
understand where the energy
system is headed.
We do maintain a comprehensive
energy statistics program.
So by virtue of being
a statistical agency,
we're vested with the
authority by Congress
to collect data from
the energy industry.
And so we do have a
comprehensive survey program.
Our energy supply survey
program represents
our largest operational area.
And we produce hundreds of
reports that rely on that data
that we're collecting
from the supply side.
On the demand
side, we have three
large multi-year
consumption surveys
that cover commercial
buildings, residential homes,
as well as the
manufacturing sector.
I'm going to breeze
through these very quickly,
but I just want to give you a
sense of the comprehensiveness
of the data that we collect.
So this is just looking at
electricity, electricity data.
It starts with natural
resources on the right hand
side, the primary energy.
We look at electricity
generation and markets,
and then, ultimately,
the sale of electricity
to end use customers.
We collect a lot of
electricity data.
Much of it is on
an hourly basis.
So this is a really
high volume of data.
And we want to make that data
as accessible to the public
as we can.
So we've developed dashboards.
You've probably, if
you work with our data,
you've probably seen our
hourly electric grid monitor.
It's been out for a
few years, but you
can look at generation data
by balancing authority.
And on the right hand
side, earlier this year,
we released the wholesale
electricity market portal.
So this is data
coming from the RTOs.
And you can look at the
same kind of information,
including generation, but
also price information coming
from the RTOs.
We also, again, this is just
another example of our petroleum
collection program.
It's our surveys, everywhere
you see a pink box
with an EIA dash number,
that's a survey that we
have out in the field.
So we're covering the
whole supply chain.
We're looking at movements,
prices, sales, and trade
of petroleum across the system.
We have a similar
survey collection
system for natural gas.
Again, this is just to give
you a sense of the data
that we collect.
We also have a variety
of analytic products.
We have a short-term energy
outlook that we produce monthly.
We actually just released
the latest one today.
And there we use an
econometric model
to forecast where we see US and
global energy markets headed
over the next 12 to 24 months.
The forecast horizon is
always through the end
of the following year.
We also produce the
annual energy outlook.
There we're looking at US
energy supply, consumption,
and trade over a 30-year period.
And we use a model called the
National Energy Modeling System
or NEMS.
And I'm going to talk a
fair amount about the AEO
and the NEMS model
in this presentation.
We also produce an
international energy outlook.
Has the same-- covers
the same kind of topics,
but it's international in scale.
And for that, we use
a different model.
We use something called the
World Energy Projection System.
We also produce a variety of
other reports and analyses.
So for example,
Today in Energy, we
publish a little piece
every day that covers
some topical issue in energy.
And then there's a
variety of reports
that we produce to respond to
Congress or key stakeholders.
I want to talk a little
bit about the energy
transition, which is really
already under underway here.
So this is looking at US
primary energy consumption
going all the way back to 1940.
And you've probably
seen this graph
or you've heard elements, heard
about elements of this graph.
The thing that stands
out to me is just
this rapid decline in coal
over the last two decades.
But you can also see a rapid
rise in natural gas consumption.
You can see that renewables, the
green line, particularly wind
and solar, have
been on the rise.
If we zoom in on the
electricity sector,
that's where a lot of these
changes are taking place.
And you see the
same basic pattern.
You see that decline in
coal-fired generation, the rise
in both natural
gas-fired generation
as well as zero
carbon generation.
And again, a big portion
of that rise in zero carbon
is from wind and solar.
We can also take a
very zoomed in view
of where we are currently.
So this is a Sankey diagram.
We actually released this
just a couple of weeks ago
and gives you more
details on energy flows.
So if you start on
the left hand side,
these are sources
of primary energy.
And as you move to
the right hand side,
you're seeing those sources of
energy enter the end use sector.
So the Sankey diagram is
looking at energy consumption
by source and sector.
You can see that
in the middle, we
have the transformation of
these primary energy sources
into both electricity
and waste heat.
So the thing that we did in this
version of the Sankey diagram
is for the thermal sources,
for the natural gas, coal,
and nuclear, you
can actually see
the split between useful
electricity generation and then
the portion that goes to
waste heat on the bottom
here in this black,
this black bar.
So if you think about it,
right, if we can grow--
if we grow renewables,
there we're
assuming a one to
one conversion.
So one unit of
renewable electricity
equals one unit
of primary energy.
But we have all these thermal
losses from the thermal sources.
So if renewables continue
to grow, all else equal,
we could potentially shrink
the amount of primary energy
we need to meet our end
use service demands.
Now, as you move to the right
into the end use sectors,
the way that we draw the
boundary on this diagram
is it's fuels that
are being consumed
by demand devices that
ultimately meet our end use
service demands.
So you have fuels
moving to devices
like furnaces, heat pumps,
vehicles, and being consumed.
Obviously, within
each of those sectors,
there are additional losses
associated with conversion.
But we draw the
boundary before that.
One of the things that I
like about this diagram
is that it strips away a
lot of the technology detail
that we're often accustomed
to thinking about.
And we're just focused on
the current flow of energy.
So if we're thinking about
the energy transition
and reducing carbon emissions,
I mean, the way I see it,
there's three basic options.
They're not mutually
exclusive, right?
But we can increase carbon
free electricity and fuels.
We can decrease
final energy demands.
Or we can do some form of
carbon dioxide removal.
And the question is, this is
historical data that we collect.
We have high confidence in this.
But how do we advance this?
How do-- what will this
look like in 2030 and 2050?
And that's where energy
modeling comes in.
So just to get us started
and talking about modeling.
A lot of people quote George Box
who said, "All models are wrong;
some are useful."
I actually this quote
from Paul Krugman.
This was in his New
York Times blog.
He was actually talking about
models of the US economy.
But it applies
universally to all models,
including energy models.
And what he said is models are
an enormously important tool
for clarifying your thought.
You don't have to literally
believe your model.
In fact, you're a fool if you do
to believe that putting together
a simplified but complete
account of how things work
helps you gain a much more
sophisticated understanding
of the real situation.
People who don't
use models end up
relying on slogans, all of which
are wrong some of the time.
So models, energy
systems, they're
too complicated for us to
develop, at least for me.
I can't develop a mental
model of the energy system
and project that forward.
We need some way to organize
all of this information
into a model.
Models allow us to build the
self-consistent framework that
allows us to systematically
explore the future decision
space.
So you can see the
schematic diagram here.
I tend to think of models
in terms of layers.
And this is meant to represent
just a generic energy system
model.
So on the left hand side,
you see model input data.
We've got to go out and
gather some primary data.
There's going to be some
intermediate transformations
of that data.
And then, ultimately,
there's going
to be a final formatted
data set that's
going to go that's going
to be fed into the model.
On the right hand side, you
can see model structure.
And it all starts with
governing dynamics.
What are the dynamics
that are actually
going to drive decision
making in the model?
Are you performing
an optimization?
Is it a consumer choice model?
Is it an agent based model,
some kind of simulation,
system dynamics?
You've got to pick some
governing dynamics.
Below that, You've got to
take those governing dynamics
and then encode them into a
mathematical representation.
And then you have to take the
mathematical representation
and then implement in code.
And then, ultimately,
you run the model
and it pulls the data
and the code together.
The model gets
instantiated, it runs,
and then it produces output
that we look at and analyze.
So there's a very
systematic approach
to the practice of modeling.
So at EIA, to do our
domestic outlook,
we use something called the
National Energy Modeling System.
And each of the boxes here
represent a separate module.
So on the left
hand side, you can
see these are sources
of primary energy.
So I showed you all that
survey data that we collect.
A lot of that survey
data is actually
being used to populate the
input data sets for the model
and to calibrate.
You can see on the right hand
side a bunch of orange boxes.
Those are the end use sectors.
So those three big consumption
surveys that I mentioned,
they're being used to develop
the input data for the end use
sectors.
Along the bottom here, we have
intermediate transformations.
And then along the top
we've got carbon management,
macro activity, and
then other drivers
like international
energy and trade,
and emissions policy,
which, of course, are
going to affect the outcome.
And then we need a way to pull
all these modules together.
So we have an integrating
module that basically iterates
through all of these modules
and finds a price quantity
equilibrium between all
of these various modules.
OK, so we've got
this great model.
And sophisticated.
What are we going to do with it?
And the first
question you might ask
is, should we use these
models to produce a forecast?
And by forecast, what
I mean is, should we
use the model to
make a prediction
about a specific
quantity in the future.
And I think the answer
for me to that question
is no, we should not do that.
And my thinking on
this was heavily
influenced by this report
by Hodges in [? DOER. ?]
It was published in 1992.
They were researchers at
RAND, and they were actually
focused on military models.
They were thinking
about everything
from models of fuze activation
to simulations of theater level
combat.
And there was a lot of
confusion about, well,
can we use these models
to forecast and so forth.
And their point was,
if you're using a model
to produce a forecast,
it ought to come
with some kind of
a warranty, right?
Otherwise, why am
I going to trust
the forecast or the prediction.
Well, how do you
produce a warranty?
You have to be able
to validate the model.
to take the model,
produce some kind of
a forecast, compare it
against real world
results, and then say, OK,
how accurate is it?
And they said, OK.
So if you want to forecast the
model should be validatable.
Well, how do if your
model is validatable?
They lay out four
different conditions here.
The first is it's got to be
possible to observe and measure
the situation being modeled.
It's pretty obvious.
Second, the situation
being modeled
must exhibit a constancy
of structure and time.
Third, the situation
being modeled
must exhibit constancy across
variations in conditions
not specified in the model.
And then fourth, you have
to collect enough data
to make the predictive test.
And when you think about long
term models of the energy
system, they fail on
conditions two and three.
The structure of energy markets,
they do change over time.
And we often-- models
of the energy system
are highly simplified.
So we're not they can change
across variations that we're not
modeling, right?
So I would argue that we can't
really validate these models.
And so we shouldn't be
using them to forecast.
The other thing that I've
just observed in my time
as an energy modeler,
is because we
can't validate these
long term projections,
there's really no
guideposts there
to determine if I add some
new complexity to my model,
does it actually add value, does
it give me more insight or not.
And so my observation
is a lot of these models
have simply gotten
more complex over time,
as people try and analyze many
of these issues in more detail.
But we don't really know
whether that complexity
is buying us more insight.
When models are used
to produce forecasts,
the results are
generally pretty dismal.
So these are just
two examples that
are drawn from the literature.
The one on the left is the
US Atomic Energy Commission.
This is a forecast
from 1962 looking
at installed nuclear capacity.
The vertical-- yeah, the
vertical axis's log scale,
they were off by an
order of magnitude.
The one on the right
were a set of predictions
about what primary
energy consumption would
be in the year 2000.
And every single
study overestimated
what-- nobody under
predicted what
energy consumption would be.
And I want you to
remember this example,
because I'm going to show you
some results from EIA that
exhibit the same
basic phenomenon.
OK?
Computer went to sleep.
So keep this in mind
because I'm going
to show you the results
that are going to follow
the same basic pattern.
We often anchor on what's
happening currently,
and we're not creative
enough about where things
might be headed in the future.
So shouldn't really
use models for--
these kind of models
for forecasting.
But what can we use them for?
What are they good for?
There's still lots of really
valuable uses for these models.
They can simply be an aid in
helping us think and hypothesize
about the future of energy.
They can help us
create a dialogue
among different stakeholders
on complex issues.
I mean, if we're thinking
about something like the energy
transition and we want
to start a dialogue,
there has to be some basis
for the dialogue, right?
So if you have a systematic
representation of the energy
system that you can
advance into the future,
we can start to have a
debate about the model
and what it means and so forth.
We can identify key system
features and effects,
pitfalls, and trade offs, right?
That's where a lot of the
insight from this modeling work
comes from.
We can also identify key sources
of uncertainty and knowledge
gaps.
It might turn out that
the model is particularly
sensitive to
assumptions we're making
about a specific
technology or sector,
but maybe we lack
the data to feel
confident about
how we're modeling
that piece of the system.
And then, finally, you
can use models to help
inform decision strategies.
I know there's a bunch
of future uncertainty.
I don't know what's
going to happen.
But I can incorporate that
uncertainty into my model
and help me come up
with a path forward.
This idea that
models should not be
used to produce forecasts
or precise projections,
they should be used for
insight, is an idea that's
been around a really long time.
So I want to give credit to the
folks at the Stanford Energy
Modeling Forum who are making
this point four decades ago.
I also really like the quote
at the bottom by Bill Hogan.
It's not the individual
results of a model
that are so important.
It's the improved
user appreciation
of the policy problem
that is the greatest
contribution to modeling.
All right.
So I want to talk a little
bit about some past surprises.
There have been some
energy market developments
that have taken not just EIA,
but many analysts by surprise.
And I want to talk through
those a little bit.
Before I do that, I
do want to mention
that EIA does produce an AEO
retrospective report every two
years.
It compares the results from our
reference case against realized
outcomes, and it's really just
focused on statistical measures.
Things like percent difference,
average percent difference,
standard deviation.
And it is really useful.
But I do find that
it's hard to interpret,
and it also ignores all
the side cases that we run.
Every year we run a dozen cases
besides the reference case,
and it would be nice to
incorporate those as well.
And this is just a little
bit of a brief aside.
But this is-- there's a risk
in just relying on statistics.
So you might have heard
of Anscombe's Quartet.
This is a for data sets that
were developed by statistician
Francis Anscombe in 1973.
And all four data sets
have nearly identical
descriptive statistics.
So if you calculate the
mean and the variance
and the correlation, they're
basically all the same.
But when you plot them, you
get what you have on the right.
They are totally different.
And his point was we can't just
rely on statistical measures.
There's value in actually
visualizing the data.
So that's part of the
inspiration for this new tool
that we developed at EIA.
This has recently been
released on GitHub
as an open source tool.
You can see the link here.
You can download and play
around with this on your own.
I'm going to show you some
results using this tool.
Just a few things
before I actually
show you the animations.
One is that our data
management practices at EIA
have changed a lot, so
the further back in time
you go, those
early AEO editions,
it can be hard to mine
the data because they're
in different formats
and so forth.
In the earliest years of what
I'm going to show you here--
so far, we've only been able
to extract the reference case.
We're working to
include side cases.
And then just another
note that the model time
horizon has expanded.
So in the early years we only
ran the AEO through 2030.
Then it was 2040.
Now we're moving out to 2040.
So you'll see the end
points for the AEO
vary depending on the edition.
So with all of that set
up, surprise number one
was shale oil and gas.
There was a lot of
technology innovation
around horizontal drilling
and treatment into shale,
and that radically changed
oil and gas development.
EIA began examining the
impacts of shale resources
in earnest beginning
in about 2008.
But our long term modeling
was slow to catch up.
If you go back to
the early 2010s,
we didn't really have sufficient
data or modeling capabilities
to have the confidence to
project exponential growth
in the production of oil and
gas from shale resources.
By 2013, we were starting to get
a handle on some of the data.
We realized that the traditional
relationship between rig count
and production was changing.
So this drilling productivity
report was launched at EIA.
And you fast forward
today, and now we've
got a large database
of shale wells.
We can analyze how projection
will happen over the long term.
But it took us a
while to get there.
So here's the animation.
You all are the first
ones to see this.
I was playing around
with the tool myself
and created the animation.
So it starts in 2005 and then
sequentially adds the results
from each AEO edition
until we get to 2023.
That dark line that remains
is actual that is actual.
Here we're looking at domestic
dry natural gas production
in trillion cubic feet.
And the thing that jumps out
at you is in the early years,
we just were--
our projections were
just way too flat.
We did not pick up on all
of the production that
was about to come from shale.
And even if you look at--
I mean, in doing this,
I realized even in 2023,
I'm not convinced
that the highest
scenarios are high enough.
And to me, the goal would be,
if we're producing this outlook,
we should be able to develop
a set of cases that ultimately
encapsulate what turns out
to be the actual, right?
If we develop an
envelope like this,
and actual is above
or below that,
I don't think we're
doing a very good job.
So in my mind,
the goal is to try
and capture actual within the
envelope of cases that we run.
This is the same exact
setup, same format.
But now this is domestic
crude oil production
in million barrels per day.
And again, you see the
same basic phenomenon.
It took us several
years to really--
I mean, you see those early
years in the reference case,
they were just very, very flat.
And every year, we recalibrate.
So we move up the curve.
But then the projections
are too flat.
So that's surprise number one.
Surprise number two was
the rapid deployment
of wind and solar.
This is one that I often hear
about when I talk with folks
about renewables and EIA.
And I think there were two
factors that drove this.
One was the capital
costs of wind and solar,
PV really began to decline
rapidly in the 2010s.
And the problem at EIA
was our baseline capital
cost data did not keep
pace with reality.
We just weren't updating
the cost data often enough,
and our learning rates
weren't high enough.
So in the reference
case, we have
something called endogenous
technological learning.
So every time the
installed capacity doubles,
a learning rate gets applied,
and the capital cost comes down
a certain percentage.
And those learning rates
were not high enough.
Second thing is
we always at EIA,
because we're a
policy neutral, we
focus on existing
laws and regulations.
So whatever the policy is,
whenever it's set to sunset,
that's what we encode
into the model.
So if a production
tax credit was
set to expire six months
after we release the AEO,
we assume it expires
six months after we
release the AEO forever, for
the entire projection horizon.
And I'll show you
some data to indicate
that there are a lot of stops
in renewable tax credits
that cause some problems for us.
This is looking at estimated
capital cost data for wind,
not just from EIA,
which is the blue line,
but from some other agencies.
And you can see that
we were systematically
high for several years, higher
than these other sources.
This is the story about
the production tax credit.
So this is showing annual
wind capacity additions.
I know there's a lot
of detail on here.
But all of those labels
are like the production tax
credit for wind expires and
then it restarts and it expires
and then it restarts.
And wind development
is very sensitive
to whether that production
tax credit is in place.
And so again, year
after year, we're
making the best decision we can
about whether is the production
tax credit in effect or not.
But we've had so many starts
and stops over the years
that it's affected
our projections.
So here's what projected
wind generation looks like.
You can see, again, we're
making the updates every year,
but it just goes totally flat
after the first few years.
And again, it took us a while
before those curves actually
start to change.
And even now, they're
still pretty--
you can see they
still level out.
Just very similar
story with solar.
You can see that our
estimates, again,
they were systematically high
compared to several sources
from about 2010 to 2015.
And this is what
solar looks like.
I mean, we're barely producing
any solar generation at all.
Now, what's
interesting, though, is
solar didn't really start
to grow rapidly until later.
And so we were able
to get caught up,
I think, with solar earlier on.
And you can see just
visually, if you
look at the range of projections
in the later editions
of the AEO, I think
we're doing a better
job of capturing the
actual Whereas wind started
to grow rapidly earlier
before I think we were really
keyed in to what was going on.
And then this is the final
example I want to show.
This is energy
related CO2 emissions.
CO2 emissions are just a
simple mass balance, right?
You have a certain amount
of fossil fuel consumption.
You multiply by an
emissions factor.
And you can figure
out total CO2.
Again, you can see
in the early years.
We were just assuming CO2
emissions were just going
to go on and increase forever.
And a lot of that
is due to the fact
that we assume that end use
demand was going to grow,
coal was going to remain
a significant fraction
of electricity demand.
I already explained how we
missed the shale revolution
in the early years in our
long term projections.
So we didn't know that
all that gas was coming.
And with all that gas
came lower prices,
which then pushed coal
out of the market.
We also didn't pick up on the
rapid growth in renewables
over the last decade.
And so for all those
reasons, we end up
with CO2 emissions that are
quite high compared to actual.
Now, where do we
ultimately end up?
Who knows.
And the final thing
I want to point out
is if you look as it
goes from 2022 to 2023,
you can see the effects of
the Inflation Reduction Act.
So that very last
light blue, you
can see that the curves
really did shift down
once the IRA was passed.
So what's going on here?
There seems to be a
pattern in all of this.
So these are my thoughts.
First thing is, as a
statistical agency,
our projections are based
on rigorously derived
historical data.
Again, we're a
statistical agency.
So we're really looking
carefully at the data.
But it can take some
time to identify
the signal through the noise.
But yet, we're producing
projections every year, right?
So again, it took time to
see what was happening.
The other thing is that I think
that judgments about model
calibration, how we design
scenarios and so forth,
are affected by
cognitive heuristics.
If you haven't heard of
cognitive heuristics before,
heuristics are just
mental shortcuts
that can facilitate problem
solving and probability
judgments.
This literature goes all the
way back to Kahneman and Tversky
in 1974.
But there's two heuristics
that I think really
matter for energy modeling.
One is the
availability heuristic,
that people assess the
probabilities of a future event
or outcome on the basis of
how easily they can remember
past examples, or
how easily they can
envision future possibilities.
And when you're focused
on the data that you have,
that's what's available
to you, and you're going
to make use of that heuristic.
The other is anchoring
and adjustment,
that people will often
start with an initial value
and they tend to anchor on it.
And even when you get
additional information
to move you off that anchor,
the adjustment off of the anchor
is often insufficient.
We don't make big
enough adjustments
once we learn new things.
And I think these
heuristics can be
hard to overcome,
particularly in an environment
where modelers can be judged
for errant projections.
If I'm going to be wrong,
and I get what happened?
I'd rather be able to say, look,
this is the data that I had.
This was the best guess I
possibly could make at the time.
It takes some courage
to really say, well,
it really could
grow exponentially.
Let's run a case
that looks like that.
And the thing I want
to emphasize is at EIA,
we're trying to be as
transparent as we can.
We have nothing to hide.
And the things I'm talking
about here, these heuristics,
this isn't limited to EIA.
This is like a
universal phenomena.
This is happening with
modeling all over the place.
And I'm just using EIA work
as an example to illustrate.
OK, so what can we
do about uncertainty?
In the process of overhauling
our long-term modeling program,
I spent a lot of time going
back to this National Research
Council report that
was released in 1992,
and they really emphasized
the importance of uncertainty.
That uncertainty is inherent
in the nature of models.
And we shouldn't just
ignore it or eliminate it.
We need to find ways--
EIA needs to find
ways to incorporate
the consideration of uncertainty
into NEMS explicitly.
And the whole report was based
around recommendations for EIA
to build and run NEMS.
So they thought it
was very important.
I think it's very important.
And to me the
question comes down
to how do you illuminate and
inform future energy pathways
given all of this uncertainty?
And I think it really depends
on the specific question you're
trying to ask.
There's not like one method
that you should always
use to assess uncertainty.
It really depends on the
nature of the question
that you're asking.
The other thing is
that I think it's
helpful to break down
uncertainty into two categories.
There's parametric
uncertainty, and that's
uncertainty in the
input parameters
that we put into our models.
So I talked about wind
and solar capital costs.
We have to make some assumption
about what those costs are going
to be out through 2050, right?
That's parametric uncertainty.
And we have a lot of
tools in the toolbox
in order to try and
address the effects
of parametric uncertainty.
We can do scenario analysis,
parametric sensitivity analysis,
we can do Monte
Carlo simulations.
There's something called
a method of Morris
that does a random walk in
the input parameter space.
Stochastic
optimization or robust
optimization if we're trying
to develop a decision strategy.
The second category is
structural uncertainty,
which refers to the imperfect
and incomplete nature
of the equations
describing the system.
So you've got this really
complex world out there, right?
And you're trying to distill
that into a computer model.
The equations that you come
up with to govern that system
are going to be highly
simplified, right?
That's structural uncertainty.
And there's also ways
we can deal with this,
although there's
been less of it,
I would say, in the literature.
But there can be alternative
formulations of the model,
different equations.
There's a technique
called modeling
to generate alternatives that
I can talk more about later on,
or just model
intercomparison exercises.
Again, Stanford Energy Modeling
Forum does a great job.
They get a bunch of
modelers together.
The models are different.
They focus all the
models on the same issue
and then see what comes out.
Why are there differences
in the outputs
across these different models?
So that's another way to
address structural uncertainty.
We know that moving forward,
the system is already
in a period of rapid transition.
And when things are
changing rapidly,
it heightens uncertainty.
And I've just got a laundry
list of things that keep me up
at night as a modeler.
What are the impacts
of climate change?
How is that going to
affect end user demands?
What are the impacts of climate
change on infrastructure
and renewable resources?
How are we going to build
out all this infrastructure
and develop new supply chains
for clean energy technology?
I showed you examples with
technology innovation.
At EIA, we underestimated
the role of wind and solar.
What's going to
happen in the future?
What about novel technologies?
What about enhanced geothermal,
fusion, space based solar power?
I mean, should those
be in the model?
What if there's a
technology breakthrough
and we're missing it?
Electricity demand growth.
There's a lot talk about
AI in data centers.
Does that matter-- is that
going to matter or not?
Or are we just going to improve
the efficiency of the chips
so much that it's
not a big deal.
I don't know.
Again, I've talked about
the role of policy.
If there's significant
changes in infrastructure,
what's the impact on people?
And then, of course, there
are the unknown unknowns.
There are the things
that I can't conceive of
to put on this list but are
probably going to happen
and we're going to
be dealing with.
So the bottom line
is we need to find
ways to deal with uncertainty.
Now, I want to talk a little bit
about what we're doing at EIA.
This example is specific to EIA.
So we developed something
called the reference case.
I've mentioned this a few times.
And people tend to
interpret our reference case
as though it is a forecast.
This goes back to AEO 2022.
This was before I joined.
And you can see on
the left hand side,
I think we define it-- the way
it's defined is exactly right,
that it's a baseline for
comparison between side cases
to explain alternative trends.
But on the right hand
side, 70% of the figures
that appeared in that AEO show
the reference case by itself.
So if you're just reading it
casually, you're going to think,
hey, this looks like
a forecast, right?
And I think that that's
really problematic.
I think as a modeler,
we never, never want
to put a single result or
the results from a single run
onto a figure.
Just think about it
mathematically, right?
Even if the reference
case was our best guess,
the probability of realizing a
single trajectory for anything
through a continuous solution
space is going to be zero.
In AEO 2023, we really
tried to emphasize again
the range of results
across the cases.
So this is looking at
electricity generation
by select technologies.
We're still showing
the reference case
as that black line,
but you can now
see that there's a gray band
around every reference case
result. And that shows the
range around the reference case.
So we're trying
to emphasize, hey,
there is a range
of outcomes here.
We don't know for sure
what's going to happen.
The other thing, we're
also experimenting
with other methods.
This is something that we
did publish in the AEO.
This is looking at
energy-related carbon dioxide
emissions.
And we actually
utilized an approach
that was published by
[? Kac ?] et al. in 2017,
and it was directed to EIA.
They took our--
they took the AEO
and they built these
uncertainty cones.
And we decided,
hey, let's actually
build this into the AEO.
All right.
So what do we do--
what do you do here?
For a given projection
horizon, let's say five years
into the future, you take--
you calculate the difference
between AEO projected CO2
emissions and actual CO2
emissions.
And then you do that
across all previous AEO
editions for that
projection horizon, right?
And then you repeat that for
different projection horizons.
For 5 years, 10 years, 15 years.
So for each projection
horizon there,
then you've got two
set of differences
between AEO and actual.
And you can use that information
to form a distribution.
And there's lots
of things to test.
And you can assume
that you can fit it
to a Gaussian distribution.
And this particular
case, we assume
that it was a
non-parametric distribution.
And so what you
do is if you have
a distribution for each
projection horizon,
you can then use
that to fit a cone.
And then you can apply that cone
to the current reference case.
And that's what we've done here.
So just to orient you, the
black line is a reference case.
The two gray lines
are the most--
the highest and lowest emissions
cases that we had in the AEO.
And then you can see the cones.
So the way to think
about the dark blue cone
is that it captures 50% of
the historical projection
errors in energy
related CO2 emissions.
And then the lighter
blue cone captures
95% of the historical
projection errors.
There's a couple
of things I really
like about this technique.
One is that it's very
computationally efficient.
We don't have to run
them hundreds of times
because we have all of
this data lying around.
So that's a really
big advantage.
The other thing is that it
captures whatever bias there
is in our projections.
It's being captured
because we're
comparing actual to projection.
The thing that's the
weakness of this,
though, is who's to say that
those historical projection
errors apply to the future.
We don't know-- we
don't know that.
But I still think
that there's something
useful to be learned
from this exercise.
OK, final thing,
just very quickly,
I want to talk about our
long term modeling plans.
A couple of years ago,
we embarked on a plan
to overhaul our
long term models.
Before I get into that, I
wanted to explain, well,
what are the goals for our
long term outlooks at EIA.
I mean, we want to be
able to capture key market
dynamics that drive energy
related decision making.
We do want to provide that
policy neutral baseline.
We do want to capture
uncertainty and capture
the fullest range of
possible outcomes.
And we want to be
flexible and nimble.
We want to be able to
incorporate new model
features easily and
produce timely analysis.
And then, finally, we want
to make our modeling work
transparent and accessible.
The little snippet I
took here was actually
from the Infrastructure
Investment and Jobs Act.
This is actually
directed at EIA.
And it's telling us
to strive to build
a single, consistent, and
open source modeling platform.
So we're on this
two-track approach.
Track one is we need to
continue to produce the AEO.
So we're updating the national
energy modeling system.
One thing we did was we
made NEMS open source.
So you can now go to GitHub,
you can clone the repo.
It's available under
the Apache 2.0 license.
So if you're feeling ambitious
and so forth, please have at it.
Make use of the model.
The data is also there as well.
It takes some effort
to get it all set up,
but we do-- but we are
making it available.
The other thing, though, is that
we've overhauled the modules.
So when we release
AEO 2025, it's
going to be using a
version of NEMS that
contains three new modules.
There's going to be
a hydrogen market
module that's going to represent
hydrogen production and pricing.
There's a brand new
carbon management
module that captures
whatever CO2
is produced across the sectors.
It can be captured
and then allocated
to either beneficial reuse
or geologic sequestration.
And then we also have a new
hydrocarbon supply module,
which will improve the
representation of upstream oil
and gas.
And among other
things, we're hoping
that these updates will allow us
to better represent current laws
and regulations, including many
of the provisions in the IRA.
OK, track two is
Project Blue Sky,
where we've embarked on a plan
to develop the next generation
energy system model at EIA.
And we want it to be modular
the way that NEMS is.
We want it to be flexible.
We want it to be transparent.
It's going to be open source.
And we're going to work
really hard on documentation
so people can understand
what we're doing.
We want it to be robust so
that we can capture uncertainty
and that we have insights
that are conditioned
on that uncertainty.
And we've already released
a very barebones prototype.
So you can scan the QR code,
takes you to that link there.
There's a GitHub repo.
So if you're a modeler
or you're a coder,
please take it for a test drive.
Let us know-- let us
know what you think.
This is very, very early stage,
and we're very open to feedback.
Anything from coding
practices to I don't like this
or you ought to think about
doing it in a different way.
We want this to be
a community effort.
So I encourage folks
in the audience that
are interested to give it a--
give it a test.
Again, we want to maintain
this modular structure
similar to NEMS.
We're hoping that will allow us
to test different approaches,
different governing dynamics.
We could even vary the level
of complexity by module.
So if we have an
individual module,
we can have a very
simple version,
and then we can add a feature.
And we can do that
systematically
to build up the complexity
where at each step,
we know when we add some
complexity, what does
that bias in terms of insight.
If it's modular, we can also
isolate particular modules
and just run a subset
of those modules
to answer a particular question.
We don't necessarily need to
run the whole integrated system
to answer every question.
So I showed you the
diagram in the beginning.
The idea here is that
you can essentially
have different governing
dynamics, again,
within each module, which gives
you the flexibility, again,
to test different ideas.
What if decision making
and transportation sector
is driven by an
agent based model?
What would that do?
It's something you can test.
I don't want to get
into the details,
but we've also worked
out some ways--
different ways that we could
solve the integrated model.
There's a way that you can solve
it as a single optimization
problem where you take the
non optimization based modules
through a set of
equivalence relations.
You can convert them into
constraints and an optimization,
or you can just use
iterative methods
to seek convergence
the way we do in NEMS.
This is what's in the prototype.
We've got different
ways to solve the model.
We've got three toy modules
to play around with.
We've integrated
a couple of ways
to analyze sensitivity
of input parameters,
and then we have some
standalone features
that we want some feedback
on as development progresses.
OK, just to wrap up
here, parting thoughts.
Energy system is highly complex.
It's evolving rapidly,
it's uncertain.
Long term forecasts.
My opinion, bad idea.
We shouldn't be producing
point estimates.
I've tried to demonstrate
that there's this built
in conservatism in the models.
Remember cognitive heuristics.
We all take these
mental shortcuts
when we're thinking
about data and modeling.
There's also that
wrong of being fear--
or that fear of being wrong
or being an outlier compared
with other modeling groups.
And I think the
bottom line is we just
need to find ways to explore a
wider range of possibilities.
Kind of step through
what we're doing at EIA.
And then this is just my plea.
Despite our best
efforts, there are going
to be unforeseen surprises.
And if you're a student and
you're starting to model,
or you're an experienced
modeler, whatever you do,
don't start believing
the numbers.
There's a tendency when you
sit in front of the computer
and you're watching the shell
spit out numbers at you, maybe
not in the beginning,
but you'll really
start to believe those
numbers with high precision.
And don't fall for it.
Always, always remain skeptical.
Which brings me
to my last point,
that we have to remain humble
and intellectually honest
about what we know
about the future.
That way we can
provide decision.
Makers with an honest
assessment of what we think
could happen in the future.
And then I won't
read these quotes,
but these come from Daniel
Kahneman's book, Thinking Fast
and Slow, about uncertainty
in judgments about decisions.
And I think it applies
so well when we're
thinking about energy futures.
So I'll leave it up here
and happy to take questions.
[APPLAUSE]
So thank you very much.
Maybe we'll take questions
from the audience.
And I would recommend you
read these quotes, too.
Question.
Yeah.
I want to start with some
heartfelt and admiring thanks
for your work.
I rely on it.
It's wonderful.
And thank you very much.
Thank you.
I'll pass that
along to our staff.
OK.
So I have a short question
and a slightly longer one.
The short one is, do you
think about or can you model--
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, sorry.
Do you think about or can you
model the political aspects
of local populations
deciding they
don't want to see wind
farms within the horizon,
and so they oppose them?
Is that kind of politics a
varying part of your model?
Do you include it?
So I'm going to
take off the EIA hat
and put on the academic
modeler hat and say that, sure.
I mean, I think that's
an interesting thing
that one could explore, maybe
with an agent-based model.
I think an EIA, that
would be a bad idea.
I think there'd be
all kinds of questions
about how are you doing this.
It would violate
policy neutrality.
But I think just as a
general modeling idea, sure.
I mean, why not?
OK.
Because my opinion is
that might be the throttle
on a lot of our renewables.
And so--
Again, it really
depends on the question
that you're trying to answer.
If it's a technical question
about the limits of renewables,
you don't really
need to do that.
But if you're a
sociologist or something,
you're trying to understand
political coalitions
and how that could
affect, then sure.
OK.
Well, I'll get to my
other question, which
is, assuming you'll agree
that to reach 2050 net zero,
we need to think about
great new things,
great new opportunities--
and I think
there is such a great
opportunity in front of us,
which is remotely harvested,
zero carbon, liquid fuel, mainly
ammonia, which can be
harvested in the Falklands
and then shipped to
Philadelphia or something.
And so my question is,
is that in your models?
Or will it be in your models?
Or what will it take to get
that considered in your models?
Yeah.
That's a good question.
I mean, I'll just be
perfectly frank with you.
Right now, we're not capable of
modeling a net zero scenario.
We're getting closer to that.
We don't have an ammonia pathway
in NEMS or WEPS right now,
but I think we need to
add that capability.
I mean, my view is we
want to have as many
of those low-carbon
pathways in the model
as possible, because
eventually, we
are going to be asked to run
those kinds of scenarios, right?
Someone's going to come to
us and say run net zero,
and we need to be prepared.
So ammonia is not in there right
now, but hopefully will be soon.
[INAUDIBLE]
Thank you very much.
So I'm wondering if
you can say something
about how you get the data.
I see, for example, that there's
this [? E-864, ?] that has all
the generator data.
So say that you
realize for your model
that you want to make--
you need some kind of data.
Do you go to the
government and say,
please make a law to tell
them to give us the data, or--
Yeah, good question.
So the way that it works
is, as I mentioned,
we're vested with the
authority to collect data,
but we can't just
do that on our own.
So there's a process.
So let's say we collect a
lot of electricity data.
The 860 or the 860M is
one of those surveys.
Let's say we decided we want
to ask another question.
There's some other
piece of data we want.
The process is we go to the
White House Office of Management
and Budget, and then
we request from them
whether we can
change the survey.
And there's a whole
approval process
in order to make that approval.
There's something called
the Paperwork Reduction Act,
and they want to
understand, what's
the public benefit of collecting
this additional information,
and then what's the
burden on industry?
And do those things
kind of balance out?
So that's the process.
If we want to set
up a new survey
or we just want to
modify an existing survey
to ask new questions,
there's a process
we go through with OMB in
order to get that approved.
And there's notices that
go in the Federal Register.
So that the public
can comment and say,
hey, that's a great idea, or
no, that's a terrible idea.
Why would they want to do that?
You could get this
data somewhere else.
So there's an opportunity
for the public
to weigh in on those data
collection proposals as well.
OK.
Maybe take one more
way in the back, there?
Thanks for the presentation.
I just had a small question.
Will the use of energy models
for long-term forecasting
be made easier as time passes
by, because of the fact
that we have more data
to verify your accuracy
of the main projections and
therefore learn from it?
I don't know if the question
was clear, with the micro.
I'm not sure if I understand.
You're saying--
The point I'm making is
just that as time passes by,
we'll have more data to verify
previous projections we have--
OK.
I see.
Yes, yes.
Would you consider that this
will allow us to better rely
on long-term forecastings?
So here's the problem
that you get stuck in.
And it goes back to the
Hodges in [? DOER-- ?]
their conditions
for devalidation.
You could go back
in time, and you
can do all the comparison,
all the validation you
want based on historical data.
But the problem is there's no
guarantee that it will work well
into the future.
And it's because of that
constancy and structure
through time.
Right?
Unfortunately, the system
is not just physics-based.
It's human behavior, it's
societal trends, it's technology
innovation.
So you could run your
model and realize, wow,
I got everything right.
My model is great.
And it could be wrong about
everything for the next two
decades.
So even though we
collect more data
and we could do try and do
some validation exercises,
you kind of get
stuck in this place
where it doesn't
mean that you're
going to do well in the future.
So more data doesn't
necessarily make it better.
That said, the
kind of exercise we
went through, where we show the
projections against actual--
I do think can learn a lot.
I just don't view it as a
validation exercise to prove
that the model is precise.
All right.
Well, thank you again.
That was a very fantastic talk.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you.
And I just wanted to
put in a shameless plug.
MITEI has a podcast,
and if you'd
like to hear more
thoughts, maybe
a little bit along
the same lines
as what you heard from
the speaker tonight,
there's some really interesting
podcasts with MIT faculty.
And so you can just use
the QR code to get to it.
And thank you again.
Thank you for your
attention, too.
[APPLAUSE]