And I'm now very much looking forward to
the closing remarks of this wonderful
first conference day. And therefore I
would like to invite another guest to
join us here on stage. He's the chief
executive officer at Advantage Austria.
So please join me in welcoming Mikail
Ot.
[Music]
Okay.
Well, ladies and gentlemen, um just a
few thoughts from my side before um we
close the conference today. Um and to
thank you all for coming.
Um it was for me it was a tremendous day
and I hope it was also for you. It was
just amazing day and we get very
inspired. Um first of all number one
thought um well having listened to most
of the presentation but of most uh
having also talked to most of you during
in the breaks I thought well we are not
in the we we spoke about the future of
manufacturing but we are not at the edge
of this transformation. We all in the
middle of it and we shape it to to bring
back the initial uh discussions we had.
We all shape this transformation. And
here comes the paradox zone. While um
while the machines and the algorithms um
are learning very fast are evolving on a
daily basis and they are adapting uh
well hourly probably one of the most
important factors in this transformation
is probably has probably less momentum
but is probably way more important in
this transformation is us. It's the
human factor and it's about people and
actually Randall this is what you said
in 2010 or 11 here on this stage it's
all about people. So for thought number
one um we are shaping this
transformation um across disciplines um
across uh the labs uh probably also
across and hopefully also across borders
and across generations. Thought number
two and this was interesting because I
think we didn't come here to admire
technology. None of us came here to
admire technology. And it's easy to be
dazzled by um by quantum technology, by
AI, by Gen AI solutions, by all this
amazing um um progress we heard from
faculty members today.
Um but when you think about it um when
you ask yourself the question and when
you talk to you in the in the break the
real questions most of us asked ourel
how is this
technology how can this technology
adoption serve the people how can we
find more important how can we find the
framework so our people our societies
our generation can follow the
technologies and not you know go into uh
left and right in political systems. We
talked about the geopolitical change. Um
so this is probably uh one of the more
question how can we sca scale the
technology not only in the labs
sometimes it's easy in the lab you know
the prototype is always easy but how can
we scale these innovations in the in the
factory floor in the classrooms and in
societies. This is even the more
important question and the answer um was
probably at least for me the most
powerful shift we explored today wasn't
the technological shift. It was this
cultural framework we spoke about. It
was how about
um having our the people follow the
technology using the technology and
serving um us. And this brings me to my
third thought, a little bit of
counterbalance maybe to Professor Pa
because I think it's a it's a posit it's
it's a little bit of a positive vision
for Europe, for Austrian for Austria and
especially for Austrian companies. Um,
and I'm thinking about this cultural
change and this cultural transformation
um because I think it would be a chance
for us for our companies not by being
the
loudest but even most trustful in this
transformation. Not by being the most
scalable. Well, we have a lot of medium
medium-sized companies, but with
in-depth expertise again with long-term
relations, with quality products, with
trust and I have to mention it again.
And I think this could be very decisive
factors and this could be our chance.
The chance of Europe, the chance of also
the chance of our companies um to help a
little bit, how would I say uh to help a
little bit in a world searching for
stability and meaning probably in a
world craving for stability and meaning.
So to conclude when we all go home, just
uh one last um thought, let's not just
be inspired, let's be activated. Let's
go all home to our factories to our
research institutes to Massachusetts in
our places in our countries around
Austria. We have some guests also from
international companies with one um
message in mind. The
future is not something um we inherited
from our parents, from our mothers and
fathers, from our grandfathers and
grandmothers.
The future is something we built for our
children and for our
grandchildren. Piece by piece, thought
by thought, and idea by idea.