The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
>> Start with a little bit of recap from uh
actually two Fridays ago. Uh but just a
reminder of things to keep in mind while
you guys are testing. You know on on one
hand most of you are as are pretty much
the most expert players in your game at
this point in time as you know compared
to anybody else in the world. You know
the game better than anybody else and
the kinds of things that um I that that
means you suck as a tester but that does
you still have a a role to play as
testers. Um you can be looking for the
degenerate strategies. You can look and
you can be looking for exploits.
Sometimes it takes more imagination than
a sleep depth MIT student is available
has available to them to be able to see
these exploits. But because you know the
systems better than anyone else you're
in a good position uh to to spot that I
mean the kinds of things that you're
looking for are obviously you know
strategies where there like like a
dominant strategy and I mentioned that
uh uh the the last time we we were in
this room. Um but also look for those um
those strategies where like okay I have
to those those decision points where I
could do decision A or I could do the
decision B. But if I if I change my
strategy and nobody else has changes
their strategy, I'm just screwed, you
know, and and and that makes it really
really hesitant for someone to to to
say, "Well,
strategy B could be really interesting.
you know I could go for this kind of
play but on the assumption that the only
way how this is going to be beneficial
is if everybody else also changes their
strategy now you have a situation where
uh where nobody wants to try that second
option you know that's that's one way to
think about parts you know it's like if
you change your decision and and the
only way that you can change your
decision is at a cost to yourself you
know and the and the benefits of
changing that decision is going to be
like higher higher than it's going to be
lower than the risks that you're taking
on then you know you've got a situation
where it's very difficult to break out
of one dominant strategy. So I mean if
you got a situation where there are like
three dominant strategies then none of
them are dominant anymore. You know it's
like you know that that that's great.
You now have an option uh of different
things that you can choose. Um so that's
just one thing to keep in mind while you
guys are looking at your game. You know,
if you just end up if everyone just ends
up adopting the same strategy and you're
just hoping the chance of your, you
know, the chance of drawing the right
cards going to win your game, then you
start to think, then you've got a game
where the individual players decisions
aren't quite that influential on the
outcome. And uh um I still need to play
your games to be able to see what you
guys are going for, but on the most
part, it looks like you guys are not
going for a purely chance based game.
you're looking for something where
someone's decision actually matters. Um
so so that's so that's that's one one
reminder um from a game theory point of
view and um the other one I never really
got time to talk about games as a system
of conflict and we don't have a huge
amount of time because uh we have
today's readings to go through um but um
the I if you think about games as you
know a games where multiple people are
striving for some sort of goal and
they're going to be winners and they're
going to be losers and the idea of
thinking of games as some kind of
conflict makes sense. Um
uh and you can think of them as you know
are games competitive or games
cooperative uh folks throw out some
games that are known to be co-op
cooperative
>> perfect cooperative
>> there are certain modes in certain
different games that you know sort of
flip it from from from compet from
competent to cooperative
>> for dead
>> for dead is is designed for four people
to play all going for the same goal
>> of war of multiplayer. Yeah,
>> diplomacy is interesting. Yeah, because
like
>> it's kind of a risk of cooperation.
>> Pandemic uh pandemic is you against the
the the board actually you against the
game rules. Um and actually that that
that leads into today's uh lecture a
bit. So hang on to that idea of of
pandmic. But um but there is one
argument that all games are competitive.
Even games like Left 4 Dead where you're
playing against a computer or Pandemic
where you're playing against the game
rules. Um or
>> Shadows or Camelot.
>> Shadows of Camelot. I'm not playing
>> those trader. Yeah,
>> you're you're mostly playing against the
game rules unless there's a trader.
There's not always one in the game.
>> But but you know that but but the the
the basic idea is that even in a purely
even a game that's generally assumed to
be co-op, you're still playing against
the world. So it's competitive against
the world and just just not you're not
comp competing against the other human
people that that are playing it. If if
you're competing against anyone is
probably the deciding you know who set
it up to to give you some challenge. So
that's one way to think of all games are
competitive. Obviously the games that
are that people generally think of as
competitive you know zero sum games like
you know chess for instance there one
winner there's one loser and there's a
draw out and nobody wins
uh or uh those those games people
generally think of as competitive but
then that's the other way to think about
cooperation is that all games are also
cooperative because if you don't agree
on the rules if you know if you all
decide not to play on the same rules
then then you've got uh that you don't
actually have game
anymore. So, you all have to cooperate
and say we have the same set we all we
have the same set of rules and we're
going to play according to to to them.
That's not necessarily the same thing as
saying that everyone knows all the
rules. Um, you know, there are plenty of
games, especially computer games where,
you know, you're going into the game not
knowing all the rules and you're going
to try to figure out the rules of being
what the system lets you. Um, role
playing games where you're just sort of
like, you know, I want to do this. I
want to, you know, get drunk now. And
how do I do that? And then the GM tells
you the rules, you know, role against
your your
>> constitution.
>> Constitution. Is it the constitution?
>> Yeah, probably. But
>> always good possibly.
Um then uh uh and then and then and then
you you get told the rules and then you
you go and do it. Um live action role
playing. I know there's a bunch of
people here who who play that. You
usually get a subset of all the rules
that were written for the game. like you
get the subset that pertains to you and
you assume that everybody else has the
subset that pertains pertains to them
and that they're playing according to
it. It's a strong order system and that
and even in a game especially the kinds
that have played in in in MIT which are
fiercely competitive you know it's like
you're literally there assassin games
you literally want to lead someone into
a dark alley and shoot them. uh because
even then you have to assume that
whatever rules that person you're
leading down a dark alley in order to
shoot them um whatever rules they got
they're playing by those rules. They're
not going to say you know it's like if
hey if you shoot them man say that
didn't work. You have to assume that
actually didn't work because they have
rules that tell them when it works and
when it didn't work. Um so so that's so
it's still cooperated even though it's
is competitive play and uh uh some
terminology now um the systemic
cooperation which is you know is what
I'm describing is the you are agreeing
that the system works and you are
agreeing how the system works. These are
the ways how I'm going to interact with
the system. when you're playing uh
Golden Eye or Perfect Dark um on a split
screen or Halo on split screen and you
agree not to look at somebody else's
screen. Um then you know then that's a
system then that's systematic rule. You
might also decide no it's on the screen
I can't avoid seeing it. Therefore we
can all look at each other's screen.
That also systemic rule
>> even though the goals are the same.
Let's shoot each other. Um and and then
there's player cooperation which is a
little bit more like uh the games like
pandemic and death or dead. So yeah,
explicitly trying to help each other
attain a shared goal. Um and that I'm
just trying to sort of like
differentiate the the the two because
it's useful sometimes to sort of try to
to figure out um the differences.
There's a game um that I don't think who
I'm making you play called the war on
terror uh that we have in the uh in the
lab. And one of the things about this
game is that this game actually doesn't
end. Um if you look at the rules, it
seems like there are conditions for the
game to end, but they're really really
hard to reach. Um and and if you're
interested in seeing how the game ends,
you know, I I'll be happy to to pass you
the board and you can try and figure it
out or or play it. But of course, that's
the point that they're trying to make,
right? It's war and turn. It never
really ends. You just keep going. Uh it
perpet perpetuates your the audience
yourself. And it's designed to be a
cooperative uh to be a competitive game.
Everybody tries to take down all the
other states, the other nation states by
either sponsoring terrorist activity or
trying to put to defend themselves from
terrorist activity, which means
everybody's responsible for terrorism in
the end. in the game. Um, and but but in
the end, what they're hoping is that at
some point of time, the players are
going to cooperate because this game is
not going to end. That that was the
whole point of of of the game and and
the entire group coming to that
conclusion in a shared way, you know, is
kind of what the game designers were
trying to go for. Um, it's a funny game.
Anybody who play Crunch is the same is
done by the same folks, but it's uh a
little a little bit more on the we have
an opinion and we want you to hear it
than you know this is a game that you
actually want to try to play. Um it's
funny it has a butter color with the
word evil on it
and you wear it at a specific time.
So um so so that so that's some opinions
about uh cooperation. That's there
systemic cooperation where you're
agreeing on the rules or you're agreeing
that the system works. Um and there's
player cooperation which means players
are actually agreeing to work towards
some sort of shadow goal. And there are
games where it flips between cooperation
and player cooperation player
competition. It's like uh web um castle
crashes. Who's played Castle Crashers?
>> The game's awesome. It's a great game.
It's Xbox Live arcade game. You run
around. It's a sidescrolling game where
you're a little knight with, you know, a
sword.
>> Oh, it's a sword.
>> Well, no, it's it's an axe. Give me a
fish.
>> Some sort of legending device. Um,
>> yeah, fish.
>> A fish is awesome.
>> And and and in general, you know, if
you're playing with three other people
with controllers right next to you on
the couch, you're pretty much going for
the same goal. There are there are you
four and there are a whole bunch of
baddies on screen and you just prime and
kill it all.
>> But then as soon as you beat the last
one, the the game switches from defeat
all the baddies to save the princess.
And wait, wait a minute. That's one.
>> No, no, you've already saved the
princess. It goes from
>> to get the princess.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it's get it becomes get the
princess. There's one princess that has
four knights and it becomes a
competitive game. of it's like
everything that you're using against the
the baddies becomes something that you
use on your teammates. Um and and there
are games that flip-flop between that
diplomacy is a really fluid game with
their friends. It's like you have to
assume everybody's competitive in that
game, but the only way to attain your
goals is to cooperate occasionally. Um
and and so and so you all that's player
cooperation. No one's disagreeing on
rules. So that's there systemic
cooperation all the way through but then
there's clear competition and
cooperation back and forth. Um so you
know uh so that's cooperation.
Um finally uh
think think a little bit about level
playing field or what it means in your
game to have a level playing field. Cuz
you know in many of your games
especially car games you're going to
start with some sort of deal. you're
going to start with some sort of hand or
maybe a drawing in some sort of
systematic way from a shuffle deck. That
pretty much means that you know uh
you're starting out with something
that's effectively random, but then um
it could be also influenced by your
knowledge of the game, like skill of the
game. Um and uh and you want to see how
h at what point h how how do you want to
balance it between someone's skill
familiarity with the game against pure
chance right you know um a level playing
field means a lot means a different
thing to a lot of different people uh
some people's mean uh for some people it
may mean no matter what skill level I am
I have a chance at winning so you're
sort of biasing it towards chance for
some people it means Um a level playing
field is no matter what hand I I get
given there is a valid strategy or the
goals then get set in a way that allows
me to attain it. A lot of trick- taking
games especially games with with bidding
actually have auto automatic correcting
system in in there is like you only bid
a game that you think that you can win.
Um, and the whole idea is the game is to
push your opponent to bid on something
which they couldn't uh which they
couldn't actually get. So, you know,
that's that's a double playing field,
right? You actually have a crappy hand,
but that's not chance so much as
as the as the decisions that you're
making. So
um
so the
what I will advocate in this class um if
there's still time in the testing and
there's of course there's two more
coming back to this so so so so
is when you're trying to balance it out
towards whatever your interpretation of
a level playing field is going to be um
try to pick uh decisions that sort of
push you in the direction of meaningful
the decisions things that players can
make a decision and they can see the
consequences. They can understand how
those consequences play out in the game
um and the outcome and the outcome of
the overall game is going to be going to
be a result of that. Um that is again
not necessarily the only definition. So
I want to be very very clear what I'm
asking of you here is not necessarily
the only definition of a well-designed
game. Um, you're designing a game to be
p played from ages 3 to 90. You know,
you probably want a game where making a
meaningful decision isn't going to bias
the game to the point that the really
experienced people or really smart
people are going to end up winning this
game because that's just not for the
three of us. Um now in this part in this
part particular class um try to bias it
so that in that competitive sense you
want everyone to feel like they have a
chance of winning but I want you to bias
your game towards the and whe and and
whether you win or lose is going to be
based on the outcome of these decisions.
clearly understanding the outcome of
position that you made in the game, not
necessarily just what you would what
what you were dealt or what you were
shar
um
you can still use those things in a
game, right? You know, sometimes it's,
you know, the whole idea of, oh my god,
I hope this red card, I hope this red
card, you know, it's like, oh, but then
but then you think things like
probability, right? You know, it's like
how much information are you giving to
the player about what the probability
that that's the right card going to be?
Are you letting them look at the deck
ahead of time? You know, are you giving
them information about how many of those
cards are in the deck, you know, so that
they can actually make guesses on all
right, we've played through half this
deck and we haven't seen any of those
cards yet, that means my the probability
of that card showing up is now gone up.
And that's now we come to the decision
that you get to make. Do I do I draw? Do
I you know do I hold that that so uh so
try so that's my suggestion for this
class I would love it to be able to see
a little bit to to to see those kinds of
uh those kind of things come out come
come out this class
um okay
so that's uh that's all the things that
have remaining there so now we can erase
that after this class
all right so uh now on actually Before
we move on, anyone have any questions
regarding that?
No.
Um, one point of administration. Um, who
here needs to print on Gambit printers,
right? Or who here has access to other
printers that you guys are fairly
confident about using for your
assignment?
>> You need
>> No, I mean, would you say that you need
a printer or you have access? You said
both.
>> All right. So, who needs to use camera
printers? Uh, who absolutely needs to
use candle printers? Okay, because we
don't we don't actually have like a
computer set up for anybody to to log in
and actually all our Europs just started
working. So, I would suggest not using
any of the computers in this lab because
lab work on it. Um, okay. So, if you've
all got access to printers, that's
awesome. Um, I know you sent an email
about card stock. Uh that that card
stock's actually out of stock.
>> That's ironic.
>> Yeah. I went to order it and I was like,
"Oh shit."
>> I'm going to take off with a long time,
but I'm sure there's other card stock.
>> Um
>> isn't there like a Staples or somewhere?
>> Tech has Staples. Stock Town has
Staples.
>> Copy Tech has I went to Copy Tech and
they said they can print and cut your
cards for you.
>> Nice.
>> Yeah. Yeah. They they they they have a
pretty awesome uh card printer. They the
their cutter is harsh harsh harsh. Um,
>> what does that what does that mean?
>> Well, first of all, really pointy at the
corners, which is kind of cool if that's
what you were going for, but I don't
think
>> Can they Can they roundy it or do we
have to use
>> I don't
>> They can't.
>> They They can't. I have a rounder. Uh, I
have a corner punch that, you know, you
have to do it four times for each card.
So,
>> we can we'll do it. You can do it.
>> Yeah. just ask me and you can borrow it.
You may want to do it on some test cards
before doing it on all your questions to
get a sense of how it works. It works
better on card stock than it does on
paper. Uh and I wouldn't suggest
punching more than one card at a time.
The the other thing is um if you're
printing it on a um not like copy check
where they obviously know what kind of
paper goes best with their printers. you
know, if you're printing it on something
like a laser jet, uh, if you go to the
paper manufacturers's website, they
actually, a lot of them actually
specifically say laser jet compatible.
Um, and the problem isn't actually the
weight of the card. It's not like the
folding of the paper as it goes through
the printer. It's whether the toner will
bond to the paper, like does the paper
get hot enough, you know, without
catching fire. Um, does the paper get
hot enough for the toner to actually
bond? Um, and a lot of card stocks
actually don't because they're so thick
that the heat doesn't transfer well. And
as a result of that, other prints, it
looks great when it comes out and it
starts flaking. Uh, so that's that's
that's the problem that you can cast
off. Sure, some card stocks just jam
your printer, but majority of modern
laser jets actually deal pretty well
with that. It gets worse with it with
paper.
>> Uh, did you want us to print on card
stock for Wednesday or was that for when
it's due?
>> When it's due.
>> Okay. So when
>> and in fact printing card stock for when
it's due is not necessary. It is it is
much appreciated.
It was a great thing for you to do for
yourself if you want to make copies for
your friends or your team uh that you
actually want to end up playing. Uh to
be perfectly honest, if you say, you
know, we our printer wasn't working and
all we could do were these like regular
weight papers, but it's all been cut in
the right shape so that I can make so
that we can just play the game. That's
fine. We can still, you know, we're not
going to take the weight of your paper
into the cover.
>> Weigh the deck first.
>> G per card. It's in size.
>> All right. If anyone played what was it?
Modern uh high society books or
something.
>> Yes,
>> those are awesome.
>> They were like they were like they were
like kids books, you know.
>> All right, cool. Um if anyone does have
issues printing, uh before you jump
straight into the gamma print printer,
talk talk to Jason or I. Uh you know,
Jason is usually in a room right next to
TV lounge, my room, which is down the
corridor. Uh and we can and we might be
able to help you with with that. But in
general, if you got access to other
printers, go right for it because going
to run us like
again not for Wednesday. For Wednesday,
just have something testable so that uh
can uh folks can print but before the
date is due try to print something. Uh
you don't want to leave it till last
minute and you don't want to like
suddenly realize that your paper doesn't
work very well with the printer on the
last minute.
Okay.
Right. So uh today's reading was Bartle
and uh chapter 11 I think of the uh of
breathway as well and um in general
they have both them are asking the same
question which is who are you designing
your game for um on the assumption that
it's not you're not designing the game
for yourself and of course realistically
if you're going to get a job making
games that's the majority of the games
that you're going to design are not
games like uh games for something in the
game for some other demographic. Um and
um the bar paper is a little bit more
influential in sort of uh helping people
think about uh games because it kind of
shifted the question from what's the age
group, what's the demographic, you know,
what do people out there who are already
buying games going to want? Uh and he
kind of flipped that into what sort of
things are people looking for in the
game. um he doesn't actually take it to
the next step which is where well I
think he wrote that in the 70s or the
80s I did anyone remember
>> I think it was like 90
I think
was 1990s
>> right
he talks about actually
>> no ever that's right um but uh he but a
lot of the the ideas come from the 70s
actually because that's when he made the
first mod. Uh Richard B.
>> What exactly is a mud? They never
actually described. I just said assumed
everyone knew what a mud was.
>> Mud stands for multi-user engine. Anyone
want to describe that?
>> It's like
like an online text adventure thing
where everyone's kind of like
interacting with the same text base
dungeon thing. Let's describe is imagine
that wow was presented inactic fiction.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> So that's I found that kind of annoying
in the text. He just assumed everyone
knew what mud was but never actually
said this is what mud is.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Because because the the the
folks who are reading their article
actually I believe he formatted that for
a forum post for a mud community. So
that's assumption.
Um but yeah um apologies for that. Um
actually if you're interested he does
define it right at the bottom which is
like right at the end of the article.
here she talks about specifically this
is what I I mean by somewhere in the
footnote says there's like you know
these text text adventures uh text style
online games with multiple people
interacting and uh and if you look at
the rest of the website there's actually
a bunch of stuff about how work but for
the most part that was that was sort of
online multiplayer gaming uh back when
he started um he was he's he's credited
for having built the first the first one
and frankly
not all that different from MMOGs that
you get today. Uh, you know, the
difference being that they were all
text, but you still went out hunting
uh uh monsters. They call them mobiles
or mobs. And in fact, actually, there's
still some of the terminology they're
playing around. Um, they drop loot. You
know, you will pick up this loot and
show it off. And sometimes some games
that you sell off the loot, some that
most games that you exchange loot uh and
then you would use your loot to go and
kill other monsters and get better loot.
Uh sometimes you do it with other
people. Sometimes you attack other
people. Uh sometimes you just hang
around and chat and talk about things
that are completely not in game like
what if I have a bunch of
some awesome Um
and uh sometimes sometimes it will take
multiple people to take down a to take a
monster you know and it was just handled
that you know how fast can you type kind
of thing. Um you know attack monster
attack monster attack and I think you
can just hit repeat
um and uh but uh
the behaviors are also not all that
different. And um how he describes it is
a whole a a game kind will will kind of
sight sight itself in a position where
it is like ve variably
appealing to various kinds of players.
Uh and that's how he describes it. Where
game studies has kind of gone to on
since then is the realization that just
because you're uh actually some people
throw out the four types that he that he
>> explorers
and killers. Yeah. So you know it's like
there are these four types of players
and just like just because you're
achiever in one game doesn't necessarily
mean that you're going to be achie
nothing. different people play different
games or possibly even different times
of the day in the same game for
different reasons. Uh and uh and that's
where we go back to earlier concepts
that we brought up in this class like
the different kind kinds of fun. What
are people trying to get out of their
game, right? Um so but he was you know
um if you're looking at the context of
any one mud you know and a little slice
of what you saw of somebody's
personality when they were logged in and
all the things that they were doing and
it and the kinds of things that they
tended to keep doing every time you
logged in. It was fairly easy to sort of
stereotype them into somewhere along
those lines. Even he acknowledges that
nobody's really all the way on on one of
these lines. grief griefers I I think
are the words that I hear generally use
for killers nowadays, but even then
that's not quite the way that he's using
it. He's actually using it as somebody
who's generally still playing by the
rules of game, you know, u you know,
they're not they're out there to cause
misery to other people, but they're not
there to break the game. Um there's
there is a class of people of reavers
where they're deliberately trying to
find ways to exploit the system to just
make to make the game just kind of
silly. Um but all the other dynamically
it draws are very much there. It's like
you get a whole bunch of socializers
together, people who want to do nothing
but chat and have a good time. Uh don't
really care about game and it's going to
be a whole bunch of people going right
after them and saying these are great
people to grief. uh you know because
they are enjoying themselves so much. We
could end that.
Um Second Life, you guessed a lot of
this because Second Life has that whole
like uh um you know, you can do anything
you want and socializing is one of the
big things. Uh personalizing is one of
those big things. But um so so so do
keep in mind that you know um that the
way that he's talking about it sounds
like all of these different
personalities are somewhat mutually
exclusive when really the discussion has
come has now come on to how do you sort
of cater to all of these uh different to
all of these different desires at any
given time. I may be achiever today, I
may be an explorer tomorrow. And he even
talks about explorers thinking that
achievers are beginner explorers, you
know, because it's like once you've
already beaten the game, what else is
there left to do but explore what else
the game can do, you know? So, so, so
that's so he he himself acknowledges
that there's some personality transfer
that can happen.
Uh, but it's kind of interesting how he
talks about the feedback loops about of
people, right? You know, it's like you
get a whole bunch of um what was it? You
get a whole bunch of achievers and you
get a whole bunch of um
>> socializing
increases.
>> Yeah, increases because the competition
is now higher or something like that.
But he also makes this weird assumption
that there is a finite pool of people
who can be playing the game which is
actually true. Even in a, you know,
a 10 to 20 million player game like
World of Warcraft, you know, all those
things have to be um like we don't have
20 million people logging on to one
server, you know,
they say I want eight eight heights of
sheep or something,
>> right?
>> Eight sheep.
>> Exactly. Exactly. And then like once you
hit level 80, you can start uh doing
these raids that are just really big
down
>> for lots of people. Uh like 25. It's
currently 25 is the highest. They used
to be like 40. Um but yeah, and you just
kill bigger monsters and get lots of
boot. Um, and then there's PvP, which
you go, the main thing right now is like
arenas, and you have a team of two or
three or five, and you fight other
players with your gear that you obtain
by doing battlegrounds and and lots of
arena. Uh, yeah, and it's that's
basically WoW.
>> They use um I can't remember. Are there
roleplay servers?
>> Yes, there are world roleplay servers. I
have actually never visited one
>> so I can't talk about that.
>> So it's a lot of dancing.
>> Dance is a you know typing in slash
dance made your your your character
dance and it was one of those things
that really is popular among socialized
type uh players all all over any
episode. Um but it's not just a I mean
slash dance means other things now. It
it could it could be I'm bored, right?
You know, it's like I have nothing to do
right now. I have to wait for this
stupid thing to respond. I guess
it's it's more fun than just standing
there. Um
but the uh uh there is a group in in WoW
and I I guess I would may maybe not a
group there is there there are folks who
play World of Warcraft um and they
engage in this thing called theory craft
which is how do we optimize uh the way
how you build a character um and uh to
the and the things that you equip a play
a character for to be make that
character really really good at doing
one or two different things. Um, so if
you're building up, you know, a
character that's designed to heal, you
know, what class should they be, what
race should they be, what equipment
should they be getting, you know,
depending on what amount of time you are
in in the game. Um, and uh, you know,
they're they're going to try to like
derive as much of math of of the kind
of, you know, cause and effect in
anything as we possibly can. Um, there's
a client called the STS uh, which uh,
which which is I can't remember if they
actually exclam
>> um it's actually kind of funny uh the
elitist jerks forums had one guy who
just happened to write a artic a forum
post about dressing up in real life like
you know like this is how you get like
really nice Taylor clothes and these are
things you'll be looking for because he
worked at a men so
uh fashion uh space. Um and it turned
out that that community was really
really really interested in learning
more about that. Uh you know, which is
actually not that weird, right? It's
like you care about what armor you get
in the game. If you care about what
clothes you wear in real life,
especially if it might have some impact
on your real life, the job that you're
looking for. Okay? You know, so um so I
would actually put those more in the
explorers part of thing, you know. Sure,
they're looking for to optimize. They're
looking to do the best, but they're not
looking to be necessarily rewarded by
the game system. They're using the game
system to test their ideas against, you
know, it's like, I'm looking for a
better way to to suck up more damage,
you know, because I'm a tank. I I'm I'm
supposedly absorbing all the damage all
all the other call it uh uh all the
attentions of the of the of the
characters being controlled by the
computer. while the rest of my folks who
put out a lot of damage, you know, can
do their job. Um, but I'm not interested
in what the system has deemed to be you
have absolved tons of damage. Good job.
I don't care what the system says. I
care how the system operates so that I
can optimize it through some sort of
metric that I figured out and my friends
have figured out and the community has
figured out. So, I want to understand
the system in the end. that's what it
comes down to the the metric that
they're using it is how do I optimize
but for the most part uh people who
engage in that kind of theory craft you
know it's like oh no this this armor
combined with those pants uh you know I
now find proof or something uh you know
those are those are well in the area of
explor
behavior seems very much let's find the
best solution whereas achievers are very
much folks like you know how do I get to
level you know it's like um how do I get
the coolest
in World of Warcraft right hands. Um,
you know, and every once in a while
Blizzard, the company that makes it will
release some of your stuff and the
achievers are like, I got to get that.
You know, it's like uh because the
stakes are usually high and it takes a
lot of effort and a lot of money to be
able to get one of those things, but and
to be able to get it gives you some
recognizable status. You'll see someone
with the limited edition some kind of uh
amount and you only and you know that
the only that they could have done that
is to spend a heck of a lot of time in
this game and play the game really well.
You know, that's that's the kind of
recognition they're looking for. So,
that's kind of the difference between
achievements and sports.
Um so I actually want to try one little
activity which is I got that I got the
chart that um uh
uh lays out the whole player versus you
know player interacting and acting
player and and the world um and he uses
this to describe where your game could
be at any given time. you know, if
you're acting on players, then you know,
you're the kind of person uh then then
your game is kind of biased towards
killers. Uh if you are in if you're more
if you're designing your game to be more
about interacting with other players,
then you're sort of biasing it towards
the socializers. Interacting with the
world is more the achievers, you know.
Oh, sorry. No, acting on on the world is
more the achievers, you know. And given
these quests, I've beaten all the quests
and like 100 per
the the quest told me that's
achievements. And uh interacting with
the world is more of the explorance.
It's like you know um what else can I do
with this world? You know, there are
these goals that are set. That's great,
but other than this world that I can do
good stuff. I found the distinction
between acting and interacting
incredibly
hard to get at. Like I didn't really
understand what he was trying to say. It
was it was easier. I think he he came
across those two terms because they
sounded cute. Uh you know acting
interacting is like
>> I mean how do you interact without
acting?
>> Well what does what does that mean?
>> Yeah it's um
>> and like the the really classic example
they use like that acting on a player is
like a killer
>> trying to attack another player but like
the other player fights back. There's an
interaction there. Right.
>> Sure. But the thing about it,
>> what's he trying to say?
>> Ah, so what so I believe what he means
by that is that the killer is actually
less interested in what the the player
does back to them. I mean, in some
sense, they are interacting because
they're trying to see what sort of
response they get, right? And it's like,
I'm going to do something to this
player. This player is either going to
die or fight back or whine uh about the
fact that I'm hating them so much. Um,
but they're not looking for the
competitive fit. They're they're not
really interested in you and now that
person going to turn around and attack
me.
>> I know. But the whole point is supposed
to be that the killers are griefers. So
they really care about how people
respond to them. Like he he says later
on that like one of the most annoying
things you can do to a griefer is just
ignore them, not rise to the debate,
right? So interacting
>> seems to be the crucial thing. So again,
I feel like he's
>> well, okay. So yeah, I I admit that the
terms are, but uh well, I guess if I can
jump how I kind of perceive it as like
does the person care about how the other
thing works in a sense, you know what I
mean? So it's like it is it is the case
that a griefer wants to get a certain
reaction, but like beyond that, it
doesn't matter, right? So in the same
case with the game system, right? like I
want it to do this thing. I want it to
give me points, but why it did that or
how the mechanic works is kind of
irrelevant. I don't know. I mean, that's
kind of how I understood it.
>> Well, well, in particular, like with the
the interacting
when when somebody is like trying to
player kill or something, it the the
reaction is not necessarily the reaction
they're looking for is to like piss
somebody off, right? Um, and that
reaction is not necessarily part of the
game.
So like the the the the it it is acting
on them because you are taking like what
the game allows you to do and using this
against a person but you don't care
about what they use in the game against
you. You you more care about this like
abstract idea.
>> So I think the the interaction is not
actually part of the game. So acting is
specifically to do with game mechanics
whereas interacting is to do with
something which is so maybe acting is
like something mechanical whereas
interacting is something dynamics
related or like well I I see it as like
acting is
um sort of like a a single direction
with mechanics. So, for example, the
mechanic there is is being able to like
hit somebody in the head with your
sword, right?
>> Um whereas interacting would be the case
where you're hitting each other on each
other's heads with your sword, which is
an entirely different thing and is more
of like a competitive thing rather than
the I just want to make you angry.
>> Well, and I think the unidirectional
perspective makes sense. Um you could
think of it as going with the hitting on
the head example, right? If I'm acting,
then I care that information is flowing
one way. I am dealing damage to you. If
I'm interacting, I'm curious as to like
how that is computed and what that means
for me in return.
>> Does that make sense? So like if I'm
>> really bad terminology
a bunch of other examples of things that
you do to like maximize interacting
versus acting and like the interacting
examples are things like make make
simple puzzles and then the acting ones
are like make hard puzzles and like
>> wait what what
so so in the context of a mud a puzzle
is often like a door right you know it's
like you've got to solve this puzzle be
able to get into a new area because
that's really the only thing that like
sometimes you get new loot. Um, and the
idea behind that is if you're sort of if
you're sort of either privileging it to
getting people to uh talk with each
other more and socialize with each other
more or you're privileging it to getting
people to look at the world more, see
more of the world and and and and
understand how how it works. Then in a
sense you don't want to put too many
barriers between you know the people
who've been playing for a long time and
people who just started playing the
people who uh uh uh you know who are in
one area of the world and people who are
in another area of the world you kind of
want quick flow. So in muds that's that
that's one thing where the the
definition of puzzle is very specific.
It's like but I have to move this set of
levers. This is another another point
that I found was really strange because
I would expect an explorer who is a
supposed to be a world interacting
person
>> to really enjoy deep puzzles which
reward them for knowing a lot about the
world.
>> Ah but the problem with puzzles in Merks
is that they're usual they're usually
single solution.
>> That's the so there's less pleasure to
be uh to be found in a very difficult
puzzle because all that told you was you
just solved this one thing. There is
still puzzle that there is still some
pleasure there. The interest that most
that that explorers are way more
compelled by kind of like that uh like
the dynamics right is like understanding
the interaction of how of mechanics
especially if they behave in a way that
might not have been originally designed
that way you know it's like that's what
they're looking for. They're not looking
for what is the solution that was
designed in the game. They're looking
for how do I get this game to do
something that it might not have been
designed to do originally but will be
cool once they figure it out. Um so so
that I mean that that unfortunately
you're absolutely right that one but
that one suffers from the very specific
terminology of what a puzzle is and as
opposed to the sort of more general
definition of what a puzzle is. Um, the
reason why why at least for achievers,
hard puzzles are very important because
there's because if you make a puzzle
that most people aren't going to be able
to get, being able to get that puzzle
gives you some bad status. Usually some
sort of visible reward even. It's like
you're now in a location that nobody
else can get to or you're now you now
have have a piece of equipment that that
that no one else has. Whereas explorers,
you know, they will probably have a
advantage in solving difficult puzzles,
but they're not necessarily the sort of
thing that makes them want to interact
well. You know, they lots of mechanics
that sort of interact with each other in
really really interesting ways, more
likely to be interested to explore.
Um, but you're right, acting and
interacting crappy crappy terminology.
Like
>> I mean you're talking about how reefers
are more like actors where they just
they try to get people to interact with
them or try to get people to get annoyed
them. I've definitely seen actually it
was last year we took game design but
not not game inter uh 300 where we
watched a video of briefers in uh Team
Fortress 2 where there's a
>> like there's a certain door that if they
stand in a certain spot that it won't
open. So this person started making
everyone interact like, "Okay, we're
going to play a game show. Do you want
to leave? You have to answer correctly."
>> Yeah. What is the capital of
>> See, like that that I see that as more
of like an explorer thing. Like you you
found some some weird combination of the
interaction and the mechanics that
allows you to do something new,
>> which is turn Team Fortress 2 into a
game show.
>> It was pretty funny.
>> Can't fight.
>> Grief Explorer is a combination of
bubble types, right? if you're going to
be a successful breeder.
>> I mean, and and that's absolutely true,
right? In all in order to be to if your
personality is oriented one way, you may
have to engage in some other behaviors
in order to be able to
in order to be able to maximize that
that core behavior that you're looking
for. So yeah, you know, people who are
looking at exploits uh at at at try
trying to understand how the world works
so they can cause maximum damage and
maximum grief to other people, you know,
uh it's that's definitely one good way
of doing it. But what I find is that as
soon as they find it, they're not
interested in finding more ways until
that first way gets boring, you know,
or or or gets fixed.
So, Team Fortress, I know there's a lot
of like teleporting you directly in
front of turret and stuff like that.
Teleporting your own teammates in front
of turret. It's like
that.
>> I don't understand.
>> You don't understand. What?
>> It's grief.
>> No, it's not actually fun.
>> It's like I'm going to mess with you
just for the hell of it. Um, I remember
in Sims Online, an effective way to
greet would be to organize a band of
people and arrive in a property since
there was a population limit.
>> Mhm.
>> Like 12 people or something on any given
lot. If that lot was a business that
required a lot of people to come through
and then you just had 12 of your people
show up and then like mill around and
sell out profanities, you could tie the
place and lock it up. No one else could
go there, visit it, sometimes including
other owners and stuff like that. It was
very frustrating.
>> Um, in fact, some of that behavior they
got towards organized crime level
actually. I mean, I would call it real
crime. It was virtual. But um there
there are actually good number of
articles about the Sims online mafia
because um that game had so much so much
built in for actually for socializers um
to be able to communicate, express
yourself. I mean, if you played the
original Sims, there's the whole range
of different expressive things that you
can do to sort of communicate how you're
feeling and and uh and and to be able
chatting with people. And um someone I
think it might have been Max itself
actually like charted out the web the
web of influence of all the players and
there was like one alpha player, you
know, that was kind of in charge of
everything. Uh and if and if she decided
that nobody was going that that you know
that this person was someone that she
didn't want uh spending too much time
with online because somehow pissed her
off or or you know pissed one of her
friends off or something and then she
organized it like that very very
effectively. Um it was called the second
market. Uh and you get that in in you
you'll get that similar behavior in
second a lot. Um, but and it's kind of
interesting to see how different worlds
respond to that. Eve online, I think, is
the world which is well actually one one
thing I'd like to do is I like to throw
different games up on that chart. Um, so
um I am looking mostly at multiplayer
games, specifically
pre preferably online multiplayer games.
Um, but and I don't know all all the
games that are out there. So, I'd like
people to like sort of call out games
and tell me roughly where it should be
put up. If you disagree, then by all
means, put up your hand and suggest that
it should be moved.
>> Uh, Minecraft should go definitely
towards like world interacting like
explorer bit.
>> You're far far.
>> So, what is Minecraft? I've heard of it.
I just don't know what exactly.
>> Basically, go around mining things and
creating objects and you can create like
your own worlds. So it's kind of like I
guess
>> Eve is definitely a world interacting as
well.
>> Yeah.
>> So about that same as Eve.
>> Uh I would say Eve is also player
interacting.
>> Yeah. I mean I guess then I see it's in
the middle then like you have to form
corporations of bunches of people in
order to do anything.
>> That's true. You have to you have to be
really good at social skills actually.
Is that one of the games that's like
most ruthless?
>> Yeah, I interact with people and the
world a lot.
>> Like I think it's more strongly player
interacting and world interacting than
most games.
>> You cannot you cannot ignore this in any
particular
>> but there's also like a huge amount of
achievement and player versus player
conflict and this kind of stuff, right?
So clearly surely it shouldn't be that
far down the interacting scale.
I mean consider for instance Second Life
instead which would be like way further
down the interacting
end of the spectrum online surely
>> assuming that
>> I'm not sure like PvP is the opposite.
>> Yeah. No, I mean it's not
>> I think it's definitely player
interaction more than player action.
>> Yeah, I believe something like having
PvP tournaments I think would be
definitely a lot of interaction. Yeah, I
think that's that's like the distinction
between griefing and like people
fighting each other.
>> Griefing can be interacting too. Like
how he put it. I what I got from his
article is that acting was like I go and
kill someone and ha I killed them and
that's it. Or I go through the world
like I killed monster, I killed monster
and you just have a goal and you want to
get the goal instead of emerging from
your goal. Um so I don't know. I
definitely think there griefing can be
hugely interactive. Like there could be
a whole bunch of like if you in Eve if
you infiltrate someone's company
>> and you like steal$10.
>> Exactly. Like that's hugely interactive
griefing.
>> But the briefing consider Team Fortress,
right? Is Team Fortress player
interacting because that means it's a
socializer game.
>> I I I personally do not think Team
Fortress calls them a player
interacting. Yes, but but um Left for
Dead is
>> uh
>> definitely interaction.
>> I would say probably more well it
depends on what way you're doing.
>> Horrible.
>> So
>> with Left for Dead, you can play you're
interacting but then you're also like
online you can go against other players
who are actually the zombies against
you.
>> Right. So So let's talk about the basic
mode where you don't have that.
>> Yeah, that's about those modes
separately.
>> Yeah. Right. So the basic most common
mode it's going to be four players
playing cooperative cooperatively
against the game world.
>> Um
>> that's just interacting world
>> and
there is
a lot of interaction that goes on uh
between players because you cannot
basically survive unless you get keep
each other's backs. So, I would say
>> and there's and there's built-in Well,
one second. And there's built-in
functions to help other people. So,
someone might get knocked off the ledge
and be holding on. You have to pull it
back up. Um, at the same time,
>> at the same time, there's also an
intelligent engine that sort of plans
that level for you and places zombies
strategically to maintain you in a state
of nervousness. Um, and so it's
different every single time you play.
Uh, so those kind of balance out and
probably place it somewhere in the
middle. maybe a little bit more player
bias than world bias because you really
have to stick together.
>> So, so it's weird because it almost like
you want to have like a plane.
>> It's in like Yeah.
>> I think it' be Yeah. I think the big
problem with this sort of graph is that
you can't really necessarily separate
games into one of these quadrants.
>> Um
>> games
world and that is actually more
interaction. It might be a little more
useful to actually draw like areas
within the graph to sort of like
represent a game. I guess draw an area
that encompasses like all the pieces the
game sort of
can be complicated with games that have
very distinct modes, you know, like Halo
co-op and Halo multiplayer and Halo
Slayer very different.
>> Uh but yeah,
that will probably be a good refinement
is just like create some sort of like
scatter charts all over again
>> because I could definitely see there
being a game where there's a lot of
acting on the world and interacting with
players and if you're just separating
you know these into distinct points that
isn't possible with this graph
>> right so that's another problem problem
is the assumption that
acting and interacting are like like
mutually opposite at least for these two
axes it almost seems like you know do
people generally accept
No, that one less than that interacting.
>> If you just warp space and then you can
have like different quadrants
overlapping
>> I think different values for like player
world interacting and acting. They
shouldn't necessarily be connected.
>> I think Eve definitely world is very
high and player is very high. World is
very high. Player is very high. But as
player is interacting and the world is
active world,
>> I mean because I mean you don't I mean
you're exploring the world spatially a
lot. Are you exploring the systems of
the world or not or you really exploring
the system by people?
>> That's true.
I mean the nice thing about um what you
know things like uh EO 9 uh for folks
who don't know EVA line is a space
exploration game basically where uh
where you start off as a captain correct
me if I'm wrong or people
>> pretty much a super sandbox game.
>> Yeah. Well um but for the most part
you're traveling in space that's that
that you get out of your ship and like
walk on foot.
>> Have they added that? cuz I know they
wanted to add an expansion where you
could actually walk on planets. Last
time I heard they hadn't.
>> Last time I heard they had dust 66 or
something like that.
>> Yeah, which is a separate game.
>> It's a separate game. So So no, you're
traveling through space. You're not like
landing anything. Uh but you're but the
whole idea is that it's all built around
this economy where you know you can do
things like mining. Of course you and
can cash. But the real power in in in in
the game comes when players start to
ally with each other. Form form armadas,
form trade trade groups, you know, form
areas that you can patrol and control uh
uh and you know, areas where if you
don't agree if you don't get along with
the the people who are in control of the
space, you will die once you fly there.
And the only the only thing that's
really making that happen are other
players deciding that this social
contract is is
so it's pretty damn amazing. What uh
some folks were talking about earlier
was there was a big story about how um
basically one person got into very very
powerful position in one of these plants
and decided to be back taking the
majority of one uh of one plant's
financial resources with that person.
And remember, this is a this is a fairly
modern people online game. All in game
assets cannot be traded for real money.
>> It's it's illegal. So that
>> illegal like in game so you can get your
account banned.
>> But so what I so what happened was if I
talking about the one that you're
talking about, someone got to a really
power place in like this banking clan
and then took all of their assets and
traded for real money. So got $10,000 by
trading by selling it on
One,
>> one was a guy who infiltrated heck of a
bunch of money. One was like a parent
who was going through financial trouble
and held like a fifth of the assets of
some of like the major bank and cashed
it in for like $6,000 to help pay off
part of his house and like his kids
medical bills and then posted a poly and
quit the game.
>> I thought you got banned from the game.
>> He was banned from the game, but he he
also quit the game.
because there's no coffee.
>> Yeah. He was like, "I'm sorry everybody,
but uh this guy."
>> I mean, the the amazing one was the guy
who actually infiltrated the company and
just like took it down as like a year
years longer.
>> He was their friend and all that.
>> Yeah.
Trying to get in and then managed to
take down this gigantic in-game
corporation.
>> How many How many players are you
online? Active players.
>> No, I feel like active players are It
sounds a lot moment.
>> Yeah. No, I mean
active we have active accounts.
>> Are they are do they have like new
players arriving regularly?
>> They're the kind of game that's they've
been like
>> it's like a ridiculous learning curve.
>> Yeah. It's like four months or
something. It's insane. But it's uh but
but the interesting thing about the
particular case where someone
infiltrated, took all their money and uh
uh and and basically decimated uh this
plan deliberately was that that person
didn't actually give a compound for it.
I believe it was like
>> he was totally sell the most recent one
I read about theoretically had the tens
of thousands of US dollars of assets in
the game and did not cash in any of it
for real money because there is no
authorized mechanism. And the article I
read basically an end note was no one
knows what you can do with it. He's
technically rich but it's not there's no
good legal mechanism of illegal gain
allowed. I don't think he got banned at
all because it's part of the game. is
it's considered part of and and once and
at least for the definition of Eve uh
stories like that tends to have helped
its reputation or anything as this is
the this is this is the wild west in
space you know and we're trying to
encourage this kind of creative play
>> and you know uh other than the real
money transaction part where you get
your content all that's part of the game
so I'm not entirely sure it became
really confident at griefing you know it
was an incredibly smart practical
>> see I I would not call that griefing
Like it was not I mean it may have been
done to like annoy the people who are
running the company that he took down
but like I see it as exploration like I
am going to try and exploration and
player interaction you know like
>> I would say achieving because I mean
a major corporation all by myself. Yeah,
it might actually be
do you put that in your resume like
single-handedly?
>> I think if you're
>> we could get hired by a lawyer
>> and you don't mind
this company.
>> So, okay. So, what I would actually like
to end this um this with we've got about
15 minutes um the special time I would
say how how many here we have 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 positive.
Awesome. So, groups of four and uh what
I'd like folks to do, am I doing this
right?
>> Yeah. Okay. And and um I'd like folks to
come up with other axis. um you know not
necessarily anything having to do with
with with models. Just give me two
things that you kind of feel are
diametrically opposed but you know in
describing a game or any series of games
you could sort of like place games along
some axis. Um, if you have time, we can
talk about another two different terms,
but you know, something to help describe
to people, you know, okay, this game is
kind of on the far extreme of one, this
game is on the far extreme of the other.
Um, the goal here is to come up with
terms that are that will help you sort
of identify what this who this game
might be targeted towards, you know,
what kind of player this game might be
targeted. not necessarily using bottles
terminology at all, you know, but borrow
terminology as we have said is kind of
weak. Uh so let's so let's throw out
some some some other words, some other
things. Use things that you use to
describe games already, but you know if
that fails because you haven't really
thought about it that way. Come up with
some new words, you know,
>> real English words.
Random versus strategy.
[Music]
Oh,
>> original versus copy.
>> Really? That's why it resonates, right?
It makes it fairly sort of easy to sort
of like discuss this, you know. I mean,
I'd rather use the word trans, but
randomly, you know, get the point across
pretty clearly.
>> Strategy or random versus deterministic,
>> right? So I think that should be random
deterministic and or reactive and
deliberative.
>> I like that.
>> That's fancy.
>> We use good words.
>> Wait. So reactive and deliberative.
and deliberate
>> or random
>> because you can definitely still have
randomness and have strategy,
>> right?
>> But random deterministic.
>> Yeah, then it'll be somewhere on the
axis, right?
>> So,
>> well, I mean, the problem is you can
have like incredible amounts of
randomness, but if you're can just like
figure out the probabilities, you can
still have like an optimal strategy,
right?
>> But then that's rander. Deterministic is
because you can't have a system that's
so complex yet deterministic that
there's no way you can predict what's
going to happen next.
>> Yeah.
>> Robot
is theoretically possible. But uh but
yeah, this is this is
>> player versus system agency. player
versus Oh, so system player is a system
and agency is kind of your it's
distributed.
>> It's a name of your of your tactics,
right?
>> Yes.
>> You also had low learning curve versus
high learning curve.
>> Definitely not into that.
>> Fast versus slow.
So,
>> so another learning another uh axis we
had was um I guess if you call it
the like freedom and like the
predetermined like paths in the game,
>> huh?
>> Constraint.
>> Yeah. Well,
>> freedom versus constraint. Yeah, I can't
remember the terms. Was it like glutus
and py or something like that?
>> Well, okay. So, one word that I use that
I hear often to some describe games on
rails.
>> Yes.
>> Um I mean
13 hours of Final Fantasy
unreal. You get to do one thing, you get
to push the X button for 60 hours.
I would say a subset of what you're
talking about, but it's a very broad
one. It's one that people generally
understand as embodying this sort of
like freedom like you you get to dig
around basically, right? You know, you
get to play Grand Theft Auto totally not
following the story line and you know As
time goes on, it becomes a little bit
less of that. You can you get to do less
crazy things. But the whole idea is that
that world has ramps everywhere so that
you can drive cars and vehicles and
anything.
>> Okay. Anything else?
>> Uh there's like realism versus
abstraction.
>> What something? So, so like the the
difference between you know like Eve
Online for example which is supposed to
be very realistic simulating something
whereas poker for example is just cards
and numbers
>> something on the on the freedom sand box
versus preturn on rails there's a very
interesting thing in uh at least I've
seen it done in Balders game too there's
a pre-triven point in the game where you
are told you need x amount of money to
be able to pay for the ship out of here
and you're placed in a sort of sandbox
environment and you are given
It is not you're not told that you can
have whatever ways you can think of to
make that amount of money whichever
amount of money you can leave that part
of the game.
>> So it's a predetermined sandbox section.
>> No I mean yeah I mean if it's a you know
a lot of adventure games a lot of role
playing games are largely predetermined
with areas of of freedom. Even in a game
like Final Fantasy maybe not 13 but in
in in other games in the in the series
the story is largely predetermined but
what you do in combat is very very
fluid. uh you know and and that's kind
of like the the dichotomy that those
that square
and in the past kind of decided that
that was okay. This helps us cater to
people who want some flexibility in how
they're going to play by making the
combat system fluid enough that they can
do play they want as but also lets us
cater to the people who really want that
that long overarching epic narrative you
know and we can only we can only create
one we can branch into different because
so that's
>> there others
I mean might be a
figure
there's only one way to do it whereas
sol
you you could have multiple solutions
and
>> you know solution
that tells you
the game is catered to it Can I tell you
something about the constraints on the
budget of the
>> No, I would I mean I prefer games that
are much more
>> right because the the interesting thing
about multiple solutions to single
solutions and multiple solutions
um it could be all design like I I could
design in a game in fact if you play DSX
uh or any of the sequels uh they
specifically stated that they made this
game with multiple solutions in mind and
for DSX 2 they designed it so that um
they thought this puzzle needs kind of
three solutions and they actually will
design the environment for it. So while
the game kind of like touted it as you
know you get to play with the system you
get to you know figure out how all these
things combine and come up with
solutions at your own really that they
tried to like design it so that you have
three very clear options but they wanted
people to realize that they had options
and so you can have multiple solutions
whereas like freedom sandboxing kind of
implies not necessarily design like you
know you got lot lots of little things
that you can do and lots of different
spaces that you can explor
But u it's not like um you've got one
obstacle and three different ways to
solve it. You've got all kinds of
different things that you could be
doing. You could be like choosing not.
So these are different axis. I just want
to point out that these are different
ways to different things.
>> Um you can have in terms of rule
changing games whether it's dynamic
rules or static rules.
>> Okay. So so
uh I'll put dynamic static and
Are the rules going to change in the
game? Yeah, that's there are some games
over here. The whole point is change
versus
>> the rules.
>> We had this before and then PvP version.
time scale of decisions.
>> So short model.
>> Yeah. Like Twitch games versus games
>> contemplate decisions.
>> Sort of like contemplative and reactive.
>> How is that compared to reactive? Is
that are you guys going for basically
the same thing? Like reactive means
things are coming at you and you have to
respond really really quickly. Maybe not
even about it. And deliberate is like
like a turnbased game.
as much time as you want to think about
how long you want to make a decision.
Doesn't necessarily mean that, you know,
you can have a turnbased game that's
very fastpaced, you know, uh because the
the weight of any given decision is not
going to be so huge. So pace, you know,
I'm I'm just going to put pace up here
because
you know, slow and fast,
you know, as one way of describing the
game, uh uh reactive versus libertous
a related way of starting game. I bet
you could take like two of these and put
them on axis and then you can
but you know I guess every once in a
while you find that game that you like
both here and here at the same time
which is fine. It's just not a way to
talk about these things.
Okay,
these are really really useful terms uh
better than
is more
>> a little bit more boxing.
It's a little bit more restrictive than
freedom
is more like values that box on rails
are more like back of the box. you know
the future
really
you wouldn't