Good evening everyone.
I'm Kai Langley, director of development
for the MIT libraries and on behalf of
our director, Dr. Chris Berg, I welcome
you to this evening's fall MIT Reads
2025 presentation.
The libraries are an engine for
creating, sharing, and safeguarding
knowledge at the institute and beyond.
The libraries work to improve the
world's collective knowledge by
equipping current and future scholars
with the best content and the skills to
use it, whether examining medieval
manuscripts or managing research data.
As part of this work, our MIT Reads
program invites the MIT community to
hear from leading authors and to engage
in solution centered discourse on some
of the world's most complex challenges
facing our campus, the nation, and the
world. Thank you so much for joining us
this evening. This webinar is being
livereamed and recorded. It will be
available on the MIT Reeds website in
the near future. A very special thanks
to all the MIT staff who have made this
presentation possible, including Sylvia
Figureroa Ortiz, Ya Fuja Ross, Julia
Lanigan, Emily Kramer, Marcela Tam,
Lauren Fairman, Brigham Fay, Ned Wolf,
and Shannon Hunt.
We also greatly appreciate our community
partners at the MIT Press that both
published tonight's selection and have
copies of the book available for sale at
their MIT Press website.
As this is a webinar, you'll find that
the chat is disabled and all parties are
muted. You will be able to submit
questions and comments for our guests
throughout the presentation on your
screen and staff are recording them
offscreen for discussion when we reach
the Q&A portion of this presentation.
In a moment, I will provide
introductions for our guests and our
author will share a few brief insights
into why he created our MIT Reed
selection followed by a discussion with
the author and our moderator.
Without further delay, allow me to
introduce this evening's author and
moderator. On disinformation: How to
fight for truth and protect democracy by
Lee McIntyre. Couldn't be a more timely
book for discussion today. Lee is a
research fellow at the Center for
Philosophy and History of Science at
Boston University and a senior adviser
for public trust and science at the
Aspen Institute. formerly executive
director of the Institute for
Quantitative Social Science at Harvard
University. He has also served as a
policy adviser to the executive dean of
the faculty of arts and sciences at
Harvard and as an associate editor in
the research department of the Federal
Reserve Bank of Boston.
The author of 10 books, five of which
have been published by the MIT Press on
Disinformation: How to Fight for Truth
and Protect Democracy is best described
as, and I quote, a powerful pocket-size
citizens guide on how to fight back
against the disinformation campaigns
that are imperiling American democracy."
End quote. In conversation with Lee this
evening is Rebecca Larson, an assistant
professor in MIT's comparative media
studies department with affiliations at
the Burkeman Klein Center in Harvard and
the Center for Governance and Human
Rights at the University of Cambridge.
An early career media sociologist, her
work uncovers and analyzes
underststudied media ecosystems,
particularly those with insightful
relations to the traditional press and
concepts of this misinformation.
Lee and Rebecca, thank you so much for
joining us. Now, Lee, we welcome hearing
your insights and we're turn turning it
over to you.
>> Great. Thank you so much for the warm
introduction and uh thank you for
everybody who works so hard to make this
happen. I so wish that I could be there
in person and this could have been a an
in-person event. I managed to break the
L4 L5 in my back so I couldn't fly. So
uh it had to be converted to to a
virtual event and thank you to everybody
at MIT who worked so hard to uh to make
this event uh still possible so that we
could do it.
Um, when I was a teenager, really just
emerging as an independent reader, I
became fascinated with dystopian
fiction. 1984, Brave New World,
Fahrenheit 451.
I don't know what it was about those
books, but they always struck me.
Something that I cared about was under
serious threat here, but the fact that
it was fiction made it somehow more
palatable. Yet the danger and warning
for the future never left me. As I look
back, I realize that in all three of
these books, not only are people and
entire societies under threat, but truth
itself.
More than this, the mechanism by which
people are oppressed begins with
hostility to truth and the written word.
Books are burned. Information goes down
the memory hole. The Bible is left in a
corner where it is motheaten and
forgotten.
Whatever books do exist are written and
produced by machines for public
entertainment.
The human mind is taken out of the
process either in the creation or the
consumption of books. We are distracted
with entertainment while the world
burns.
How do these things go together?
I think that what Orwell, Huxley, and
Bradbury were warning us about is
something that fascists learned early,
and these lessons are still being
practiced today. That control over a
population always starts with control
over information.
In our own era, we find words and people
again under assault. In a time when
practically the entire sum of human
knowledge is as close as our iPhones, we
are drowned in a sea of misinformation.
Yet, ironically, an important part of
this misinformation
is made up of people who the who deny
that misinformation the misinformation
problem even exists.
More and more we find hyperbolic
political rhetoric, usually coming from
the right, claiming that we live in an
era of great censorship,
that misinformation isn't really
definable
or is rare or may not even exist.
But how can all of these things be true
at the same time?
Everyone understands what true
censorship is. It's when information is
taken away, changed, destroyed, when
it's put down the memory hole.
It's what happens when school board
members in Florida want to ban certain
books or the Chinese government doesn't
allow its citizens access to certain
websites.
And this is the framework that some
right-wing members of Congress in the
United States have latched on to when
they don't like content moderation or
deplatforming that refuses to amplify
the kind of lies
that serve their political goals. Ask
yourself, who would defend the idea that
misinformation has a right to exist?
Someone who profits by it. That's who.
They will defend misinformation as quote
alternative speech or recommend that one
should just let everyone speak and truth
will somehow magically rise to the top.
Yet loads of empirical work has shown
that this just isn't true.
That misinformation is more prevalent
now than ever. That it's having a
terrible effect on us. And that where
there's a competition between lies and
truth, lies almost always win.
To claim that the fight against
misinformation is censorship is to
misunderstand what the fight against
misinformation is really about, which is
the preservation of truth.
But more than this, I think that
disinformation is really itself a form
of censorship.
Do you remember that scene in Indiana
Jones and the Last Crusade where
Harrison Ford is finally found the Holy
Grail? But he can't tell which one it is
because it's surrounded by a thousand
fakes.
That's the point of disinformation.
If you can't hide or destroy the truth,
you can cover it up with
There's always time to kill it later.
The goal of disinformation and
censorship are really the same, which is
to subvert the truth. Whether you
destroy the truth or surround it with a
hundred fakes, the outcome is the same.
People can't find it. And this is why I
believe that in our current era, even
when truthful information is all around
us, it is nonetheless the case that
truth has never been under greater
threat.
We live in an era in which, as one Wag
recently put it, the truth is behind a
payw wall and the lies are free.
In my 2018 book, Post-Truth, I defined
this notion as the political
subordination of reality.
In my 2023 book on disinformation,
I extend the story and explore how we
got into our current situation and what
we might be able to do about it.
Disinformation is a strategic tool that
is created by malign actors who seek to
weaponize and amplify false information
to form an army of believers so that
they can get what they want, money,
ideology, or power.
But the point isn't merely to get
someone to believe something false. It's
to dominate their reality so completely
that they're less likely to resist.
Indeed, in some cases, people may simply
give up.
The great political philosopher and
Holocaust historian Hannah Erent once
said this quote, "If everybody always
lies to you, the consequence is not that
you believe the lie, but rather that
nobody believes anything any longer. And
a people that no longer can believe
anything cannot make up its mind. It is
deprived not only of its capacity to act
but also of its capacity to think and to
judge. And with such a people, you can
then do what you please. End quote.
That last line is always gives me chills
because it makes explicit the connection
between disinformation and the threat to
democracy.
If you control the information that
someone hears, in some sense, you can
control their reality.
And when that happens, you make them
much more pliable for control through
autocracy, authoritarianism,
fascism, whatever you want to call it.
I think that repression, torture,
persecution, deportation,
incarceration, execution are the endgame
of this strategy.
But it always starts with targeting
trutht tellers and their power over the
written word.
Orwell, Huxley, and Bradley understood
this. Though each had different ways of
characterizing it, they were all talking
about the same thing. How the subversion
of truth is a necessary step in the
oppression of people.
And although they all presented this
within the context of fiction, the truly
frightening thing for me is that what I
saw presented in novels in my most
fevered dreams when I was a teenager are
now in danger of becoming reality.
That's all I have to
to say about that. and I would be more
than happy to
have a conversation with Rebecca.
>> Thank you, Lee, um, on multiple fronts
for showing up today despite all of the,
um, roadblocks, but also for writing
this book. It's so powerful, so focused
on galvanizing citizens. And as an
academic who's also who's often in the
weeds about um complexities and
specificities, it was very refreshing to
read a book that weaves that so well.
What can we do right now? But also here
are some empirical things that are
happening. Um so I'm going to start off
with a question that's directly
connected to the comments you just made.
Um, so in on disinformation, your 2023
book, you argue that disinformation
today isn't just confusion or error.
It's a deliberate campaign to create
deep distrust. It's strategic denialism
for political or ideological gain or for
profit, um, monetary profit as you
argue. Um, and this is an approach
that's different from some scholars and
journalists. He's just drawing a very um
sharp line between misinformation or
unintentionally circulated
problematic information and
disinformation, the intentional
falsehoods that you describe um being
spread for power or profits. You even go
so far as to call misinformation at one
point in your book a a euphemism. So um
why is that distinction so central to
your argument and do you think that
distinction still holds up two years
later and where we are now politically?
Great question. Yes, I do think it holds
up uh today more than ever because
I mean language is important. What you
call a problem matters for whether you
feel empowered to do something about it.
And I see this so much on cable news
when they even bother to talk about the
problem of miss or disinformation.
They prefer to use the term
misinformation
and I think that they do that because
well because the terms have become
politicized. Now you ask yourself who
politicized them you know who who didn't
want you to you know to to hear it one
way or the other. But the problem is
that the media
um tend to like the word misinformation
because it's this umbrella term that
gets them out of the problem of having
to talk about who's behind it.
>> Uh dis misinformation is a mistake. But
disinformation is a lie. And if there's
a lie, there has to be a liar. So the
minute they say disinformation,
then they have to say who the liar is
and what the liar hoped to get out of
it. And the problem is that if you
report on the problem as one of
misinformation, then it's just a
confusion, a mistake. But it's not often
a confusion or mistake. I mean, think
about if if something is misinformation,
then it could be cleared up by getting
evidence. You go, "Oh, really? Oh, I I
had heard it the other way. I I didn't
know, you know, I always thought that uh
you knowh corn snakes were dangerous,
but it turns out they're not. I was
misinformed.
Um I I would get mixed up which is
which. I don't I don't know. Is it a
king snake, coralnake, who who knows? Um
so
that's misinformation just kind of
accidental that that uh somebody hears
and they, you know, get it cleared up.
But disinformation is a plot and that's
a danger because
think about what you're empowered to do
if you hear that something is
misinformation.
What can you do? It's like a natural
disaster.
You know, hurricane's coming, put your
head down, you know, uh put some uh uh
you know, board up your windows. There's
really nothing you can do. But if the
problem is disinformation
then there is something you can do
because it is a plot. There are people
behind it. They have interests and you
can expose those interests and expose
the people
that really resonates again as an
academic who I I would say
more often I see in academia that we use
the term umbrella term misinformation.
>> Yeah. They're all mau disinformation
these days because of the sort of you
know social cultural political economy
texture around disinformation but it is
like in some ways very limiting when
it's when we're approaching this as like
what can we do um so
I think I also want to ask you another
question since you've brought up cable
news that's a great segue for us to talk
about another um
>> really useful framework work throughout
your book. Um
the three or I guess it's three groups
that you describe um and you break down
in terms of disinformation flow and
success in terms of um strategic
denialism. So the truth killers or
creators, the amplifiers, which cable
news would be one, and the believers.
So, can you walk us through what these
actors are, how they connect to each
other, and if we get to it, where you
think the real leverage points are for
change?
>> Sure. And I just want to apologize the
commotion behind me. My my uh
15-year-old German Shepherd, Gigi, uh
has decided to come in and join me. She
she hears me start to talk about
disinformation. She decides, "Oh, it's
nap time. I'm going to lay down on the
couch." So, you hear all that jingling.
That's that's what's going on behind me
there. You might have to pay the dog tax
at some point.
>> Wingman. Yeah. Um, okay. So,
when we're thinking about what to do
about the problem of disinformation,
it's important not to waste our time
because [laughter] the problem is so
great and, you know, our tools are sort
of limited or can be misused. I mean we
have to identify what we what we can do
and and you know put our efforts in the
right uh in the right direction.
So the reason I started I even have
chapters called the disinformers the
amplifiers the believers
if you think so how so how do you solve
this problem? Well I see that as a
pipeline it goes from the disinformers
to the amplifiers to the believers.
Can you get a disinformer to stop
creating disinformation?
By and large, not.
Why would they? Why would they stop? Uh
it's something that benefits them. I
mean, think about the cigarette
companies in the 1950s that created
disinformation about uh whether
cigarettes were addictive or were
dangerous for your health. They did that
for profit. How could you get them to
stop? Why would they stop? They they
didn't, you know, they didn't want to
stop. Um, sometimes disinformers are in
foreign countries and so no matter what
law you pass, you know, in the US,
you're just not going to stop them.
Disinformation with AI now is so easy to
create. I mean, you you're just you are
not going to be able to stop the supply
side of disinformation. It is it is
coming and it's going to be terrible. I
I just read the other day about uh Sora,
which is a new ver uh uh version of I
know version of from the people who
brought you chat GPT what they did for
text. Sora is going to do for video. So
you can put you know the face of
whomever you want into a video and have
them do whatever you want. Oh my
goodness. You know, well geez, how could
that go wrong? But I mean, the
possibilities for disinformation are
going to be endless in the hands of a
malign actor. And you you can't get
malign actors to stop doing malign
things because that's who they are. Turn
this telescope around. Look at the other
end, the believers.
believers have gotten the brunt of the
invective,
the hatred,
um the
name calling uh in what's going on in
the information war that is the United
States these days. Look what happened
during COVID. Look what happened, you
know, for for climate change. I wrote a
whole book on this called How to Talk to
a Science Denire. think making the
argument that you needed to talk and
that's even the word denier. That's
that's not good. That's name calling.
But you need to talk to people one on-
one to see if you can reach them. The
the the human contact, but you know what
I mean? It embarrasses me to say I wrote
a whole book on this, but it's not a
scalable solution to the information
problem. Though it may be the right
thing to do or the right thing to do for
science, but you know the huge problem
that we have today, it's it's not enough
because think of it this way. The people
who believe the lies are victims
and in some cases they're the people who
are the worse off. I mean because
they're not only amplifying
disinformation, which I suppose you can
make an academic argument at that point.
Is it still disinformation? Isn't it
misinformation? because they're not, you
know, doing it knowing it's false. Okay,
we could talk about that for a few
hundred years in a philosophy seminar,
[laughter]
>> but um, you know, they they are
they're dying of CO.
>> They're they're believing the lies about
whether they're microchips in the
vaccines and they a lot of them died of
CO. So, I mean, they're they're the
victims and victims deserve empathy
and yes, we should talk to them. It's
the human thing to do, but it's not
enough to solve the problem. I think
that the only way we're going to solve
this problem is to grab the the pipeline
and squeeze in the middle. The middle,
the amplifiers. Sometimes believers
amplify. Yes, they do. But what are the
tools of amplification? The tools of
amplification are
cable news, social media, um you know p
paid media. Uh it's you know th that
that those are going to be the areas
where we can uh do more and we really
you know it's it's sad to see the extent
to which they have crumbled under the
pressure to do something now saying that
because they can't do everything they're
going to do nothing. And I'm thinking
here of the Facebooks and Twitters of
the world um who just have kind of given
up on content moderation because they
they
I don't know. I don't really don't know
why.
>> Yeah. I I mean this is talking of pinch
points and the amplifiers. Um yeah, I
was wondering how you would if you
rewrote this book 2025
if you could write it like that. um
given what's happened with uh the third
party factchecking program at Facebook
with all the cow towering the
inauguration funding the line behind
Trump at the inauguration of tech
people. Do you think is there some way
that you would rewrite especially this
chapter on the amplifiers and that being
a particular pinch point for the
disinformation pipeline?
I I I wish
I mean I wish I could rewrite it because
the book was not successful enough you
know to to the scale of the problem. Um
I don't know what more I could have
said. I mean are there other things that
I could have said other avenues? Surely
I think there there would be I mean I
probably would have said more about you
know um
the profit motive of the amplifiers. I
mean the amplifiers,
>> if you think about it, you know, the the
the algorithms in social media or the
profit motive in in major media, even ma
in mainstream media, I mean, sometimes
you wonder why would they change either?
I mean, are they if if they know they're
doing something wrong and they do it
anyway, doesn't that make them
complicit? You know, isn't shouldn't
that be called out a little bit more
than uh than I did? Uh, so yeah, I I
probably would would uh uh say more
about that, but um it's hard because
it's a short book, but I really put
everything I had into it. And I don't
really know what more I could say
to solve that problem. There there is
one thing there is one thing that I
would say and and it's it's what people
ask me about now.
because we're up to our hips in fascism
now. It's not just a warning. It's here.
[clears throat]
>> Uh you know, uh I just read today that
um the the FBI has now increased by 300%
the number of people who are under
investigation for uh domestic terrorism.
And there are people on the left. There
are people who don't have quote American
values,
Christian values. I mean, is this going
to result in detentions? Am I going to
go to jail someday?
>> Um, you know, we're we're hip deep in
this already.
I think of Alexi Nali.
I mean, he was not hip deep. He was over
his head deep in an electoral
dictatorship, but he still told the
truth. Why did he do that? He did that
because he recognized that even one
voice for truth
is a thorn in the side and an
inspiration to all the other people in
society.
Telling the truth and amplifying the
truth is important. I didn't say enough
in the book about amplifying truth. I
talked about how not to amplify lies. I
didn't say enough about how to amplify
truth because the same cognitive bias
that helps people to believe something
when they hear it over and over and over
again when it's a lie, it works for true
information, too. So, the strategy that
I've been talking about more and more as
I go out on the road now is what should
we do? Tell the truth. Tell it over and
over from the largest platform that you
can find. That is the number one best
thing that you can possibly do in an
information war. Understanding that
you're putting your neck out when you do
so.
>> Yeah, I might use that to put on my more
like traditionally questioning academic
hat.
>> Sure. Um,
I think one thing that I looked for in
the book, and it's a short book and it
has a very big punch that you can't, you
know, put too much in there to get the
the force of that punch. Um, but one
thing I did wonder why it wasn't in
there was the political economy of
journalism at this point or some of the
amplifiers that are supposed to speak
truth.
you talked about things like both
sidesism, um false equivalencies, you
know, horse race type coverage of
political events. Um
but there is a discussion in scholarly
as well as more public circles that
a there's not really incentive for truth
speakers traditionally understood as
such to speak the truth and um b for
those of us who say do try to get a
platform and speak the truth our sort of
targets
might not align in terms of um
>> targeted ads like we're not pushing the
same sort of
>> emotionally identity bolstering language
or you know narratives. I hope you
understand where I'm going with this.
>> I do
>> we need to like maybe think about those
structural things in addition to the you
know
>> I I didn't emphasize that
>> as much as I maybe should have for a
couple of reasons. I mean it's a short
book but one is if there are structural
reasons why we're in that
>> situation
>> writing a kind of a short pmic and
explain to people what the structural
reasons are doesn't necessarily give
them the tools in hand to do something
about it. It explains it but it doesn't
necessarily offer them you know the
context of here's what you can do
>> uh you know tomorrow. But the most
important reason I didn't write that
book is it's already been written. It's
called Merchants of Dow uh by Naomi
Reskis and uh and uh Eric Conway. And
there's another terrific book by Jane
Mayer called Dark Money. So if people
want to understand the
>> economic forces and the and the other
structural forces behind the information
ecosystem that we live in today, those
books have been written and and I I did
say a little bit more about those in
some of my other work, but you know, I I
hardly recommend those two books as your
introduction. And because here here's
the interesting part too that that I
noticed. I mean my work is based on on
on this idea from merchants of doubt.
The this all started with science denial
and science denial was about money
and then it became about ideology and
political power and then post-truth
comes along and you know they said oh
look we can do to any reality we want
what they already did to science and
then it's not necessarily about money
it's about other things but the but the
structure the reason that it existed
that that that blueprint
uh um the pathway was economic.
>> Yeah, those are some great Rex to point
people towards. Um, I guess I'm just
trying to
marry the the spirit of your book in my
mind and in my work of going out there,
getting the word out, speaking to people
respectfully and empathetically, but as
much amplification as possible
>> with.
So, one of the things that I focus on in
my work is how varied a lot of
Trump voters are in terms of um
>> where they are, where they voted for uh
why they voted for him, their
backgrounds. And I think sometimes when
we don't think about the very specific
grounded
>> communities and the problems they face,
then
>> when we do want to send messages to them
or even engage with them, it kind of
gets lost in translation. So, I can give
you a quick couple quick examples, but
it sounds like you might know
>> you already get the gist of what I'm
saying.
>> I I know. I mean, I've I love your work
and and I've tried to do similar work as
a philosopher, you know, untrained in
field work, going out to talk to
flat-earthers, you know, to to talk to,
you know, other deniers and see and and
they are varied and they, you know, they
do have different, you know, I ideas
about, you know, why they're doing what
they do. But the the common thread is
mistrust.
The common thread is that
they're getting bad information.
It's not that the the true information
is not accessible to them. It's that
they don't trust the people who are
sharing it with them. And the thing to
realize here is that one goal of
disinformation is not just to get people
to believe a falsehood. It's to distrust
the person who's telling them the true
information.
>> Absolutely.
>> So that's that's a nice entree if you
think about it. If you're out talking to
someone, if you're out talking to a a
Trump supporter, you're talking to
somebody who thinks that there are
microchips in the vaccines
or you're talking to somebody who
doesn't believe in climate change,
they universally think that they've been
lied to. They they mistrust because they
think they've been lied to. And you can
work with that because the truth is they
have been lied to. They just don't
understand who was doing the lying. Oh,
you the example here uh is is uh uh
preient about um microchips in the
vaccines. Everybody's heard of this idea
that there were microchips in the
vaccines. And I think I forget who did
the estimate, but it was a it was a
reliable source that
hundreds of thousands of people died
from not taking the vaccines because
they thought that there were microchips
in the vaccines. Where did that come
from? It came from Russian intelligence
>> and and but they didn't know that. So I
mean they were lied to by a malign actor
and died lost family members in that. So
I mean could you convince somebody that
they could take the vaccine because they
were being lied to? Maybe if you spent
the time to find out what they really
what their interests really were and who
they could really trust.
>> Yeah. I I will say I was very struck by
not just your call for empathy and
respect talking across the aisle or
however you want to put it. Um but the
way that you wrote the whole book um it
made sense to me at the end when you
said
essentially I grew up in a working class
non-ol household. um to me I thought you
know he he gets it on some level like
he's he's in he's been in multiple sort
of social worlds let's say um so I was
curious if you want to talk a little bit
about that I have a very similar
background um and I find that very
informs the way that I approach
my research but also our politics today
and how I try to talk to people about it
so did your background if I'm sessing it
correctly do you think it really
impacted this book and the way that you
wrote it.
>> Yeah, it it did. I grew up poor. I grew
up in a house where my parents believed
in education and we had books. I mean,
mostly we had the encyclopedia which I
read and enjoyed. Um, but I grew up in a
neighborhood that was,
um, close to the airport, uh, the city
dump, uh, strip clubs, bars. Um, it was
a dangerous neighborhood. Uh, uh, and
and it was, uh, you know, the the
schools were not terrific. And I mean,
we were we were poor. There were three
trailer parks within walking distance.
And the reason we had a house is because
my mom and dad built it. After World War
II, came home. Uh my dad more or less
stole the nails from a job site and
built a house. Um these were the nails
that fairness to my dad. The nails that
carpenter bends dropped the nail and
just leave it. And he
and we had it just a little bit better.
We had a house. We had an encyclopedia.
They wanted all their kids to go to
college and they did. But I know what
it's like to be talked down to. I know
what it feels like to have people think
that if you're poor, you couldn't
possibly be smart.
Every um respect for, you know, who you
can or cannot make a joke about or talk
about doesn't extend to people who grew
up in trailer parks. it doesn't extend
to, you know, people from the
neighborhood that I grew up in. So, I
know what that feels like. So, it felt
to me when I got into this that the
people I was trying to convince were the
people that I grew up with and they're
not stupid.
They're not unable to reason. Um, they
need to be respected and they need to be
spoken to um with,
you know, a a a good a good deal of
empathy. So yes, it did inform inform my
approach because I feel that
I feel a lot of people got cheated in
science denial and a lot of people are
getting cheated today with reality
denial. I know I met a guy at the flat
earth convention
um who was one of the the guest speakers
and um you know we we talked for a while
and
I found out a few years later that he
died of COVID because he was also a
COVID denier. Now he he was a victim. He
it was it was it was too bad.
>> I absolutely agree on all that. um as
like someone who came from a
working-class background and now you
know um
>> you know you're at MIT.
>> Yeah.
Um I but it's interesting because I I
almost feel like a lot of my work which
does look at very specific pockets of
conservative um rural conservative
religious communities um is partially in
reaction to a lot of the rhetoric that I
have seen in spaces elite institutional
academic spaces that sort of just deride
Trump voters as you know racist
uneducated stupid at large and that
>> yeah it's just not a helpful
thing, especially if we're
>> It is not
>> Oh, here's the book if nobody's seen it
yet. It's very small and portable.
>> Um yeah, keep it in your purse or your
backpack. Um but especially if we're
going to, you know, do something about
it in talking to believers um but also
amplification um and creators. So, I
also wanted to talk given that this is
MIT as you just pointed out a bit about
institutional
knowledge creation. Um so in the book
you do point towards truth in that sort
of direction. So like institutions like
the press um academics as trustworthy
places. Um how is that looking these
days? Would you would you like to opine
on that in terms of the sort of attacks
we've seen on the press and academia
right now and your work? Any thoughts? I
I I find it shocking
that the main people who are standing up
are comedians and Harvard.
And I got to give a shout out to Wesley
and I went to Wesley and his
undergraduate and uh uh
their uh their president is doing a
terrific job standing up as well. But a
lot of places have capitulated. I you
know you you held up the book and people
can see that tiny little book and the
reason it's so tiny and what it is is
because I love love love
Tim Snyder's book on tyranny. That's the
book that I read and it kind of got me
through Trump's first term and thinking
about I want to do a book like that now
on what I see the problem as. And you
open on tyranny and the first chapter
says do not comply in advance.
What are the tech companies doing? What
are the media companies doing? What are
the universities doing? A lot of them
are complying in advance. Uh that is the
one thing that you really cannot do. I
mean, it for one thing that amplifiers
the perceived power of the person who's
oppressing you. It makes them not have
to expend the power to do more to get
you, but it makes other people feel
like, oh, well, it's inevitable. I mean,
if Colombia is going to, you know, roll
over, we might as well roll over, too.
So, I have and comedians,
it's funny, isn't it? I mean, because
comedians
I read a piece about this the other day,
and I don't I don't want to plagiarize.
Uh, comedians have a sharp eye for the
absurd, for the ridiculous, for the the
places where things don't fit. And I
guess it maybe shouldn't surprise us
that comedians are the ones who who are
being attacked and who are resisting and
see things uh, you know, as they are. I
mean, the really shocking thing is the
people who they really could take a risk
and don't.
And so it always makes me admire more
the people who really have something to
lose and they take a risk anyway.
Um so I mean that's can I opine on it?
That's that's my opinion. There are just
shockingly few people who you would
think would see where we are. I mean we
are not on the road to fascism.
We are
arguably there
early when when post-truth came out. Uh,
I'm sorry. When on disinformation came
out and I went on the road and I did
talks and that, you know, kind of when
the mic and the camera were off, people
would ask me and now I wish they'd been
on so I could get credit for the
prediction, but you know, they would ask
me how how is this going to come out?
And I said
military uh in the streets policing
American citizens, mass deportation,
uh ultimately concentration camps,
political prisoners,
Where are we not there so far? Uh I mean
concentration camps maybe not that yet,
but but arguably so in ICE detention
centers and
>> and who knows where I mean we're we're
not even a year into this yet. So I mean
we are I've got friends overseas who
will not come to the United States.
They're they're so you know people from
Europe who they they've seen this
before. you know there there's this is
how you boil the frog right I mean
they've seen this before and it is very
scary time and you know if you ask me as
a human being living here in you know
the hell hole that is Portland Oregon um
do I worry about somebody knocking on my
door in the middle of the night? Yeah I
I really don't at this point
>> could it happen? Yes it could. And the
thing is
if you look at countries like um
we're not going to become Russia or
China overnight. The worry is Turkey.
The worry is Hungary where you look at
what happened in those countries.
They're professed to be
um democracies.
But what they did a few years ago in
Turkey is that they said that um
propaganda misinformation was punishable
by a prison sentence.
But who was spreading the
misinformation?
It was the people who were fighting it
>> and then they were declared terrorists
and a lot of them were in prison. So
they have a number of journalists in
prison in Turkey. I can't go to Turkey
based on you know things that I've said
though one of my earlier book was
translated into into Turkish but um you
you know you wonder well why are these
journalists in prison and someone from
Turkey said oh well they're all
terrorists uhhuh that could happen in
the United States why are all these I
mean Antifa has already been declared by
Trump a terrorist organization
I don't know if he's done the same for
Black Lives Matter matter. I I know
people in those
movements. They are not domestic
terrorists, but could they be targeted
and hauled away in the middle of the
night? Yes.
>> Yeah. Oh, boy.
>> I mean, it's interesting that your book
also has, I would say, a sort of
optimistic flavor to it. Um there is
still things we can do fight back. Lots
of different lists about practical
guidance like when you interviewed
various counter or um counter
intelligence officials um
>> counter intelligence and army
intelligence.
>> Yeah. Do you still feel that way or some
of this is coming from my
>> Yeah.
>> You know my um experience too where
people are just tired and scared and
much more than they might have been in
2023. So Before we transfer to
questions, I'll throw that last one at
you.
>> And and they're not watching the news
either because they can't stand it.
>> Exactly.
>> Somebody told me resistance is a form of
self-care. And and I get that. You know,
I if I say I'm optimistic, then it tends
to undermine the seriousness of the
problem.
>> Yeah. I want to say I've graduated from
optimism to hope
because hope
optimism kind of has this feeling that
things are going to get better. You
know, I believe in the future.
But I forget who it was who said it.
It's written down here and I I can't
reach it without getting off camera. But
hope is a discipline. Hope is a
practice. I mean you you if you have
hope, you have to work at having hope.
You have to do something
to make hope
fulfill itself.
So I wouldn't say that I'm optimistic
because the predictions just keep being
worse and worse and worse. Uh you know
the fulfillment. But am I hopeful? Yes.
Primarily because I don't want to give
up on my country.
And I don't want to give up on the
people that I know who are being
victimized by this. Some of whom are
people who voted for Trump,
>> but
and it's just on the tip of my tongue
who said hope is a discipline or hope is
a practice. I'm going to get that wrong
and it's going to bug me. Hang on.
>> Yeah, go for it.
>> Hang hang on a second. It's the academic
in me that it's gonna that's gonna bug
me until I until I get this.
>> Yeah, I know. This citations are are the
thing.
>> Hope is a discipline. Uh Miriam Eaba
Miriam Cabba.
>> Look it up.
>> All right, [laughter]
that's a good place for us to segue to
questions from the audience. Um,
actually the first one is kind of very
closely connected to what we were just
talking about. Jane asks, "What do we
do? I am infuriated, terrified, engaged,
doing what I can see to do, but none of
it feels enough."
>> Um,
we need everybody to grab an or to do
what they can. Nobody can do everything.
That doesn't mean that you can do
nothing. If if we all I mean how many
navalis do you need to bring down a
Putin? Maybe not that many which is why
you know Putin identified him. I mean we
we need like I said tell the truth
loudly from the largest platform that
you can. If if there were more people
who understood that, if there were more
the one thing I wanted my book to do was
to empower people because now now this
is actually a nice uh uh uh book end to
what I said earlier.
>> Disinformation has three goals.
One is to get you to believe something
false. Two is to mistrust and even to
hate the truth tellers. But third is to
feel hopeless and powerless.
and cynical. I don't want you to feel
hopeless and powerless and cynical.
That's why the end of the book has 10
steps of things that you can do. Some of
which are now dated just, you know,
within a couple of years. But I mean,
damn right you Yes, there there are
things that you can do. So, even when
you feel like there's nothing that you
can do,
there are things that you can do. Even
if what you're doing is supporting other
people in not feeling hopeless, that's
very important. You know, this is like
the 12 Angry Men and the the movie,
right? If one person, which is, you
know, based on earlier social psych
work. If one person stands up, sometimes
that's enough for other people to
follow. If two people stand up, then
sometimes you get a whole herd. So,
you know, use the words they don't want
you to use, the words that are now
banned on federal websites. Be loud, be
annoying, go to the protests.
Um, I don't you don't have to get
arrested or teargassed, but you have to
show up.
>> Yeah. I actually opened the book to that
last chapter where Lee gave gives those
10 things because I think yeah there are
some things there particular number nine
take solace in the fact that there are
many out there who are also engaged in
this battle like Lee
>> um that for me at least gives me solace
um
>> yeah looking at all the people who are
doing good work um
>> thank you
>> so
this is an interesting one why the
puzzlement about platforms having given
up on content moderation, given Elon
Musk and other platform [laughter]
owners alliance with subsidies slashed
with subsidies by the Russians who pedal
the most dis disinformation including
vaccine disinformation.
>> Yeah.
>> Or if you're asking if we're puzzled
>> the minute I said
I was give up.
Why am I puzzled by why Elon must give
up on it? Yeah. Okay, I'm not. But but
here's here's the thing that the Center
for Countering Digital Hate found in
that
some shocking amount, I think it was 65%
or more of the
false information about vaccines on
Twitter was due to 12 people.
So, and that was pre Elon Musk.
Now, the night before Elon Musk took
over at Twitter, I checked all 12 of
those cuz I know who they are.
Eight of them were on Twitter. So, it
means that even before Elon Musk,
Twitter wasn't doing a good enough job.
I mean, what could they have done? They
they could have deplatformed the liars.
You know who one of those liars was? RFK
Jr.
uh they they abdicated their
responsibility and I mean what happened
with Mark Zuckerberg he you know
crumbled all of a sudden uh he used to
believe in this he understands the
problem he once pretended that he didn't
but he he does and then and then he
gives up on it so I mean yeah um
I I shouldn't be puzzled
I I I shouldn't be
it's just Um, how do you how do you
explain that level of cowardice
by billionaires?
I just I don't understand it.
>> I will say from my end um so I've been
involved in some projects looking at
specifically third party factchecking
and how it was almost single-handedly
funded the industry itself post 2016 by
Facebook. Um, in my opinion, it is
largely a PR effort, but then the, you
know, the plug was pulled 2024, 2025
after Trump was elected. Um, the writing
was on the wall for a while with that
with the fact checkers that we
interviewed. Um, like it it wasn't a
surprise for the people inside. It
wasn't like the complete about face that
we've it looked like from outside. Um,
so I Yeah, it's
>> Yeah,
>> I I get that. I mean, the fact checker
Glenn uh Kesler, the Washington Post,
the guy with the Pukios,
>> he he just left the Washington Post.
They have no plans to replace him.
>> Um,
>> yeah.
>> Yeah. No, no, you're you're right. The
these things were coming. It wasn't
overnight. It was it was coming for a
long time.
>> Yeah. Um, so here's another one which is
still focused on social media and I
think uh, yeah, you talk about this in
your book, but we can update it a bit.
So given the role that social media
plays in spreading disinformation, do
you believe tech companies should be
regulated more strictly? And if so, what
kind of regulation do you think would
actually work without endangering free
speech? And I'm going to tack on are
there things other than the fairness
doctrine and section 230 which you talk
about in your book that you think could
be levers now?
>> Yeah. Uh well I mean one thing we could
do is point out the hypocrisy of all the
folks crying about free speech in
Congress and censorship and then turning
around and you know embracing censorship
in another name. But that's probably not
going to work. But the the best idea I
ever heard was by Steven Luwendowski
who's a professor at University of
Bristol over in England. And he said
that the real problem was the
algorithms. That the algorithms were a
black box.
And that what we need is
not to regulate the companies
in terms of the content that they
put up, take down, you know, the human
action. What we need is more
transparency, which doesn't sound like
censorship to me at all. We need more
transparency in the algorithms. Could
you make the algorithms that run YouTube
and all these other companies
uh such that they had to be have a board
of overseers?
experts, academic experts say uh have
all of the private user data blinded so
that you know you you couldn't um so
that privacy wasn't an issue because it
always seems to me that the crisis comes
it's too late a whistleblower or after
the harm's done then they go back and
they go oh my god yes it was the
algorithm so why aren't more eyes on the
algorithms the algorithms are black
boxes their inner workings are known
pretty much only to a few people at each
of the big tech companies. That's where
the problem lies. Uh I'm convinced
Stephen uh uh convinced me of this. So
could the US Congress
um do something about that? I think
that's not exactly lowhanging fruit, but
I think that's something that you could
have a persuadable sort of an argument
about. Well, but don't you believe in
transparency?
But you're against censorship, right?
So, let's not censor the speech, but
let's have more eyes on the algorithms
of these private companies that are
doing public harm. Um, I I think that is
a winnable argument and and I credit
Steve Luwendowski for for sharing that.
>> When you say transparency,
do you I think in your book you say
something about credible academics being
able to look at the inner workings.
>> Yes. But I'm curious what that looks
like for you. Um, when you say
transparency
from a practical standpoint,
every I I could I could name
so many people who are disinformation
fighters who are now out of work because
their universities abandoned them,
who are, and I'm not going to name them,
because anybody could do a Google search
and find out who they are and I I don't
want them to be you know cause them any
more trouble but
who are experts all all women by the way
who are experts on tech who are experts
on
um
how
reach from uh tech platforms that are
not careful about privileging say
engagement over truth. So I mean
practically what could we do? There are
I don't want to say unemployed
but
uh undermployed
recently uh uh criticized and maligned
disinformation fighters who I can think
of who would be terrific.
>> And then people maybe say oh but but you
know the but what about their politics?
Well, gee, that's why you have more than
one of them. That's why you have a
board. That's why it's actually
transparent.
Um, I I I don't know. I just I like the
idea of that because it immediately
defangs the claim that this is some
censorship.
It's not censorship, it's transparency.
If Elon Musk's beliefs so much in
transparency, why are his algorithms
opaque?
I don't understand it.
Yeah, I'm not disagreeing. I'm just as
someone who's in an academic environment
and who's
>> wanted transparency as well. I also see
that it's not a panacea. There's a lot
of systemic stuff like yeah
disinformation research was being
flagged and defunded right now. Um
>> yeah,
>> but also like academic capacity. Um but
that's a whole another rabbit hole and I
won't go down it right now because we
have more questions. Um
>> let's see. Oh, Katie, I'm a NASA
astronaut who lived on the space
station. How would you respond to these
two different types of flatearthers?
Number one, ones who are hoping they are
wrong but want proof. And number two,
ones who don't want to be convinced.
>> Oh, that's that's interesting. Um,
flatearthers. I wrote about this in the
opening chapter of my book, How to Talk
to a Science Tonight, where I talk about
my experience at the Flat Earth
International Conference in uh um in
Denver in 2018.
They are convinced, they're conspiracy
theorists to the last person.
And the reason they believe in flat
earth is because they think that there
is a cabal of people in power who have
lied to them. Um so drawing a
distinction between the people who are
hoping that they're wrong
makes it sound like they're open to
evidence. But to be open to evidence,
they would first have to be open to
trust. The trust is the barrier. I think
um I said I think in print and certainly
out on the road when I was talking about
it that to me the problem of science
denial in general is not an evidence
problem or a fact problem. It's a trust
problem.
So that distinction while a sharp
distinction between the ones who are
hoping that they're wrong
I mean and the ones who aren't.
Here's one thing that I noticed.
If you're a scientist, which I hope that
somebody who lives on the space station
is, you understand that a scientist is
relentlessly looking for evidence to
show that they might be wrong. Whether
it's they're hoping or not, they're
they're looking for they're open to that
evidence. They care about uh evidence.
And here's the crucial point. If there
is evidence to show that they're wrong,
they change their mind. It's that last
part that the flatearthers are missing.
They will not change their mind when
presented with evidence that shows that
they're wrong.
So that first group is very very small.
The group of people who are hoping that
they're wrong. I just I didn't I didn't
meet a lot of them. Maybe they're not
the ones who go to the FEIC convention,
but I didn't meet a lot of them. They
were convinced that they knew the truth.
And they knew the truth because they
were the ones who had been awakened to
the astronauts. Yes. Professors,
pilots, government officials who had
been lying to them because they were
presumably getting something out of it.
It's a fascinating subculture and that's
why I went to this convention because I
thought if I can go there and talk to
them and get them to listen to me and I
listen to them then I can talk to
climate deniers then I can talk to
vaccine deniers.
Well then COVID hit and so some of the
research for the book was curtailed by
the time I got to some of those uh
latter topics. But it was uh it was
really fascinating.
>> Yeah. Shout out to On the Ground
Research.
>> Yes.
>> Um always pushing it. Okay. So, as a
good followup, um talking about who we
can talk to and convince. Uh as a
college instructor, I understand and
agree with Lee's arguments. My question
is, how can we engage college students
to read and persuade them about the role
of disinformation when they don't like
to read for school purposes?
>> God, I wish there were a book. Uh, you
know, a really short book that you could
read in an hour.
>> Um, yeah, you could, you know, I tried
to get MIT Press. MIT Press is
wonderful. Their publicity, their
marketing, just terrific team. I I came
up with a wacky idea that what they
should do is uh you know, print up a few
extra hundred and just leave them on the
bus, you know, leave them on the subway.
Kind of a gorilla marketing campaign.
And their their money was better spent
uh doing other things, I'm sure. But,
you know, that's um I don't know. How do
you convince people to read?
I wish I could get the book banned. If
you could get it banned, then people
[clears throat] would read it, wouldn't
they? There's a I live in Portland,
Oregon, and there's a the my favorite
bookstore here is Pal's bookstore, and
they have on their reader board right
now, I just drove by it the other day.
It said, "Banning a book only makes
people want to read it."
>> I mean,
I think I also
>> I don't know. I don't know what to do to
get people to read a short, cute, timely
book. I don't know.
>> Yeah. I mean, I personally, as someone
who also teaches college students, um I
yeah, I think I get where this person's
coming from because it's it's not just
like about disinformation. It's just
hard to get them to read, period. But I
think there are ways to get them to care
about disinformation as younger people,
even though it's
>> a world that they've grown up with more
so than
>> some of us.
>> I haven't taught in 10 years. Uh I I
recognize this is a growing problem.
Look, that's one reason that I made the
book so short and accessible because
people don't like to read. Even readers
sometimes don't like to read. So, I
wanted to have it be a book that they
picked up, started the first page, and
then couldn't put it down because they
could read it literally within an hour.
I I don't know what to do. if you can
think of an idea because I've still uh
you know the book's still in print and I
I know the folks at MIT Press publicity
would you know love to hear uh uh other
ideas. I I if you have any idea for how
to get people to read it or other
marketing campaigns I I tried to get
them to to print it out in different
colors, red, purple, blue, yellow,
orange and sell it as a six-pack so that
you kept one and you gave five away, you
know.
>> Oh, that's nice. uh I you know I I had
all these ideas uh you know or or take a
page from the book and blow it up
>> but but take out the identifying
information just put it up in the tea
tunnel so that people would read that
book and go and then take a picture of
it go I've got to read this book and
then they'd go get it. I I I like
gorilla marketing. Um well we'll see
maybe for the next one.
>> Okay we're going to get to the AI
questions now. Um, I had a few lined up
too since this is MIT. Um,
>> yep.
>> Uh, let's see.
>> You mentioned AI will lead to more
disinformation than ever before. How
should this be addressed?
I think you should I'm also going to
tack on to the this person's question.
Um, how will it lead to more
disinformation? Because I think that
will connect with how you answer. that
the problem of disinformation used to be
there used to be a barrier to
disinformation. If you look back at the
disinformation that existed in the 2016
presidential campaign that was coming
out of Russia, it was bad. I mean, it
was persuasive enough that, you know, if
you just get a certain percentage, but
it was it was not good disinformation.
They were memes that had misspellings
and you know diction problems and I mean
it was just the quality was not good. Um
but now it's so much easier. I mean it's
like asking the question of how did the
Canon personal printer uh impact
counterfeiting?
Very much so. Because you no longer
needed an engraver to you know fake
those bills. You could do it on on a a
personal copier. Better be careful. I
used to work for the Fed which detected
counterfeiting. But I mean I I think the
technologies probably moved on that that
printer that Canon and I can't remember
what it was made counterfeiting so poss
much more possible. Um so you know
putting the tools to make it easy just
you know makes it easier.
you I I've often joked that
you look in it's not a joke in Russia
they have troll farms they have people
pumping out this information
um and the primary uh uh
screening tool is how well do you speak
English
they don't have to worry about that
anymore
they've got chat GPT they don't need a
troll form they need a troll garden they
need one person who's a very good
speaker of English and they can produce
you know the the the number uh you know
the volume and the quality of
disinformation are going to increase.
Now the hard part what can you do about
that? Here's the problem.
I've always been worried since the
beginning of this debate going back to,
you know, 2016 before
about things like deep fakes that the
real danger is not going to be that it's
going to get you to think that a false
thing is true. It's going to be that it
gets you to think that a true thing is
false.
When f when fake videos are so prevalent
that you say, "I don't believe any
videos anymore."
That's the real trouble. I I read a an
article in a law journal. Don't ask me
why I was reading a law journal, but I I
read an article in a law journal
recently where there was a a an attorney
who was bemoning the day when um you
would no longer be able to use audio and
video evidence in court because fakes
were going to be so prevalent that they
would no longer be seen by juries as
reliable sources.
I think the only possible way to fight
back against that is education, you
know, to let people to to try to help
people understand
how to differentiate between uh fake and
real, not to get cynical, to to instead
bore in. In Finland, they have a
curriculum starting in kindergarten,
first grade for how to tell fake news.
We could do that here.
We can't.
We got to do that for the adults, too.
But we better get more literate about
what's fake and what's not because I
mean, again, we're not on the road to
this. We're here. Uh they just announced
the other last week was a bad week. I
mean, they just announced the first AI
actress. Her name is Tilly. She'll say
and do anything you want. And she's uh
looking for Hollywood representation.
agents are clamoring to represent her.
Maybe put the screen actors out of
business. Um, Sora was just announced
uh, so far only available through
invitation. But can you create a video
in which they had you and me jumping out
of an airplane with parachutes that were
pizzas? Yeah, they could because they've
already done this. when we've all seen
as educators what chat GPT and I haven't
taught in 10 years but we've all seen
what chat GPT has done to the student
essay I mean it is it is it is shocking
so I think the only thing that we can do
is try to become more aware and try to
keep the tech uh uh you know for
finding it up to date but even as I say
that I recognize the problem because
there is no technological solution to
human malevolence. You You can't We're
not going to out tech our way. I'm
sorry. I know it's MIT. You cannot out
tech your way of the disinformation
problem and AI making it easier. Yeah,
we need a lot of tech help, but we, you
know, they've got a philosophy
department and a really good one,
philosophy and and linguistics as I
believe at MIT. And they need them, too.
And they need the sociologists and the
science writers and the other people on
this problem too. It's not just a tech
problem.
>> Yeah. So much of that was throwing me
back to a lot of the work that I've done
in previous groups around deep fakes and
factchecking and how much fear there was
in the last few election cycles around
it. Um, but I will say on the education
front, at times it's easy to say
literacy and just leave it at that or
education and just leave it at that. So,
I'm really glad you pointed out
>> Finland. Um,
>> Finland,
>> I think that it's a similar pedagogical
thing, but I worked a lot with some
Norwegians who've been pushing
>> this concept of source criticism. So,
really looking at where these things
come from, not just like the content
itself. That's one way to sort of get
around,
>> you know, the initial like, is this fake
or not? Are there multiple hands or
arms? Is the is the language wrong? Um,
and we'll have to adjust as we go.
>> And you shouldn't be lost on anybody
that if you look at a map, Finland
shares a border with Russia. I mean,
they're they're they're used to this.
There are other things that adults can
turn to. A friend of mine, Andy Norman,
wrote a book called Mental Immunity.
Um, another friend, uh, Sandra
Vanderlin, wrote a book called
Foolproof. I mean there are tools
available to uh adults who care to learn
how to think better about these sorts of
things.
>> Yeah. And it's often very context
dependent. Unfortunately, there is no
like panacea. So anyway, okay. We have a
lot of questions and we have 15 minutes
I think. So I will try to get us through
a few more.
Um,
right now there is a lot of focus on the
dialectics of free speech and what the
limits may be. How do we think that
social media companies can moderate
disinformation but do it in a way that
is not considered censoring free speech.
>> Just wrote an article on this with
Sander Vanderlin in Time magazine. We
did an op-ed called How to Fight
Disinformation Without Censorship.
There are several ways to do it and I
don't I we you said we've got a lot of
questions so I don't want to just repeat
the article here but I will say that if
you think that there aren't ways there
are
>> um
>> was that a copout answer? I'm sorry. I
>> I don't think so. if you point them to
the Times article. Um,
>> yeah, but I will say you also
>> you also talk about free speech, as I
would say, almost a smokeokc screen in
this book, which I think is a really
important point.
>> Um, to keep in mind when whenever the
censoring or free speech stuff comes up,
it can be really weaponized. Um
>> well well yes because it's the easiest
thing I mean it's the easiest thing in
the world to claim that the people who
are fighting myths and disinformation
are trying to censor
>> exactly executive order 14 whatever.
>> Yeah. And and the thing is
that it's important to realize that that
claim is itself part of the strategic
campaign
by disinformers. This was true of Jim
Jordan way before you know Trump got
reelected. It was I mean this was a a
strategy. There was money behind it.
There were political interest behind it.
I talked to my pals and we saw this
coming and tried to get, you know, major
media outlets to take this seriously
early on and they finally did. But I
mean this
this was upsetting because we saw it
coming.
related
>> they're going to claim it's censorship.
Yeah. [snorts]
>> Yeah. Yeah. Uh asterisk to always like
sort of look at the politics of it when
there's a censorship claim is kind of
what I was trying to put in. Um so
somewhat related question. How do we
distinguish between difference of
opinion and disinformation especially
when it comes to interpretation of
current events? Example are people
protesters or terrorists? Is something a
war or a genocide? Those are two
examples they're giving.
>> I love that question.
Um because and the reason I love that
question is because I think that
the best way to approach something like
that is human face-to-face
conversation.
It's I mean online in the comment
section,
you're not going to get there. But if
you're having a face-to-face
conversation with somebody that you
really disagree with,
um, they're going to ask you, "What do
you mean by terrorism?"
H how, you know, we we disagree? Do we
disagree over facts? Why do we disagree
over the facts? What are your sources?
One of my most powerful questions when
I, you know, go out on the road, I'm not
a physicist.
I'm I'm you know I'm not an expert on
climate change or vaccines
but I'm a philosopher and so I will ask
people
why do you believe that
more powerfully I ask them what evidence
if I had it in my back pocket could
change your mind that's the question
that really flumxes them that's Carl
Pauper's question the philosopher
>> par excalance right because if you're
really a scientist
you would change your mind if somebody
could produce compelling evidence. So
tell me what is the evidence that if I
had it could change your mind and if the
person can't tell you what that evidence
is
then they're not a scientist and and
that's that's a that's a moment that can
only be appreciated in face-toface
conversation. I think somebody somebody
asked uh uh uh Theodore Dubzanski one
time, eminent evolutionary biologist,
what it would take for him to give up
evolution by natural selection
and he said rabbit fossils in the
pre-Cambrian era.
Pretty damn specific, right? Great
answer. Great answer. I mean, so then
you know,
but so ask that of your conversation
partner. What would it take to convince
you of, you know, whatever the thing is?
I I am really in I mean, look, it's not
going to solve the problem. It's not
sufficient to solve the problem. But I
enjoy and I need to do more of
face-to-face conversation because if
people remember that disinformation
doesn't just poison somebody's ability
to reason, it makes them hate you.
But it's hard to hate somebody face to
face with a smile on their face who's
curious about what you really think.
somebody who will say to you, um, but
why do you think that? Or or I would I
say, well, I'm gonna ask you a hard
question now. You know, I'm a
philosopher. You you going to let me ask
you a hard question? And they always
say, oh, yeah, sure. I say, why do you
think that? I mean, who who who
told you that? And then they tell me,
and I say, but but why do you trust
them? You know, I mean, you can do that
in person much better than you can in
writing.
I love that. That drives so much with my
fieldwork with rural media, conservative
media. I I But you have to also like be
there and enjoy it on some level. Um
yeah, anyway,
>> if you're not if you're not enjoying it,
you shouldn't be there. Uh there's a I
have a um
friends that I wrote about in the how to
talk to a science book. um who run a
their own tiny in tiny I mean I think
they're running out of their dining room
called hear yourself think and they go
out to political rallies
and present the opposite point of view
and engage people in conversation and
film it and then offer seminars about
how to do it.
Not angry spitting shouting
conversations but real genuine
connection conversations.
>> Yeah. or for entertainment of the other
side. Um
>> yeah, absolutely. Um this is a direct
followup in some ways to what you were
just saying.
>> Sure.
>> How do you deal with deniers that have
backgrounds in science and engineering
yet they still insist on coming up with
ways to dispute the evidence based on on
their own view of the data or their own
identity? I'm adding that in based on
your book. Um example, making the
statistics fit their own model.
It's a a shocking fact that sometimes
the most virilent deniers are the best
educated ones because they know how to
defend their point of view, they know
the 16 studies that you haven't read yet
or they can or when you say if you could
show me such and such. I I did this one
time. You know, they asked somebody
asked me, "What would convince you that
uh
the MMR vaccine
caused autism?" And I mentioned some
specific
thing and then they immediately shot me
a study.
Well, it was a flawed study, but by God,
they had it at their fingertips. They
were, you know, they were ready to go.
So, what do I say to them? I mean, look,
theoretically they sometimes they're the
hardest because they're ready to go. I
mean, they're, you know, they've they've
got their arsenal, but they also might
be
open to the, you know, to your side of
it if you've got the information as
well. I remember that that exchange
ended in something of a mutual
understanding, not about that topic, but
that we had a lot more in common because
as the conversation went on, this was
online, but as the conversation went on
and on and on,
>> it turned out that we had just a
shocking amount in common from our
background, the way we grew up, you
know, I mean, it was just it was
amazing.
And so that that wall of hatred began to
disappear. And by the way, uh, for me
too, right, for for me to just not to
say, "Oh, you're not worth my time.
You're not worth talking to." Um, I I
don't I don't like it when I feel that
way.
>> When I feel that, you know, like
somebody's not worth talking to, because
usually, I mean, unless somebody's a
show, unless they're, you know, making
money on it or something,
>> there's something behind it. And
sometimes it's fear.
And if you really listen to somebody,
vaccines is a good topic. If you really
bother to sit down and just listen to
why somebody's scared, they will tell
you and they'll tell you what could
convince them because what parent wants
to put their child at risk? I mean they
will you know you you can have a good
conversation and there are instances in
which scientists have convinced uh
people to change their mind because you
know through empathy through uh through
listening that was in the in the earlier
book not in on disinformation.
how to convince other scientists. I
mean, look,
scientists should be the easiest to
convince because
we, you know, scientists are committed
to being convinced by data and it is
irrational to believe the hypothesis
that has worse data over one that has
better data.
Some people kind of read themselves out
of the profession or worse. Look,
sometimes they go beyond like they're
super eminent in this field and so
they'll think, well, I'm so brilliant,
you know, but I'll make this speculation
on this other field or I have no
credentials whatsoever. That's
sometimes, you know, a factor, too. But
I mean, scientists should be easiest to
convince
>> if they embrace
the scientific attitude, I call it,
which is to care about evidence and be
willing to change your mind on the basis
of evidence. If they've got that, you
should be able, you know, to convince
them with evidence. Doesn't always
happen.
>> Well, this is the third in a tree of
questions that I think are all very
related. Um, and it follows up again.
So, how do you have a debate with
someone about a topic that you're not an
expert on, but you know it's true.
>> Um,
>> uh, have I got
>> So, say you aren't a scientist.
>> Yeah. Have I got an article for you? Um,
in nature human behavior 2019, there is
an article by Cornelia Bich and Philip
Schmid.
I forget the title of the article, but
they did an empirical study of two ways
of interacting with science deniers. One
was called content rebuttal where you
present them with the facts and the
other was technique rebuttal where you
recognize that deniers all
follow the same blueprint. They
cherrypick evidence. They're conspiracy
theorists. They are illogical reasoners.
They believe in fake experts and they
think science has to be perfect. But if
you understand those five points, they
talk in that article about how you can
engage whether you have specific content
knowledge or not. Here's the brilliant
thing about their study and and why I I
mean I wrote about this study in my in
my book.
They found that technique rebuttal was
just as effective as content rebuttal.
So, I mean, I'm not disrespecting
anybody who got a PhD, you know, in
whatever, but a lay person who
understands how technique rebuttal works
can be just as effective in talking to
somebody who who's a denier,
which means that we don't have an
excuse. We can't say, "Oh, the
scientists ought to be out there doing
it."
>> You know, I I I mean, look, you you're a
scientist. You're a sociologist. You
know, you're you're a scientist. I'm a
philosopher. I'm not a scientist, but I
understand technique rebuttal because I
understand, you know, those five steps
and, you know, I mean, illogical
reasoning, you know, cherry-picking. Uh,
uh, yeah, I I understand how to do that.
So, that's the energy that I go in with.
So, put your mind at ease. Not only can
you use that, it's just as effective as
if you were a scientist.
>> That's a great note for us to to end on,
I think. an optimistic or hopeful note.
Um,
>> hopeful.
>> I'm going to turn it. Yeah, hopeful.
Thank you so much, Lee. I'm gonna turn
it over to Ka to close things out for
us.
>> Great questions. Thank you to everybody
and to you, Rebecca.
>> Yes. Thank you both, Lee and Rebecca,
for such a provocative conversation and
questions and answers from the audience.
Thank you for engaging and for showing
up this evening and for wanting to learn
more about this topic and what we can do
in the world to mitigate some of these
challenges that we are moving through in
this present time. As a reminder for
those in the MIT community, we will host
a lunch and community discussion
tomorrow, October 9th, at 12 PM noon in
the Hayden Library Nexus. And I want to
thank you again for joining us virtually
for this evening's presentation. I hope
you all have a great evening. I hope you
enjoy your dinners. This now concludes
our event. Good night.