welcome I know there'll be a few uh
additional people and if people could
slide over that'd be great as new people
arrive uh it's my pleasure uh to welcome
all of you here today uh my name is
Steve lurman and uh I've been at MIT a
long time but I certainly for this
occasion my my singular honor has been
to be associated with open courseware
since its Inception uh I served as chair
of the interim management board and
chair and I'm now chair of the faculty
Advisory
Board uh it's my privilege to be your MC
today but in fact while this event is
meant to honor the achievements uh of
open cours whereare I sort of like to
emphasis emphasize my own view that the
best is still yet to
come in 2001 MIT made an extraordinary
commitment to publish in electronic form
the teaching materials we use in
virtually all our courses the entire
undergraduate and graduate curriculum of
this institution
and we committed to make those materials
freely and openly available for any
non-commercial purposes including giving
people the right to reuse them to modify
them and to repurpose them in in other
ways for educational and research
purposes today a little more than six
years later we're here to celebrate the
Fulfillment of that initial promise this
accomplishment was possible because of
the dedication of the MIT staff and
faculty the commitment of a dedicated
open course Weare staff the tremendous
financial support of donors and the
extraordinary leadership of the MIT
senior
Administration MIT open courseware now
provides the materials for 1,800 courses
to Educators and Learners throughout the
world unlocking what was previously a
closely held Treasure Trove Trove of
human
knowledge astonishing figure to date
these materials have reached an
estimated 35 million
people we welcome the many friends and
supporters of open course Weare who are
here to share with us this
celebration we are also privileged to
have with us today colleagues from other
institutions around the world who have
made open courseware a global movement
rather than just an MIT
project some are representatives from
the 160 members of the open courseware
Consortium that has recently been formed
there are more than 3,000 courses Beyond
those we from MIT provide that are now
freely available through open courseware
sites around the world from other
academic
institutions we'd like to make a special
note to the representatives of uh the
open Weare course Weare site just
launched today from the University of
Massachusetts at Boston this site just
opened for Public Access as as far as I
understand it uh this
morning we also have with us today our
translation Partners about 600 of mit's
courses are now available in other
languages including Spanish Portuguese
Chinese and Thai as well as some other
languages together these translations
have made open courseware content
accessible to about 14 million other
individuals worldwide Beyond those that
our site has
reached and we're joined today by the
open course sare external Advisory board
members from around the country and
abroad we're honored to have so many of
you here uh we had a meeting this
morning which was yet another
stimulating and
fascinating discussion about the
potential that open course wereare can
unlock as we make knowledge available
globally and more accessible to around
the
world this afternoon we'll revisit the
path MIT took to reach this moment
explore the impact of open courseware uh
on the world and on education here in
the United States and abroad and look to
the future of open course Weare and
education both both in the short term
and in the longer term we're fortunate
to have here as our keynote speaker
today New York Times columnist Thomas
fredman I'll introduce him more in
detail later but he'll talk about
individual empowerment and how the
internet and Innovative usage such as
open course where of that technology are
making a difference for people around
the world we're also going to have a
panel of distinguished academics
researchers and scientists that will
include Hal abson Charles vest John cely
Brown and Sam patroa and they'll help us
explore the implications and the future
possibilities of open
courseware later this afternoon we'll
also announce the launch of a new and
exciting MIT open course Weare
Initiative for secondary education yet
another chapter in the growing story of
what happens when we make course
materials accessible and freely
available but first let me introduce the
president of MIT Dr Susan hawfield she
serves as mit's 16th president and'll
give she'll give us her reflection as an
open course whereare I'd like to mention
I went back uh to her inauguration
materials uh I was involved in that and
I recalled that the theme of her
inauguration festivities the sort of
tagline was this sort of catchy phrase
uncommon in commmon which tried to evoke
what's uncommon about the place and what
we share in common with each other at
MIT and elsewhere around the world I can
think of almost nothing we've done at
MIT that better embodies that tag phrase
than open
courseware uh as someone will tell you
later over 90% of the faculty of MIT
have actually donated materials the air
course materials it's something we have
in common and the uncommonness of the
decision of MIT in around
2201 to take those materials and make
them freely accessible is truly uncommon
so with that I'm going to turn this over
to
Susan thank you Steve uh it is a great
joy to be here today for the celebration
of where we are and the celebration of
where we're going to go um I want to
begin my comments by thanking our
faculty uh the MIT faculty as Steve just
said they invented open courseware and
they've made it the ESS that it is like
um so much of MIT it's also true for
open course where our faculty are the
real stars of our show um it was a
committee of Faculty from MIT uh that
first proposed the idea of open course
Weare in
2000 and since then Steve just said
about 90% of the MIT faculty have
participated
voluntarily by contributing their
teaching materials uh to the free and
open their free and open publication in
ocw now I have say i' say voluntarily
this is the nature by which we do the
work of the University our faculty do
things voluntarily and it is simply
wonderful that our faculty chose to
participate in open course were at such
a level um it's a remarkable level of
participation 90% I'm not sure there are
many things or even one or two things
that you could say all of our faculty
have chosen to do in unison the way they
have chosen to participate in open
courseware um and it really underscores
is the dedication of our faculty to
mit's teaching Mission often people
think of a place like MIT which is a
very profound research Mission and
imagine that our faculty are only
devoted to the research m mission but we
are enormously benefited by our
faculty's dedication to the teaching
Mission and they take this
responsibility very seriously our
faculty are passionate about teaching
and they're remarkably good at it over
the years this has been reflected in the
admiration MIT students have for their
professors and since open course were
launched we've seen that kind of
admiration reflected in the comments of
people who have used open courseware
around the world in addition to the
faculty our students have played a
seminal role in open courseware they've
been integral to its success um both as
ocw staff and as
collaborators MIT students have helped
to publish the faculty materials and
have contributed content as part of two
of our International programs the MIT
international science and technology
initiative which we call Misti which is
a program where we place MIT students
around the world and a second program
called the Africa internet technology
initiative both of these are essentially
summer programs MIT students have
traveled to China and to Africa to teach
courses at other youth universities
using open courseware materials in fact
what they've done in distant
universities is help the faculty of
those universities understand how they
can use open coursework in their courses
and last but not least um our students
have themselves encouraged faculty to
participate in ocw at a level that um we
could never have achieved without
them this kind of student faculty
collaboration is really at the heart of
MIT now in addition to the students and
the faculty there are many an enormous
number of individuals advisor
institutional partners and of course the
ocw staff who deserve our thanks for
their remarkable dedication to ocw and
to the realization of its promise that
we're celebrating today now there's
excuse me a special section in your
program where we list the people and I
would uh uh send your attention to that
as a way of understanding who and how
many participated in this but I do want
to mention just a few people by name
whose extraordinary contributions and
Leadership really had an a huge impact
on
ocw first I want to call out the faculty
leaders uh I think many of if not most
of them are here dick U Hal abbl Steve
lurman Tom magnanti and chera M migawa
without their Visionary contributions
and I'm flagging support the ocw project
would not have become what it is today
and I would just ask these faculty
leaders please to stand so we can thank
them um believe it or not institu
leaders sometimes have a role in what
happens that's good at a university and
there are two past institutional leaders
who were exceptional and absolutely
unwavering champions of ocw from its
initial concept to its Inception and
through its initial stages MIT president
ameritus Chuck vest now president of the
National Academy of engineering and and
former proost of MIT Bob Brown who's now
president of Boston University were
tireless Advocates of ocw both on and
off campus their leaders ship was
instrumental in securing the funding
that allowed MIT to get started and you
know I'm bringing early Skeptics of the
program on campus to understanding some
of the opportunities that ocw presented
uh I don't think Bob is here but Chuck
is and let's thank Chuck
also and last in this line of individual
recognition is uh ocws found found in
executive director an
marges uh an much to our sadness but joy
in her next opportunity she left MIT
earlier this fall to take a role in
public service with the Commonwealth of
Massachusetts she has taken on another
opportunity for transformation another
opportunity that will allow her to serve
thousands and thousands of people an was
executive ocw from its Inception and we
owe much of the success of ocw to her
day-to-day leadership and her ex quisite
managerial expertise and thank you for
joining us today and thank you for your
contribution
govern now what you're going to hear
about today you're a lot of numbers
reflecting the use of open course Weare
and you know numbers um after numbers
after numbers that Express the success
and the penetration of ocw into you know
the minds and lives of many I would just
provide one anecdote Everywhere I Go
over the world people provide me with
ocw anecdotes and um you know they
capture in interesting ways this spark
of curiosity that got lit the
satisfaction of an educational desire uh
that was made um uh one uh insight into
the impact of ocw actually comes um from
my daughter who is of that young
generation who is you know lives out
there on the frontier of Technology um I
only visit the frontier through her and
our students um I'm not out there myself
I'm too old um but in the middle midd of
September I was on a a a trip and I got
um I was talking to our daughter on the
telephone and she said mom you've got to
go on iTunes video this is not a site
that I have bookmarked I can tell you um
you said you what you'll find on iTunes
video are some uh MIT courses but what
she was pointing out to me is that
iTunes video does um a best 10 a top 10
ranking it's always changing telling you
what the top 10 courses are top 10
courses the top 10 videos are now you
all probably know that iTunes has a
segment of the of the site that's iTunes
U so iTunes University this is not
iTunes University I'm talking about I'm
talking just about iTunes video um for u
a week or two I don't know how long it
lasted but certainly for the middle week
in the middle of September um there were
two open course Weare sites videos that
were rank ranked in the top 10 guess
what they were number three was
classical mechanics we know it as 801
number
seven differential equations
1803 go figure I
mean what this expresses to me is the
hunger in this world for Quality
education the hunger for great
educational materials and I would say
and reflect on that is our joy in having
provided ocw to a world that is using it
so so one so wonderfully um we're
delighted that all of you have joined us
this afternoon thank you for coming uh
to help us celebrate um but also thank
you for coming to partner with us as we
reflect on open course where and its
impact and we also think about uh where
ocw might take us in the future now the
story of ocw is best told by The Faculty
who created it and the individuals who
use it so we will begin the afternoon
with a short video that tells you a
little bit more about Open course we
thank you