Right. So last time we were looking at a
function from say R. or could be some
interval in R. And then we say that and
then we have a point X in R and we say
that
that f is differentiable
[Applause]
uh at x0
if when we form this different quotient.
So this was this quotion here.
If this thing here has a limit as uh if
if this here if this here has a limit
as uh x go to x0
right and so again this means that there
is some number so that if x is
sufficiently close is delta close to x0
then this quotient here is close to to
that number, right? And it's always
assumed that x is not equal to, right?
So that the denominator makes sense. So
that that is what it means for a
function to be differentiable.
And then the like one of the first
things we saw was that we had a lema
uh that if
uh if uh f is differentiable
at x0 then it implies that it's also
continuous at x0. here,
right? And then we had uh four just very
briefly we had four uh rules that if you
had two functions f and g
and they're both differentiable and
you're looking at where you add the the
two functions then the sum here of the
two functions is also differentiable and
the derivative is sum of the derivative.
Another thing we had was that if you
take a constant times a function and
this function is differentiable then
this new function is also differentiable
and the derivative is that constant
times the derivative of the original
function.
And then the third thing was the
lightness rule
and that was if you take if you have
these two functions they're
differentiable
and you take the product and you take
the derivative that exists n is equal to
the derivative of the first times the
second plus the first time the
derivative of the
And then the fourth of these was the
quotient rule.
And the quotient rule was that you have
again these two functions. You assume
that g here is not equal to zero
uh at any point. And then you're looking
at the quotient here and the quotient is
also differentiable and the derivative
is given by this formula.
Um
this this is the formula for the
derivative where this is the function
multiplied by itself. Right? And then
there was a last rule
uh that was the chain rule.
So the chain rule
uh and that was that if you take a
function say from some interval into
some uh set uh let's call it uh let's
say that it's say that the interval that
the function is defined is some interval
from a to b and this function takes
value in another interval from C to D.
And then you have a function G that is
defined on C to D
into R.
Then you can look at the composition,
right? You take some X and you first
apply F to it and then afterwards you
apply G. And this is typically written
as this.
And and the chain rule was that if f and
g are differentiable then this uh the
composition here is also differentiable
and the derivative of the composition
is the derivative of the second function
evaluated
at this point here
times the derivative of the first in
So this was the chain rule.
Okay, that was just a quick recap.
And now uh
the first thing we'll be interested in
is if we have a so suppose
that f here is a function let's say
defined on some interval from a to b
into r and f is differentiable.
It doesn't need to be differentiable for
this here to make sense. But uh but we
say that x0
and x0 is now in
the open interval here. We say that uh
so we say
we say that
x0
um is so we say that
f
has a local maximum
at x0.
If if there exist
[Applause]
exist delta greater than zero such that
if you restrict f and you just think
about f on this little interval
around x0.
So you're forgetting about how f looks
like everywhere else. Then if you're
looking at the maximum
of this function. So this means that so
this is the same as just the maximum of
f on uh on this little interval
then the maximum
is achieved at x0. Right? If this is the
case, so you have the picture here. You
have a function. We talked about this a
little bit last time. You have a
function. Maybe the function looks like
this.
And this here point here is x0.
And so this here is the value at x0. And
you see that there's some little
interval. Say this interval here. If
you're looking at the function in this
little interval, then it's clear that
the maximum is is at x0, right? But of
course, it's just a local maximum. If
you were allowed to move further away
over here, you see that the value of the
function is much larger. Right? So this
is a local maximal. And for this to make
sense, you don't need the function to be
differentiable.
But we will when we apply it we will
assume that it is differentiable. So
this is a local maximum right and this
is sort of the picture right that is
it's it's just maximum near
uh if you're looking at at values near
x0 but it's not a global maximum. Of
course it could be a global maximum.
And then similarly
for
a a local minimum
and I'll just draw a picture, you know,
because the definition is kind of
obvious. It's the same, right? That um
that you take a function here and and
you're looking at and so the function
maybe could look like this.
Right? And you see that if this here was
X0,
then in some little neighborhood around
this the value here would indeed be the
minimum, right? But if you're moving
much further away, then there might be
other points that are even small where
the value is even smaller, right? So
this is like a local minimum. And so the
the first observation you have about
this is the following lema.
If f here is a function say on an
interval like this is differentiable
uh and
has
a local
maximum
or minimum
local minimum
at x0. And now here if I'm thinking
about a function defined on a closed
interval like this, it's important that
where the local max or min is in an
interior point. It's not allowed to be
one of the boundary points.
So if it has a local if it is
differentiable and it has a local
maximum or minimum at such an interior
point then
then the claim is that then the
derivative
at x0 is is equal to zero.
Okay.
And so now let's try to prove that.
[Applause]
So we have here right. So the picture is
let's just assume so uh prove
assume
that if
has a local
uh maximum
at x0 if it's a local minimum the
argument is is the same with obvious
modifications. Okay. So you have some
picture like this again here you have x0
and now this here is like the function
that oops maybe this so this is like the
function and we see that at the value
here at x0 it's maximum and then who
cares you know we don't care about what
happened when you are further away here
right and so you divide into two cases
you're looking at where x here is bigger
than x0
If x is bigger than x0 and now you're
looking at so then you have that f ofx
minus f of x0
right this the value here is maximum. So
this thing this value here is by it. So
if this is the case and
x is
sufficiently closed
close
to to x0 right if it's very close here
then it has a maximum at this point. So
this means that this difference here is
non-positive,
right?
This didn't really use that it was
strictly bigger than, right? It just
used that it was close to x0, right?
But but now this is where we're using
that it's bigger than because you also
have we also have
that x - x0 and again this is where this
assumption is used. This in here is
positive. Right?
So this means that if you take something
non-positive and you divide it by
something positive then the then what
you get is something that is nonpositive
right so this means that so this implies
that for the difference quotient f ofx
minus f of x0
x - x0
right again this here is non positive
this here is positive
which means that the whole thing is non
positive. Right? So as you are
approaching as you're going towards x0
from the right the difference quotient
here is non positive. Right? If you if
you now go to
x0 from the left if you go
if you go in this direction. So this
means that now you have x here is less
than x0 here right and sufficiently
close.
So if you have that then uh well you you
again have this was just because it was
a local maximum. You still have that
this thing here is not positive.
But now you have that now now we have
that x minus x0
right this thing here now is be right
because of this this means that this
thing here strictly lessens right. So
you take something that is non-positive
and you divide it by something negative
then you get something non- negative
right. So therefore this implies that
for the difference quotient f ofx minus
f of x0 for the difference quotient here
you get that this thing here this is
nonpositive this is negative this means
that this here is non negative right so
as you're coming in so you see that
that as you're approaching in this this
direction to x0 then the difference
quotient is non positive. When you're
coming in here, it's non- negative, but
it has a limit. And so the limit from
this side would have to be right. This
is the limit from this side would have
to be non-positive. And the limit from
this one non- negative. So therefore the
limit must be zero. Right? So we
conclude that the limit here So we
conclude that the limit
hence
uh the limit here as x goes to x0 of f
ofx of the different function
must be zero.
And so this is the derivative
at that point. And similarly if it was a
local minimum. Okay.
now
and and a point where and a point where
the derivative
um so maybe I'll just say that um so so
if
if um fprime at x0 is equal to zero then
we often say that then x0 is set to be
a critical point
for for for f. Okay. And let me just
give you an example. So I mean let me
give you three two examples.
So suppose you take f ofx
= to x2. Right? This here is a polomial.
We know how to compute the derivative of
any polomial. This is just using the
lightness rule. And I mean using these
rules in this case you would only need
the lightness rule together with we know
what the derivative of of the function f
ofx = to x is. So in this case the
derivative of this here
is 2x.
And so this means that x = z is a
critical point.
It's actually the only critical point
and so you see in this case this is how
the function look like right this is
sort of how the function look like here
you have zero
right
another example is that if you take the
another polomium uh where it's instead
of x to the^ 2 it's x ^ three, then the
derivative of of of this function is
3x^2,
right? And so you see again that x = 0
is a critical point. The derivative here
if you plug in zero gets zero. So this
is a critical point.
But in this case, in this case the the
the
graph of the function for this example
here the graph looks like it looks like
something like this
becomes very flat here like this. Okay.
And so you see that so zero is a
critical point but it's not like it has
a local maximum minimum. Okay. And and
it's this Yeah.
Okay. So the next thing I want to do is
I want to now apply it uh I want to
apply this symbol observation uh and uh
uh I want to apply it in to get a
consequence
simple consequence and then I want to
apply that simple consequence to get a
lot of other consequences.
So the first thing I want to do is
what's called roles lema theorem.
So,
so we have uh
so this is the following
that I have a function f
from uh a to b
uh into
uh R
and I'm assuming that F is
differentiable
and I'm also assuming that the value
initially
and the value at the end
that those two values are the same.
Sometimes one set those value equal to
zero but it's just they just need to be
the same. Um and then the claim is that
then
there exist
uh x0
where
x0 is strictly between a and b
and
the derivative
at this x0
is equal to zero. Okay.
And so the idea is just very simple that
you have
you have uh
you have a function
and the function initially this is at a
here you have b the function initially
and at the end end up at the same value.
So this here is right. So this is
this here is f a and that's the same as
f of b
and then who knows what happened in
between
maybe like this and the claim is that
then there's always some point where the
derivative is zero. In this case it
looks like that those two would be the
point right where the derivative was
zero.
And the proof is just this. So prove
that there's three cases to consider
to consider
one is I mean you don't really have to
divide it up by list but let me divide
it up into these three cases. One is
that the function here is constant.
It's everywhere equal to the same.
Right? Well, if the function is
constant, then the derivative is zero.
Right? We have already proven that. Case
two
there exist
uh somewhere there exist x such that
the value at this x is strictly bigger
than the value at the end points.
And then case three,
uh, there exists an x such that the
value at this x is strictly less than
the values at the input.
Right? It's clear that one of these
three cases happen, right? I mean, of
course, it could be that case two and
three could have both happen, right? But
at least one of the three cases would
happen, right?
In case one, we already know that the
derivative is zero everywhere. So let's
just look at case two. Case three is
similar, right? So if there exists some
x where the value so in this picture
here, this here is maybe x the value
here is larger than at the two end
points, right?
Well, by the extreme value theorem right
that we proved earlier just because if a
function is differentiable it's also
continuous by the extreme value theorem
there exists somewhere where actually
the maximum is achieved right and since
somewhere in between in in this case
here the maximum is the maximum is not
achieved at the two end points right so
the maximum must be achieved at at an
interior point, right?
But now it's it's not just a local
maximum. It actually is a a maximum. But
already if it was a local maximum, the
derivative would be zero at that point.
Right? So this proved case two and case
three is is similar. Right? So this is
ro theorem.
Okay? Now Bless theorem have then a
bunch of applications
and the first one is to uh what's called
the mean value theorem
and there are two versions of the mean
value theorem.
one is is the active mean value theorem
and the other is like a fancy version of
it which where you have two functions in
play at the same time and that's called
the cushib value the
so so
consequence for first consequence
of the
uh and this is the mean value the
okay and so the first one is the the
actual mean value theorem
and then actually Meanwhile, theorem say
that if we take a function uh f
from a to b on some interval like this
that and the function is differentiable.
Then uh then there exist a x
X strictly there exist X where X is
strictly between A and B
and so that the derivative
at X is equal to the difference quotion
where you do the difference quotient at
the at the two end points.
So this here is this this side of it
that's what you often call the mean and
the mean is equal to the derivative at
some intermediate points. This is what
they say. Okay.
And so now
right so this seems a lot better than
the uh but it's an easy consequence of
the
because if you look at so
So if you look at
suppose you take the function. So pro
suppose you take the function
uh h of x
equal to f ofx
minus uh f of b minus f of a.
divided by uh x uh sorry divided by b
minus a * x - a suppose you're looking
at this function here h right
then observe first that so this one this
function is differentiable this is just
a constant
right this is just a linear function
right this is a is a constant also So
this is differentiable. This is a
constant. This is differentiable. And
we're subtracting it from a
differentiable function. So h is
differentiable.
Uh h of a is f of a, right? And then
this thing here minus f of b minus f of
a
b minus a. And then this here is a minus
a. So this is zero. So this is f of a
h of b
is f of b
minus and then f of b minus f of a
b minus a. And here you plug in b. So b
minus a. And so you see that this here
these here cancel out
and you are right. So you are
subtracting this but this is a minus
minus so you're adding so this is f of a
right so you see that for this function
it's the value at a and b are the same
right
so so now we apply Water is still.
So now we have bibles.
by them applied to
to to h, right? Then we have that um
that h
is equal to zero. The derivative of h is
equal to zero for some x
where
X is strictly between A and B. Right?
This is R theorem. This because this
function H has the same value at A as at
B. Right? Now, what is the derivative of
H? Uh h H. Yeah. So the derivative of H
is the derivative of F.
And this is just again this is just a
constant. So we have to keep that minus
f of b minus f of a
b b minus a and then u the derivative.
So this just a constant and then
derivative of this is just one. So this
here is what the derivative is. And so
you see that so we have this x where
this the derivative is zero. So this
here is zero.
But if this here is zero, it means that
this thing here is equal to that. Right?
And so that was the mean value theorem.
So let's prove the mean value theorem.
Okay?
There's a second mean theorem and the
second one is the Kushim
and so this is a little more fancy.
Uh so the cushiming I assume.
So this is the following
that you have two functions uh f and g.
So we have f g
on some interval
from a to b
into r and they are both differentiable.
um they're both differentiable
and then the claim is that there exist
there exist
uh there exist uh x let's call it x0 uh
maybe I should have called it x0 up
there just two just one exist x0
with
x0 strictly between a and E
and and um okay and so that it's
something about that the derivative of
the both functions kind of behave like
the mean value theorem at the same time.
Okay. So it is that the derivative
I I will explain this in in a second
that the derivative at this point times
uh g of b minus g of a
is equal to the derivative of
of g at x0
f of b minus f of a
okay
so this is the this is the kushi uh mean
theorem okay so say that for this
And let's let's just look at that
expression here before we prove it.
in your thumb.
So
if you had if if now so as a consequence
so observe
that if
uh g of b
is not equal for
to uh g of a
and
g prime
at x0
is not equal to zero.
If you have that then you could divide
you could have this expression let's say
that um then you would by just dividing
this here on both sides and this here on
both sides you would get that fprime of
x0 divided by g prime at x0 is equal to
f of b minus f of a
uh G of B minus G of A.
Okay, you would have that. Right?
Now, I could think about this thing here
as f of B minus F of A
divided by uh B minus A.
So, I could think about it like this.
and then times b minus a
g of b minus g of a.
Okay. And so you see that this here it's
something about right the actual mean
value theorem say that this thing here
that there would be some point x0 in
between that was equal to this right
that would be the mean value theorem
applied to f right and the meani term
applied to g would be that there exist
some x0 so that one over this is equal
to this thing here Right? And the Kushi
Min theorem say that you can kind of
arrange so that both of these things
happen at the same time. Okay.
So, so this seems actually pretty good,
right? I mean, you can do it at the same
time. It's a little bit surprising in a
way, but but the proof is is quite
trivial.
Uh so, but it's it's useful. So the
proof is the following
that you just look right. So this is
what we want to prove right. So you just
define so you just and the x0 is
unknown. So if I if I take this
expression that I want to prove if I
move this thing here over on the other
side right then I would get then I would
get so I would define in this case I
would define f of h of x to be f
of x g b minus g a minus
uh g of x
um fb minus fa.
So I would define it like this. And you
see that when you now take the
derivative of h,
you just get this here,
right? This is because everything else
is constant.
So this is what you get right and you
want to find a x0
where you want to find so want to find
x0 where this thing here
is zero right to find such a x0 is the
same as saying that you have find an x0
over here right
now
so now let's see what What is the value
of h at a?
If you plug in a here, then you get uh f
of a g of b minus g of a
minus g of a
f of b minus f of a.
Okay. And so now you see that the here I
have f uh sorry I have uh this one here
this one here I have f of a times g of a
that comes with a minus sign I have the
same term over here but that comes with
a plus so those two cancel out so I'm
just get f of a
g of B minus G of A
F of B.
So that's what I get there.
And now I look at H of B.
So if I plug in B up here for X, then
I'm getting
then I get uh F of B
g of B minus G of A
minus G of B
F of B minus F of A.
Okay.
And now you see that this when you
multiply this by this
that term f of b g of b you have this
over here also but it comes with a minus
sign. So those cancel out and so you're
getting a term this the only term that
lives is this one times that so minus g
of a f of b and then you get this term
minus min - or plus g of b
f of a
and
right that's right and now you see that
this is the same as that and the these
two here
uh are the same. Right?
So you see that so we conclude here from
this we conclude that h of a is equal to
h of b right so again it's satisfying
the requirements of roller theorem and
so there is this intermediate point
where the derivative was zero but we've
but if the derivative of h is zero
that's exactly the kind the point we
wanted to find right where you have this
Okay.
And so so again, you know, the kushi mim
is sort of a stronger statement,
but it's just it's a it's a stronger
statement because it's like it allow you
to have two functions and then you uh
know this point where sort of the to
some extent the mean value for both
functions are satisfied. Right? That's
the idea.
uh and but it's an example of where
actually the proof
it in fact worked more generally than
than than what you used it for initially
to and the initially you just use it for
a single function right to prove the
mean math theorem.
Okay.
Now uh so now we want to prove so now we
have a number of consequences of this
um and um and the first one
um
let me that
let me start with um
with another consequence of polytherm
and then I come back to the kushid meth
so tail taylor expansion
So the idea here is that you have a
function uh f
um and you have a function
um let's say let's say that it's a
function on r doesn't need to be defined
on all of r into r and uh f
uh I'm assuming so Let me do a special
case of this. So a special case first.
So I assume I have a function like this
and uh that is differentiable
and then I'm assuming that the
derivative so the derivative is our
function from R into R and I'm assuming
that the derivative is also
differentiable.
And the idea is now that I'm looking at
the function and the idea is so the idea
is like this again in a minute I'll
prove a more general statement but I
just prove this one first to make the
idea clear. So the idea is that you want
to say
that
f locally
can be
approximated
by a polinomial.
So that's the idea of the tail
expansion. Okay, that that if you if you
take a function
that's if you take a function like this
some function and you take a point then
in a neighborhood let's say that this is
some point here x0 then in a
neighborhood of this point
instead of looking at the function you
get you could get a very good idea about
how the function behave in this small
neighborhood if you look at a certain
polomial. Okay? And the higher degree
the polomial, the better the
approximation is to the function. And so
we'll just do a simple version of this
first
where you're looking at the
so in this case I would look at the so
so I have
um so I so we have f here
and I'm interested in in in uh in f so
we will be interested in f near
x0
and then you're looking at what's called
the tailor polom
at x0. Okay. And the tail polom it
depends on how many times you're willing
to take the derivative. And so in this
case I just look at the first tail
polinomial.
So this here is and now it is the tail
polomial at x0.
So this thing here is by definition the
value of f at x0 plus
uh and then the derivative
of f at x0
x - x0.
So this here is the first order tailor
expansion. So it's this here would be is
often often called the first order
tail expansions
expansion
addiction.
Okay.
Now the what you're interested in is
you're interested in showing that this
one this polomium here. So, so the again
the idea is
that uh that f ofx
should be almost equal to p1 of x if
x0 here
sorry if x is almost equal to x0 right
so near x0
the function is very well approximated
by in this case this linear function.
Okay. And so now but you want to so now
the key here is
is what is uh
how do you estimate
how well it approximates? Okay. And so
the thing is that
that um so so the statement is then that
so you have here x0
you have here x and the claim is now
that there exist there exist
some c between
uh x0
and x strictly between So between which
means that it's strictly between
let me just write that
X could also lie on the other sides
right then I you know it's sort of
obvious what I mean strictly between
also
so there exists some X some C in between
these two so that uh f of x is equal to
this tailor polinomial
plus and then um uh the second
derivative. So this is the derivative of
the derivative.
This is so so f2 here is the derivative
and then you take the derivative like
that
and that is evaluated at c and then
divided by two and then it's x uh minus
x0
square
okay
and in a minute I would just do the
general case of
Okay. So this is this is the
um
right and so now
how do you prove this?
So
what you do is so let's try to prove
this. So
So I define a M. We define a M.
m is just some real number
and it's defined so that um f of x
uh I wonder if I should in my notes here
in my notes I call it just because I
thought it was clear and maybe I will do
this here also I call this point here A
and this here B and then C here is
somewhere in between. Right? So this
means that this thing here is B and this
here is B and this here is is then B and
this here is A.
Okay, it's just to be clear that somehow
you know you're kind of fixing X, right?
Okay.
Now, so to prove it, so I we look at
this thing here
and you uh you look at
this thing here and you define uh and we
subtract
P1 of B and then we uh define M. So that
you have that this thing here
uh is b minus a squared right. So, so
define M
by this thing here, right? This here
just gives you some number.
A and B are difference. So, this is non
zero. So, this here so M is just given
by that is this difference here divided
by this here
times two. Right?
So, that's how we defined M.
And but now we want to show need to show
right so like M is like in if you do it
like this it's like M is okay it's just
by definition
the you have so so now we have by so so
so we have by definition we have
we have that uh f of b again is equal to
p1 1 of B uh + M 2 B minus A square.
Okay.
But we need to prove
we need to show
that M here is the second derivative of
the original function at some
intermediate point. Right? That's what
we need to prove. Right.
And so you're looking at at um
you're looking at. So now we're looking
at the function h ofx
equal to f ofx
minus p1 of x - m / 2 x - a 2. Right? So
if we're looking at this function,
well if we're looking at h of let let me
do b first. So if I do B then this here
is F of B
minus P1 of B minus M / 2 B - A^ 2 but M
was defined so that this thing here is
equal to that. So by definition this is
by by definition of M
I have that this thing here. So,
right.
If I'm now looking at h of of a
well this thing here, here you get f of
a.
Here you get minus p1 of a. If you plug
in a here then this is zero. So you get
so this is what you get right. But
remember how P1 was given P1 was here
right and we now do it at A. So this
here is really A.
Okay. So you see that when you plug in X
here this thing here is zero. So you
just get f of a here. So this thing here
is is f of a minus f of a. So that's
zero.
Right?
So you see that if you're looking at
this function here then at a it's zero
at b it's zero. So, pyrolysis pyosium.
Uh they exist they exist
uh C1
with between
A and B
such that
H prime of C is is equal to zero. Okay.
Now,
that's not the that's not the sorry,
this is the C1, right? It's not the C we
want we're looking for, right? The C
we're looking for is something where the
second derivative is something, right?
But now you see that now you have this
function H and here you have a,
here you have C1 and then you have B is
further away like this. And you have
that the derivative in this case the
derivative is zero at at a and the
derivative
uh sorry not the derivative not at at a
but the derivative at this point here h
prime
is equals to zero. Let's calculate what
the derivative of h is at a. Right? I
want to apply the RERS theorem a second
time. But in order to apply Roers
theorem a second time,
I really need the derivative of h at a
to be zero. But let's see what it's
equal to.
And so again,
we have h up there at the top.
And so this means that h prime
is equal to fprime minus and then the
tailor polomium here was a tailor
polomium. This is just when you take
derivative this is just a constant
you're getting frime
a right this is all it gives you when
you take the derivative of this here.
Um and then uh you're getting minus and
you're getting m
x - a. That's when you take the
derivative of the last term. Okay. So
this is what you get and this here is at
x.
But so now h prime at a
this is frime at a minus frime at a this
thing here is actually zero.
So you see that this whole thing is zero
right? So we have what we have is that
we have that h prime at c1 is zero and
this is also equal to the derivative of
a right.
So we can apply what is them a second
time right? So by applying water sim
a second time
uh we have
a C2 and now this C2 that's really going
to be our C in this case. Uh so we have
a second
uh C
where the derivative of the derivative
so the second derivative of H
at that point is equal to zero. Okay.
And this one here, remember this here is
when you apply roer theorem, you started
with A, you had here B, then you got C1
that was between these two, that was C1.
But now you're looking at H prime in
this interval. And so the second one is
lying here,
right? So it's it's certainly between A
and B, but it's actually even between A
and C1. Right? Now what does this here
means? Right? So we hope that this is
the one the point we're looking for. And
so to calculate the second derivative
you to calculate the second derivative.
So this here uh this here was the
derivative of h. So we just need to take
another derivative of h. So if we do
this then uh we get that so hp prime of
x at some x is equal to f double prime
at x and then you see this thing here
this is just a constant this is a linear
functions the derivative of this one
here is one so you're getting this minus
m
right and now we know that hp prime at
this intermediate point C2 which we also
call C that's equal to zero. So this
means that FP prime at the C minus M is
equal to zero. So this means that M
really was the second derivative
of F at this point, right? Okay. So
she's proves sort of clever that you
you know it's you know it's but if you
the proof seems very clever but if you
think about it um
I mean it's so it's applying royers
theorem twice but it's sort of in a way
the only thing it could be but anyway
okay so that was uh so that was Taylor
this was just a special case of tail
expansion. Let me state the general
case. So the general case is so so
right. So in in for to proving the
special case we applied roy theorem
twice but you can actually apply roy
theorem like k times and so if you apply
it k times then you're getting the kt
tail expansion.
So, so this here is the the general case
of the tail expansion.
So, general case
of tail expansion.
So the general case is that you take a
function
on R into R. You assume assume
that f is differentiable
but also that f prime is differentiable
and all the way up to say f the k the k
uh by you you assume that that that it's
differentiable and all the way up to the
k minus one derivative is also
differentiable. So this here exist
right? So all of these exist all these
derivative exist.
And then the claim is that so now the
tailor polomium the k
taylor polinomial
or some
or or if you or sometimes called the uh
tailum
uh of the
uh uh uh k minus one
is that you're looking at
so this sorry this here should be the k
minus one tail for
so this is where you write so you take
again
You have here A and you have B.
Let me write it with A and B instead of
with X, you know, because I think it's a
little clearer. So, so the thing is that
the polomium is where you say you expand
around um a and so the polomium
this is the k minus one polomium
there that for that we write it in terms
of x and this is the polomium where the
constant term is the value of f at a
the um The derivative, the coefficient
to the first order term is frime at a
and then x - a.
The coefficient to the second is the
second derivative at a and now it's
divided by 2 x - a squared. And then
it's this next one is f triple prime.
And now it's really 3 * 2 * 1
* x - a to the^ 3.
And then you continue like this
up to the k minus one derivative.
And then it's k -1
factorial
x - a k minus one.
So this is this is the k minus one ton.
Okay. And so you observe that you can
just write it. So it's typically written
like this that f the k d the i
derivative
in a divided by i factorial
x - a to the power i. and I is now
summing from uh from zero
to to uh k minus one.
This is by definition equal to that.
Okay. So that's a tailor polinomial the
the k minus one tailor polomium. And now
the tailor the general case of the
tailor expansion
is then
so the general case of the tailor
expansion is then that
that's um so
so this is like the third
cell expansion.
So you have again this function on R
into R and you have that all of the
derivative
up to and including the K derivative
they all exist
and then you have that uh F of B is
equal to the K minus one tailor polomial
at B
plus and then the this is this term is
usually called the remainder term and
the rema and the key point here is that
it's easy to estimate to estimate the
remainder term because there's an
expression for it this is the k
derivative of f in this point that is an
intermediate point divided by k
factorial
uh C minus
uh sorry uh B minus uh A to the power K,
right? And and where where where
C here is lying between A and B.
Okay.
Right. And and again the idea is that
you take you have a function any
function
it needs to be differentiable
k times but then actually it's very
close to a a polomium of degree k minus
one and you can estimate it how close it
is in terms of this term here
and so the proof of this right so the
proof It's really just what we did. But
let's just go over it again. You know,
we only did the first uh where we did it
in a case where K was equal to two. And
now let me try to do this in general.
So you're looking at f of b minus right
we have this tail polomial k minus one
tail polomium
um
um and you're looking at you define so
define
m by the equation
that this here is m / k factorial
* uh b minus a to the power k.
So this here is how right u m is defined
right b is not equal to m. So this is
just some positive some whatever some
yeah it's actually a positive constant
right and so you can just uh right so
you can just so so
m here is given as the difference of
those two and then divided by this and
multiply by k factorial right so this
defines m
and so and now uh what you do is you
then define h as before or similarly to
before.
H is then going to be f of x - p k -1 of
x - m over k factorial
x - a to the^ k
right that's how you define
uh h right and by definition of m
by definition
of m you have that h of b is equal to
zero. Right? This is how this is another
way of of saying how we defined m.
Right?
Now if you look at so now h of a
well h of a here is
um well h of a is just f of a
minus p k minus one of a minus m over k
factorial x - a to the power k and this
is you know a so this one here is
clearly zero A minus A is zero, right?
So that's clearly zero.
And this thing here, that's this
polomial Ivered up here, right? So if
you plug in here, A, you see this term
here and all the other terms drops out.
It's only this one that lives, right? So
this thing here is this is the same as f
of a.
And so you have that the whole thing is
actually zero. Right?
So because we chose M this way, we see
that now RM can get started. Right? And
so RM can get started and uh this means
that there exist a C1 between A and B
where the derivative of H is zero.
Right? Now you check that the if you're
looking at this function again that and
take the derivative at a the derivative
at a is also zero. Right? In fact, the
the whole idea is that all these
derivative up to the k minus one
derivative
of you know if you're looking at the k
minus one all the way up to the k minus
one derivative of h they are all zero at
a. Okay. So you can repeat the romium.
So this first here, this thing here
together with this allows you to find
this C1
strictly between A and B where the
derivative
is is zero. Then you observe that the
derivative of h at a is zero. This then
allows you to find a point between
a and a second point c1 which was less
than b where the derivative second
derivative
is zero. Now you use that the second
derivative at of h at a is also zero. So
this give you you apply v theorem one
more time. Each time you apply radium
the se is moving to the left right
towards a right and so you apply it
uh you apply the k times and it and once
you do this you get eventually that this
m here is the derivative of of the
original function at this point. Okay.
So I I wrote this out. I now I did the
special case and I try to explain this
here. I wrote it out in the notes. It's
written out in the general case only.
But it on the other hand is written out
completely there.
Any questions?
There's two things we didn't get to.
There's these two rules about how to
evaluate fractions that uses the Kushi
mean value theorem and I'll start with
those those they're in the notes but I
will start with that next time. Yeah.
then you get the the that's when you get
the C that you're actually looking for,
right? And so in the special case I
looked at K was equal to two and the
tailor expansion was a linear so it was
a right it was a polomial of degree one.
So k minus one was one right and so so
in in the special case we applied them
twice
um and in this case we do it k