All right. Well, today's guest lecture
is James Shepard uh with Quant Quantile.
>> Quantile. Yeah.
>> Which is a uh wholly owned uh subsidiary
of LSCG.
and uh your background in quant finance
is quite long. Yep.
>> And so I'll let you share some of the
highlights. Okay. Thank you very much,
James.
>> Thank you very much. Do I need that or
not? Okay. Thank you very much. Thank
you for having me. Um this supposed to
finish about a quarter to 4. Yeah, I
would hope to leave some time for for
questions.
>> Yeah. 10.
>> Okay. Uh thank you very much for having
me. Yes, I'm James. Yes, I work for
Quantile Technologies. Um, that's a
fintech company. Um, founded in about
2016 to do counterparty risk
optimization, uh, which is the subject
of today's talk. Um, a couple of years
ago, we got bought out by the London
Stock Exchange Group, which is why my
email now says uh, LSEG. Prior to that,
I was at Morgan Stanley for quite a long
time, which is where I know kind of
Vasili and Jake from, which is kind of
how I've ended up here.
Um, so we're going to talk today, we're
going to kind of work our way up to
talking about um optimizing a thing
called initial margin, which is a
measure of counterparty risk. Um, so
we're going to start off talking about
different types of risk. Sorry. Sorry.
>> Uh, I've just emailed them to Peter.
Sorry about that.
>> Um, the first few is just kind of like
warm-up stuff so you're not missing too
much. Um, so the first the first part of
the talk we're going to talk about are
different types of risk that you have
with um, derivative trading. Um, and
we're going to talk about um, expected
shortfall and and value at risk. Um just
out of interest, do people know what
these terms are or is it worth my
explaining them a little bit?
>> Okay, I will do that. Um then we'll talk
about how that relates to initial margin
uh and counterparty risk and then we'll
kind of work our way up to uh how we
optimize uh this initial margin uh
within a network of uh financial inst
institutions.
and we'll talk a lot about the sort of
challenges that you get in in the real
world. Um, because this is a maths kind
of talk, I feel morally obliged to to
chuck some equations in the thing from
time to time, but largely I'll kind of
skip over that and talk a little bit
about some of the intuition, some of the
toy models. Um, and I put a bunch of
references when you get the thing.
There's a bunch of references at the end
uh which have got sort of some of the
proper maths and proofs uh and more
detailed stuff behind it if if you're
interested in that.
Okay, so in the shape of derivatives,
when we talk about the different kinds
of risks that can arise when you're
trading derivatives, um market risk is
probably the most common one, right? So
that's the value of your derivative goes
up and down as the as the market
changes. Um credit risk um again is sort
of reasonably well kind of uh
understood. It's um the the arises when
you've got exposure to uh a data um
defaulting, right? Operational risk is
is largely when somebody screws up. Um
it's probably actually the hardest one
to do any mathematical modeling on
operational risk because it's quite hard
to to to to model people just messing
up, right? Which is really what that is.
Um liquidity risk um is when you've got
a transaction which is um it's well as
the name suggests illquid. It's going to
happen when you've got a very large
position. So if you're trying to sell a
massive position in some particular
stock you start selling that thing and
then because you start selling it that
moves the market and so you can't sell
the whole thing at the position that the
market was kind of when you started. Um
so liquidity risk happens. It happens if
it's a kind of obscure instrument and
we'll come back to it in this it happens
again if you've got a very very large
position and what we're mostly going to
talk about today is counterparty risk um
which is the the exposure that you've
got uh to when you trade derivatives to
a counterparty defaulting um I think
maybe question you might come ac have
here is what's the difference between
counterparty risk and credit risk. Um so
the example you can have to
differentiate this is if I do a trade
with Goldman Sachs that's say a credit
derivative swap that has some JP Morgan
uh corporate bond as the underlying then
I have credit risk with respect to JP
Morgan because if JP Morgan defaults on
its corporate bond then the value of my
derivative will will will change and I
have counterparty risk to Goldman Sachs
because depending on what happens to the
value of that derivative Goldman Sachs
may or may not pay me that amount of
money. Is that that's that's the
difference between those those two
make sense?
Okay. Uh so once you've got uh type of
risk once you've got some risk um
generally speaking you want to mitigate
it. I reduce either the probability of
it happening or reduce the impact of uh
that risk happening. Not just for
counterparty risk for all kinds of risk,
right? um should hopefully reasonably
obvious that people want to try and make
the the impact of the of once you've
identified the risk make the impact of
that smaller. So there's a bunch of
different ways that you can uh do that.
We're largely going today to talk about
the hedging, right? Which means book
some trades to offset book some new
trades which will offset the risk that
you've just discovered that you've got.
Um and we'll talk about uh
collateralization, right? which is
really paying margin payments from um
from the person you've got the person
who you have you're exposed to. You
would collect a margin payment from them
which is kind of like an insurance
payment against them defaulting and
that's mostly what we're going to talk
about today. Um there are other things
you can do. Um, and there's a thing
called central clearing counterparties,
which I thought nobody would have heard
of, but apparently someone's Andrew
Gunstensson has already sort of
mentioned this a little bit, so hope I
might skip over this slide. Um, because
they are kind of important in the
trading of of derivatives. Um, so I have
a quick slide on CCPs. Um, so normally
you trade derivatives and they're
bilateral trades, right? So JP Morgan
trades with Goldman Sachs and so on. So,
we've got here you've got four parties.
Say A trades with B. A trades with C.
Um, it's got a position of 100 versus B,
125 in the opposite direction versus C.
And what a central clearing uh
counterparty does, as the name kind of
suggests, is that it steps into the
middle of all these trades, right? And
so instead of A facing facing B and A
facing C, A just faces the CCP, right?
And so does B and so does C and so does
D. Um just by doing that you haven't
really achieved much. You've just
changed your counterparty risk from
being uh from being versus uh uh B and C
to versus the CCP. But once the thing is
in the CCP um you've got both the 125
and the 100 and you can net those two
positions together, right? And so you
can net that down and say, well now
instead of having 100 plus 125, I've
only got 25, right? As my as my risk,
right? And the same story for all the
others, right? So in the case of B,
right, when it had exactly equal and
offsetting positions, B's ended up with
no counterparty risk at all. So B's in a
very very happy situation and everyone
else is slightly happier than they were
before. Um there are other advantages of
CCPs. Um which um I'm not really going
to talk about too much, but the thing to
know is that some derivatives are
mandated to clear at CCP. So interest
rate swaps pretty much if you have a
standard vanilla interest rate swap, you
have to do this, right? You don't get a
choice. Um but more exotic trades like
say an interest rate swap or something
sorry an interest rate swapion. Um they
are not eligible to be cleared at a CCP.
So some are some are not. So what you
end up with is a portfolio with some
bilateral trades versus a bunch of
different counterparties and some trades
at the CCP. Right? So almost everybody
will end up with a mixture uh of stuff.
Okay.
Um so now we're going to talk about uh
quantitative risk risk measures, right?
So what you want from a risk measure or
any general risk measure. Um it should
quantify somewhat the size of the total
risk or the size of the total impact.
How much money could you possibly lose?
and it should also quantify the
probability of uh
of losing that amount. Right? So there's
two aspects to it, the size and the
probability. Um so in 1999
um there's a paper by Artsner um there's
a reference in the at the back um kind
of came up with these um properties of a
risk function which are sort of nice
properties right which are known as as a
coherent risk function if it satisfies
those uh five five properties right
mostly they say things like um the
function behaves kind of normally right
Um we'll come back. So the important one
is subadditivity,
right? Uh anyone heard of subadditivity
as a thing? So basically what that says
is if I have two portfolios X1 and X2
and I've got some risk on X1 and some
risk on X2 and then I bash those two
portfolios together, right? And now I've
got a combined portfolio. the risk on my
combined portfolio according to my risk
measure ought to be less than or equal
to the sum of the risk on the two
portfolios I had in the first place
right which seems kind of sensible if I
put two if I put some stuff here and
some stuff here and put it together it
seems unlikely that I've manufactured
some risk out of doing this but
conversely it seems highly plausible
that there might be some diversification
of putting these two things together and
so my overall risk might well be smaller
it seems a very plausible and reasonable
uh property to um ask for from a risk
from a risk measure. Okay.
Um so we're going to talk about two risk
measures in particular, right? Which are
probably the two most common ones for
looking at a whole portfolio. One is
value at risk, which um I probably will
keep referring to as VAR. Um and the
other is expected shortfall, right? So
value at risk right is this this amount
here says if I've got it say is um
what is the maximum for a given
confidence level what is the maximum
amount that I can say that I will lose
more than that amount right so for
example
um can I be 99% certain that I won't
lose more than $10 million over say the
next 10 days Right. So I have a
confidence level here is called uh beta.
Um there's a time horizon which we'll
talk about uh in a sec. And the VA is um
that that how much money can I be 99% or
beta percent confident that I won't lose
more than this amount. Okay.
The expected shortfall says conditional
that I've exceeded that amount of that
amount of loss. Right. So given I'm in
the the 1% tail, right? If if if bet is
99% or the 5% tail if beat is 95% if I'm
in that tail right what is my expected
loss given that I've exceeded VA right
so that's what expected expected
shortfall is right so hopefully it's
indicated on here that this is the
percentage this dark area here is um one
minus beta so this is say 1% or 5% right
the var is the biggest amount before I
get into the the tail right and the
Expected shortfall is the average value
of that tail. Yeah. Uh clearly the
expected shortfall should be bigger than
the VAR, right? Hopefully that's
obvious, right? Uh for the same for the
same confidence uh level.
Um
got that.
Um so VAR was kind of popularized by JP
Morgan and about the 1990s um something
like that. expected shortfall came
around in about 2000 and both of them
are heavily used by regulators and lots
and lots of kind of counterparty risk
measures uh today. Um,
var is probably the most well-known one,
right? And most common. Um, it's got a
couple of problems, right? The first
problem is if you have these kind of
weird sort of fat tail probabilities,
right? So, you've got two probability
distributions, red and blue, right? Um,
the blue has this weird fat tail bit
over here, right? And we'll just say,
well, the area under the blue bit and
the red bit is the same. So both these
distributions have the same var right
because the area up to here right assume
there's a little bit of blue here the
area up to here uh is the same as the
area under that so both these
distributions have the same var right
but clearly the blue one has a much
bigger probability of doing some fairly
horrific loss right and also hopefully
clearly the blue one would have a much
bigger expected shortfall than the red
one because the average of the blue one
is about here the average the red ones
about here, right? So that var doesn't
distinguish between those two different
cases, right? And you might say, well,
this is ridiculous because nobody's
going to have a in real life that kind
of distribution can't possibly exist.
But that is not completely ridiculous uh
distribution. Um it's not totally
uncommon trading policy to have to sell
a whole bunch of out ofthe- money
options. And if you sell a bunch of out
of the money options, what most of the
time going to happen is you're going to
take a small profit from the sale of
those options. And most of the time they
will expire still out of the money. They
won't get exercised and you're going to
take a profit. But some of the time the
market will move enough and if it moves
enough they'll get exercised and you're
going to lose a lot of money on those
options. So that even though I did
contrive that for the purposes of this
lecture, right, that kind of
distribution is not as ridiculous as you
might think.
Okay, so that's the first problem. The
second kind of related problem um is
that value at risk is not uh sub
additive. Right? So this again a little
bit of a contrived example um to show
that um if you take say the 95% VAR uh I
take two two portfolios A and B with
those kind of uh probability of
happening right um A and B by themselves
that the VAR is zero right because
there's a 96% chance I'm going to lose
nothing right so 95% the VAR is going to
be zero um the expected shortfall of
those things is given I'm in that last
5% tail right um 1% % of the five I'm
going to lose nothing and 4% of the five
uh I'm going to lose 100 so I get to 80
right and if you do the maths and just
add the two things up um and you do the
a plus b you can discover that the var
of the combined portfolio is 100 and the
expected shortfall is 103 right um so
that is a kind of example that shows
that var is not subadditive expected
short obviously this is not proving that
expected shortfall is subadditive it is
in this case um it's quite hard to isish
to prove that expectant shortfall is
subadditive. It is and uh I put one of
the things at the end is is seven
different proofs that it is subadditive.
So you can pick pick your favorite one
from the the the thing at the end. Um I
also put an example at the end. So even
though this one is a very contrived
example, right? So in real life most
things are kind of normal or normallike,
right? And in that case, var is
subadditive. Right? So in real life
situations, this is not as much of a
problem as you might think. And there's
a paper at the end that talks a little
also a lot about that and says actually
lots of people criticize var because of
they come up with these kind of crazy
examples. But it's not too bad for our
purposes given we kind of want to go on
to optimizing stuff. It is critically
bad, right? Because subadd additivity is
we'll come back to this again in a sec
is basically the same thing as
convexity. So not being subadditive
means var is not really a convex
function in general and convex functions
are way way way easier to optimize than
non-convex functions. So even though
it's not a problem if you just want to
know var, it is a massive problem if you
want to optimize one of these things,
right? We'll come back to this uh again
uh in a little bit.
Um I just want to quickly point out that
there's lots and lots of other risk
measures you can possibly choose here.
Uh v and expected shortfall just happen
to be the two kind of common ones. um
you can kind of characterize uh a risk
measure by sort of how much weight uh it
puts on a particular percentile, right?
So VA is putting all of its weight on
the beta percentile. Expected shortfall
puts zero on everything less than beta
and averages out everything above beta,
right? But you could say, well, both of
those h you could you can make some
criticisms of them. You could say, well,
I should put a little bit of weight on
something that's a bit less than the
beta percentage and I should wait the
the the the really really extreme tail
losses. I should weight them more than
the than the just beyond the tail
losses. Right? So you can imagine having
these sort of exponential spectral risk
functions that have these kind of
functions which do exactly those things
that they put an awful lot of weight on
uh the the really bad losses at the 99
and 99.9% things and it sort of scales
off going down, right? Um it's just to
point out there's there's a there's a
few different choices you can make here.
Okay.
Um, so both VAR and expected shortfall,
they've basically got two parameters,
right? They've got the confidence level
and they've got the time horizon. Um, so
um we'll talk a bit about the uh the the
time horizon, right? So that means I
want to make sure that I'm going to lose
less than this amount of money over one
day, 5 days, 10 days, right? What that's
the time horizon. how how long have I
got to avoid losing this amount of
money, right? If you were to make the
assumption that um the change in the
portfolio, so this uh this delta p is a
normal distribution, right? Then var and
expected shortfall would have these two
uh these these two formats here, right?
So um they would also be normal. um or
uh and if you assume that uh people make
these kind of assumptions and I think
that the uh the the mean change right on
a daily basis is zero which is not a
crazy kind of uh uh assumption then both
VAR and expected shortfall would be
proportional to the standard deviation
right uh with these things they would be
normal and if you did that and you
assumed that all the daily changes were
independently uh they were all kind
independent identical normal
distributions. So you could add them all
up. Then you would discover that the
t-day var and the t-day expected
shortfall is proportional to the square
root uh of the one day var which is the
normal approximation that uh that people
make uh with those things. In reality it
seems that the uh the losses the changes
that you have on a typical portfolio or
typical market data are not independent.
Right? If you lose a lot of money one
day, there's a reasonable chance you
might lose some money on the the market
might go down on the second day. So
there's a thing called kind of
autocorrelation, which is basically the
correlation of a time series with itself
shifted by one day, right? And so you
can which is what this uh thing here.
And if you assume that that
autocorrelation
row is is some uh number then it would
modify uh the t-day var accord well for
two days by by this formula right which
I put in this in this table. So the top
row is assuming that there's no
autocorrelation, right? So that's one,
roo2, roo 5, root 10 and so on
is the top row. Um and then as you
increase the autocorrelation,
um the t-day var right as a function of
the one day var gets bigger and bigger,
right? So I did some I'll show you some
market data in a sec, right? So I took
one a set of observations from the euro
stocks uh stock index, right? And that
suggests that the row right the the
autocorrelation is about 0.1. I did some
other indices and they were all between
0.05 and one 0.15. Um so now that so 0.1
is kind of reasonable and generally um
people take a 10day VAR thing as a
normal thing. So you'd be looking at
about this um this number here right um
this uh 3.46. It's about that means to
say that the standard approximation of
using the square root of the of saying
the square root of the of of of the one
day var uh sorry the square root of of
of t times the one day var is probably
going to underestimate the actual t-day
var by about 10%. Right? Because the
3.46 divided by 3.16.
Okay. Um but nevertheless almost
everybody just says that the t-day var
is the one day var times root t. Uh
okay. Um so this is where I got the data
from. So uh I picked uh four four stock
indexes uh IBEX DAX and Euro stocks.
That's um if you don't know Spanish,
French, German and a pan European uh
stock stock index. Um so from 2006 to
2024 you can see there's a couple of
periods of uh stress in here. one in
sort of 2008 kind of time time frame
round about kind of here um which was
the global financial crash and one in
about 2020 which was uh COVID right and
some degree of calmness in in between
those in between those two periods right
clearly some correlation between these
uh um things um that's there on a
practical note there's a couple of
things worth pointing out I picked these
stock indic indices because they're all
European, which means I don't need to
worry about FX rates when I'm playing
with these things. Um, but because but
even though they're European, they're
from different countries. And the
different countries have different um
holidays. And so you have to decide what
I'm going to do, what you're going to do
when one of these indexes is is on
holiday and not and not and not trading.
Um, what I did here was said if all of
them were on holiday, I'm ignoring the
day completely. And if one of them was
not on holiday, but the rest were, I
just fill I just fill forward. And so
you'd see a daily change of zero on
those. The might not necessarily be the
most sensible thing to do. Doesn't
really make that much difference. But
the reason I mention it is because if
you work in this kind of uh industry and
stuff like that, you end up spending a
surprising and disproportionate amount
of time dealing with both FX and holiday
calendars, right? You probably don't
expect to be doing this, but holiday
calendars spend you spend a lot of your
time trying to work out what are you
going to do with these kind of things.
Okay.
Um
so there's a couple of different ways
you can estimate VAR. Um one is
historical simulation and uh one is um
doing a model building. We'll have a
quick look at both of them. Um so the
historical simulation basically we're
going to go back and look at these look
at the time series. We'll look at the
we'll look at the value of each of these
indices the CAC DAX and Euro stocks on
each day right um and we'll come up with
a portfolio. So I just made up some
portfolio say I'm going to have 3,000
units of of CAC 4,000 of DAX and so on
and so on. Um and we'll call that the
portfolio weight. And so now um I can I
can figure out that on the day the the
change in value on on day I right is
going to be the relative change in the
underlying market index right so it's
for example the second row minus the
first row for the first day and so on
multiply by the weight for that that uh
that index then just sum it up over all
the indices right and that will give me
um the change on the i day okay
um
And so then I can take the distribution
of those things and I will get something
that looks like that. Hopefully that's
big enough. Um so one thing to add here
is that when you're doing that when
you're looking at these um uh historical
simulations, you have to decide over
what period over what historical period
am I going to look at. Right? And the
main thing to notice here is that
depending on what historical period you
look at, it makes a massive difference
to both the VAR and the expected
shortfall. Um, so what normally happens
if you normally talk about VAR, you talk
about the most recent say two years. The
these are all two-year periods by the
way, right? So the top left 2022 to the
end of 2023. Given my series went up to
the end of 2023, this would what this
this top left box would be what you
would normally put in as as var, right?
The most recent 500 days, basically
assuming there's 250 days in a year,
which is more or less true. Um, the ones
on the right, they're from the two kind
of stress periods, right? The global
financial crisis and uh COVID. And as
you might imagine, if you compute VAR
based his if you compute VAR based off
those two periods, you get a much much
bigger number than you do of either of
the kind of calm periods, the kind of
most recent one 2022 or a period in
between the global financial crisis and
COVID 2015 to 2016
uh with with that right. So that makes
by far and away the biggest difference
which which period you choose. Um and
because of that um regulators have
recently introduced the well not that
recently introduced the concept of a
thing called stress var. So in addition
to taking the most recent two years,
five years, 10 years, whatever you
decide to choose, you also pick a fixed
period known to be stressful, right? So
people will pick either COVID or they
will pick uh the global financial
crisis, right? And then that's generally
known as SVAR or or or stressed far,
right? Because there's such a big
variation in these in these in these
terms uh that are that are that are
there, right? And then just to kind of
break it down in terms of what you
actually did here, what what I actually
did was I took all those changes, right?
So there was 500 changes in each period
more or less. Um I ordered them from the
biggest change to the to from the
biggest loss to the biggest gain. Um
these things here and then the fifth
worst one, that's the VAR for the for
the for the 99% VAR. Uh because that's
that's 1%. And the 12th worst one,
that's the 97.5. So there's there's not
it's not that complicated. you just
ordered the thing. You take the fifth
worst one, 12th worst one. That's what
virus and expected shortfall. Um for the
99% you take the average of the of the
worst four, right? Um and for the 97.5
you take the average of the uh worst 11.
Um there is some debate about that,
right? Some people claim you should take
the average of the worst five including
the 320 uh and the average of the worst
12. Um I think standard market
convention is to take the four. doesn't
matter that much, right? But that that's
all that's actually happening here,
right? Uh to to to do these.
Okay.
All okay. So far,
um to do the model building approach, um
it's kind of similar, right? We just
make the assumptions that everything is
uh normally distributed. Um the daily
changes are normally distributed with
mean zero uh and a sigma i. um we assume
that there's some kind of correlation
between all the different indices and so
you say well the sigma for the portfolio
is going to be um uh this this this term
here right um so there's a variance
coariance matrix uh between the right
that you that you get um and using the
assumption that var and expected
shortfall are uh proportional to the
sigma again you get these two you get
these two expressions so all you need to
do for the model building approach is
figure out what the uh variance
covariance matrix is between these
different uh elements which I computed
here and I come up with a var and I get
these two numbers 225 and uh 257 um the
main thing to note about that is that
it's significantly significantly less um
than the historical VAR right so the 99
that's this is computed for the 2022
2023 period right so Um the historical
VAR was those equivalent numbers were
320 and 377, right? Um basically showing
that these normal distributions, right?
It's clearly not a normal distribution.
There's a fatter tail in there than
you'd expect. Um but you can say well
you can work out is this an acceptable
VAR model, yes or no. Right? So what you
can say is
given I've got something where I'm going
to take 500 trials and I expect to see
an I expect the VAR the the actual loss
to have exceeded the VAR 1% of the time.
That's the definition of VAR, right? And
uh what is the probability that I'm
going to see 12 or more? Uh so this
there there's 12 violations by the way.
So if I take this um 225 right and say
how many times did it actually according
to that period how many times was it
actually the loss was bigger than 225 or
there were 12 scenarios bigger than 225.
So what is the probability that I would
see 12 or more days out of a sample of
500 that exceeded um the um that
exceeded the VA right so that's comes
from the binomial uh distribution which
is that formula and you get 5.2%.
And the general rule of thumb is that if
the probability is 5% or more of getting
that degree of that number of uh of of
violations of the VAR, you say that the
model's okay. And if the if there's the
probability is less than 5%, you'd
probably reject the model and say the VA
is it's not a it's not a good model. So
even though the VAR here is
significantly lower than uh the
historical simulation,
um you would probably accept that as as
an okay kind kind of kind of model. Um
and the only other point I wanted to
make on that is that what we've
basically done there is a back testing
of VAR, right? So we basically came up
came up with a model and we said how
good is that model, right? how many
times uh based off some historical
simulation was the VAR uh um exceeded
right so it's really really easy to do
back testing in VAR the main single main
reason why people still use VAR over
expected shortfall is because doing this
for expected shortfall is quite tricky
right it's not even clear what it means
to do back testing of expected shortfall
because
I your the expected shortfall is is a
function of the probability
distribution. It's the mean of the tail.
You can't really compare that with one
sample that I've drawn from the
distribution, right? It's like comparing
apples with oranges. Um there's a whole
bunch of debate around whether um back
testing expected shortfall is flatout
impossible, difficult um or or not. And
there's a bunch of papers at the end
kind of uh on on on this as as as well.
But it's definitely a lot trickier than
doing it for var. Um and that is the
main reason people still use VAR despite
its shortcomings around the
subadditivity and the handling of the
tails.
Okay. So I'm just going to skip over
some stuff. Uh this is some stuff around
regulation.
Um and I quickly mentioned this slide um
because I um so one of the problems with
uh expected shortfall is it's kind of
defined in terms of uh VAR, right?
Because it's the prop it's the mean loss
that you would get given you've exceeded
VAR uh in the first place. What you can
do this is a this function here. This is
in the paper by Rockefeller and Ria Sev
which is in the the back says if you
take this function f which is this
expression here right and you try and
then you minimize that over alpha
consider this to be a function of x
which is the portfolio and alpha uh is
just a number right and you minimize
this over alpha then the minimal value
of that function is the expected
shortfall and so you can find the
expected shortfall
by taking that f and minimizing it,
right? And that is basically if you
replace the integral with a with a sum,
that's basically a linear problem,
right? And so it's relatively easy to
find the expected shortfall. Um,
moreover, if you minimize it with
respect to alpha and x, now what you've
done is you found the portfolio with the
minimal expected shortfall, right? I.e.
you have minimized the expected
shortfall which is basically what we're
trying to do in this whole uh in this
whole thing. So you just have to
consider this function here. You can
minimize that over x and alpha right
which is basically a linear problem and
um that essentially is how you minimize
expected shortfall. Um no such
equivalent thing exists for for value at
risk. Right? So even though expected
shortfall is trickier to um is trickier
to uh uh uh back test, it's easier to uh
minimize, which is what I care about
more.
Okay. Um
skip over it. So that's expected
shortfall and VAR, right? So now we're
going to start talking about
counterparty risk and and margin, right?
So if you have um in the derivative uh
world right so if I have A has got two
trades one with B one with C right
derivatives typically swaps means I'm
going to exchange a series of cash flows
between the two between between between
between the two parties right and
typically those cash flows will be
exchanged say over a three-month period
or six month six-month period so um A in
this case is receiving some cash flows
it's paying the series SI to be and
receiving TRI from uh from B. A is
exposed to the fact that before the next
cash flow arrives from B, B might
default and not pay the cash flow,
right? And the same story for for C. So
A has counterparty risk to both B and C
because when we get to the next cash
flow date, say 3 months time or six
months time or a year's time, they might
not pay that cash flow that they're due.
Right? So that's the fundamental reason
why they have counterparty risk for for
derivatives in order to mitigate against
the fact that they might not pay uh that
cash flow. What actually happens is that
they pay is that both all these
counterparties exchange on a daily basis
the exchange variation margin right um
which uh means that which is equal to
the value of these derivatives. Right?
So as the value goes up and down of
these things, they'll be paying
variation margin to one to one to one
another, right? And that mitigates
against the cost of the cash flow not
getting paid. But if they're paying
variation margin from one to another and
then one party or other goes goes uh uh
goes bust and defaults, then you still
got to pay the variation margin to the
other person. And as soon as one party
goes bust, what A would try and do, so
if C goes bust here, A would try and
replace that trade. It would take it
some number of days to replace that
trade. uh with something else or unwind
that trade, right? During which time the
value of that trade might go up and
because the value of that trade is going
up, it's having to pay an increased
amount of variation margin to to B,
right? And so therefore, it incurs a
loss, right? And so it incurs a loss
because during the period between when C
defaults and when it manages to replace
that trade, the value of the trade will
change or go go up basically.
and that that is the loss. So in order
in order to mitigate against that risk,
right, A will collect initial margin,
right? That's what initial margin is.
That's the essentially a covering you
for the risk um in between when a party
defaults and when you've managed to uh
unwind or replace that position. Okay,
that slide just says what I just said.
Okay. And then I have another slide
which says the same thing again in a
picture. Right. Um so you have the
variation margin is getting paid up
until uh here between all these things.
Uh you get some default will happen
here. We don't know what's going to
happen. The risk can go up or down. Um
and there's some uh loss could
potentially be incurred right at this
point. This should hopefully sound to
you a little bit like what we just
discussed right with VAR an expected
shortfall. And so initial margin in
order how much initial margin should I
should I should I collect? Well,
basically it's going to be a VAR based
on how long you think it's going to take
you to unwind that position which is
called the margin period of risk, right?
Um
there's two kinds of initial margin
depending on whether your trade is a
cleared trade uh or a bilateral trade.
Um the cleared margin
is set up by the clearing house, the
CCP. Um and that's always been the case
for years and years and years. Um up
until 2016, people were not paying uh
initial margin on bilateral trades. Um
that changed when ISDA came up with
their standard initial margin. Um which
is um the form I've put the formula down
here, but it's kind of similar. It's
basically VAR, right, is what they put
here. Um, and the only difference
compared to what we just discussed, um,
is that because it's handling nonlinear
portfolios, there's a gamma term, uh, in
there, which I didn't talk about, uh,
before. Um, and when you work it all the
way through, you make exactly the same
assumptions that everything is normal.
Uh, mean is mean is zero. Um, you end up
with the exact same term we talked we
saw before, right? And you also sim
assumes that it's a 10day margin period
of risk, right? and it's a 99%
confidence interval. So the 99% conf
confidence interval uh is that's the
inverse normal of of 99%. That's the uh
10day uh um margin period of risk.
That's the exact same term we looked at
in the VAR before. And then you get two
additional terms that come from the
convexity, right? Which is kind kind of
similar. The main point is that initial
margin is basically some variant of VA
or potentially expected shortfall. Okay.
Um
in real life um there's lots and lots
more simplifying assumptions um that uh
people
um make around all these things to try
and uh simplify stuff um and all these
kind of correlations between all the
different uh parameters. This covers the
entire world, all all different asset
classes. Uhuh.
And so they get kind of recalibrated on
a yearly basis. Um, if you Google um,
SIM COVID uh, now, you'll probably see
quite a lot of stuff uh, in there
because SIM 2.7 is about to come out in
the beginning of December. And that'll
be the first one that's calibrated
without any of the COVID or global
financial uh, crisis data in there. And
what's going to happen, what people
expect to happen is that the initial
margin calculated by this sim is going
to massively reduce by somewhere in the
region of kind of five to 20%. Um, and
what that will do is release something
in the region of kind of $40 billion of
margin back out into the wild because
today people are paying initial margin
or these different things with these
high levels of uh using these high
levels of VA. When they recalibrate in
the first week of December, everything
will come down. Everybody will release
all the initial margin. Um so there's
quite a lot of stuff around that kind of
in the news at the moment. Uh um that
just talks about how to structure you
you um roll everything up into one
number across all the different port
portfolios.
Um and skip over that. So that's what
margin is right. So now we come on to
trying to optimize
the the initial margin. I put margin
here. I I mean initial margin, right? So
the the situation that we're thinking
about is we've got multiple different
financial participants ABCDE. Think of
them as banks, right? And we've got I've
put one CCP, right? There could in fact
be multiple CCPs in the middle, right?
And all these participants have got a
bunch of bilateral trades versus each
other and they've got um a bunch of
trades versus the CCP. That's the
situation that that that we've got,
right? and they're all posting margin to
to each other, right? In this situation,
okay? And what we are trying to do by
optimizing stuff is come up with a bunch
of hedge trades, right, which is these
XH variables between all the different
participants in order to try and
minimize the margin, i.e. the VAR, in
the entire system, right? That's the
goal of what we're trying to uh get to.
Okay? And you might say, well, why are
there no trades versus the CCP? Were you
ignoring the uh cleared margin? Um,
that's just a practical issue. We can't
book, you can't book trades between the
CCP uh and um and a bank. All you can do
is book bilateral trades between A and
B, A, A, and E, all these different
things. And depending on which trades
you choose, some of them will be cleared
or not cleared. If you ch if you pick a
trade where the trade type is like an an
interest rate swap, then that'll be
mandated to clear. And so even though
it's between A and B, it'll get cleared
and it will affect the cleared margin
and not the bilateral margin. Okay,
that's why there's no actual trades
booked between the CCP and any of these
people. Okay, so that's what we're
trying to do.
So
that's the problem we're trying to
solve, right? which looks like a lot of
maths um but in fact is not that
complicated right so what we're trying
to do is we're trying to minimize summed
over all of the parties right so all of
the banks ABCDE E right the margin of
all those people so the margin is made
up of the sim the bilateral margin
summed over all the all the
counterparties right plus the cleared
margin summed over all the CCPs that are
there so that just says the sum of all
the margin margin in the system is what
I'm trying to minimize right and we say
well where sim and the initial margin
there's some functions of risk as we've
just discussed right we know what the
function is it's var like let's say
right so we know that sim and uh whoop
sorry initial margin are some functions
of the risk and we know that the risk
position that's there is equal to the
initial risk which is this the zero plus
the sum over all the hedges that we're
going to book. So, we're going to
propose a bunch of bunch of trades. So,
we sum over all the hedges that we're
going to book, the size of the hedge,
right, which is the x, which is the
thing we're trying to find, multiplied
by the risk of that particular hedge,
right? So, that's that's how we know
what the new risk is, right? And we've
got a couple of constraints that we need
to put in the system, right? This is the
most important one, right? This is this
is what we call the symmetry constraint
even though it looks like an looks like
an asymmetry constraint. What this says
is that if JP if if if P sells something
to Q, Q had better buy that same thing
from P. Right. Exactly. And this was
when we first set this up, this was in
reality the thing that people were most
worried that we would mess up. Right.
Because the biggest problem that could
have happened here is that we told we we
set up a thing. We tell uh Goldman
Sachs, go and buy a h 100red million of
stuff from JP Morgan. And then we tell
JP Morgan, go and sell 200 million of
stuff, right, to Goldman Sachs. So
Goldman Sachs sees their thing, says buy
100 million. They think that looks good
to us. We'll we'll agree to this, right?
JP Morgan sees their thing, which sells
says sell 200 million of stuff to
Goldman Sachs and JP Morgan goes that
looks good. We we'll we'll agree to
this. Goldman Sachs doesn't see what we
told JP Morgan and JP Morgan doesn't see
what we told go Goldman Sachs and they
only discover that something's gone
horrifically wrong when they try and do
that trade, right? Um so the reason that
doesn't happen is because we've got this
constraint in the system, right? That
says that whatever I whatever Goldman
Sachs buys from JP Morgan, JP Morgan
better sell that exact same thing to
Goldman Sachs, right? That is the most
important constraint in the whole
system. Right? The second constraint,
the big one that we've got in there is
this one, right? Which says this is cash
flow flatness, right? This says that for
any party, let's say Goldman Sachs, if I
sell something, if I if I sell something
to one party, I'd better buy that exact
same thing from every from some
combination of other people, right?
That's what that constraint says. We
don't need that to be in the system.
It's a kind of safety valve uh that's in
there, right? The advantage of having
this in here is it says if I'm
definitely sure that everything is cash
flow flat across the system, nobody's
going to make any money or lose any
money out of the out of the whole system
because I'm going to sell something. I'm
going to going to sell something to
there. I'm going to buy it from
somewhere else. So, I'm just all I'm
doing is shuffling risk around the
system. Right? You could relax that and
you could say, well, some parties could
make some money, some could lose some
money, some could change some risk, but
it makes everything a lot trickier,
right? So, we basically enforce this
around around the system. And then the
last constraint is a risk constraint
which comes from the uh parties
themselves,
right? And what this says is that
Goldman Sachs or some party might say,
well, I don't really want to go uh I
might not want to go long a particular
risk factor versus some particular
counterparty for whatever reason, right?
Um so the first two are sort of
systemwide kind of constraints that we
kind of impose on the thing and the last
one is a constraint which basically says
don't change the risk too much, right?
Which is what parties say, right? So all
of that all of that math that's all it's
saying. Okay. Um so if we look at it's
kind of if we look at a very very simple
example if we take a three-party system
right uh ABC this might be a bit small
uh and you put it in there and say well
how could I minimize the margin around
that system right and the way you
minimize if you've got AC's got to trade
with 10 AB's got a trade with two and
BC's got to trade with nine. Well, what
you do is you move the median trade
around the whole triangle, right? If you
move one median trade around, one trade
around the whole triangle, right? I'm
guaranteed to satisfy like by
construction those first two
constraints, right? Uh because I'm only
moving the exact same thing around the
whole system. And if uh I'm moving just
say in this case nine, I'm going to A's
going to buy nine, sell nine. B is going
to buy nine, sell nine. C is going to
buy nine, sell nine. So I'm going to
satisfy the second constraint as well.
Right? I've ignored the third constraint
for now. Um and the reason I picked that
is u those particular examples with 29
and 10 is that actually if you fiddle
around with the maths a bit the thing
you should move is the median trade
given any triangle and you can take any
network and you can always break a
network into a bunch of triangles,
right? And for every triangle you just
move the median around, right? That's
what you should do, right? The problems
are this won't satisfy all the different
con if you have additional constraints
causes problems and obviously um some
edges of this triangle would also be
edges of other triangles and so you end
up but you can it won't generally solve
the problem right but it's a good way of
thinking about it we always think about
triangles and how you would move risk
around uh in a particular triangle
okay
so it's that um
In reality, we just use a big numerical
solver around this. So, what we're in
the business here is we're solving uh um
minimization problems. So, operational
research type type problems. They're of
the form minimize uh f subject to uh
some other stuff. And um as I mentioned
earlier, solving convex problems is way
way way easier than solving general
nonlinear problems. And convexity is
basically the same thing as
subadditivity, right? That's the
definition of convexity, right? And that
should remind you of the definition we
saw earlier of subadditivity, right? So
we saw earlier minimizing expected
shortfall. That's basically a peace-wise
linear problem. All these things we're
talking about sim is nearly convex,
right? There are different add-ons that
you can have which are usually convex.
And some of the math that we get into is
that how do you come up with approx
approximations of these things which
genuinely are convex. Right? We tried
using non like proper nonlinear solvers
on these things. way easier just to
approximate the function you want and
use a convex solver on it because the
state of the technology for solving
convex optimization problems is really
really really good, right? Uh it would
be crazy to write your own version of a
convex optimization solver because there
are loads of open source and commercial
availables things available. Uh so don't
do it. Just plug it into a system uh and
it works. The thing to note is that that
how difficult it is to solve the problem
is really really really sensitive on the
specifics of the problem, right? And
that doesn't really mean the size of the
problem. The size is not really too much
of a an issue. It's it's all kinds of
the structure of the problem. How sparse
is the problem in the thing? These are
the things that matter uh in the real
world. Okay. Um also it's a good idea to
use modeling languages, right? So um
there are lots of modeling languages
available. Gro is the one uh we use. I
think you may people might have used it.
I think you can get it free if you're
academic uh in institution. Um in case
anybody wants to spend 10 seconds trying
to solve that uh in their head. Uh so
this is in integer problem. Uh trying to
minimize 5x1 plus 8x2 subject to those
two constraints. Uh you can probably do
do that in your head. Uh
hang on.
Do that. Sorry.
Um,
so we did it on Groi using 24 physical
cores probably is overkill for that
problem, but it uh comes up in uh 10
milliseconds with the answer of 31,
which is hopefully if you did it, that's
what you tried. Uh, just to show how
easy it is to solve some of these uh
problems. In real life, a typical
problem that we would have uh might have
sort of 25 different parties in the
network might be say for FX delta 30 odd
different currencies, right? Uh that
we've got in there. Um we pick different
kinds of hedge instruments. So we try
and pick simple ones. The reason for
picking things like non-deliverable FX
forwards is that each individual hedge
type there has exposure to exactly one
underlying namely the currency. If I
pick a dollar euro uh non-deliverable
that's got exposure to the dollar euro
FX rate and nothing but the dollar euro
fx rates rate in this case right which
turns out to be useful um and if you do
that you end up with a system which is
something like say 20,000 variables
40,000 constraints something like that
is the real size of the is the real size
of the problem right
and really when you're solving convex
optimization problems solving convex
optimization problems is easy because
they A convex problem looks like a bowl,
right? And so they have one minimum. And
so you can convert the optimization
problem into a a root finding problem.
Just find where the root of the
derivative is so where where the
derivative is equal to zero. Right? Um
so that's root finding. People generally
use something like Newton Rafson for for
root finding. Uh when you use uh Newton
Rafson, you've got to compute a Hessen
matrix, right? And then you need to
invert that hessen matrix. That's the
slow part of the entire system is that
you're repeatedly
inverting hessen matrices, right? So the
matrix might be 40,000ish, right? Um
matrix inversion is basically an ncubed
kind of operation. So you end up with
this unfeasibly large number of uh
operations to to solve. In general, most
computers will not be able to factoriize
a 40,000 uh matrix for a randomly chosen
40,000 uh by 40,000 matrix. Right?
However, the problems that we have here
are very much not randomly chosen uh
matrices. They have an awful lot of
structure involved and they're massively
massively sparse, right? and any most
solvers the reason why they're very
mature is they take advantage of all
this matrix structure uh that's there
and so they can do way way way better
than you'd expect from this so in
particular for fx delta right the matrix
looks a little bit like this right so
you got a bit of stuff kind of at the
top of the matrix which is the thing I
talked around around the symmetry
constraints and the flatness constraints
right but the vast vast majority of the
constraints are those ones at the bottom
of that picture which are the the risk
constraints specified by the individual
parties
and they are guaranteed to be uh block
diagonal right because each if I have a
particular hedge say the hedge a b right
that's only going to affect the risk
between party A and party B right at
worst case and then the hedge the hedges
between A and C they're only going to
affect the risk between parties A and C
right so I'm definitely going to get a
block diagonal matrix down down here and
everything else is going to be zero. So
the vast majority is going to be zero.
And if I pick these NDF trades as well,
right, and those NDF trades only have
exposure to one risk factor themselves,
I'm just going to get a straight
diagonal matrix here, right? And
obviously inverting a straight diagonal
matrix is trivially easy, right? So I've
got a bit at the top, which makes it a
bit more complicated, but it's a little
bit at the top plus basically a massive
big diagonal matrix, right? That's
called a dancing wolf uh structure and
it's it's there are techniques known to
factoriize and invert those kind of
things. Okay.
So then I like this slide. I think this
is one slide I've used all three years.
Uh the problems that you get into in
real life are not solving the uh kind of
uh um the big minimization problem. You
just literally write down the math that
you want. more or less plug that into
the uh the the the solver, right? But in
real life, you get situations where
you've got nearly parallel risks. You
have two trades which are nearly the
same, right? Um but not quite exactly
the same or can't be represented exactly
the same on a on a computer. So this
example here, right? If I really wanted
to solve this this first equation here,
right? Obviously, everyone hopefully you
can see that there's essentially there's
there's lots of solutions to that,
right? Uh w with this, but you can't
represent a third properly on a
computer, right? So if you actually
tried to represent that on a computer,
what you might end up with, for example,
instead of putting a third uh a third x1
plus a third y1 as your second equation,
you might end up with this thing here
333 uh x1, sorry 333 x1 plus 333 y1,
right? And that has this solution 01,
but you make a tiny tiny change to that
thing, right? So all I did was I flipped
over uh the um solution here instead of
having three threes at the end having
four threes at the end. And instead of
getting a solution 01, I've now got a
solution one zero. Right? And if I make
another small change uh to those things,
it says instead of I'm going to get 3,
right? Then that has a single solution
of minus 110 111. Right? That's that's
that's that's the solution to that that
problem. Now it's highly plausible. I
might also say well I want all these x's
to be positive right that might be a
thing in there and so entirely due to
numerical noise it will say if I want x
to be positive but the only solution to
this problem is minus 110 111 um any
systems going to go well that's
infeasible and so refuse to solve it and
so the problems that we get into real
life is trying to understand these
things and coming up with techniques to
remove these kind of situations from the
from from from the system right um
rather rather than trying to actually
solve uh sort of convex optimization
problems in in their general form. Um
so there um this is the same thing as
before except now for the FX delta the
full kind of FX delta problem we're up
to 48 cores now. Um and you can see here
it really was 114,000
100,000 by 100,000 matrix right is what
we ended up trying to solve. Um it's
worth noting this um kind of presolve
thing here removed close to half of it.
Right? What presolve is is sometimes you
get all these different constraints and
you have them in there and you end up
with a constraint that says X1 is
greater than one and another one that
says X1 is greater than two, right? So
you might as well chuck out the first
constraint and say well if X1 is greater
than one and it's greater than two,
chuck out the first one and just keep
the X1 is greater than two uh
constraint. And that happens a lot and
so you can massively reduce the size. Um
and we get down to a thing like this. Uh
but you can see even this this problem
we can solve it in um uh 11 seconds
right and with very very few iterations
which is basically a testament to the
the amazing power of Newton Rafson
quadratic convergence.
Um so what happens when you try and
solve it? Um
this is kind of how you have the initial
risk and this is with the optimized risk
on the right hand side as you might
expect it tries to form it tries to
basically get it that I don't have some
positive numbers and some negative
numbers it tries to nest all the risk
together right uh what you can kind of
see uh here um
you try this on a 20 uh party system
again just removing all the constraints
again it can remove almost all the
margin between the different systems and
you end up with either if for any given
row either pink stuff or green stuff.
It's either positive or negative. But
you don't have pink and green stuff in
the same row or in the same column.
Right? What that says is it managed to
get rid of all the situations where I
was up I was up here and down there. I
just want to be up or down. Right? So
I've netted all the risk together.
That's what the system was basically
trying trying to trying trying to do.
Okay. Um you try it on a real system
with all the constraints and stuff like
that. it's less convincing what it was
uh trying trying trying trying to do
because the constraints hold this stuff
um in in check here right with there um
just out of interest this this kind of
diagonal line down the front that's
essentially the margin versus itself
right so you obviously cannot pay a
margin to yourself which is why you get
uh a kind of blank sort of line down the
diagonal and the square stuff in the
middle I originally thought that was
kind of some bug Um but what that is is
trading between inter affiliates of the
same of the same entity right so
somebody like JP Morgan or Bank of
America will have lots of entities some
of which don't pay margin to to each
other what I probably did here was I
ordered all the entities out
alphabetically right so this is probably
I'm guessing given I did that that's
probably all the inter affiliates of JP
Morgan is the one in the middle since
that's uh or maybe it's Morgan Stanley
it'll be some some company which has got
a letter roughly in the middle of the
alphabet with many entities not trading
margin versus each other.
Uh that
um it's another example doing interest
rate stuff.
So what we've discussed so far is
solving the optimization problems. It
has to be feasible which means it
satisfies all the constraints and it has
to be optimal right which means it finds
a good margin saving right um but on top
of that it's interesting to try and make
them nice right and try and make them
fair. So what a nice uh thing would be
is that you don't really want to have
horrible looking notionals. You don't
want to have to have a trade with some
like complicated notional in there.
you'd like to just have trade a 100
million of this or 200 million of that,
right? The biggest amount of headache we
got into ever was trading with these NDF
uh FX trades where we would trade it
with a dollar notional with some like
200,000 million.74
and then something else with the euros
uh like 0.53 in the euros and then we
compute the FX rate which would be the
the the uh one divided by the other and
the FX rate would come out to be a like
15 decimal point number and everything
would be fine and then we give it to the
uh the banks and they would complain and
they would say well our system only
handles six decimal places or eight
decimal places in the trading system and
when I do that and I put six decimal
places in the FX rate it changes my
euron notional right it gets a little
bit off and so we ended up having to put
notionals in that were round numbers of
dollars and they came out as exact round
numbers of euros using a four decimal
base FX rate or a six decimal point uh
FX rate and that turns out to be quite
tricky because you need to round all
these numbers right and you can't just
take a solution right and just round it
to the nearest 10 right so if I take if
I have a party let's say I've got a and
I'm I'm selling uh I'm selling eight
units of something to one person and
I've offset that by buying four units
from a second person and four units from
a third person everything is flat. But
if I round everything to the nearest 10,
right, then I've rounded the eight to
10, right? And I round the both fours
down to zero. So now I'm no longer flat.
So you can't do this rounding as a
post-processing step afterwards because
it breaks the flatness uh in the in in
the whole system. So you have to do it
as part of the optimization. If you do
it as part of the optimization, that
makes it into a mixed integer problem
and that um makes it considerably
considerably harder, right? Um we also
people also want by nice they want like
a small number of trades. They don't
want to have to trade thousands and
thousands of trades in order to get some
of this uh margin saving. They like to
have a small number of trades. We talk
about it as notional efficiency. Um and
there are other advantages of CCP as I
mentioned earlier
um in addition to just the netting. And
so there's some advantage of saying,
well, I want to put I I'd like to put
more trades into the CCP, right? Um, and
so you might do some that might be a
nice thing to have, right? For other
reasons not directly related to initial
margin. So you can add all these
niceness features into the system. The
problem with adding the nicest things
like round numbers, small numbers like
trade counts, these these kind of
things, they all make the basically
continuous problem into a mixed integer
problem which is which is hard to uh
which is hard to solve. Um and
so skip and then fairness
um is well the first question is what
does it mean? What does what does
fairness mean uh in a optimization
problem? So you have this example
hopefully you can see this is a four
back to the triangle system right four
party system okay every it's kind of
symmetric between A and D there are four
there are three possible things you can
do all of which have the same kind of
overall saving here right essentially
you can ignore D right and solve the ABC
problem in which case D gets no saving
right you could ignore you could ignore
A right and get the and get the same
saving right or you could kind of split
the saving between uh A and D right so
they're the three different scenarios
that you can get right so I put them
down in the table at the bottom so
scenario one is the ignoring D this is
the saving that you get A gets a saving
of four ABC all get a saving of four
right D gets nothing right
um so this is where this is you can
argue that's not fair Right? Because D
gets gets uh gets nothing there. Right?
You can argue scenario two is not fair
because A gets nothing. Right? You can
argue that of these scenarios
um scenario three is the fairest, right?
Just intuitively, right? It still might
not be the fairest because well, why did
A get two and B D get two? But B and C
got their full four allocation, right?
So the concept of fairness is not a
well- definfined uh one. One thing you
can look at, right,
um, is Whoops. Have a two-step system,
right? So, you first of all figure out
what is the best possible saving that
any one party can get, right? So, the
best possible saving that all these
people can get is always four, right?
And so you do a whole bunch of
optimizations where you ignore everybody
else and just try and optimize for A,
then just optimize for B, then optimize
for C, then optimize for D. Now I get
the best possible thing that each one
can be subject to all of the constraints
still being there. Right? When I know
that, now I'm going to say what I'm
actually going to solve is how do I
minimize the square of the difference
from my actual solution to those things.
Right? Right. So I've got a le squares
problem that's uh that's uh in there
which is this this problem here and
that's the things and I'm going to do
one more optimization at the end when I
solve that problem right and I'm going
to say that's the answer that I've that
I've got and you can see if I did that
in this case clearly
um with the squared scenario three is
going to definitely come out as being
the best uh solution is b and c will be
zero in those things um and then uh for
scenario three I'll get uh uh four plus
four right whereas in scenario one and
scenario two I will get uh a 16 right
from the from the square right so if I
were to do that on this case right it
would this would this would be an
algorithm that would deterministically
give me scenario three as as the fairest
um but there are other ways of of
defining fairness um and I don't think
it's a wellestablished kind of uh uh
thing yet I think it's the single most
interesting problem uh that we've got
kind of in the optimization uh uh kind
of kind of space. Um and then I skip
over these are just some pictures of
what we've kind of really got as terms
of uh saving. The more interesting one
is really this right which is showing
the kind of network effect right so you
can kind of expect obviously that as I
put more and more uh uh banks or parties
into the system right the saving should
go up right that's kind of a reasonable
thing but more than that um the saving
divided by the initial that also goes up
right so you get um not just the total
saving in the system goes up but the
total the the the the
efficiency increases the more people you
add into the the system. I wouldn't put
too much faith into whether it's really
linear or whether it's a kind of not
linear uh uh thing in there. But the the
there was clearly a drift upwards right
in these things which basically says
that if you want to do this the most
effective thing you can do is get big
networks of people and big networks of
people are beneficial to everybody uh in
in the system. That's basically the
story uh of that of that picture. Uh
that's there. I think that is the end.
Yeah. So that's just a quick summary. We
talked about value at risk and expected
shortfall. Talked about the diff uh
centrally cleared and bilateral.
We talked about counterparty risk. What
variation margin is initial margin. What
we're really trying to do is optimize
this initial margin. Uh that basically
comes down to doing constrained convex
optimization. The difficulty in
constrained optimization is really all
the numerical issues uh that you've got.
Um and actually the interesting problems
are not it's too much solving the
feasibility and optimality bit but how
do you add the niceness and the fairness
on top on top of that.
Hopefully that is the end of your
slides.
There you go. Thank you very much.
[Applause]
that make sense to anybody or
anyone have any questions?
>> Go ahead.
>> Yeah, a question about the sim that you
mentioned that like
>> it's going to like the new that's coming
out in you said.
>> Yeah.
>> Is going to be the first one where it's
not using um data from like
like a stressful time for example.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Uh I was wondering like what goes into
like that data cut off and then what
implications do you think that will have
for like just overall behavior
or just affecting the economy?
So I don't think it will necessar well
the effect on the economy is going to be
well potentially there's going to be a
lot of margin released back into the
system right so essentially margin is
money that cannot be used for trading
right it's essentially locked away in in
in in sort of segregated accounts so the
release of all that margin into the
system means there's more margin
available for trading right that's
that's kind of the effect that it would
have on the on the system um in terms of
the kind of choice of parameters right I
think effectively must show that really
it's a sort roughly a two-year look
back, right? Similar to what I was doing
in the kind of toy examples that I had
earlier, right? So, this this is this is
even though it's looking at other
different things, the stress kind of
ended roughly 2021 22ish, something like
that. So, basically, it's going to be
looking at a at a at a region that's say
from 2021 or 2022 beyond, right? And
that's the reason that all these big
shocks that happened in 2020, they're
too far in the past uh to be to be
counted in the correlation uh these
days. Now, of course, there might be
some more. This the exact same thing was
about to happen in in 2018 2019 just
before that happened and they would also
uh been about to say, well, let's just
smooth it smooth it all out. And then
what did happen was then all these
shocks came in and people decided that
what SIM was doing was massively
underestimating the the VAR and the fact
that they were only reccalibrating on a
yearly basis was kind of problematic,
right? Because they had to wait a whole
year and in fact a year and a bit
because of the timing they had in
December and the way they come out
before they could start including these
shocks that were um that happened in in
in in 2020. So actually as a result of
that they moved from a annual
recalibration process to a semi-reanual
process so that they could bring uh
these um these the effect of these
shocks in more quickly.
>> Is they the regulators
>> is the so it's the international uh swap
uh derivatives association. So there's a
panel they chair it is it's it's model
they're the ones who ultimately put put
that thing there. But there's a lot of
collaboration with various banks and
other other sort of uh parties and
interested parties.
>> Yeah.
[Music]
>> It's a different beta.
>> Uh yeah. So that's a beta in terms of
well this beta here is just a confidence
uh interval right so that's just saying
it's the beta is the I'm 99% confident I
won't lose more than this
>> yeah do you mind going back to the slide
you talk about
back testing or I guess the limitations
on back testing expected shortfall
>> uh yeah
>> hang on
that Yeah, I guess it was
um
I I guess in my
what are some ways that you can like
almost cut corners like make some
assumptions that allow you to calculate
um expected shortfall? What do you have
to assume for it to be possible? to be
possible to back test. Uh
>> well, you kind of have to make some
assumptions around the form of the tail,
right? So, if you were to say, well, the
tail is is is kind of flat, right? Or
you have some structure in that. I think
you could start to you could start to
say, does it fit in there? What what
normally happens in real life uh is that
regulators have moved from VAR for
saying well your actual initial margin
and capital should be based that used to
be VAR then it was stress VAR uh and now
it's moved to expected shortfall but
they still require you to back test VAR.
So what you generally do is you build a
model which contain which will will
predict both VAR and expected shortfall.
You compute the number using the
expected shortfall number and then you
back test the VAR because that's a lot
easier, right? And then you say, well,
I've built the model consistently and
all I did was apply a different
multiplier for the expected shortfall
versus the VAR. So if the VAR back test
properly, then I'm prepared to accept
the expected shortfall,
>> right? So if if you like assume a
different shape of the tails, yeah, then
theoretically that's like not
necessarily like a valid
um like statistical test
>> well it is but when you're back testing
you're back testing and you say well
what happened on the 23rd of December 20
2015 well there was no distribution
that's just whatever happened on that
date right so there's no distribution uh
there so you can't say it's difficult to
make an assumption about whether or not
that was kind of predicted or not
predicted because it just it it's a
single uh draw from the distribution as
opposed to the shape of the
distribution. It doesn't tell you
anything. You can make any assumption
you want about that about the the tail.
But because I've taken one number, it
doesn't really show me anything. Does
that does that make sense?
>> Yep.
>> I guess building up on that. So you
mentioned that you can like backpass on
both the shortfall and bar on bar
instead of the shortfall and that's like
kind of like p like and then helps you
like predict more accurately. Are these
model like accurate enough to account
for like the difference that
bar and are they precise enough
are they well it depends how you build
up the model right so essentially my
model here right the model wasn't really
a var model or an expected shortfall
model the model that I proposed here was
that everything is that that the daily
changes are normally distributed right
and in this case that they're
independent uh All the daily changes are
independent. That was essentially my
model, right? Having made that
assumption, I get a VAR number and an
expected shortfall number, right? And I
can back test the VAR. In real life,
people make more sophisticated choices.
They don't assume that it's normally
distributed. You can have other
distributions. You don't assume that all
the changes are uh in independent of of
each other. But the model is not really
a VAR model necessarily or an expected
shortfall model. the model is what did I
assume about the distribution
having made those assumptions I get a
var number and I get an expected
shortfall number does that make sense
on on this example when you were
explaining it u you said that uh let's
see I guess the actual shortfall was
5.2% 2% was it or through the model or
through the historical simulation but
>> yeah so what so what I said so what I'd
said was that this came up as so the var
came up as 225 right based on the model
if I go back to this table right so this
is the leftmost column here right in
reality we can see that there were 12 uh
there were 12 there were 12 actual days
when I exceeded that number there should
have been five that was the intention
Right? So you say, but if I was trying
to produce something that had a 1% that
I'm supposed to exceed VAR 1% of the
time, that's the definition of VAR,
right? So if I'm trying to come up with
a model and I'm where I expect something
to happen 1% of the time. So I expect
the VA to be exceeded 1% of the time,
right? Then I do 500 draws of that thing
and I say, well, how many times was it
actually exceeded?
>> That's and then the probability of it
being 12 is 5%.
>> So you were being conservative. At least
this
>> Yes,
>> this bar is conservative. Therefore,
it's okay even though it's wrong in a
sense or at least it's not calibrated.
>> It's
>> but it's conservative. Uh
>> it's not that conservative. A
conservative VA would be bigger than the
historical VAR. Right? The actual thing
is the historical VA was 300 or
something. Conservative would be a
bigger number, right? But it's not
overly aggressive, let's say. I think
that's probably the way to to to put it.
>> Any other questions? Anyway, thanks very
much.
>> Okay. Thank you.
[Applause]