We're moving on to our next startup,
Tinfoil.
>> So, hi everyone. So, I'm going to talk
about Tinfoil. Uh, my name is Jules Din.
I'm one of the co-founders. Uh, I did my
PhD at MIT in security and hardware
security specifically. So, we're going
to talk about verifiable private AI
today.
Oh, so the challenge that we're
addressing is that your private data is
now more than ever your most valuable
asset. Um and when you use AI on private
data, you risk to expose it to third
parties. So short-term solution that
we've seen uh in industry for instance
is to restrict the usage of AI on
sensitive data. So our goal at Tinfoil
is to unlock the use of data on personal
uh proprietary and regulated data for
instance. So current solution have like
strong limitation. You could do all your
deployment on prem or even like on
device like really in your basement but
this has a like that's difficult to
scale and has a lot of um limitation. Uh
you can have legal enforcement. Uh but
the problem here is that there's no
technical way to enforce this contract
and this could be like prone to data
breaches and other things. And finally
you can do pi reduction. But the problem
here is that uh if you remove the um
like very important data um or important
detail on your data like you will lose
accuracy or you will lose utility out of
your AI system. So at info we're
building using a different technologies
and specifically uh hardware based
security or hardware backed u enclave.
So the latest Nvidia GPUs actually
include already hardware mechanism to
protect your data. So they've been
mentioned several time in the webinar,
but this type of technology is called uh
secure hardware encloses or trusted
execution environment. Um so the concept
here is that all your data is going to
be encrypted directly to inside an
enclave that lives in the GPU. Because
all these mechanisms are implemented in
hardware, you actually do not have
performance overhead or very negligible.
And you will also be able to prove which
code exactly is running inside of that
secure environment. So you get a
cryptographic proof that uh it's the
correct uh secure uh environment that's
running there. And so what's interesting
once you have set up this environment is
that even someone who controls the
computer who has access to the computer
cannot extract the sensitive data.
And so you get several very interesting
security properties out of uh this
system. You have data privacy which mean
that no one not even us cloud provider
can see your data. You have
verifiability and integrity which means
that you can get a proof that you're
running exactly the code that's open
source and expected. So this address all
supply chain worries or this kind of
attack vectors. And you can also have
model privacy. So for instance, if
you're fine-tuning a model or like
creating a model from scratch with very
sensitive data, you probably want to
keep the model private to some extent.
And so that also achieved these kind of
properties. But just to give you a
concrete example of how this works and
how this materialized real life, I'm
going to show you a demo on a website uh
of a chat implementation for instance.
So uh this is our chat and so uh as you
can see we have like a wide selection of
open source model and so you can uh ask
it uh simple question like you would do
with chatg and so uh the difference here
is going to be the security. So here as
you can see we have like a bunch of
security check that are happening in the
browser to actually guarantee that your
data is end to end protected that no one
can access it. So I'm going to skip over
the technical details. Happy to answer
any question later. But basically every
time we publish code uh it's open source
automatically compiled measured and then
the hardware is going to prove that it's
exactly that code that running in the
secure environment.
Okay, back to my slides. So uh to take
this kind of very um low-level
technology and build something uh very
integrated that works like this like you
need a bunch of expertise from very
different angles of security. And so we
have a team that span very different
aspect of security practice. So as I
mentioned uh I did my PhD at MIT in
secure hardware cryptography. I also
worked at Nvidia on um like helping uh
implement and use the type of technology
that we're using. Uh I also worked at
Microsoft research and also with Intel
Labs during my PhD on this kind of
commercial um computing technologies. Uh
Tanya uh was at Cloudflare before
Tinfoil doing also cryptography. She has
deployed internet security protocol um
for two millions of people. Uh Sasha was
my labmate at MIT in cryptography and
privacy system and Nate uh is um uh my
fourth co-ounder and he has been working
on a lot of privacy infrastructure
including um tour and other like privacy
systems.
So just to show a case study for
instance uh we've been working with a
government contractor u to help deploy
AI in mission on mission critical data.
So the advantage here is that with
tinfoil uh they have complete isolation
of data across team. There's no operator
access to all uh this sensitive data and
you also have end to end uh supply chain
transparency. uh in term of where we are
at as a startup. So we're in production
with a lot of consumer and startups and
we're also doing a proof of concept with
several entropas client. Uh we also went
through y combinators a few months ago
and so the ask is that we're
specifically looking for uh customers in
regulated industries. So finance,
healthcare, insurance, government. So if
you want to roll out AI in sensitive use
cases where current security options are
not enough, uh please come talk to us.
And these are my contact and feel free
to add me on LinkedIn.
>> Thank you so much Jules. Uh we're
running out of time so if anyone is
interested in asking the questions
please um reach out to Jules directly or
connect with us. Thank you both for
startups and to all of you for joining
us today and please reach out again for
if you need help connecting with these
startups.