Okay. So remember that projection theory
works differently over uh if you look in
finite fields it works differently over
a prime field or a notp prime field. And
here was the key example.
Um, so we're going to do projection
theory in FQ and Q is P ^2 and our set
of points is going to be FP^2 which is a
subset of FQ ^2 and our set of
directions is going to be FP which is a
subset of FQ. So remember that uh if
theta is in fq then pi theta is going to
be a projection a linear map from fq ^2
to fq
which is given by pi theta of x1 x2 is
x1 + theta x2.
So this is our set of directions
and then s which is the maximum size of
the projection of x over all these
directions
um is uh is is p um because pi theta of
x is just fp
uh for theta and d.
Okay. So if you uh just write down the
sizes of all the things in this
important example, x is p ^2 which is q
and s and d are p which is q to the
half. So in in particular notice that
the size of each projection is the
square root of the size of the set.
Okay. Um so
so nothing like this is supposed to
happen over FP and there's a hard open
conjecture that um that gives bounds
that are much stronger than this
example. Um but the techniques that
we've talked about for most of the class
do not depend on the field. So the
double counting does not distinguish
prime fields from not prime fields and
the 4A method does not distinguish prime
fields from not prime fields.
Um the summer ready trotder theorem
proves that this numerology cannot
happen for a set of points in R2. Um but
the proof has the proof is very
important but it has some limitations in
how it could apply. It certainly won't
apply over FP. Um and it also doesn't
seem to help very much from the point of
view of uh sets of balls in R2 with some
kind of spacing condition. It depends
what spacing condition but for the most
interesting spacing condition it doesn't
help very much.
Okay. Nevertheless, we know that this
cannot happen over finite fields
and the main theorem that we'll so this
week we will prove a theorem that says
that this cannot happen. So this is the
theorem of Ban Kats and Tao.
So again cat's tow projection theorem.
Okay it says the following thing. So if
we have x in fp^2
and let's say that the size of x is p to
the s where s is uh somewhere between
zero and two.
Okay. And then we have a set of
directions
in FP
and the set of directions will be p to
the t and t is uh bigger than zero.
Okay. So then if you look at the maximum
size of a projection,
[Applause]
it's significantly bigger than half of
the the square root of the of the size
of of X. So this is bigger than P to the
S over 2 plus epsilon
where this epsilon only depends on S and
T.
It's bigger than zero.
Okay. Um, so some remarks about the
epsilon. It's it's an explicit function.
I just don't write it down because it's
a little bit messy. For example, it's
continuous. It's not that hard to write
it down, but it is also pretty small.
Pretty disappointingly small.
Okay.
Um
there's also something called Bans's
projection theorem which is what publish
MKin is going to talk about today which
is the analog of this over the in the
setting of the real of balls in R2.
Um so there's an analog of this example
using C2 instead of R2 and then BN's
projection theorem is the analog of this
theorem that rules out that example.
So
this is an analogous theorem
for balls and art.
Okay. And these two theorems in spite of
the fact that this epsilon is very small
are very important sort of landmark
results in the field of projection
theory and they play a key role in many
applications. Um uh this ban projection
theorem it plays a key role in getting
the sharp projection estimates in R2 the
recent work uh that publish mkin and
others were involved in. Um this banan
projection theorem also plays an
important role in the solution of the ka
problem.
Um and this finite field projection
theorem as well as this one have some
have a important role in some
interesting applications about um how
fast different processes mix. Like if
you take some generators of a finite
group like SL2 over FP
um and then they make a random walk. How
fast does this random walk become evenly
distributed in SL2FP?
This is an important ingredient in
studying that.
Okay. Um so okay. So in spite of the
fact that the epsilon is small, these
theorems are are very important and
they're also qualitatively different
from the other theorems because they're
sensitive to what kind of field we're
working. Yeah.
>> What is the analog of P for ball or R2?
>> The analog of P. So we would have uh the
setting would be you'd have unit balls
and a ball of radius r and r is the
analog of p.
So all the sizes of things we would we
could think of them as powers of r.
Yeah.
>> Do the proofs use kind of similar
arguments or they completely
>> the question is do these two proofs use
similar arguments or are they completely
different? Um there are multiple proofs
of this um but at least one of them is
very similar to this with one sort of
layer of additional ideas
and so yeah so my plan is that we'll
we'll do this and then we'll talk about
the additional ideas to do this.
Okay cool. Well so the key difference
between FQ and FP is that FQ has a sub
field and FP has no sub field. Now, it's
elementary to check that FP has no
subfield, but because we're proving some
kind of quantitative estimates, we need
some quantitative lema that that says
that FP not only has no subfield, but it
doesn't have anything that's kind of
approximately a sub field. Um, so the
main goal for today will be to uh to to
prove to develop uh lambas like that.
And let me show you. So, so here's the
first version of a lema like that.
level one. Actually, let me do I think
we need a little notation.
Okay, so suppose that A is a subset of
FP.
If I write a + a, then that means the
set of all the sums a1 plus a2 where a1
and a2 are a and we could write a * a.
That's the set of all the products a1 *
a2 a1 and a2 and a
and so on. So there you can write a lot
of similar things like this and um I
think it'll be clear what they all mean
but if it's not of course we we'll talk
about it. Okay, so here's the lema. It's
a quantitative lema that says that um
that no subset behaves too much like a
sub field.
So it says if A is a subset of FP
then either
one option is that A minus A over A
minus A is all the death P
and the second option
is that
[Applause]
if you multiply try and add stuff in a
and subtract stuff. A lot of times it
will get bigger. 1 2 3 4 5 six. Six
might be enough. I think it might be
eight.
[Applause]
Okay. So, one possibility is if you
multiply, add and subtract elements of A
lot of times, then you get a lot more
stuff than just a. So this says A is not
too close to a sub field. And the other
options is if you do this you get all of
FP.
Now of course A could have been almost
all of FP already. So then it is kind of
almost a field. But if A was originally
a lot smaller than FP then in this case
this thing is a lot bigger than A.
Okay.
Um,
cool.
All right.
[Applause]
So, here is the proof.
Um, observation one.
So if uh c is not in a minus a over a
minus a
um then
a + c a
has size a squ.
Okay. Let me make sure it's clear what
all the notation means. So if I write
this thing, I have four copies of A. So
you take A1, A2, A3, A4, any four guys
in A and sort of plug them in for the
capital A. All the things you can get.
That's what this set is. And similarly
over here the lowerase C is a particular
element of FP and this means take any A1
and A2 and and do this.
Okay. Um so the proof of observation one
is quite simple. So suppose that I have
two different uh ele uh elements in here
but that are equal to each other. So
suppose a1 + c a2 is the same as a1
prime plus c a2 prime.
Well, if I do a little algebra, I can
solve this for C. And I discover that C
is um A1 prime minus A1
/ A2 - A2 prime, which is in A minus A.
So if C is not in A minus A, sorry,
which is in A minus A over A minus A.
So if C is not in here, then all of
these different representations are
actually different numbers. So the size
of this set is A^ squ.
Okay. Now if you want to be really
careful, maybe we should worry about
whether I have divided by zero. But if
a2 is equal to a2 prime, then the only
way that the top equation could be true
is if also a1 is equal to a1 prime and
then I just had the same thing. Okay.
All right. Great.
Okay. So,
so if I can locate some C that is in um
you know the ring of stuff I can make by
adding and multip maybe the if I can add
and subtract and multiply and divide a
bunch of elements of A and I can locate
some C which is not in here then I can
use this observation and I can get some
I can show that I can build out of A
many different things.
Okay, cool.
Okay,
now somewhere in our proof, we have to
use that FP is a prime field.
It wouldn't work in FQ and we haven't
used it yet. Well, how are we going to
use it? Well, let's just remember how we
would prove that FP is a prime field.
Um, sorry, how would we prove that FP
has no sub fields? How are we going to
prove? Well, um, if it had a sub field,
it would have to contain one
and then it would have to contain then
it would be closed under addition. So,
it would have to contain two and three
and four and so on and then it would
have to contain all of FP.
Okay. Um,
so we we're basically going to use that
argument in observation two.
[Applause]
Okay. So observation two if a minus a
over a minus a is not everything
um then there exists some b in a minus a
over a minus a
so that b + 1 is not in a minus a over a
minus
Right.
Right. Okay. So why is it um so so zero
is an a minus a over a minus a. It's a
proof of observation too.
zero is in there because you could
choose these to be the same and you can
choose those to be different.
Um okay if one is not
uh yeah okay so then then we just if
okay either everybody in FP is in A
minus A minus A minus A or somebody's
not and so then we take uh B + one is
the smallest
number which is not
an A minus A over A minus A
and there we go.
Okay. And the special thing that we're
using about FP we've used that we have
it's a prime field is just we're using
that if you start at zero and you keep
adding one you get all the elements.
Okay. So that's the proof of observation
too.
Um
and so now we are basically done. So now
we have seen that if a minus a over a
minus a is not fp
then if you take a and you add this b +
one. So b is an a minus a over a minus
a. I'm going to add one to it. So b +
one is in here. There is bigger than a
square.
So if I take six elements of a and I do
this uh the number of different guys I
will get is is really much bigger than
okay and then this doesn't look exactly
like my two but I just like clear the
denominator and expand things out.
So when I clear the denominator, I'll
get
a * a minus a * a from this guy. Inside
of here, I'll have a minus a plus a
minus a all multiplied by a. Okay, I
have a bunch of stuff.
Okay.
So, I know so Nets Katz and I are old
collaborators and I remember talking
with him about this and and uh that
it it took quite a while for them to
figure out how to get started on this
problem.
Um okay, now looking back at this this
this proof is really clean. this lema is
perhaps not the the statement of the
lema is perhaps not the nicest thing
that you might like. Um and um
[Applause]
so there are much there are kind of
cleaner things like for example later
today we'll show that you know just just
this is significantly bigger than a
um and and different variations.
Okay.
Um,
so maybe we should mention we could ask
some much simpler questions like we
could just say um if you have a subset
of FP called A, is it true that A plus A
is always much bigger than A?
That's true for most subsets, but it's
not true for all of them. Um, but
thinking about that much simpler
question is actually uh so that that's
like a a foundational question in in
additive combinatorics to understand
that um and and understanding that well
feeds into being able to understand this
this stuff better. Okay. So, let me pose
this on the board and we'll start to
talk about it.
So my question for us is
um when
is a + a
small?
So here I have in mind that A is a
subset of FP. Although we could have a
very similar conversation if A was a
subset of Z or A was a subset of R or
dot dot dot.
Okay. Can anybody think of a subset if
FP or A plus A is only a tiny bit bigger
than A?
Yeah,
>> is some set
um
and that includes like numbers and then
the negative values of those numbers in
F like only one 2 -2 or something like
that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So the comment is maybe I
should have some numbers and negative of
those numbers. Let me ask you a more
precise question. So you have to choose
L numbers in FP and you want to choose
them to make A plus A as small as
possible. Who would you choose?
>> Yeah.
[Music]
>> Yeah, you could choose an arithmetic
progression.
So example one.
Um suppose A was just the numbers from
one up to L.
So a plus a will be the numbers from 2
to 2 l. Uh so a + a is at most 2 * a.
It's tiniest bit less than that but not
very important for our discussion. And
this is the small this is the the
smallest that a plus a could possibly
be.
Okay. And it doesn't have to be one up
to l. It would work just as well if it
was an arithmetic progression. So
example one prime
our set A is little a + n d where n goes
from one up to l.
Um and then if you think about it a
little bit the size of the subset
behaves just the same.
Okay.
Um
there's another example that's a little
bit more general than this. So this is
an arithmetic progression where you have
just one kind of difference.
Um
and you could have something uh
uh so you should you could visualize it
like this.
And you could have a similar thing
involving a two-dimensional grid or a
higher dimensional grid.
All right. So example two is that a is a
+ n1 d1 plus dot dot dot plus n r
where um n i goes from one up to l i.
So what happens when you take a plus a?
It is contained in two little a plus n1
d1 plus dot dot dot plus nr
where now the n i go in between two and
2 li.
And so we see from this and I well which
so it which is contained in I could put
a one um so it's contained in something
that is 2 to the r * bigger. So we get a
+ a is bounded by 2 to the r * a.
So this thing here is called a
generalized arithmetic progression. It
has a dimension little r and it has a
volume or cardality which is
L1 to LR.
Okay. Um
can anybody think of any others?
So it is hard to think of other ones and
in some sense and and depending on how
we quantify it a little bit um these
sets or maybe these sets and their close
cousins appear to be the only sets that
have a really small subset
and um this was investigated by framan
starting in the 60s and 70s and he
proved a theorem to that effect called
framan's theorem Um
and um
uh and this was this is a a cornerstone
of additive combinatorics.
Um Framan's
Framan's proof was was somewhat
difficult to read and Rusa thought a lot
about it and clarified it and so this is
now called uh the Framan Rousa theory.
Okay. So it says the following thing.
Says that if a
um
so if a is in z the same thing would be
true in z mod p and a + a is less than
or equal to k a.
Um then
a is contained in a gap
with dimension
uh little r that only depends on k and
volume at most uh v that only depends on
k times the size of a.
So it roughly says that if a plus a is
small it is because a resembles example
two which is a generalization of example
one.
So in some sense these are the only sets
that have a really small subset.
Okay. So this is an important theorem in
additive combinotaurics but there are
two caveats about it. So one caveat is
that it's a it's a pretty deep theorem.
The proof is substantial
and the other caveat is that the
quantitative bounds are weak.
Um so in the original version
r of k was quite large. So r of k was
something like x of k to a power and v
of k was even larger. It's like x of x
of k to a power.
Okay. Um now
it is a trivial fact that any set A is
contained in a generalized arithmetic
progression of dimension equal to the
size of A.
So this is only interesting if R of K is
smaller than the size of A.
Um so this was only interesting
only meaningful let's say
if k was quite small.
Uh there's a big in um goal in additive
combinatorics to improve the
quantitative bounds in framan's theorem
and um
one benchmark is a conjecture called the
polomial frame and roua conjecture which
would say something meaningful even if k
was a small power of a. So there's a
conjecture that they would have a
meaningful bound
if k is a to the delta
for some small but universal
delta bigger than zero.
Okay. And this is still an open
conjecture. So it's out of range maybe
only a little out of range of of uh
current techniques. Um but if k was say
I don't know a to the 0.1
all this stuff about about framan's
theorem uh we we are very far from being
able to to deal with that.
Um
now if you look at framan's theorem what
we're trying to do is to give a complete
classification of all the sets A that do
this
and the complete classification is
something we only understand if K is
really really small.
But you could also ask for something
which is not as strong as a complete
classification but just some kind of
interesting information about sets A
with small subset.
Um okay
so if you look at this example you'll
notice that not only it has small subset
but it has uh also small a bunch of
other stuff like in these examples a
plus a is small also a minus a is small
also a plus a plus a is small
um and and and those so those for those
things we have much simpler proofs and
the quantitative bound s are much better
and they come from some lemmas that I
think originally were designed as uh
lemmas for this theorem but which have
lots of independent applications.
Okay.
So this theorem we I don't plan to prove
in the class but I wanted to mention it
for historical context and and these
lemmas are are really important and have
reasonable short proofs and I think are
worth for a wide range of people uh
knowing about.
[Applause]
Okay,
so the first of the lemas is called the
rusa triangle inequality.
Okay, so it says if Z is an Aelian group
and A and B and C are subsets of Z,
then
size of A times the size of B minus C is
bounded by the size of A minus B times
the size of A minus C.
Okay, so this might uh take a little
digesting. Have all of these letters
feels a little bit like alphabet soup.
Um the fact that we have can put three
different sets
makes it a little harder to digest but
it you know of course it makes it more
flexible in general and by plugging in
different choices for these three sets
you can prove some simpler things. Let
me illustrate this with an example.
As a correlator of this we will see
that if the if the sum set is small then
the difference set is also small.
Okay.
So correlary
if a + a is smaller than k * a
then
a minus a is smaller than k^ 2
k^ 2 * a.
So this lema is meaningful as long as k
is slightly smaller than the square root
of a.
So in a in a much wider range than than
the um uh frame and rusa theorem this is
a meaningful statement.
Okay. So proof um we're just going to
use roua and I have to tell you who are
a and b and c. So A will be A and then I
think
B
uh
yeah B and C are both negative A.
Okay. So if you look at B minus C that's
there's a lot of minus signs. This is a
little bit silly looking.
Um,
so that's just a minus a.
Okay. And a minus b or a minus c.
They're the same as each other because b
is the same as c. That's a minus a. So
that's a plus.
Okay. So now if we just plug in ra it
says a * this guy a minus a is less than
this guy times this guy that's a + a 2.
And by hypothesis that's smaller than k
2 a 2.
And if you cancel the factor of a that's
it.
Okay. And this has a a very simple proof
that will fit on this board and which is
already says something interesting and
non-trivial about how sums and
differences and stuff fit together. So
here's the proof. uh we will construct
a map fee that goes from a cross b minus
c
into a minus b cross a minus c which is
injective.
So this is the cardality of this set and
this is the cardality of that set. And
the reason that that this set is bigger
than that set is that we have an
injection from one into the other.
How does the injection work?
For every D in B minus C, we can choose.
So by definition, this D can be written
as somebody in B minus somebody in C.
Let's pick them. We choose B of D and B.
C of D C so that D is B of D minus C of
D.
Okay. Now what's our map?
V takes an A and a D. A lives here and D
lives there. We need to output somebody
in A minus B. So we take A minus B of D
and then A minus C of D.
So that is a map from here to here.
Why is it injective?
So to to check that it's injective.
So we're going to suppose
that v of a d is given to us. It's xy.
And then we're going to find
A and D from X and Y
and from this choice.
So the choice we made once and for all,
we used it to build the map. And now we
have to prove that there's only one A
and D that give a certain X and Y here.
Okay. So how do we recover them? Well,
if you if this is X and this is Y, we
see that Y - X is B of D minus C of D,
which is D. So that's how we find D.
And once we find D, it's easy to find we
once we find D, then we know B of D and
C of D. And now it's easy to find A. Um,
so uh X uh minus X plus B of D is A.
It's very short. It feels a teeny bit
like a magic trick to me.
But so on this board and this board we
have seen that if the sum set is small
then the difference set is also small.
Okay.
Yeah.
uh you
like divide
by *
you get like something that looks
exactly like a triangle
way.
[Music]
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. So the question is
it's called Ruse's triangle inequality
and it sort of looks like if we take the
logarithm and play with this then
something will look like the triangle
inequality.
Um and uh yeah so Russa did have that in
mind when he named it that way. So he
produced a pseudo distance between
different sets say you know between A
and B or B and C or whatever. And this
um this translates into saying that the
rud rou pseudo distance obeys the
triangle inequality. The distance from B
to C is bounded by the distance from A
to B plus the different distance from
from B to A plus the distance from A to
C.
Um I'm not sure whether that is helpful
or or not. Um it's his pseudo distance
is a little bit funny. Like it's not
true that the distance from A to itself
is zero. So it's not quite like
distances that I'm used to. Um so that
intuition I don't know may or may not be
helpful.
Um I guess we will see tomorrow that
sometimes you use this many times like
how you know how how would you use the
triangle inequality? Well the distance
from A to Z is bounded by the distance
from A to B plus the distance from B to
C plus the distance from C to D D D D D
D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D
D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D D and
maybe each of those things is easier to
understand and by the triangle
inequality, we can put them together. So
you can use this inequality in that way.
Um, and we'll see that tomorrow.
Tomorrow, Thursday.
Any other questions or comments?
>> Can I ask about the previous removing
denominator?
Just not sure how that works out. Does
it require something like this?
Um the question is about the removing
the denominator trick.
>> Um like when we had we had an a minus a
in the denominator and we multiplied it
out.
>> So that that was just um
algebra.
Um it's not it's not something fancy
like this.
Um
we'll u yeah let me bracket that we'll
see a little later something else with
removing denominators and and let's come
back to it then
do do you think did I understand your
question or
>> yeah I'm just not sure how that how how
that was actually
>> I think you only need six instead of
eight
Yeah, let's check in about it at the end
of class. Okay, the other important um
lema from from this field that went into
the proof of framan's theorem is called
Plunka inequality.
Plunka inequality allows us to say
things like if a plus a is small then a
plus a plus a is small.
So if A and B are subsets of Z in a
billion group
um and A + B is bounded by K * A
then
um okay let me make a little notation.
So sometimes we might want to talk about
b + b many times
um so let's say this is n times this is
sometimes written as n * b um although I
feel like that is slightly confusing um
so I have decided to adopt this notation
b like sum n times
okay so I could take b + m * - b + n *
and that's bounded by k to the m + n *
okay so let's do a few corlaries of this
um so just by plugging in a equals b we
see that if a + a is less than or equal
to k a um then a minus a is less less
than k^ 2 a. Uh that's actually the
correlary we already proved. Um but also
we could say a + a + a is bounded by k
cubed a
uh just plugging in a b and this is m is
three and n is zero and you can see you
can put higher powers here.
Also another corlary we can get is we
can switch the role of these guys in the
first corlary. So we can say if a minus
a is small
then a a plus a is also small.
So
proof is that b is negative a. So this
is a plus b and then this is basically b
plus b.
Okay.
Okay. Um,
we can also use this. So, we'll prove
this. That'll be our last big goal of
the class. Um but using
so this rera inequality and plunic
inequality have many many uses and one
simple use is we can use it to sort of
clean up and improve the statement of
our lema that fp if that has no
quantitative approximate sub fields. So
let me recall what we proved so far and
then we'll improve it a little bit.
Um so lma one was uh
if a is in fp
then either
um
a minus a over a minus a is all of fp
or
uh a * a min - a * A.
Okay. So now I can write this better. We
have three or four of those
minus three or four of those
as it is.
Okay. So we can improve this in a way
that you don't need to have so many
different expressions floating around.
So we can say that if a is in fp
and the size of a is p to the s where s
is strictly less than one then the size
of a * a minus a * a is at least p to
the s plus epsilon of s.
And here you could you could put either
plus or minus.
And this epsilon of s is bigger than
zero.
So again it's continuous it's explicit
but it's a little bit messy and it's
it's a little bit small.
You take any subset which is
significantly smaller than the whole
field. If you do take a * a minus a * a
it will be significantly bigger than you
started with.
So, you know, if you just took a minus
a, that wouldn't be good enough because
a could be an arithmetic progression. It
might so that might have almost the same
size as a. If you just took a time a
that wouldn't be good enough because a
could be a geometric progression. Two 2
1 2 the 2 up to 2 to the l.
Um, but if you take both sums and
products, then you have to end up with
significantly more stuff than you
started with. Okay, so that's why this
is called sum product theory. If you
have both sums and products interacting
with each other, then something happens.
Okay, so uh proof
um
okay so if
okay so there there are two cases case
one and case two but I'm actually going
to do case two first.
So case
um
okay so it could be that a * a is
already much bigger than a then we just
declare victory. So if
a * a is bigger than a to the 1 + delta
then we declare victory and here delta
is going to be much smaller than epsilon
um
or maybe we could say okay otherwise
otherwise
um
uh otherwise a * a is basically the same
size as a.
Okay. Now, if a * a um plus a * a is
much bigger than a, then we declare
victory.
Uh where is I writing? Yeah, here. I
guess let's just put this
and we declare victory. Um otherwise
we would have a * a + a * a is smaller
than k a * a where k is like uh p to the
epsilon
and then we can use plunker
and that would tell us that a * a to a
big power
minus a * a to another big power
here. We could put
four. Um that would be bounded by k to
the eth a * a.
Um and so that would be bounded by maybe
um a * p to the tan epsilon or something
like that. And this contradicts the fact
that this we know this set is bigger.
Okay. And case one is similar but I
think maybe I'll make that an exercise.
You can just practice using pluna and
rua things.
Okay. And I'm going to do one more
correlary. Um so suppose you you know
you start with the set A and you start
multiplying and adding and subtracting
and see what you get and we've proven
that after you do after you do this
operation it gets a bit bigger
but suppose you don't just yeah
>> one question about this so you said that
kind of the idea is that if you have
sort of arithmetic progression or
geometric progression it can be small
but with both it has to be large. Is it
possible to prove that instead of the
the difference of a * a and a * a you
can just say a * a is large or a plus a
is large.
>> Okay. Yes. Great question. Okay. So the
question is so so in the theme of lema 2
is we tried to simplify as much as
possible the expression that we put here
and there is a suggestion um how to make
it as simple as possible. Um, so let me
I'm going to erase this proof and write
that as a as a I'll write it as a
theorem. It's a theorem.
So
even better
there is a theorem
um ban cat's towel.
So if a is subset of fp
uh a equ= p to the s0 less than or equal
to s less than 1 then
you could take um the maximum
of a + a and a * a
and that is bigger than p to the s plus
epsilon of s.
So this is better than this
qualitatively.
And actually the word sum product
inequality it could refer to a lot of
things but the the the inequality it
most often refers to is this one. So
either either the sums or the products
grow. Yeah, that's right. Okay. So all
the stuff we've seen are steps towards
the proof of this theorem. But there is
actually still some more ideas to get
all the way down to here. And we may or
may not end up doing it in the class.
It's unclear to me if getting all the
way down to there is actually uh
important in in projection theory.
Yeah. Cool.
Okay. So, one goal you might have in in
in simplifying and clarifying this story
is to make this expression as simple as
possible and get some gain. But another
goal that you might have is to make this
gain really large and perhaps this
expression will be more complicated and
you can also do that.
So let me make some uh notation.
Let's say poly k of a some sort of
polomials of complexity k. So I take a
to the k. So that's means I multiply
uh k different elements of a together
and then I add k things like that
together and then maybe I also want some
minuses
right so a a to the k is a * a * a k *
okay so these are polomials in A of
complexity
and uh another corlary which is at the
same level follows easily from this one
is that if we have zero less than s less
than t less than one and a is in fp. So
okay then there exists some k that only
depends on s and t. So that for any set
A in any FP where the size of A is P to
the S, the size of poly K of A
is at least P to the T.
Okay. And the proof of this is is easy.
The proof is use lema too many times.
So I start with the set A. A * A minus A
* A is a bit bigger. Called this B. B *
B minus B * B is even a bit bigger.
And if you think about what B * B minus
B * B means, it would fit in like
probably four again.
And you keep doing this.
Okay, cool.
Cool.
Um so these these lemas theorems and
stuff they are important because um
and plumac's inequality and ruse's
inequality they are important
um because um
you so once we once we see so if we see
something like a plus a is small that
then that tells us that a has some
structure and all these inequalities
then imply that lots of other things are
small. So it's sort of like a contagious
structure like we start we input some
structure but we find out more and more
structure and that's a very useful tool
and so lots of problems that we see in
projection theory uh it seems to be
helpful to try to phrase them in the
form that some subset is small because
then we can use Pluna's inequality and
we can find out lots of other things.
Okay. So in the last part of the class
we will prove this inequality. This is
the trickiest thing that we will prove
today.
All right. So the original proof of the
pluna inequality was somewhat difficult.
Um and there was a short proof that was
given by Jorgus Petritus
um about 10 or 15 years ago which is the
one that I'll that I'll show.
Okay.
So it's based on a key lema.
So the key lema says that if a + b is at
most k * a
then there's a subset x contained in a
so that for any set c
x + c + b
divided by x + c is also at most k.
So okay by the way this top inequality
of course we can divide by a. The top
inequality says a + b over a is bounded
by k.
The lema says that if this is true
then it's so if it's true for the set a
then it's also true for the set x plus c
where x is carefully chosen. I'll
explain in a bit how it's chosen but c
is a totally arbitrary set. So there are
many choices for C. So there are many
different you know this this is many
inequalities
right? Okay let me um tell you who X is
which is an important idea in the proof.
Um so first of all so x is a subset of a
that we choose in order to minimize
minimize the ratio x + b / x.
So let me give an example that might
help to motivate why you would want to
look at this x.
So suppose that a is the numbers from
one up to 100
which has a lot of additive structure
together with some random number. So
I've put a million
and b is the numbers from one up to say
50.
Okay. So if you add A and B together,
this stuff plus this stuff is quite
small. There's a lot of structure there.
Then there's this stuff plus this stuff
that doesn't have any particular
structure, but since there's only one
stray element here, that's not so many
of those either. So A plus B is pretty
small.
Now, who would X be?
X is the subset of A which is chosen to
minimize this ratio.
and including this guy is not so
helpful.
Um so x would actually be here just the
numbers from one up to 100.
Okay. So I think perhaps that
philosophically the point of doing this
is identifying the part of A that really
has the additive structure and throwing
away possibly some parts of A that are
not not that relevant.
Okay. And then once you have found the
heart of the matter here um then
you can you can add anything else to it
and you still have that amount of
structure.
Okay.
All right. So, let's give a name. Let's
say that. So, that's who X is. And let's
say x + b / x is k lower bar which is at
most k.
So a + b over a is at most k and x is
allowed to be all of a but we might
choose a smaller set if we can make this
ratio even smaller. So k bar is less
than or equal to k. Okay. And really the
key claim
is that x + c + b over x + c is at most
k lower barc.
Okay. So now we're going to prove the
claim by induction.
So we're going to prove the claim by
induction
on the cardality of C.
And if the cardality of C is 1, then X +
C + B is just X + B
and X + C is just X. So if the cardality
of C is one, I'm just shifting this set.
and shifting that set doesn't change
their cardalities.
Okay. So now we can do the inductive
step.
All right. So let's say that C prime is
C union one more guy. And by induction
we know that it's true for C. So we know
x + c + b is bounded by k lower bar x +
c and we want to check for crop.
All right.
Okay. So the key character in this
argument that Petrus came up with
is a set y which is the set of x and x.
So that x + little c + b is contained in
big x plus big c plus b. Let's see how
that naturally comes up.
Right.
All right.
So we we we're thinking about x plus c
prime plus b. We want to see that it's
not too big. And we're using induction.
So we want to see how it changes when we
added this one guy. So this is the
previous guy x + c + b plus um
the new ones.
And I want them to be really new.
So, here are some new elements that live
here. And I'm going to take out any
elements I've already counted,
right?
Sorry. Um,
how, um, I don't quite understand the
definition of y. How can x plus c plus b
not be a subset of x plus c plus b?
>> Right? So this uh so c prime is a
previous set c union with some little c
>> and little c is not in big c.
>> Okay. Now I have to write all the little
c's and big c's really carefully. But
this is a little c and this is a big c.
Cool. Okay. So this X is automatically
in big X but in a failure of
functorality of not of notation little C
is not in big C.
All right.
Okay. Now, one thing to note about this
definition that helps to motivate it is
that y + little c plus big b is
contained in x plus big c plus big b
because for each element of y, little y
plus little c plus big b is defined to
be in here.
So this is at most x + c + b plus
x + c + b take away y + c + b.
All of these were already counted. So
there are at most this many new guys.
All right. And this is x + c + b + x + b
- y + b because this is a subset of this
and the plus c just translates things.
So I have so this thing is that big and
I remove from it this thing which is
that big.
So that's the upper bound for um the
numerator.
Okay.
Um,
so I'm I'm trying to bound this thing
with a C prime. I need I want to prove
an upper bound. So I need an upper bound
for the numerator and a lower bound for
the denominator.
Okay,
so the denominator is x +
uh c prime
and so that's x + c plus um the the set
how many x and x. So that little x plus
little c is not contained in big x plus
big c.
So it's the guys I already had and then
I have guys of the format little x plus
little c. And I only want the new ones,
the ones that aren't already counted.
That's an equality. And I'm gonna write
it as x + c plus x minus the x and x. So
that x + c is an x plus c.
Okay. And now key observation is that
these guys are all in y.
This is a subset of y.
Right? Because if little x plus little c
is in big x plus big c. Um so if little
x plus little c is in big x plus big c
then I can add b to both sides and this
is in there.
So those are all in y.
So this is a subset of y. So the size of
this guy is at most the size of y. And
since I'm subtracting here, I can say
this is at least x + c + x minus y.
Okay.
So now we'll just put together
everything that we know.
Okay. We know that x + c + b over x + c
is at most k bar. We know that by
induction.
We know that x + b / x is equal to k
bar. We know that by definition. That's
just what k bar was.
And we know that y + b over y is greater
than or equal to k bar. That was the
definition of x. x was chosen to
minimize this ratio.
Y might perhaps be equal to x, but
that's that's okay anyway. But it's
never going to be any smaller.
Okay? And so therefore by algebra by how
fractions work x + c + b. Okay. So so
now I can say I I want to say x + c
prime + b over x + c prime. And I want
an upper bound for that.
Okay. So the numerator is bounded by 1.
x + c + b + x + b
minus y + b.
And the denominator is lower bounded by
part two and it's x + c + x - y.
And then because each of these ratios
has the correct sign, this is at most k.
Yeah. So this is short. It is a little
tricky and I must admit I don't quite
understand how Petrus thought to do
this.
Um
Okay. So from the key lama we can prove
uh plunic's inequality
and then see if anybody
yeah if you have room you can turn turn
over in your mind
why did philosophically why did this
work out so nicely. If anybody has
thoughts about it I would be happy to
hear.
[Applause]
Okay. So, proof. Okay. So, say we're
starting with this.
Um
so by the main the main we use our main
lema.
So it tells us that there exists some x
and a and we have x + c + b at most k *
x + c for any c.
How might we use this?
Um
right. So okay, C could be empty. So we
get X + B is at most K * X.
C could be B. So we get X + B + B.
That's at most K * X + B.
And X plus B was at most K * X. So
that's at most K 2 * X.
Okay. And you can see where this goes.
So I'll do one more. you'll get the
pattern. If I add one more b, that's at
most k x plus b plus b. Plug in what I
already know about this. That's at most
k cub * x. All right. So if I add x + m
copies of b, that will be at most k * x.
Okay.
And then uh
we'll use the roua inequality. So this
is already you know if um
uh this is already pretty good thing uh
like if a equals b here then I could say
a to the m is bounded by k to the m * a
right because a to the a to the m is
obviously at least as big as x plus a to
the m. So I get a the m is bounded by k
the m * a. That's a typical correlary of
Pluner.
Anyway, to get the uh advertised finale,
we use Ruse's inequality.
Ruser was a times
there.
So can plug in um
uh
I say so x * b + m - b + n is bounded by
x + b + m
x + b + n.
Uh
and then we plug in each of these and we
get k to the m + n
* x*
x.
Yeah, that's right. Okay. So then I uh
get this by itself. So b + m - b + n is
bounded by k m + n * x which is bounded
by k the m + n * a because x is a subset
of a
Okay, so this proof is short. It is a
little tricky, but I think it is well
worth spending some time with uh because
this inequality is really quite
important. I would say that it plays
really a key role in all the later
developments in projection theory and
the solution to the CA problem in a lot
of things.
Um and uh so as we keep going, you know,
tomorrow, Thursday, and so on, we'll
reflect more about why this is useful
and important. Um and um maybe I'll try
to come up with some homework to try to
reflect on on uh how this proof got put
together.