Hi everyone, I'm Shingi. I'm a graduate
student working with Carolina and Shiva.
I'd like to pres present our multimodel
framework for understanding a holistic
representation of cell states and tissue
organization. So we've heard from
previous talks that there are many ways
of understanding cell states. Not only
can we look at the gene expression to
understand transcriptional cell state,
we can also look at chromodine images
which is which contains very rich
information of the mechanical state of
cells and we can look at additional
modalities such as protein stains or how
cells organized in tissue by looking at
spatial transcripttoics or looking at
tissues um tissue imaging. But the
challenge coming with all of these data
is that it's very hard to compare cross
modalities because we cannot easily just
look at compare image pixel intensities
to the value of gene expression. So in
order to fully under fully utilize all
of the available data modalities, we
need to develop a method that can take
into account the very different
measurements and we propose a framework
for doing that. So we have one
autoenccoder for each data modality and
then we can uh have the autoenccoders to
jointly encode into the shared
representation that now have a union of
information from all the input data
modalities. With this shared
representation, we can then perform
downstream analysis such as
visualization and clustering. Not only
comparing the similarity of cells based
on gene expression, but also comparing
the cells based on if their chromatin
image is pathologically similar.
So now if we for example if we cluster
the cells based on the sharp
presentation then the cells would be
grouped together based on their
similarity in all of the input
modalities. So we then uh apply this
model to for to to look at the special
transcrytoic data set uh of Alzheimer's
disease MOS model and now we're
integrating the into the shared
representation this the gene expression
the uh cell chromatin images and
location of cells in tissue and we can
then look at what the clusters tells us
and how does it differ from the
clustering of a single modality alone.
So if we apply the clusters back into
where they're located in the mouse
brain, you can see that it's nicely
outlines where the cortex region is and
where the hypoc campus region is and
it's very consistent across the
different mice mouse brains. And if we
look closely into this cortex region of
mouse, our clustering is saying that uh
there's this novel separation in the
mouse mouse brain cortex as this differs
from the horizontal layers in a
reference atlas. So we wondered what's
separating this mouse cortex brains. And
if we look at an orthogonal stain that
we did not actually use to train our
model, which is the MOI beta plaque, a
pathological protein associated with
Alzheimer's disease, we can see that
this novel separation in the cortex
region actually correspond to how likely
the plaque is going to accumulate in
that particular region. And in
particular, a cluster three region is
more likely to accumulate more plaques
and larger plaques. So this tells us
that um the integration of multiple data
modalities is able to identify this
spatial progression of Alzheimer's
disease and the likelihood of the
special regions in accumulating um the
the pathological
proteins. And since we have the power of
multimodality, we can then look at
tissue mark look at disease markers not
only in terms of the gene expression
differences, but we can also look at the
uh the biomarkers in terms of the
difference in cell chromatin. So for
example, we can look at where in this
chromatin image is more predictive of
that there's a ml beta plaque nearby. So
we al so we indicated this
predictiveness of chromatin image of an
M beta plaque in the image by the
intensity of blue pixels. And it turns
out that the predictiveness is not only
highlighting particular cell types, but
it's picking out very specific single
cells within one cell type. For example,
this microglea, but not the microglea
next to it. It's not only just picking
out entire cell nucleus, but it's also
picking out denser regions in a cell
nucleus such as this region in the
inhibitory neuron, but not the entire
nucleus. So this leads us to the
hypothesis that perhaps um our model is
really looking at the denser regions of
the chromatin or the hetrochromatin
region as a pred as a for the prediction
of amaloid beta plex. So if we quantify
the hetrochromatin across different cell
types we can see that there's a very
consistent increase of hetrochromatin
whether it's in neuronal cells or glyo
cells when we compare the ad mice to the
control mice. So this tells us where
chromatin is a very simple and cost
effective biioarker. It contains a lot
of information about cell states and can
be directly used as a disease biomarker.
And because it's so informative, we then
wondered can we use chromatin as a way
to predict missing modalities. So as
we've heard before that um in the same
experiment we cannot simultaneously
measure all the possible modalities and
that's especially the case when we are
going into the measurement of proteins.
So if you want to understand protein
localization, we can take protein
stings. However, we have 20,000
different proteins in a human that can
be possibly expressed in a human cell.
And then if to study this protein
localization across all the possible
cell lines and then this will be
experimentally
invisible. And because to fill up this
matrix of protein localization in the
different cell lines, we need to perform
one experiment for each pair of protein
and cell line. Um so people have
actually done that uh to and to create
one of the largest existing database uh
for protein localization namely the
human protein atlas and even after many
years of efforts and resources our
understanding of protein localization is
still incomplete that we only have 41
different cell lines measured in HPA and
we only have 17,000 proteins measured in
HPA and and more importantly not all
pairs of these um proteins and cell
lines are measured that only 0.25% of
all the possible pairings were measured
and this is because the number of
proteins that can be measured in the
same experiment is limited. So it's
perhaps not possible to experimentally
profile all the possible pairings. So we
need a computational tool that can allow
us uh to predict the protein
localization from measurements that we
have that we have and uh with all that
if we combine the protein sequences
together with cellular stains that tells
us the cell state the cell states and
cell types we can then make predictions
of the protein localization with a
single cell and cell type specificity.
So to do that we first uh look at the
sequence representation of proteins by
using a language model and this is and
the ESM2 is a structural prediction
model that takes protein sequence to pro
predict protein structures. We tailor
the sequence representation learned from
ESM2 to the particular task of a
localization prediction by training this
classifier that takes the sequence
representation to predict the local the
localization labels.
We can then learn cell states from
cellular stains and we are not only
using the chromatin stain but we also
have stains for microtubial and er in
the human protein atlas. So with this uh
image representation that tells us the
state of single cells uh we can then
combine the sequence representation with
image representation to make a
prediction
uh of that particular protein in a
single cell.
So we tested this model across many
unseen proteins and unseen cell lines
that we not that we did not use in the
training uh in the training of our model
and we can quantify the prediction
errors across different proteins. If we
categorize this prediction errors across
proteins in different cellular
compartments, we can see that our
prediction uh is quite accurate and
performs equally well across different
compartments. And we collaborated with F
chro institute to perform experimental
validations to see in addition to um
predict localization in unseen proteins
and unseen cell lines, can we also
predict localizations in new
experimental context. So we looked at
two cell lines that the model has seen
in training. And we can see that our
model prediction is aligned quite well
with the experimental validation even
for proteins that were not used in
training. And we can then look at cell
lines that the model has never seen
before. And again, our model performs
quite well and aligns well with the
experimental validation and even for a
cell line that's not included in
HPA. And now now since we have the
ability to mix predictions of proteins
and cell lines that a model has never
seen before and fill up this matrix of
proteins by cell lines to understand
protein localization, we can then be
able to perform tasks and understand
protein properties that were not that
were not accessible before because of
the missing data. And one such protein
property is how protein varies how
protein localization varies across
different cell lines in the human
protein atlas. One protein is only
measuring up to three cell lines. So
it's hard to understand the variability
of proteins across different many
different cell lines. And since we
filled up this matrix of um proteins by
cell lines, we can now compute the
variability of proteins across many
different cell lines. And if we then
rank the proteins based on their
variability, we can see that the most
variable proteins are associated with
processes that are known to be dynamic
such as regulation of transcription,
cell differentiation, and chromatin
regulation. And here's one example of a
protein that our model predicted to be
highly variable. So for example, in this
MCF MCF MCF7 cell line, the protein is
more in the in uh in inside the nucleus.
Whereas in a different cell line like
this MB4 cell line, the protein is more
outside of the
nucleus. And we can also do the same
analysis not only on a cell length
level, but to also understand the
variability of protein localization on a
single cell level. And since we're using
a multimodel um input to make a
prediction of protein localization, we
started to wonder that which cellular
compartment that we used as an input is
contributing to this variability of
localization. Additionally, we showed
that our model can predict quite
accurately for many different proteins.
But where's the limitation of such a
prediction? Are there features in
protein localization that cannot be
derived from cell states learned from
cellular stings?
So to answer these two questions, we
developed a model that not only
integrates different modalities but also
explicitly disentangles what's the
shared information between the different
modalities and what's the modality
specific information because in this
case if we want to know where's the
limitation of a cross modality
prediction, we can then look at the
shared information versus the modality
specific information and only the shared
information capture captured by the
shared latent space would be something
that's that's predictable in a cross
modality prediction.
uh and and then we can also try to
interpret what's in the share space and
modality specific space uh in order to
understand which which component in the
input modalities is contributing to the
variability of protein
localization and because we have a very
segmented latent space that we have a
shared latent space versus two modality
specific latent space in order to make
such training possible uh we're having a
novel training scheme that instead of
training the encoders and decoders
together as a standard autoenccoder. Uh
we have a two-step training process that
we train a randomly initialized latent
space together with a decoder and then
to generalize two cells that were not in
involved in the u train in the first
step training we have a second step
training process that maps that trains
encoder to map the input modalities to
the shared
spaces. So with this model we can then
disentangle the share space and the
modality specific space and compare the
chromatin stains versus the different
protein stains. So for example if we
want to know if we actually need to
experimentally measure the protein stain
for gamma H2AX versus predicting gamma
H2AX from protein from chromatin ST and
protein sequence. we can look at the
share space and modality specific space
and then we found that for the for some
general characteristics of gam 2a x uh
intensity that's something that's in a
shared written space and that can be
predicted from chromine things whereas
if we want to understand what's the
number of DNA double stranded breaks
marked by this counts of gamma h2ax
that's something captured in a protein
specific space and that has to be
experimentally measured and cannot be
relied and cannot rely on cross modality
prediction from chromatin to predict the
gamx fosi
counts. Um, additionally we've seen that
the protein localization are quite
variable across cell lines and also
across single cells. We want to
understand what's the source of this
variability. Is it the nucleus stain
that's different or is it the
microtubial stain that's different and
which one is causing the differences in
the localization difference across
different single cells. So to do that we
can probe the shared or modality
specific latent space by clustering the
cells in each latent spaces and look at
the properties within each cluster. For
example we can look at what's the
intrauclear proportion of proteins in
cluster 2 versus cluster one. And uh if
there's a significant difference in
intrauclear proportion in a shared space
then this means that the variability in
the protein localization within the
nucleus is something that's captured by
the share space.
So for example if we do this for the CL
and S1 1A protein then we can see that u
the clust the two clusters in the
nuclear specific space show significant
difference in in the intrauclear
proportion and specifically if we look
at the high intrauclear proportion cells
versus a low intrauclear proportion
cells that there's a significant
difference in their nucleus morphology
and more specifically that the high in
the cells with high intrauclear
proportion of this protein has a higher
content of it
chromatin and We can similarly do this
for other proteins such as DDB1 and we
found that the variability of DDB1
localization is something that's not
related to nucleus but is instead
captured by both the microtubial and ER
and the variability is associated with
the intensity of microtubial and ER
channel as well as the volume of
cytoplasm to uh the ratio of the volume
of cytoplasm to the nucleus.
So, so to summarize, we've I've shown
that our framework not only learns a dry
representation uh that takes into
account all different modalities and
allows us insights uh into the cell
state and tissue organization
differences beyond what we can learn
from a single modality. We can further
disentangle the contribution from
different modalities and learn the
shared and modality lat modality
specific latent spaces. And this not
only allows us to uh have a better
experimental design in terms of in terms
of understanding the limits of um cross
modality prediction but also allows us
to understand the contribution of
different cellula compartments to uh an
observed phenotype. And with that I'd
like to thank my mentors and
collaborators Caroline Shiva and um
other group members. Thanks.
[Applause]
And I think we have time for one
question. Any questions? All right.
A very nice presentation. Um just one
quick questions. uh I wonder whether the
the chicken and egg you know uh paradox
is that when you try to measure the
croentine structure to predict you know
um the Alzheimer disease state and I
wonder whether you know the chromatin
was changed as a visa or the disease
state or you use the you know chromatin
as a predictor for the disease state.
Yeah, that's a question we've been
thinking a lot and that's a question we
don't have answers for and we need
additional either time course data or
perturbation data to understand if the
chromatin stays the chromatin change
happens before the disease change or if
there's something that's upstream of
both like cell state change and
chromatin change.
Thank you.