Episode
one. Congratulations. You are a terrible
robot. You may already know a lot about
innovation. Even if you're an expert or
you have already made millions, for the
next hour or so, which is what this
series of videos is meant to last, I ask
you to open your mind to a new
possibility while I take you through
what we have learned as we have
developed and practiced what has become
the MIT way to do innovation. Why? There
are well over 40 years worth of
technology sitting out there on the
proverbial shelf waiting for a new
generation of hands-on innovators,
someone like you, to put them to use to
make a real problem go away sustainably.
That is for good. It just takes another
innovation mindset. To be clear, I am
not talking about another app or another
social media scheme or yet another
startup pitch. I am inviting you to get
real and to believe there are
technologies out there you can master to
make the problem you care about go away
even if you do not think you have the
right background. Flying cars to solve
traffic local manufacturing to address
inequality. The question isn't whether
the problem you care for can be solved.
Rather the question is how you're going
to do it and which technologies you will
bring together to do it sustainably. You
have plenty of options. We have created
this free video course to share with you
the MIT way of thinking about and doing
innovation. You'll learn about the
mindset we've instilled for nearly two
decades in hundreds of MIT students. It
is based on concepts in the course I
lead called innovation teams or it teams
for short. ITM students learn how to
solve problems with technology and move
technology from lab to impact. Let me
tell you a little about these students.
You might see yourself in them. They
come from all backgrounds and life
experiences ranging from humanities and
business to engineering. Some have been
in industry for years. Some are
self-made professionals or entrepreneurs
or investors. Some are pursuing a
master's or PhD degree and some have
just started college. When they first
come to IT teams, most have thought and
read about innovation, sometimes a lot.
Through their readings, they've been
trained to think that they are limited
to ideas that fit their background. They
have been told that when it comes to
innovation, they have to find a
disruptive idea or to follow recipes
with steps like robots do.
Chances are, you have thought or read a
lot about innovation, too. That's fine.
If you're anything like our MIT
students, you will soon discover that
you have been looking at a rather narrow
view of innovation, and you're missing
out on about 95% of what you can do.
Here's what I mean. If you two have been
thinking about finding the disruptive
idea or about applying some step-by-step
innovation recipe like try, fail, rinse,
repeat, that sounds like something we
may ask a robot to do. You are missing
out. There is more you can do. Humans
make for terrible robots, but we make
great Leonardo da Vinces. Leonardo did
not seem to pay attention to some
difference between the humanities, the
arts, engineering. He treated the world
around him as his lab and he invented
technologies, water pumps, flying
machines, painting techniques to make
that world work another way. These
videos present a whole new way to think
about innovation. Innovation understood
as making problems go away with
technology as a tool. To get you there,
we'll give you tips for how to imagine
and make ideas tangible the way
generations of creative engineers have.
In the videos, you learn that one
technology can lead to many ventures.
That you do not need to paint every
problem as a catastrophe. That ideas
look different at the start. The best
ideas look rather bad. You learn that
what the real garage culture looks like.
How to fund innovation for impact. To
prototype problems, not products, and to
progress by being wrong. It may feel
counterintuitive at first. Some of my
students start out thinking the content
is a bit contrarian. But as you watch
it, you'll see it is easy and
straightforward. It only feels
counterintuitive because we train our
entire lives to carry out jobs
robotically and to try to be right at
every step. You are not a robot. This
mindset for innovating has helped many
of my students start new, highly
innovative companies. Our MIT class and
program has proven quite successful at
moving technology into the world. You
are in the company of thousands of MIT
students.