good evening everybody my name is Tom
olich I'm the associate director for
science Communications here at the Bro
Institute and it's my pleasure to
welcome you all to this evening's broad
Discovery series talk if you're joining
us for the first time uh the broad
Discovery series explores the genetic
and biological roots of human health and
disease the mechanisms that govern how
our cells and our bodies function new
technologies that are redefining what's
possible in science and the progress
that is being made to translate new
discoveries into treatment
for common and rare diseases I'm excited
tonight to bring to the stage Lloyd bod
Lloyd is a cancer immunologist an
associate member here at the broad
Institute in the claran cell
Observatory a principal investigator in
the CR Family Center for Cancer Research
at Massachusetts General Hospital and an
assistant professor of medicine at
Harvard Medical School through his
research Lloyd and his colleagues are
asking how we might better harness the
cancer fighting prowess of the immune
system and tonight he's going to take us
on a tour of the immune system and also
give us a sneak peek into what it is
that his lab is been working on it's a
couple of housekeeping notes before I
bring them on stage uh if you have any
questions for Lloyd I encourage you to
raise your hand and flag down one of our
mic Runners doing the Q&A portion of
this evening if you're watching us
online I'll be keeping an eye on YouTube
chat so if you type your questions in
there I'll do my best to try to work you
into the discussion during the
Q&A if you're a Brody or a scientist
with a deep technical question about
Lloyd's research I'm going to encourage
you to please talk to him during the uh
the reception so that members of the
community have an opportunity to ask
their questions uh during the Q&A and
lastly there is a reception I invite you
all in the room to join us in the broad
Discovery Center right outside of the
auditorium right after tonight's talk
and I encourage you to explore the
Museum's exhibits and interactive
elements Lloyd over to you
[Applause]
hi everyone can you hear me
well thank you Tom for the kind
introductions it's a really pleasure for
me to be here to actually kick off the
broad Discovery series um you know I'm
an immunologist as as Tom mention
actually and I I find this initiative
actually critical to diffuse a bit about
the science because there is always this
disconnect between what we do in the
labs and actually how we diffuse the
science to the to the broad audience and
I will bring you to a tour about um
Immunology which has been my passion for
more than than 10 years now actually
that not that I
realize and
so first what is in the name Immunology
stand for the science of the of the
immune system or the science of immunity
immunity comes from the Latin immunitas
which actually comes from the freedom
from OB obligations or privilege so you
can see it as a sort of exemption from
diseases or protection from diseases
disase everything is in the
terminology so
today I start to ask you a questions why
should we care about immunology and I
will involve you actually in the room so
and you can raise your hand to answer me
how many of you know someone with an
with an allergy any
allergy almost everyone in the room
right how many of you know someone with
that got the flu or got any infection
infectious disease almost all the room
and I could go on if I ask you about
autoimmunity there might be less hands
but there are still many I can do the
same and it's unfortunate about cancer
unfortunately many of us know someone
that had cancer the link between all of
these diseases is actually that all of
them involve the immune system either in
a good way or in a bad way and why
should we care about Immunology because
we need to understand how the immune
system works to face these diseases and
to tackle them better why because most
of these diseases actually are
exponentially increasing over the past
years and I will keep it will keep
increase actually in the future you can
see in Orange the allergies are
increasing the autoimmune diseases the
cancer but you can note here actually
that the green line here shows the
infectious diseases and we do a pretty
good job about that because of our way
of living we have a pretty hygienic way
of life we are pretty protected against
bacterial infections or viral infections
but if you look at this timeline it
stops at 2020 and we know what happened
in 2020 right so we are not entirely
protected against infectious diseases so
today my talk will be a five course menu
about how the immune system is uh
composed of and how the immune system is
actually playing a role in diseases but
also in normal functions of our body so
I will briefly have an historical
perspective about the immune system then
we will go together through the basics
of the immune system I will show you I
will highlight how it's not only related
to diseases that the immune system have
also Ro in normal functions in our daily
life and we will focus of course on how
the immune reactions uh to cancer occurs
and is is taking
place and then I will give you briefly
some insights about what our lab is
doing and the angle that we are taking
to tackle cancer so first is to
perspectives Immunology has been studied
for centuries there are so many
discoveries related to Immunology many
Nobel prices and instead of going
through each one of the discoveries I
want to guide you through main concepts
related to
Immunology the first concept is related
to immune
defense and from the ancient
Greece to the vaccines against MPX to
Pastor's gy germ Theory there is this
concept of the immune system is our
natural defense against bacterial or
viral threats and that's there to
protect us against these
threats then this pretty good actually
uh defense defense system
could also backfire and attack our own
body that the emergence of the this type
of disease that we called autoimmune
diseases and
another concept that actually took place
back then is the concept of immune
tolerance how the immune system is
actually educated to not attack our own
body our own
self then more recently over the past 50
years I would say and that and this is
still
ongoing we go more into a concept of
immune networks actually the immune
system is interconnected with our other
systems the nervous system the endocrine
system the metabolic systems and the
immune system actually can perceive
receive signals from the environment and
respond to these signals one of the key
example here is the checkpoint molecules
the immune checkpoints where the immune
system can receive signals from the
environment and that can completely
change the function of the immune system
and I will talk about a little bit about
the checkpoints later on because that
change Cancer Care uh
nowadays so the basics of the immune
systems and the immune system is quite
quite
complex it is um it is it could be a
mess because it's a it's a I would say a
network a node of multiple different
Pathways different cell types different
intricacies that are uh melting together
but we could break it down in three main
aspects the first aspect which is what I
call behavioral immunity this is kind of
of our consciousness of avoiding danger
you know when we see a fire we avoid the
fire and this is kind of our immune
response to to protect ourself when it's
cold right like today we accumulate
layers actually to not get flu or to not
get a cold or something like this and
also when we have a bad smell we also
have a reaction towards the bad smell
that also protective effect this is kind
of the the first layer of immunity which
is just the behavioral
immunity the other aspect the second
aspect is more anatomical or
physiological which is really an example
is that is our skin actually represent a
physical barrier that protect Invaders
that goes into through our body another
example also that is on this slide is
the stomach that is highly acidic that
can destroy everything everything that
goes through it most of the
time so beyond the behavior beyond the
physical barrier the immune system is
then composed of cells
and of produ product of the cells the
soluble molecules that the cells can can
produce and here again it could be
divided into two main kingdoms as the
imun immunologist like to say the innate
versus the adaptive immunity the
Adaptive is more the acquired one the
Adaptive One is actually seen in the
Jord vertebrates and this is something
that we have in similar uh to the Sharks
for
instance so the innate immune system is
supposed to be our first line of defense
that is fast but
non-specific the Adaptive immune system
is supposed to be is composed of te-
cells which contain the kiler t- cells
that we will see return that are the
ones that kill cancer cells and also of
B cells another lineage of this of this
Kingdom the adaptive
immunity takes longer to kick in but can
recognize specifically the Target and
destroy it and remember it later on so
that confer us a a stronger response in
the
future and you can see that there are
two layers the cellular layer on the top
of the slid where we have the cells
involved in the innate immunity and the
cells involved in the adaptive
immunity but then these cells produce
also factors small molecules in the
innate compartment some of and and we
call this this I would say non cellular
immune system as humoral the innate
humoral response contain factors such as
antimicrobial peptides which are our own
antibiotics basically and we can
directly eliminate bacteria by producing
this antimicrob peptides on the other
hands we have also antibodies which are
produced by B cells that you will see
later on in a few slides which are
highly specific and if you have to
remember something from this slide is
really that the innate
is nonspecific but quite fast within 0
to four hours and the adaptive
immunity is highly specific you have the
concept of memory when you can remember
the the threat later on but it's slower
it takes four to 14 days to kick to kick
in now let's do a little bit of
philosophy the root of of immunity in
general is about one simple question how
do you see
yourself because the basic role of the
immune system is to recognize what is
supposed to be there the self or what's
not supposed to be there the nonself and
this distinction is kind of essential to
understand the immune system basically
how it works to really make this
distinction how the immune system does
that I will give you one examples I
mentioned the antibodies in in the
previous
slides the antibodies have been have
this extreme ability to precisely
recognize the self versus the
nonself they are small proteins which
have two different portions a
recognition arm that is depicted here
and effector function the effector
function is basically when they
recognize something that is not supposed
to be there it needs to be discarded and
the effector portion of the antibody
will allow the ability of other cells to
pick them up and discard what is not
supposed to be there and I will
highlight one of the study that shows
how specific they
are this is an example of a paper that
was published in 1987 so quite old um
not too old and they were the the the
researchers were looking at calcitonin
so calcitonin is a normon that controls
your calcium level in your blood stream
and what they found and this is the
chemical structure of calcitonin that is
depicted here
what they identified they found an
antibody that can recognize
calcitonin and they predicted that this
antibody that they called
C7 could recognize this portion of
calcitonin but to really test if it was
that much specific what they
did they changed the molecule they
remove this portion here nh2 which is an
amine domain they swap it for an hydroxy
domain
o they tested again this antibody
against this molecule but it was not
able to bind at all so this is really
showing how precise and specific are
antibodies this notion of precis and
specificity made something that we call
nowadays monoclonal antibodies so it's
basically an antibody that Target a a
unique specific molecule the discovery
and all the studies around monoclonal
antibodies obtained the Nobel Prize in
in
1984 by Jan ker and and
milstein and it opened a whole world it
completely changed the face of biom
medicine we use antibodies nowadays in
90% of the lab of the research lab and
90% of the clinical labs to either see
ourselves to treat our patients we use
antibodies every day in our daily life
as a researcher at least so antibodies
really uh change the face of biom
medicine so I mentioned a lot about
diseases and it's a defense mechanism
the immune system is really our our our
defense but then more and more that we
could understand the immune system the
components of the immune system we could
also realize that the immune system
could play other roles Beyond just
diseases here I don't know if you can
see um this is a review that is that was
published in 2018
where the ARs basically summarize what
are the non- disease function of the
immune system here depicted in
blue and we could find in the literature
that the immune system can regulate
basic functions such as how we burn fat
for example they regulate thermogenesis
in the white adipose tissues or the
brown tissues as well they regulate
the heart functionality they regulate
how we generate our muscles how we
regenerate our muscles the system also
controls how the motility of our gut and
these are functions basic functions that
are routinely in involving the immune
system in their actions and for me one
of the mindblowing example and I will I
will show you one of the the paper after
the slides is the recognition that the
immune system can even control our own
behavior and our social behavior you you
remember the beginning of few slides I
mentioned that our Consciousness
provides a behavioral
immunity but now it's more the
retroaction of the immune system on our
behavior and this is a growing
literature where they actually recognize
that this is happening uh uh most of the
times so one example is this paper
published in 2016 in the journal Nature
where the ARs interrogated the role of
interon gamma interon gamma is a the
small molecule produced by the immune
system mostly T cells or the kiler T
cells that regulate viral infections or
that plays a huge role in cancer as well
and to test the role of interfering
gamma on the social behavior they use a
pretty interesting model it's called the
three chamber sociability
assay in this assay they have a box they
put a mouse into the box the box has
three chambers that are interconnected
with these openings that you see
here on the left chamber and the right
chamber you have separate
cages within the
box and at the beginning they let the
mouse go and discover the Box itself and
move between the right and the left
Chambers after a while they would
introduce either another mouse in the
left chamber or an object in the right
chamber for instance and you you can
directly understand the system it's
pretty simple if the mouse is pretty
social it should spend more time with
the other Mouse right and if there is no
social aspect if the mouse doesn't
really care the mouse would spend as
much time in any chamber right and M are
like humans they are quite social
actually they spend twice much time with
the Other M compared to the object in a
normal
situation however
without interfering gamma that the
molecule that they
investigated then these mice lost
completely their social behavior which
shows that one single molecule produced
by the immune system can control the
whole social behavior of of these
animals so beyond just diseases we have
also this interconnection between this
these two different systems and the
immune systems will I'm I'm pretty sure
will teach us many more about our social
child behaviors and more about our
Consciousness as
well so now let's dive into the role of
the immune reactions to
cancer
so I put the title here is about the
cancer immunity cycle that has been
recognized for the past 50 years I have
to say that these mechanisms is actually
true which is for in um for infectious
diseases for allergy uh for autoimmunity
this will be the same kind of
cycle and the cycle is composed of four
different
steps the first steps is the fact that
the immune system is there patrolling
throughout our body to find what is not
supposed to be there right so the first
step is really to identify cancer cells
that would not look quite right right
there would be subtle differences that
would make the cancer cells becoming
different than than the normal cells and
these immune cells would then recognize
the ID card of the of the tumor cells of
the cancer cells this is the greatest
prettiest picture of of tumor
cells then once these immune cells would
recognize the would get the ID card of
these cancer cells they would then
migrate to an immune organ such as a
lymph nod or the
spleen and they would present this ID
card to the immune cells resid there
either the T cells or the B cells in
that case in the case of cancer they
really want to show this ID card to the
killer T cells right this step the
second step of this of the cycle is
called the immune priming we called a a
a primed immune cells when the immune
cells is conscious that there is a
threat to
attack once the cells are primed then
they can migrate within the two more
tissue and and do their job of D showing
cancer cells right
and I give you one example so this is a
microscopy picture of immune cells that
are heing green surrounding two more
cells that I don't know if you can see
the color is supposed to be purple and
that are doing their job of destroying
the cancer cells and this is how in
theory it should happen and you will
tell me so Lloyd if the immune system
was so great why cancer is still a thing
right and you're right
there is a mechanism that is a sort of
double edge sword where by being so
effective of recognizing and destroying
cancer cells the immune system also
provokes something called immunological
sculpting this
concept has three phases the first one
is the job is done quite well the first
part the first phase is the elimination
phase the immune system recognize and
Destroy most of the cancer cell
however in the subsequent stage
sometimes they can be
outnumbered and then they could they
could actually maximize their effect
they destroy most of the cancer cells
but there are still some that are
remaining this is called the equilibrium
phase and in that phase it's really kind
of keeping a wild animal into a cage so
you can control the growth you can
contain the wild animal but it's still
there right
and what is happening during this phase
the imation phase is that some cancer
cells can actually learn how to overcome
the immune attacks and out grow and
develop into real tumors that are on the
right of of of the slides which which is
called The Escape phase or the evasion
phase of the immune system and you can
you can relate it to a sort of Darin
Evolution uh concept where the cancer
cells would evolve to adap adapt to the
immune attacks to actually survive and
this is really similar mechanism that
are occurring
here then in that case here why then the
immune system wouldn't be able to still
attack these cells what are the
mechanism of evasion that makes the the
the tumor so resistant to the attacks
and there are different strategies that
the cancer cells have actually to evade
the immune system I will highlight two
of them uh uh uh here today
one is that the cancer cells can become
invisible completely invisible they can
hide from the immune system how do they
do that I don't know if there are some
Game of Thrones fans in the room they
can actually build a wall surrounding
them they can corrupt the cells around
around them to make them build the wall
surrounding the tumor tissue and this is
not fantasy I can show you an actual
microscopy example this is a l tumor in
blue in the middle you can see the
cancer cells in red here you have the
fibers of fibronectin that are really
building this wall around the cancer
cells and the immune cells in green here
you can see them they're stuck within
outside of the tumor tissue it just
cannot get there in that case the tumors
is completely invisible and the immune
system cannot do anything so that's one
of the evasion mechanism that is quite
striking on this image here another
strategy is even though the immune cells
can get there cancer cells can become
highly
resistant and I we that there are many
resistance mechanism but one of the key
resistance mechanisms is depicted in
this cartoon here remember this uh this
this slide when I showed this cancer
cell surrounded by immune cells that
tried to to to destroy it what could
happen is cancer cells can also hijack
one of the normal uh functions of the
immune
systems called hijacking the checkpoint
molecules so in the first panel of the
cartoon the t- cells in blue here which
I don't know why there are archers in
that case um have the ID card of the
cancer cells in their hands and they're
supposed to attack them however the
cancer cells can fight back by using
pdl1 which is the baseball B baseball
bat
and Target pd1 on the surface on the
head of the t- cells this would
completely dysmantle t- cells it would
be dysfunctional and then the tumor can
then evade the immune system again here
instead of a Caron I wanted to show you
what is actually when we look at it in
situ when we look at at a human tumor by
giving an example of colcy
cancer in pink here are the cancer cells
and in the light blue you can see see
the immune cells the first thing that
you see in this microscopy image is that
again you can have a sense of the wall
that the immune cells right seems to be
stuck outside of the tumor tissue right
so you have also this so none of them
are actually separated they can all
converge and be in play in the same time
if we zoom on one of the region for
example here in this region when we can
see that there are some immune cells
that could get there
right what we see I don't know if you
can actually see that nicely here it's
all of these cells in orange or red as
you can see Express pdl1 so the bat is
there even though they made it there
they could get through the tumor tissue
they still are completely dysfunctional
because the PDL one is expressed highly
on the surface of the cancer cells and
that dismantled their function so this
is an active mechanism of resistance by
the cancer cells that really can avoid
the immune
destruction but what can we do if there
are so many different strategies of
invisibility of resistance how can we
actually boost the immune response to
the context of cancer and what are the
strategies that we can do in clinic
nowadays there are three main therapies
so therapies that affect the immune
system are called immunotherapies so I
we use this terminology for the rest of
my talk so cancer immunotherapies have
have three kinds one is modulating this
checkpoint the signals that actually
inhibit the immune system one strategy
is if the the immune cells are
outnumbered then let's just put more so
it's a strategy of actually overcoming
the the the low amount of immune cells
in the tumor tissue and the last
strategy is something that has been
around from the beginning of the world
of Immunology is making cancer vaccines
so actually preparing the immune system
to recognize better cancer cells to
destroy them even before they would
outgrow and become a real tumor it's
really trying to stop a fire before it
spreads a small fire before it
spreads I will give you one example of
each strategies the first one is uh
immune checkpoint blockade
therapy where in this cartoon again here
you can see pretty simply that the
strategy is just if the cancer cells can
use the bat against the t- cells the
killer T cells let's just put a helmet
on these cells and then they will be
protected and you know what that
works that actually works by adding this
helmet the pd1 checkpoint blockade we
would actually protect the T cells from
being uh uh inhibited by cancer cells
and allow them to work better and then
they can they can again fight
cancer this strategy got the most recent
Immunology Nobel price in 2018 by G
Madison and tasuku honjo but I also want
to highlight people that were also
involved in the discoveries leaping
chain in Yale but also two broes that
are also part of the
community Gordon Freeman and Arin Shar
because these type of therapies were
really GameChanger in Cancer Care some
cancers that were completely and
treatable with chemotherapy the standard
of care when now actually had some hope
because of this immun checkpoint
blockade
therapies the second aspect is also
quite simple in in the reasoning right
it's just there is not enough immune
cells let's just put more one of the
strategy actually is uh uh is highly
clever is using the best of both world
we know there are these killer T cells
that are highly efficient of of
recognizing
remembering and killing cancer cells but
we know also that antibodies have this
highly precise and specific way of
recognizing what is not supposed to be
there right so let's just combine them
let's just put an antibody on the
surface of te- cells this is called car
te cell therapies and the principle is
that we would take tea cells from
patients we would genetically add the
recognition portion of the antibody on
the surface of this t says the car we
would multiply them in vitro and then
put them back to the patient and that
would actually enhance the recognition
of cancer cells and also enhance the
killing aspects this C cell therapy
completely cured some cancers some
lymphoma were completely cured than to
the carticel therapies for
example the other strategies is still
controversial nowadays I have to say it
has been around for decades and decades
and decades but they were not pretty
effective 50 years
ago the cancer vaccines I took this
Magazine review that was published in
2004 so 20 years ago and back then they
were already questioning if it if it is
a hype or a hope
and I have to say for the past 20 years
the results were not quite right however
since 5 years since 20 everything
changed and you will understand why
there are so many different literatures
that are like Reviving The Field of
cancer vaccines because of specific new
uh strategies new uh I would say tools
to improve cancer vaccines highlight I
highlighted in in in green or in in
yellow some names which are basically
the names of uh the researchers behind
biotechn and mod
we all know that uh with covid vaccines
uh the the way the the new methodology
behind vaccines could actually bring
more hope into cancer
vaccines right now and there are some
recent clinical trials that show that
some cancer vaccine are highly effective
in cancers that were completely
Refractories to any therapies such as
pancreatic cancer for example here
because of all of these years of
strategies understanding better how the
immune system works understanding the
cancer immunity cycle understanding the
different components of the immune
system it finally got to place as a one
of the five pillars of cancer treatment
and Cancer Care originally there was
only surgery that was feasible for those
patients then there was the emergence of
radiotherapy or chemotherapy that is
still heavily used these two then became
the world of targeted therapies and
immunotherapies despite the fact that
that immunotherapies could change Cancer
Care
nowadays uh is still quite limited I
have to say we are still at the
beginning of the Revolution regarding
immunotherapies and I will give one
example
here this is a Klan Meer curve so this
is a survival curve for the one the the
the people that are not really used to
these curves this is basically showing
the survival of the patients over
time between three different groups I is
a patient that got two different types
of immunotherapy neolab or epab which
are just different types of helmets
basically the green and the blue and the
red is basically adding the two helmets
on top of each
others because the rational again here
was maybe we can improve the protection
by having two helmets at the same time
and you can see that it works actually
by adding only epil mumab we got 27 so
31 patient out of three actually
responded pretty well and survived well
to the therapist by adding this helmet
in blue it's actually more effective one
patient out of two but combining both
gave rise to almost 60% of the patient
that would respond well and and had
survival benefit with
immunotherapies but these numbers also
mean that 40% in that case would fail to
respond to
immunotherapies and we have to
understand also that immunotherapies the
principle is quite simple it's boosting
our own our own immune defense right our
own defense so why 40% of the patient
will not respond well and this is by the
combination therapy but here half of the
patient do not respond at all and here
70% of the patient do not respond at all
it's always nice to look at the numbers
the other way around
and the goal is really to understand why
immunotherapies are not applicable to
everybody and also what can we do to
improve therapeutic
efficacy and right now most of the field
has been focusing on the helmets so
basically trying to make fancier helmets
heavier helmets combining different
helmets but the numbers are not
improving just by trying to put more
helmets on the surface of the cells and
the field is more recognizing that the
immune system is more complex of course
that we have seen earlier but is is not
only composed of killer T cells and
cancer cells the Killer and the target
there is more complexities and more
different flavors of immune cells can we
harness these other immune cells
actually here I switch gears I showed
you lung cancer then coloral cancer here
it's an image of melanoma skin cancer a
type of skin cancer the cancer cells are
depicted here in green and blue and in
Gray are all the other cells in the
environment and here on this the same
image then I highlighted these other
cells and to show you what they are you
can see that the kiler T cells are the
cells in light blue you have one here
you have one
here but you can see also Bur bunch of
other cells right B cells in red
depicted here the one producing
antibodies helper T cells and another
type of the cells in Orange here here
and here and also microf fages microf
fages are the immune cells that are from
the innate uh part of immunity that just
eats everything so they are they are
super efficient there when you have uh
destroyed cancer cell to actually clear
the place and discard the the the
actually the dead canc cells so it's
more complex and the question around
that is can we try to change the
environment to provide the kiler T cells
a more supportive environment and not
trying to make them work harder faster
better it's also a philosophical concept
about how we would treat our trainers
nowadays at the same
time so I will give you now some
insights about the lab because this is
kind of the core of our research is
trying to find to find a new angle to
tackle cancer the angle we chose is to
leverage B cells the other immune cells
from the Adaptive uh Kingdom that are
producing these
antibodies and these are the cells at
the beginning they look like these cute
cells that could be useless and then
when they get angry they produce all of
these different antibodies that are
highly
specific why should we care about B
cells it because they are everywhere and
in all the cancers as possible on this
plot um this figure you have each colon
represent one different cancer types so
you have 29 different cancer types in
Gray each tack are different immune
cells in purple I highlighted the B
cells and you can see that they are
present everywhere in each one of
different cancer
cells however the way we look at this is
this is nice this is correlative they
are there but how can we predict their
function in these different cancers a
simple way is to look to relate the
abundance of the cells and the outcome
of the patient to look into the more a
patient have B cells how does that
change the survival of the
patient and this is a summary here
because this is quite controversial in
the context of B cells in some cancer
types
such as breast lung or skin cancer the
more a patient has Bell the better it is
for the Survivor they survive much
better in some cancers there is just no
effect that's the case of brain colon or
kidney cancer you can have like more or
less B cells that doesn't change at all
the survival of the patients and in some
other cancers such as adenoid or
pancreatic it's actually the other way
around the more you have bells the worse
it is for your
prognosis so this controvers could be
explained by the different flavors of B
cells that are found in these cancers
maybe that's not the same type of B
cells in that tumor then that tumor then
that tumor and that might explain why
you have these discrepancies there might
be bad versus good B cells and that's
kind of the core of the lab to identify
these different flavors of B cells and
then test
them another philosophical question for
you to be or not to be this this is the
core question of the lab and I hope we
are
B the lab is really trying to understand
the Mosaic of the flavors of B cells
within cancers in all the different
cancers that can help us to identify
actually the the good bells and the bad
Bells the goal would be really to find
the one that can promote two more
control to keep the tumor in check and
the one that can promote tum more growth
again the good versus bad bells and how
can we actually Define them what do we
do with this information when we have
identified by bad or good B cells the
goal would be to then Target them to
find checkpoints like have been found
for T cells in B cells and that's the
second big aim of the lab big goal of
the lab and we were fortunate to have
dive into B cells that much in melanoma
coloral cancer lung cancer or breast
cancer
that we could find some molecules that
could promote good B cells and could
inhibit bad B cells and we are
continuously working about these
molecules nowadays I will give you one
example of one of them that we recently
discovered that is called team one that
is a molecule that is spef it's it's
it's an equivalent of the pd1 on T cells
that I've shown earlier where when this
molecule is blocked on B cells then the
tum more can be
grow this could offer an
opportunity to tackle this other angle
of the immune system by harnessing and
exploiting B cell
functionality so this could lead to more
promises in in in cancer because instead
of adding helmets we would add one
helmet and maybe also boosting another
immune cells to combat cancer
better beyond all of
this what we find when we analyze so
many different flavor of bers would be
also uh
biomarkers and this is really something
also that we are investigating in the
lab one of the key goal of these types
of analysis is to identify cancer
fingerprints imagine if we can predict
if an individual will develop cancer
imagine if we can uh actually predict if
a patient will respond or not to
immunotherapy that would be key
component to help for the diagnosis or
actually for the management of these
patients and to do this we study
antibodies that are produced by B cells
and we recently collaborated with a team
in San Francisco at
UCSF where what we did is we profiled
antibody in over 700
individuals these individuals were
either lung cancer patients
at risk of developing lung cancer but
asymptomatic so far and healthy
individuals then we developed an AI
model that could accurately distinguish
if a patient had cancer or was healthy
and we could with this tool efficiently
be able to improve potentially the
diagnosis of this patient with lung
cancer and we hope to expand this type
of analysis to any kind of cancer the
first stage was identifying cancer
versus not cancer so what's supposed to
be there or was not supposed to be there
the self and the nonself but later on
the goal will be really to identify the
ones that would respond or not respond
to imuno theapy to chemotherapy to
radiotherapy and so on that could really
help the management of of of of cancer
patients so this is the core of the
lab I'm good I'm not too late and as
conclusive notes I would say that the
immune system are like ants this is how
I see the immune system to me I see as a
highly highly
organized Melting Pot of different ants
that serve the same goal that works
together that could be
dangerous sometimes right but at the
same times that would uh have these
intricacies that makes them to to
overcome many different
challenges and there are still
challenges in cancer immunotherapies I
mentioned some of them earlier that
there are not every patient is actually
responding to
immunotherapies and I wanted to finish
on the key future challenges for cancer
immunotherapies obviously we need to
improve the response we need to find why
the patient do not respond and improve
the
response this also implicate that we
need to understand the resist resistance
mechanisms I give you two example the
invisibility or just the basic
resistance with checkpoints but how can
we alleviate this resistance that's
something that we really need to
understand
better most of the field right now is
focusing on the resistance they are
trying to add elmets to make the cells
work better faster and be more
aggressive but you know the immune
system is also dangerous as I mentioned
like the ants
because if you boost it too much it
could go Rogue and provoke toxicities
and even autoimmune reactions right so
at the same time that we try to improve
response to alleviate resistance we also
need to avoid
toxicity as an example is in
numbers man's General Hospital and and
and Bram and Women's Hospital treat over
4,000 patients per year with
immunotherapy out of the 4,000 patients
if they were treated with a single
agent only one single helmet for example
seven out of 10 patient would develop
toxicity but fortunately only one out of
10 would develop severe
toxicity however if you combine
immunotherapies the two helmet that
provide the most response the 60%
response then nine out of 10 patients
would develop toxicities which is a huge
number and half of them would would
develop severe toxicity
so really the the the goal would not be
to add helmets on these cells would be
many to find other angles to to improve
the response right avoiding
toxicities so we recently joined the
forces of a Pioneer in the field of
toxicities Chloe villani that is
depicted here with Will and and David
Ting and we formed this new project
called protect which stands for
promoting response to oo immunologic
therapies while erad ating toxicities
the goal of this project now we we we
actually bridged our forces to
understand the components of the
resistance the components of the
response but also the components of what
makes makes it toxic to alleviate this
toxicity these immune reactions so wish
us luck for
that so overall these are my my last
slides to learn more about Immunology
which is really uh uh an amazing field
to learn more about you can go onto the
different soci societies so the American
societies of immunologist or the
international Society of immunologist
some of the cartoons that I have shown I
took them from uir which is a great
resource to explain immunotherapies to
the Le audience and every April 29th is
the uh International Immunology day and
there are many events across town and in
the world so please look out for that
and then if you have kids or teenagers I
highly s recommend this book that exist
in many languages about the immune
system and that's kind of a fantastic
resource and you have the QR code here
to to download it with this I really
want to thank you for your attention um
here is my lab that is between the broad
and and my general hospital and then we
recently won uh the lab Olympics last
summer and what we we won because of
what because we had the best slogan
which was let it
be one last slide um about some recent
events you know in research or In Clinic
Cancer Care and all of these therapies
and all of these studies wouldn't exist
wouldn't actually be happening without
the infrastructure and especially the
administrative infrastructure so I want
to take the opportunity today also to
acknowledge them both at MGB Harvard or
also at the broad that without them I
wouldn't be standing here today and the
advancement in the field wouldn't have
happened at the same time thank you for
your attention that was a pleasure to be
with you
tonight thank you so much Lloyd now if
you had told me ahead of time that April
29th was International Immunology day we
would have scheduled the talk for then
mhm true if you have any questions the
mics are yours uh we have a couple of
mic Runners here who are um here to hand
things up but before we actually dive
into the the audience questions I would
just want to ask you a question really
quickly Lloyd can you just describe real
quickly your your career path um how did
you get interested in Immunology in
cancer and how did you come to be at the
bir and at MGH yeah um so it's it's it's
a it's it's a interesting pass I when I
was a teenager I grew up in martinic
that's a small French island in car you
can you could tell from the my first
sentence that I was French right my
accent I cannot hide it that well um and
I grew up in in in Martin and I was
always interested by surgery actually I
went into a mdphd program in Paris and I
did many many surgeries then I remember
that class when they were teaching
immunology and that completely snapped
my brain
I was so fascinated about all the
different possibilities and complicities
of Immunology so I decided to move on
and do a PhD in immunology and so on and
so on and then uh my uncle uh developed
melanoma Advanced metastatic
melanoma and he got in 2012 he got uh
actually in a complete remission uh with
anti C4 on tpd1 so the the two helmets
that I've shown earlier and that
actually prolong is is life for 10 more
years and that also is why I decided to
focus on on cancerology and moved here
to develop my program and to make better
helmets yeah
exactly uh I think we had a question
right down the front here yeah so so my
question is um about the immune system
and what happens to it during pregnancy
oh great question so remember about the
the concepts the defense the tolerance
the the pregnancy is a is a such an
example because the fetus is actually
quite not exactly self it should be
the mother self right but it's half of
the father self so the immune system is
actually trying to attack it because it
recognize it as something that is not
supposed to be there which is not self
so again here the immune system learns
how to tolerate the fetus and allow the
fetus to grow and that that mechanism is
really about I use a lot of terms that
are used in the society like education
the immune system then get educated to
tolerate the fetus and let them grow
that's a great
question question over here yes uh can
you hear me yeah yes so you you talked
about hygiene and innate immunity right
so I have a two-part question one is is
too much hygiene a bad thing and number
two isn't cancer a last 50e
environmental you know thingy that's
come up now and we're all trying to work
on it and figure out what's going on
yeah and it wasn't there many years ago
yeah so for the first part of your
question it's actually a good point um
there is in there was in the 1970 the
hygiene theory meaning that the more we
are protected against infections the
more we are weakened and the more we the
immune system doesn't know what to
protect ourselves from so it start to
attacking ourselves and this is the
hygiene Theory which could be the case
in in some cases and there are studies
unfortunately in the statistics that do
not show that the hene theor is tense
but this is theories that are out there
in the case of cancer you know with the
numbers increasing over the past years
and so on since the 198 to now so it's
not entirely fair to say that they
increase it's also that we diagnose them
much better we have the Technologies
nowadays to diagnose so efficiently
cancer at the Single Cell of cancer that
a patient has or to diagnose allergy
very quickly so the tools change so we
see more of them maybe also because we
have the tools to see them uh more often
but what you said is also right that the
way of life the new environmental change
es the the pollution the diets and so on
are also factors that provoke cancer
more efficiently one of the saddest part
of it is that usually cancer is seen is
elderly populations but nowadays we see
more into uh young people and these
young un set cancers are now a question
about why do they rise so fast and
actually they also more aggressive in
the young populations so you're totally
right these also are questions about the
way of
life actually while the mic is making
its way so you mentioned t- cells a lot
Yeah you mentioned B cells a lot yeah
are there other cells within the immune
system um that also play a role in in
cancer surveillance in in in attacking
cancers yeah totally so I mention a lot
T cells and B cells because at the end
these are the only cells that can carry
this memory and you know this feature of
the immune system to remember the threat
is kind of what we really need to go to
go after to prevent the occurrence of
cancer later on but you're totally right
there are other cells in the innate
Kingdom of the immune system that are
highly affected to I mentioned the
microf fages that's really helpful to
actually clear out cancer cells but you
have also a cell type that has a name
prol which is natural killer cells and
their function is to kill the basic
function they will not check the
specificities they will not have the
memory aspects they will just have a on
and off R of killing and not killing and
this has play also an important role in
cancer Yeah question over here hello it
was really interesed talk and I want to
ask about what technologies are
currently uh Innovative to understand
better the relationship between uh all
the types of immune cells and also if
you think like because you lab like
trans omic that you also do like uh
research on on that like uh how do you
approach approach yeah so uh thank you
for that question some of the key
Technologies were actually from the
broad and they Revolution the world of
research nowadays again monoclonal
antibodies were the first phase of
Revolution and the genomics field were
also the second phase of Revolution now
we can understand at a high depth each
single genes each single proteins that
are produced by each single cells of the
body which is too many data but with
this if we have a focus question then we
can actually leverage these Technologies
to understand better the relationship
between cells and also there are
different flavors there are continuity
so the dynamic over time before therapy
after therapy and this is something that
we leverage here the genomics aspect a
lot in the lab at the broad and at
MGH thank you thank you I could just
repeat the questions of the people
watching online yeah the questions is
related to how T cells and what what T
cells recognize if all T cells recognize
the same thing or you have different
divers T cells that recognize different
things and then how they grow and then
you touch on on on also unique feature
of T cells and B cells which is that
when they know what they should should
recognize and they can recognize many
different
things when each one recog has a
specific Target in mind they can
actually
multiply so we call that clonal
expansion so they they expand towards a
specific targeting a specific unique
molecule and you can have multiple
different clones so they recognize
multiple different antigens that we call
which are the different targets and that
is happening for T cells and B cells yes
I'm trying to remember how many like I
know there's a number out there like a
theoretical number of how many different
targets your immune system is able to
handle it's like 10 to the to the power
of 18 it's it's really trillions and
trillions and trillions of Target the
diversity we call it the repertoire of
the immune system is so diverse and that
evolved actually across the normal
evolution of the human being to be able
to recognize so many different threats
so the diversity is also a a function of
our protection to recognize any any
flavors of B bacteries viruses cancers
that we can encounter yeah good question
question up there thank you I have a
slightly specific question for the CT
therapy how do you design the chimeric
antigen receptor like how what's the
inventory strategy to make sure it's
specific to the tumor yeah so first you
have we have to have in mind a Target we
have to have a sense of what what the
the cancer looks like right so C cell
therapy were the proof of concept was
established with
lymphoma so lymphoma is actually a
cancer of our own immune cells in the B
cell lloma that's our own B cells that
would expand in an anarchic way and
would would really become their own
tumor
right but there is something in common
is that they are B cells all of them are
B cells so they have proteins of B cells
on their surface even if they became
cancer cells right so we could arm
that's how that's how we call it
actually the car the the t- cells with
only the recognition function of the
antibody that we took from a monoclonal
antibody mount it on the surface of the
t- cells against one of the B cell
proteins and then they would kill every
B cells not only the cancer cells
actually so that's a great point because
now it's really difficult to make the
distinction between what is the ID of an
exact cancer cells or the ID of just a
normal cells can we make the distinction
between normal pancreatic cells or
pancreatic cancer cells this is really
tricky questions uh now with car T cells
it's still limited to make this
distinction but the field is moving
pretty fast toward identifying the
subtleties between the two thank you
great question one more question over
here yes when you're when you're
developing uh IM immunotherapies have
you found much commonality across
patients in the antigens you're trying
to develop uh antibodies against yeah or
is it just very individualized and even
within a single patient do you find
different clones that have different
antigens that you have H how how much
customization do you have to do or there
patterns that you that you that you yeah
now that's a great question the dream
would be to have an off offthe shelf
therapy that could work for every
patient right the helmet is kind of this
of the shell therapy then we would be
agnostic of the antigens of the type of
cancers and so on we would just give a
helmet to the T cells and they would
recognize whatever they recognize and
then kill better right however it's
still failing a lot so now the field is
more looking more into distinguishing at
an individual
level what are specif personalized to
that patient to that cancer types and
that's more related to the C therapy for
example that will evolve or also the
cancer vaccines and more and more that's
more related to the cancer vaccine phe
for immunotherapy globally it's mostly
trying just to boost the response
without having every specificity Patient
to Patient actually thank you for the
question
so last question yeah five 10 years from
now like how do you see this story of
cancer in the immune system
unfolding I think more and
more we will hopefully have the strategy
of
promoting the othero immune cells
involving the network the
interconnection between the system not
only trying try to put a helmet stronger
but really trying to understand better
when when when the tumor evaded the
immune system which cells were involved
in The Invasion where does that happen
what is happening and by understanding
unfolding all of this with the new
technologies I believe that in 5 10
years from now there will be more
combination therapies but instead of
combining on the same cell type would be
combining across different cell types
and different context
and hopefully there are many promises
but the cancer vaccines might be also
effective in 5 to 10 years fingers Quest
so Immunology day five years from now
we're getting you back on stage we're
going to see if you're right okay sounds
good thank you so much Lloyd thank you
thank you so much thank you and thank
you also to all of you in the room and
online who have been watching us tonight
uh we will let you know when our next uh
broad Discovery series will be it's
probably going to be sometime this
spring I hope you all join Jo us then
again and with that have a great night