hello everybody and welcome to our last
video at least for a while on music
representation and I want to talk about
a remarkable tool created by a
researcher at Stanford Craig Stuart Sapp
that he calls the Rosetta
Stone I'm going to be skipping a few
slides from his presentation and if
added a few other things but in this
module I will also present his entirety
of
slides that he has given and my hats off
to Craig sap for all he's done and his
generosity so the Rosetta Stone was a
stone discovered in I think 1799 and
deciphered over the next uh I 10 years
or so that was a remarkable
um Discovery because up until that point
Egyptian hieroglyphics such as those
highlighted here were not legible by
anybody living at that point but the
Rosetta Stone had two forms of Egyptian
hieroglyphics and also in the top two
sections and also at the bottom the
exact same text in Greek and so since
people knew how to read ancient Greek
they were able to go through each of the
signs of ancient Greek and figure out
what the signs of the hieroglyphics and
the two forms of writing
meant Craig saps Rosetta Stone allows us
to look at how different digital
representations of Music work by
encoding the exact same melody in I
think almost two dozen different formats
these aren't all formats that have ever
been used but it's a good chunk of them
so here's the melody and it has um some
interesting things here it has different
octaves it has uh key signature time
signature has beaming information the
only thing it really well some of the
things it doesn't have Are chords and
triplets and things like that but once
you see how this melody is encoded in a
lot of formats you can figure out how
all the other things might be encoded in
those formats
so here's an example of a code that's uh
not used as much today but was once very
important uh plain and easy code and you
can see that we have something like I
can decipher okay maybe that's a g on
clef on line two and then we have a flat
on the on b 2 four and then we have an
eighth note with a DOT on c um and then
uh I I guess the three means 302 note
DC and there's a little bracket around
it and that probably means they're beam
together then we have two eighth notes
on C beam together have slash means new
measure and so on throughout the whole
thing we can see um that oh maybe octave
isn't encoded here or um something like
that and um we can figure out how those
go here is another format this is uh
primarily used for folk songs called ABC
and we can see that um well example
maybe that's the title of the piece 24 K
is key is f l means the smallest
possible encoding is a 16th note then we
see that c is worth three of those 16th
D is worth I guess 1 half C is 1/2 C is
worth two of those that's eth note C is
worth two of those we have a bar line
and so on and we can see that the high C
is encoded with c with a um apostrophe
after
it this is what's called dar's code it
was once highly used but it hasn't
really been used very much recently
and well I don't know how to read dar's
code but uh I think that the numbers
represent pitch here we have an eth with
a DOT and t means 302 I'm guessing and
so on we have some rs's which might mean
16th note this is Guido music notation
which uses uh backslashes to indicate
certain kinds of musical elements we can
see CS Keys meters are encoded in here
uh bar lines are explicitly encoded it
looks like you put a slash before a a
beat a duration and there's some dur
notes that don't have durations but they
seem to be the same duration as before
and so on
I think it looks like underscores our
rest this is Muse data which Michael
good said was one of the um inspiration
behind music XML it's a little bit
bigger format takes more space uh it was
one of what we used to use a lot these
fixed position encodings so that if
you're writing in a monus baced font
every single place uh has a particular
meaning so you can look at column 8 or
something like that and see the duration
and then this was a a major positive
step because it encodes duration in
terms of the number of uh something the
number of 30 second notes and also
separately the the look of the duration
and so you can still see that in music
XML and formats that are still in use
today I really like the use of these uh
left and right square brackets to
indicate the start and an end of
beams humdrum is a code that we have
encountered a couple times and here it
is and maybe it's easier with humdrum to
rotate the musical examples so we can
see how things go maybe maybe not but we
can see that there's L's and J's that
represent the starts and ends of beams
and different octaves are represented by
doubling or tripling the
letter little Pond is actually a set of
macros for the scheme programming
language which is a kind of variant on
list and so you can actually write
computer code in Lily Pond and here we
have the same representation you can see
again backs slashes indicating uh starts
of larger musical elements time
signatures bar lines that are explicitly
encoded with what they look like and so
on
melisma was an interesting uh code
format that's a little bit similar to
what we might have with midi and what
we're doing here is we're encoding only
uh the numeric duration so we can say
that I guess uh
125 is a 302nd note and we can figure
out from there that 500 is an eighth
note and so on and on the far right
column we have the pitch encoded so
we're losing here
beams and some other things we we're
actually been losing the clef and the
time seure but we do have an info tag
that tells us a key
signature algro is a more compact
version the same format looks like we
have midi numbers 72 74 72 um for C DC
and so on and um I believe 64 is
encoding the velocity that is having how
loud each note is and since we haven't
encoded any Dynamics here they're all
64s and we have toward the end start and
end offsets of each note I think if we
can go through Note One 2 3 4 five 6 7 8
nine would be a rest and at 1 two 3 4
five 6 7 8 um we have there sorry we're
not doing start and end we're doing
start offset and duration and there we
have have a start offset Note 8 of 2.5
duration of one and then the next
element does not start at 3.5 but it
just starts at 3.75 so we're not even
encoding rests we're saying that they
are gaps in the
musical
format director musicus is also a list
based format I believe that's why we
have all these extra parentheses where
we're loading things into a stack and we
can see that we're encoding uh the meter
after the first note it's kind of
interesting and um 302 notes are one
over 32 that's kind of nice um the
dotted uh eighth note is 316th notes
wrong long so we see 316th can be
interesting for
ahead score has come up at least once in
class it is perhaps the best uh most
beautiful music editor ever
this is how a user might input
score and it makes it a little bit
easier to enter things you're putting
slashes between notes and so on and then
it generates an internal syntax that uh
specifies exactly where on the page
every note is and so musical engravers
really like working with score because
you can precisely move things around
probably a professional engraver would
have moved the C at the beginning of the
second measure a little bit to the right
because it's a little bit close to that
bar line and you might confuse the bar
line for a stem so score is sometimes
still used even though it hasn't been
updated in
decades this is music XML as we've seen
from Michael Good's presentation it is
uh much more verbose format um things
are uh displayed you know it takes a lot
more space to do it but music XML was
invented around the year 2000 some of
these other formats were around since
the 80s so there's a lot more space on
the hard drive well there are hard
drives now um to be able to store all
this information so here craigp has
simply highlighted the part uh one
measure in order to see how this would
work in music
XML Mei is another format you can't
really see things here but it's very
similar to music XML it's um
as we said it's the format or as Michael
good said is a format mostly used by
professional musicologists and almost
nobody else for for encoding common
western music notation I don't see it as
having advantages over music XML and in
fact uh has many disadvantages because
it's not supported by many formats but
Mei can also encode music such as
Medieval music um which uses different
representation format so it has a
particular
Niche this is a standard midi file
represented in binary and it's a little
bit unfair to compare the two because
it's a binary format so we can't really
see anything but look at what's um been
highlighted here we begin with
0090 which is the indication for a note
off so we're ending the previous note if
we go to the beginning of the next line
we can see ad0 which is the beginning of
a note on and then 4D which let's see if
I can still wear my heximal so 4 * 16 is
64 add D to that that is uh what was
that I don't know 14 13 and so you end
up somewhere around 70 uh 78 or so which
is the representation of the note F and
then the 40 after that is 64 in
um uh in in decimal and so that would be
the velocity how hard we're hitting
since velocity hasn't been encoded in
this and there's a number between 0 and
127 64 seems a pretty good number and
then we state that the note is turned
off with the 90 and we say it's turned
off after a certain amount of time so
how much time has passed and you'll see
this 51 seems to be a represent
of the length of a 16th
note if you really want to look at midi
you want to use a translator there's one
in music 21 there's one other places
that will translate this format into a
series of events like no on no offs
pitch bends and the time Deltas which
move us forward in time that will allow
you to actually give this uh particular
a fair
shape you can see also this is nith
format which has um which craigp has uh
translated some of the um some of the
hexad decimals into particular uh
letters so that we can see what they are
um somewhere in the middle of the page I
see CLA I see fing fingering I see a
font change glissant harp uh I'm not
sure that this is oh this these are just
all the things that could be in here so
we haven't even gotten to encoding the
uh the piece yet but basically niif
encodes where each shape is on the page
it is a format used by music scanners
it's not used very much anymore but the
idea is that it's much more important to
get an exact representation of what the
page looks like rather than what it
might
encode the last format which uh in this
presentation Flex outputs first isn't
really a digital format at all but is
the Braille music code which is US
encoding of music notation that was
created by Louis proud um at about the
same time that he created the text
Braille so he was really interested in
music en coding also and we can see some
parts of Braille that does encode a clef
even though it's not really used um in
the reading because we're going to
encode specific notes why encoded cleff
because um
because blind and uh visually impaired
musicians often need to talk to
musicians who have sight so it's easy to
say well you know it's in trouble clap
and there's one flat key signature and
so on um so there's a time signature and
then that's not October 5th it's octave
5 we set the octave we see that there's
a C8 we encode in augmentation dot d32
C32
c16th uh
F16 and so on and so there's um
interestingly we can usually get both
the note and the duration into a six dot
segment which would represent six b six
bits or less than a bite so it's a very
efficient encoding that makes it reading
music with your fingers very
fast if you want to know more about the
Rosetta Stone and these various musical
encodings I have also included cra saps
which I'll video thanks for watching