Hello. Thank you so much for joining us
this evening for our 2025 cohort of
women at MIT fellows. My name is Tara
Webb. I'm the women at MIT project
archist at MIT.
This fellowship that we're celebrating
today provides funding for artists,
activists, musicians, writers, and
scholars who are engaged in the
expansion and expression of knowledge to
help inform the understanding of women
in MIT's history and in the history of
science, technology, engineering, and
mathematics, particularly through the
interdisciplinary lenses and
methodologies of women's studies, gender
studies, and race and ethnic studies.
This evening we will be hearing from
Jamie McGee who wrote the interactive
hypertext novel Athena's Archive and
from Loose Capco Lincoln who created the
short film Counteracting the
Limitations.
Each fellow will present for 15 to 20
minutes and then we will have a Q&A
period at the end. Feel free to add any
questions you have to the chat or
possibly to the Q&A box that I think
that I activated um but I'm not 100%
sure. Um, closed captions are turned on
and you can select close show captions
at the bottom of the screen if you would
like. There's also an option to view the
whole transcript. This event is being
recorded and will be posted online later
on the MIT Libraries YouTube channel.
Before we get started, I'd like to give
people a brief history of the story of
MIT for people who are not familiar with
it. MIT was founded in 1861 as a moral
act land grant university, profiting
directly off this land stolen from
forcibly forcibly displaced indigenous
people in locations throughout the
United States, including what we now
call California, Kansas, and Nebraska.
The land of Massachusetts, where MIT is
located, includes unseated territories
of the Massachusett
tribal nations. MIT was originally
located in Boston's Backbay, and it
moved to Cambridge in 1916. The first
classes began in 1865 and Ellen Sweller
Richards was admitted as the first woman
student in 1870.
Since [clears throat] then, MIT has been
a home to women scientists,
mathematicians, architects, and
engineers. Women students were granted
full traditional student status in all
departments by 1883. Although notably,
despite its diverse student status,
student body, and the women of color
enrolled at the institute over the
years, the first black women to graduate
from MIT did not do so until 1968, a
little over a hundred years after its
founding. So, to start off the
presentations, I'm pleased to introduce
Jamie McGee, who is a novelist and
historian. Her books include You Mean It
or You Don't, James Baldwin's Radical
Challenge with Dr. Hollowell of Duke
University and what I must tell the
world the story of Lorraine Hanssbury
with director Lena Waist McGee's work
has been supported by Harvard University
MIT and Zurich University of the Arts.
She lives in Berlin where she instructs
graduate students at Humble University.
Jamie,
>> wonderful. Thank you for the
introduction and thank you everyone for
being here. I'm really excited to share
what I've been working on. Um, as a
disclaimer, I am currently visiting my
family in a rural part of an island. Um,
so you might hear chickens, just so you
know, just just go with it. You might
hear chickens. Um,
going to share my screen real quick.
Perfect.
So, Athena's Archive, um, is a hypertext
novel about the experience of women at
MIT.
Um, first Oh.
One moment. Sorry, it seems
Is it working now? Hold on.
Let me start over. I apologize.
Technology is fun. Um,
okay. Beautiful. Um so yes, first I want
to go over the story. Um I'll talk a
little bit about the theory of uh hyper
narrativity and hyperlinks um created by
Dr. Janet M or really developed and
forwarded by Dr. Janet Murray an MIT
professor. Um I'll look at the creation
process a couple of the difficulties and
then we'll follow up with the next
steps.
So, Athena's archive, the driving
question I had was, what was it like to
be a woman at MIT 100 years ago? As Tara
was saying, MIT has been around for um
more than a hundred years. Um, and women
have been allowed to be there for so
long, but their experiences have varied
so much both with race, ethnicity, but
then also just by decade. Um, and so
building on that, Athena's Archive is an
interactive digital novel that follows
three women attending MIT across three
different decades. Readers can interact
with the story by choosing their own
path through the text and in some cases
choosing their own ending. The
narratives are heavily based on true
stories collected through the Amida oral
history project and they build on the
narratological theories around hypertext
and interactivity as developed by MIT
professor Dr. Janet Murray.
So what is the actual story of this
novel?
It follows three different characters um
Georgie, Francine, and Shelley. Um
Geette or Georgie is a mechanical
engineer who graduated in 1922. Francine
is a chemistry major who graduated 1949.
And Shelley is a mathematician who
graduated in 1965.
And these three characters, they are
fictionalized, but they are drawn from a
lot of different accounts that were
given in the oral histories. I chose
these decades in particular um because I
wanted a broader spread of women's
experiences rather than just pick one
decade or even one year. And I thought
that this would give a really good
introduction to the experience of women
at MIT um across the early to mid 20th
century.
Specifically um I based all of these uh
these three stories on the oral history
accounts from 44 different MIT grads. Um
Amida right now has I think 121
interviews. Um, and I went through all
of them, but I ended up going with these
44 and picking vignettes. Some, uh,
people I just picked a few lines or
ideas from. Some I went more in depth.
Um, but these I do want to give credit
where credit is due. Um, these 44 women
really inspired the story.
Next, I want to just quickly go through
the three different strands. The way
that the novel is set up, um, at the
beginning, early choices will allow the
reader to take one of three different
paths to follow one of three different
characters. And then along the way,
they'll be able to make different
choices and interact with the story in
different ways. The first character
taking place 1920s is Georgie.
After World War I forces her to flee her
home in Belgium, Geette or Georgie
struggles to adjust to the United
States. The men at MIT who can't believe
there's a woman in their engineering
classes just make life worse.
A slow burning friendship with another
female student finally makes Georgie
feel at home. But when tragedy drives
them apart, will she have anywhere left
to go? That's a synopsis of her strand
of the story. And then to give a bit of
a feel about um how the text and the
textuality of the story is set up, I'll
read the opening lines from her part of
the narrative.
Home, you see, is the dead place.
When I close my eyes, home is a burnt
black spot, scorched and cracking
through the earth. It is a graveyard
with the soil still loose. It is typhus
soarses and mortal shadows and newspaper
photos I tear into little tiny pieces.
You would tear them, too.
It wasn't always this way.
The second character is Francine, who
takes place in 1949.
Born into poverty, Francine has
struggled and sweated for everything in
life. She dreams of becoming a doctor
after she graduates from MIT so that she
can finally put her financial stress
behind her.
For medical school, though, she needs
money and she'll do any odd job to get
it.
But when one final jaw becomes more
sinister than it seems, will Francine be
able to recover, or are her dreams gone
for good?
And the opening to her section is as
follows.
Regret is a luxury reserved for those
with time and money. Do I wish things
had been different? Do I wish I turned
down that last money gig? Do I wish
Harvard Medical School hadn't resended
its offer and my life hadn't gone the
way it did? Well, there's no time to
wish because I have bills to pay.
That's why I took that last gig, after
all, and why I ruined my life. I had
bills to pay.
And the final character who takes place
in the 1960s is Shelly.
This is the synopsis of her strand of
the novel.
Shelley has never been a girl's girl.
She's never had to be. As a beautiful
cultured expat, she's always turned
every head in the room and gotten
exactly what she wanted from men. It was
true overseas and now it's true at MIT.
But when the man she trusts the most is
the same man to destroy her career, she
might have to find out whether there's
truly strength in sisterhood.
the opening to her novel.
Men made me what I am. My father raised
me to be brave. My brothers trained me
to be strong. And my husband sharpened
my wit. But my mother unfortunately made
me a woman. She birthed me with this
curse. See, everything good that I am,
well, that came from men.
Well, at least that's what I thought
until the same men destroyed my life.
Now I want to go a little bit into the
underlying theories and methodologies
that I used in order to create this
interactive novel.
Specifically, I want to answer these two
questions. One, what is interactive
hyperfiction? And very closely related
to that, who is Dr. Janet Murray?
Hyperfiction uh is just a digital novel
that allows reader to traverse and
progress through a narrative via
hyperlinks rather than turned pages. So
they can generally proceed in almost any
order that they want to. They can loop
back around. They can take different
paths. They can jump from story to
story. It really allows them to have a
choice in how they want to experience a
certain story. It allows for greater
agency as well as in some cases
depending on the material greater
learning because it's been used as a
learning tool. Um, in fact, it was
largely spearheaded by former MIT
professor Dr. Janet Murray, um, who
first really got involved in this format
because she wanted to use it to develop
language learning projects. Um, and it
was her archival materials that I pulled
on um, the most in order to get the
theory and the basis for this project.
So going hand inhand with that the
actual creative process of it
step one was to gather all the
interviews um as mentioned there were
about 121 and I nailed it down to 44 but
first I had to go through all of them.
Um, originally I wanted uh to just focus
on a
originally I wanted to just focus on
computer science because I thought that
it would go hand inand you know like a
digital medium with people who are
studying um the digital arts. However,
once I really started getting into the
different interviews, I realized I just
had to include more perspectives.
And I also knew that I wanted to work on
the interviews because I wanted to
prioritize the actual worlds of women
and their experiences rather than my own
narrative. Um, after all, who knows what
it's like to live through this time
better than the people who actually
lived it. Um, I had thought about many
different ways to approach this. Um,
where one of them was to use a lot of
secondary material. Um, and I'll talk a
bit about the problems I ran into later,
but originally this is going to be a
very different project. Um, and one I
would end up having to use a lot of
secondary material for. However, turning
to the interviews allowed me to get a
much more present and a much more
immediate look at that time period. And
so once I discovered these um it was a
no-brainer. I decided I really wanted to
prioritize the words of the actual women
who lived this. Um and what changed my
mind specifically was when I was reading
through for fun um just one of the a
couple of the interviews. I was like,
"Oh, what is this project?" And I
decided to start with the earliest one I
found, which was from 1922 out of pure
curiosity. um she's like, "Oh, what was
it like to be back there?" Because it
was so different. Um I assumed, but I
didn't know how. And then on the first
pages, she was talking about learning
wireless telegraphy um to aid the World
War I effort and then about how she was
struggling to find a career during the
1920s because they wouldn't hire women
at all. And then about during the Great
Depression and then she talked about
discovering bootleg coal mines. I was
like, "This is very different." Um and I
really want to include these points. And
so after hers, I started wondering what
else am I missing? And so I started to
go down a rabbit hole. First, I read the
1920s accounts, then the 1930s accounts,
the 1940s accounts, and then by the time
uh I had gotten to the end, I was like,
"This is all too fascinating. My problem
is I don't know what to cut out because
I want to include it all, which led to
step two, which is all of the annotating
that I ended up doing. Um, I ended up
taking really extensive notes because I
knew that I wanted to make a project out
of this, but I wasn't quite sure what
exactly format I wanted to take or what
format I wanted the narrative to take.
Um, so I took different notes on a lot
of different elements and different
themes so that I could go back um and
have that ready for whichever path that
I wanted to take. Uh, and in the end uh
I ended up going through 3100 pages of
interviews. They're all very colorful so
they're kind of fun to look at.
But uh I would say that this was one of
the hardest parts um was actually
narrowing everything down. reading, but
3100 pages had taken a long time, but in
some ways, cutting it down was harder
because, as mentioned, I wanted to use
details from um everything really. Um,
and in the end, I had to leave a lot of
my favorite um inserts on the cutting
room floor because they just didn't fit
in with the rest of the narrative um in
this particular iteration. Maybe I'll
expand it later and bring in some of
these. Um, I want to read one of the
stories that particularly struck me that
I didn't wasn't able to fit in because
it didn't fit the time period that I
wanted to work with. Um, but this is one
of the first vignettes that I read where
I was like, "Oh this is a kick in the
stomach."
One funny episode is when I got
pregnant, I decided to work on my
teaching and get a grant and get
established for three years. And once I
got all of that, I said, "Okay, now I'm
going to have a baby." When I got
pregnant, they had this little handbook
for employees. And I was looking through
to see what there'd be for maternity and
it just said, well, I don't know what it
said because I couldn't find it. I was
flipping through and finally it says
pregnancy c disability.
So, I turned to the page for disability
and it says you can get two weeks off if
you have a doctor's note. That's what
we're working with.
Uh then I went through and I decided to
sort everything. Um once I narrowed down
the 3100 pages to about 100 or 150 pages
of different vignettes that I wanted to
use, I need to decide how to arrange and
build the text into an actual narrative
that people could interact with. Um and
so I settled on doing in three different
layers. In layer one, I decided that um
for each girl, Georgie, Francine, and
Shelley, I would choose one specific
Amita interview and use that as sort of
a base, a skeleton. I would take the
most bare bones details from that and
the major overall,
I guess, narrative arc, you could say,
from what the women had described um
their time at MIT. And then I would
build on top of that. And of course, I
would change um different names and
different details. didn't want to take
someone else's life and just completely
like redo it and like fictionalize it
and say, "Okay, this is my work now."
It's more if I read a story and an
emotional arc in it really struck me and
I thought, "Okay, this is something that
I do think really needs to be shared and
really needs to be put forward." So, I
focus on that. Um, so for example,
Francine, um, the one who had to work
and overwork is based on a real woman
who had to struggle and fight her way
all the way through MIT because she was
getting absolutely no support. Um, we'll
call her Jane D. Um, and she really did
lose her spot at Harvard Medical School
um, because she was doing a lot of odd
jobs because she had to do said jobs to
make enough money um, to try to save up
after going to MIT for medical school.
Um but one of her final jobs she was
caught on camera doing something
scandalous with a goldfish. Harvard
medical school saw that in the newspaper
and then rescended her offer. Um and in
the interview she talked a lot about how
she wished she hadn't taken all of those
jobs but she also felt she had no choice
because she needed money. And so her
story um as I said in the interview and
also I suppose like in in this to a
large extent is just about really
wanting and striving and trying to work
hard for what you want. But when that
working hard is also the thing that
takes away your dream. Like how do you
hold those two things together?
After I have narrative one or like layer
one like the narrative core, I decided
to flesh out each character. So I would
choose two or three other interviews um
and interview subjects that I found
particularly striking and pull heavily
from those as well. So for example with
let's call her Jane D again um while I
was trying to build out her story uh
she'd mentioned that she was struggling
for money since she was a child but she
hadn't really given a lot of details
about her childhood. But then I read the
interview from another story, another
female student who described what her
life was like growing up in a hotel um
that her parents owned and it was crazy
and it was colorful and it was also like
a speak easy and it was legal and
underground and it's kind of also like a
circus and a lot was going on. It was
really like fascinating. Um and so I
decided to combine that with the
original J&D story. Um so I thought,
okay, what if um this fictional
character is struggling for money
because her parents own a hotel because
this was during the Great Depression.
Um, and so if you own a hotel during the
Great Depression when no one actually
has money to go to a hotel, um, then
that would put you in on hard times. Um,
and so these are ways that I started
combining stories that would also have
as many different perspectives from as
many different women at MIT as possible.
And then for the third layer, I would
sprinkle in bits of stories and
vignettes from other interviews because,
as you saw, there was just so much I
wanted to include and so many stories
and tiny anecdotes that I thought were
really important. And it kind of broke
my heart that I mean if you go and
search these interviews out of course
you'll read them but for people who
don't actively search out these
interviews and I feel like it's a lot of
fascinating things are and important
information is just going unheard and
unappreciated. Um and so I really wanted
to sprinkle in as much as I could um
that still fit the story but things I
thought were just I felt that they were
really important. They're things that
moved me when I read them. So I thought
it was important to put them in.
Um, and one
story that I liked and I actually
sprinkled it in through all three
narrative strands, um, was the story of
this one woman, how she was in class,
place during the 60s and she was in
class and a professor started jabbing at
her because she was the only woman and
she ignored him, but they started making
really runchy, sexist jokes, and the
woman walked out. Um, but then also all
the men in the class also got out and
walked out with her and she was so
shocked because she hadn't spoken to any
of them. Um it was just
she was really moved by that little bit
of solidarity. And so I included that in
the 1920s I had well men probably
wouldn't walk out at all. Um and the
woman might not even walk out because uh
in the 1920s the the accounts I read the
women were just so grateful to be there
that they didn't even dare speak out
against sexism at all. Um from the
interviews they talked about that. The
1940s I had that okay a woman walked out
but the men probably wouldn't walk out
with her. And the 1960s I included the
original story which is when by that
time the men also did walk out. Um and I
kind of did that. I know obviously
progress isn't perfect or a straight
line but I did think that this was an
opportunity to show how different
attitudes towards women and specifically
women at MIT can shift across different
decades.
And in the part where actually turning
um the different interviews into actual
elements of the story, I really wanted
to keep the details the same. Um and I
wanted to prioritize women's original
voices. Um I thought that was really
important, but I also did need to add a
little bit of narrative connective
tissue in certain places that tie
everything together, especially because
I'm combining strands from so many
different stories. Um, and also because
it's interactive, readers can choose to
go down certain paths and they'll see
some things and they won't see other
things. Um, and so I had to figure out a
way to make the stories flow together
and make sense even if you have only
seen one half of it and you completely
missed or bypassed another half. Um, so
a lot of the fictionalizing that I did
was to bring these different elements
together. So here's an example of um an
passage. This part is the
uh actual quote from the woman. And the
next slide I'll show the way that I
added um a bit more of a literary voice
to it so that it was more cohesive with
the rest of the text as an example of
the work that I ended up doing. Um
well, I missed having that as a career
because I really wanted to go to medical
school. I didn't have any money to do
that. I didn't have any money at all. I
was already married even then, but I
always wanted to go to medical school.
And then the fictionalized version,
I missed it. You know, my chance. We all
get one chance in life and I missed
mine. Sometimes I like to delude myself
and pretend it's not too late. It help
keeps me saying this little lie because
otherwise I have to accept that it's
over.
It's hard to believe that I had the
grades, I had the admission, I had my
whole career ahead of me. But the money
just wasn't there. Money, it's always
always money in the end, isn't it? I
wanted to go to medical school, but I
didn't have the money to go, so I didn't
go. 2 plus 2 is four, and it will always
equal four. And besides, I was married,
so when would I have found the time?
Still, I always wanted to go to medical
school.
And the final step of this was to
actually turn this into a narrative that
people could play with, um, which is the
coding section. And because I'm a
novelist by trade and not a computer
scientist, this part was the most
difficult, but I had a lot of friends
who did a lot of help. Um, and so yeah,
it ended up I use Twine um, which is
just an open source software
particularly made um, for interactive
narrative and then Twine combined with
CSS.
And so for this um I wanted to just
finish up by giving an example um of
uh the the narrative just to like walk
through a bit how it works and how it
ended up looking. Um I'm still going
through and like finishing up play
testing and editing for bugs and
everything like that. Um and obviously I
can't show the whole game right now.
This is a 20-minute presentation. I'm
bumping up against that. Um but I did
want to show uh just a little bit to
give a taste.
So the
yes okay so the context for this um is
Georgie's story and her family fled
Belgium um for the US before World War I
began when she was still a young
teenager because they did sense the
danger that was brewing. Um since then
she spent all of high school trying to
feel at home and fit in in America but
it's not working. One of her teachers
suggested she join the war effort by
learning wireless telegraphy.
um she and her female classmates did and
marched over to the military and said
quote we are ready to save the world for
democracy but the military turned them
down because they were teenage girls. Um
and so Georgie decided to become a
farmer instead and that's that part is
actually part of a true story. Um this
is picking up where she's describing
that and I wanted to give a piece of how
she got to MIT.
Jordy says, "So then we decided, well
then we'll become farmerrettes."
Now this isn't a word that's common
today, although people who lived it in
that time remember it very well. See, if
you were a farmer, you saved the world
for democracy by shoveling manure. And
what you did was you went to a farm
school and we took the place of men who
were fighting the war. So we shoveled
manure all day and I'm sure that helped
save the world for democracy.
Um, and then clearly the red words are
the hyperlinks. So then depending on
which one the reader clicks, it will
take them down a slightly different
narrative path. Um, for example, you
click save the world for democracy and
then it leads to this next path.
Still, I dedicated every night to
tinkering with my crystal radio. I spent
hours hunched over that tiny little box,
fiddling with the cat's whisker probe
and the Kina crystal, listening for
distant Morris code signals.
And with my fingers on the desk, I
drummed out all the words I wished I
could scent.
And then the reader can choose which of
those Morse code paths they want to
follow. They choose the first one. It
means home. The second one, it means
family.
The third one, it means longing. And all
three of those paths will lead back to
this one.
Even though I didn't have a transmitter,
part of me hoped that someone back in
Belgium would hear me and send a message
back. and that I'd be the only one in
the world to receive it. If I just kept
listening hard enough, this could come
true. And because she wanted to be the
only one in the world, there's also only
one hyperlink on this page.
My classmates had no idea that I kept up
with the crystal radio long after the
military had rejected us. When she found
out, one said, "Well, you oughtn't go to
Smith College. You ought to go to MIT."
And actually clicking MIT will lead you
to how she got to MIT.
And these are her actual words. I didn't
change these. She said MIT they don't
take girls but the idea stuck in my crop
but I wrote a letter to the registar and
I signed my initials so he wouldn't know
I was a girl and the circular came and I
looked through it and on the very last
page it says something about female
students in small print and I said ah
they must take girls if it says female
students. So I ran for my aunt and I
said would you take me to see the dean?
I'm quickly touching on a couple of the
difficulties that we bumped into.
Um first was the lack of material on the
Athena project which is the project um
that Janet Murray spearheaded and was
actually what I really wanted to focus
this on originally. Um my original
project was to create a hypertext novel
about the creation of the Athena
language learning project and the
experience of women specifically at MIT
during that project. Um so that project
developed by Dr. Murray aimed to use
different interactive scenarios to teach
learners French. Um, for example, by
playing a video game where the
protagonist needs to read apartment ads
and rent an apartment, then the player
would theoretically learn how to read
apartment ads in French and rent an
apartment in French, which was
groundbreaking um for the 1980s. It
would be groundbreaking even today
really. Um, however, when I went through
Murray's archives, there was not enough
material on the actual um creation.
there was material
uh there were very dry notes and there
were programmer notes um but there
wasn't a lot of actual emotional detail
um which I was kind of hoping maybe you
never know what's going to pop up in the
archives um but it wasn't that um but I
knew that I really wanted to include
perspectives of women at this time so
switching to the Amita oral history
project was I think the best decision I
could have made because it really gave
everything I was looking for uh the
second issue was a lack of certain
narratives um as Tara mentioned the
first black woman didn't graduate till
the 60s. Um, and there were very few uh
narratives from queer people, POC
people, disabled people, and the few
narratives that there were painted a
very different picture of MIT than the
other narratives did, which I found
interesting. Um, for example, a lot of
the women, I would say 40% of them of
the interviews that I read loved
McCormack the House and loved living
with women and said it was like a
sorority and said they felt so at home
and they really loved this. They finally
had their own dorm and their own space.
But then I read a narrative from um it
might have been Shirley Jackson, one of
the black women there who talked about
how she said in McCormack, no one spoke
to her. It was really awkward and she
didn't feel comfortable there and like
that was all she had to say. She's like,
"Yeah, I did like it. No one talked to
me." I was like, "Oh, that's a new
perspective." Uh and that's important.
Those things are really important
because it's something I wouldn't have
thought about if it hadn't been. But
there were only um I think two or three
interviews from black women or at least
women who identified themselves as black
in the actual interview. a couple from
people who identified as Latino Latina
um and one who um I think was from China
I believe um but then again out of 121
interviews total this is very small um
and then also going hand in hand there
was a lot from the 1960s which makes
sense because that's also um when it
seemed like larger numbers of women um
started to graduate from MIT and also
just the availability of who is still
alive to give interviews um when this
project started but I decided that did
want to also look at the 1920s,30s, 40s,
and the earlier decades to really see
how it had transformed because by the
1960s, it wasn't perfect. Um, but it was
a lot better than it had been 40 years
ago. And so, I wanted to be able to show
that shift.
So, from here, um, it's in the very
final stages. I'm just doing a lot, uh,
like last minute going through all the
modes and like having a couple of, um,
play tests also go through everything
just to make sure everything's in place
and then naturally turn it over to um,
MIT um, if they want to put it on the
website. It's just HTML and CSS, so it's
very easy to host. Um, and yeah, and so
thank you, uh, thank you very much,
Terara, and also the MIT team. Thank you
for all of your help. They were so, so
useful for sending me all the different
resources and for going, um, with me
through the archives because I had to do
it digitally. Um, and so they were
really wonderful and so I appreciate the
support and thank you for having us
here.
>> Thank you so much, Jamie. That was
really cool. Next we have Loose Tappo
Lincoln who is a Brooklyn based
filmmaker, artist and cultural worker
born in Gainesville, Florida. Lincoln's
artwork and films transverse time
connecting historical stories to the
present day to imagine the future. His
works take form as personal documentary
documentaries, collaborative
experimental films and multimedia
[clears throat] installations.
Currently, Lincoln is directing
slashproducing a feature documentary
autobiography of a scientist working
title about their mother who attended
MIT in the 1960s. Lincoln is a
co-founder of an intergenerational
worker-owned media cooperative
Shadowwork Media and an art curatorial
project, Tala Arts. Lincoln studied film
and video at Antioch College and holds
an MFA in film and media arts from
Temple University.
Thank you so much for that introduction.
And let me see if I can do the tech of
this.
Um,
if I hit play, does this
work for folks? Can everyone see it?
Well,
um, I tend to be a little bit more
interactive, so apologies as I'm like
trying to figure out the Zoom and how to
find my chat. Wait, how do I This might
not be my forte. Okay, so I do want to
do some some upfront like I can't really
see my chat, so I will go back to the
chat thing. I'll have Tara help me if I
need to. Um, but uh yeah, so welcome to
my presentation of this work in progress
called counteracting the limitations. Um
I what I'm going to go through today is
more of a theoretical process, some
context of how I got here, um what I
found in the AR in in the MIT um
distinctive collections and then also
share um you know some rough things here
and there um with uh a caveat to say
that the film is in progress. films take
a while to put together. Um, and but I
feel really excited about the script
form that it's taking right now. Um,
so as we go. So before I get started,
this is the one where I wish I had the
chat up and um it's just that I would
love for folks to think about this word
archive and think about when I say this
word, what are the thoughts, feelings,
reactions, maybe even sensory
impressions that come up for you. Um I
don't I think I was want to start here
because I feel like this is where I
started is that I um applied to this
fellowship and got really excited about
it because well I love the archives
[laughter]
and maybe I romanticized the archives
quite a bit and so um I just would love
to see in like what people's uh yeah
thoughts Sorry about the archive.
Um,
this is where I want to be a little
interactive. Anybody, if anyone typed
anything in, can somebody get off mic
and say it to me since I can't see the
chat?
>> I'll read anything that comes up.
>> Okay. Thank you.
All right.
Well, um, for me, I'll start with, um,
just thinking about, uh, the the
cultural producers, the theorists, the
writers out there who are really working
in the archives. And we can't really go
that far without thinking about Sadia
Hartman's work. And I just love this
quote so much that I wanted to share it
with you before I start which is um
really sort of embodied uh where I I
feel like this work has taken me. I work
intuitively and I will follow a trail of
documents or my instincts until the
project emerges. I have an impression of
the kind of thing I might want to do and
that's very clear as opposed to having a
full outline of the book. I think partly
it's because of the way I engage
archival materials. I have a deep
encounter with them. Sometimes that
means there are things that I think I'm
going to write about that actually can't
write about once I encounter that
particular material or sometimes it just
takes me in a direction that I wasn't
expecting to go in at all.
So I just wanted to you know think about
that. Um and
I will start with some of the questions
that I came to this project with. Um
really uh I'm grounded in a lot of
personal work um using my film and
artwork to really like explore personal
stories. So really I started there. What
personal stories can be unearthed to
show the historical connections between
science and technology and on one hand
and the historical oppression on the
other? What are common tools and ways
forward that women um were implemented
to find their own voice and pathways to
success? And what are personal
narratives um from the act archives that
u demonstrate survival resilient
strategies um that can be uplifted? So
really thinking about um
yeah like how do we how do we kind of
come back to uh using the archives as a
way to be like all the answers are there
right like in some ways not maybe not
all the answers but some things that
that um is about
people's experiences and having tools
and and and
survived uh places like
MIT, right? Um Jamie, you gave a great
context for for for the 20s, 40s, and
60s. And um I appreciate that because
I'm going to take the baton and take us
from the 60s onward. So, um so let's
start with, you know, the personal
archive, right? So, this is where I
usually start all my work. um is to
think about well what am I thinking
about in my personal life that I need
answers to or what are what are some
curiosities
and um I just want to start here.
So this is me and my mom Gloria Capo
Lincoln and um you know when I think
about personal archives I think about
photo albums. I think about um I think
about the ways uh papers are left around
my my family's house or even um books. I
think about a lot of like think about
all the things objects that are left
around um for us to be able to touch. Um
and then I think at some point there's a
there's a clarity that there's a lot of
things that are aren't left around,
right? like maybe the best-selling
novels of the 1980s
are really in the bookshelves, but maybe
not um those stories that we really need
to hear about. Like um for me it was I
really uh was born I was born in
Gainesville, Florida. Um, I had a lot of
clarity about
uh my dad's family who was from
Massachusetts.
Um, and this, you know, very white
family that uh I could travel to. And I
would always ask stories about my mom
and and I never really felt it. I didn't
I didn't have the objects of of her
childhood. Um I I w was able to go back
to the Philippines but there was a big
chunk of time where um I was a child and
we didn't go back
for a lot of reasons and a lot of them
had to do with social political reasons
and and so um so that's kind of how I
started this journey back in college.
[laughter]
So this is like 20 years ago I started
to be like well let me gather my mom's
stories and so here we are continuing
that. So, in in 2021, I started
recording my mom. I started recording
her a lot before that, but to this is
when I was like, I'm going to do a
future documentary about my mom.
And um so that trailer exists and I'm
going to drop it in the chat when I find
my chat thing again. I will drop it
before the end of this talk. Um but uh
one of the things that uh really excited
me about this fellowship was that I
could deepen the context of her story,
right? Um because I get a lot of a lot
of visuals, a lot of um information
visuals as in her narrative, right? Like
about the 60s in MIT. And I really
wanted to know more about
what that space was like, what um who
was there, like what was the political
context around her, what was the
institutional context around her. So um
that's what kind of brought me to this
project.
Um
okay, wait, sorry, I'm still trying.
Okay. So, uh I I have to really thank
Tara for sending me this picture because
I had a clipping of it from the Boston
Herald, but I didn't have this picture
until um till until we started
communicating over email. And um so I'm
going to This is a picture of my mom and
then an audio. So, let's see. Wait, can
can you guys hear my audio if I share
this?
Wait, did you hear that?
>> No, I think you have to select to share
audio as well. [laughter]
>> Okay, hold on one second. I'm gonna do
this thing where
stop. Do it again.
Okay. Yeah, I see. Share sound.
Okay,
back it up a little.
I was at MIT uh in 1962. Started uh my
master's degree and finished that in
1964.
And right after that I started uh to be
in a PhD curriculum until
December 1967.
It is a department of food science,
nutrition and food science.
All I know was there not many women in
MIT but in that department were at least
six Filipina.
Yeah. Oh, at this that same time that I
was there, me first and then uh Mina and
then Lita, Mina, Lydia, and then uh
Hilda came. So, we're all five. Who Who
did I Oh, me. [laughter]
Counteracting the limitation of being a
short Asian woman.
Uh,
I just smiled and everybody liked me
smiling
and actually
for the longest time he said I everybody
just said I'm the most innocent person
they know. So they don't cor they don't
want to corrupt me. [laughter]
This I mean I think is a sexual advances
or so I just ignore them. So they think
that I'm just didn't know
even in my my uh oral my uh my final
oral uh defense of my dissertation.
Uh after I passed
one of the professors said you are the
prettiest
PhD I have known
is a put down
you know like
did they pass me because I was pretty is
that what's this implying
they can't help it I have no idea
>> so that's it
I So either so there are so many things
you know socially advances you ignore
it. This comment sticks to my brain but
I just one ear in the other ear out.
So yeah it sounds like MIT was hard.
>> [laughter]
>> It sounds like the 60s might have been
hard but especially in uh STEM like
science, technology, engineering,
mathematics and that is what I found out
in the archives too. And so one of the
things that uh that I I'm even this is
an antidote. So so I I love that this
this photo was sent to me. Um, one of
the things that stuck out was this was
this would have been kind of hard to
find if if if archavists were not on it
because
the reporter, the photojournalist wrote
my mom's name wrong. [laughter] So, the
captain says, "Miss Gloria Capo Capco is
her name." Um, and then you can see
multiple different spellings here.
Gloria Copco with an O. Anyway,
it's not it's one thing that you know
like to to find a photo. It's another
thing to to actually find it in
somewhere, right? And it to be
preserved, but it to be cataloged
correctly, it to be remembered.
So, I do think that part of my artwork
is this way of trying to remember the
things that we might not be able to um
the things that might uh get forgotten.
But I think it's also about um for us
looking back to to
heal the moments that need to be held,
you know, because there's a lot of um
grief in that in that in that uh
invisibility, right?
Um so anyway, so that's that's how I got
here. And so this is where I'm going,
right? is that I do think the idea of
the short film that I'm making for this
fellowship is informed by my mom's
story, but it it's about trying to find
what are the other resilient stories out
there um and how do I find other women
of color, black women, Native American
women, Latinx women out there doing um
hard work of trying to be scientists or
engineers. Um, so in in the actual daily
of trying to look for these stories, um,
what I found was similar to what Tara
started us off with, which was that the
first black woman to to graduate was
1968, right? Um, that in general, these
stories are kind of hard to find, so
similar to Jamie. Um, so I I I really
sort of lend I went down all kinds of
different um pathways to get different
places. Um but some of those pathways
actually were kind of um surprising like
um in the 60s what I found um was that a
lot of
a lot of the sort of intern like I went
down this sort of rabbit hole around
international students and trying to
find stories about international
students but instead found out that the
center of international affairs got
started
in in the 60s, which is actually kind of
a huge um think tank to to continue the
war in Vietnam and and other uh Asian
countries. And so so that just kind of
contextualizes what the social space
MIT's taking up in this moment, right?
Um, so I did I did lean into a lot of um
really looking hard at what are
uplifting stories. Again, I'm trying to
find resilient stories. And so one of
the things that I found to be completely
inspiring is the work that came out of
1994's conference um black women in the
academy defending our name um 1894 to
1994. And this was a conference that was
um organized by Robin Kilson
and Evelyn Hammonds who were both um
assistant professors at MIT at the time.
Um and
this uh conference is really
just delightfully documented. So there's
um all the keynote speakers um are have
videotaped were videotaped and are
digitally accessible. So feel free to to
watch it whenever you want. Um Angela
Davis was keynote speaker. Um there were
uh so many powerful women in attendance.
Um, but I really want to give um props
to Robin Kilson and Evelyn Hammonds um
for the visionary uh just leadership to
to think about this conference. Um and
they even admit in their opening that
they've never done this. This is not
they're not conference organizers.
um they expected
um maybe 500 people to show up. 2010
people came to this conference.
Yeah. From around the world.
Um, and so I do think that these moments
um really are about how do we create
spaces um for dialogue to happen for for
people to develop collective action
together, collective um language,
collective
um
in and grievances is it starts but but
also to to find solutions together. Um,
so I really leaned heavily into this and
I just I do think that I just want to
share this really sweet clip because um
let's see if this
>> So on behalf of all of us,
I would like to ask
Robin and Evelyn to come on stage again
because I want to thank them in a proper
way.
Heat. [applause]
[applause]
>> [cheering]
>> Um,
I I think when I when I'm sort of going
through these archives, uh, what I what
I've really noticed was the different
feelings I was getting from looking at
different sources, different things, And
um I really wanted to stay with this
moment because it really captured the
feeling of celebration of honoring
people who are um
who are taking risks to to make space
for community in a different way. Um, I
think uh we I don't know if everyone
here knows Angela Davis's work, but
Angela Davis is, you know, an important
um person that I've been following
since, you know, I was a teenager, so
probably around this time. And, you
know, I don't I didn't but I don't know
Robin Kilson's name and I don't know
Evelyn Hammond's name before this um
fellowship. And I think that's really
important to say that that even in um a
feminist space or or a radical space
that we we tend to have um some
celebrities, you know, people that we we
hear again and again and again. And I I
want to like really spend time, you
know, giving flowers to the people that
are are doing the work um that might not
be known as much. So, um what I would
love, uh for this [snorts] film is to
continue down this this
um
path of thinking about
this conference. Um I I'm going to shout
out a friend of mine who's on here, Amy
Angiri, who who was who was at the
conference. Um, and I would I would love
to to like really think about the ways
that um we capture stories that are
outside of the archives as well. Um, so
I'm I'm excited to sit down with them
and have a conversation about the impact
of the conference um had on their life,
but also um people like Robin Kilson,
who was one of their mentors. Um,
so that's that's coming. Um
the other the other thing I will say
that came out of this research is really
thinking about um I said this in the
conference in in relationship but like
what are spaces that allow for us to
find each other to find uh ways out of
um what seems from Jaime's narratives is
these depressive like situations, you
know, like whether whether it's um my
mom's story saying, you know, like
advisor giving her a sexist comment, you
know, at a at a moment of of celebration
really. And or and so I'm thinking about
the spaces of MIT a lot when I'm like
going through the buildings and all that
stuff. And one of the things that my mom
highlighted was the Cheney room. So I I
I'm like sort of piecing all these
things together and then I want to
visually share with you what I've been
working on. So when I was um not in um
when I wasn't in the archives, I was at
the makers lab in the basement of MIT um
cutting out 16mimeter films. And um part
of this is just me doing some
experiments myself of of experimental
film practice. So, I'm going to share
with you some possibility of like what
that visual could look like for for
these stories of like thinking about
spaces, but also like how to use I can
Yeah, we'll we'll I'll get back to it,
but let me share with some like
conceptual visuals that will will pull
this together a little bit. So on behalf
of all
>> okay this
so as you see here this is just um me
animating the the film strips that I've
um put together and I've looped on top
of pictures of the Cheney room. Oops,
sorry. Um
so there you go. One more time.
And so you I took the laser cutter and
we cut f frame by frame uh holes into
this um film. And this idea I'm going to
use continually to be the mask of like
the feeling of trying to find things
that you know um may may you know may
may be there may may not be there where
where there is stories. Um, and it seems
like the Cheney Room, uh, for those of
you who are not familiar with MIT is
this women's lounge that has been around
for a long time, [laughter]
hundred years or more. And um,
uh, my mom talked about it as being like
the when the first year she came, she
used it a lot to sleep and just relax
and to kind of feel a little bit of
comfort um, and relief. and it's still
around today and so I was able to visit.
Um so yeah um the last thing that I want
to say is that um I just wanted to show
the faculty
because I did go down this other route
which is that one of the um most famous
women who really are fighting for
women's rights especially in STEM at MIT
is Nancy Hopkins. And I did go down the
rabbit hole of Nsky Hopskin story. Um,
but I think it's important for us to
contextualize also women of color
specifically. Um, when that conference
was being held in 1994, there were three
black professors, black women professors
at MIT. There's now 16,
which is better, but not great, right?
Still. So um so yeah just just
continually uh thinking about the space
of MIT, the space of academia, but also
thinking about um what are the stories
we want to be collecting? Um what are
the solutions we want to be thinking
about? Um that's really where this film
is going.
Um, some of that is also finding um,
earth story accounts of attendance of
people um, like Amy, but also uh, other
academics like uh, uh, Cadia um, Hartman
was at the conference too and writes
about it and um, has a lot of good uh,
questions for us to be thinking about
which is like how how if you're fighting
for um, space in institutions like MIT.
Do we not um forget to to also think
about working class thinking about
abolition? That was a huge thing for
Angela Davis's speech is like how do we
think about uh women in prison as well
like how do we never leave behind anyone
ever even when we're fighting for
science and STEM careers, you know? And
so I think that that's something that um
I will be coming back to as part of the
solution to to thinking about um the
best way to capture
uh resilient stories is really thinking
about intersectionality and and tactics
toward coalition.
Um
that's it.
I'm going to throw in some links that uh
that I that I would um
Great. Thank you both so much for
talking about your projects. Um
these were both fascinating. I hadn't
heard any of this. I knew the things you
all were working on, but this was really
a delightful to hear about your
research. Um,
I really appreciate how different the
two projects are, but how they show the
variety of ways that like these rich
historical materials can be used. Um,
and they highlight the value of the use
of historical collections in ways that
aren't like traditional scholarly
papers. Um, and I think that's really
cool.
one question I had. I'll I'll start with
the first question and then if people
have questions, you can put them in the
chat or you can just ask them since
we're a small enough group that you can
just unmute yourself and ask a question
if you'd like. Um, had either of you
done historical or like archival
research before or was this a new
experience for you?
Yeah, I'll jump in. Um I had but never
with oral interviews. I'd worked mostly
with um like actual written texts like
people's diaries entries or journals or
published books before. So that part was
new.
Yeah. I realized in the process of this
that I've been going to archives
specifically um starting in undergrad um
to really look at films and film
archives and try to do my own archival
producing of for documentaries I was
thinking about and working on.
Yeah.
plenty of questions if nobody else does.
Um, but please feel free to jump in with
a question or a comment if you have one.
Um,
oh, good. You put a link to your trailer
in the chat. Thank you, Liz. Um,
I was wondering
I know that there were sort of some
changes in direction for both of you
from your like original proposals to
what came out of it. And I think
there's
first a comment and then a question. Um,
I think that there's something about
archival research that's really similar
to like the creative act where like what
you think you're going for isn't like
necessarily what you're able to get to.
Um, I was wondering if either of you had
any I know you both sort of touched upon
like a lack of information. Um but if
there's anything you want to expand upon
talking about that um because there were
I think quite a few gaps that both of
you experienced.
>> Yeah, I can I can start it off on that
which is that like I really I made sure
to go to MIT to be at the archives. um
that for me is really important partly
because I'm so visual and I want to be
in the space that I'm making things. So
it was actually also part of my film
making practice. Um, but one of the
things that really struck me was when I
was saying I was trying to find anything
like I don't know. I was just looking up
like how do I find these Filipinos that
my mom talks about, you know, [laughter]
like I was just like sort of having like
I know they're there but the archives
doesn't feel like they're there, you
know? And I think that that's something
that really strike struck me. And then
what really also struck is like the
prolle of terrible things that I didn't
want to read necessarily.
um that because I because I couldn't
find that I would go down these other
routes that I were like let me
contextualize the 1960s and like I you
know that's when I started learning
about certain academic professors that
were you know like people's papers that
I didn't necessarily want to be reading
um that were like about cold war
strategy or you know like be you know
like um I one of the foreign affairs
professors really hated all Chinese
people and really thought that they
shouldn't govern themselves. [laughter]
It was pretty wild and um that's feels
like a legacy of MIT too, you And I
think it's important for us to be
talking about those um parts of the
archives and these institutions that for
me what I walked away with is that um I
can't ignore like there's part of me
that is not part of I'm not in the
academic world in the way that um that
my mom was or even as Robin or Evelyn
were. But what I would say is that we
can't ignore what's going on there
because it's where empire begins. It's
like where the like intellectual thought
partners of everything really starts.
And so um and and for MIT that is uh at
the forefront of biotech, that's the
forefront of military industrial
complex, the medical industrial complex.
like we want we really need to think
about what's being thought there both
historically and currently. Um, and
that's what I hope my work to kind of
also bring out is is a little bit of
this dialectic of like what's being
emerges outside of that to to sort of
counteract that, but also what should we
be thinking about? Because what I really
walked away with that I'm living in the
imagination of somebody from the 1960s
like whoa. Like that's wild. like that
some white dude really just thought
about social media and now
we're in it. [laughter]
So that really struck me.
And then um for me I really had to stop
and think about what people find
important to include. Um and I think
there's definitely a difference like
when outside sources decide like which
um you know which books to preserve or
like which uh documents but I for
example I was going through Janet
Murray's papers and so the things that
she had decided um to keep and I like
the entire papers from her entire time
at MIT um and I found it very
interesting I think just like from her
she had boxes and boxes and boxes but
almost no nothing personal no real
personal correspondence. Um, no, not
even really like notes to sell for
letters. Um, and but there were almost
endless boxes of like programmer notes
and just like the same draft of the same
couple projects over and over again. Um,
and since then I've also looked at other
people's like collections of papers at
other um, uh, universities and there
were a lot more personal things, a lot
more like back and forth notes, a lot
more just like notes to yourself or
things you've scribbled down or like
different handwritten drafts, a lot more
personal. I just found it interesting
like neither way is good or bad. And I
just kind of wonder about the mindset of
the person who decides, okay, this is
what I want to keep or maybe this is
what I want to keep and have university
to have. And maybe she has her own
personal thing like somewhere else that
she doesn't want to have, which is like
fine. Um, but I like those really asking
those questions.
I think Jayen maybe has a question. If
you wanna pop in, please feel free.
>> Uh yes, I do. Hi. Uh
both of you are I want to say how how
incredibly interesting your projects
sound and how cool it is that you were
sharing with us. I have a question a
little odd in nature, I suppose. How do
you balance being informed about the
history of MIT and not being overwhelmed
or disheartened by the history of the
place, the realities that the women in
the past faced while also realizing that
it can be difficult to carry all that
knowledge? Uh I know you mentioned
briefly in your presentation uh loose
your name that you didn't want to go
down the rabbit holes of some of the
more negative stories and I just want to
know how you balance that in your the
stories you present and in your projects
themselves. Thank you.
Yeah, I mean I think I think similar to
what I just said is that sometimes we
have to share the negative stories to
give the context to the other stories if
that makes sense. So um
yeah, even starting off this
presentation with that little clip from
my mom like that I know that you know
her time at MIT wasn't negative the way
that story is. you know, it's just that
like that's what came up when she
thought about counteracting the
limitations. Like what are the
limitations? The limitations are that um
often the people around us um don't are
are the limitations [laughter]
basically, but the oppressive nature of
the of the institution or the people
around us with power are the
limitations. But um but yeah um some I
think that that's the the I would say
the thing that I've learned from the
archive experience is though that like
when you put out of when you put out a
request for a box of things you don't
know what's going to come back, right?
Like it's not it's a little bit of a
surprise and sometimes that surprise is
like um part is is part of the work
though. It's part of the work of like
shifting through all the other things
that you like I literally would go
through like a box of just like a to a
toz you know like just to be like what's
in here you know and trying to find
something like unusual or interesting or
as Jamie was saying with like you know
the personal story potentially like that
that maybe somebody left something in
the margins of the paper to like to
actually look more at you know um or
maybe this person knows this person that
will and lead me to another person.
Uh and for me in terms of uh like how to
bear it all the weight of the dark side
of MIT and everything um that I've
uncovered during the research process I
think at least for me emotionally um
what helped a lot were that in the same
oral interviews where they had talked
about something really dark and
terrible, they also talked about either
how they surmounted that or like they
gave like a funny anecdote or something.
Um, and it made me think I think about
how it is terrible, but people are
pushing against it. And also life goes
on, like it's terrible, but people, I
don't know, have existed and are
existing and are pushing against it. And
a lot of women um that were in the
interviews talked about how when they
were at MIT, even if, for example, there
wasn't necessarily a lot of solidarity
among women, one woman talked about um
how they kind of just either didn't
think of themselves as women or they
just like wanted to like put their heads
down like get through it. um but then
after that had like joined women's
associations and then were like now
giving money back and like now like
actively trying to work um and so the
same women that had been put down and
discriminated during their time at MIT
are now actively working against that
and working to make it a better place um
in a lot of regards and so for me that
gave me sounds cliche but that did give
me a little bit of hope um I think
especially yeah looking at how and I
know it's also cliche to say like oh it
was so much worse back then um so I
think some ways worse some ways better
like I'm not going to like fit value
judgment, but I do think there's a lot
of active work being done. Um, and
looking at that work and the people who
have been working and are still working.
I have hope in those people.
>> Um, we have one question in the chat and
then Amy and then we probably have time
for one more after that if anyone else
wants them. So, I'll read the chat
question, you two can respond and then
Amy, you can hop in and ask your
question. The question in the chat is
for Jamie and Loose. How much of your
research involves written
accounts/recorded media versus oral
history? And how are the oral
recollections different from like
recorded?
I can jump in this time. Um, for this
one, I started with written, but then I
moved over to only oral. Um, so I looked
at just or primarily the oral histories.
Um, I found the oral histories much less
edited, which I liked. Um they like
especially the earlier ones that they
done I think in like the 90s they left
in all the ums they left in the weird
pauses. They left in people like
breaking in um and they left in like
starting the tape, stopping the tapes.
Like they wrote that in and it was very
raw and I liked that a lot. Um and so I
think and there was a lot of laughter
and there was a lot of back and forth um
because they would also have the
interviewer talk about themselves which
in the written accounts was a lot more
straightforward and formal, a lot more
formal register. Um so I feel like the
oral histories I definitely got more of
a sense of who each person was and I
loved that. That's why I ended up going
there specifically.
>> I would say it's 50/50 with my research.
I mean, a lot of the things that I came
across that wasn't the conference was
written. Um, that I looked at Nancy
Hopkins papers and like read every
letter that she sent [laughter] to back
and forth and that was kind of really
interesting. Um and then I also uh had
an opportunity to look at um actually
kind of the organizing of the oral
history project was interesting to look
at the lunchon transcript um is so
interesting 19 you know like 75 them
really thinking about all it was it was
a lunchon to talk about the oral history
project launching but then in that
people sharing what else they were doing
around equal you know basically like
fighting for women's um professionally
at MIT. And so there were what was cool
and almost frustrating for me as a
filmmaker and somebody who wants that
archive video material is that they kept
referencing all these films that I was
like where are those? Where are those?
And you know like and and that felt
frustrating is like this sort of um you
know this like you know what I want is
the recorded material. like I do want
the oral and I do want the video and and
I'm sitting here looking at paper being
like h this title will never exist or
there was like this really awesome um
anecdote they were saying that they they
had a high school and like uh firstear
students in acting doing like
videotaping
um workplace like harm basically and
like and videotaping it as a way to kind
of like skid it out but also feel
empowered in situations to like come up
with alternatives. That's what I mean.
Like I would love to see that. And 1975
that probably is like I don't even know
what kind of format because that was
like that was pretty BHS. So [laughter]
yeah,
my question is like L said, I was at
this conference um and I have to say
that I have I feel like the conference
was very formative to me. It made me a
scholar essentially. Now I'm like a full
professor. But um and then I wasn't even
in grad school I believe. But um I have
to say MIT was not a welcoming space
whatsoever. Um so I was really surprised
that they had preserved this at all. Um
and I don't I don't think you said loose
but Robin Kilson tragically died really
young of cancer. Um I think they had
meant it to be an ongoing thing but it
wasn't. I think there was another one
but only two. But um I guess I mean this
is a long prelude to my question which
is what are and other people have kind
of asked shades of this but I feel like
what actually happened at that
conference can't be captured in an
archive cuz I feel like of all the
people who were there I'm sure there
were many many many people like me who
were young and it made them a scholar or
made them see the possibility of
scholarship and in a way it doesn't
surprise me that the first um black
person graduated in ' 68. that's
literally still in my lifetime, you
know? So, it just wasn't a welcoming
place. I don't find archives in general
to be welcoming. So, I'm wondering like
what is left out cuz I 100% don't think
what happened at that conference, which
was pure magic, was captured in that in
the archives. But, of course, I haven't
seen it, so I don't know. But I'm just
curious about that.
I mean, I think that
it felt very like what I understand from
even just reading people's accounts of
it um that it that feeling and the level
of energy that was brought at that
conference was not captured. what was
captured was the keynote speeches, the
program. Um,
I would really have loved uh what they
did with the lunchon of the oral history
to have existed for that conference.
like I want to be a fly on the wall when
Evelyn Hammonds and Robin Kilson are
talking about the nitty-gritty of like
you know how how did they make the
decision to just keep letting people you
know like this is so important that
we're just going to keep thousand you
know like that two we're at 2,000 people
registered now like how like I want to
know that nitty-gritty conversation but
and maybe that will be the conversation
I ask Evelyn Hammonds you know of of
really like getting more clarity about
um what are are the things that
that conference did for people and for
herself that um and I would love to hear
from you Amy more. Um and for me I feel
like the thing that um I really was
reminded is that archives are not in the
institutions, they're in our
relationships. they're in the legacy
that's left behind by people like Robin
Kilson, right? Um I think I think it not
coincidence that um that Amy was there
and that now I get to talk to Amy um who
was mentored by Robin. I I think that
that's a full circle that I'm I'm really
leaning into.
>> And obviously I I can't speak on the
specific conference, but thank you Amy
um for your perspective and for bringing
that up. Um, and I do think and it
doesn't surprise me that MIT itself did
not feel like a welcoming place. Um, and
just the fact that they the first black
student graduated in 1968. Um, but even
so, that's what like 50 plus years,
there were still only like two black
accounts in the entire of all the oral
histories. So, maybe they just didn't
want to speak on their experiences or
maybe they weren't asked because they
weren't thought people thought like
their perspectives weren't important. I
don't know. But you're right, there's so
many voices and so many things that
aren't being captured that should be
>> just one more thing real quick. But um
because like the one thing for me was at
my school there was one black female
professor and um the weird thing that
happened there was just actually seeing
a bunch of black academics. Like I'd
never seen that. And I don't think you
can capture that in footage. Like I
remember where I was sitting in that
Angela Davis speech, you know, but like
you can't capture the sense of like
wonder of seeing a bunch of black
academics in an archive. But anyway,
I'll stop.
>> No, I I agree. Archives are only part of
the story. We usually just preserve sort
of the records, the paperwork, letters,
sometimes really cool, surprising,
interesting notes, but it's certainly
not like we need people who can
interpret the history and who can do
oral histories and like interact with
people. And that's one of the special
things I think about fostering a
fellowship like the women at MIT
fellowship where we're not just looking
for people who can take
something from one piece of paper and
put it on another piece of paper, but
people who can really help the um
stories come alive and bring them to
like a new generation of people and
connect with people who were there. I
mean, I think it's so cool that you were
there. And then I know someone who was
in one of the AMDA oral histories that
Jamie used, she posted and she's she's
also on this call. So, I think it's just
a really a great way to see
ways that archives can like still
operate as part of the community even
years after like an event has happened.
But yeah, they in no way will ever be a
way to capture the whole picture,
especially if it was something pre
cell phone era when like probably some
parts were filmed that we don't have
that maybe deteriorated or just were
lost
in the shuffle of time.
Um well, thank you all so much for
joining us. Thank you again, Jamie
Eloose. Um, this is really awesome. I'll
be putting
this recording up on YouTube in the next
couple of weeks and we'll send an email
out to everyone who registered so that
you all can watch it, pre-watch as you
will. Um, and yeah, thank you all for
coming and have a great rest of your
day.