[Music]
so then we'd like to think well how can
we avoid this what are therapies uh that
we could do or apply to a patient to
shift this distribution of te- cell
States so we want to go away from being
in the terminal exhausted State and
favor progenitor te- cells in these
affector te- cell states that are good
at um dividing making more of themselves
and killing tumors so really part of
this challenge is thinking about how we
can shift distributions of these T Cell
States and there are therapies that do
exactly this and uh you know the most
exciting class of therapies are cancer
immunotherapies and cancer
immunotherapies are uh therapies that uh
actually just boost the immune system's
ability to fight cancer and there are
two uh main therapies out there immune
checkpoint blockade and car t- cell
therapy and both of these therapies act
on t- cells so they're both modifying
the te- cells in some way to make them
better at killing cancer and so I like
um you know looking at what oncologists
have said about these immunotherapies
and just seeing you know how much
improvements there's been since we've
started using immunotherapy so here's a
quote from Jason Luke saying you know
we're talking about diseases where we
used to tell patients uh during their
first clinical visit that they were
going to die from this cancer so really
really um you know immunotherapies in
certain cases have made a big difference
so uh there's two types of
immunotherapies we're first going to
talk about uh immune checkpoint blockade
so let's return to a cartoon that's
similar to what you've seen before where
we have a t- cell engaging with a tumor
cell or cancer cell on the surface of
the t- cell is a t- cell receptor that
recognizes the non-self antigen from the
cancer cell so you saw this earlier and
actually on T cells there's many
molecules so another molecule on the
surface of the t- cell other than the t-
cell receptor is pd1 and pd1 is a
molecule that is a major regulator of t-
cell exhaustion and what happens is uh
tumor cells Express another molecule
pdl1 which binds to pd1 and turns off
the t uh the T cells and keeps them from
activating their killing response so
anything that could really disrupt this
interaction would free the te- cells and
make them better Killers so when this uh
interaction is happening the te- cells
are kind of being driven into this
terminal exhausted State and so the idea
with checkpoint blockade is to disrupt
or block this interaction ction by
designing proteins or antibodies that
bind to pd1 and block the interaction
from ever happening so in checkpoint
blockade we have these antibodies they
block this interaction and this frees up
the t- cell to not go into the terminal
exhausted State and to stay in a
progenitor state or an affector State
and be able to uh kill the tumor
cells so now let's look at an example of
one of the first clinical trials that
was done using immune checkpoint
blockade so so the one of the first
trials was iaab which is an advanced
melanoma so that's a very uh bad stage
of the melanoma disease and here we're
looking at the results of that clinical
trial data where on the y- axis we have
overall survival and then on the x-axis
we have how long the patients uh
survived and so here we're seeing the
control uh arm of the trial where these
are patients who did not receive the
checkpoint blockade and then here we're
seeing uh the treatment with iila map
and so at first glance you know this is
a significant difference but it's not
maybe not a huge difference but what
you're seeing really in this data is
that you know in the control arm of the
trial patients are you know
unfortunately dying you know you know
from 8 to 12 to 16 months and with the I
Aluma treatment you have patients living
out to like 60 months a certain subset
of the patients so not everybody
responds toap but those who do actually
live quite longer and you know this was
a trial that was done in 2010 and since
then in the last 10 years there's been a
lot of uh advancements in immune
checkpoint blockade and I like this
quote from um Jed walchuk at Memorial s
ketering uh saying that when he first
started um you know treating patients in
in the year 2000 the average survival
for something like Advanced melanoma was
you know only seven months and now with
the latest sort of FDA approved
checkpoint Inhibitors average survival
has increased to over six years so
things have really got better and better
and better but still we have this issue
that not all patients uh respond to
immune checkpoint
blockade so the other form of of uh
cancer immunotherapy or the other main
form is car cell therapy and again like
checkpoint block a this is working with
te- cells so uh car T Cell Therapy is
really uh clever and cool and how it
works is it's actually a living drug
that's derived from the patient and so
what happens is uh the cancer patient
gets a blood draw and uh scientists in
the lab extract tea cells from that
blood draw and then they genetically
engineer the te- cells to express on
their surface another molecule called a
chimeric antigen receptor or car and
this car is engineered to actually
recognize the nonself antigen on the
surface of the cancer cell and so uh
this is something that really is you
know very clever and then what happens
is you take this car T Cell that's now
been engineered to recognize the cancer
cell you grow up tons and tons of them
millions of the cells and you infuse
them back into the patient and then the
car cell goes from the blood and
traffics to the tumor and starts to kill
the tumor cells because I recognize the
nonself antigen on the surface of those
tumor cells so this is really amazing uh
you know here's an example it's been
used to treat diffuse large B cell
lymphoma and 50% of treated patients
have a durable complete response however
again what about the other 50% of the
patients so cancer immunotherapies are
amazing in so many ways and they really
transformed the lives of a lot of cancer
patients however the big problem
everybody is really focused on is why do
these Therapies only work for some
people and for some cancer types and can
we really get these therapies to work
for more individuals across more types
of cancer so what are some of the
reasons cancer immunotherapy fails so
first in immune checkpoint blockade um
not all cancer cells are acting through
pd1 or the related molecule
ctla4 so uh in these cases checkpoint
blockage just doesn't work because you
don't have the appropriate Target now
also in cancer uh individuals can
involve resistance to the checkpoint
blockade therapy there are changes in
the cancer that result in the cancer
becoming resistant to checkpoint
blockade and this can either work by the
cancer cells starting to directly
inhibit te- cells through another
signaling pathway or the cancer cells
can start to change their surrounding
environment to make it suppressive to
the immune response and then finally car
T cells themselves can be exhausted so
there are a lot of efforts to address
these different problems and if you look
in clinical trials.gov there are
thousands of studies that are going on
for immune checkpoint Inhibitors and
thousands of studies going on for car T
cells so there's really this huge unmet
need where we need to understand what
can we do to tea cells to make them
better uh in terms of cancer
immunotherapy and so the big focus of
this challenge is really thinking about
what are genetic changes we can make in
te- cells to make them better at killing
cancer and that's really what we're
going to be uh focusing on across these
different tasks in the challenge and so
um you know to do this we really need to
at a basic level understand everything
we can about the pathway that leads from
these sort of naive T cells these
progenitor affector and terminal
exhausted t- cell States so we really
need to know the gene expression
programs and the changes responsible for
all these uh steps and uh doing this
really has been the work of decades and
furthermore we would like to not just
understand you know the gene expression
programs that are happening here but you
know what perturbations uh we could make
how they would affect this process so
this is a really slow process it
involves a lot of biological
experimentation however in the last
decade or so um our Technologies and our
computational approaches have really
empowered us to believe that we can make
this discovery process a lot faster and
that's what this challenge is really
about of understanding this process of
t- cell differentiation when they're in
these exhausted uh States and how we can
perturb the te- cells to shift them away
from those terminal exhausted States so
uh that's the overview of the biology
and the introduction to biology for this
data science Challenge and then next
we'll talk about uh how we actually
measure the cells in the immune in the
immune system and how we look at their
gene expression values and how we can
actually perturb the immune cells uh to
get you know maybe more desirable states
that would be more effective in a cancer
immunotherapy
[Music]