Today
today we're going to talk about
stochcastic processes uh the second set
of lectures and we're going to begin
with a discussion of brownie in motion.
Uh, brownie in motion is a process that
I'm sure most of you have heard of. And
it was named after Robert Brown, an
English botonist. And this is an
interesting case where a scientist
observes some dynamics in nature and
then is concerned about what
mathematical model uh might describe
that behavior. Turns out that it was I
guess Albert Einstein who uh formalized
this brownie in motion model
mathematically
and Norbert Weiner, our MIT uh hero. Uh
those of you familiar with the math
department know about the Norbert Weiner
uh room that we have. and he developed
the mathematical foundation for Brownie
in motion. Now let's take a look at a
simulation of Brownie in motion in two
dimensions. So this is the kind of
dynamics that Brown was observing. And
so in these slides, we're going to start
the process at the origin of the space
where the red dot is and then move
around in two dimensions where each step
is a random move in the x direction and
a random move in the y direction. And
for this simulation uh we use Gaussian
uh distributions. But as I page through
these graphs, one can see how a particle
moving according to these dynamics will
start at the origin and evolve to the
final red dot.
And if we hold down
the graphs and see where it goes, you
can see that basically there's
purely random dynamics. but um of a very
special kind. And so uh the special kind
is that the movements are jagged
and uh unpredictable in terms of their
direction.
Something that's really quite
interesting when you just look at this
and page through the dynamics here sort
of animating the process. The movements
in fact have no uh trend in them to move
left or up or down. And so the movements
we see
uh basically are movements that are
symmetrical in their dynamics.
And so that's a very interesting
property that we would like to uh
characterize mathematically.
So let's look at how we define Brownian
motion in one dimension.
So in one dimension we are simply
looking at
a graph. Let me find the eraser here.
Okay.
In one dimension we have time t. And
we're going to think of a process BT
um which will start at zero and then
it's going to evolve
over time in such a way that
the increments of the process from t to
t plus delta t. So if we have t and t
plus delta t here and we look at b of t
here
and b of t plus deltat t,
this vertical increment is going to be
normally distributed
for any increment of time delta t. And
the normal distribution for the
magnitude of that increment will be a
normal random variable with mean zero
and a variance that is proportional to
the length of the interval. So as we
consider increments delta t that are
larger, we'll have greater variation in
the vertical increment that's normally
distributed. Now in addition to normal
increments we have independent
disjoint increments. So if we have
different time points
like t1, t2 and then t3, t4
if these increments are separate or
disjoint from each other then the change
from t1 to t2 and the change from t3 to
t4 those will be independent random
variables.
Finally, uh, B of T turns out to be a
continuous function of time if it
satisfies these properties. And so this
is a very
simple model in terms of a continuous
time stochcastic process.
Now uh the properties of Brownian motion
and we are that um it's a marov process.
So if we're looking at the value
at b of t plus delta t at this time
point
um that is equal to the value at any
prior time point well at b of t plus the
increment.
And so given the information set up to
time little t, the conditional
distribution
simply um is
equal to that starting point b of t plus
the random increment. So displacements
uh are independent of the past apart
from the last value of the past.
Okay. mean and variance of B of T. Well,
because the increments are normally
distributed with mean zero, then the
expected value of B of T into the future
will stay at zero, but the variance of B
of T will increase with time. And so the
standard deviation of b of t will be
proportional or will be sigma times the
square root of t. So if we think of
drawing curves
which correspond to sigma square root of
t this corresponds to one standard
deviation above the zero mean for the
process.
Okay. The covariance function of
Brownian motion. If we want to look at
the co-variance between two times s and
t. So suppose here is time s and here is
time t. Then
the process
paths
to time t include the process paths up
to time s but then have this independent
increment beyond time s. And so when we
look at the co-variance
of the process at times s and t, it's
equal to the expected value of the
product. But we can split B of T into B
of S plus the increment and we simply
get sigma^ 2 S for the co-variance. So
the degree to which the process is
correlated with other values of the
process it depends on how much overlap
there is in the time intervals uh
corresponding to those two values.
Now this process that starts at
zero
B of 0
or B sub0 or B of 0 equal to zero. We
could start it at any other level and
have a process that has similar
properties but just has a different mean
level from time zero. So we can talk
about starting the Brownian motion at
any given point.
And so uh in order to work with these
models um we'll find it convenient to
introduce the notation for normal random
variables.
And so if we have Z be a standard normal
that is a normal distribution with mean
zero and standard deviation one then the
probability density function is given by
this formula. I'm sure everyone is
comfortable with that. And the
cumulative distribution function is
simply the integral of the density from
minus infinity up to C for f of c. And
this notation of smallcase f and
uppercase v are standard for referring
to gaussian or normal densities and
cdfs.
Well, if we have a normal with non-mean
nonzero mean meu and variance to squar
or standard deviation toao, then we have
uh the density of this normal
y is a simple function of the density of
the standard normal. uh we simply
subtract the mean mu and divide by toao
inside fee and we have a toao
denominator factor in front and what's
particularly
uh convenient at times is that if we
want to calculate the cdf
of y
then this cdf of y is actually the cdf
of the of under the standard normal of C
minus mu over towo.
So um we basically have you know y is
equal to mu plus uh sigma or toao
z. And so um z is equal to y minus mu
over towo. And so we're just
substituting in this equation for y in
terms of z.
Now uh the probability model of the
whole Brownian motion process
is
given by or we can represent it by
saying the conditional distribution of
the time t value given the time s value
is normally distributed with mean equal
to the time s value x and variance sigma
squar times the length of the increment.
So its PDF has this form.
So the notation
here is the density of y at time t given
x the value at time s.
We have this Gaussian density that's
centered at x. And the variance of y
depends on the increment from s to t
multiplied by the sigma squ.
Now with this probability model
um
it turns out this density function
satisfies the diffusion equation
and the diffusion equation is going to
arise again and again in this course um
especially when we get into the
valuation of derivatives.
And so
for now let's just
understand this diffusion equation. It
says that the partial derivative of P
with respect to time T is equal to a
multiple of the second partial
derivative of P with respect to Y.
So this is easy to verify for s= 0 and
sigma= 1.
And if we look at this
set of graphs, here's the density of
x um the given uh or let's see here's
the essentially the density of y
uh represented by x. So the notation
symbol here is we're using x now instead
of y and we're considering the initial
value of the uh brownian motion being
zero. Um
and if we increase time
then this normal density drops in the
middle
and it increases
far from the middle. And so the change
in the density
is negative near the middle
and positive
outside.
And that's because if we look at the
second derivative of this density
function,
it's positive.
Then it's negative. For the second
derivative, the curvature is negative.
And then it switches from being a
negative curvature to a positive
curvature. And those points of
inflection with the normal density are
actually at plus and minus one standard
deviation.
So if we increase the time from uh one
to two
to three or two and a half here you can
see how it's basically um dropping in
the middle of the distribution and it's
rising on the other side. So, so this
kind of motion or dynamics
um satisfies the diffusion equation
and uh so
what's I think important is just to have
a good sense of what it means when a
function such as the density satisfies
this uh diffusion equation. Now um
let's see this diffusion equation
relates to sort of a conservation of
probability for every x.
So regardless of what the sort of
starting value is, we have the
probability density integrating to one
always and the uh it turns out that this
density
is a unique solution to this diffusion
equation. So an important issue in the
mathematical
uh development framework for models is
our solutions to our equations. Do they
exist? Are they unique? In fact, for
this diffusion equation, we get uh a
unique solution satisfying uh
properties.
Okay. um in other disciplines well in
physics there's a heat equation in uh
let's see in uh the dynamics of sort of
populations there's the fauler plank
equation and cole mcgor forward equation
these these uh arise um outside of uh
mathematical brownie motion as well now
um
the interesting question
perhaps or at least the interesting
question to mathematicians is um how do
we really define Brownian motion a
formally as a stochastic process?
And so it turns out that brownie in
motion can be defined as the limiting
stochastic process
corresponding to a random walk.
So let's consider
random variables x indexed by integers
that are independent and identically
distributed.
And let's assume that those X's have
mean zero and standard deviation one.
Then if we look at the random walk with
steps X1 to Xn for the nth uh position
of the random walk. then the limiting
distribution
of the normalized random walk is
actually a standard normal distribution.
So um f of c is our standard normal
cumulative distribution function. The
standardized
random walk uh will the limit as n grows
large have a Gaussian distribution with
mean zero and standard deviation one.
So what we can do is consider
normalizing the random walk process
by
having
the sort of partial sums of the steps
uh divided by root n. But rather than
focusing just on those increments, those
integer increments, we consider for
times say between zero and one. uh we
can consider
values for time t between say integer k
/n and integer k / n + 1 /n to define a
continuous
path of bn of t given s of n and t.
And so what we then can do is say let's
consider the limit as the number of
increments uh number of steps increases
arbitrarily let's consider the limiting
process and that turns out to be a
brownie in motion process.
So with this normalized random uh walk
process,
it turns out that this limiting
distribution
is or this limiting process is invariant
to the distribution of the x's.
So if we have random walks with
independent
steps that have mean zero, standard
deviation one,
then
regardless of what that distribution is,
the limiting normalized random walk will
be the diffusion process.
So let's take a look at two cases for
the steps. Bernoli X's and Gaussian X's
which of course will be uh Gaussian
and
so here
is a
accumulation or a random walk with with
10 steps. The top panel corresponds to
unit plus one or minus one steps and the
bottom panel corresponds to Gaussian
steps.
And if we increase the number of steps
and normalize them by dividing by root
t,
we end up getting these different paths
tracing out. And so what's important in
this display is that as we let n get
arbitrarily large, the process will be
equivalent to brownie in motion. So
we're going to go up to 2,000 steps
here.
And one can see how this normalized
random walk process evolves.
And when we get to the end of the
simulation here of 2,000 steps, this is
what we have. Um, and so the key
takeaway is that the limiting process
will be a brownie in motion
and it doesn't matter what the step
distribution is in the limit.
And so this
implies that this model may be useful in
a variety of contexts where underlying
steps of the process increments may have
some distribution that's non- Gaussian
um and but the distribution of
increments over long periods of time uh
will then follow the the diffusion.
So um
so the key properties of Brownian motion
are independent increments and the
variance of those increments are
proportional to the time period between
the measures.
Now there's a reflection principle
in working with Brownie in motion that
is very powerful. Um this is an example
where
the mathematical theory is uh
a bit tricky but if you're clever at
solving the problem you may find an
elegant simple solution to the problem.
So let's just understand what it means
to be reflecting Brownian motion first.
So um
we consider brownie in motion to be the
process B
of T.
And so this will be one realization of
the path perhaps. And then if we
consider
the first time the process hits x
and define toao
um equal to the first time b of t is
equal to x.
Then
okay this is the first time
it hits that level x.
If we consider
reflecting this path
about the level at time x going into the
future. So this would be sort of going
like this
and then up like that. Okay. This is the
mathematical formula for doing a
reflection of B about X.
And we'll see some examples of this
uh in a minute. But what is important
in these reflected paths is that the
probability model for the original
process and the reflected process those
are identical.
So let's take a look at this reflected
brownie in motion simulation. So, what
I'm doing here is simulating brownie in
motion over 10,000 steps and looking at
an original process in red and then
reflecting that in green. And because of
overlapping colors, I guess the
beginning process at time zero is the
original and the reflected path. So, it
appears as the reflected. So once it
hits this level X
in red, the green reflects
about X the value and it continues
reflecting
uh across the remaining path of the
original series.
Now, here's another realization
of reflected brownie in motion. Has the
same property.
And
here's a third, you know, basically with
different realizations of brownie in
motion, we'll get different paths. Uh,
and the reflected paths have these same
properties.
Now um
the interesting
question
is
um well it's actually let me go back to
the notes here
and
the interesting question is to ask what
is
the maximum of a brownie in motion
up to time t.
So we can define m of t to be what is
the maximum value that the brownie in
motion has realized between time zero
and t.
Well, the probability
of the maximum
exceeding X some level
will actually be twice the probability
that the ending value of the process
exceeds X. So let's take a look again at
the reflected paths.
Um
so if we look at the reflected paths
about X
then
the red and the green paths
have the same probabilities of
occurring.
And
the uh if the let's see if the uh if we
look at whether the ending value of the
original Brownian motion
sorry or the ending value of
a Brownian motion is exceeds uh a given
level then
there will be twice that number twice
twice those realizations for which the
maximum exceeded that level. So for both
of these reflected paths the maximum
um let's see the maximum of the path
exceeded x
and um so
looking here
um the probability of uh
the maximum exceeding x. Well, we can
just look at
the probability of a path exceeding x at
the end point and the reflected
intervals will match those one for one.
And so we basically have the formula
that
we have
twice the final
value of the process exceeding X is
equal to the probability that the
maximum exceeds X. And we can write out
what that
probability is in terms of the standard
normal CDF.
Um now from this
result
we can differentiate
this probability with respect to x
and get the density
of the uh maximum
and um
so let's see here.
So here is a graph of the sort of
cumulative probability
of
the maximum exceeding a level x. And
this is uh basically um we're interested
in what's the probability of exceeding x
before time t. And with lower values of
x like one, the probability is quite
high. If the uh
let's see if x is is very
let's see or sorry is that x there
right okay so so so the maximum level at
the maximum is three the probability of
exceeding three is much lower the
probability of exceeding two is is in
the midway there
um and what's also Also very interesting
is that uh we can use these results
to calculate the density function for
the first hitting time of a given level.
And so importantly we have the
probability of the max up to time t
exceeding x is twice the probability
that the ending value exceeds x.
And we can differentiate this with
respect to t and we get this density
function for the density of the stopping
time for hitting a given level uh x.
So let's see here if we have that. So
here's the hitting time densities.
Um
so with standard Brownian motion if
we're looking at the time to hit the
level one
starting at zero then there's this nice
unimodal distribution for that time
which is relatively short. But if we're
looking at hitting times for higher
levels like two or three then that
hitting time distribution spreads out.
So now um let's say we can talk about
some extensions
of brownie in motion. Um one is just
reflected brownie motion around zero.
So if we have the process
bouncing off zero level
um we can think of that process being a
positive stochastic process and it's
fairly easy to show that the expected
value of this reflected brownie in
motion is a multiple of roo t
of 2 over pi And the variance is 1 - 2
over pi t.
And we can also consider absorbed
brownie in motion. Um if we consider
toao being the first time zero is the
level zero uh or a level x is hit then
um we can define our process being um
equal to the original brownie in motion
b of t or being zero for t greater than
toao. And so with absorbed brownie in
motion um these kinds of processes are
useful
for example when we have a brownie in
motion like process for a stock price
which um is generally positive so long
as the company is viable but if the
company goes bankrupt then it gets the
price gets absorbed at zero.
Now um we have
another extension um of Brownian motion
which is called the Brownian bridge.
And so
if we consider
a Brownie in motion process starting at
zero
and it goes up to
let's say time one
starting at zero
um we can define
we can define the procedure
X
which is equal to B of T
uh
let's see B of T minus T B of
one let's see is that right
minus T * B of 1 so if we consider
Um
let's see looking at well let's see this
process so x of 1 is equal to b of 1 - 1
* b of 1 which is equal to zero. Um if
we basically sort of draw
a line
to
if we consider this line as one and this
has slope B of one
then um if we subtract TB of one we're
looking at sort of pinning down the
brownie in motion.
um and looking at the distance from
sort of a constant slope t b of 1 and b
of t. And this particular uh process
actually arises
in a very interesting context
of normalized empirical distribution
functions. So
what do we want to
uh highlight here? If we have a sequence
of random variables
that are uniformly distributed
between zero and one
and we calculate their empirical
distribution function.
So it's the count of the u's less than
or equal to t / n.
Then
this empirical distribution function
will have expectation
equal to
t
and variance equal to t * 1 - t / n. So
if we think of
these
u
so we have ui is distributed uniform
from 0 to one
we have the scale from 0 to one
and we consider a value ui as a
realization
then the probability that ui is less
than or equal to t
um
is equal to t
and the uh
variance
of the indicator of ui being less than
or equal to t. This is a Berni outcome
which has variance equal to the
probability of occurring times the
complement of that. So we get this
um t * 1 minus t being the variance of
the indicator of the ui being less than
or equal to t. And then if we
consider the empirical distribution
function which is summing over these
indicators
then we get
a process which has a limiting value
which is uh basically the deviation from
its mean times scaled up by root root n
is normal with mean 0 and variance t * 1
minus t and this is actually the
brownian bridge uh process.
Now um with the uh
let's see with these examples where we
use uniform
random variables and properties of
functions of those uniforms. Um
it's important to note that for any
continuous distribution
say um y
uh distributed with some
this is the cdf
of y.
Um if we calculate
f of y
this happens to be a uniform
distribution.
So this is the probability integral
transform of any random variable. And so
when we have this property for the
empirical distribution function of
uniforms well of uniforms
um if we replace the u's which are
uniform 01 by assumption with a
distribution function f of y where we
have y1 to yn iid
with this uh cdf
f suby.
Then um
the u
i equal to f of yi
f suby of y these will be iid uniform.
So uh that's that's a really nice
result. Um and it leads to issues
involved with uh modeling model
selection.
Uh if we want to know whether a given an
assumed probability model for y's is
true or not, we can do this
transformation and test whether the
transformed series or transformed sample
is consistent with being a uniform or
not.
All right.
Well, um, with simple brownie in motion,
standard brownie in motion, we can
consider an extension of that to brownie
in motion with drift mu. So, we can
consider a drift parameter and a
volatility parameter.
Um and uh
such a process will have independent
increments
with variances um of differences
proportional to
the time interval between S and T.
And
we can
um
work with the Brownian motion with drift
um using a uh one-step analysis
and
in considering
this X
process.
So x
is equal to t mu plus sigma b of t. So
this is x of t.
Um
if we look at the increment ahead deltat
t from little t then
expanding out the representation of this
brownian motion with drift we get that
it's equal to the brownian motion at
time little t plus mu deltat t plus
sigma times the increment of the brownie
motion process from t to t plus delta t.
And
so increments of x correspond to
increments of time plus times the drift
rate mu plus sigma the volatility
parameter times the increment of the
standard brownie motion.
So our process X brownie in motion with
drift will have nonzero mean
increments and increments variances that
are proportional to the change in time.
And this
increment will have an exact normal
distribution
uh with these properties.
And what's
particularly uh important is that as we
let um deltat t the length of our
increments get infinite
then the expected squared increment of x
ends up being equal to well it's exactly
equal to the variance of that increment
plus the square of the mean.
But this square of the mean
uh is a term that is small order of
deltat t.
So our expected squared increments will
be uh
to order deltat t equal to sigma squar
deltat t and then a small order of delta
t uh term after that. Also if we
consider
powers of delta x so our increments to a
power
then when our power c is greater than
two it's equal to two here when it's
greater than two then this will also be
of small order delta t. Now the reason
why uh we're interested in
these properties is because
um we're going to be working ultimately
with um say a value of some derivative
that depends upon x of t.
So there's basically a uh derivative
value
which
depends upon
the uh
underlying
underlying uh I'll just say the
underlying asset price.
And so the dynamics of this of the
derivative prices
can
be written as a tailaylor series.
And so we'll want to be able to deal
with increments of x
and
powers of increments of x as our
valuation function uh may be expressed
if it has a tailaylor series
representation.
Okay. Um
all right. So so let's consider a
brownie the problem of uh brownie in
motion
uh underlying a gamblers's ruin problem.
So let's let x of t be brownie in motion
with drift
mu and variance sigma squared.
And we'll consider a level
an initial level equal to x that's
between two levels a and b.
And we want to
consider
the uh stopping time being hitting A or
B
and ask what's the probability that we
hit B first.
So
over time t we have
basically uh
levels a and b
and an initial level x at time zero
and we're interested in
hitting a or b.
So toao is equal to the hit time
of A or B.
And we're interested in what's the
probability of hitting B first before A.
And um
this generalizes our uh problem in the
first lecture on stochastic process
where we had a random walk with unit
steps with drift
and um or so there was a bias of maybe a
plus one versus a minus one occurring
and we wanted to solve for what's the
likelihood of hitting a level B before
level A.
So with this
um we use an infiniteesmal one-step
analysis and this solution approach is
illustrative of how many uh problems are
solved with uh stochcastic processes.
We can define U
of X to be the probability function
which is the probability that the
stopped process equals B given that it
starts at X.
And so if we consider
u of x
and write it as the expected value of u
of x plus delta x.
Then if our deltat t time increment
is
very very short then this
expectation
will equal u of x.
So the likelihood of hitting B first
will be the expectation of U of X a very
short increment into the future. And so
if we take the expectation with respect
to the delta X variable, well delta X is
X of T plus delta T minus X of T.
Then
if we
assume that our function u this
probability
is
twice differentiable then the tailaylor
series about the center x will equal u
of x plus delta x * the first derivative
plus a half delta x^2* the second
derivative plus small order terms of
delta x squared.
And so if we take an expectation of that
first
tailaylor series
on both sides, well the u of x is a
constant and then we have u prime of x a
constant times the expected value of
delta x and then plus a half the
expected value of delta x^2 time u
prime.
And we have mu deltat t is the
expectation of delta x. Sigma squar
deltat t plus little o of delta t is the
uh expectation of delta x^2.
So we have this
expansion
from the tailaylor series.
And from what we said before,
this expected value
of u evaluated at x plus delta x should
simply equal u of x.
And if that's true, then we get this
equation
for U prime and UP prime.
And if we take that
equation in U prime and UP prime, we get
and we divide by deltat T. We then get 0
is equal to mu
u u prime of x
plus a half sigma^ 2
up prime of x
and to be really precise you know a
little low uh factor to make it an an
equation. Now this
equation here is a second order
differential equation.
And so what are solutions to
this second order
differential equation?
This is
sort of an interesting challenge. Um,
let me just get some more chalk here.
It's maybe been a number of years since
people have taken uh differential
equations, right? Um
but let's uh
let's consider um let's see u prime over
u prime is equal to
let's see have I done this right
u prime / u prime is equal to - 2 mu /
sigma^ 2
And so this is the derivative
is equal to the derivative of the log of
u prime.
Um
and so if we integrate this
um we basically get log of u prime
is equal to sort of - 2 mu / sigma^ 2
x
plus
a constant.
And this is true if mu is not equal to
zero.
And so we basically get that u prime is
equal to e minus 2 mu x over sigma^ 2
times a constant.
Um
and what if we integrate
both sides of this? We then get u.
So what function has a derivative equal
to an exponential?
just the exponential. Yeah. So, so we
get u is just going to equal a constant
time eus 2 m u over sigma^ 2 x.
Um
and if mu is
equal to zero
then uh
we have the log of u prime
is equal to zero.
or the derivative.
Yeah, we or we have yeah we we basically
have the derivative of the log of u
prime is equal to zero.
So um we end up getting uh
let's see basically a linear function
for the solution. So let let me go to
the notes here. Well, we basically get u
um is equal to ax plus b if mu is equal
to zero and it's equal to this a
constant a * e - 2 mux over sigma^ 2.
All right. Well, this general solution
has to satisfy the initial conditions.
U of a is going to equal zero and u of b
is going to equal one. So if we start at
a where the uh basically we we stop at a
if we start at a so u of 0 is going to
equal zero and if we start at b um it's
equal to one we end up getting this
formula for what u is
and so what's interesting to
ask is how Does this probability vary
with different drifts and volatilities?
Okay, so here's the uh
graph of these probabilities of hitting
B before A
when
X well when A is zero.
So if we have zero here and b is equal
to three
um
then
here's the uh initial value x between
zero and three
and we have the probabilities of hitting
b before a. Okay. And if our mu is very
high, so the trend is up in the brownian
motion.
So basically if if mu is greater than
zero, then we basically have sort of an
upward trending
path on average and we get high
probabilities of hitting B first.
And as we decrease the drift from three
down to
0.5, we get this brown curve. And the
limiting case where mu is equal to zero.
So there's no drift at all
corresponds to um
the probability given by this line.
And so given the starting value X, the
closer you are to B, the more likely you
will be to hit B first and vice versa
with with A.
So
these probabilities um vary with the
different model parameters. Here is the
corresponding graph when there's a
negative
drift.
So the likelihood of
sort of hitting B
first
um
is sort of proportional when the drift
term is zero uh basically to how close
you are to be. But um as we increase the
magnitude of the negative drift we
basically get lower and lower
probabilities coming out. So that's that
solution.
Okay. So uh see the next comment about
brownie in motion is a very important
property that the brownie in motion
process is not differentiable.
So when you look at a brownie emotion
path, it looks very jagged. And in fact,
that jaggedness is characteristic of
there not being a smooth derivative or
or it's not being smooth enough to
compute a derivative. And so if we look
at the increment of the Brownian motion
from t to t plus delta t and have that
being normal with mean zero and variance
delta t the length of that increment. If
we
normalize the increment by deltat t. So
we're basically trying to look at the
approximate or the slope between t and t
plus delta t. then that has a normal
distribution with mean zero but variance
1 over delta t. So this normalized
increment
is going to not be well defined in in
the limit. It's basically going to be
equivalent to or the limiting value
basically doesn't exist. It's basically
becomes an explosive distribution.
So, so that's a very important property
of Brownian motion.
Something that is a a sort of a positive
property of Brownian motion is the issue
of quadratic variation.
And so to define quadratic variation
um we consider looking at partitions
of
the time.
So we have pi which is what a partition
of the interval from 0 to t say
where zero to capital t.
So we have a time scale finishing at t
starting at zero
and we can just draw arbitrary points tj
j equaling one up to n say
um
or one to n minus one
that are inside
this uh interval and they're ordered
If we consider
um
the partition corresponding to these
time points,
we can define sort of this a magnitude
of the partition
equal to the maximum of uh TJ
minus TJ minus one
over Okay. Um
and then we can talk about the quadratic
variation of the process
which is to look at increments
of B over these
intervals from between TJ minus one and
TJ. Square those
and sum the squared of those values.
Um this
is a sort of an appropriate term for
quadratic variation.
Um
and if we uh consider the uh
limit as the partition
width gets narrower and narrower then
we'll define this limiting value to be
the quadratic variation of the Brownian
motion process.
So we can define the quadratic variation
corresponding to a given partition and
then the quadratic variation overall if
we take the limit over partitions that
are getting uh infinitismally small.
And the claim is that this quadratic
variation
is going to equal
capital t the length of the period with
probability one.
So what does that mean? That means that
for every realization
of the process
or almost every realization,
this quadratic variation
is going to equal a constant.
So here
I'm looking at
examples of random walks
that are uh
normalized to be sort of uh between time
zero and one. So these are the
normalized random walks which are
effectively brownian or whose limits are
brownie in motion. And in the top panel
I'm drawing the path of the uh random
walk with Gaussian steps. And in the
bottom I'm drawing the cumulative
quadratic variation.
So this is up to 20 30 40 steps. Now as
we increase to
100 steps
um
this cumulative quadratic variation is
getting pretty close to the uh
time t of over which we're accumulating
the quadratic variation. And as we
increase
the number of steps
from 200
to
many more, a thousand and then 2,000.
You can see that basically the quadratic
variation of the process
is
accumulates basically to the time
period over which that's being
accumulated.
So this property is a really nice
property. What it highlights is that
there there are some
significant regularities to Brownian
motion
and the regularity here is that the
variation of the increments
um
normalizes basically to the length of
the period over which they're
accumulated. So the quadratic variation
is proportional to the time period. Now
this idea or this property of Brownian
motion is one that can be sort of
explored with time series that we might
think are well modeled by Brownian
motion.
So if we were to take um
if we were to look at um
a time series of the log of PT
divided by P 0
for PT
equal to 01
up to capital N.
the uh
basically this for prices of assets in
equity markets. This corresponds to the
log return from time zero to t.
And
that log return from zero to t might
follow a brownie in motion process
um with drift
positive return. And so you know we
basically can have this process
evolving. If we were to calculate
the quadratic variation of this process,
then if it followed
if it followed a Brownian motion
process, it would tend to grow
according to a straight line with slope
equal to uh sigma squared.
And
in empirical modeling, if we look at
this quadratic variation of an asset
and see that
it's not a straight line,
there may be periods where the slope is
low and periods where the slope is
higher and it curves around.
a way of trying to model the dynamic
volatility
could be um
suggested by studying these plots and
and using them. So it it's a very
interesting uh property. Now um
let's see I want to uh
let's see there's one last note
in the uh slide in the notes but before
doing that I wanted to um
highlight
a connection of Brownian motion
to
uh the lelass distribution. And so if we
if we have um let's see if we have B of
T
um which is Brownian motion
and we observe
uh it at uh
let's see if we if we look at um
basically X of
Okay, if we observe it at
at times t = 012
sort of discrete times.
Um
then um the delta b of t are distributed
as normal with mean
I guess it's mu t
and variance sigma squar time
1 which is delta t
and these are iid
if so we have basically
time points
0 1 2 and so forth.
If instead of observing the process at
equal increments of time,
let's
consider the possibility that the time
increments are random.
So we have um let's consider
b of t
for t equal to um
t1 t2
up to tn
where the deltat t's
the increments of time are distributed
as an exponential random variable with
some mean lambda Okay.
So, we're not observing the process at
regular intervals. We're observing it at
at random intervals.
It turns out then that the
Brownian motion process
has increments
that are lelass distributed.
So the delta b of t
then will in fact have what's called a
lelass distribution.
And so instead of having a bell-shaped
curve, which is a Gaussian distribution,
it'll be sort of a bilateral
exponential distribution about the mean.
And it turns out that
with standard and pores 500 returns,
this lelass model seems to fit the data
much better which leads to the
consideration of what are called uh
subordinated stochastic processes where
the time scale is different than our
sort of clock time.
All right. Well, let's see. The final uh
slide here for today addresses what are
called adapted processes. And so
in financial modeling,
um we can think of there being a
stochastic process X of T characterizing
relevant dynamics in the system.
And
we can think of X representing the
prices of a single asset or a collection
of assets as it varies over time. Then
as we let time increase,
there are
events that relate to what has happened
so far.
And we can think of these
f script f subt to be the information
on realizations up to time little t.
And if we consider
script f subt prime with t greater t
prime greater than t then that's
corresponds to information about all
realizations from t up until t prime. So
it's giving us more information about uh
what's happened with the process.
Well,
if we want to look at the stochcastic
modeling of a process
Y that depends on trading on assets with
dynamics X.
Then we want our process Y to be adapted
to X which essentially means we can't
see the future in trading. And so our Y
of T which is perhaps the value of
trading up until time t um is a function
only of the values of the process prior
to time t.
And so we consider transformations of
our original process to the process of
say trading gains and losses according
to some trading strategy and these will
be well defined if the process is
adapted.
So um with that
the topics connect with what we had in
our previous lecture which was we can
have martinales
defined on x
and then we can define martingales
relating to y
if when we combine sort of adapted
fun adaptive uh functions to X. And so
the martingale theory sort of extends to
modeling trading strategies effectively.
And what's interesting with those
techniques is that you end up
transforming the process
to have a constant mean. You know,
martingales are processes with a
constant mean. And uh so those arguments
um are applied again and again uh in
solving for their properties. And these
uh
option pricing you know can be expressed
um in this in this uh context as well.
All right, we'll finish there for today
and uh