The rates of improvement with generative
AI are unbelievably fast. I want to show
a series of images created by midjourney
over different generations of that
technology. So here's the prompt. Female
and male couple striking eyes and soft
lighting. So here we are in early 2022
with this response which to me is
frankly terrifying. This looks like the
stuff of a nightmare. This is nowhere
close to giving the user what they want.
Second generation, okay, the shapes are
getting a little more recognizably
human. And then we start to see it hit
its stride. These are actually kind of
people, or at least a lot of them are.
And then things just keep getting
better. It is very clear that generative
AI is a technology that's improving with
remarkable speed.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu. edu.