good
afternoon
so here we
are and let's see where where we are we
have uh introduced this energy versus
entropy diagram to summarize Concepts
and we have obtained these important um
inequalities that I called generically
clavus
inequalities that essentially um talk
about say something about how much
entropy uh must be exchanged between two
systems if these two systems start in a
stable equilibrium States
and they need to exchange energy with no
other uh
effects
so if this is the curve for stable
equilibrium stat for system a and this
is for system B we suppose that the
system a starts in this state and that
we want to extract this much energy from
it and give it to system
B okay we realize that the there is no
way to since there are no States below
the initial State we need to extract
also some
entropy
uh
okay but the problem is that system B so
if we extract entropy from system
a uh that entropy can only go into
system B because there are no other
external effects
but starting from this state system B
and receiving this much
energy the amount of entropy that it can
accommodate is only this much which is
called s Max so that's the maximum
amount of entropy that needs to
accommodate whereas for system
a this is the minimum amount of entropy
that it needs to uh give to system be in
order to find a state with this lower
energy level so we are left with a
possibility of possible states that are
on these dashed lines for system a and
for system
B that U correspond to entropy transfers
within the range Allowed by these
constraints that we have described okay
so that turns out to
be writable as a couple of
inequalities the Claus traditional
statement is as we've seen it for
infinitesimal amounts of energy
transfers this is for finite but the
concept is the same uh so today I wanted
to talk about some traditional uh
results
uh and uh we still need to Define what
we mean by heat okay first of all we
Define what we mean by work so work is a
mode of interaction in which there is no
entropy transfer and no uh transfer of
amounts of
constituents
okay uh so that's for example what
happens uh in in a weight process in a
weight process
if during the entire process there are
no external
effects then the weight
process experiences
a the system experiences a work
interaction as you may read here it says
that the weight process may be a
diabatic we call a diabatic process a
process in which uh there are only work
interactions and then we say well a
weight process may be a diabatic why why
maybe and not is a diabatic well
because a weight process is uh a process
in which the only net external
effect is uh the lifting or or lowering
of a of a
weight the net effect but you could have
some temporary effects that are
initially done and then undone
uh and in thata which may not be
describable by lifting or lowering a
weight so in that case it's still a
weight process but uh during the uh the
process there were interactions that
were may not be uh
work but for Simplicity if you want to
fix ideas
uh a good example of diabatic process is
a is a weight process in which there are
no entropy transfers all along the
process anything that has an entropy
transfer we call it non work so non
work
uh is a very broad class of proc of
processes of types of
interaction and uh in this broad class
there is one limiting condition that we
call heat interaction so we will see in
a moment and why what's defining idea
behind what we call
heat
uh it is a limiting process and it
doesn't exhaust all the possible non
work interactions so not all non work
interactions are
heat and in fact I already anticipated
the the
the last time that
uh uh this during a heat
interaction we have a very well defined
ratio between the energy that is
exchanged that we call Heat and the
entropy that is exchanged and the ratio
is equal energy to over entropy is the
temperature at which that interaction
occurs so much that therefore in order
to characterize a heat interaction we
only need to say it's heat we
uh how much energy is transferred and
what is the temperature at which it is
transferred
but what's the defining
Criterion for
heat okay one way to put it is we
we want to Define an interaction which
is completely distinguishable from
work so an interaction in which these
two systems say system a and system
B exchange energy and
entropy and nothing no fraction of the
energy that is exchanged between the
two can be recognized as
work what does it mean all right we do
it operationally let's say that uh we
extract some energy uh from system
a and let's suppose that we intercept
that energy and before giving it to
B we feed it to some
Machinery some Machinery that will try
at its best to split that energy into
part that is recognizable as work and
the rest
okay so
this sometimes I mean traditionally you
would call it a Carno engine or let's
but let's call it cycling Machinery
cyclic because it U uh it has to return
to its initial State and so whatever it
does it's not because you consume the
machine but because of the operations of
the
machine okay so in this situation
suppose we extract this much energy and
this much entropy we fed it to the uh to
the engine to the Machinery how much
work can we extract well this is a
standard problem in thermodynamics that
gets solved by writing energy and
entropy
balances so we write energy and entropy
balances for the uh systems a and system
B uh we also assume that um
uh the system a and system B uh in begin
and end in stable equilibrium
States and we write this bunch of
equations if you count the equal signs
it's how many equations 1 2 3 four five
six seven eight
equations considering the initial
temperatures as fixed
parameters the variables here are the
valious entropy
exchanged and the energy and entropy
changes for system a and system
B so you can uh if you count them I
think there are
nine variables eight equations cannot
solve the system but you can solve it
solve it for a ratio of those two of of
two of those variables and we choose the
ratio that we are interested in uh
namely the work that has
been separated out of that
stream over the in Inlet energy Inlet
into the cyclic engine so and this ratio
as we all know because we've all taken
thermodynamics before it's the carau
ratio uh between the uh two initial
temperatures of uh these
systems okay so this says that if these
two temperatures are
different this ratio is not
zero it's a definite
number it could be suppose the system B
is at 300 K 6 ma is at 600 K this is 300
over 600 is a half so
-2 is 50% all right so that means that
uh the cyclic engine here could split
50% of the received energy from a and
make it uh go into the work
Channel
sure if we want to uh complete the the
job once uh we have split this energy
and give it to the weight then we take
the weight back and give that energy to
system B so the end result is the same
we transfer the energy from A to B with
no external effects but in between we
manage to recognize a part of what What
flows from one system to the other as
work that's not what we want to call
heat we will call heat only in the limit
in which this ratio goes to
zero and that goes to zero only in the
limit in which the two
temperatures get equal or very close to
one
another and
U in terms of that train of inequalities
that we have seen the cus inequality
last time uh that interval of values if
the two temperatures are equal shrinks
to a single value and therefore uh we
get a definite uh uh
entropy transfer for a given energy
transfer and that's how we get the
famous equation that Delta s the entropy
exchanged is the energy exchanged over T
So Q over
T and of course I have stressed it so
many times but we notice that we have
defining heat here using
entropy usually it's the other way
around the traditional expositions start
from a uh some uh hand waving definition
of heat and then some definition of
temperature and then Q overt becomes the
entropy and that's the hand W I call it
the hand waving
euristic uh definition of
entropy that to be frank with you is
what got me started with this subject
because I was so unhappy of the way I
was explained the subject that I want
you to study
more it's funny you you you you hate a
subject because you don't understand it
and then you become to love it because
you no you want to understand
it all right but how does this
definition um match with our usual
understanding because if I ask you
what's heat well heat is the energy that
is transferred between our systems at
different temperature you would say well
we just said no heat is the energy is
transferred between systems at the same
temperature so is there something
wrong and in fact there isn't because
think of uh the typical model that we
adopt in uh heat transfer now suppose we
have two systems at different
temperature and we put them in
contact in the region of
contact
uh
there the their initial equilibrium if
they had the temperature initially as
soon as they go get in contact in the
region of contact you get non
equilibrium
situation but
we may
describe uh
this system as a composite of many
smaller
systems Fu mechanics you would call them
infinitesimal fluid
elements uh um in in a two-dimensional
problem you could have infinitesimal
slices of your of your solid or
body uh and then then you may you may
assume that we'll return when we do non
equilibrium we return very much to this
idea but we we subdivide our
system uh in such a way that each local
subsystem it's still known in
equilibrium State not not but not too
but it is not too far from equilibrium
okay so it turns out that we can assume
that
U this is a what we do when we describe
a temperature
distribution in our
solid okay temperature distribution
means that there is a temperature at
each location so that means that each
infinitesimal element is close enough to
a stable equilibrium state that you can
assign the temperature of that stable
equilibrium state
okay and the fact that the temperature
distribution is typically except extreme
cases uh
continuous means that if you look at uh
uh from the small partitioning point of
view uh each element has a temperature
which
is differs only slightly from the
adjacent element and so on by continuity
so each lamina or each element is at a
temperature very close to the
temperature of the near of the
neighbor and therefore the interaction
between them is an interaction in which
there is exchange of energy and entropy
and in which the two uh adjacent
elements have almost the same
temperature which fulfills our
definition of a heat interaction so
locally it is a heat interaction at the
local temperature and then with the
other element it's another heat
interaction at the lower temperature and
so or higher temperature and so on
okay this describes what I just
said the for a say a
solid so suppose we concentrate on this
infinitesimal element of of solid or
Continuum in which uh um the coord is
only like say one dimensional coordinate
is between X and X Plus DX so it's
infinitesimal
thin and it is in
contact with the element to the left and
to the element to the to the right and
for simp Simplicity let's just study a
steady state situation here and make the
energy balance and the entropy
balance so if I make the energy balance
to this
lamina uh it's a I should put on the
left hand side the rate of change of uh
the uh energy of the lamina and on the
right hand
side the net contributions of the
interactions to which that lamina is
subjected so it receives a q dot that's
now I'm assuming it is a heat
interaction so it's ites a q Dot from
the left and it gives Q dot to the
right if the if what comes in to the
left and goes out to the right is
balanced same
rates the energy balance says that the
rate of change or the rate of
accumulation of energy of my system is
zero so that property doesn't change
with time
for
entropy the entropy balance should be
written this way uh left hand side the
rate of change of the property so the r
rate of change of the entropy of this
um see this is our system the
lamina on the right hand side I have two
terms the the terms having to do with
the net uh
entropy received by
interaction and the last term is the
entropy produced by
irreversibility within the
system
so from the left the entropy that is
received the rate of which entropy is
received is Q dot over T and T here is
TX T of location
X from the right
there is an outflow of entropy which is
Q over T but here the temperature is
different it's t at X Plus
DX
okay one with a plus because it's
entering one with the minus because it's
leaving and that's the entropy balance
so if we assume a steady
state steady state
means the state doesn't change with time
the state is what it's the properties so
the proper none of the properties
changes with time including entropy so
St State implies that the stdt is equal
to
zero
then using this expression we can
compute the entropy produced by
irreversibility and
uh
we we recognize here TX and TX Plus
DX if I divide that by DX that's an
incremental ratio so that's the
derivative of t with respect to
x uh
t^2 at the denominator so this is the
result it says that the entropy produced
by reversibility is proportional to the
heat that goes
through divided by t^2 then multiplied
by
the dtdx X is the gradient in
temperature in the X
Direction with the minus sign in
front so this tells us a few things
first of all it tells
us in which direction
Q can exist for a given temperature
distribution because the entropy
produced by irreversibility can only be
uh positive or zero if you if we were in
a reversible case but it cannot be
negative so it means that Q dot here I
have t squ so it means that Q dot must
have opposite sign uh of the gradi in
temperature so the Q dot flows in the
direction of decreasing uh
temperature which is of course what we
know what Claus told us uh uh
in another way the other
day the the point though is that uh
let's look at what uh what kind of model
we're doing by assuming by assigning a
temperature
here it's really an approximation that
we are making so in the in the whole of
heat transfery mechanics when we when we
make the local equilibrium assumption it
is an
approximation which is
good in order to assign local properties
like temperature pressure chemical
potentials to the fluid
elements but we should not take it too
literally because if we were truly in a
equilibrium
State this things couldn't happen and
look at it this way U let's say that
this is the E sucess diagram of my uh
system here the lamin the infinitesimal
element uh
now uh yeah I think I it bigger here
okay
now so the
state I I draw the state of this lamina
just a bit off the stable equilibrium
State
curve and let's see what happens there
okay so this is the
state the lamina receives both energy
and entropy from the
left so that energy and entropy from the
left that received from this side
Uh
u so the left hand from the left hand
side there is a pull that tries to put
this pull the state up because want to
receive
energy and to the right because it
receives an entropy given by q do/ t
Okay the
net result is that the state is pulled
in this direction it wants to move
there on the other hand
there is also an interaction to the left
I'm sorry to the right which takes
things away it takes a energy down so it
pulls down the same amount so these are
balanced and therefore the state will
remain at this
level
but it pulls to the
left a different value because
the temperature is
different and here I at X Plus DX the
temperature I assume it's
smaller so this
ratio since it's a denominator smaller
than denominator means bigger so it
means that this pull uh to the left
is higher than the pool to the right so
there is an
unbalance and if if there were if there
weren't entropy produced by
irreversibility this state would follow
the imbalance and go backwards okay
so that to say that that is to say that
I need this
irreversibility to be produced locally
in order to maintain the steady state of
that fluid
element but in order to produce entropy
by r ibility I must not be at stable
equilibrium because at stable
equilibrium system is happy and it
doesn't uh uh rearrange things in order
it already it is in the maximum entropy
there is no uh tendency to produce
more so this is to say that
uh there is a bit of a
contradiction or at least that we have
to be careful in understanding what the
actual assumptions are this state is a
non equilibrium State otherwise it
couldn't produce entropy by
reversibility but it is close to a
stable equilibrium State and therefore
we can use uh the idea of
temperature and assign it to the fluid
element but indeed what it is is the
temperature that would be reached if I
took that fluid element and isolate from
the rest and let it relax to equilibrium
because if I shut the interactions left
and right this non-e equilibrium state
will
spontaneously move to stable equilibrium
and then it will have a
temperature and that's the temperature
that we assign to this non equum
State this is interesting
because it is the local equilibrium
model
that we are used to use in in in flu
mechanics
but you can
improve and people are doing uh
extensions of fluid mechanics treatment
in which you deal with this little
difference in entropy because uh maybe
you can assign a temperature but the
entropy of this state is slightly less
than this the temperature than the
entropy of a a truly equilibrium State
at that temperature and that difference
in
entropy does
some sometimes has
uh as as an importance for certain
applications
okay so now I want to uh talk about um
these
um very traditional ideas of heat
engines heat pumps and Refrigeration
units and see the energy and entropy
that flows and uh and also uh it gives
us the opportunity to Define what we
mean by first and second law efficiency
of devices like this
so let's start from what
we uh are seeing so let's do it uh our
own
way suppose
we we we take the closest inequalities
that we have seen the other day and
remember that these subscri
subscripts over the extreme
inequalities
uh indicate uh what the condition should
be for the strict equality to be to hold
and
here if you
remember we have an strict
equality if the system is in a stable
equilibrium State and ends in a stable
equilibrium State and it is a reservoir
so that the second derivative is equal
to
zero so
let's consider our system to be a
reservoir at temperature
ta I drop the subscrip one because for a
reservoir there is always one
temperature for all
states and let's assume that also system
B is a reservoir so also for B here I
have an equal
sign
okay uh because because I also assume
that the final states are stable
equilibrium all right so then either
this or that in if the two temperatures
are different and here we would like to
consider reservoirs at different
temperatures even large
differences
um there is no way that uh this left
extreme can be equal to the right
extreme and
therefore
somewhere there must
be uh some irreversibility either in
system a or in system
B so as to make this
uh things this train of equalities and
inequalities satisfied
so so it is necessary if I transfer
energy from a reservoir to another
Reservoir at a different temperature it
is necessary that some entropy be
generated by
reversibility uh in either one because
there are no other systems
around but suppose
we
interpose a
Machinery between that
exchange well in that case
it is
possible to have things uh to operate
without irreversibility so without
entropy uh
production this is the entropy balance
for the
Machinery it says that well if the
Machinery produces some um entropy by
reversibility it must be equal to the
difference between what it puts out from
what it
receives and uh this is the energy
balance for the Machinery it says that
uh it can produce work if it can
manage
to give to Reservoir B less and energy
than it receives from Reservoir
a okay so we
can
assume
that everything it is possible to assume
that everything has no entropy produced
by reversibility so
no no no Delta s here in system a no
Delta s ear in system B and also no
Delta s ear in system
X in that
case from the entropy point of view the
Machinery simply passes the entropy that
comes from Reservoir a and gives it to
Reservoir
B but it also recognizes that the
Machinery is made there just to
recognize that um in order to pass that
entropy to system
B it doesn't need to give it all the
energy it received from a there is an
unbalance difference which can be
um which which can be transferred
out by means of an interaction in which
there is no entropy transfer
work okay so that's the
idea of the Heat
engine Machinery that received
heat from a reservoir at high
temperature this is a heat engine
between thermal reservoirs because you
could have also heat engines between
systems that have that are not
reservoirs okay I take a a big uh piece
of Steel out of a steel making plant and
I want to recuperate the energy that it
has before it cools down that's way of U
um um recovering uh energy from
industrial processes and of course as I
cool it
down the the piece of Steel decreases
its temperature and so it's not a
reservoir that doesn't mean we cannot
compute also for that situation what is
the maximum work that you we can extract
but that's another
situation and for example the maximum
work we can extract in that case is not
the
carau
coefficient whereas here if you do
energy and entropy balances and here
they are uh I'm going sort of quickly
here I'm not going to into the details
just give you uh some ideas on by
following the flows of the entropy but
here are the full um glory of the
balance equations for um uh
for the
Machinery um from which you can
compute the
work okay here is the result so the work
that the Machinery the useful effect
that the machiner can produce is equal
to a
fraction of uh the heat that it receives
from the hot Reservoir and that fraction
is the caral
coefficient between those two
temperatures and then there is also a a
terms which detracts and that is
proportional to the entropy that is
produced by reversibility within the
Machinery it has a minor sign so if you
if the Machinery does produce entropy
that will detract and will will allow
you to get less work than the maximum
okay let's view it from the point of
view of entropy flows actually maybe we
can also do
it
uh in terms of uh e sucess diagrams
so this is system a reservoir
a and this is Reservoir
B and I'm extracting some
energy so I want
to take this much energy out of
his clearly there no stage here so I
need to extract also some
entropy at least this
much but in order to extract that
entropy I need another system that's why
I need the reservoir
B that picks up that
entropy and so it will end up here
it will end up
here provided uh since there are no
states to the right of the maximum
entropy uh I need also to provide some
energy and that energy is this much it's
Q uh received by
B okay so the difference between this
and that is the work you can also
if I if I draw a line with the slope of
of reservoir a
here this is the
work that I have extracted actually this
is W
rev because I have
assumed that system B takes just barely
the uh uh entropy that uh we need to
that is being received by System a so it
flows uh the entropy comes from uh from
a the Machinery doesn't add because it's
reversible it doesn't produce additional
entropy it simply as to uh transfer it
to system
B
and the energy that is required to
transfer uh uh that to system B is less
than QA and therefore there is a
difference and that difference can be
transferred in an interaction where
there is no entropy transfer which is
work so this is the reversible operation
if we have an irreversible operation so
if the Machinery is irreversible like
most practical machineries and therefore
it produces some entropy that entropy
will also need to be disposed of into
the uh environmental
Reservoir and therefore it will
require more
uh more energy to follow so in so the
system B I need to add not only this
entropy but also the entropy that is
produced by irreversibility so that is s
here produced in a machinery and the
Machinery is called M okay
so system B ends up
here the amount of u q is
higher and therefore the amount left the
difference which is what will be
transferred as work is less
okay good
so we have seen it in in various ways
now typically one defines the
efficiency
actually you
know uh most of you probably remembers
that
um this ratio is not called carau
coefficient like I'm calling it but it's
called carau efficiency okay which is
true in the sense that I can
define an
efficiency we are going to call it here
first low
efficiency as the ratio of the useful
work so the
work uh divided by uh the the energy of
the resource that you have used in this
case the resource is the hot Reservoir
so the energy extracted from the hot
Reservoir so this ratio is the first low
efficiency
and the result and the the result of the
energy balances shows
that U the the Caro coefficient is the
upper limit of this efficiency which is
reached when s here is equal to
zero so the car
coefficient is equal to the first LW
efficiency for the reversible engine
what is
somehow um inconvenient of first LW
efficiencies is
that you know usually want say if
something is 50%
efficient uh I would I would say oh why
why aren't you doing better no there
there is 50% room for improvement
uh not here though because uh there's no
way suppose you have a TA is equal 600
and 600k and TB is 300K so the carau
coefficient is 1 half
50% that's the maximum you can do
there's no improvement you cannot
improve so it would be better to have a
to call efficiency or to
so people have introduced the second low
efficiency which Compares what you
actually
obtain and put it in the numerator to
the maximum that you could have
obtained given the constraints and the
physical laws so without violating
anything uh okay so in that case this
ratio for the reversible uh case is one
so it's
100% And so if the efficiency is 100%
there's no room for
improvement if it is not uh 100% or one
it means that there is a something that
reduces that
and that something is the entropy
produced by irreversibility so uh by
thinking in these terms this second low
efficiency allows you to
identify uh the
actual
um places in your um Machinery or power
plant uh
that uh that are the the sites where
entropy gets produced by irreversibility
because that the higher the entropy
produced by reversibility the Lesser
this efficiency so the more room for
improvement and in fact a lot of energy
uh technology
engineering uh is
into uh improving this efficiency that
means identifying where the
reversibilities are and removing them or
reducing them optimizing from that point
of view
okay so let's
uh do even more
quickly uh the same idea but for a
refrigerator
unit it's again a situation in which I
have two reservoirs ta and
TB and uh
I identify the
environment as
the system at higher temperature
now
and the other
system at the lower
temperature is for example the
refrigerator cell the the the the room
in that you want to keep refrigerated so
and you want to keep it refrigerator so
it seem typically uh there are heat
losses from the walls of this uh uh
refrigerator you need to compensate by
removing
heat so the the unit wants to extract
heat from a low
temperature from a temperat from a
reservoir which is at lower temperature
than the uh
environment so if we go on our
uh do again
the
construction
here now I want I have my system B which
is the refrigerating refrigerator uh
room you want to uh extract
energy and uh as usual in order to
extract energy you need to extract also
entropy so this is QB
out and this is
s
the
out so if I have this entropy going uh
somewhere I need to put it to another
system now this system a which is my my
environment is there
and I would like to give
it uh this much
entropy but in order to give it I I also
need to give some uh energy which is
actually
higher than this
one because the the because it's the
environment is hotter so it has a higher
slope so if I plot here the
slope of system
B this is the the energy that I extract
from system
B
okay but I need to give to a more energy
in order for it to accommodate the
entropy that I must extract from B so
this much
is the
work that I need to
spend
okay and of course if the Machinery is
irreversible and it produces also some
entropy by irreversibility not only I'm
not I must accommodate this much entropy
but but I must
accommodate even
more that's the reversibility of the
Machinery this
much so system a must go up there and
therefore I need to spend more work so
this is what was W
rev and this much is W uh say IR
revers okay now also here
the Carno
coefficient or similar does play a
role
usually in practice when you buy a
refrigerator you
uh um you want to know what the cop the
coefficient of performance is which is a
first flow uh ratio it's the ratio of
the useful the cooling effect which is
the energy you extract from the low
temperature
cell to the uh
work typically electrical work that you
need to spend in order to uh this to do
this and this
cop has the highest
value and then there is a term which is
always is positive and that is bigger
and bigger the
more IR revers irreversible is your
Machinery
okay also here
cop is typically a number greater than
one doesn't give you an indication of
what
the room for improvement is
the second LW efficiency
instead does and again we can Define it
as the actual use useful effect divided
by uh the best uh useful effect the
maximum useful effect you could obtain
uh with a reversible
Machinery that
two as a maximum value equals to one
100% in that case there is no room for
[Music]
improvement and it's less than one due
to the entropy produced by
diversability the last of these series
of
uh of
traditional uh machineries say is the
heat
pump the heat pump it's very similar to
a
refrigerator more or less the same
equations except that
now what switches is the position of the
environment of your environment the
environmental rest
OFW whereas for the
refrigerator you
were uh extracting energy from something
which is colder than the
environment in the heat pump you want to
put energy in a a a reservoir which is
hotter than the
environment so now the environment
system
be but the idea is more or less the same
that
um except that the useful effect now is
not the cooling of B but is the heating
of a you want to heat up something like
the house in a
and using heat pump which is nowadays
been done
worldwide at least in places where you
need Heating in the winter time
and so the useful effect effect is QA
therefore you define a different cop
it's called cop but it's
different different
definition
uh and uh
this time you
put in the numerator the useful effect
which is the heat uh given to the
hot
system divided by the work that you have
spent in order to do
it and
again the second law
efficiency is the ratio
between the useful
effect of your actual machinery and the
useful effect of the reversible
Machinery so uh that uh it would be
equal to one for a reversible machinery
and it's less than one if there is
entropy produced by your Machinery here
okay
so since now we are talking about some
practical
aspects let's talk
about
uh another chapter of of themodynamics
that has to do with establishing the
properties of substances at stable
equilibrium and let's see this is an
important
chapter uh
many scientists have devoted their lives
in constructing the properties of
substances for
example to
stay
uh here
um Professor Kenan in
1940 uh maybe earlier um spent a lot of
time developing the steam
tables which is uh the properties of
water so how do we measure properties of
substances in stable
equilibrium well much of uh
uh um the tools that we have is
uh to is related to the the conditions
for Mutual stable equilibrium that we
have
developed like equality of temperature
equality of pressure the quality of
chemical
potentials the the good thing is that if
you have a
thermometer what is a thermometer
thermometer is a is a
system in which in some way you have um
put a scale in which you can read uh uh
the uh the value of the temperature then
what you do you you you stick it in
contact to the system you want to
measure and
uh you leave enough time so that you
convince yourself that the two systems
have reached the mutual equilibrium and
if you are convinced that they are in
mutual equilibrium then the theory says
that the two temperatures are equal so
by
by uh
reading the the temperature of the
thermometer you have measured the
temperature of system a of which you may
know
nothing so it's an indirect uh uh
measurement of a
property
similarly the
monometer you can construct the
monometer as uh so that you can read out
a scale
uh the value here you put it in
equilibrium Mutual equilibrium with your
system by drilling a little hole in this
uh in the boundary and uh and um with
either a little piston or some um
moving interface like
here
um if you're convinced that they are in
mutual equilibrium reading the pressure
of B gives you information about the
pressure of system a so this is one way
of measuring
it
yeah
uh this is just to remind U of that
proof that I don't want
to go into details all but that it shows
why the pressure can be
measured by measuring a force per unit
area
anywhere in on the boundary of your
system so you take the boundary of your
system when it is in stable equilibrium
drill a
hole and substitute that piece of wall
with the movable wall and then you find
a force per unit area that keeps that
wall where the original one was once you
found it that you have measured the
force per unit area that
balances the pressure pressure of your
system and when you are in stable
equilibrium that Force per unit area is
equal no matter where you go and do this
uh
procedure whereas off
equilibrium it can be
uh you can always measure force per unit
area but it may be non uniform not equal
everywhere and there is no pressure
because you're not in
equilibrium
other another kind of measurement that
we
can
do is like uh uh the so-called Jew
apparatus in which you input some
mechanical energy in your substance or
in
your in a piston or in a in a variable
volume or in a constant volume container
you put some energy in
wait for the system to go to a new
stable equilibrium and measure uh
how much um they measure the how much
the temperature has changed for your
system
so mg Delta Z represents the ra the
amount of energy that you have put in in
the form of of work so you produce a
work interaction uh and put energy into
your system let it relax towards uh
until it reaches equilibrium so new
temperature compute the difference
between the new temperature and the
initial temperature delta T this ratio
turns out to be equal to this the
partial derivative of this property that
we we're going
to Define in the moment and that's
that's the property that we call heat
capacity at constant pressure it's a
stable equilibrium State Property we
obtain it from the fundamental relation
there is one heat capacity uh for for
when that is equal to the same ratio
when you do the experiment at constant
volume and there is another heat
capacity when you do it at constant
pressure so let's start from the
constant
pressure because G this gives us also a
procedure
to
Define um the enthalpy so and to get to
this derivative
that turns out to represent this result
of this measurement so it's important
because it is the way in which you
measure that
property Let's Do It um starting from
the fundamental relation in energy
form and this is its
differential so
H in a moment we will see that um this H
is a
particular uh transform of the
fundamental relation which when we
change variables but for the moment
let's just take it for um as a abrupt
definition let's say that we call H the
sum of energy plus the product of
pressure and volume we call it
enthalpy then by taking the differential
of this expression and recalling that
the differential of a product is equal
to P DV plus
VDP and where I see da I
use the differential that I have written
up here so I substitute and this is what
I'm left
with from this
expression I can view this
expression as a the
differential
so you see the the independent variables
are under the D so uh DS DP DN so I I
can
since if so this is would be the
differential of a function in which H is
a function of s
pnn and also the coefficients of the
differential are the partial derivatives
so for example the t is the partial of H
with respect to
S the partial of what the partial of
this function so the partial of a
function in which the enthalpy is
expressed as a function of s p and
N so that's the
temperature now in the business of
measuring
uh
properties we like to have instruments
okay so we have a thermometer measures
temperature bar monometer measures the
pressure there is no energy
meter there is no entropy
meter we measure energy and entropies
indirectly
through
uh temperature and
pressure and
volume so let's do that also
mathematically so you look at this um
equation here and this other equation
then consider it as a system of two
equations in which you want to eliminate
the property that is hardly
measur difficult to meas hard to measure
which is the entropy so for example
solve
this
um expression this function here as a
function instead of t as a function of s
write it say s is a function of
T and then take that s and put it in the
original function up
there you manage to find H as a function
of tpn so you change the independent
variables to ones that can be easily
measured temperature and
pressure so this new function and this
is the way you have obtained it so we
have a precise way recipe to obtain that
function if we start from the
fundamental relation
is of this function you can take
derivatives for example derivative of H
with respect to
T is what we call the specific heat
sorry the heat
capacity uh at constant pressure and it
is a function of T and
P so pressure and temperature we can we
can measure heat capacity we can measure
with one of these with this uh
instrument here and so this is a fully
measurable
function a similar
procedure we can follow to define the
heat capacity at constant
volume so we start again from the
fundamental
relation and notice that the temperature
which is the derivative of partial
derivative of e with respect to
S is uh being a function of this
variable I mean a derivative of function
of these variables has the same
independent variables so it's also a
function of
sbnn and also here play the game of
eliminating
the uh not so easy to measure property
entropy so
solve this as s s function of T and
substitute up there to obtain that the
energy a new function in which the
energy is expressed in terms of the
independent variables temperature and
volume these
are things that are easy to measure
because temperature you measure with the
uh
thermometer volume you measure with
the the
stick okay so the first derivative of
this function the partial of e with
respect to T is
called the uh heat capacity at constant
volume and it is the thing that you
measure with the other other the Jew
apparatus at constant
volume soain
that but we can also do this other uh
procedure to take uh okay the
temperature like before here but now we
make a system also with the pressure the
pressure is the derivative of e with
respect to
V and being a derivative of a function
with these independent variables it also
has the same independent variables
eliminate entropy also from these
two that results in a relation between
pressure volume and temperature which we
call the equation of State pressure
volume and temperature tempature are
also easily measurable
stuff that's the equation of state and
the partial derivatives of this equation
of state so the derivative of V with
respect to
T
says how much the volume of your
substance changes as as you vary the
temperature as you heat it up so it's
the
a coefficient of expansion if you do it
divided by V it's the the percentage
increase in volume per given amount of
given increase in temperature uh
and uh and you can measure this when you
do uh the experimented constant pressure
or the second the other derivative
derivative of V with respect to
P it says
uh how much uh the substance get reduced
in volume if I increase the
pressure so the reduction is minus Delta
V per unit of uh increasing pressure and
again if I divide by V is the uh
percentage
uh reduction in volume
so this when you do the experiment uh
increase the pressure at at constant
temperature this is the isothermal
compressibility of the
substance being derivatives of the
equation of State they are function of
TMP and these are easily measured
because it's simply relates measuring
changes in volume measuring
temperatures so the differential of the
equation of State done
at fixed
amounts uh is
has these two coefficients isobaric
expansion and isothermal compressibility
appearing uh directly
here there are other things that you can
measure in other experiments for example
an interesting one
is the speed uh of sound
propagation should be an off here
and or the jewel Thompson coefficient in
in the expansion of a of a gas in a
throttle which occurs at constant
enthalpy you measure the change in
temperature
over drop in pressure and it can be
positive and negative and uh that
allows you that is related to um the
things the properties that we have
already defined before
so and also the the May relation shows
that um CP CV Alpha p and uh Capa T are
not
independent so you don't need to measure
all four of them you just need to
measure three
um let me skip that one for a moment no
no it's not no I need it I need it okay
in order to measure chemical
potentials I do need first to show that
chemical potentials can be written as
functions of temperature and pressure
so because you see uh if the chemical
potential is defined as the partial of e
with respect to n at constant s and
V but that way it isn't easy to measure
because of the S so UI is the partial of
e with respect to n i at constant s v
and all the other uh ands
held well I shouldn't say that where
where the where the function that I am
taking the derivative of is a function
of SV and all the
ends
however this when you view it this way
it's not easy to measure because I don't
have an energy meter and I don't have an
entropy
meter so the trick is to change
variables and one way to do it is to uh
Define a function which is called the
Gibs um free
energy uh for the moment think of it as
just an arbitrary definition so I say
take defined as energy minus TS plus
PV write the
differential use the differential of a
fundamental relation in order to express
de
and here is what you're left
with this expression shows that you can
view this function G as a a function of
the independent variables that appear as
under the D of the differential so the
temperature the pressure and the
amounts so G has as say natural
variables TP and
n and from and since this is the
differential of that function the
chemical potential
can therefore be written now also as a
uh the partial of G with respect to
ni and since it is a partial of G which
is a function of T pnn it's also
function just t
pnn Okay so the chemical
potential we would like to measure it it
is very important to determine the
properties of uh multicomponent
systems but it cannot be measured
directly there is no
uh chemical potential
meter however it can be measured in
directly via the definition of what we
call the partial pressure of a component
in the
mixture here the experimental setup is
this I have my mixture in which I have
many components and they are in a stable
equilibrium State they are at some
pressure some temperature and they have
their chemical potentials and so
on so what I do is to drill a hole in
the wall somewhere of my
system and substitute the wall with a
membrane a semi oror medium or a semi-
peral membrane where only MO ules of
type I can cross the others
don't
okay so I put on the other side I I I
put on the other side uh molecules of
substance
I and uh with the Piston I I keep them
there and I measure the force per unit
area that is necessary
to keep them uh uh in U in mutual
equilibrium when I reach Mutual
equilibrium between this this little
system I I the double script I we use as
a way to to say that it is a pure
substance so in this little
box uh there is only substance
I there is whereas in the mixture there
is substance I mixed with other
stuff okay when we are in mutal
equilibrium cross this
membrane we have proved um also the
other day
that the conditions for mutal
equilibrium are equality of
temperatures so the temperature of
system I I must be equal to the
temperature of the mixture and the
quality of chemical potentials for for
this for the substance that can be
exchanged uh so the substance is I and
so I need that the chemical potential of
substance
I of the
mixture must be equal to the chemical
potential of the pure substance I just
on the other side of a semm membrane
okay
okay here I also put the uh functional
dependence because I used what we just
proved before that the chemical
potential or functions can be can be
written as functions of T andp and so
these are the functions that we're going
to use for this
measurement okay and so
by looking at this equation
which
is required by the condition for Mutual
equilibrium we see that uh inside the
independent variables are all
easily measurable things
temperature
pressure and also this pii
it's the pressure of the system on the
other side of the semi membrane we call
that pressure the partial pressure of
constituent I in the mixture it is a
property of the
mixture and it can be
measured and by measuring it and by
knowing how the chemical potential of
the pure substance depends on so if I
know this for the pure substance I can
infer from that measurement
the chemical potential of the
constituent in the mixture this is how
we characterize uh
mixtures so here is a little summary of
properties that we have talked about so
far energy
entropy also the volumes and the
parameters that enter in the uh the
amounts of constituents entering the
definition of our
system these things are these properties
are defined for all
states equilibrium and non
equilibrium then we defined some other
properties uh based on the fundamental
relation for stable equilibrium
States so clearly these are defined only
if you have a fundamental
relation uh so it's they're definally
for stable equilibrium
States temperature pressure chemical
potentials the enthalpy that givs free
energy the enthalpy because it it's it's
a a e plus
PV uh and P is the pressure pressure is
defined only for stable equilibrium or
the Gibs free energy as the p and the T
also so it also is defined only for
stable equilibriums
St and then we can also we also defined
the these four properties today uh the
heat
capacities
the coefficient of expansion and the
coefficient of com uh
compressibility these
ones also are restricted for equilibrium
States but they're even more restricted
because some of those uh mathematical
steps
that for example if I go
back
here when I do this eliminating one
variable uh I can do that
uh only if some derivative uh is not
equal to zero so for example uh if um
the the partial of t with respect to S
is equal to zero I cannot invert that
function because it's not uh it's not
monotonic uh
and and this is what happens for example
when I
have two phase
States like liquid and Vapor
coexisting in that case uh
some of these
functions uh are not defined or which is
the same
uh take up infinite value infinite
values
okay okay so we go back to
here
now this
also
says that if we do our
measurements and we can for a given
substance or for a set of
mixtures
develop or measure experimentally these
functions the alpha p is a function of
TP and
composition Capa T is a function of
temperature pressure and composition the
specific heat at constant PR I'm sorry
the the heat capacity at constant
pressure is a function of temperature
pressure and comp iOS and the chemical
potentials as a function of temperature
pressure and composition if I have all
these
functions then with these functions I
can
reconstruct the fundamental relation so
I know everything that I need to know
about the stable equilibrium states of
that
substance and
actually the Reconstruction is done
through uh these relations here for
example the energy
uh this expression for the energy
here can be
related to these properties in this
way so if I
integrate from one temperature to
another from one pressure to another
this
expression I can get variations in
energy the entropy also is related this
way the enthalpy is related that
way and
uh and these are General forms that are
valid for any pure
substance if you also need to
consider uh mixtures then you need to
generalize this to use the Expressions
where also the N
appears so in this way we have uh
uh a way to
measure the fundamental relation of
substances
okay
now
yeah yeah we have five minutes I can do
this I want to
show that
um some of these
function like the enthalpy and the GS
free
energy
uh are obtained
as LeAndre
transforms of the fundamental relation
legan transform is a particular
procedure
that we can explain uh in this way with
start with a function of a single
variable
so suppose you give me a function of a
single variable like U uh any function
but to
simplify let me suppose that this
function is a
um either convex or concave and
monotonic monotonic so that I can uh um
invert and play with it okay so usually
we Define a function I'll call it f of f
of
Y meaning
that for each value of y I get the value
of
F and as I move y the function tells me
how F
moves but there is an alternative the
idea of Leandra is that there is an
alternative description
because that function also has a tangent
and has a line tangent to every
Point
okay so this tangent is
characterized by two uh items one that
we will call uh
Lambda which is the angular the
coefficient the slope of the line
and this other value here that I we call
L which is The
Intercept at y equal
Z
okay so the idea Leandra is that uh you
can if you
draw like it's a sketched here this
slopes at every point of of the line you
get a family of
lines the envelope of which is your
original
curve
okay each line is characterized for a
given
Lambda for a given
Lambda by an
L I change the point so I take another
Lambda suppose I want some this l this
this
much okay so I fix Lambda so say this is
Lambda one now I fix Lambda
and that gives me L of L of
two so selecting
a uh a value of
Lambda specifies select the point in
which the
tangent as that slope of the original
curve and therefore when you place the
your line there it also selects an
intercept so there is a relation between
Lambda and
L and that relation is the Lend
transform of your
function the procedure
is uh runs this way that you
U you take the function you write the
equation for the U partial for the
derivative and
then you define
l by the geometrical construction so
it's the function
f
minus this distance here
okay and this distance
here is equal to the horizontal
segment times the slope so the tangent
of this angle so this Lambda so L is
equal to F minus Lambda time
y so it corresponds to that
description and uh I think the time is
up for today so we'll yeah we'll pick it
up from uh from here uh the next uh time