okay so today what we're going to do is
uh talk about health economics um I
essentially this is sort of really just
an applied lecture where I want to talk
about a particular policy topic and
throw in along the way what we've
learned in this course that informs you
think about that topic so this just an
example of how you can take the set of
things we learn the semester and help
understand really one of the one of the
two or three most fundamental public
policy issues of our time and also the
one I happen to work on so uh the one
that I find particularly important uh
and appealing okay so let's set the
stage talk about Healthcare economics by
talk about Healthcare in the US and
let's just throw out a couple of facts
the US in
1950 spent 4% of our GDP in 1950 we
spent 4% of our GDP on Healthcare that
was that's pretty big that's a 25th of
the economy but it was you know the 10th
biggest sector of the economy
today we spend more than 18% of our GDP
on Healthcare it's the largest single
sector of the US
economy okay so we have the spending on
healthc care has grown enormously
now do you have to the question is um
has it been worth it both overall and
distributionally so overall if we want
to think about how it's been worth it we
can't look at many people look at these
numbers say oh my God we've got a crisis
well that number does not tell you
there's a
crisis okay what we care about is what
has been the benefit and cost of this
growth in healthcare
spending okay maybe this number was just
disturbingly low and this is the maybe
this number is still too low maybe we're
not at the right level you can't look at
these big numbers and this is sort of
how we want to you to think coming out
of this class is to not have the
knee-jerk reaction you'll do and say oh
my God we have a crisis think well do we
have a crisis it's been worth it and the
answer to that is
mixed on the one
hand if you look at the overall average
health of the US the growth and spending
has been worth it that is as I've
referred to a few times in this class
economists have methods for trying to
Value Health improvements trying to
Value life I talk about them more in
1441 we'll get the methodology now but
we have methodology putting a value on
extending life a value on improving
health and by those estimates it's been
massively worth it healthc care sucked
in 1950 babies who are born prematurely
we're four times as likely to die okay I
have a friend just had a baby eight
weeks prematur at four pounds that baby
would have been dead in 1950 they just
went home today the baby's perfectly
healthy okay if you had a heart attack
in 1950 chances were you were going to
die today you'll live four times many
people live after heart attacks today as
they did in 1950 the odds are four times
higher or you guys aren't having babies
or having heart attacks it's a relevant
number okay how many skiers do we have
here okay if you were skiing in 1950 and
you crashed and tore your ACL or or or
spraying your your MCL or one of those
things okay you're in the hospital for a
week you're on crutches for six weeks
and you arthritis the rest of your life
today you get arthoscopic outpatient
surgery within a day you go home that
night and you're back on the slopes
within a few weeks okay healthc care is
just much much better and if you look at
a typical value of how Economist value
improved Health it has been worth it we
are better off as a nation
spending 18% of GDP on healthare today
than we were spending 4% in 1950 but
there's another way to test that what's
the other way economists would say if
someone says well we're worse off today
how would an economist challenge
them how could you prove that people
don't want 1950s Healthcare 1950s prices
yeah no one's demanding 1950s Healthcare
at 1950s prices no one's out there
saying oh yeah I want crap happy
healthare for low prices it's sort of
the opposite of the airline example
remember with Airlines we talked about
people about service but the truth
is if it was really a problem there'd be
expensive High service Airlines which
there aren't okay it's the same thing
with
Healthcare so Fact one is we spend a lot
more Fact Two is overall it's been worth
it fact three is the distributional
consequences have been very bad so the
other fact the reason people'll say us
Healthcare is bad you'll hear facts like
we are the most expensive by the way 18
% plus we are on average about a third
relative to what unit space based on our
income richer countries spend more on
Healthcare it is a luxury good as your
income goes up you spend more of your
income on improving your
health okay it's a luxury good the
income eless is greater than one so
richer countries do spend a higher share
of the CHP in healthcare but if you draw
a line we're way off that line we spent
about a third more than you'd expect or
other way put is Rel to other countries
at our income love we spent about a
third more than You' expect and if you
look at overall outcomes despite the
fact I just told you about how we're
healthy overall since
1950 today our outcomes on International
standards are
terrible we are about 16th in the world
in infant mortality on any measure of
sort of Health outcomes we look terrible
other other countries so we spend a
third more than we
predict based on our income we have
outcomes interntional comparison that
are terrible well how's that consistent
with the facts I just said that's worth
it it's consistent because the the
outcomes that we point to are driven by
the bottom of our society which is not
true in other countries a white baby
born in America today has the same
chance of seeing their first birthday
it's a white baby born in Europe a black
baby born in America today has a lower
chance than a black baby born in
Barbados okay we basically and I talked
about we talked the inequality lecture
about those neighborhoods three miles
apart Freddy Gray's neighborhood versus
the rich neighborhood a 17-year
differential life expectancy the bad
outcomes in the US are not relevant for
the people in this room for the people
in this room the US is where you want to
be for healthcare in terms of
outcomes what's the way economists would
test
that what's would prove that for those
who are in the system the US is the best
place to be
well every year about 1 million people
come to America at Medical Care no one
leaves they might go to k keeper drugs
but no one's flying to France for
surgery they fly to America once again
that's how economists think about
testing hypothesis we look at the data
the real preference is for those who are
in the system we have the best
Healthcare in the world the reason our
outcome is so terrible of to other
countries is we have taale outcomes
other countries don't have and that's
about access and
Equity so the bottom line is where we
stand today a system that's
expensive that delivers flows in the
system as good outcomes as other places
but it's highly
inequitable last point I did say a white
baby born America day is the same
chaning their first birthday as one born
in Europe but not a not a 50% better
chance even though we spend 50% more in
healthcare so while we spend 18% and
it's been worth it we still may waste a
lot the fact that it's worth at 18%
doesn't mean we couldn't have equally
good outcomes at 12 or 13% it doesn't
mean we're on the efficient Frontier it
doesn't mean producing Healthcare
efficiently in other words there were so
many good opportunities to improve
health that even though we might be
wasting money we're still better off
spending it and that's the key Point
remember to avoid one lesson from this
course is let's avoid extreme thinking
if you have a something that's wasteful
it doesn't mean it wasn't worth doing
you've got to compare the benefits in
the cost we are probably and I'll come
back to this relative to the efficient
Frontier wasting a lot of money we can
produce the same Healthcare outcomes in
the US for a lot less money that doesn't
mean we're worse off today than we used
to be it just means we could be even
better okay questions about any of
that now what I want to do then is focus
on two topics
today the first topic is the fairness
topic and that revolves around insurance
coverage so I want to talk about the
fact the US is the only developed nation
in the world without Universal coverage
buing
insurance and what we're doing about it
the second topic is what do we do about
the fact that we spend much more on
Healthcare to other countries that have
better or at least comparable outcomes
to ours so let's talk about the first
topic the US is the only country in the
world where citizens face the risk of
being uninsured so I want you to cast
your mind back to when you were little
kids before
2010 okay before the Affordable Care Act
the way the US looked in
2009 was about 60% of
Americans had employer sponsored
insurance they had insured through their
employer like I have through
MIT about 20% of
Americans had public
Insurance okay that's insurance through
two programs
Medicare Medicare which is in Universal
coverage for the elderly so do have
Universal coverage Once you turn 65 and
Medicaid which is Health insures
coverage for the poor so we had public
coverage entitlement but only if you
were poor or
elderly okay the other
20%
okay why because remember what I talked
about insurance market equilibrium okay
I talk Insurance market equilibrium I
said give an adverse selection several
things can
happen Okay and the thing that is going
to happen now I don't know what they
could do with that on the video they
bleep my swears I guess they G have to
like like sorry I'll just I'll erase
that because I'm GNA be in trouble on
the
video they'll just they'll have to like
white it out or something um so um I am
I am I'll have you know proudly I'm the
most Bleak professor at MIT so um at
least who has videos online um so
um what we have a situation with with
other 20% of people the insurance Market
is broken if you work for a big employer
the insurance Market Works remember we
learned our insurance lecture people
want to be insured that's optimal they
want to smooth their consumption across
States if you work for a big employer
like MIT it works MIT offers me
insurance they offer that insurance at
basically a pretty fair rate given the
health risk of people at
MIT okay and I buy it and MIT subsidizes
it for to help me buy it if you public
insurance is typically free or low cost
for everyone else if you want an insur
to walk in insurance company and say I
want Insurance they're like whoa why do
you want Insurance you must be sick if
you want insurance I'm going to test the
Wazoo out of you deny you if you're at
all sick if you're not sick I'll offer
you insurance but if you get sick I'm
going to drop you so essentially there
was no insurance essentially the rest of
this 20% of the population had no access
to insurance and we know that's a huge
market failure we know that people are
much worse off uninsured than
insured we had about 50 million American
about the majority of this number were
uninsured and about another four to
five% of
Americans uh were uh about 15% of
Americans were uninsured about 45% of
Americans were buying Insurance because
they were the healthy ones who could get
in the market and buy
it so what did we propose to do about
this well we proposed to do
was first proposed here so um by
Governor Mitt Romney a Republican and
then eventually picked up by President
Obama democrat was to propose what I
call a three-legged stool solution to
this problem I actually wrote a comic
book to explain this uh it's called a
graphic novel but it's a comic book uh
ambitiously entitled Healthcare reform
um it's like nine bucks on Amazon and uh
to try to explain this I think of
graphic images about how we think about
this law and I think it's a three-leg
stool leg one is to say insurers you can
no longer
discriminate anyone of a given age you
could charge old people more than young
people within reason and you could
charge people in an expensive area more
than a less expensive area within reason
but for a given age and a given area if
I come in coughing and hacking and sick
you cannot charge me more than someone
who comes in running having run in and
looks healthy okay you can no longer
discriminate you can't charge women more
than men for health insurance which they
did you can't charge sick people more
more than healthy for health
insurance
okay but we realized that alone would
not work and in fact we had evidence why
that wouldn't work because in the 19907
States including Massachusetts tried to
do that they passed laws which said for
those will leave these people alone but
for there remaining of people the people
have to buy in what we call the
non-group
Market the people left to buy in the
non-group market okay for those people
okay we going to say insurers can't
discriminate what do you think happened
so think of yourself as an insurer
you're the guy like I set you up selling
Insurance to MIT students you suffer a
massive adverse election or that risk
and I tell you you can't
discriminate what do you
do you quit you say well forget it the
Market's gonna fail if you're G to tell
me I can't discriminate I'm not going to
make money because I know I'm going to
get selected against so I'm just going
to bag and that's what happened the
insurance markets collapsed
in all these states which is you can't
regulatorily enforce a pooling
equilibrium by just saying you should
have to charge everyone the same that
doesn't work if only the sick buy so the
market
collapsed so that's why I realize we
need the second leg of the stool and by
we I do actually mean we like I work
with Governor Romney on this uh and help
design this program okay we as we need a
second leg of the stool which was a
mandate that individuals buy health
insurance which was to say look if if
we're going to tell insurers they have
to charge the pooling price then we got
to enforce the pool and the way you
enforce the pool is a mandate so an
individual it's called an individual
mandate requirement that people buy
health insurance or they have to pay a
big
fine okay so that was the second leg of
this tool say we're going to have a fair
prices insurers be able to offer a
pooling price because they know what the
average price is going to be because
everyone's going to buy but that laid a
third problem in 2004 before we were
writing this law the average family
health insurance plan was
$122,000 and the US poverty
line that the family plan and the US
poverty line for a family of four was
about
$188,000 you can't mandate a family pay
two-thirds of their income for health
insurance that's both INF feasable and
bad
politics so we need the Third Leg of the
stool which was subsidies we need to
make health insurance affordable for the
lower income groups
so the pool was the three legs of the
stool were no
discrimination or what we call an in in
health insurance terms Community
rating which means you have to charge
everyone the same
thing that matched with the
Mandate was the second leg matched with
subsidies
okay to basically make it
affordable so essentially the idea was
by doing all three things at once you
make health insurance affordable for
low-income people we set up a program
called Commonwealth Care remember I
talked about the poverty line in our
lecture on inequality we said anyone who
lived below three times the poverty line
we would heavily subsidize their health
insurance to make it
affordable then we said make it
affordable we're going to make you buy
it we're not make it it free make it
affordable we set have a slide what's
called a sliding income scale scale you
had to pay a certain percent of your
income to get health insurance we have
sliding income scale we're going to make
it affordable we're going to make
everyone buy it and make insurers offer
insurance with no discrimination offer
Community rating and we passed that law
in
2005 okay what happened 20 God now my
dates are bad was it 2006 I don't even
remember getting old anyway 2005 2006 I
don't remember um what
happened was uh an enormous success now
you won't find any more any more biased
than me okay on this topic but I think
it's hard to argu as anything but a
success how would you measure success
first of all was it popular yes it never
had below 60% public support Second of
all did it achieve its goals what were
its two goals the first goal was
covering uninsured people the mass
uninsurance rate fell fell by 2third
bring the insurance rate to 3% in
Massachusetts which is lower than which
is as low as many countries in Europe
that was a success
the third Al was did it fix the broken
non-group Market the market we' broken
by just trying to do this alone we tried
to this alone first and broke the market
and the answer is it did fix it many new
insurers came in prices came down
50% so what you had at the end of the
day after this was a state where anyone
regardless of Health could get fairly
priced health insurance subsidized if
they couldn't afford
it so this was viewed as a huge success
let me say on the right and the left
okay if I can develop into politics a
little bit because I'm personally
personally upset about this okay this
was a law signed by a republican
Governor the speaker at the event where
they signed it the main speaker on the
podium was a conservative someone for
conservative think tank this was viewed
as a victory for individual
responsibility conservatives praise
individual responsibility we're going to
make people take responsibility for
their own Healthcare by having this
individual mandate and indeed it was so
successful that many other states wanted
to replicate it probably my favorite
experience this was getting to work in
California now as a child of 80s action
movies getting to work person with
Governor Schwarzenegger was pretty cool
indeed in the anti room before you meet
him I he has the sword from Conan the
Barbarian so I got to hold I have a
picture holding the sword from Conan
which was really cool and Schwarzenegger
really does he says we must cover all
the uninsured in California you know it
really sounds like that and uh that was
very cool and I work with California
other states and we'd get almost the
finish line and then every time they'd
say wait a second how are we going to
pay for this this is really expensive in
massach since it turned out we had sort
of a cheat which is we were already
spending a lot of money uninsured we
could just
rededicate other states didn't have that
benefit so every state when they got to
finish line we're like yeah sounds good
in theory we can't afford it they
stopped and we realized that if you're
were going to do this nationally there
had to be a national source of financing
and that's what led President Obama to
propose the Affordable Care Act
Affordable Care Act was basically the
Massachusetts law with three more zeros
it's basically the national massach law
at the federal level what do the foral
Care Act do it opposes Community rating
and
insurance okay it mandates mandated
individuals to have health
insurance and it set up subsidies to
make that health insurance
affordable in particular subsidized in
two ways one is it expanded the Medicaid
Program the Medicaid Program used to be
only for very very poor people people
living below like a quarter of the
poverty line like super poor people now
it's available to everyone up to 133% of
the poverty line so like $30,000 for a
family still poor but many more people
and we set up subsidies like in
Massachusetts for those who were above
133% of the poverty line but below four
times the poverty line so it's like a
three- tier system if you're below 133%
of the poverty line insurance is free
from 133 to four times the poverty line
we're going to subsize Insurance on a
sliding scale and then above four times
the poverty line you're on your own but
we did one other thing which we set up
exchanges so people could easily find
and shop for insurance so they could go
into the exchange we said the state
exchang could easily find and shop for
their insurance using these subsidies to
buy health
insurance okay and that's basically what
the Affordable Care Act did now um let's
talk about the Affordable Care Act on
policy front it was an enormous success
within several years of the law was
passed in
2010 implemented in
2014 by 2016 we covered about 20 million
Americans with health insurance
coverage okay which was and we had fixed
discrimination there was no longer
discrimination Insurance markets I
cannot emphasize this enough people do
not talk about this enough with that
with the foral Care Act they talk about
its effects on costs or coverage they
don't talk about the most important part
of the phal Care Act which is the US is
no longer a nation where you can be
denied Insurance because you're sick
it's no longer a nation where women get
charged more for insurance than men it's
and these this is these are critical
change every other nation in the world
has this principle no other nation in
the world allowed Insurance to
discriminate the discriminate the way we
did and that ended so in policy grounds
enormous success politically massive
failure why why massive failure well
books have been written and we'll
continue written on
this I think a couple of interesting
lessons one lesson is you know we don't
talk in this class about political
economy which is the study of how voters
make their decisions and how politicians
make their decisions but if you go back
to these numbers the idea of both the
massachusett bill and the Affordable
Care Act was look for 80% of people the
system's working let's leave them alone
let's focus on 20% it's not working
for in mass that work great because 80%
said hey look I don't care and you're
helping uninsured people great I'll
support it
nationally we had the problem that there
are many people out there saying this
law was terrible and the 80% said wait a
second maybe this Turbo's not doing
anything for me so may his law isn't so
great so the conversation was changed in
a away wasn't in
Massachusetts so essentially by leaving
80% of people alone the theory was gee
they'll at best at worst be neutral at
best be supportive because they we doing
good things we missed the fact that they
were up to being
persuaded and they're easily persuaded
because of these important numbers if
you pass a law in 2010 and don't
Implement till 2014 you give four years
people don't like the law talk about how
terrible it is with nothing to point to
so for four years people said this could
to be disaster it's destroying the US
economy D D D D D and all the supporters
says well wait after 2014 things will be
better but by then opinions had kind of
hardened so it's interesting lessons
politics what's the economics of
this the economics of this is that
basically when that in some sense when
thinking about optimal policy polic
design politics is another
constraint that we can't just as
economists and policiers say well I
studed 1401 here's the optimal policy we
have to recognize that optimal policy is
constrained by what politicians want to
do and voters want and that's okay that
just means that when you optimize
there's another constraint in
optimization which is recognizing that
you need to think about the real world
political
consequences of uh decisions you make
like delaying for years pass to have the
law take effect or like doing nothing
for these 80% of the public Etc now a
funny thing happened in 2016 well not a
funny thing happened first in 2016
partly as a result of this the
Republicans took over both the
presidency both sides of the Congress
and their number one policy platform was
repealing the Affordable Care
Act and so we pretty much figured all
the supporters figured well it's been a
good run but it's over now but then a
funny thing happened by the time 2017
rolled around the law in place for a few
years and people were like gee this law
isn't so bad we kind of like it we don't
want to go away and so actually repeal
never
happened so in in fact in 2017 support
went above water went above 50% for the
first time and the law was not repealed
and now will not be repealed president
you know candidate Trump has talked
recently about wanting to repal the law
repeal the law again it's going to be
politically very challenging because
it's now popular it's now a popular
piece of legislation it's now sort of
embedded into our system it's an
interesting lesson here in some
behavioral economics as applied to
economy which is we talked about loss
version the endowment effect another
version of the endowment effect is
what's called status quo bias which is
Once A law is in place it is harder to
take it away than it is to implement it
in the first place so one of the uh the
main criticisms you heard of the foral C
is oh it's socialized medicine and those
same critics would say it should be more
like Medicare
well Medicare is socialized medicine
Medicare is government provided
healthare for the for the elderly it's a
government system and you know one of
the most famous moments in the B foral
Care Act is people holding up a sign
saying keep the government's hands off
my medicare which is ironic because it's
a government program but it's embedded
it's in our endowment it's in the status
quo so we kind of like it so it does
sort of speak to how behavioral
economics matters in world world
political decisions as
well okay that's what I want to say just
last thing on coverage obviously there's
still
about uh on the order of 25 million
uninsured Americans maybe 30 million
uninsured Americans we still do not have
Universal coverage we've cut the number
almost in half the Affordable Care Act
which is great but it's still much too
large the question is what next and that
becomes the the debate that your
generation will have to engage in which
is how do we take it all the way to get
to getting everyone insured
okay so that's what want to say about
insurance coverage questions about
that all right now let's talk about the
other big topic let's talk about C
healthcare
costs by most estimates this is
imprecise by most estimates about a
third of what we spend on Healthcare in
the US does not actually improve
health which is sort of consistent with
the notion that we spend a third more
than other countries that are in
level okay about a third of what we
spend in healthcare is not actually
Health
improving so what is going on what's
going on is that there is no Market that
exists in history which is as Rife with
market failures as Healthcare every
market failure we learned about in this
class is Central to healthcare let's go
through them what's the First Market we
learned about Market power and Monopoly
well talk about Market power what
defeats Market power is the ability to
shop when you're in the back of an
ambulance having had a heart attack
you're not a very good
shopper okay there's no shopping in
healthcare information is incredibly bad
it's hard transaction costs are huge
there are very few competitive pressures
in the healthcare Market leading to
massive Market power some of the market
power is geographic okay if you have a
heart attack on Nantucket there is one
Hospital on Nantucket you're done talk
about timal Market power okay some of it
is not Geographic reputational
Boston has probably the highest density
of hospital beds per capita of anywhere
you cannot fall down without hitting a
hospital okay yet when David Ortiz was
shot in the Dominican Republic and flown
to America for treatment because
remember we do have the best Healthcare
if you're in the system did he go to the
official Hospital the Red Sox Beth
Israel one of the nation's top rated
hospitals no he went to MGH which is
slightly higher in the nation's rankings
and paid considerably more okay there's
also reputational monopolies monopolies
not have to be purely natural they can
come for other reasons which is people
always the very best hospital and that
gives Market power to the very best
hospital in Boston which is
MGH Mass General Hospital so basically
first market failure massive Market
power second market failure information
imperfections we talked about the
imperfect information in Insurance
markets what about imperfect information
in medical markets I go to the doctor
they tell me what test I need how do I
know if they're right how do I know
whether that's whether I need that test
or not how do I know whether I need the
treatment there's enormous information
asymmetries in healthcare third Mark of
failure we talked about
externalities Healthcare is a classic
externality if I don't have health
insurance and I get sick and I come and
cough on you you get sick that is a
classic negative externality or more
realistically if I'm
uninsured there's a law in America
called mtala which says emergency rooms
must treat everyone who shows up
regardless of their insurance coverage
so when uninsured people go to the
hospital they have to get treated how
does that get paid for by the hospital
charging more to their insured patients
that's an
externality so every market failure we
talked about is r in healthcare you
would never find a
market Which is less well
suited to the classic analysis we did in
the first half of this class and yet
unlike the rest of the world we allow
the free market to determine many of our
outcomes in healthcare
settings okay and in particular
there is a fundamental difference from
the rest of the world in the US we're
the only country in the world that does
not regulate our health care prices
let's go back to the Monopoly analysis
we talked about how with
Monopoly you have a situation where you
can improve outcomes through regulation
not necessarily you can go too far but
basically there a deadweight loss from
under production and regulation can
prove outcomes we talked about
information asymmetries we talked about
regulations like mandates and subsidies
can Pro outcomes externalities we talked
about corrective taxation when there's
market failures you need government
involvement and the US now to be clear
let me be very clear the US does not
have a purely private healthare system
literally if you look at us Healthcare
spending 50% is government and 50% is
private we're a very mixed system the
difference from other and other
countries are mixed too every other
country also has some public and some
private spending the difference is other
countries regulate the private sector in
a way we don't other countries set the
prices that doctors and hospitals and
drugs can charge and the US does not
okay and that is the fund I think where
Health economists now are that is the
fundamental difference the fundamental
challenge that we face it's a challenge
that leads to a number of problems the
first problem is we know in the Monopoly
case prices will be too high okay the
first problem pric are just too high
price too high we spend too much money
so for example for a typical drug or
procedure we pay two to three times what
they pay in Europe
okay an MRI in a Boston Hospital $1,500
in Japan is
$75 okay we have massive differences
that's the first
problem the second problem is more
subtle but important as we think about
Market design thinking about more
sophisticated models of markets than we
covered in this class which is when you
have imperfect information and so when
selling good soone buying the good there
will emerge a class of middlemen which
will help negotiate between the
uninformed seller the informed selling
or the uninformed buyer of the good
which in principle is good they can help
squeeze the rents out the problem is in
practice the whole extra layer of
expenses you add in America you don't
have in other
countries the bottom line is we spend a
lot more simply because we not regulate
prices okay and the answer is really
easy we just need to regulate prices we
do what the rest of the world does
regulate prices the problem is the
politics and it's once again the status
quo bias if it's one thing to set up a
new system with regulated prices it's
another thing to take an existing system
and regulate the prices and the reason
as the famous Health Economist U
Reinhardt once said is that health care
costs are also Healthcare income and
when you cut costs you're often cutting
someone's income and that person will
get politically involved to stop you so
let me give a classic depressing
example some drugs we buy at the
pharmacy some drugs are
injected those injected drugs are at the
doctor's office those injected drugs are
reimbursed by Medicare for elderly with
a specific rule which is when the doctor
get you with those drugs the doctor's
reimbursed besides the cost of drugs the
doctor's effort is reimbursed at s and a
half percent of the cost of the drug
think about what that means that means
if I give Andrew a shot that cost $100 I
get
$7.50 if I give Andrew a cost shot that
cost $1,000
effort same risk of carpal tunnels okay
I get
$75 that makes no sense remember we
should reward marginal costs we should
said the marginal benefits of the
marginal costs well here the marginal
benefit of my giving into a more
expensive shot is way higher my marginal
cost is the same that makes no sense so
20 Senators wrote a letteror President
Obama shortly after he entered office
saying this system's broken we to fix it
and President Obama then developed a
proposal to fix it he said no we should
pay doctors the fixed amount it's a
fixed amount of effort so it should be a
fixed
reimbursement okay makes sense every
Economist in the world said that was
sensible okay um shortly that after he
made that proposal 80 Senators including
almost all the original 20 wrote a
letter to him saying how dare you
propose such a radical and destructive
reform to the US Healthcare System
you'll destroy the US Healthcare System
with such a proposal what happened well
the guys give the Thousand shots are
called on ol ologists they're cancer
doctors they lobbied they got to the
congressman and said look we want to
keep getting 75 bucks for th shot we'll
make up some reason why it's a
bad
idea and you'll advocate for us because
we contribute to your campaigns and they
did and the proposal was killed we still
pay in this broken
way okay it is that's the difficulty
that the status quo bias so while status
quo bias in some sense was my friend as
a fan of the Affordable Care Act and
preserving the Affordable Care
Act as someone who wants ultimately
rationally regulate Healthcare prices
it's it's an enemy it makes it hard to
go forward so what do you do well it's
very hard and I don't really know the
answer this is really in some sense the
struggle of your generation let me be
clear this 18% number we can afford we
can afford to spend 8% of Healthcare on
the US the projection is by the end of
the century this number is 40% we cannot
afford that something has to give we are
going to going to have to take steps
burden on I I like to say there's only
two things in the world that really
matter for the long run which is global
warming and healthare costs because
either way you're
underwater okay we cannot as a nation
afford to spend 40% of our healthare
spending 40% of our GDP on Healthcare
Something's Gonna have to give so how do
you do this well the first step the
first B first sort of victory has
already been struck which is that the
place where people are most interested
in regulating drug prices and regulating
prices in drugs pharmaceutical sector
why are they most interested in
regulating pharmaceutical prices well
the theory most people give is because
they're the most transparent prices in
the healthcare sector you don't know
when you get surgery you have no idea
what the doctors get what the hospitals
get when you buy a drug you see the
price of the drug so that transparency
and the enormous high prices make people
upset and that's why they come at it I
have another theory my theory is that
people are mad at the drug companies
because they're ads now kids are a
little bit younger than my kids but grew
up in a similar era did you ever ask
your parents as my kids did what's
Viagra and why is that guy throwing that
ball through the tire over and over
again okay I got pissed I was like why
are they putting this stuff on TV indeed
I have a friend true story he's a
pediatrician in Lexington where I live
and he said a nine-year-old come into
his office and say I'd like to talk to
you about seis which is an erectile
dysfunction drug for those who don't
know and the pediatrician said why and
he said well it's said on TV talk to
your drct about
seis okay I think people are mad at the
drug companies the price are high and so
in the recently past inflation reduction
act for the first time in our nation's
history we came in and regulated drug
prices on a very small sub 10 drugs 10
of the thousands we take it was an
incremental step but it was a step
forward so the so maybe that's a good
sign that we can move forward to this by
the way
editorializing many economists would not
agree with my position on this okay but
I think that that up a step forward now
why would other economists not agree
with me what is the best
counterargument against regulating
prices well there's two the first is the
government will screw it up and that's
an absolutely valid argument remember we
talked about Monopoly price regulation
if the government set the price too low
it was worse than not regulating at all
totally valid point you know uh we can
debate that all day there's a second
point which is less valid which is it
will kill innovation
and here's how the argument goes the US
has the highest drug prices in the world
we also have do the most drug R&D in the
world indeed a huge share of all the R&D
done in America is pharmaceutical R&D
it's the largest source of famous
manufacturing R&D in America is
pharmaceutical where do they get the
money from that R&D from the excessive
prices they get for their drugs so the
argument was if we regulate drug prices
pharmaceutical compies would no longer
innovate and deliver the incredible
drugs that that are amazing miraculous
okay the drugs we have are miraculous
now okay look no further than the covid
vaccine to see the miracle that we get
from drug
development that argument is in theory
right in practice very misleading and
why is that once again this is I want to
think about how we apply we learned in
this class think about that so you could
see the argument which is Monopoly
profits the rents monopolis earn have a
different effect because remember I
showed you in external we underinvested
R&D right we undervest in R&D so it's a
totally legitim economic legitimate
argument that the cost of distorting the
Distortion from monopolis making too
much money is worth it because we
subsidize R&D as a positive externality
like the externalities could cancel the
market value of monopolis getting too
much money could be canell by the
positive
externality of producing more R&D people
see so that's just a classic
externalities argument
what it misses is R&D consists of two
parts the basic science and applying the
science and in fact the basic science is
not paid for by the drug companies it's
paid for by the government and it turns
out the rate of return Innovation to
basic science is incredibly high so
here's a super cool empirical study done
here at MIT give you an example kind of
empirical work economists do they looked
at
NIH
grants that got funded and get funded
that were very similar got funded and
didn't get funded and they followed on
and found what happened and what they
found is that NIH funding funding from
the National Institute of Health for
basic science is incredibly productive
in causing
Innovation and by their estimates if we
regulated drug prices and took that
money and gave it to the government to
fund basic science we'd be way better
off in other words the notion these that
you sort of in some sense have to give
Monopoly profits to fund R&D is not
right you can fund R&D with public
dollars and you raise a lot of public
dollars by regulating those drug prices
this is an argument if you want to see
this is sort of fleshed out much more in
my book jump starting America uh with
Simon Johnson we talk about how public
R&D is an incredibly important part of
the American growth story and uh these
are places where it could play out so
that is a very rapid overview of the the
Healthcare System okay if you want to
learn more there's lots of resources you
want to learn about the ACA you can read
my comic book if you want to learn more
about Healthcare you can take my class
1441 I spent about four lectures on this
topic uh we don't currently have a
health economics class unfortunately in
MIT uh we may have one eventually but
there's lots of resources you can look
at to learn more and this as I said is
the key public this and global climate
change are the two key public policies
who facing your generation going
forward okay stop there new material
here's the good news Okay hate to say it
now nothing I T today on the exam okay
this is all all for fun in quotes Okay
so I hope you enjoyed learning that for
Pure learning sake okay last thing I
want to say which is um what I hope you
got out of this course who what I hope
you got out of this course was learning
how to think like an economist I hope I
inspired you to take more economics
that's awesome even if I didn't I hope
that you will take from this course the
ability to think like economists the be
able to think critically about the
important problems and to recognize that
everything has an opportunity cost
everything is a trade-off nothing is
easy okay everything requires thought
everything requires some subtlety in
trying to figure it out okay and we've
given you the tools to do that okay
we've given you the tools to always
think about the marginal cost and
marginal benefits of different decisions
we've given you tools think about where
markets working where they don't and to
use those tools in everyday life and the
best way I think can do this is with a
joke okay and the joke which quite
frankly could be told about engineering
as well as economics but I like
economics is about the priest the doctor
and the economist to go golfing they go
golfing and they get in the golf course
and they're behind one guy golfing alone
which is already unusual what's more
unusual is he's awful he takes about 30
shots per hole and what's even more than
usual is he won't let the people behind
him play through good golfers are
supposed to if you're much worse people
in front of you you're supposed to let
people behind you play through he
wouldn't let them so after nine holes
the queue behind this guy is like
hundred people these guys are so pissed
they just quit they go back to the
clubhouse they're so mad they're
pounding their fist like what an
why do you not let us play through
someone comes up to them and says You
must be new at the club here and they
said yes we are they said well I could
tell you're new because if you weren't
new you'd know the guy who's playing
ahead of you was blind and actually it's
pretty amazing he can get the ball in
the hole at all and you should be pretty
you know upset at yourself that you
would criticize this guy who's actually
a pretty amazing go forgiv he's blind he
walks away and there's a hush silence
and the the doctor goes like I I feel
terrible I can't believe I'm someone
supposed to heal the sick and I here I
am like insulting the sick I'm going to
dedicate a wing of my hospit to the
Blind and the priest goes you feel
terrible I feel terrible I'm supposed to
be giving Comfort to the ill and the
sick and here I'm insulting the man I'm
going to have a free soup kitchen for
the Blind and they go to The Economist
The Economist says well if he's blind
why doesn't he golf at
night which sort of points out that the
role of Economist is to be a pain in the
ass okay is to actually ask the
difficult questions point out the
challenges ask and to really think
through the trade-offs that are inherent
every decision we make in life okay and
I hope you'll take that with you I hope
it'll Inspire take more economics and
thank you very much for for coming to
class
[Applause]