Hello everyone. Here we are in the
fourth session h of this amazing program
that's coming up closer. In this case
today we have Susan Mitchell. She'll be
talking about healthcare research into
healthcare entrepreneurship and I'll
pass it to her and I'll let her
introduce herself. Please remember
we want to hear from you. So feel free
to ask questions. You can put them in if
if you don't want to interrupt you can
put it in the chat and I'll I'll read
them to to Dan.
So ready ready for you forward.
Good morning. I'm really um happy to be
here on this side of the boot camp. I uh
was I think in the second MIT boot camp,
entrepreneur boot camp uh cohort um and
it was an intense experience. It wasn't
healthcare specific um but it was very
um formative for me and began my journey
as an entrepreneur. Uh I'm going to tell
you my story and the story of my
company. uh throughout this session. So,
um I'm gonna not do a formal
introduction right now um at this
moment, but um I want to first say hello
to everybody I got to meet in the
interview process. It's good to see all
of you again. And and Gifty, say hi to
you. Shout out.
And I'm going to just start out by
throwing out a question because I think
this is it's important to kind of root
ourselves in what my um intention was in
transitioning, you know, or or just
embarking on the work that that I do.
And so, uh, I'm just going to ask any,
you know, anybody here ever have the
opportunity or try to, um, stay on an
exercise program, floss your teeth every
day, um, change your eating habits, wear
a condom every time, anybody here have
an experience like that?
Pretty much. Pretty much everybody. and
in and in and in one tell me in one word
what that experience was like for you
and and just you know shout it out or
put it in the chat but I'd really love
for us to be interactive and and
conversational so feel free to just open
up your mic and and say I see um Balaria
you have your hand up. What was it like
for you to try to embark on something
new like a behavior change?
Well, in the beginning you
it's always hard and it's hard to keep
up like with the habit especially when
you're trying to read something about
your dig
able to
Yeah.
Yeah, I I saw somebody put lifech
changing
um which means that it was probably um
your
All right, we'll come back to you.
Anybody else have a a a one-word um
story for for a lifestyle change?
Painful. I see painful.
I mean, in general, right, it's hard
work and full of ups and downs, right?
Um, and you know, it's hard to, you
know, is and and for those of us who are
in pretty good health, I mean, that that
can feel just like a um, you know, a
thing that maybe we we keep coming back
to and trying, it's it's, you know, it
become it raises its level of importance
when it becomes a matter of life and
death. um or or even harder if it
becomes a matter of consequence but
you're not really feeling any of the
negative consequences um in the in in
the moment of opportunity to make a
difference in your future health. I
would add the additional complication or
complexity that when you are not able to
meet your basic needs in life or if you
have a complex comorbidity like mental
health or other issues you know getting
it together is really difficult and you
know in in my experience taking care of
people and and working with people in
that situation I it was both difficult
as a clinician to feel unsuccessful, not
able to provide people with the kind of
support that they needed uh and to watch
people face the consequences. And so my
story is really about how I was trying
to help myself while also trying to help
my patients because I was starting to
feel burned out uh by the lack of
progress that I was making with people.
Um and and I just felt like I couldn't
have another conversation about quitting
smoking without better tools. And so I
started to but out of the my own drive
to try to make um my patients
better serve my patients trying to find
better ways to deliver health care. I
also have a personal story with um my
husband who experienced um a very
serious brush with cancer and thankfully
I had a very good outcome but a a very
ex difficult experience. Um and those
kind of um those experiences informed my
journey from uh being a primary care
doctor to a paliative care doctor,
health services researcher to ultimately
what I spend most of my my time doing
today which is trying to deliver better
health care um through uh as an
entrepreneur. So I'm going to try to use
some slides to tell my story but I
really would like this to be
interactive. So, please, if you have
something to share, you can just raise
your hand or or shout out and um or you
can write a comment in the chat. We're
going to be monitoring the chat. Um but
feel free to um share your your comments
or stories. Okay, I'm going to screen
I'm going to screen share. Can you see
my slides?
I can see my slides, but I cannot see
you. So, I'm going to stop again and
see. You can't see your slide. You
can't? No. Okay, let me try this again.
I'm going to try to do it so that I can
see you and still
uh see my slides. So,
all right. Now, I've lost my slides.
Hang on a sec.
All right.
Sorry. Hang on one sec. Okay. Glad I had
them ready.
Okay,
here we go. Share.
All right. And then
slideshow.
We can see them right away. How's that?
Now I can see you and I can see my size.
Sorry about that. All right. So, we're
gonna talk today about translating
health services research into healthcare
entrepreneurship. And you know in my
experience as a researcher most of the
time uh research questions or people
pursue research questions um or pathways
that really have something to do with uh
their own passion or or curiosity. So my
story began began that way as well. So I
um I'll tell you I started out I'm from
the area here. I grew up in Arlington,
Massachusetts. I went to Bentley College
to study business. And um after spending
a couple of years working for a a think
tank uh that was working on the internet
for the military, I made the decision to
uh go to medical school and I changed
gears, went to Wake Forest University
Medical School in North Carolina. And uh
from Wake Forest, I uh went to
California to um study family medicine
at Adventist Health primarily because I
thought, "Oh, I'm going to go in the
Peace Corps and I want to deliver a lot
of babies and take care of people from
cradle to grave and learn Spanish." And
so I ended up in California for 10
years. And um in East Los Angeles where
my practice was, I was experiencing a
lot of um difficulties delivering care
to my patients. And I couldn't figure
out I didn't understand why it was so
difficult to get services for my
patients at that time and why they were
experiencing poor health outcomes. Um
and so I kind of embarked on a on a
journey um through epidemiology. I
wanted to build up my skills to
understand and and study what I was
seeing in my practice. And so I got a
master's in clinical research at UCLA
and I started studying childhood obesity
of all things because at the time I did
a lot of maternal child health and I
just started to see ch very very young
children, infants, toddlers,
preschoolers with obesity and it was the
very beginning of the um obesity
epidemic in childhood. And when I went
to the library to get the answers where
I always went to get answers, there was
no literature about obesity in children
at that age level. And I started going
and looking for people who were experts
in the area and they would tell me, "Oh,
they're just chubby babies. They grow
out of it." And you know, fast forward
20 years later, we know that children um
there is an epidemic in very young
children and even in infants and
toddlers of being overweight and that
those con those have consequences uh
lifelong consequences. But at the time
um I was just starting to understand how
to translate what I was seeing in my
practice in a population level way. And
that became kind of a fascination for me
because I was talking to patients and
they were telling me how um you know
difficult it was to manage their child's
diet and I thought that daycare programs
were the problem and I went and talked
to a woman who studied uh early
childhood education and she re basically
laughed me out of the room and told me I
had it all wrong and that it was
actually structured daycare that was
helping children stay healthy.
And I started to realize that um there
was a there was a process to
understanding one how to translate a
question that I was experiencing in
clinic into a researchable question that
would then turn into a solution because
what I didn't want was to just
understand a problem. I wanted to find a
solution. And that is really the story
of my journey from becoming a researcher
to um going into um entrepreneurship. I
ended up coming back to Massachusetts
and I joined the faculty at Boston
University at Boston Medical Center
where I was for 16 years doing um health
services research and that was really a
formative experience because my very
first research project was called
project red the re-engineered discharge
and it went viral while I was on that
study. It was one of three studies that
came out at the same time that the
federal government started issuing
penalties for hospital readmissions. And
so immediately there was an unbelievable
demand for Project Red implementation.
And I became an implementation
specialist without really even planning
to because there was such a demand for
an evidence-based solution to avoid
penalties. And so my experience told me
that good research should go out into
the world and make a difference. Today,
Project Red is one of the top 50
research studies um ever disseminated um
around the world really. And so that was
my first in you know insight about
research and um it really informed my
next in important study which I'm going
to share with you called women in
control. So designing research that
solves a real problem with potential
real solutions. That was what I really
wanted to do. So when you do research,
I'm sure some of you out there are
researchers and know how this process
works. You know, you have to start with
a researchable question. And for
clinicians, a lot of times, you know,
you understand the problem, but you
don't know how to formulate it into a
researchable question so that you can
develop evidence around it. And what's
been very interesting for me in going,
you know, going from a research
environment to a a entrepreneur
environment is the what I think of as an
artificial line between what is rigorous
research evidence and what's considered
real world evidence. And I would love to
have a conversation about that uh while
we are here today, which is you know to
me evidence is evidence. It's got to be
rigorously gathered, interpreted, and
and um and uh and analyzed in order to
be in informative. And the the the what
I think of as an artificial distinction
between research um and real world
evidence um is something that I
encountered in my life in my in my
journey from research to um
entrepreneurship. So the research
question what happened was I started
working on project red and we started
working on um chatbot systems now called
embodied conversational agents and uh to
fill the role of educating people at the
point of hospital discharge. And that
introduced me to this com human computer
interaction that is a um com that is was
um a a device a human uh character
teaching people their discharge
education. Um and from there I started
to study technology to fill gaps in
healthc care services. And in that
process I was introduced to immersive
technology a virtual world gaming uh
systems and we wanted to see if we could
use that system to um address gaps in
care delivery uh models that were
unscalable but effective. So that led to
my work called women in control. So the
women in control study was designed to
look at a model of care called group
based medical care visits and whether we
could make those that model of care
scalable with the use of technology. Now
you have to put yourself in the mindset
of you know pre- pandemic like 2010
before technology was really as
ubiquitous as it is today or even in the
five years following. So um we were
really looking at using really um you
know innovative but really unfamiliar
technology in a group of patients that
were facing significant barriers to
health care but also had digital
barriers to you know to accessing health
care as well. So they weren't familiar
with technology and they didn't have
good access to care and as a result had
poor health outcomes.
Does anybody have any questions or
comments up until this point about the
research process?
Any comments?
Anybody here familiar with research?
Just so I know who my audience is. I
don't want to over uh over share my
research um expertise here, but I'll
keep going. Okay. So um so we did this
study called women in control. We wanted
to look at diabetes. We were looking at
an important medical condition that had
been studied up to that moment a model
of care for chronic disease management
that uh was effective
was a population level solution but was
unscalable in its uh implementation in
real world settings. So in in-person
settings and so that study was called
women in control and our our question
let me just minimize this here. So we
what did the evidence show us? The
evidence showed us that um and and in
research generally when you're
developing a research question like in
entrepreneurship you do your customer
discovery process. In in research, we
usually look at what is the evidence
already available to answer this
question. Um and and what are the gaps
and then the research should address the
gaps. And so what the evidence showed us
was that there was poor access to
effective chronic disease management
among uh underserved populations that
were leading to poor health outcomes and
health disparities. There was a model of
care with a lot of evidence called
medical group visits where instead of
having one-on-one appointments, people
come together for a 2hour appointment uh
in groups of about 10 with a clinician
and an educator, they get
self-management education to teach them
how to manage the disease. They get peer
support which teaches them strategies
for implementing those care programs in
their home life. They get medical
management counseling and it's a
tremendously satisfying model of care
for patients and clinicians. The problem
is the typical barriers to cost
effectiveness and efficiency. No shows
transportation, child care
responsibilities, managing group
infrastructure in primary care settings
and billing issues. So there was here's
a great model of care. It works for
population health, but there's
significant barriers to implementation.
And so we wanted to ask, can technology
make this model of care more scalable
and efficient? So we're asking, can we
offer diabetes group visits in a
technology-based environment that will
increase patient engagement,
increase efficiency and cost
effectiveness, and will it be as
effective as in-person classes or
standard of care, which is one-on-one?
So that's how you create a research
question. It's not that different from
how you start thinking about how to
build a a a um product. Uh but usually
with the product, you start with the
customer interviews. So we're starting
with a a problem that we have, which is
how do we use this medical group visit
model of care in a way that's more
effective and efficient.
And so the women in control study was a
comparative effectiveness study. We had
two active arms. One was usual care
which is in-person group visits and the
other was an immersive world translated
curriculum where the women came together
as avatars went through uh 12 weeks of
of educational programmings and and
medical management as a cohort and we
looked at whether technology would
deliver results that were as good as in
person. We call that non-inferiority
and that means it doesn't have to be
better. It just has to be as good
because in-person is good but not
scalable. And so we needed it to be
cost-effective, efficient, and equally
as effective clinically. And so we
looked at physical activity, we looked
at glucose control, and we looked at
engagement. And the most important thing
and the pivotal moment for me thinking
like an implementation specialist was
engagement. So, if you don't know
anything about lifestyle uh products,
research that looks at lifestyle change
and lifestyle management usually has
extremely high dropout rates. We had 77%
of our participants complete our
program, our study, which is
exceptional. It's very exceptional to
have that many people stick with the
program. And for me that was uh that
turned on a light bulb that you know
this is good research. It's solving a
big problem with patient engagement,
access to care, health disparities. We
should be trying to find ways to bring
that to the real world. We showed
improvements in A1C for a very high risk
population. The mean A1C was 10, which
if you're a clinician, you know that's
very high um at baseline. And we had a
group of women who were, you know, not
necessarily sedentary um but you know
were needing to be a little bit more
physically active. And so what happens
after you do a successful research study
is you publish, right? you publish your
results, you publish a bunch of papers,
you present at research meetings and you
know you share your um success and then
you try to build on that success or
disseminate that success. And so my
experience as an implementation
specialist was, you know, I'm going to
try to disseminate this. But at the time
I was uh starting to get a lot of visits
from entrepreneurs like you asking me to
give my opinion about uh their ideas
about new products and I started to get
curious about what is the entrepreneur
process? Um what what are people doing?
And it seemed like they were moving a
lot faster than I could move as a as a
health services researcher. And so I
started to wonder how do I get into that
lane? What does it take to start to um
do uh dissemination through that
pathway? And that's what yes sorry to
interrupt before you go into the next
step there's a question on can you
elaborate more on the billing issues?
On the billing issue.
Yes. Yes. On the billing issue. So the
the issue with medical billing is um
that you um there the insurance
companies have um rates for uh how much
they would bill for a group visit versus
how much they would bill for a
one-on-one encounter. And so the group
visit model was um reimbursement was
much less than um the one-on-one
encounter. And so the people in the
group visit movement have managed to
figure out how to um circumvent that
although it still remains you know an
issue because as you may know there's
two models of of reimbursement from
insurance companies. There's valuebased
compensation where you get like a
monthly subscription or you bill fee for
service which is as people come you can
bill. Now, if you're billing and you
know you have everybody show up, then
you might be able to cover your costs
for implementing a group visit. But if
enough people don't show up, then you
don't get then you can't cover your cost
and then your model becomes, you know, a
a a problem for cost effectiveness. And
so if your major barrier is getting
people there and you can't bill unless
they come, then your model starts to
become weaker. And so, you know, group
visits at that time had faced the
barriers of um transportation and
no-shows that made the the model um
problematic for the most part.
Engagement was part of the issue as
well. Does that answer the question? I
think
and I guess and and there's another
question. How did you engage those with
limited digital literacy? Exactly. So,
so that was actually one of the most
illuminating um aspects of my what my
very first so the the paper that the my
very first um we did a feasibility study
and that was my introduction to this
work and I did the qualitative
assessment of the women who did
participate in the feasibility in the
feasibility study and at that in that
moment we enrolled 89 women over half of
them had never even sent an email. The
average age was 60 years old. They had
not just low health literacy, they had
low digital literacy and poor um poor
diabetes control. And so I was extremely
skeptical that they would be able to
participate in this program because the
the gaming platform was complex. we had
to give them um uh computers that would
run the um application and they had to
learn how to use a laptop. They you know
they didn't have they at that time the
many people didn't have smartphones,
they had flip phones. So the whole
aspect of teaching people how to
navigate the technology was part of the
development of agency towards the
disease. And that was what really
captured my attention was that teaching
people how to successfully use the
technology was actually giving them more
confidence to deal with the issues that
they were facing with the disease
management. And there's interesting
literature about that in education as
well that you know using technology to
help people build not just um digital
literacy but literacy about a subject
matter like health actually makes their
confidence in dealing with their health
um stronger and more actionable. And so
we had to create a instructional design
that integrated learning digital skills
with learning health um management
skills. And that's how we delivered our
platform. And so each we had people from
from 40 to 82 in women in control. And
some of them it took them longer, but
they were very they had a lot of
perseverance and we gave them um we we
gave them um training sessions and if
they needed extra training sessions, we
would give them individualized
attention. We also had the ability
because we were in control of the
laptops, we could uh remote into their
laptop if they got stuck and help them
get unstuck. So those tools helped us
navigate large groups of people at the
same time with different levels of
digital literacy and we still use those
skills today in seeyou yourself's
program hope app to help people with
digital literacy barriers.
Does that does that help? I think that
answers the question. Yeah. Great. All
right. So after um after we published um
I started doing talks and and sharing
the results with uh about our success
and um I met through one of my
presentations. I met the CEO at
Guisinger Health Plan in Pennsylvania
which is known to be a very innovative
health system in terms of designing
health service um models and uh Dr.
Fineberg invited us to uh implement
women in control in Pennsylvania and
gave us our first contract and with that
funding I established seeyou yourself
health and um became an entrepreneur. I
it took me a long time I I really uh for
the most part would consider myself a
founder. I took me a long time to really
feel like an entrepreneur. Um but I
decided to take that opportunity to um
go on that journey and uh it's been a
life-changing experience uh to both um
try something new um that was really not
in my wheelhouse um and to uh learn the
skills that it takes to be an
entrepreneur. And I would love to ask
another question to the group and just
say who here woke up one day at 5 years
old and said I want to be an
entrepreneur.
I'm guessing that most of you thought I
I want to I want to have a lemonade
stand. Um maybe I want to have a I want
to be a fireman or a or a princess. Um,
but you know, most people most people
don't wake up and say, I you know, I
want to be an entrepreneur when I grow
up. And and and yet my greatest obstacle
was I'm not an entrepreneur. Like I
thought to be a doctor, you had to know
you wanted to be a doctor when you were
born. And I learned that, you know, you
could become a doctor. And so I kind of
used that I idea to um allow myself to
take the journey to become an
entrepreneur. And it really was the MIT
program that showed me that I could do
that. You know, I up until that time I
thought entrepreneurs were born and you
know that you you really had to have
that. Um and you do have to have a
certain disposition to be an
entrepreneur but you can learn what it
takes to be an entrepreneur. And I think
that was um something that I really
contribute to the MIT program um and my
experiences and in the boot camp that
taught me you can become an entrepreneur
um and but you can't do it alone. It's
definitely not something to do alone and
I I think that is important. So, we set
up um we used the funding from Guisinger
to set up See Yourself Health, which is
our um our early stage startup that's
still in the you know that we're still
building and we're still growing and
still launching. Um and we um our
platform is called the Hope app. The
Hope platform B really modeled on hope
uh healthy opportunities and personal
empowerment. And what we're doing is
delivering group- based care with an
immersive technology uh platform that we
call um immersive an immersive teleaalth
platform and what I had to learn going
from a health services research because
as a researcher your story is kind of
done a a lot of times once the research
is done and you either get an
implementation grant and you study
implementation or you go on to do
something different and your work is
done. Um, and but my experience was good
research should go out into the world
and serve. And so I started to try to
find how how do you take something out
into the world and sustain it outside of
a research um environment? And there was
a lot I had to learn along the way. And
you know, I think the first thing is one
way to do that is to, you know, get
people on your team that have experience
doing that and, you know, know how to do
it. But most entrepreneurs are, you
know, highly motivated, missiondriven
people with a vision, um, but don't know
all the steps it takes to be successful.
That's my experience. And, and I think
that, you know, it's a very steep
learning curve. Uh, but it's a it's a
very exciting journey and you I think
the the if you have the people to do it
that inspire you along the way, then it
can be a very positive experience. So uh
one of the questions that was uh asked
of me was what so what was the problem
that you were trying to solve? And uh
you know we focused on diabetes because
women in control was we were resting our
um our our success on women in control.
And at that time the one of the
questions I was asked was what um
assumptions did you make along the way
that might have been incorrect? And one
of them was that my research was enough.
That my successful research program was
going to be enough to be um convincing
to get people to partner with me that
people would just be dying to partner
with me. Um kind of like what happened
with Project Red because uh you know
that's what my experience was. My what I
didn't realize was that one and this is
something you should be aware of you the
argument that people want to reduce
readmissions isn't the same for all
stakeholders in the healthcare
ecosystem.
two that you know um that different
stakeholders in in in the healthcare
ecosystem might need to be served at the
same time which is something new about
healthcare right if you're an
entrepreneur in another in another area
you might have one stakeholder that's
you know your decision maker in
healthcare it's multiple you need to you
know your your success depends on
patients adopting or providers adopting
your solution um and health plans being
willing to pay for it or somebody has to
be willing to pay for it. And so one of
my, you know, assumptions going into
this was my research success, you know,
outcomes were going to be enough to get
me um on the path to success. And and it
wasn't. It it got me to the first step,
which was with Guisinger. I I was
extremely fortunate that Dr. Fineberg
was um really um driven by patient
engagement and our success with patient
engagement was um you know the the thing
that got us started but it didn't get us
all the way there. Um so why did we
start diabetes? Because diabetes group
visits was the most established
evidence-based group visit but there are
other group visit models um that you can
translate to. And that's one of the
advantages of doing a platform that can
be translated to other verticals. But
the other thing I learned early in my
entrepreneur journey was stay focused.
Don't try to solve all the problems.
Stay focused. And so today I'm still
working on diabetes because one it's not
solved and two there's a huge business
case board study you know trying to
solve uh problems with diabetes and
three it's because that's where I have
the most experience um but you know
translating it now we have enough
expertise that we can start talking to
people about translating what we do for
people with substance use disorders for
caregivers for I have a group with
autism them uh that's interested in our
platform and our instructional design.
So, you know, that's another lesson that
I had to learn was the discipline of
staying focused. And so, the problem we
were solving is and and this is
something as an entrepreneur
I I I don't know if how long I can't
tell you how many times I had to iterate
on the problem statement. And so if you
find yourself, you know, a year from now
still trying to refine your problem
statement, you're not alone. This is a
hard thing to define. It's very hard to
be able to say your problem statement in
a way that makes, you know, that makes
sense. And so our problem statement is
living with diabetes is a full-time job.
That's what our patients told us. We've
talked to hundreds of patients and many
health um many health system leaders and
and health plan leaders. We did um
participate in the NIH C3I program and
did all the whole customer discovery
process. Um and at this point, you know,
my my informed what was really informing
me was my patient um input. And so
diabetes, a full-time job. Twothirds of
37 million people living with diabetes
struggle to manage their care. And as a
result, almost half have poorly
controlled diabetes, which leads to
complications, unnecessary hospital
visits, consequences, long-term
consequences, and higher cost. And the
hard part about diabetes is what you see
in front of you. There's four
stakeholders.
There's people who are working as care
managers. There's health plan
executives, there's providers, and
there's patients all in the, you know,
stakeholder chain of um, you know,
people that could be impacted by your
product. And so understanding, you know,
who is the where is your entryway into
the market, which one of these
stakeholders is going to get you there,
um, is important to, you know, your
success in going to market. So 7% of
people with diabetes don't get the
self-management education. they need to
actually be successful in managing it.
As a result, health plans pay, you know,
two and a half to three times more for a
diabetes patient than they do for a
person with well-controlled diabetes or
no diabetes. There's high rates of ER
use because of that. And half of people
end up facing consequences.
So, as you go on your entrepreneur
journey, you'll become familiar with the
idea of having a persona.
So Martha is our persona. Meet Martha.
Martha is a composite of all the
patients I've ever met with diabetes.
And this like living with diabetes, a
full-time job is a quote from one of my
patients. Martha is probably been living
with diabetes for five years or more.
She has had her ups and downs most of
her life, managing weight and then
managing pre-diabetes and then
ultimately being diagnosed with
diabetes. She is feeling exhausted and
burned out with her attempts to get her
diabetes under control and is starting
to experience a phenomenon known as
burnout, diabetes burnout. And she's not
taking her medicines and she's, you
know, kind of in a a place of giving up.
And as a result, her risk for
complications is increased four-fold.
Her cost of care is going up because
she's facing acute complications. She's
disengaged, not showing up for
appointments, and she has poor control.
And that's this person is experiencing
what we call diabetes distress. And it's
an actual marker that we tr that we
monitor our patients for and is an
indicator of one, who is our target
patient. It's a person with a high
diabetes distress score, and we've
confirmed that with our research data,
and it's a person who's most likely to
improve quickly with our support. And so
when you're thinking about who is your
persona, that's the kind of person
you're, you know, you want to identify
to that level of specificity, you know,
and I would add Martha has a smartphone
and she's comfortable using a tablet,
but she doesn't really use computers and
so she has a little bit of a digital
barrier um to using our tablet, but
she's not um she she's open to learning
and that is our persona. So what is the
problem is self-management? If you're
not familiar with self-management,
substance use disorder requires a
tremendous amount of self-management.
All chronic diseases require patients to
manage complex medications, diet,
exercise, stress, uh navigating the
health care system. There's eight
pillars that people need to master in
over a lifetime in order to live well
with a chronic disease. And what we know
is what I've told you, self-management
training in its form has been successful
but unscalable. And so what you see is
low engagement, limited access. The
benefits Wayne because Medicare only
pays for eight sessions in a patient's
lifetime. There's difficult workflow in
primary care settings, low
reimbursement, and as a result, costly
consequences. So this is the problem
that we are, you know, that we were
really trying to solve is how do we help
people become high-erforming partners in
chronic disease management that meets
the needs at the population level so
that we can actually serve the epidemic
of people every year being diagnosed
with diabetes. I I want to pause for a
second. I saw a couple of hands go up
and I just want to see um if there are
questions coming through that we can um
address before we go further. Anybody
want to question? Yeah, there are some
I'll read them because I think you may
mention it as you go ahead and you can
choose how to answer them. So one is
from Mark is diabetes is a huge market
with large numbers of competitors. From
a market segmentation point of view,
what angle did you decide to follow and
why? Uh from Roger, how pivotal was to
have your clinical trial published and
then and done to fund sorry and launch
your company.
Maybe one how long was it? How pivotal?
Oh, how pivotal. How key? Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay. So, I'm going to talk about
the competitors and and the the intense
competition in diabetes um in a couple
of more slides. So, I I'll pause I'll
hold off on that one. Um how you know I
actually started trying to uh
disseminate women in control before I
published my findings. Um and so that of
in the middle of the pandemic which was
you know really it was very challenging.
I I actually that was another assumption
that I had to face which was have one
having the CEO's support was critical
but it wasn't enough that I had to have
the support of other people in the
system and there were people that were
not in support of us and we ended up
having significant challenges staying in
uh the the system and and getting the
support that we needed to actually
recruit people to the program. I would
say be very careful in that environment
and I can talk to you a little bit more
about how you navigate those
relationships because even if the CEO
says good, come and bring your platform
to my comp my huge company, there's a
whole infrastructure of people that have
to support that in order for you to be
successful. And if you don't navigate it
carefully, uh you'll find yourself in in
hot political water with um people. Um
we we I learned that, you know, lesson
early. Um the other piece was um so
having I had evidence it hadn't been
published. It is important depending on
who you're talking to. Doctors love
evidence. Health system leaders, you
know, appreciate it. But then the health
plans, you know, really want to see um
results and uh you know, what they
called real world results, which I I
couldn't really understand because I
felt like I had real world results. I
still feel like I have heal and and what
you really need are is a network and
connections, not just results are not
enough. you need a network of adviserss
to help you enter the ecosystem because
if you don't it's going to be impossible
to to compete and and those
relationships take a long time to forge.
So I just you know it's a it's a
cautionary tale but you know people do
it it's it people are successful but it
takes a lot of uh perseverance to to do
it. Uh so use your literature to use
your your evidence to u get people's
attention but you know be aware that it
won't be enough and one thing I would
mention is like we were in you know in
guisinger implementing
and it seemed like a natural fit for a
teleaalth platform serving diabetes
patients to be promoted but when um an
epidemic is coming that nobody knows how
to manage you know everything else is
extraneous and so were we. And so um you
know we were sunseted we kept all the
patients that we had but we were
sunsetted because they were really
started to just focus on you know ICU
beds and ventilators and that was a
surprise to me as well. So, you know,
health systems, health plans, you know,
they have priorities that you may not
make sense to you, but u the more you
can understand, you know, what it feels
like to be in that position, the better
you can anticipate potential bumps in
the road. Um, so we managed to do our
demonstration, we managed to get our
company funded, but then we had to
figure out a way forward after that. So,
our solution Yes. Go ahead. Just so I
think that Thank you so much. I think
that addresses the how did you
commercialize your research idea and
also if later you can talk a little more
about how hard this is in in corporate
and another question is was your focus
only in the Medicare population or did
you also have the commercial population?
Uh the diabetes epidem is pretty broad
especially in employee population etc.
Yeah. So we were looking for the
unserved population. So if you've read
Clayton Christensen and the disruptors
dilemma, you know, we knew this was a
crowded space and I felt at the time
that we were going to need to find a way
to differentiate ourselves and one of
the ways that we differentiated
ourselves was by working with a Medicaid
population. So even though we were
working with middle and older aged
adults, um Medicaid was really at the
time, you know, untapped and also, you
know, uh trying to work with an older
adult population with a technology
platform. So our niche was to look at
Medicaid, which at that time now
Medicaid has become incredibly
fashionable. And there's a lot of people
trying to get into Medicaid managed care
uh plan um programs, but at that time
Medicaid was not and people weren't
really looking at Medicaid. They were
looking more at employers and commercial
plans where there was seemed to be more
money and maybe more patients where
technology was more familiar. So we were
trying to really serve the unserved
where there was no alternative. And even
today I can tell you I'm working in a
market where the alternative is to us is
nothing. And so that's an advantage. If
you're thinking about how to go to
market, find a place where the
alternative is nothing because then
people have nothing to lose by working
with you and you know everything to
gain. And so we've used that advantage.
Our advantage is being able to engage
highly engage. You know I use patient
engagement as a differentiator. our
ability to engage Medicaid populations.
And I can talk more about that business
model in a couple of sides. It's, you
know, you need to kind of if you want to
differentiate yourself, you need to find
a part a way into the market that isn't
crowded. And and that's at least was my
experience. And so we differentiate
ourselves that way and um you know have
really tried to work with uh health care
providers that are serving you know
Medicaid populations. I can talk more
about that as we go along. Uh just
quickly, you know, our solution to the
problem was to develop a techn an a
technology platform that wasn't just
Zoom. Like this was one of our big
challenges was why not Zoom, right?
Because now we're facing the pandemic
and everybody is getting on Zoom calls
and um and and why would they need to go
into a gamified platform? And so it was
a big challenge for us. And this is
another thing about entrepreneurship.
You never know when the playing field's
going to change on you, you know, and
so, uh, we had to be agile and and pivot
and and really face the threat that Zoom
was going to take us out. And what
happened and I I just was like, okay,
well, now we just have to embrace the
the challenge. and Zoom was really
pivotal, but at some point people were
like, I can't I don't want to look at a
at Hollywood Squares anymore. I need
something engaging and interactive. And
so it really helped us understand what
we were bringing to the table, which
was, you know, an environment that was
interactive, that was engaging and
whimsical with an instructional design
that helped people not only connect to
others, but to master the complex skills
they needed to implement every day that
would be available to them all the time,
not just eight sessions in a lifetime.
And that is our value proposition. What
we've been trying to prove to health
plans is that this is more coste
effective than fee for service one, you
know, once in a lifetime trying to get
people to be effective partners in care
and deliver these complex plans. And
that's that is, you know, what we how
we're going to market. So our platform
is an is an immersive platform. People
get an avatar, they navigate it with an
avatar, they engage in health behaviors
that are designed to prime their real
life behavior change. And there's
neuroscience that supports this. And our
experience working with patients shows,
you know, if we create engage them this
way, engaging them in yoga, dance, uh
physical activity, calisthenics, as well
as teaching them, you know, other key
actionable behaviors. We see behavior
change, improvements in uh disease
control and long-term engagement. And
so, uh, our platform uses VOIPE for
speech and and text chatting as well as
3D interactive, um, exhibits to teach
them how things work like how does a CGM
work and and those kind of things. Our
outcomes showed that we can improve uh,
health system costs, improve glycemic
control. Interestingly, emotional
distress, you know, that diabetes
distress uh aspect also improves uh
while improving patient engagement and
adherence to self-management. This is
all based on a scientific foundation
that I won't go into unless you're you
want to ask questions about it, but we
use um the experience of presence,
self-presence, physical presence, and
social presence in our instructional
design to engage people in a highly
immersive experience. Our patients do
not use headsets. They don't like
headsets. They do, you know, we had a
lot of negative feedback with headsets.
So, we use and and also just access to
this technology. People in our pop
target population don't even have a
tablet. So, we are partnered with a
company called PCs for people that help
us get refurbished devices that people
can um have to participate in our
program.
So these are the study the you know
these are the results from women in
control. These are my proof point that
we get 70% engagement significant
improvements in glucose control in a
short period of time reduce cost and
reduce mental health distress and that's
our value proposition in a you know in a
population that's very high risk and
difficult to access. And you know,
people always want to know how do your
patients feel about the experience. And
so we have tons of documentation about
patient focus groups in key informant
interviews about how the experience uh
helps them improve their lifestyle
management.
And so the story about going from a
research project to scale, you know,
really comes from going from a research
environment to a real world environment.
The biggest lesson is how do you
navigate that real world environment?
How do you engage clinicians? How do you
engage health plan leaders? How do you
engage health system leaders so that
they support your implementation?
After Guisinger, we needed to find
additional funding so we could continue
to make our platform scalable. One key
thing that happened to us, we learned
that when we went to Guisinger, people
wanted to participate and they couldn't
download the application. They had no
all they had were tablets or work
computers. They couldn't download it.
And so we had to figure out how to
create a cloud gaming solution. And
today it seems so yesterday, but at that
time nobody could answer my question
about how to do this. And so my partner
Oscar Cortez helped us create a cloud
gaming solution so that people could
access our platform on a tablet or a
Chromebook. And that was a very
important step forward for us otherwise
we would never have been able to succeed
at Guisinger. So a technology glitch
that really pushed us to make a more
scalable platform um happen happened in
our you know experience in trying to go
to market after the pandemic hit and our
sun and our program was sunseted. We
needed to figure out how to get
additional funding to continue to make
our platform scalable from all the
lessons we learned at Guisinger and we
turned to the SBIR program at the NIH.
We successfully won phase one and phase
two funding and um that has allowed us
to advance our platform so it's
integrable with an EMR system to help us
track patient reported outcomes and risk
scores um and to make a a scalable
immersive environment that actually can
be navigated easily um by patients of
all levels of digital literacy. So
that's where we are right now is uh and
we're implementing with a health plan
partner Molina Health Plan a national
Medicaid managed care plan in the state
of Kentucky um to demonstrate that we
can once again build traction with our
newly designed platform in this
population.
So just in terms of competitor I know um
people asked about competitors. It's
important to know who your competitors
are. They're they haven't remarkably
changed very much. So the gold standard
was you know in-person self-management
education 9 hours in a lifetime. Other
uh digital health competitors have come
in the market are really well
established is Mada and Labongo. Um but
the thing they don't bring is the live
peer action um experience the immersive
experience that we think makes a a
really important difference in our
demographic. Um in in addition tracking
apps that track people's behaviors are
also things that uh people use to manage
their self their their self-management
needs. Our vision is a platform that
integrates data from different sources
to create a living breathing experience
for people um in similar to what would
be called digital twinning. Um just
looking at seeyou yourself health's hook
platform versus new weight watchers lark
these are our major competitors I think
our main thing is the immersive
liveaction programming our expertise
with Medicaid populations and our um NIH
researchbacked evidence.
Uh so the market if you really look at
the market it you know the diabetes
market in and of itself is is enormous
and and it's incredibly competitive. If
you you know if you span out to
pre-diabetes and and even the weight
loss market is even a a richer
environment. The number of potential
people to serve is enormous. 96 million
people living with pre-diabetes
um and uh or at risk at least um and 37
million with type 2 diabetes. I mean the
there's just the numbers are staggering
and and it gets you you don't have to
touch every life to be successful.
That's the good part of a a problem like
diabetes. But you know the competition
is stiff and it's very difficult to
partner with um health plans. So I can
talk more about that. The business model
that we use is um a valuebased
reimbursement model. So we are
partnering with Molina on a per member
per month subscription. So the and we
get paid based on patient engagement and
enrollment. And then we hope that with
that initial success with just based on
traction that we will negotiate a bonus
um pay for performance shared savings
kind of bonus where we are responsible
for a population and the cost of that
population um you know we're not
responsible for their costs but we if we
can show an impact on the cost then we
get a cost share and that can be a
significant in you know additional
source of revenue. So, just this per
member per month uh reimbursement is
about $800 per person if you can keep
them engaged for for the year. And and
we've been we have people in our program
who've been with us for five years. So,
you know, we're showing, you know, some
good numbers for long-term use. Um but
even short-term use, the market is so
big, you know, you can have a
sustainable business um even just
getting, you know, somebody engaged for
a year. Um, and then there's also fee
for service options as well as direct to
consumer, but right now we're really
trying to uh demonstrate that we can
work with health plans because they just
have control of a lot of the market.
This is my team and I can tell you more
about them, but I can tell you right
now, you can't do it without a team and
you can't do it without a good um team
with diverse skills um that can tolerate
the uncertainty and the difficulties
that it takes to um endure, you know,
this experience. So, you know, you
really it's worth finding people that
you can work with that uh can endure the
challenges and the ups and downs. Uh so,
a couple of other questions that were
asked. um you know what regulatory stuff
have we encountered? The biggest one is
HIPPA. We haven't tried to get FDA
approval as a medical therapeutic at
this point. We are trying to go to
market without that. But HIPPA is a huge
obstacle with technology platforms. Um
anything about working with partners,
providers and payers, it's hard. It's
really hard to work with them. They it
takes years to de develop real
partnerships with them. They are, you
know, they are, you know, they are
running the ship. They have control of
the lives. They get to decide what
people have access to. They, you know,
can decide what they want to reimburse
people for. And the only leverage you
have is with the government. The
government, you know, they have to honor
what the government requires from them.
So, in our case, the government requires
them to provide self-management
education uh and support. So you know
that's something they need to deliver
and we leverage that. Also Molina worked
with us because of a health equity
initiative that they are trying to
implement in Kentucky. There's
significant and published disparities in
outcomes among minority populations. And
so uh they brought us in as a health um
health equity initiative. So you can
find ways to partner if you can
understand what the health plan's needs
and priorities are. And and I think I
mentioned most of these assumptions that
I that prove to be wrong. Uh one is you
definitely need lawyers and good ones
because the the further you get down the
road, the bumpier it will be and the
more legal advice you need to get. Um,
and it's not, you know, I had to learn
that, you know, if you don't skin your
knees, you're not playing hard enough.
It's scary. It's scary when you get, you
know, into legal um, contention with
somebody, but it's important and
navigable, but you just got to have good
lawyers. Um, making mistakes is not the
end of the world. You know, we you have
like I almost think you have to make
mistakes, but you feel kind of bad when
you do. And um but it's inevitable um
that you'll make mistakes and and learn
from them. So, you know, you can get the
best advice you can get um and that's
that's what you can do proactively is
try to have good advisors, but don't
don't beat yourself up if you're making
mistakes. And and the most important
thing is to be educable, coachable, and
and to learn from them. So, I'm gonna
I'm going to stop sharing and and open
up the floor for questions. And thank
you um very much from the bottom of my
heart for listening to my story and you
know um I hope that um you find some
benefit in it. So what other questions
do you have?
I think it would be great if you can
talk a little more about like selling to
the big organizations and and also like
why did you decide to go for the four
like um target audiences, right? You
could have chosen one or two. Yeah. Or
three. Yes. So I would say that um you
know we kind of learned this
we we're still learning it to some
extent. So we we I was not I didn't
realize that we would have so much
trouble getting partnered with health
plans. I really thought that it would be
my experience with Project Red was, you
know, in some ways it was kind of a
fairy tale of, you know, like something
happened at in, you know, once in a
lifetime and and and the demand for our
product just took off with a life of its
own in a unicorn kind of way, I guess.
Um, but mo the real world is that those
relationships are hard to forge and and
even harder to keep. And so um you know
sometimes that's an important role for
an advisor or an investor right that you
know if you're working with investors.
Now I'll tell you my very first group of
adviserss sat me down and told me to
build my company with um non-diluted
funding for as long as I could. And um
there's pros and cons to that. The road
is slower for sure with non-diluted
funding, but you remain in control of
your destiny. And I think that for in
some ways that is important that you um
you know are able to fulfill your vision
without the pressure of you know
generating revenue um when you're not
ready for it. And so I think that's an
important thing to consider. If you find
the right investment partner, that can
be a dream come true. You know, somebody
who a group of people that are, you
know, so um you know, committed and
generous uh and and can wait it out. But
at an early stage startup, like making
money is not going to happen for a very
long time. And so you've got to find a
way to, you know, find partners that are
can can stick it out with you. Um I'll I
I saw a question about diluted and
non-diluted funding. And so, uh, you
know, when you take on an investor,
usually there's a cost, right? The
investor wants a piece of equity, um, in
the company for the money that they give
you. And depending on how much value you
have in the company at the time that the
investor um, makes the commitment, they
will be able to request more of your
company. And eventually as your company
and your success grows, you can diminish
your your ownership and your control
over your vision to the point where some
people lose their company entirely and
and get displaced. And that's a true
story. Sometimes it's a you know, it's
not entirely negative, but it's a it's
it's a true story. And so, um, we kind
of decided that once we, you know,
because of our first contract with
Guisinger, we really were able to go
into our first kind of preede round
without, um, giving up any equity and we
got, you know, a half a million dollars
in that contract. And then, but from
there, you know, I was kind of trying to
figure out where are we going to go from
here? Um, and going to the NIH just felt
familiar to me to be perfectly honest. I
knew how to navigate the NIH. I wasn't
that familiar navigating investors and
you know my adviserss really pushed the
idea of not engaging an envir you know
investor partner until we were further
along where we would have more leverage
um to negotiate you know a better
agreement. And so we uh went for the
SBIR funding and I just I'm a good
writer. I'm a good researcher and I'm a
good grant writer. And so we have been
very successful with the SBIR program.
If you don't know about SBIS, I'm happy
to talk to you at length about it. Um
and and how you can be successful with
that um funding. It's it's really you
can get up to five four or five million
on a single idea. And there's people
whose companies just keep putting in
SBIRS and getting more funding doing
different types of projects. Um, and so
you can have as many SBIRs as you want.
Um, at some point you have to
demonstrate that you're you know you're
getting commercial success, but it's a
it's a great way to get non-diluted
funding if you can. You also have to
realize though working with the
government is also a pain in the neck
and you there's a lot of things you have
to abide by working with the government.
But that's my bread and butter. I know
it really well. So that has worked out
well for us and we've gone a long way um
in getting to our go to market strategy
working with a a national health plan
partner um and and getting traction in a
um in a Medicaid market. So I'm happy to
tell you more about that um if there's
if if you're interested. I see a couple
of hands up in grid. What where should I
go?
We can uh but with that on Donica Donica
us hi. So firstly I wanted to just thank
you for sharing your um your journey. I
have a women's femalth startup called
wingwomen. We do virtual and inerson
gynecology family planning coaching and
doulaare. We're also in Massachusetts
um serving the Medicare and Medicaid
patient population. So, I appreciate um
meeting and running into another founder
that has navigated that because with
startups, it's not always common that
people will go after that patient
population because of the complexity.
And then to your point around dealing
with investors, a lot of them don't want
to deal with the government. Yeah. Um,
so again, I appreciate your um, honesty
about that piece as well as um, trying
to wait as long as possible before
taking investor money. My question was
at this point, have you taken any
investor money? And then for those of us
because our company has already taken a
bit of venture when you've hit periods
where you just need to kind of I'm just
going to do like air quotes grind and
grow where there's not a lot of revenue
coming in like how to kind of position
those milestones and those wins when
it's not translating into dollars. Um,
and then for those of you guys who
haven't taken investor money or don't
know, just if you take it, usually you
have to give them a monthly and or
quarterly snapshot of how much money is
in your bank account, what your burn
rate is, um, anything you have coming
up, so they have constant access to how
much money you have at any given time
the moment you take it. So, um, with
that in mind, um, kind of how to
position those milestones and those wins
when it doesn't translate into dollars.
Yeah. So, I had one period where we were
running on fumes um, and interns were
helping. Um, so, thank you, Gifty. and
and uh we you know we didn't we we were
waiting for our phase two and we were
running out of our phase one and we
weren't generating revenue. We were
generating a little bit of revenue and
doing side gigs with our platform but it
was you know we were we still needed to
do more development on the platform in
order to be able to partner around cyber
security. So, if you're going to work in
healthcare, don't wait till the last
minute to think about cyber security and
HIPPA because when you want to that's
another piece of if you want to partner
with a large health plan, you need to be
able to play at that level of security
and that means have insurance.
I hear somebody's
do you hear that? Okay. So um it's uh so
you have to be able to show that you can
deliver secure data sharing. You have to
have a a a significant amount of
insurance that secures you. Um you have
to accept it, you know, a significant
amount of risk for data sharing. So if
you want to play ball with payers and
and big employers, you have to be able
to com you know reassure them that you
have the ability to manage the data
because that's their biggest risk. And
it's it's a very you know we failed our
first security audit which was that was
another eyeopening experience like I had
no idea and the guy practically laughed
us out of the zoom room you know because
we were so poorly prepared and you know
we we learned quickly what you needed to
be um in you know to be able to partner
with a large help plan and that was a
growing pain and so we were in that
window of needing to develop that cyber
security Um, and I honestly I played
poker. Um,
Donica, I played some poker there where
I didn't have enough money to do what I
needed to do and I was trying to build
it and and and you know that's the
entrepreneurs's journey like you're
playing poker a little bit. um you know
as you're because those those contracts
take a long two years to get a signature
on a contract and you know you can't
believe the way the lawyers will talk
about you know what you're going to do
you know you're trying to you think
you're trying to serve patients and they
are just you know layering on all these
other complexities and so it takes a
long time. If you sit around and wait
for that ink to dry, you will not be
prepared when when when go when the time
comes to hit go. So, you know, you have
to deal with that timeline. We were in
that donut hole where we were waiting
for our phase 2 funding. Our phase one
was gone. We're barely kind of keeping
the lights on. and we did take on an
investor um with a safe note and it was
a small amount of money and we don't
give him any kind of reports uh but he
is still a good friend to us. He's
somebody I met on an airplane. You never
know who's sitting next to you on an
airplane. Um and you know he's he's a
good friend to us. Uh and we are in
still in debt to him for um for that
funding but it got us through to our
phase 2 funding. So sometimes if you can
find that I would say don't wait to
develop your your partner your
relationship network with investors uh
while you're using non-diluted funding
because you you know you never know when
you might need that investor to step in
and help you out. But we just know that
when you do it, there will be, you know,
some you'll be giving up some of your
freedom, um, some of your equity. But
for some people that's, you know, that
actually helped them get to win. So I I
don't judge, um, either way as better. I
I think it's very dependent on who you
are, what you're doing, and the kind of
investment partners you're able to work
with. Yeah.
Any other questions specifically? I can
talk more about working with big um
health plans or what it means to work
with a m Medicaid managed care plan or
the business model. Anybody have any I
see a hand up. Roger.
Yeah. Yeah, I wanted to ask you uh if
you so with the SSB, SBBR or the
business program at the NIH,
if you were
when you wrote that proposal,
is this something you were leading the
company or you were partnering with a
different company while you kept your
academic position or how did you
navigate that
uh that process? Have any conflict of
interest or um just curious? So you know
the sorry so when you develop something
in an academic environment usually the
uh academic institution will have
intellectual property rights. I went to
beu and I told them I wanted to do you
know do this in they had no interest
and I was like so I can just go do this
by myself and they were like yeah we're
not you know we we're not interested and
I was like okay first of all I was
devastated because I thought I I was
just devastated like how could they not
want to do this with me but I also felt
freedom to go do it on my own and um and
So, but that was not easy and and also
you know the again I would say the point
in time you know BEu wasn't really on
the like they were looking at patents
and engineering but what software would
bring wasn't really on their radar and
so because this was a software
um type of innovation they just didn't
you know they weren't that interested
and so um so initially I was just this
was like a plant on my window sill
that's what I say it was like little
plant on my window sill that I was
trying to see if it was going to grow
and you know the the critical thing was
you know when I met Dr. Fineberg and and
you know he gave me that opportunity to
implement in Pennsylvania. I kept my day
job. I kept my research job and I you
know brought people along that uh you
know helped me do that implementation
and and were co-founders really at that
time. Um and you know that my team has
had some turnover in the last five years
that you know that was also difficult
but you really need if you're going from
a research to a entrepreneurship you
need to understand what tech transfer
means and go to your tech transfer
office because it's not the end of the
world if they you know have some equity
you just have to put it in writing so
you know how like basically if you de
develop something at an institution like
an academic institution ution what
wherever the product is at that time is
what they own and anything if you take
it out of the institution then you know
they own what you know they own a at
least some of the intellectual property
of where it was them but you're going to
build on it grow it change it do things
with it maybe make it a lot better um
their rights are limited um to what was
you know what was available at the time
of the tech transfer depending on the
institution and how they deal with text
transfers so be sure you clear those,
you know, bar those kind of regulatory
um barriers if you're working in a
research environment. That's important.
Yeah.
Thank you. Yeah. Sure.
And do I have one final question or
I will somehow Well, I was going to ask
if it's I don't know if I don't see any
other hands, but I'm going to ask again.
And this is Adonica again. Sorry, I'm
just really excited to hear from you.
Um,
uh, just I would just say from
experience, there are some harsh
realities around being a female founder
and then navigating in this space that,
um, don't often come up until you
learned a hard lesson. Yeah. Can you
share maybe a hard lesson you learned
and just like a piece of practical
advice um for you know for all of us? I
know it doesn't have to be specific to
being a female founder. I just I call
that out because you're a female founder
and it's sometimes rare to engage with a
female founder in this space because it
can be really difficult to navigate
especially if you don't have an advanced
degree or um uh certain partnerships in
place. And I would just kind of love to
hear like something practical that you
learned um even if it was a really
really harsh lesson. I know you shared
the example about kind of being laughed
off of the phone for not being prepared.
And I'm like I'm listening to you. I'm
like I have such a hard time believing
that. But I've also been in those
situations. You can be brilliant and
noteworthy and all of the things and
still be unprepared for what actually
happens in those meetings. But I would
just love to hear another like story if
you had one to share.
I have a lot of them actually. I mean,
thank you for bringing it up because I I
don't like to lead with that. I was part
of the mass life sciences nextgen
program. Uh I was in the second cohort
of women entrepreneurs
and
um I at first I wasn't like in my entire
career and in medicine
I never felt treated differently because
of being a woman. I felt like it was all
really based on,
you know, your academic and and your
skill as a physician. And, you know, I
felt always evaluated based on my
ability or my, you know,
accomplishments. Um, until I started
trying to navigate the entrepreneur
field and initially I thought I was
crazy. I was like, this is weird. I'm
having these I'm having this really uh
challenging time connecting or making
connections or or or st you know
competing and then I went to um a
program that Babson I think um hosted
and they had five investors
um and the theme was about um
disparities against women founders
and it was profound. found. I mean,
first I felt validated. I I felt like
something I was experiencing and
couldn't name and label, I guess, what
we would call a microaggression
was real, that I wasn't crazy. I also
think there's some agism. It's not just
about gender. Um, you know, there's some
agism. I I had a woman
uh who was a mentor and an investor in a
seed uh group, invest angel group, say,
"Suzanne, what are you going to do?
you're a doctor, a woman, you know, and
um a a a scientist. So, she named three
things. She's like, "You're never gonna
make it." And I was like, "I can't
believe that someone had like I think
she thought she was letting me down
easy."
And I I couldn't believe that she even
like said it to me as a woman, you know,
and I was like, I thought those were
going to be advantages.
I thought being a physician with
research and a research track record and
implementation expertise was going to be
enough. And um and it definitely was not
just not enough. It was sometimes it was
um a red flag. My people are like, "Oh,
doctors are terrible business people.
Doctors are terrible
um managers." And um I and you know I I
mean like those I stood up at um one of
the mass challenge
um this entrepreneur
uh program for women to pitch and we
were supposed to be getting practice
pitching from you know a group of 30 you
know uh people in in um health sciences
pharma all these things right so you're
like totally vulnerable. You're standing
up there
and it was almost all men in the room
and this one guy who knew me from beu
just started railing on me. It it just
started and and it wasn't even about my
pitch. It was you know just about you
know my presence, my you know like my
tone of voice. It was it wasn't even
about like you should have brought the
content from the end up front or I and I
I had I I walked out of there. I was I
thank goodness I had a strong mentor
network that I you know because they
picked me up. That was a very difficult
experience. It was first of all it was
very difficult to have that happen to me
in front of an audience and here I was
like I was used to public speaking in
front of you know very elite scientists
you know like I was used to being in
front of people it wasn't that it was
the way I was treated in that
environment as somebody who didn't you
know warrant respect and it took me a
long time to digest that and finally me
um write a letter because this was
supposed to be a program to lift up
woman entrepreneurs and you know it
reminded me a lot of experiences I had
in medical school um that were were
harsh and toxic and so I feel like you
know learning experiences are meant to
be you know you know help people grow
and I felt like I was treated that way
because of you know um because of all
the stereotypes that I represented and
um I do this mentoring and um I mentor
women in my company because you know I
don't want them to have that experience
and if they do I don't want them to be
without a network to support them and so
you know I would just say that you are
not immune to having that happen to you
whe no matter who you are I think you
know you're not immune into having that
experience, you'll need to have people
that can help you navigate it, make some
meaning out of it and move forward and
know that next time it happens, you
won't be um taken down as as um you
know, as harshly. And I tried to turn it
into an experience where I could, you
know, grow. Um so I feel like um you
know, this entrepreneur experience, the
startup world can be harsh. I it can be
full of the hard knocks kind of
philosophy, but it doesn't have to be.
Um and it and it really shouldn't be. So
don't take it if you're if you're facing
it, but you know, try to um handle it
with grace and and dignity. That's my
that's my advice. So I thank you. Yes.
And I'm happy I'm looking forward to
working with all of you um in person and
I'm happy to connect with you um
offline. If you're interested, please
feel free to reach out um to me. I'll be
happy to share whatever I've learned and
I'm very excited to meet all of you um
in person. So, thank you so much and
happy holidays.
Thank you everyone. Bye-bye. See you
soon.