[Music]
good morning Bangkok how are
you yeah so my name is Anuj Bala I am a
Sloan fellow graduate of MIT 2016 I'm
the CEO and chief data scientist at
service Mob We are an AI and machine
learning platform for the customer
service industry providing analytics to
drive insights that are somewhat
unintuitive right we are revolutionizing
customer service in the ontological
customer block we'll tell you what that
actually means um the big problem is
it's
2025 we could land a rocket ship upright
back on the
Launchpad but customer service is
terrible this is a huge huge problem
across many different Industries despite
the Advent of so much technology so much
AI customer service worldwide is the
worst perceived than it's ever been and
it's costing companies more money than
ever especially when switching costs are
low uh uh qualtrix estimates $500
billion dollar US globally just on the
switching economy but businesses are are
still struggling with customer service
why is this
and I'm going to let everybody in this
room in on a little secret of why your
customer service is bad in
2025 we're measuring customer service
all
wrong I'm going to say that again we're
measuring customer service all wrong
just like the good professor was talking
about training AI to look at cats and
dogs and understand what those are from
a machine level we are doing the same
thing except
we're doing it for customer
experiences imagine that customer
experiences it's not a real thing it's a
it's a concept right but we at in
customer service are measuring
interactions we're not measuring
customer experiences until now service
mob is the first company ever to use
machine learning to identify experiences
in the data customer service doesn't
necessarily happen on one transaction
every single passive and active
interaction you have with the brand is
part of your experience all the way from
a service perspective from your need of
customer service all the way to a
resolution and every single touch point
that you have in between is part of that
experience it's never really been
measured or looked at until now so we
are using machine learning to truly
understand experiences and redime I this
for measurements that are new and novel
for the space as a result we've been
able to help companies this is a case
study from a publicly traded travel and
hospitality company one of the emerging
uh you know companies even in the uh
APAC space and we were able to save them
$5 million to their bottom line that
blue line was the amount of headcount
they needed before the the uh purple
line is the amount of headcount they
needed after using service to find the
insights in the data that are truly
improving customer experience uh service
Titan one of the largest IPOs the
largest IPO in 2024 one of our first
customers we saved them over 13 million
in cost of flection just last year 78%
reduction in contact rate 80% reduction
in Abandonment for a hypergrowth company
and look the data problem has changed
with generative AI we can interrogate
these large ontologies ontology is just
a word for data model but we're looking
at that that data model for the customer
experience and we can inter uh
interrogate those large ontology models
with llms to get Precision level
insights on what's affecting you and
your customer experience with the brand
and now predict and prescribe actions to
improve that experience with your
customers so that they're spending more
money with you and not your competitor
we're we also providing the Performance
Management so whether you're a bot and
or a human or something in between we're
providing that eval Loop to essentially
provide if you think about those pairs
of outcomes and the pairs of inputs part
of what we're doing is being able to
show what a satisfied customer really
looks like which is the product of
customer service so please uh you know
we think that uh we're already in the
region working with many companies
uh you know here in Southeast Asia we'd
love to partner with SAS companies
utilities companies Telecom we're ready
in the US market and the global market
helping companies really achieve
Millions to their bottom line and we'd
love nothing more than to help you and
your companies achieve the same here uh
to provide great customer relationships
come see us outside thank you
[Applause]
[Music]