coming across people that are suffering
from the same stuff that you're
suffering from they've been affected by
Wars they lost their homes they lost
loved ones it sort of helped in my
healing process or in my like
understanding process of absorbing
everything that is happening or
currently happening in Sudan this is the
part that is sentimental to this
[Music]
journey welcome to open Learners a
podcast that tells the stories of
Learners all over the world who use
mit's open courseware I'm
emmanueli an open learner from Cala
Uganda and I'm Michael Jordan Pilgreen
an open learner from Memphis
[Music]
Tennessee hey Emanuel how are you doing
I'm good Michael I'm good I'm enjoying
summer I'm enjoying
Toronto Emanuel you know this episode is
really special Our Guest today is
someone who has leveraged mit's open
learning resources during a really
difficult time for herself her family
and her country that's right Michael
today's guest is Saud khed Ahmed alumar
an open learner from Kum Sudan she
earned her bachelor's degree in
electrical and electronic engineering
from the University of katum in 2022 one
year later in May of 2023 sadly sujud
was forced to flee Sudan because of the
ongoing war in her home country the
company she was working for shut down
and she was forced to leave her home and
some of her family members behind she
currently lives in Egypt where she's
working on her certificate in computer
and data science as part of mit's
Imaging Talent program and she's working
towards a micro Masters in statistics
there are so many difficult and
inspiring parts of saud's story but one
thing that stuck out to me is that sujud
applied to emerging talent because she
felt like she had nothing left to
lose now a year into the program she
sees the skills that she's learned
through MIT open learning as essential
tools that will help her rebuild her
home country sujud is deeply committed
to building a prosperous future for
Sudan and placing her home country at
the Forefront of technological
advancement her long-term goal is to
establish a research center in Sudan
which will use data science to address
local social economical and
environmental challenges by in the short
time she's already putting her data
science and program
programming skills to good use she runs
a database called NASA Al Sudan which
curates a list of scholarships available
to stanes students yes ajude is a really
inspiring person and I admire her deep
commitment to her country and her own
learning I'm really excited for our
listeners to hear our entire
conversation with suude we talk about
her hopes for Sudan along with how ocw
helped her make lifelong friends and how
she keeps herself motivated during the
dark times this is a really really great
episode Michael and the perfect story to
end our first season with so without
further Ado he's our conversation with
Saud khed Ahmed alumar from Kum Sudan
[Music]
in
Sudan my name
is um I'm 25 years old almost 26 I was
missed by saying 25 but I'm almost 26 um
I come from a country in Africa called
Sudan and I graduated from University of
Harum electrical and electronics
engineering department and I specialized
in control and instrumentation I've sort
of drifted into data science and data
and data related stuff and yeah I'm just
exploring it and learning about it would
you want to just uh start off with sort
of how you grew up and your experience
with education then I grew up in the
capital city of
Sudan basically Kum consists of three
cities umman and bah I grew up in umman
uh it's a lovely city and my childhood
was was lovely I guess I grew up with
four siblings they're all males also I
shared a hoppy With My Father which is
reading and I think it participated a
lot into the person I am today and the
personality I have we just like read
books and discussed them as of my
education in my basic school I went to a
private school and then after that my
experience like changed a lot because I
moved from a private school into a
public high school which had too many
number of students there they all come
from different backgrounds they all have
different stories and different
personalities I think it was around that
time I started to realize that I'm
interested in mathematics that and I
love it I love mathematics so I started
to explore it I did not have like much
room to explore it I didn't know what
where to look or I didn't have anyone in
my circle who was also interested in
math and I think it was around that time
where I realized that I need to find
other sources or I need to find one
place to pursue this uh interest so I
applied for University of Kum one of the
prestigious universities in Sudan and I
applied for the electrical and
electronics engineering department I got
in and I was really excited because all
the things I heard about it was that
engineering was embedded with these
mathematic courses and that we get we'd
get the chance to explore so many of the
stuff in math but then then I think I
was shocked because the content was not
did not have like in-depth things about
math or like too many Advanced topics
about mathematics and I think it it was
that there that I realized that it's not
the answer maybe it's like the start of
the answer but it's not it and I need to
like seek my uh pursue my interest
somewhere else I love your journey
particularly because I understand and
resonate with the fact you know when you
come from a small
a private school then you go to a big
school and it's like oh look at all
these people and it's a new experience
and we I can also understand actually I
can understand this as well I also
wanted to take an engineering background
I ended up taking a science uh so a
computer science course as well but
that's an interesting journey I just
wanted you to shed some light on the
difference between online learning when
you first when you finally encountered
it and traditional learning back home
how was that for you so I think the
difference between traditional uh
learning or maybe the learning at school
and then we had like structured content
that was not always up to dat with what
was happening in the world especially in
specializations like engineering and uh
that are like they're changing at the
moment and they're evolving in too many
Technologies are being Advanced every
day and that was not reflected in the
content that we had at the time but then
on the other hand the online learning
and the online material it's embedded
with uh knowledge it's unlimited let me
talk about YouTube you go to one link
and then you start learning and then you
find another one that takes you to
another thing or another topic and it's
just like it opens a world full of
possibilities and you can get to explore
everything you want so just a follow-up
question there so when you first found
MIT open course where was that through
YouTube and was that during your
undergraduate studies or was that during
uh the time when you started becoming a
teacher assistant my first experience
with MIT open course s was during my
undergrads actually it was through one
of my Tas uh around the second year of
my undergrads we were struggling with
programming classes at that time it was
like our first impression with it and we
did not just fully understand it and we
wanted something more to understand it
and one of the T suggested that we look
at one of the courses at MIT I think it
was in YouTube the course was in YouTube
it was recorded it was not just me I had
like couple of other fellow students
with me and we studied the course
together and then after that we wanted
to like okay there's this website it has
so many courses not just about
programming about too many other stuff
some of which we had we already had in
our undergrad or in our materials and
it's just delivered differently
structured in a different way and yes I
owe MIT open course where a lot of my
mathematical knowledge and mathematical
understanding it comes from there I
guess amazing amazing it's really cool
that you were in a group too you know I
think you might be the first learner
that was using MIT open course where in
a group would would you just maybe talk
about how using open courseware
especially in the group it sounded like
it helped you academically but did it
help you like with personal
relationships with friendships I did not
actually reflect on this throughout my
life but now looking at it I think it
did help me and uh especially when we
were we were just like we were in the
our second year of my undergrads and
around that time the structure of
University um like I applied for
electrical and electronics engineering
specialization but at first two years we
study like from different
specializations so we were too many
students coming from different areas and
going into different areas and I didn't
like have the chance to meet for with
with students from my patch or who we
going to like spend the rest of my
undergrads with and then when this came
up and when we started like to form the
groups and other students from my patch
came in who are now are some of my best
friends in my life even after like 10
years of graduating uh we spent too many
time together we would like uh sit we
maybe we would not just like attend the
lectures or go through the content
together but we would come and discuss
it and uh share maybe some some people
go through different course and then we
would share it we would share the
knowledge we had and in between this
time of learning we would like just
chitchat and exchange just like the
basic human interaction and boom we
became friends did you ever use ocw for
other things outside career because they
have so many topics on there that are
outside so was it strictly for book
purposes are you still using ocw right
now in your life I think originally it
was for the pure academic reasons that I
started like going through and studying
it it was just for pure mathematic
content and other stuff related to my
academic Journey but definitely in
between then and there I did go through
some of the courses that are not just
related to my academic Life currently
I'm using it to go through my uh MIT
emerging learning uh program it's also
academic but uh it's helping me a lot
which brings me to this other thing
that listening to these videos and
attending these lectures had has helped
me a lot with my English language and it
was a challenge at first because as I
said during my uh high school and before
my undergrads I did not attend a school
or university which was in full English
and then when I joined my undergrads
when I joined University it was like
just pure English which was an extreme
challenge but listening to these courses
and going through them has helped me a
lot in listening and understanding in
the academic English and how to
communicate with this language so this
is one of the major parts that helped me
with throughout my
[Music]
life uh how did you find Imaging Talent
first of all uh maybe you could give us
a b brief background about that I was
going through through really hard time
in my life when I found out about the
MIT emerging Talent program um if you
don't know I come from Sudan and Sudan
is currently suffering from uh a
conflict which is it's it's a war it's
not just a conflict it's a war that's
happening in Sudan and in May of 2023 I
was forced to flee Sudan and uh relocate
to Egypt I lost like everything that I
love I lost my home um some of my family
were still stuck there and even at the
moment I still have parts of my family
still stuck there I have friends stuck
there and we we all lost loved ones and
I just couldn't find the purpose of my
life or why am I doing anything or
what's what's the reason I remember I
met this one friend and she was talking
to me and we were discussing just how
this words affecting our lives and how
we need to how we need to overcome it
not just overcoming but we need to work
on on ourselves so when the time comes
for us to go back to Sudan and build it
we have the knowledge and we have the
power to do so at that time I was
looking for materials and stuff and this
same friend she sent me the application
for MIT merging Talent is coming in like
couple of hours and it was talking about
the program and that Sudanese people are
now eligible for it because it's
directed toward people who are suffering
from Wars conflicts and who are refugees
and everything the deadline was
approaching like couple of hours and I
needed to prepare for it and write all
the essays and it has like a
mathematical tests and other programming
tests and everything and then when I
reached like the last part it needed a
video recording this is really funny
because every time I remember it I just
I laugh about it um it had like a video
recording thing and at that time I was
in Egypt and it was summer and they had
like this power outage that comes in
Egypt for a couple of hours and I needed
to record the video for this and I
didn't know when will the electricity
come back so I said okay I don't have
anything to lose let's just try so
instead of recording a video I sent a
voice recording I didn't think they
would accept it because why would MIT
accept a voice memo when when they
clearly stated that they wanted like a
video recording but I sent it anyway I
had nothing to lose and I didn't have
Alternatives so I sent it and couple of
weeks after that I got the email I got
the acceptance email and I think the
program has been really helpful for me
coming across people that are suffering
from the same stuff that you're
suffering from or have been going
through the same Journey the same things
or not just maybe not just the same but
something similar and they they've been
affected by Wars they they lost their
homes they lost loved ones like going
live with people who understand the
things that you are are going through it
it sort of helped in my healing process
or in my like understanding process of
absorbing everything that is happening
or currently happening in Sudan this is
the part that is sentimental to this
journey what project are you working on
that side uh how is it important to you
how did you arrive to that kind of
project maybe if you can shed some light
in that aspect as well the project that
we're currently doing so our graduation
project from the program uh we United me
and another fellows from another MIT
fellows from Sudan uh and we're doing
this project which is directed toward
education in Sudan the educational
system basically just fell down the
schools are not working universities are
not working some of them are working
online but the majority of the schools
and universities in Sudan has not been
working for more than a year now which
is a disaster and we need to look at it
and we need to like find solutions to it
so our graduation project that we're
trying to offer students with
alternatives to this there is this uh
there's this website called NASA Sudan
it's an initiative that collects all the
other Alternatives or all the other like
scholarships universities that accept
Sudanese people outside of Sudan and the
requirements and all the process that
they need to go through in order to
apply for these universities so we're
helping with their databases we're
rebuilding the databases for this
universities and the website and
everything in between that I was just
curious if you wanted to talk about you
know after the
program after all the learning on open
course where if you have a vision for
your own future or if you have an idea
of where you want to go in in the future
at this point in time well I'm still not
quite sure I don't have like a clearer
vision of where I want to go I think
merely because the situation in Sudan is
not quite clear yet and all my career
plans and my life plans are oriented
around Sudan and I think this past year
has affirmed me that I really want to
give back to Sudan and I want to help
build San because I can't I can't belong
anywhere I can't find anywhere to belong
and I want to build Sudan for the other
people the other Generations that will
come to find some place to belong to
because belonging is one of the it's one
of the most
important uh feelings for for human
beings and I sort of want to contribute
this knowledge I have or I think I have
to building Sudan and
to to its healing and it's its recovery
so currently I'm just looking for
opportunities uh throughout the program
and after after finishing the program
I'm looking for opportunities to
contribute this that's perfect no we we
understand that having certainty in the
future um you know one final question
from me and then I'll let Emanuel kind
of take over is do you have any advice
for anyone that may be in the same exact
situation that you are if I can give
like advice for people coming from not
just the same background but from
communities where they do not have
access to maybe quality education or uh
opportunities don't wait for them just
seek these opportunities and do
not I remember I read this somewhere
that it was something about
self-rejection and how we always like
self reject ourselves and we do not give
ourselves the opportunity to even even
be considered for something and just do
not self- reject yourselves you're not
losing anything by trying but when
you're not trying you're not even
presenting yourself and you're not
giving yourself the opportunity to being
considered for something or to take
something so self-rejection is the worst
enemy for everyone so just don't self-
reject yourself if there is opportunity
and you're not going to to lose anything
so why not just try it and why not just
like take this
[Music]
opportunity if they gave you a magic one
and they told you okay you could add
something to the
ocw movement like you could add
something to this or remove something
from it what would that be if I have a
magical power and I am to add anything
to MIT open course whereare what would
it be I think the one thing that I would
add and uh to find some medical way or
some medical power just to to get rid of
the language barrier and maybe give
everyone the opportunity to benefit from
from the material and from all the stuff
that are out there without the language
barrier that's awesome that's great s
Jude I love your story and I would like
to personally thank you for you know
telling us your story and we hope
that anyone else listening to this will
get inspired you know will know that
actually this is not just some online
learning thing online it's actually
helping lives it's helping people not
just in school outside school in the
toughest situations I guess my final
question to you would be first of
all as someone who has gone through all
this I know it can't be easy maybe how
do you
stay focused how do you stay strong you
say you mentioned don't self reject
which is a powerful thing like what do
you do to self motivate to self you know
push to drive when in that moment when
you feel like giving up what moves you
well about staying focused I won't lie
I'm not focused most of the times
because like as you said the world is
still happening and people are still
suffering so most of the times that the
all the news coming from Sudan just
absorbs us and we find ourselves
even though we're not in Sudan but we
are in Sudan and even so we're not
physically like there and we're not
physically hurting and we're not hearing
the bombings and everything but we are
there and it's hard to stay focused and
it's hard to to continue with our lives
even though we know that a war is
happening back there and people are
dying back there so most of the times
it's really hard most of the times it's
impossible to focus or to study or to do
anything productive so I could say that
maybe every couple of productive days I
just cvel in my bed and I don't do
anything I don't find the energy in me
to get out of my bed and do something
productive and I understand that I
understand the reason behind that but
then I try to just remind myself with
the whole purpose of it and why am I
doing it and that there will come a time
that we will build Sudan it will come
even though we don't know when whether
we are going to be alive to witness it
or to participate in it but if we are
Sudan will need us to be at a strong as
possible to build it and to participate
in it and this sort of gives me some
peace it sort of helps me a lot with
okay I'm not doing it just for myself
I'm not doing it just for my family but
in the bigger picture and with with a
heart filled with hope I'm doing it for
Sudan for when the time comes
that Sudan needs to be built that I'm
ready well thank you sujud again I think
so many people around the world are
going to be inspired by how powerful
your story is and the knowledge you've
shared so we are very grateful that you
came on and were able to share your
journey and you know I know it may not
be complete uh representation of your
journey but I hope it does capture a
small piece of it that other people can
find inspiration from thank you again
thank you Emanuel Michael thank you for
the opportunity and thank you for having
me I'm really grateful for this
[Music]
opportunity wow sujud has really been
able to do something extraordinary she
spent the most most difficult moment in
her life expanding her own knowledge so
that she can rebuild her home country of
Sudan it's very
inspiring what's been on your mind since
we spoke to suude Emanuel yeah Michael
I've been thinking a lot about this
episode because it's a very touching
episode it's a very inspiring episode I
like the part where she says never self-
reject but here we have someone a young
person in their mid 20s trying to start
their life and the worst possible thing
that could have happened to someone
happens but in the midst of all that
she pushes through she perseveres and
what amazes me the most is somehow ocw
was may not have solved all our problems
but it kind of provided a Guiding Light
it kind of provided a hope in the midst
of all this glimmering Darkness so what
about you Michael how was your takea
away from this I found saud's
honesty to be the most impactful thing
to me she doesn't shy away from sharing
that there's multiple days where she
just can't find the energy to get out of
bed and when you think about the
separation from first her
land but also her family and her
language you should really just take a
moment and pause and reflect on how that
would be for you as well but despite all
that she continues to improve herself
she continues to hope for a better day I
just find that so inspiring especially
coming from a country like the United
States where we've never had to worry
about that type of separation from the
ones we love so that was the most
impactful thing for me and Michael how
you feeling did this leave up to the
dream we drummed up on that Zoom call so
many months almost years ago now we
surpassed any dream or Vision that I
could have thought
of all that time ago it was uh full of
inspiring moments it was full of
inspiring stories and inspiring people
just seeing learning and all these
different contexts how it affects people
you know that are trying to get their
degree and just want to add some more
education or that are actually having to
flee their countries and still try to
figure out a way to make everything work
out in their lives um I hope that
highlighting these stories about humans
just like all of us from all over the
world really gives people a glass to
look through and see what their life
might be able to become I always
remember the first one of the first
calls we had with cat where he mentioned
that when they started all this when
they started ocw they thought their
biggest clientele was going to be the
teachers you know and it brings me back
to a quot I read somewhere once where
like when you create something and put
it out in the world you never know you
never know is going to use it you never
know how it's going to impact them you
never know and that's what I've Loved
about what this podcast has brought to
light in that his resources that are
open to everyone in all over the world
yes you know people are using them but
you don't know what for you don't know
how they're using them you don't know
what they're developing you don't know
how it's affecting their lives now that
we have a platform for at least people
to show us and tell us about that impact
it's something really I'm really loving
and I won't likee it's been a fun J it's
been more than anything I could have
expected more than anything I could have
asked for I'm even shocked we got here
I'm even shocked we actually did this so
stay tuned into mit's channels to learn
about other Learners and perhaps take a
few courses yourself which I can
guarantee you will change your life you
may not know how you may not know when
but take a course it will change your
[Music]
life open lers is produced by alexas hot
special thanks to the supporters and
donors who make ocw possible to learn
more about mit's Open courseware and to
check out the courses mentioned in this
episode visit the ocw website at
ocw.mit.edu
[Music]