Hi everyone, welcome back to the
introductory uh series for the obesity
machine learning competition. Uh today
uh we'll be talking about uh the data.
This is the third uh and final lecture.
Uh and specifically uh we'll be talking
about uh the experiment uh harnessing
the technologies that we spoke about in
the second lecture um was performed to
generate the data. uh and then we'll uh
discuss how the data actually looks like
the the data object that you'll be um
working with
and finally we'll talk about the three
uh crunches the task that you'll be
performing
uh and so uh as I mentioned we'll break
this up into three part going over first
of all uh the perturbse experiment uh on
adiposite cells to generate the data
then uh the data objects that you'll be
working with and finally uh the three
crunches uh or the three challenges.
Okay, so just a quick recap. Hopefully
by now uh you're familiar with uh this
scheme and the different uh adiposite uh
cells that we see uh in adapost tissue.
Some that are associated with
differentiation uh and others that are
associated with um specific flavors of
metabolic activity.
We also discussed um how these are
therapeutically uh relevant because uh
we know that different proportions um
that deviate from uh the normal of these
different cell populations uh are
actually linked to uh obesity.
And finally we spoke about the gene
expression programs which uh govern each
of these different cell populations. Um
and we also spoke about the specific
functions that individual uh genes
within these gene expression programs
have. So for example we spoke about um
the capacity of the padiposytes to
proliferate in the presence uh or when
PDGFRA is active and also uh the ability
of the adiposytes to signal to other
tissues uh when adipoq is active.
The issue, however, was that uh while we
know information for some of these genes
in the gene expression programs and some
of their functions, we'd like a more
systematic uh whole transcriptto view of
what's going on. Um and so on the
experimental side, we learn about this
technology called perturbse um which
allows us to both delete individual
genes in the cells and then measure the
gene expression profiles um in those
same cells. And so uh one aspect of this
is this gene editing technology called
crisper cast 9. Uh the the cast 9
nucleas which is directed to individual
genes in individual cells and inserts
these uh doublestranded DNA breaks uh
breaking the function of the gene.
And the second component is combining
this pertubation with uh single cell RNA
sequencing. So this is the schematic of
individual uh cells being isolated in
these droplets uh barcoded um for then
downstream uh uh counting of the
individual RNA molecules uh i.e. the
expression levels of every gene. And so,
BetabSeek is really the combination uh
of these two technologies allowing us to
get the uh transcripttos with the
individual RNA molecules uh in the
different cells as well as the identity
uh of the gene that was knocked out in
that cell in this case denoted by A or
B.
And so, combining this, combining the
biology and the technology, what's the
experiment that was actually uh
performed? Uh so first of all this was
performed um by three expert scientists
uh at the Broad Institute uh experts on
adiposite biology
and um what the team did was uh to take
preadiposytes and differentiate them in
uh the lab in a dish. So this is very
exciting already because it means that
the kinds of gene expression programs uh
that we've been talking about that we
know exist in uh tissue in people uh
like the differentiation programs and
the metabolic programs. Um this means
that we can actually study that now in
the lab uh in a dish. And so um this
differentiation protocol lasts 14 days.
And so you can imagine uh that roughly
speaking uh initially we have a
population of just priiposites and after
these 14 days we may still have some
priiposites shown here in blue uh but
we'll also have uh generated this more
differentiated population of adiposytes
shown in uh pink or red. And so this is
step one uh and what uh Thiago and the
team did was to combine this with uh
pertubations. So um knocking out as
we've spoken about individual genes in
these cells um at day zero and then
proceeding with the differentiation
protocol and then finally at day 14
performing uh the perturbse experiment
uh to both get the transcripttos of the
resulting cells at this day 14 but also
know whether um whether a partic which
gene uh was knocked out in each of these
cells.
So shown here is just an example with
one gene, let's say the red gene. Uh but
in reality uh they tried many different
um pertubations in a pulled format and
so every cell would receive uh a
different gene.
The second experiment um which is the
data set for uh crunch 2, the first
experiment was the data set for crunch
one. Um and so in this second experiment
the setup is very very similar. The only
difference is that now rather than
single gene knockouts um what the team
did was actually knock out two different
genes uh in every cell.
And so again this is reflecting the
pertubation um the actual uh
doublestranded uh break that happens in
the cells. um and then subsequently
again um the cells were profiled by
perturbse and those um double
perturbation identities those double
gene uh knockout identities uh
retrieved.
So um just to comment on uh the double
gene uh pertubation screen something
that is worth considering uh when you
build your models um here is a scheme of
a the hypothetical pertubation effect of
knocking out gene one. So let's say it
has a perturbation effect of one um and
then the pertubation effect uh on the
cell of knocking out gene two which
we'll say also has a perturbation effect
of one. Now uh one kind of naive model
might expect that uh the combination of
these two knockouts so knocking out both
gene one and gene two in the same cell
uh would lead you to pertubation effect
uh of two. This is what I call the
additive expectation. But in reality we
see um all sorts of interactions between
genes um that deviate from this
expectation. So uh here are two extreme
examples that I'm showing. one of what
we call a synergistic relationship
between gene one and gene two where
actually the combined effect of knocking
both of these genes out is far greater
uh than the um expectation based on just
summing their individual perturbation
effects.
And conversely, you can also have
antagonistic relationships where the
combined effect uh is less than uh you
would expect based on uh the sum of gene
one and gene 2 effects alone.
Okay. And so uh the outputs uh of both
of these data sets in the single gene
knockout and in the double gene knockout
um perturbosite
cells uh this is the output that you'll
get. Uh so on the left here we have the
single cell RNA um expression matrix
with every row corresponding to a
different gene in the genome um and
every column corresponding to a
different uh adiposite cell that was
profiled um at day 14 after the
differentiation treatment.
And every value inside um the matrix
corresponds to uh the RNA counts for
that gene in that cell or the um as we
refer to it more generally generally uh
the gene expression level.
So that's one part and then the second
part is this pertubation identity matrix
where we'll be able to say for a given
uh gene expression profile in a given
cell whether that same cell received a
pertubation or not and if it did what
pertubation it received i.e. what gene
was knocked out or perhaps for cell
three, what pair of genes was knocked
out.
And then finally, it's important to note
that there are also in the data set uh
some cells which won't have had any gene
knocked out. We call these the
non-targeting controls. Uh in the data
set, they're they're referred to as NC.
Um and uh these are a important uh and
uh revealing population because we can
compare the effects of the pertubations
from uh for example in cell one the
effect of MLX IPL to this uh wild type
population that didn't have any gene
knocked out at all.
Okay. So just to review on the uh
experiments um that on the data sets
generated by these experiments.
So first of all uh in terms of the
number of genes knocked out uh in the
first data set the data set for crunch
one there are 166 single gene knockouts
uh and we'll hold out 10 to 15% of these
uh for evaluation
and then in the second data set there
are 105 uh combinations of uh knockouts.
So 105 uh double pertubations and again
we'll hold out 10 to 15 uh% of this for
evaluation.
And so how were those genes selected? Um
for this we consulted experts uh in the
field uh adiposite experts uh and they
chose uh genes that they believe uh
could be relevant to uh obesity. And so
this is the uh set of genes that we
focused on.
And finally, as I mentioned, yes, there
are negative controls. Um, these are
cells that uh did not receive any
genetic pertubation. Uh, and we call
these the non-targeting controls and
you'll be able to identify them in the
data sets that you receive uh because
they'll have this NC um annotation
rather than the name of a gene under the
pertubation column.