Spontaneous coronary artery dissection
or SCAD is defined as a tear or a
separation in the wall of the coronary
artery, but it's not associated with
athoscerosis or trauma.
>> Scad has been known to affect men and
women. However, SCAD most commonly
affects women. SCAD patients are often
healthy and without risk factors of
heart disease such as high cholesterol
or diabetes.
>> SCAD is a rare condition linked to
arterial fragility sometimes caused by
well-known genetic disorders like
vascular ellers stanlo syndrome, morphan
syndrome and lois deed syndrome. These
conditions involve mutations that weaken
blood vessels and increase the risk of
arterial tears.