My name is Hitan Sonal. I'm the CEO of
Rise Robotics. Uh our affiliation with
MIT is that three of the four founders
of the company are MIT alums.
They recently brought me on board to
help commercialize the acceleration uh
to accelerate the commercialization of
their technology. My prior experiences
with iRoot where teams that I led
shipped 9 million units and generated um
over $2 billion in revenue. And I'm here
at Rise to help them accomplish that.
The challenge that we're trying to solve
is that heavy machines are dirty and uh
they're dirty because certainly there's
a lot of fuel that's being consumed. U
in addition to that 88% of the energy in
the fuel is wasted because most of it is
wasted in the engine and then another
large chunk of it is wasted in the
hydraulics. Um in addition to that uh
they release half of a gigaton of carbon
dioxide every year. And what's much
worse is that they leak 100 million
gallons of hydraulic oil which is
hazardous into the environment. So the
clear fix for this is electrification.
However, inefficiencies in the hydraulic
system make electrification unviable
because the inefficiencies of the
hydraulic system drive up the size of
the batteries and the cost of the
batteries and make it so that the
machine is too expensive and doesn't
generate the necessary ROI.
What the founding team at Rise has done
over a period of 10 years is designed a
new technology that we call beltra and
you can see the inside of one of our
cylinders. What we've done there is
we've taken out the oil from hydraulic
systems and we replace them with belts
and pulleys. And by being very
intentional about the molecules that we
move, we've created something that's
three times faster, three times more
efficient, 20% lighter, has half the
operating cost, has no fluids, so it's
very easy to maintain, and it's 100%
digital and AI ready. And by that, I
mean that out of the box, this
technology has all of the sensors you
need to build a digital twin and then
use a an ML system to convert it into an
automated system.
Here is a quick demo of our actuator.
As you can see from the movement of the
actuator, it's very smooth and very
precise. Uh, compared to a hydraulic
system, it moves very, very fast.
There's no oil. There's no there's
nothing leaking here. So, we can take
this to shows and demo it in ways that
you couldn't with a hydraulic system.
And finally, it moves much, much faster
than the alternative screw type
actuators.
I'm going to pause the demo here.
and move on to the next slide. Um, go in
slideshow mode again. All right. So, our
traction till date, we've sold $1.5
million of Beltraik products under
commercial terms to the United States
Air Force. Um, they were really
delighted with the product. Um, and I
won't read the comments here, but this
is the feedback by our point of contact
who purchased uh all of the the product
that we shipped to them. Um, and then on
the strength of our delivery, we were
awarded uh 3 point uh almost $3 million
in two separate contracts to modernize
the ground support equipment for the Air
Force. What you see there on the right
hand side is actually the world's
strongest robotic arm. And the reason
why I'm saying this is because our
technology is not only all the things
that I described, which is it's fast,
it's efficient, it's light, it's AI
ready, but it's also very, very strong.
and we got into the Guinness book here
in the first week of March. It was very
exciting. Had a ceremony here. Um we had
Guinness, we had an Irish band and we
had the adjudicator here giving us the
award. It was exciting for the team. Um
but the key thing the key takeaway here
is that we can basically do almost
anything that the hydraulic systems can
do.
One of the things that we're doing with
this system is deploying our own
product, a liftgate. And what this
allows us to do is get the product out
to market faster and get customer
feedback. And the liftgate has all the
same properties of the core technology.
It's faster, it's low maintenance, uh
has many premium features including
smooth and safer operation. Um and the
ROI on this product is roughly 6 months.
So we're very excited to be launching
this in the second half of next year. Um
next quarter we'll be doing pilots.
And what we're currently looking for as
we build out our portfolio, which is you
see our vision there for different size
actuators and actuators that have the
the motor remote, which is something new
that we can do with our system that you
can't do with say a screw type actuator.
Um, and also steering cylinders that you
can see at the very bottom. As we build
out this portfolio, we're looking for
companies that are interested in being
partners in sales, distribution, and
manufacturing. And we're also looking
for OEMs of electric or autonomous heavy
machinery that see that could use
benefit from the higher speed and higher
productivity of our actuators and the
higher efficiency and the lower
operating costs, not to mention the ease
of uh autonomy.
With that, I'm going to stop and open up
for questions.