the MIT energy initiative presents
turning carbon dioxide into valuable
products written by Nancy W stoffer
carbon dioxide CO2 is a major
contributor to climate change and a
significant product of many human
activities notably industrial
manufacturing a major goal in the energy
field has been to chemically convert
emitted CO2 into valuable chemicals or
fuels but while CO2 is available in
abundance it has not yet been widely
used to generate value added products
why not the reason is that CO2 molecules
are highly stable and therefore not
prone to being chemically converted to a
different form researchers have sought
materials and device designs that could
help spur that conversion but nothing
has worked well enough to yield an
efficient costeffective system two years
ago aiel first the Raymond 1921 and
Helen St Lauren Career Development
professor of chemical engineering at MIT
decided to try using something different
a material that gets more attention in
discussions of biology than of chemical
engineering already results from work in
her lab suggests that her unusual
approach is paying
off the stumbling
block the challenge begins with the
first step in the CO2 conversion process
before being transformed into a useful
product CO2 must be chemically converted
into carbon monoxide
Co that conversion can be encouraged
using electrochemistry
a process in which input voltage
provides the extra energy needed to make
the stable CO2 molecules react the
problem is that achieving the CO2 to co
conversion requires large energy inputs
and even then Co makes up only a small
fraction of the products that are formed
to explore opportunities for improving
this process first in her research group
focus on the electric Catalyst a
material that enhances the rate of a
chemical reaction without being consumed
in the process the catalyst is key to
successful operation inside an
electrochemical device the catalyst is
often suspended in an aquous water-based
solution when an electric potential
essentially a voltage is applied to a
submerged electrode dissolve CO2 will
helped by the Catalyst be converted to
co but there's one stumbling block the
Catalyst and the CO2 must meet on the
surface of the electrode for the
reaction to occur in some studies the
catalyst is dispersed in the solution
but that approach requires more Catalyst
and isn't very efficient according to
first you have to both wait for the
diffusion of CO2 to the Catalyst and for
the Catalyst to reach the electrode
before the reaction can occur she
explains as a result researchers
worldwide have been exploring different
methods of immobilizing the Catalyst on
the
electrode connecting the Catalyst and
electrode before F could delve into that
challenge she needed to decide which of
the two types of CO2 conversion Catalyst
to work with the traditional solid state
Catalyst or a catalyst made up of small
molecules in examining the literature
she concluded that small molecule
catalysts held the most promise while
their conversion efficiency tends to be
lower than that of solid state versions
molecular catalysts offer one important
Advantage they can be tuned to emphasize
reactions and products of Interest two
approaches are commonly used to
immobilize small molecule catalysts on
an electrode one involves linking the
Catalyst to electrode by strong calent
bonds a type of bond in which atoms
share electrons the result is a strong
essentially permanent connection the
other sets up a non-covalent attachment
between the Catalyst and the electrode
unlike a calent bond this connection can
easily be broken neither approach is
ideal in the former case the Catalyst
electrode are firmly attached ensuring
efficient reactions but when the
activity of the Catalyst degrades over
time which it will the electrode can no
longer be accessed
in the latter case a degraded Catalyst
can be removed but the exact placement
of The small molecules of the Catalyst
on the electrode can't be controlled
leading to an inconsistent often
decreasing catalytic efficiency and
simply increasing the amount of catalyst
on the electrode surface without concern
for where the molecules are placed
doesn't solve the problem what was
needed was a way to position the small
molecule Catalyst firmly and accurately
on the electrode and then release it
when it degrades for that task first
turn to what she and her team regard as
a kind of programmable molecular velcro
deoxy ribonucleic acid or
DNA adding DNA to the
mix mention DNA to most people and they
think of biological functions in living
things but the members of first lab view
DNA as more than just genetic code DNA
has these really cool physical
properties as a biomaterial that people
don't often think about she says DNA can
be used as a molecular velcro that can
stick things together with very high
Precision first knew that DNA sequences
had previously been used to immobilize
molecules on surfaces for other purposes
so she devised a plan to use DNA to
direct the immobilization of catalyst
for CO2 conversion her approach depends
on a well understood behavior of DNA
called hybridization The Familiar DNA
structure is a double helix that forms
when two complimentary strands connect
when the sequence of bases the four
building blocks of DNA and the indiv
idual strands match up hydrogen bonds
form between complimentary bases firmly
linking the strands together using that
behavior for Catalyst immobilization
involves two steps first the researchers
attach a single strand of DNA to the
electrode then they attach a
complimentary strand to the Catalyst
that is floating in the aquous solution
when the latter strand gets near the
former the two strands hybridize they
become linked by multiple hydrogen bonds
between properly paired bases as a
result the catalyst is firmly affixed to
the electrode by means of two
interlocked self assembled DNA strands
one connected to the electrode and the
other to the Catalyst better still the
two strands can be detached from one
another the connection is stable but if
we heat it up we can remove the
secondary strand that has the Catalyst
on it says first so we can
dehybridized surfaces without having to
disassemble the device or do any harsh
chemical steps
experimental
investigation to explore that idea first
and her team post dos gang Fon and
Thomas Gill former graduate student
Nathan Corbin PhD 21 and former postto
amuda carbar performed a series of
experiments using three small molecule
Catalyst based on porin a group of
compounds that are biologically
important for processes ranging from
enzyme activity to oxygen transport two
of the catalysts involve a synthetic
porine plus a metal Cent of either
Cobalt or iron the third catalyst is
hemon a natural porine compound used to
treat pereria a set of disorders that
can affect the nervous system so even
the small molecule catalus we chose are
kind of inspired by Nature comments
first in their experiments the
researchers first needed to modify
single strands of DNA and deposit them
on one of the electrodes submerged in
the solution inside their
electrochemical cell though this sounds
straightforward it did require some new
chemistry led by carar in thirdy year
undergr graduate researcher Rachel alar
the team developed a fast easy way to
attach DNA to electrodes for this work
the researchers Focus was on attaching
DNA but the tethering chemistry they
developed can also be used to attach
enzymes protein catalysts and first
believes it will be highly useful as a
general strategy for modifying carbon
electrodes once the single strands of
DNA were deposited on the electrode the
researcher synthesized complimentary
strands and attached them to one of the
three catalysts when the DNA strands
with the Catalyst were added to the
solution in the electrochemical cell
they readily hybridized with the DNA
strands on the electrode after half an
hour the researchers applied a voltage
to the electrode to chemically convert
CO2 dissolved in the solution and used a
gas chromatograph to analyze the makeup
of the gases produced by the conversion
the team found that when the DNA linked
catalysts were freely dispersed in the
solution they were highly soluble even
when they included small molecule
catalyst that don't dissolve in water on
their own indeed while pfer and base
Catalyst and solution often stick
together once the DNA strands were
attached that counterproductive Behavior
was no longer evident the DNA linked
Catalyst and solution were also more
stable than their unmodified
counterparts they didn't degrade at
voltages that caused the unmodified
catalus to degrade so just attaching
that single stranded DNA to the Catalyst
in solution makes this Catalyst more
stable says first we don't even have to
put them on the electrod surface to see
improve stability when converting CO2 in
this way a stable Catalyst will give a
steady current over time experimental
results show that adding the DNA
prevented the Catalyst from degrading it
voltages of interest for practical
devices moreover with all three
catalysts in solution the DNA
modification significantly increased the
production of Co per minute allowing the
DNA linked Catalyst to hybridize with
the DNA connected to electrode brought
further improvements even compared to
the same DNA linked Catalyst in solution
for example as a result of the DNA
directed assembly the Catalyst ended up
firmly attached to the electrode and the
Catalyst stability was further enhanced
despite being highly soluble in aquous
Solutions the DNA linked Catalyst
molecules remained hybridized at the
surface of the electrode even under
harsh experimental conditions
immobilizing the DNA linked Catalyst and
Electrode also significantly increased
the rate of Co production in a series of
experiments the researchers monitored
the co production rate with each of
their catalysts in solution without
attached DNA strands the conventional
setup and then with them immobilized by
DNA on the electrode with all three
catalysts the amount of Co generated per
minute was Far higher when the DNA
linked Catalyst was immobilized on the
electrode in addition immobilizing the
DNA linked Catalyst on the electrode
greatly increased the selectivity in
terms of the products one persistent
challenge in using CO2 to generate Co in
aquous Solutions is that there is an
inevitable competition between the
formation of Co and the formation of
hydrogen that tendency was eased by
adding DNA to the Catalyst in solution
and even more so when the Catalyst was
immobilized on the electrode using DNA
for both the Cobalt poring Catalyst and
the humm based Catalyst the formation of
Co relative to hydrogen was
significantly higher with the DNA linked
Catalyst on the electrode than in
solution with the iron porer and
Catalyst they were about the same with
the iron it doesn't matter whether it's
in solution or on the electrode first
explains both of them have selectivity
for Co so that's good
too progress and
plans first and her team have now
demonstrated that their DNA based
approach combines the advantages of the
traditional solid state Catalyst and the
newer small molecule ones in their
experiments they achieved the highly
efficient chemical conversion of CO2 to
co and also were able to control the mix
of products formed and they believe that
their technique should prove scalable
DNA is inexpensive and widely available
and the amount of catalyst required is
several orders of magnitude lower when
it's immobilized using DNA based on her
work thus far first hypothesizes that
the structure and spacing of The small
molecules on the electrode May directly
impact both catalytic efficiency and
product selectivity using DNA to control
the precise positioning of her small
molecule Catalyst she plans to evaluate
those impacts and then extrapolate
design parameters that can be applied to
other classes of energy conversion
catalysts ultimately she hopes to
develop a predictive algorithm the
researchers can use as they Design
electrocatalytic Systems for a wide
variety of
applications This research was supported
by a grant from the MIT energy
initiative seed fund