hello computational music theorists our
topic for the coming week is going to be
on intervals and equivalents and working
with what equal and the same and so on
mean I am very much trying to treat
everybody
in this class and everybody I meet as
equals but that doesn't mean that I
think that everybody is the same in fact
that would that would be a very unequal
way to treat people so we can have this
notion that equality does not mean the
same thing and that equal does not mean
identical this is something I hope we
practice in our lives but it's also very
important in thinking about how we
compare musical
structures I'm asking you over the
weekend to read a very interesting
chapter from Dimitri tko's a geometry of
Music in which he talks about five kinds
of
equivalents a few more but mostly about
five kinds that he calls optic octave
permutation transposition inversion and
cardinality
these ways of thinking about equality of
notes or melodies or chords or other
musical structures even whole pieces is
going to be very important when we want
to find particular musical gestures or
we want to identify particular things
using a computer I'm sitting at the
piano because I'm going to demonstrate a
few of the things that we might think
mean that something is equal or
something is the same but maybe they're
not
identical but first I want to play
something that doesn't work very well on
the piano so listen to these two
pieces the way you wear your
hat the way you sip your
tea the memory of all that
no no they can't take that away from me
the way your smile just
be the way you sing off
King the way you wear your
hand the way you sip your
tea the memory of all
no no they can't take that away from me
the way your smile just
been the way you sing off
King I asked you to listen to two pieces
actually I just played excerpts but did
I play two pieces or did I play One
Piece twice
were those two pieces the same
piece were they the same
recording I think will think that well
they were
the same piece but different recordings
different performers different styles
different interpretations but there was
something the same about them so we can
think of an equivalence class or a kind
of equivalence between pieces that
doesn't necessarily mean that they are
identical now let's turn to some musical
structures that we can demonstrate at
the
piano so I want to talk concretely about
some ways that we might think about
equivalence and what do we mean by
equivalence when we're talking about
notes or chords or melodies or pieces
and I want to think about some of the
things that we might be doing
so for
instance can we think of a context
where
notes as a group are the
same regardless of the order that we
talked about them let's start with just
a C major chord c e
[Music]
g and if I say C3 E3
G3 and that's the chord
or if I say that it's G3 E3
C3 it's still the same chord or if I
said that the chord is E3 C3 G3 it
really doesn't matter so this could be
when we're talking about chords a place
where there is a
permutation equivalence doesn't matter
what order they're in on the other hand
if we're talking about um a melody or
something some sort of piece that has
you know
[Music]
um then it matters if we
go
sorry those don't seem to be equivalent
in some context that we might think of
as
equivalents so there could be a context
where P permutation equivalence is
active and context where it isn't uh we
can also think of
cardinality especially on the piano it
doesn't matter if I play c e
g as a chord or if I play c c e
g you can't even tell maybe I can put
two fingers on the c or something like
that but on in a cordal context on the
piano we would normally say well that
that cardinality doesn't really matter
in terms of the sound um if you're going
to be notating it then yeah it
matters we also can think of octave
equivalence that all those notes are C
when we say something like all of these
things are we're saying that they're
equivalent in some way so we're saying
that in this case when I say all these
notes are C we're talking about an opave
equivalence relationship
but I can't say that all of those notes
are
C3 only that note is
C3
C2 C4 if you were um you know uh in
instrumental teacher and you ask
somebody on uh on an instrument like you
know flute to the clarinet or the violin
to play a scale in three octaves and
they just play the same octave
[Music]
you'd really say no no NE I asked for
three octave so so we can think of a
world where there isn't an octave
equivalence and we can put these two
things together that we can think
[Music]
cegc we have a kind of world where we
say well that's the same as c e g in the
sense of play the tonic Triad in C major
it doesn't matter if I
[Music]
play those all fulfill this particular
equivalence
class
and there are other ones um one of the
ones that
Tacho sort of assumes throughout is and
isn't even a part of his optic
Opti world is um spelling so it doesn't
matter
or C major is a little bit hard but it
doesn't matter if
I think of a single note play E
flat play D
sharp it's the same thing so we can
think of a spelling equence um now if
you were to be in theory one class and
you're asked to write a C Minor triad
and you write
c d Shar G you probably going to get
marked wrong because that's a context
where there is not spelling
equivalence we can also think of a world
where there's a transposition equivalent
so for
[Music]
instance
and we can say oh well those are both
the same piece those are both Mary had a
little l so that there's um a
transposition equivalence that makes
that piece still Mary had a little
L and we definitely use that when we're
talking about chord types so we talk
about that's a major Triad that's a
major Triad that's a major Triad um so
that we can have talk about a concept
like major Tria that takes into account
that there's um a transposition
equivalence probably the one that uh
people like the least and and think that
it's not really a context that we want
to be working with is the inversion
context and when we play something in a
tall context like a C major
Triad and then we invert it so let's see
from E to G is a minor thir so we'll go
from G B flat is a minor third and E to
C is a major third so B flat to D is a
is a major third so we can
say in an inversion and transposition
context that those well I guess those is
not even a transposition context um that
those two are equivalent and not like go
whoa whoa you what are we talking about
but um there are some places in
post-tonal theory where that's important
but we can even think about it even in
the tonal or in this case a pre- tonal
context here I'm going to play four
pieces one goes well I'll do the one we
just
[Music]
played here's another piece
and here's another
[Music]
piece play that one one more time so you
get in your
[Music]
ears and then we can have a piece like
this
[Music]
I played in some sense four different
melodies or something but maybe I only
played three different pieces because we
can recognize oh those last two are the
same piece but one is upside down from
the other this is actually a a piece
that was really famous in the 15th
century called lar or the armed man and
composers at that time like to play
around with it they transposed it they
did diatomic transposition so that you
play in um in well you know different
modes so instead
of may you play some maybe you play
something
[Music]
like and it's a slightly different piece
but still the same piece so you can
think of a dionic transposition
equivalence but they also definitely
played with what I was showing the
inversion equivalent context so that uh
at are in some ways the beginning of the
same
piece we're going to be asking you in
the problem set to see if you can come
up with other contexts where we talk
about well that's the same thing like is
this a C major
Triad good well this is a fancy piano so
I'm going to change the temperament to
mean tone and now we
go maybe over Zoom you can't hear the
difference as much but we can go to a
you slightly different one
even
[Music]
or and those are all the notes c e g
they're not exactly the same but we
think of them as the same so we can
think of a temperament context or a
tuning context where we allow things to
be equivalent so I think this is the
background that you need in order to uh
go through uh the reading of Dimitri
tachko on Optics and
equivalence as usual you're going to be
implementing your code in Python using
musical objects either that you create
or that you have unlocked in music 21
and when you're doing this you think
about what two objects are what are two
notes that python defines as equal or
that I have defined in music 21 defines
as equal what do we mean by that and
you'll see that each object in the
computational language generally has
only one
builtin uh sort of equivalence set that
defines what the equal equal operator or
whatever it is um means and well there's
actually a second one that is operator
that defines something else what do we
mean by these two
objects are the same that they is the
same I is what I wanted to say but um
and what choice was made and how could
we have made a better choice and who's
going to hate me for the choice I made
and who would have hated me if I made
another choice on defining equality in a
note or in a chord
thanks for listening to this video and
now let's get started with reading what
Demitri chatko has to say on this
subject