Our next speaker is Anel Enrique, senior
manager, digital health and digital
health scientist at Amwell. Anel Enrique
will describe how a digital mental
health platform that connects
individuals with mental health coaches
and video modules can improve mental
well-being. Over to you, Anhal.
>> So, thank you everyone. Thank you for
the invitation to to be here and also
thank you everyone for for being here
this morning. I want to talk today about
the digital mental health intervention
we're using and the effects that it's
having at scale and more in particular
in in workplace outcomes.
So just for those who are not familiar
with Amwell and then Silvercloud, Amwell
is a teley health provider and it has an
ecosystem of care spanning inerson,
virtual and automated care and within
the automated care offering, Silvercloud
is a provider of digital mental health
interventions and it's evidence-based.
I'm part of the clinical research team
and I've been in the company for the
past eight years validating the platform
in different ways. So effectiveness,
cost effectiveness and different uh
other areas. uh as well and to the point
that you know this is one of the most
well validated interventions worldwide.
We have more than 1.7 million uh users
across all the organizations health
systems pay providers we work with
worldwide and most in particular we have
presence in the UK, Ireland and in the
US.
We don't do this alone obviously you
know and and we're very proud of the
partnership we've had over the past two
years with with the HSI with the work
with is Joe and and and an basically you
know through this work we are trying to
delve more into the data and really you
know uh find signals in the nose about
what makes this product uh to to work
and and finding the the best ways to to
use this information.
Today I want to talk you about you know
one particular partnership which is of
importance because this is the data that
my my colleague Brian will be talking
about later on as well which is
basically a partnership we have with the
national health service in Ireland
called the the HSSE the health service
executive the health service executive
is a national healthcare organization
for public health and social care
services in Ireland and it's free at the
point of contact for for I citizens and
people living in Ireland so in
partnership ship with the HSSE. In 2021,
we launched the LA National Digital CVT
service which basically had the aim of
making mental health support more widely
accessible in in Ireland. As we all
know, prevalences of mental health are
you know problems are on the rise and
this was a way to to address this this
problem for us in particular was an
exciting opportunity because also would
give us the opportunity to derive
important insights regarding service
delivery engagement and outcomes. Just
for you to get a sense of this service
delivery model. It's a prescription
only. So basically referrals may come
from primary care, primary care
physicians and then specialty care and
some charities. It's meant for
individuals with mild to moderate
presentation of the depression and
anxiety and it's offered with coaching
from a psychologist who trained in low
inensity interventions and they offer a
weekly reviews in a six to8 over over a
treatment course.
You can see here in terms of the most
used programs is mostly the anxiety
program and then the comorbid depression
and anxiety program and in terms of the
service utilization we are quite proud
in this partnership which is quite
unique in terms of like the the success
it's not the case for many of them and
I'm happy to talk more about you know
what what contributes to this uniqueness
of this partnership but you can see you
know that the volume of referrals is
very high you know and it has been
continuously growing over time only in
the last year to year from the December
24 report there an 18% growth from the
you know in yeartoear and the activation
rate which is basically users activating
the account is 67% which is very good at
an industry you know based on industry
standards and you can see that you know
primary care physicians are the highest
source of referrals so most of the
referrals are coming from from primary
care
in this um you know in our efforts to to
continuously do service evaluations we
have been sharing many reports with the
with the HSSE and they have been using
this information either to you know
inform the decisions around expanding
the model of care and adjusting
optimizing service delivery you know and
it has been very very useful in in this
regard. It also has shown some of the
outcomes that we're achieving. So 90% of
people who sign into the intervention
report positive expectations which
speaks about the quality of the the
referral by the by the physician. And
then when it comes to clinical outcomes,
we also see that 50% achieve reliable
recovery. This is people who start with
clinical levels of depression and
anxiety and transition to recovery by
the end of treatment. And most of them
are satisfied with the treatment. We
published some of the results already
two years ago on the one-year
evaluation. Happy to share this paper if
you want to know more about it after the
the talk. And today we just want to talk
about uh an internal piece of work we've
done. It's in review right now, so not
published yet. So take it with a pinch
of salt but basically we were asking the
question what are the indirect effects
of DTX for depression and anxiety on
workplace outcomes. So over the course
of one year we collected work related
outcomes on clients of this service. We
implemented a a validated measure called
the WPAI which basically measures
absentism presentism overall
productivity loss and activity
impairment alongside routinely collected
data on depression and anxiety. Here you
have a flowchart that basically displays
you know the people that was included
into this evaluation. We included the
full sample for all analysis which was
people who was employed at baseline and
it was around 7,000 clients.
This is a you know just a snapshot of
the sample characteristics. So 66% with
ages 18 to 44 70% female which is quite
consistent to what uh Joe was uh sharing
at the beginning. they are more willing
to to engage in these in these uh
offerings. Moderate levels of depression
and anxiety, 50% receiving concurrent
treatments. And then when it comes to uh
absentism, presentism and productivity
loss, you can see that it was quite
affected which is in line with people
having uh moderate depression and
anxiety.
So what were the key findings? So when
looking at the pre-post effects using
the the the overall sample, we saw that
over the treatment period, patients
demonstrated significant improvements
across the four constructs and the
effect sizes were going rang in the
small to medium effect size which is
quite good as an indirect effect and
these functional gains were also
positively linked with reductions in
depression and anxiety.
We tried to put a monetary value and it
was an estimation. So we basically used
a human capital approach to to um
estimate the the cost savings the
product productivity related cost
savings of this and for that we
leveraged the Irish national salary data
stratified by education and gender. So
you can see that overall in terms of
productivity loss there was an 4,000
saving peranom per treated patient
overall. Obviously this is an estimation
but this is kind of what we are seeing
based on the treated sample. If we look
at clinical levels of depression versus
those who were with subclinical, we see
a huge difference. So basically those
with with clinical depression at
baseline were much likely to uh lead to
cost savings compared to those
subclinical. And this difference would
be even higher when it comes to clinical
anxiety versus subclinical where those
with clinical anxiety at baseline would
lead to lead to um higher cost savings.
All this together including all you know
from from this sample from this national
representative sample of 7,000 patients
equals uh you know around 29 29 million
um euros in in cost savings based on the
based on this improvements in workplace
uh productivity outcomes which is uh
quite of a cost savings. Obviously again
going back to the point that it's an
estimation but this is kind of like
aligned to what the literature is also
showing.
So just as a takeaway message from from
what we're sharing here. So DTX you know
can effectively improve workplace
functioning by attenuating symptoms of
depression and anxiety. Remember this
was you know offered at a national level
for people who was showing up for in
primary care and specialty care. But I
can't stress enough the importance of
adjusting a service for optimal
performance. This takes time and takes
uh resources, you know, to continue
finding how to make it more more
pleasant for for clinicians to refer and
all and all this. So, you know, this
this these results weren't there from
day one is the is what I'm trying to
say. Something that takes time, but if
you do this properly and you really work
on the integration, realizing the
potential of DTX at a scale may lead to
huge uh cost savings. So, I want to uh
leave it here and happy to answer any
question you may have. Thank you.
Thank thank you Anh Hill. So I I have
one one quick question for you which is
um you talked just about generally that
this partnership happened but what were
some factors that made this partnership
work so well?
>> So it's a good question because not all
the partnerships we've had and we we
have more than 500 partnerships you know
in you know with clinical organizations
and payers providers over the world and
not all of this successful. I think what
uh made this partnership quite
successful and unique was there was a
trust in brand you know in terms of like
silver cloud being you know NHS back to
it's used in many chess many NHS
services in the UK and you know that was
a mirror that the the HSSE in Ireland
was looking to and also there was a
continued education campaign and I'm not
saying an intensive education campaign
I'm saying a continued education
campaign of clinician raising awareness
about how this intervention can help
patients You know and I think another
important point and this sometimes you
know is different to what we see in
other partnerships are the incentives.
So what were the incentives for a
clinician to refer to this intervention
and the main incentives would be the
clinical gain. So the clinicians would
see this as an opportunity for patients
to gain timely access to evidence-based
mental health support which is sometimes
you know these incentives are misaligned
when there are other priorities for
incentives. So I think this is something
that it was quite unique here.
>> All right. Well, thank you. I know we
have we have one more speaker coming up
and Brian will talk a little bit more
about the research side of our
collaborations. So, uh, thank you very
much.