uh it's a pleasure to be here um and uh
I'm excited to be uh presenting to this
audience today we'll talk a little bit
about uh enabling Innovation and you'll
get a little bit of a an Insider look as
to uh mit's own administrative systems
processes and services and some of the
work that we're doing to really um uh
innovate and uh modernize a lot of those
uhst systems I think you know sometimes
we think about all the great uh Leading
Edge research uh that MIT does in the
area of Technology uh but we don't
always think about the fact that uh MIT
itself is an organization with its own
uh internal systems um and in some cases
those internal systems don't always take
number one priority uh it's a little bit
like the the shoemakers kids have no
shoes um a lot of the the focus and the
priori ation goes to the research and
The Innovation uh but uh looking
internally at MIT systems um you know
we'll talk about kind of the journey
that we've been through and what we're
looking to undertake over the next
several
years let's see
here okay so um I am part of the
organization of the Executive Vice
President and Treasurer um and I'm uh
partnering with the uh Chief Information
officer at MIT to undertake a multi-year
business and digital transformation
Journey um uh Glenn Shore who I report
into uh I think had a great statement
which was when you walk around campus
you see a lot of cranes often you'll
hear loud construction noises and might
have to rroo from time to time as we
pursue the work of expanding and
renewing our campus's physical
infrastructure to give MIT the spaces
needs to do its best work well now is
the time to similarly renew our digital
landscape and we'll talk about what that
means and how we're going about that and
how we're leveraging Innovation to
really Drive some of that
work um when we talk about our digital
landscape a lot of the areas we focus on
again are our internal administrative
systems so what do those systems enable
us to do they uh really enable us to do
everything from fundraising and
connecting with our community
uh of alumni to buying goods and
services and managing our finances
recruiting hiring paying and supporting
our employees through our HR and payroll
functions conducting research uh and
meeting compliance requirements through
both our pre-award and post- awward
administrative processes and of course
educating advising and supporting our
students um if we look a little bit at
the history of some of these systems
you'll see that um they've been around
for quite a while uh I myself was a
graduate student at MIT I graduated in
1995 so I'm dating myself U but I'm also
dating our administrative systems some
of which are as old as I am um and so we
you you will see here um our finance
system and data warehouse uh application
launched in 1986 our student system
launched in 1984 our budgeting system
launched in 2001 our HR System somewhere
in the early 2000s and our advancement
or fundraising system launched in 2013
so um I was brought on board um in
September about a little over a year ago
2023 to really uh help to lead an effort
for MIT to modernize and transform and
innovate its internal administrative
systems in order to be able to reduce
the administrative burden on the MIT
community so you know our our systems
are aging they're they're out of date
there hasn't really been a lot of data
governance you know there's I think a
wonderful spirit of
innovation uh at MIT um which is which
is wonderful uh but at the same time um
over time uh that needs to be balanced
with uh making sure that uh we have um
alignment data governance best practices
um and a little bit more structure to
ensure that we avoid duplication of
effort and streamline our
operations so what digital
transformation means to us is not just
popping in a new system it's really a
holistic engagement with our community
on systems processes capacities and
support it's also not just customizing
the way we do our systems to do things
the way we we've always done them and um
if you look at some of the systems that
we have in place we have sap for finance
and HR which were implemented some 25
years ago um at that time MIT went from
a paper based uh set of processes to uh
sap and a lot of it was really just hey
I want to do in the system uh things
exactly the way I do them on paper today
um so not a lot of um streamlining of
processes uh not a lot of trying to to
find
commonalities um and I think that's one
of the challenges that MIT has seen over
time is the fact that it's been very
difficult to keep our systems up to dat
and upgraded because of the heavy
customization that we placed upon them
25 years ago so we're trying to really
find the right balance between
simplification and accommodating unique
needs going forward um considered done
as soon as deployed is also not our
approach we want to make sure that we're
providing ongoing support across campus
after implementation to ensure uh we uh
maximize the benefit of these changes
changes so our approach if you really
think about the different dimensions or
pillars of our approach there's really
four key pillars um and these are people
process technology and data now you've
probably heard these a number of times
before but what do they really mean to
us so from a people perspective it's
really about having a robust support
model and engaged and able users a lot
of this revolves around providing good
training good Communications what's
often referred to as organizational
change management to make sure that the
community is supported every step of the
way through the change process and there
are some methodologies that we leverage
uh there's one called the adcar model
which was developed by prosi which walks
through the different stages of change
adoption and that we look to leverage in
order to make sure that the community is
supported every step of the way the
second is around processes so as I
talked about before it's really about
reexamining and simplifying our business
processes wherever possible um we like
to say that we want our business
processes to be as common as possible
but as different as necessary and the
word necessary is really important where
we think there are unique needs and
unique um aspects that provide value to
the community then we will we will make
sure that those unique needs are are met
otherwise you know as much commonality
as we can can provide um the easier it
will be and the less the administrative
burden from a technology perspective
we're looking at seamless Cutting Edge
systems to power our administrative
functions a lot of these are um U start
with off-the-shelf packages uh that are
cloud-based software as a service
platforms uh we'll talk a little bit
also about uh some of the AI related
work that we're doing uh with specific
use cases uh because no presentation is
complete without talking about AI these
days uh so we'll make sure to cover that
as well and then um from a data
perspective having access to Salient and
understandable data for informed and
enhanced decision-making I think a lot
of the environment right now in the
administrative functions at MIT um are
focused on reconciling data across a lot
of data sets uh because a lot of systems
either are disjointed or don't talk to
each other so we want to move away from
the focus on data reconciliation and
validation to really focusing on Data
Insights and uh having informed and
enhan decision- making through those
insights so what you'll see here is a is
a multi-year view of our initial road
map that we've developed um on the left
hand side you'll see the various tracks
uh that we've broken them into there
there's a total of 16 projects um some
of consolid validated into one bar there
um but you'll see that we have a
foundational track which really focuses
on a lot of the work that we plan to do
around data governance reporting and
analytics uh we'll talk more about data
governance but a lot of that is around
ensuring that we have common data
definitions you know we have uh five
schools and one college and something
like 15 different department labs and
centers and institutes at
MIT and that can lead to a lot of
different ways of interpreting data a
lot of different ways of defining data
elements so we want to make sure there's
consistency across that that's really
foundational um in order to make sure
that we have good uh data and uh that
people are speaking the same language
the other element around data governance
is uh defining data stewardship roles
and
responsibilities and those data stewards
will be responsible and accountable for
the quality completeness of specific
data elements so to the extent that we
find issues with specific data elements
we can go back to those data stewards
and make sure that those issues are
fixed at the
source um then we look at uh HR um so
we're planning and implementing a new HR
payroll solution uh we've been spending
the last several months looking at um
three platforms sap workday and Oracle
um to provide that that uh that platform
um and again it's people process
technology and data so we often talk
about the systems because it's easier to
refer to the systems um but we're we're
looking at that in conjunction with best
leveraging best practices around
business processes um making sure that
we are uh developing um Communications
and training capabilities to support our
community Through the change effort and
making sure that we have
good data governance practices in place
for each one of these projects um around
the finance space um you'll see we've
pushed off financials and post award
grants management solution a little bit
we thought we're already taking on a lot
in those first three or four years but
we are looking at the possibility of
trying to bring that forward right now
we have a six to sevene road map we'd
like to try to get as much as we can
done within the next four years four to
five years to provide the most benefit
to the community so we're actually
looking at a possibility of moving that
forward in the research space um
providing the community with the ability
to do research forecasting so to be able
to say if we add another postto to this
grant um how is that going to impact my
grand budget uh when am I going to run
out of money doing what if scenario
analysis um that's really uh an
important need for the community we've
developed some pilots in that space and
we'll continue to uh further enhance
those those capabilities to do research
forecasting uh we have some new
compliance modules around research that
are going in and then we're going to
focus on a new pre-award grants
management solution so this is around
really supporting the proposal
development um uh process for MIT which
is really really critical MIT being such
a strong uh research institution uh
everything we can do to really make sure
that we have streamlined processes
around um uh grants proposal development
is is really core uh to the
organization from a student perspective
uh we currently don't have a Student
Success and degree audit solution so
what does that mean Student Success is
really about making sure that we
identify when students may be at risk
and when they may need some additional
help where how it's a providing them
with a platform where they can connect
with their advisers and get realtime
support um so we don't have a formal
platform around that and uh that's
really a key priority for us as well as
from a degree auditing perspective how
do we make sure that our students are on
track to complete their degree and meet
all of the requirements associated with
their degree within the the expected
time frame so that's another area where
we're very focused on uh we've been
looking at various Platforms in the
marketplace and we're currently
evaluating those
platforms um and then finally the two
areas uh here at the bottom are around
advancement so this is really our
fundraising um platform uh implementing
a new customer relationship management
platform to keep track of all of our
alumni um and be able to better connect
with our alumni um and other donors uh
through uh those platforms and finally
we're developing a new MIT
intrnet uh which we're calling Community
Home uh so this is a platform where we
really want to create a bigger sense of
community within MIT I think we do a
really great job of communicating to the
broader Community about all the
interesting uh research that's happening
at MIT but how do we make sure that
people are connecting internally as well
identifying those places where um they
can leverage each other's areas of
expertise and uh find out how to uh
connect so um as you can see a lot of
work uh over the next uh especially 3 or
four years um but um we're we're excited
about uh the the journey uh and and the
leap forward that MIT will take now a
lot of these projects take two to three
years to implement so how do we make
sure that we balance that with shorter
term quick wins and and improvements and
of course this is where AI comes in um
so we've recently kicked off two
workstream relating to um AI in
administration and operations um the
first one is partnering with MIT faculty
from mit's computer science and AI lab
as well as from the Sloan School of
Management um we're very fortunate to
have Simon Johnson who is a recent Nobel
Prize uh uh Laur winner um from the SL
School of Management who's part of our
working group on AI uh really studying
um how AI will impact uh the future of
work
um and this is you know MIT is is a
great use case uh internally for that
understanding how a lot of the work that
we're doing around leveraging AI will
help to streamline Administration and uh
operations um and that first working
group will help to establish some
guidelines around responsible and
ethical use of AI and and other things
we'll talk about more in the next slide
and then the second working group um is
around focusing and identifying and
deployment
um aib based systems that could lead to
high impact improvements in these areas
so the community has already submitted
we we kicked just kicked this off a
couple of months ago we've already
gotten over 30 different use cases uh
from the community that we're evaluating
and determining uh which ones we're
going to move forward with so the first
working group we're calling setting the
foundation and this is where you know we
do have a unique opportunity at MIT
because we have such great research
that's happening in the space such
leading research we want to make sure
that uh we leverage um that uh research
in defining our AI Vision developing our
strategy um planning and prioritizing
the work that we do and making sure that
we can measure uh the benefits that
we're going to get from these AI use
cases so um we are focusing on
understanding the technical complexities
involved in pursuing these opportunities
including legal constraints and uh
making sure that we evaluate potential
pitfalls I think a lot of people have
heard about AI
hallucinations uh and other challenges
um including uh bias in AI so our
faculty members are making sure that we
are um really taking those things into
consideration as we look at these use
cases and understand the implications of
implementing AI within our
administrative areas um and you know
really provide us with guidance around
policies and security and privacy
considerations as well so this is really
around setting that core Foundation
which will help to really uh advise the
second working group um which is really
we're calling high impact opportunities
and this is where we're focused more on
evaluating value versus cost and risk
and if you look at that chart it means
everything from simple tasks like
automating exist listing tasks through
embedded assistance and co-pilots um
copy generation coding assistance in
fact a lot of the software as a service
platforms that we're looking at today
are making significant investments in
their platforms for example on HR
payroll helping with u reviewing resumés
and providing um um feedback on uh those
resumés and and evaluating them against
job descriptions or things such such as
creating new job descriptions as opposed
to having to start from scratch really
being able to put in a few key words of
what you're looking for and it can
really help you to get a head start on
developing those job descriptions so
there's a lot of opportunities to
leverage AI as part of the the software
as a service solutions and we're
evaluating those things as well if we
know something's coming uh a couple of
years down the line does it make sense
for us to build our own probably not
unless we have a dire need for it so
we're really going to focus on use cases
on areas where we think there's really
uh quick wins and high value for
relatively little effort and that's how
we're evaluating all of those those
requests um so de we're developing
business cases um to identify those
Pilots that we're going to focus on we'd
rather focus on a few key Pilots that we
think are going to provide high value to
the community rather than spreading
ourselves too thin um and uh we are
going to uh leverage the the the the
guidelines that we're getting from the
first working group to really uh advise
on um the use cases that we're going to
select here so we're very excited about
this work we're starting the journey uh
we're also bringing in guest speakers
from other organizations uh we have the
CIO of Harvard who's speaking to the
group they're a little bit ahead of us
uh they've been doing some of this work
for a year or so they have some great
Lessons Learned they have some great use
cases that they've implemented they've
seen what's worked what's not worked so
we're looking to leverage that
experience as well um so it's an
exciting journey and it's important for
MIT to uh to make sure that we're uh
we're along for that Journey uh and
leveraging the the capabilities of AI
it's it's not very often that you get a
chance in the administrative world to
really leverage some of the research
that's going on in the academic world
and this is a unique opportunity where
we can do that so we're quite excited
about
that in terms of um the the benefits
that these projects and this Innovation
is going to provide to the community um
you know we think about we I've talked a
lot about the administrative side of
things but the administrators are not
really are not the only group that are
going to benefit from this it's really
ultimately about reducing the
administrative burden on the entire
community and that includes faculty and
students so what does that mean well um
it means that U you know faculty will be
able to get reports more quickly they'll
be able to get better insights from
those reports because their
administrators will be able to focus on
uh developing insights as opposed to
spending a lot of time manipulating data
reconciling data as I said
earlier um and and provide greater
efficiency to the community as a result
some specific examples of that are in um
improving the research planning process
um so providing enhanced tools for
forecasting research expenses against
budgets I mentioned the example of like
adding a postdoc to a grant and
understanding when that Grant uh will
run out of money for example as a result
um it also revolves around more accurate
budgeting and planning um for faculty um
to look at uh you know when um these
various uh you know how do we how do we
leverage um the need for control and
accuracy while balancing uh our budgets
um automated proposal management that's
really key uh better workflows and
collaboration Tools around the
development of project proposals um and
providing um uh fewer bottlenecks in the
grand application process so making it
easier and faster for for us to secure
those
grants it's also uh from um a
centralized funding overview perspective
it's looking at a place where faculty
can easily see how to map people to
funding sources including detailed
insights into the researchers that are
appointed to each research Grant um it's
from a student perspective providing
more holistic student advising I was
giving the example of the Student
Success platform um so enabling uh
students to progress through their
degree more quickly have more visibility
have more support um early student
intervention tools for atrisk students
um and then finally streamline Student
Success
communication um throughout their
academic careers uh through the
development of some of these tools as
well so even though we we talk a lot
about how do we make administrators
worlds easier how do we increase
efficiency and productivity within the
administration function there are direct
relationships and impacts to how our
community including our faculty and our
students are going to benefit from a lot
of those
improvements so um what is my role in
all this and my team's role um so the
the digital transformation team which is
the team that I lead really tries to
direct um the organization to uh really
focus on modernizing systems and our
business processes so we really act as a
funnel to try to focus resources on the
work ahead that's required to provide
expertise on best practices that we've
seen both across um the uh higher red
industry as well as other Industries um
I spent a lot of time working in
financial services in the past um and
I've seen best practices across both
Industries um to really help Drive the
successful execution of pretty complex
projects as you saw we're taking on five
tracks of really kind of heavy uh
projects and complex projects with a lot
of interdependencies and interactions
across those various tracks so making
sure that we keep track of all that
identify those interdependencies making
sure everybody's connected making sure
everybody understand what comes next and
what role they need to play in that and
understanding how their day-to-day work
will change right so when we talk about
the future of work um post digital
transformation and the use of AI I get
that question a lot is what will my job
look like uh in five years once we're
done with this and really the goal is to
uh enable people to focus on higher
value added activities and let some of
the technology and some of the AI take
on some of the more administrative tasks
that they're doing today um so again
people can focus on insight
and more complex analysis rather than on
repetitive administrative tasks um and
then really making sure that the whole
Community is engaged so as we looked at
new platforms for our finance HR and
payroll platforms we engaged over 400
members of the MIT community in demos
over this past summer to make sure that
we could make to to get their input and
feedback on where they felt that uh
these various platforms could add value
to their day-to-day work and what their
preference were across those platforms
so Community engagement is really key
especially in high right it's a highly
decentralized environment and we want to
make sure everybody feels like they're
part of the journey and not the
transformation journey is being done
onto themselves but really they're
they're part of it every step of the way
so um there are four core disciplines
that go along with uh providing uh the
the the services that I mentioned
earlier and those are project governance
and project management business process
Improvement organizational change
management and data governance analytics
and business intelligence and those are
really the four key pillars of what my
organization does and brings to to the
table um I'm not going to go through all
the sub bullets here but just to kind of
give you a flavor of each one I've
talked about some of these already from
a project governance and project
management perspective it's around um
establishing a clear governance
structure making sure that we have good
escalation procedures and
decision-making processes um identifying
and clearly communicating team roles and
responsibilities overseeing scope
schedule and budget actively managing
those risks using agile methodologies
wherever possible from a business
process Improvement it's making sure
that we're looking at processes end to
end it's very easy to um uh look at a
process but only really look at a part
of the process and try to optimize that
I kind of call it squeezing the balloon
at one end if you're only optimizing a
part of the process you risk actually
making things worse Downstream um so
it's really important to look at those
processes end to end um and again
finding the right balance between
simplification and accommodating unique
needs uh from a change management
perspective I've talked about um
targeted Communications
making sure that we um uh provide
continuous support we'll use metrics to
track adoption and make sure that once
we've implemented change the change
sticks and people don't revert back to
the old ways of doing things uh which is
always a risk from a change management
perspective and then from a data
governance reporting and analytics
perspective I talked about establishing
a robust data governance model aligning
and common data definitions establishing
data Steward and data trustee roles and
responsibilities to make sure we have
complete accurate uh data um and um
making sure that we're providing the
community with flexible Tools around
reporting and
analytics um so from a just to emphasize
that point you know we're really
focusing from a data governance
perspective on making sure we have data
informed decisions that we have
centralized access to data with common
data definition and enhanced support
those are some of the foundational
pieces that will ensure um that we build
a robust business intelligence and
analytics suite and a community of data
informed decisionmaking going
forward so there's a lot of work uh
ahead of us uh to go through this
transformation Journey um we're looking
to uh really innovate in the space of uh
leveraging AI to keep our community
engaged and excited and providing them
with quick wins every step of the way um
we have some pretty uh ambitious plans
looking at people process technology and
data um and making sure that all four of
those dimensions are aligned um as I
talked about you know we need to make
sure from a people perspective that we
have solid governance and sponsorship we
need to make sure also that our key
subject matter experts are available to
participate in the transformation
activities and one of the things we're
doing is really looking at who are those
subject matter experts across the
community and how do we make sure that
we free them up to participate in this
work they have a day job today so how do
we make sure we can create enough
bandwidth either through backfill
resources um through uh various um uh
compensation programs through in some
cases bringing in retirees who have
recently left MIT um because MIT has
such a complex environment of systems
and processes today it takes a long time
to bring somebody from the outside and
ramp them up the learning curve so
that's one of our big challenges is how
do we make sure that we free up our
subject matter experts but we only have
a limited amount of time to bring new
people in and get them up the learning
curve so the idea of bringing back
retirees part-time who can act as
rotational resource provide more
bandwidth that's already worked in a
couple of areas where we've piloted that
um and provide change management support
uh every step of the way including what
is our ongoing support model going to
look like so you know we talk about new
technology I think technology is a great
um enabler for business transformation
but we really need to think about what
how do we improve the quality of the
services that we provide to the
community how do we need to in some
cases restructure our internal
departments and organizations to make
sure that we're providing high quality
service and how do we measure that going
forward how long should it take for a
particular particular service to be
provided to the community establishing
service level agreements for example to
be able to measure that how long does it
take today what do we think it should
take and then measuring the improvements
that we've done once we've actually
implemented the new
transformation um from a process
perspective I talked about end to-end
processes common as possible different
as necessary approach um technology
using the AI to really enable us to get
quick wins leveraging best-in-class Erp
technology platforms and finally
from a data perspective establishing
those common data definitions and those
data stewardship roles and
responsibilities so we're excited about
the Leap Forward um and uh uh really uh
you know uh partnering with the entire
Community to really bring MIT to uh the
same level of quality and Innovation uh
that we have in our research and
academic Enterprises to our
administrative Enterprise
thank
you thank you Reno so much for a great
talk there's a couple of questions that
have come up here I guess I I'll read
them to try to facilitate getting four
votes glad you are collaborating with
the other school in Cambridge why not
toine problems for startups to solve
instead of old systems like workday
invest in problems to be
solved yeah so that's a good question I
think um you know there are uh we're
trying to find the right balance between
what I would call buy versus build uh
and so um when you look at um some of
the platforms that I talked about like
work day and Oracle and sap um there are
uh there's a lot of there's a tremendous
amount of investment being um uh put in
by these companies to stay relevant and
modernize their platform form so when we
talk about AI a lot of AI advances that
are being built into work into workday
um uh oral Etc service now Salesforce a
lot of the big platforms out there and
so uh there are some cases where it
doesn't make sense for us to invest in
building our own Solutions because these
are
industry um uh platforms that are built
on best practices and where there's uh
so much investment being put in to their
road map over the next several years
that you know we wouldn't be able to
match that level of investment and keep
up with modern technology in the same
way um while in other areas that I think
are more Niche and unique to um the
needs of MIT uh there are opportunities
there to focus on um you know
potentially leveraging startup
activities and uh finding unique and and
modern and and Innovative and more agile
ways to solve some of those problems so
we're trying to find that right balance
U between leveraging established
companies that will continue to innovate
um in some of the core areas but also
finding those areas where we can get you
know a competitive advantage through
leveraging smaller more agile startup
companies just a quick comment too here
on that same question maybe you've
touched on this already but have you
ever considered using an open source
approach yes so I I that's part of what
we're looking at as well when we look at
some of the the smaller uh organizations
and the areas where we might be able to
um uh leverage uh unique uh Solutions is
is leveraging op Source data where it
makes sense great thanks our next
question is from innovator when
designing innovative business processes
through digital
transformation what is the most
important factor to consider in the ini
stage yeah so I think you know it's it's
really key to think about the fact that
uh again we don't want uh in many cases
what we'll do is we don't want to start
with
necessarily um documenting the current
state um the old way of doing things was
you document your current state you
define your future State and then you do
an Asis to 2B map mapping and you
identify where those key areas of
differences are um the problem is when
you've got 150 Department lab centers
and institutes and a lot of do a lot of
them are doing things their own way it
would take you two years to document all
of the current ways of doing things uh
and by the time you're done documenting
them they've changed uh so instead what
we do is we really focus on best
practice uh PL uh processes to start off
with um and uh we bring our subject
matter experts who know how things are
done today and we walk through with them
what the best practices are and then we
talk about where we think there's going
to be change and change impact and
really have them participate in saying
hey that's not how we do things today
and then we can question okay well why
are we doing things that way today is it
because there is valid uniqueness is it
some regulatory requirement that we need
to meet um or is it more because we've
done it like that for the last 25 years
and we're really wanting to challenge
the way people think about the way they
do their processes today um CH challenge
the status quo um and really drill in to
understand how can we create as much
efficiency as we can um in uh designing
the future state for our business
processes um so I think that's the most
important is really coming at it with a
uh um an open mindset uh and thinking
about looking at things with a fresh
perspective of what's you know what's
best practice um rather than just kind
of you know carrying maybe some of the
baggage that we have from the way we've
done things over the last 20 25 years
fair enough fair enough thanks okay I
think we have time for one question I'm
gonna see a sort of thread here in some
of the questions having to do with uh
resistance so I'm going to read this
question question
here see um how excuse me digital
transformation impacts both work
processes and organizational culture
often causing employee resistance how
can such resistance be effectively manag
and and any hints you have from uh the
home crowd here at MIT if you have any
stories that'd be great too yeah yeah oh
no this is a great topic and um you know
just like uh AI when you say Ai and you
talk about leveraging AI
um to many people it sounds great to a
lot of people it's very scary right
because it means what how is my job
going to change am I going to be able to
adapt to leveraging new technology um so
um we we do follow um so so
organizational change management is
really the reason I talk about people
process technology and data and I always
talk about people first is because the
hardest part is the people part uh and
it's all about organizational change
management um and I mentioned I
referenced a model that we use which is
a prosize atar model and that's an
acronym for awareness desire knowledge
ability and reinforcement and those are
the five stages of change adoption so
what that means is first you want to
make people aware of why are we doing
this right um and then with that comes
the next phase which is desire so you
want to get people excited about what
the future is going to look like you
want to get them excited about the fact
that they're not going to have to do as
many administrative repetitive tasks um
our goal is to really enable people and
support them through um these different
ways of working and leveraging this new
technology we want everybody to still
have a job we want them to have a better
job uh at the end of this process um so
building that desire in people is
important and then giving them the
knowledge of how are we going to get
there and we're going to get there
together and these are the steps of how
we're going to get there um and then
giving them the ability to get there so
now we've told you how we're going to
get there but now we need to give you
the skills to get there right so we're
going to train you we're going to hold
your hand every step of the way we're
going to make sure that you're feeling
comfortable um and we're not going to
move forward until you know you've been
trained you feel comfortable you
understand how your role is going to
change um and um
uh and then you have really
reinforcement is the last stage of the
outar model and reinforcement is once
we've implemented the new ways of
working how do we make sure that you
don't revert back to the old ways of
doing things how do we make sure to
continue to support you as you continue
to enhance and improve throughout the
process so great question R know thank
you so much again for giving us a great
talk thank you so much thank you very
[Applause]
much
e
e for