(lively orchestral music)
(traffic rumbling)
(lively orchestral music fades)
(upbeat jazz music)
(David laughing)
- (laughing) Ooh!
Ooh! (laughs)
(upbeat jazz music continues)
(vehicle pedals squeaking)
(moves to bright jazz music)
Hello!
I'm David Wallace.
(glass shattering)
- Oh, my God!
It's Product Man, I can't believe it.
- And I am a Professor
of Mechanical Engineering
and Design at MIT.
(bright jazz music continues)
And for 30 years, yep,
it's actually a long time,
I've been doing research and
teaching about product design.
Hello, everybody!
- Hello.
- [David] I really think and live design.
It's what I do.
- My opinion matters more.
- Oh, yeah, right on.
(bottle shatters)
(audience gasping)
- But more than anything,
the goal of my career
has been to create learning environments
that help inspire students
(starter gun pops)
to give them confidence to dream big,
to even be audacious,
(student shouts)
and to feel good and do good work,
to develop the humility to do the work,
and to tackle the challenges with zeal.
(bright jazz music continues)
I want them to dig deep and get it done,
and to feel the joy, the
thrill throughout this process.
- All done!
- And that's all
in the pursuit of excellence.
(bright jazz music continues)
So, in this series, I'm just
going to be sharing things
that I think I've learned
in my teaching journey,
and I hope that will help
you realize your dream
to take action and contribute
and just feel the satisfaction
of whatever road your
passions may take you.
So, what I'm going to do
is explore seven ideas,
in my world, I call them principles,
that have emerged during
my own teaching quest:
everything is an example;
(bubbly music)
have a plan and be ready to change it;
make students' stars shine;
everyone has something to teach;
goals are essential;
(bird chirping)
play seriously;
(bubbly music continues)
and experience the euphoria of growth.
As a bonus, you'll also find out
what this crab vehicle is all about.
(bubbly music continues)
(moves to lively instrumental music)
(lively instrumental music continues)
For each idea, I'm going to
provide a lot of examples
of the principles in action
with students at MIT,
and I'm going to suggest how you might use
these same ideas in your own pursuits.
(lively instrumental music continues)
Do you have ideas that you
want to bring to light?
How might you make them happen?
How might you help others grow
and realize their own aspirations?
Get ready to play seriously.
(lively music continues)
(lively instrumental music fades)