I'm Emily. I'm the founding product
engineer at Nowadays and we're a team of
MIT engineers at a Wongwide Combinator
building the first AI co-pilot for
streaming corporate events.
So, I studied computer science and
design at MIT where I led large-scale
initiatives from running the institute's
1,500 person career fair to organizing
fine dining pop-ups that served hundreds
of students. Coordinating the logistics
down to each minute taught me firsthand
just how complex event planning can be
and how much better it could be with the
right tools. Nowadays was founded by Amy
and Anna sisters who both led events at
Google, Facebook and MIT before starting
the company. I joined early to help them
build the product translating these real
world pains into AI powered solutions.
Every organization here runs events.
Whether that's leadership offsite, sales
kickoffs, global conferences, or company
retreats. With an increasingly
distributed workforces around the world,
organizations rely more than ever on
these gatherings to retain talent and
strengthen their company culture. The
demand for in-person connection is
clear. But the way events are planned
hasn't caught up. For the first time, AI
can meaningfully automate these tedious
tasks that are manual for event planning
and make the process scalable.
Behind every off-site or conference is a
surprisingly manual process. Planners
actually spend weeks juggling emails,
hundreds of hours creating spreadsheets,
and phone calls with hotels while
pricing remains really opaque. Current
legacy tools like CVET dominate the
space, but they're clunky, require
training, and don't address the last
mile, actually sourcing venues,
negotiating, and making decisions.
nowadays solves this by using AI to
contact venues, negotiate rates, and
deliver a dashboards of results within
24 hours, allowing teams to make faster,
smarter, and more cost-effective
decisions.
Nowadays, powers the entire event
workflow end to end. Our system will
pull live flight data to recommend the
best cities for distributed teams.
It reads, understands, and filters venue
options automatically, so you don't need
to look through thousands. With one
click, our AI sends requests to the
right hotels.
Within 24 hours, a dashboard updates
with live proposals.
Nowadays, gives companies a holistic
view to minimize spend and maximize
their options, not just for venues, but
also for restaurants, activities,
attendee management, and transportation.
One of our strongest signals of traction
has been referrals. Yan, a director at
Google, used nowadays for an incentive
trip. He loved the experience and
referred us to other EAS. And within a
week, four of his peers at Google also
became paying customers.
We've also powered events like Amazon's
executive dinners in New York and
Google's 375 person offsite at Universal
Studios. Customers consistently say
nowadays negotiates better rates than we
can ourselves. Some have gone even
further. Four of our customers became
investors after using our platform.
In the last two years, we've planned
over $11 million in event spend across
300 events for startups and enterprises
alike. Our business model is
straightforward. An annual subscription
or a percentage sourcing fee plus hotel
commissions. We're also an IATA
certified travel agency which allows us
to guarantee the best group rates
globally.
Corporate events are an excellent market
because customers have a high
willingness to pay and very little
churn. Cvent's recent $4.6 6 billion
acquisition demonstrates the size and
value of the market. Our advantage is a
combination of an international database
of over 400k venues and an AI first
model. This allows us to build faster,
cheaper, and more scalably than any
competitor out there.
We're looking for corporate partners
globally who host recurring off sites
and conferences as well as travel agency
partners to white label our technology.
And if this is not part of your
day-to-day role, we'd love for you to
connect us with your executive
assistant, chief of staff, or travel and
events team. They'll thank you for it,
and you may finally get that company
offsite that's been in the works for
years.
I'm Emily, and we're nowadays, a
sister-ledd MIT's built startup at a Y
Combinator, making planning simple.
Thank you.