GVAS is short for genetics of vascular
disease. This is a research study that
is designed to gather health information
from patients who have been diagnosed
with SCAD or other vascular
abnormalities. The study operates out of
Massachusetts General Hospital and the
Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard.
Participation in the Gvas study includes
completing surveys online about your
health information and providing a
saliva sample which can be mailed to
your home. All information will be kept
confidential and in a secure database
and will never be sold for profit. Gvas
study staff and researchers abide by the
policies and guidelines instilled by the
Mass General Bighgam Institutional
Review Board. Visit gvasstudy.org or to
learn more and enroll into the study.
And visit scatalliance.org to find
resources and support groups for members
of the SCAD community.