Hey, so I had written up a bunch of
closing comments and you'll be happy to
know that I'm not going to subject you
to all of them. I just want to make a
couple of points in uh closing up the
ceremony here. Uh well, the one thing I
do need to do is thank everybody. I I
want to thank uh well, the man behind
the curtain who you don't hear from but
makes everything work. um our wonderful
people from MIT audio video which do
what they do as as good as anyone and
it's testament to everything going
smoothly today. Also all the people uh
that haven't spoken up here today that
actually did all the work to make things
happen to do the registration everything
like that. So there was a lot that that
went into this. back and then especially
I want to thank you the audience. I I
honestly think this is one of the best
audiences I've seen at at an MIT uh
event of this type. The uh engagement
was great. The questions were wonderful
and I think the speakers in some cases
enjoyed you as much as you enjoyed them.
So um I guess I can't ask you to clap
for yourselves but you should. Uh so uh
thanks. And now, um, I want to keep this
quick because if there's one thing I
learned in my years at MIT is you don't
want to get in between a room full of
hungry engineers and their pizza and
beer at the end of a long day. Uh, so
what I want to do is just end with a a
quick story and that's why I'm not going
to go in things I had prepared. But as I
sat through the different uh talks here
today, it reminded me of and this is
something that's happened to me several
times with working with ILP members and
my colleagues can say that it's happened
with them where when somebody comes to
visit MIT
particularly in this group was from
Europe. So when they came to Boston,
they set up a whole bunch of meetings
with a whole different comp bunch of
companies, not only MIT and then they
came on the last day to MIT and we did
rapidfire meetings with MIT faculty and
their comment was that wow this was
refreshing. We spent days with
consultants and and our vendors and
there's nothing wrong with them. I mean
they have a a living to make but we came
to MIT and we got this unfiltered
perspective from some of the people who
are the best at at what they do and it
was just really nice to hear that. So uh
I didn't hear a lot of like strong
pitches from MIT speakers that were here
today. So I'll make a little one for
them. Um they all want to work with our
industry partners and uh as I said this
morning our motto is mens at Manis or
mind in hand. Um, you all are the hand
and MIT wouldn't be MIT without the work
that we do with our entrepreneurs and
with our industry partners. So, if you
saw things that were interesting here
today, um, for all the ILP members,
which is most of you, please contact
your program director and have them make
the connections for you so you can
continue those conversations. And they
could be just talks, they could be
exchange of data, they could be
sponsored research.
the field is wide open for that. But the
all of the MIT speakers that we're
talking to here today, I know that they
would love to hear from you and to
continue that conversation. So, please
do that. Uh so, with that, we'll
conclude MIT Data Center Day. Thank you
all for being here. Thank you all for
the folks online. I'm sorry you won't
join us for the pizza and beer, but
we'll we'll raise a we'll raise a toast
to you on that. Uh thank you. Hope to
see you all again soon. On to the
networking.