hi everybody our first thing that we
really want to think about is how are we
going to
represent
musical objects
music on a computer so let's start with
maybe one of the most fundamental things
and that is pitch so
in a score-based class we might
represent pitch with a score and we
write notes on
it I guess then we assign it to a
variable well that's not going to work
um okay so we we take a a frequency and
we assign that to a variable well I'm
not exactly sure how to do that either
um maybe we just assign a variable to a
particular number representing a
frequency or to a
string representing a
pitch
okay first thing I want you to do is
take five minutes no more than that and
jot down some notes on how you like
represent pitch on a computer very
naively