Okay. So,
right let me just so let me just quickly
review some what we have done so far in
the class. So we talked about first we
talked about R as a ordered set
and field.
Then we have talked about sequences and
limits.
Uh and then we talked about series
and then finally we have talked about
and this is where we will continue
today. we talked about metric spaces
and so the
the idea here is that uh we want to
there's a lot of things that from the
from R that actually generalize
uh and make sense um and some of those
are sequences and limits so they
generalize from R to metric spaces there
other things that don't generalize like
it's not a order a general metric space
is not a it doesn't necessarily come
with a ordering and it's not like a
field uh and uh in particular you can't
typically you can't sum elements so a
series doesn't make sense either right
but but these things here make sense in
a metric space
and so let me just remind you what is a
metric space.
So a metric space
uh is uh a set. So x is a set
and then there is a distance function.
So this is a map from x cross x into r.
And for each two pair of elements
uh uh x and y in x
you have that let me make it a capital
like x like this for every two elements
in in this set the distance between them
should be positive
and it should be non- negative and uh n
equal to
to zero. The distance between two points
should be zero if and only if
this points are the same. Right? And
then it should be symmetric. So two
property two is that it should be
metric. So it doesn't matter whether you
go from x to y or from y to x the
distance is the same.
then and the third which is like the
most non-trivial part is the triangle
inequality. So this here is symmetric.
And the third property is that if you're
looking at X, Y, and C, so you have
three points
and you go from
from X to C,
then it's certainly not further than if
you first go to from X to Y and then go
from Y to C. Right? So this should be
less or equal to the distance from X to
Y plus the distance from Y to C. And so
this third property here is is what's
called the triangle inequality.
[Applause]
So this is the triangle inequality.
Okay.
Now, so that's that's what a metric
space is. And again, the the the sort of
canonical example.
So the canonical example of a metric
space is where you're taking x equal to
the real numbers. And then for two real
numbers, the distance between them is
just where you're looking at the norm of
the difference. Right? So this here is a
nice distance, right? It's clearly non-
negative. It's clearly equal to zero if
and only if x is equal to y. It's
clearly symmetric. And the triangle
inequality is this inequality that we've
used all the time, right?
The same. So this here is um slightly
more fancy version of the same
is where you're looking at uh R2
So the X here is is R2
or it could even be a general Rn.
And then if you think about two elements
in Rn
and you think about say X here as
it's written as X1 comma X2
up to XN where each of these X's are in
R and they are in many of them and
likewise for Y
and then the distance here, the natural
distance
is where you're taking
uh this is what's called the ukidian
distance. It's given by pagras. And so
it's the square root of the sum of the
squares. So x1 - y1^
2 + x2 - y2
plus and then all the way up to
xn
- y
squ
and so you see that if n here is equal
to one well then each element is just a
single element in R and so then this
thing here is really the same as that
right because it's a square of X - Y
it's a square of this distance and then
you take the square root so it's the
norm
okay so this these here are both of
these is called the ukian usually
referred to as a ukian distance
So
we looked at a few other example
and and I won't look at all of them
again but just two more. One is this
with a box distance
and let me state it only in R2 but you
could just like this you state it in any
RN. So the spaces are two and um and the
the distance between two elements. So
again we write it like this and we think
about x as being x1 comma x2 where these
are real numbers y = y1 comma y2
and then this distance here is the sum
of the of the of these distances these.
So this a plus x2 minus y2 like that
right and this is clearly again
symmetric it's clearly non negative it's
clearly equal to zero if and only if x
and y are the same and the triangle
inequality well that just follow quite
easily from the triangle inequality
for this distance okay
then there is one more example I mean
there's There's other you know uh but
there's one or more example that is
often useful to keep in mind and this is
uh the last one I will review
and so this is the uh the continuous
function. So if you take a interval
a and b are real numbers
and you're looking at the interval from
a to b where both end points are
included and then you look at the
continuous function on this interval
and then if you have two elements f and
g
so these are continuous each of them are
continuous functions.
Then the distance between these two
continuous functions is equal to the max
over x and then f ofx minus g of x.
Right? And so x here is in the integral
from a to b.
Right?
And so this thing here so this here was
on the midterm this particular example
and uh this thing here that the max is
achieved is just like if you're looking
at these two functions then this is the
difference between these two functions.
So this is also continuous and this
means that the maximum at the minimum by
the extreme value theorem is achieved on
an interval of this form. Right? So this
thing here is really achieved
and it's clearly non- negative and it's
easy to see that it has the other
property of a metric space. Okay, so
these are just the examples that we
talked about. Uh and I just wanted to
remind you uh
and so then the question is what
generalizes what generalizes from uh R.
So, so right. So, we started with a
class uh talking about R and uh you know
right so it was order field but but a
lot of the things we talked about for R
these subsequent things we talked about
sequences and limits
they as we will see make total sense uh
in in a general metric space and has
important consequences
uh including to solve differential
equation equations and or solving all
kind of equations including differential
equations.
Okay. So now
let me
remind you also. So we talked about that
if we have h if this here is a metric
space
then a sequence in a metric space.
This is just a map is is a map
from the natural numbers into x. So a
sequence is like a map like this.
And so usually the image of the n
element this we will typically denote
again like this xn. So this is what a
sequence is. Uh a subsequence.
This is a this is defined very similar
to what we did on the real line. So a
subsequence is the composition
of f with
an increasing strictly increasing
map.
Uh G from the natural numbers into
in and then the sequence is then
uh where you looking where you apply
first G and then you apply uh F right so
this gives you when you first apply G
then it gives you another natural number
and so this thing here the image of this
is then a element in X right so that's a
subsequence and again this will strictly
increasing guarantee you that the
elements appear in the same order.
You're picking a selection of them, but
they appear in the same order as in the
original sequence. Okay.
So, so sequences and subsequences make
sense.
Um, we can then also talk about and I
know we talked about but I just want to
because of the break I just want to
review quickly
uh a few of the things we talked about
right before the break.
So one is that so
uh a convergent
sequence
in a metric space.
So if you take uh if this here is a
matrix space
and xn is a sequence
in x
xn xd sorry um then um then we say that
we say
that xn converge
2x.
If the following hold
that for all for all
um
for all
uh epsilon greater than zero there exist
capital n such that
if little n is bigger equal to capital n
then uh x n the distance between xn and
this limit
should be less than epsilon right so
that's exact parallel to how we defined
the limit of a sequence or that a
sequence is converging if it was a
sequence in r
and likewise we can define a cruise
sequence in a metric space. So we define
a C sequence
a C
in a matrix space
XD.
So this is a sequence. So that for all
since is a sequence
xn such that
for all
epsilon greater than zero there exist
uh capital n such that
if little n m and little n are bigger
equal to capital n. Right? So remember
that a crique sequence mean that the
tail is bunching together. This means
that if you're sufficiently far out then
these elements xn and xm are epsilon
close together.
So this is what it means for a sequence
to be a cy sequence.
And so now we have this theorem and I
think I mentioned it before the break
but let's just quickly run through it.
It's very short.
So uh if you have um so if this is a
metric space
then the theorem is
that any
any uh convergent
sequence
is also
accuracy sequence
and the proof is like this.
So given given epsilon
uh since
since xn
is a convergence sequence so you assume
that xn is a convergence sequence that's
called the limit x. Since xn converts to
to
x, this means that there exist
there exist
uh capital n such that if little n is
bigger equal to capital n, then the
distance between little x, little n and
uh nx here,
this distance here is less than and then
I use epsilon / two.
And so this means that therefore
if little m and little n are both bigger
than
than capital n then the distance between
the two
distance between this these two elements
here. Well, by the triangle inequality,
we have that this distance is less than
if you go over the point x. So if you go
from xn to x and then from x to xm like
that, right?
But each of these because both of these
uh both little n and little little m and
little n are bigger than capital n then
both of these distances are bounded by
epsilon / two. And so you see that this
thing here is smaller than epsilon.
Right? So this proved that in a metric
space any convergent sequence is also a
cush sequence.
And we we saw that. So we know that if
we if the metric space is R with the
usual ukian distance
then actually
uh you also and that was the cush
convergence. So the cushy
convergence.
So cushive convergence. It said that in
if
x comma d
is r
with the ukian distance. So I denote the
ukian distance like this.
Uh then then we also have then we have
the converse
so i.e uh i.e that any
cushy sequence
this uh is also convergent.
Okay.
Now
we looked at a very simple example and
and if I have time I will talk about a a
little bit more interesting example
uh otherwise I'll talk about that next
time. So if uh so so if the metric space
was was uh was r with a ukian distance
by then we had a converse but if the
metric space was say so we looked at
where the metric space was so where x
here the set was the interval from 0 to
one and the distance here was just the
usual ukian distance right so then if
you Looking at the sequence xn one / n.
This one here.
This is a sequence in this space. It's a
cusy sequence but it doesn't converge in
this space because zero is not part of
the space. Right? So it so so this here
is a cis.
So this you may say this is rather
trivial
uh example. not very interesting.
Um, I'll show you another example a
little bit later or next time uh that is
more interesting but in a in in in some
sense has some of the same feature that
the space is just not quite large
enough. Okay, but it will seem more
interesting. So this here is a CI
sequence that is
not convergent.
Okay.
Right. So, so again you know the cushy
uh bite. Yeah. So this leads to the
following this leads to the following
notion here
that um
that so this is the following
definition.
of being cushy
complete.
So a space a metric space x comma d is
cushy complete.
If uh every
cushy sequence
is uh convergent.
Okay.
Okay. So now uh let me define some uh
some so if let me begin with extending
some notions from uh from R. So the
first one I want to extend is what it
means in a metric space what what is a
ball.
So, so we have here
so a metric or
so we have a metric space
we have a point in the metric space we
have some r which is a real number
positive real number
and then we define uh p r of x Here this
here is the set
uh y
in x so that the distance from x to y is
less than r strictly less than r.
Okay.
Uh and so this here is called this here
is called the metric ball. This set here
it's called a metric ball or just a ball
uh uh with radius
R and center
uh X. Okay.
Now um
let me just sort of illustrate it. So if
you so a lot of the intuitions about
metric spaces but you have to be careful
because sometimes that intuition fools
you just because metric spaces are
allowed to be very general but a lot of
the intuition about metric spaces come
from just thinking about things in ukian
space. So now when I'm talking about
ukarian space I'm thinking about mostly
about it could be on the line. So in the
case where x's are or it could be in a
plane where x's are two or it could be
where x is three. And so in either of
those three cases the distance is the
distance that you're used to which is
the ukidian distance we talked about.
And so you if in that case if you take a
point here so just thinking about
the example where let's think about the
example where x is two
then a ball here well a usual ball is
really just everything that is the
distance r from x right so this is kind
of what I defined over here right
there's another thing you could also
look at some other sets. So imagine that
you take a line
in the plane
and you could look at or maybe this
could even be
it would look more interesting if I'm
thinking about a line in R3.
So imagine that this is now sort of this
is supposed to look like in our tree and
then you could look at a line and you
could look at instead of looking at a
metric ball you could look at a tupler
neighborhood. So suppose you're looking
that that's very similar to a ball.
So tubular neighborhoods
let's say our tubular neighborhoods this
is where you know you have some positive
number R and you're looking at
everything that is
that has distance at most or let's say
strictly less than R from this line. So
if you do that that would look like a
cylinder where the boundary of the
cylinder is not included because I
require things to have distance strictly
less than R. Right? This is like this
here would be a R2 neighborhood of a
line.
So this is just to say that this sort of
notion here of a ball you could even
have something more general and both of
these things right that you know well
from ukian space they make sense in just
a general metric space right you know
line maybe doesn't make sense right
sometime often it does actually but it's
uh but that's something more complicated
but you could just think about it as a
subset and then things that have
distance strictly less than r to that
subset. Okay.
Okay. So,
uh right. So, this is what it means for
a uh this is what a a ball is metric
ball. Then there's a the notion of a
subset of a metric space being bounded.
So, a bounded subset
So this is another definition
bounded
subset
uh of
a metric space.
So we have a matrix space here
and we have a is a subset
and we say that
a is bounded.
Uh if there exist
um if there exist uh x
an element in this metric space and d
is some d is some positive real number
such that
a here is contained
in the all of radius D
center at X
right
now
with this. So there's a few things like
this that we'll see uh you know for for
these things the empty set right the if
you take X and you take the subset that
has no elements that's the empty set
then it's it's you know the empty set is
is contained in everything right so
actually the empty set would be bounded
okay
um but it's not a particular interesting
example of a bounded Right? And it may
be that the whole metric space right
it's possible that the whole metric
space is bounded right if it was like a
interval right if it was just a interval
where both in in so first you have some
interval from a to b
then this thing here is uh if you think
about the usual distance on that
interval then that's a boundary set the
whole the whole set x is bounded so in
particular any subset would also be
bound.
Okay. So now uh let me just prove one
theorem uh one little lema that is
another thing that generalizes
from R and that is that if you take a
cushy sequence so any cushy sequence is
bounded.
So let's throw this
So,
so we have again a metric space.
Uh, XN
is a C sequence
and then we think about the set XN,
right?
So this is this subset of X and I claim
that this subset here
this subset here. So A here
uh is bounded.
Okay.
Now why is that the case?
So since
Xn is a cruisy sequence
if I choose epsilon with so with epsilon
say equal to one you have that there
exist
capital n. So that if little n
and s just then
if little n and little m bigger than
capital n then the distance between the
two
smaller than one right this is just
using that is sequence and just pick
using one particular epsilon namely uh
taking epsilon to be equal one.
So now of course this means and now you
don't need this event for all of these.
You don't need it like this. You just
need so in particular therefore
uh as long as n is bigger than capital
n. Well you can use one of you can use m
here. You can use capital n for m. So
then this here say therefore for little
end bigger than this we have that this
in here
the distance to this is smaller than one
right
and so now
so now you have that if you if you now
set
r equal to uh 1 plus the maximum
of the distance from
uh uh x n x capital n to x i
where i here
is runs from one up to capital n minus
one. So there are n minus one of these
right that you take the maximum over
right. So if you define little r to be
like this then obviously little r is
some positive number it's finite right
uh and and you have that and and now I
claim that our set a here is contained
in this ball here around xn. So I claim
I claim this thing here.
Okay.
Now let's see. So why is this the case?
So if we have if x here if capital so we
need to prove that we need to show
that for all
and you have that the distance here
is less and not right if that's the case
then the whole set here would lie in in
in in this board right but you see that
if n here
well if n is bigger equal to capital n
but this remember that then we have then
we have
So this is uh right. So we need to show
this in here. If little n is bigger than
capital n then we have that the distance
from this little end to this one here.
Right? The tail tail was less than one.
Right? But this thing here is actually
right by this is actually less or equal
to r because it was one plus this
maximum and then this is maximum over
non- negative numbers. Right? So you see
that for the whole tail we have this
property
but for all the other ones right for
n less or equal less than n minus one
right these are the the remaining ones
well there the distance
from
x n to x capital n
Uh it's this is one of these guys,
right? So it's clearly this one here is
clearly less than
capital, right? And it's really strictly
less than because that's this one also,
right? Yeah.
>> Does it have to be one plus the max or
could it be the max of one for all those
elements in the sequence?
>> Uh I wanted it's this one here to be
strict.
It's just a silly thing, but that's why
I took it like that. Yeah, because
otherwise this would be sweet. But it's
just a a trivial thing. Uh, and it
doesn't matter very much. If at this
stage it makes no difference actually,
but it was just to use this. We'll talk
a little bit more about the balls
because there is another way, you know,
you could define the ball. Maybe I'll
say a few words about that now.
Okay. So, this here. So, so what this
prove again is that in any metric space
a a cruise sequence is automatically
bounded right and so remember in any
metric space a convergence sequence is a
cushy sequence so a convergence sequence
is also bounded right
and now you now there's this question
which is a natural question and this is
connected to the definition of ball
so the way we define and it's actually
worthwhile emphasizing because it's
useful in the next uh thing that we want
to get to.
And so when I define a ball, I assumed
so the definition of the ball, let me
just write it up again here.
Uh so the definition of a ball in a
metric space, these are the y in this
set. So that the distance
to the center is strictly less than
right. You could of course have defined
it differently.
You could define it that this is
strictly le or instead of strictly less
less or equal to. Right? I I want to use
strictly less here. Yeah. But sometimes
if I want to be very clear I will talk
about open and closed ball. And this is
what we're getting to next, right? And
so when I talking about open ball, but I
I'll try not to use that term here. Uh
but but open would always mean this.
Closed ball will mean that it's less or
equal to. Sorry.
>> You were talking about like example.
>> Yeah.
>> Like is that referred to like is X in
that case like a subset of
>> Yeah. Yeah. That's right. Exactly.
That's right. And so so now uh and and I
didn't you know this I I didn't actually
in the I already posted the lecture
notes and so in the lecture notes I
didn't actually talk about tupa
neighborhood but it's it is it it maybe
is worth thinking about. So you could
you could look at as so you again you
have a metric space here
and you could have a subset
A here is a subset any subset of the
metric space
and you could define the tupler
neighborhood of a subset and so you
could do this similarly. So this would
be the y in x. So that the distance from
y to
um to
uh x x here is strictly less than r
for some
x
in it. You see what I mean? So this here
is like this is how so again if you take
if you think about our tree you take
some I mean maybe we shouldn't talk
about maybe we should draw it more crazy
like some curve maybe
and if you're looking at the set that
are have distance and most this is like
some sort of tube like this
right this is like uh this here would be
the sinks and then here at the end you
know it look like a cap like this,
right? This here would be like a tubular
neighborhood of this curve. Yeah.
Okay.
And and so as you saying that in the
case where a here is just a point then
those two coincides.
Okay. So now like one of the key things
uh one of the key things when you're
thinking about convergence in in R
remember that this stuff and we use this
time and time again that it was often
you know we saw this for series that it
was often difficult to determine the
exact limit of a series right but the
question was always does it converge
right and so if it converge
If it converts then often often you know
you I mean also if you were have using
this in some sort of application it's
it's often in all kind of fields that it
comes up that things are written in
terms of a series and it's it's not
clear what is converting to but you want
to know whether it's converting and then
you also want to so you want to estimate
what is the limit within a certain error
term. Right? And you can use some of
these comparison tests to to to
determine to to to estimate how close
you are to the actual limit. Okay.
But in any case, right, the thing is
it's very useful to have a criteria that
say that is easy to work with and that
uh say that it's converging without
having to be able to find the limits,
right? And like the cus sequence, this
was like a notion of that, right? And so
so the again the and the key on on R the
key for using that was the Banano bio
theorem.
So this was the one that was the key for
using to to get the cush convergence
theorem. So the pulsano vas are simil.
So remember that this was this is four R
and it say that any any any
bounded sequence
has a convergent subsequence Right.
That was what I assume in a general
metric space. This, you know, it it
makes sense to talk about a bounded
uh sequence, right?
uh but it's not it's not always the case
that a bounded sequence has a convergent
subsequence. So it does not hold the
bolano does not hold. So, so, so warning
um
uh balsana vas
does not hold
in a general metric space.
And in fact, of course, you know, the
example that we looked at with um with
where the example was x here like this
and where we're looking at that
sequence, this is a bounded sequence,
but it's uh it's bounded, but it doesn't
have a convergent subsequence, right?
It's a actually sequence, but it doesn't
have, right? So, it doesn't hold in a
general metric space,
but it does hold
It does hold
if the metric space
is compact.
And so that's what I want to talk about
next. But in order to talk about uh what
it means for metric space to be compact
then I need to
to talk about
uh I need to define what it means for a
set to be open.
Okay. So
so so we need the notion
We need the notion
of an open set, an open
subset
of a metric space.
Okay, so we have a metric space again.
And so A here
is set to be let's call it O for open. O
is set to be
an open subset
if for all
uh X in O.
So the idea is that you have here this
here is this here is O. So O is
this is maybe O.
And so the idea is that for each element
there exists some ball centered at that
point. So for each x for all x in O
there they exist
r greater than zero. It may be
incredible small so that not just x but
the whole board around x is contained in
the open set. So you see that not just
this point here but the whole ball here
would have to be contained in O right.
So in this picture here my when I'm
illustrating this I'm thinking about
excis being R2 and I'm thinking about
the distance being the usual ukian
distance right and then but then
actually if this is open it means that
you cannot include these points here on
this curve right they would not be
included in the set because if you take
any point on this boundary here so to
then a ball part of it would be outside
the set. Right? So, so if this hair
really was open, then this curve here
was not included. And you see that as
you're getting closer and closer to that
curve,
you know, you can still have a little
ball that is inside the set, but as
you're getting closer, the radius of
this little ball have to be smaller.
But that's fine.
Okay. So this is what it means for a
subsets to be open.
And the first the first thing uh that
you observe that with this definition
there are always two open subsets. So so
again this thing here. So note
that the empty set but there's no
condition if there was a empty set it
say for all element in the set but there
is no element so there's nothing to to
to be satisfied so the empty set and all
of x are open subset
okay so So, so do note that, right? So,
in particular, if if like so, so if you
take if X here was not the whole real
line, but it was just an interval from 0
to one and then the distance between
elements was the usual distance. Then
actually even the closed interval which
is the whole set would be open right. So
so you just should be careful with you
know what the set is right
with what the set is.
Uh okay. Um
so so now
right so now the key here is that that
so if you have an open set you know how
do you kind of construct
um well maybe the first thing I should
do is I should prove a lema
that is the following
and then then after that we will talk
about how to
get lots of uh open sets.
So let me so we have two example at the
moment we have two examples of so so
right by so if you take a metric space
at the moment we know that there's
always two subsets that are open the
empty set and and and x but they're not
very interesting so a more interesting
example is that if you take a metric
space
and you take a ball and now it's crucial
how we define the ball and so it's
crucial that that it this inequality is
strict. Okay. So for a metric space X
here is in X it could be it's it could
be any element in in in X this thing
here R here is positive strictly
positive it it's also has to be strictly
positive then this thing here is open
any metric ball like this is is is an
open subset
okay let's try to prove that And again
when you're proving things like this for
a metric space
the only non-trivial thing is a triangle
inequality. So this is relying on the
triangle inequality.
And so
for a lot of things when you're proving
things about a metric space it's often
quite helpful to draw a little picture.
So, but of course you had to be careful
with again that then the intuition comes
from you know RN or and uh and sometimes
the metric is a little bit more
complicated than that. So this here
imagine that this is the ball of radius
R. Here you have some X.
Now take a element Y. So suppose that y
here is now in this ball here.
Then we want to show want to show
that there exist
that for some
s bigger than zero the ball here of
radius s around y is now contained in
this ball here.
So here you have y and we want to prove
that there's some little ball around y
that is contained in the original ball.
Right?
And so again this is going to rely on
the triangle inequality.
So you take you have y here. y was
supposed to be in this ball here. This
means that the distance from X to Y is
strictly less than R. Right?
You take now S here to be R minus this
distance here.
Okay. Why do I do this again in my
picture here? I have here X. I have here
Y.
And our intuition is that if we kind of
go from X and we go through Y and then
we go straight to the boundary then this
thing here is D X comma Y and this one
here is R minus D X right this is the
remaining this whole here is R. This
here is DX Y. So this here must be be
this here, right? And so if you're
setting this equal to S and now you
imagine taking a ball here, well then at
least on the picture this whole ball is
contained in the original ball, right?
So so let's try to see if that works,
right? If that works, then it really
only used the triangle.
So we're setting S equal to this and
then we're looking at this ball here
around S and we take an element here
in this ball and we now need to prove so
we need to show
we want to prove that this whole ball is
contained in the original B. So this
means that we need to prove that for any
such element
set here is in this thing here
right that's what we need to prove
and so now you see
uh
so we take um right so we take C so
we're now looking at So we're going to
look at this distance, right? In order
to prove this, we need to prove that the
distance from C to X is strictly less
than R. So let's examine that distance.
Triangle inequalities say that this is
is bounded by the distance from X to Y
plus the distance from Y to C.
This one here from Y to C.
C lie in the ball of radius S around Y.
So this means that this this thing here
this thing here is lesser is strictly
less than S. Right? And so you see that
this thing here is now uh less than
uh d x y
uh + s. Now you fill in what S is. This
here
S was equal to R minus DX Y. That was
the definition of S. And so now you see
that this thing here is R, right?
Because those two cancel out. And you
see that this here I guarantee you that
the inequality was strict, right? And so
right so it really is that that whole
ball was. So we conclude that this whole
ball here
uh was contained in in the original ball
right and and again
again the proof of it was just from this
picture right that you make kind of
rigorous and the only non-trivial things
at the moment we really have in a metric
space is a triangle in quantum right
because we haven't built up a lot of
stuff
okay so so So, so actually so this as
you see this immediately gave you a lot
of example of um of open subsets of a
general metric space and if we had
looked at exactly the same stuff this
with tupal neighborhood we we would find
that those are also open subsets. Are we
also going to look at subsets or are
those like common value
>> close? Yeah, very much so. Uh but we
haven't defined what it means to be
close. Uh but you you're right that and
we'll do this uh you're right that uh
but we so at the moment we don't know
what a closed thing is you know uh and
maybe I will just define it and then
then then
we can so
okay
so let's define
so I but I'll talk more about this next
time but now when you're asking
So again, so we have X here
is is a metric space again and then C
here
it's a subset of X is set to be closed
and then now it's may may seems almost
cheating. said to be closed if the
complement.
So this means that the complement of of
C. So the complement of C. So the
complement of C the complement
of C. Right? This is these are all the
these are the x all the x in x so that x
is not in c.
Okay.
So the complement of a set is everything
in x that is not in that set. Okay. And
a set is set to be closed if the
complement is open. Okay.
And so now once you have this definition
and I'll prove this next time that uh
that if you're looking at
what I denote like this so this is the
elements
where the distance to uh x is less or
equal to. So this here is not any more
strict right this thing here is then a
closed set. Okay.
>> Could you also define it by like the way
we define an open subset but saying that
arc instead of being strictly
>> No. No. I couldn't define it like that.
Yeah. Right. But so I mean you could
define it other ways. There's another
standard where we talk about there's
another equivalent to say that if you
take but I don't want to get into that
because you know but but there's another
way. We'll get to this in in in just but
but uh and and close sets we really
mostly talk about next time. It was just
because you're asking
um but let me just talk about so this
here's one but I'll just repeat this in
just a second.
So in order to produce more sets. So so
we start with um so by so now so by
actually I should just note although you
know just now when I talk about clo you
know just the definition I should just
immediately note that there are always
two closed sets
because you see the empty set was always
open and the full set was always open.
Right? And so the complement of the
empty set that's everything. So that's
closed. And the complement of everything
is nothing. It's empty sets. Right? So
that's also closed. So those two sets
are always closed. But let me just talk
about so I want to think about you know
how do you produce
uh open sets?
So how do you know that that there are a
lot of open sets?
And so if you take sets, if you take so
this is like operations
on sets on on on subsets
of a given set.
So here I'm thinking about just X as
being a set. It's it does not need to be
a metric space. So if I take a set then
and I take two elements two subsets.
So these are two subsets. Then I can
form the union of these two.
This here is the union
and the union here of two sets. So the
union and again I denote it like this
cup
like this. These are the elements in X
such that X
is in U1
or X is in U2
or both. What's
right? And so you often illustrate this
with like if you have this here is X,
this here is U1,
this here is U2, U1 and U2.
Then this thing here
is the union
and likewise the intersection the
intersections that is lying in both
sets.
Right?
So the intersection
the intersection. So this is again you
have these two sets and this is the
intersection.
So and you denote it like this
and this is the x
so that x is in u1 and
uh x's in the two that's intersection of
these two set
okay and then um then there is a
third and then let me talk immediately
about generalization of this so there's
a a third and this is this with a
complement but let me also introduce the
notation
so if you take this subset of X than the
complement and and people
there are sort of slightly different
ways of doing it of defining it uh or
not defining it but of notation for it
and I always use this one because I
think that's the clearest one. So this
is like x take away u and this is
totally standard. There's another one
that's often used where you have C
that's slightly less standard than this
one and sometimes it can be confusing.
This one can never be confusing.
And so this thing here is a complement
and so this means that it's the X
such that X does not belong to you.
Okay.
And so now uh okay so that's like
standard operation of sets but there is
a generalization of this of this union
here where instead of just two sets you
could take potentially infinitely many
sets. So if you take a family of
subsets. So if you alpha here is a
family
of subsets
then you could look at the union of the
u alpha. This is like denoted like this.
And this is the x
in in x
such that x is in u alpha
for some
uh alpha. I mean it could be in many of
the u alphas but it has to be at least
one. Right? So this is the union of a
family and likewise the intersection of
a family is the x and then it has to now
lie in all of them right it's x in x
where x is in u alpha for all alpha
okay that's a union and the
intersections family
Okay. Uh and so now
um
let me look at some example.
uh in particular
uh let me look at
the
uh an example of this
uh
and then let me prove something about uh
open sets. So let me look at an example
here.
Suppose that u alpha or u n I'm just
going to look at is going to be now a
family of subsets of the real line and
they're going to be indexed by the
natural number. So this thing here is
going to be minus one / n to 1 / n.
And if I'm looking at the union of these
guys,
but you see this is this is a a this is
a sequence of of um of uh of open sets,
right? I mean it's like for each n you
have a open set, but they are as n get
larger they're smaller. The first one is
the biggest one. So if you take the
union of these guys
that just gives you the the first one
you started with. So this is the union
of these right?
If you take the intersection of them
well the only thing that is in all of
these sets that's actually this zero
right. Okay.
Now um
now we need some we need some stuff
about
uh operations of sets and so how does uh
things and so there's some standard
operations
uh and
my recommendation is that
not try to remember this
uh I don't remember it myself so I
always have to kind of run through but
the once you have done it once or twice
the proof is so trivial that it's not
worth remembering and and I think if the
danger if you try to remember these
things you may remember it wrong and
that's much worse than just running
through the proof so so you have so you
have the following lema here
so you have a set and then you have
subsets
uh um uh let's call it a b and then and
then a family uh of subsets
and the thing is the first one is that
if you take the complement of the
complement
so if you take a and you take everything
that is not in a right
so just think about it that if you take
so here you have x here you have A, this
is A. If everything that is not in A,
that's over here, right? But then if
it's not over here, then it's A. So the
first one,
it's just that, right? And actually, we
sort of just because we're also running
out of time, right? We really prove
this, right? I mean, so if you have
something that is not in A, then it's
lie here. But if it's not lie here, then
it lie there. That's that statement.
Okay.
[Music]
The second one is that if you take the
complement
of that it's in the union
of these guys.
So if it's not
this just means that it's not in any of
these guys. Right? This here is the set.
Imagine that you have something that
looks like you have a bunch of sets like
this. These are the the this is supposed
to illustrate the a alphas and if it's
not this say that if it's not in any of
these
well then the claim is that then it's
it's it's
in the intersection
of that it's not in this one. It's not
in this one and it's not in this one and
it's not in that one. Right? So that's
also clear enough. Right?
So this is the second one. Again I I
actually wrote out the proof uh in the
notes um
um so you you can check that out.
And the third operation,
the third operation is that if you take
uh if you take uh x and you are removing
the intersection of this family.
So this means that it is not so this
means that the intersection of the
family this in this picture here would
be this thing here and so it's not right
there everything else is allowed right
but that's the same you see that's the
same as the union of x take away
right this here is this here is the
element
that is in not in one of that that
there's at least one of the u alpha a
alpha where it's not in right and so
that's the same so this is this is uh
the same as this okay again um I wrote
it out in in the notes the proof
actually right of these things right
okay
and let me just say Maybe we can't quite
uh I mean we'll pick up in the notes
where uh the other stuff but let me just
say that uh when you prove this sort of
thing and and we even did this here when
in in this when I'm just illustrating it
with a picture.
So um so we prove it using the following
sort of trivial lema and I wrote that
out as a lema in the notes that if you
are trying to prove that two sets are
equal right so suppose you're trying to
prove that two sets are equal then in a
way it's natural to divide this into two
parts. So this is the same
as proving
that A is contained in B and
B is contained in A. Right? So if you're
trying to prove that two sets are equal,
then you would prove that for any
elements in A, it's also at B. This is
this thing. And you prove that for any
element B, it's also an A, right? And so
that's that's you know when I wrote out
the proof of this these three things,
then I wrote it out like each of them
has two parts, right? That you prove
that this set is contained in that and
you prove that this is contained in
that. Okay?
Now,
uh right, we're almost actually there.
Um so so now
let me um let me just
say that so that's actually in in one of
the
one of the pets problem but that's no
pet it's uh you have a little break now
for pet sets uh because I want to make
sure that that there is no pet in
material we haven't yet covered in class
so that's why there's a
and and and anyway the all of the pieet
at this point I actually posted. So the
the last one I think is due I forget
whether it's the 8th of May or something
like that and there's again there's five
left you've already done fine. Okay. So
now uh if you take uh if you take if X
here B is a metric space then you have
the following lema
that if O alpha are open subsets
then the union of the O alpha is also
open
right And this is actually but this is
quite trivial as you see I'll just
indicate why but it's actually left on a
pie set. So the proof here
but I will just illustrate it anyway
that if you take a element here in the
union.
Well, this means that this means that
there exist
you
this means that that x is in
alpha for some alpha, right? For some
alpha
but this means that there is a ball
around it because this here is open. It
means that there's a little ball around
it that is contained in in this, right?
But therefore, it's also contained in
the union
of these guys,
right? And so this this is really just a
proof that the union of open sets are
open.
And next time, so we're out of time now,
but next time we'll talk about why if
you take finally many sets, why the
intersection of finitely many sets
of finite many open sets, why that is
also open. But for intersection of open
set, you have to be careful because for
union, you can take the union of any
number of open sets. It's always open.
But for for if you take intersection you
it's in general it's only true that
finite intersections are open and the
example is one of the examples we looked
at before where you take these sets here
they are these sets are open subsets
but if you take the intersection of all
of them then you just get zero and
that's not a open subset. Okay. So,
okay. So, we're we're done.