Yeah, it's coming up. Um,
so energy systems optimization is is a
hard problem. Uh, we are talking about
heterogeneous physics. Uh, we are
talking about different uh spatial
temporal scales and how do we approach
this typically in practice is through
physics based modeling. And the good
news is that we know the fundamental
physics of most of these engineering
systems and we can build high fidelity
digital twins. But on on uh the downside
is that they are typically
confidentially very expensive uh in a
forward simulation and even more so for
closed loop optimization and control.
And then this creates uh lot of
scalability issues and a lot of uh
software integration issues from
practical engineering perspectives when
it comes to real-time decision makings
for uh sustainable energy systems. So um
one of the specific examples I want to
walk you through is a practical
deployment of high fidelity model pretty
control in real world uh office building
in Belgium. that was done during my time
at Cow Lumen as a postoc with Lea Helen
at the mechanical engine department
where we spent two years in developing
high fidelity uh building models and
model control to uh optimize operations
of heating ventilation air conditioning
systems in buildings. And you may ask
why we would like to do that why it is
relevant. Well, the buildings uh
globally uh use over 40% of the energy
and in the US alone 70% of the
electricity goes to residential and
commercial buildings and with the raise
of like the growth of the data center
this this percentage will grow even
further
and the problem is that the current
controls in buildings are very simple
rules and proportional integral
derivative controllers that are very
inefficient.
um
that creates a lot of u energy waste, a
lot of overheating, over cooling in in
times that it shouldn't be really
happening. So on the upside of these
advanced control technologies in in
academia in in um practical tools, we
have the capability to op highly
optimize these systems. And in this
specific case study that was running
several months in the field, we have
been able to save over 50% uh on the
energy bill and at the same time improve
thermal comfort in the building uh
occupants. But on the downside, this
project took over a year and army of
PhDs to deliver. And the reason was um
in the modeling and simulation layer
where we spent half a year just building
the high fidelity digital twin using
modelica language and then we have this
high fidelity model but is not really
tailored for control. So we had to
develop second model that is control
oriented with linearizing and and
decomposing the system uh into different
pieces uh then design uh optimal control
strategy using Gurobi and and MATLAB uh
optimization libraries. Then use the
machine learning models for forecasting
our disturbances and then stitch it all
together with functional macab unit in
this uh horrendous uh software project
that took one year to build in order to
actually deploy this in real time
decision making uh on the cloud by
hacking the building management system
with the help of uh the control system
vendors. So obvious that was obvious
that we cannot really commercialize this
technology. Even when we talk with
several building automation companies uh
they are saying to us that okay we don't
have the manpower we don't have the
necessary expertise to deploy this u in
the field. So what are the actual
bottlenecks when it comes to uh
deploying these advanced control
technologies that have been developed
and are in practice in aerospace
automotive and process control
industries in the energy systems. Now
the first one is that uh the building
toolkits um are heterogeneous and uh
high fidelity digital twins are not
control oriented while the blackbox
machine learning models they typically
don't have guarantees. So we're
typically restricted to relatively
simple reduce order uh gray box models.
The second challenge is that we are
solving heterogeneous problems. We are
solving real-time optimization for
constraint decision making. We are
solving forward simulation models for
the complicated heat transfer including
all the nonlinearities and we are
typically solving some supervised
machine learning for forecasting and we
need to stitch them these together but
these methods and uh to theories have
been developed in different communities
and all the software toolkit is very
heterogeneous. So we have different
tools for constraint optimization
control, different tools for solving our
differential equations and different
tools for machine learning. And this was
historically like separated silos that
have been quite uh complicated and
laborous uh to integrate in uh end to
end software stack. But what is exciting
opportunity I see in academia is the
confluence of these two domains. machine
learning community, computer science
community bringing wonderful tools that
enable automatic differentiation um at
scale and democratize u these toolkits
through user-friendly APIs and more and
more ideas from constraint optimization
dynamic systems being embedded in these
uh machine learning toolkits and we call
this scientific machine learning or
physics inform machine learning that uh
enables us to do so and brings us two
major benefit benefits. One, we can
learn with way fewer data because we are
having fewer degrees of freedom in the
model and we can enforce certain
properties like safety or physical
quantities like dissipativity or energy
conservation in applications when we
know that we have these. So we don't
need to discover them from data.
And there are a lot of different domains
that are already working in in this
broader field of scientific mer machine
learning that is emergent and growing
very fast. Here are a few papers uh that
I want to highlight that influence my
thinking in this area is it incomplete
and biased literature review. But this
kind of sample uh a few things in
physics informed neural network for PDS
learning to optimize learning models
which is typically nonlinear system
identification area and learning to
control and what I want to argue today
that even though that these different
methods have been developed by operation
research community machine learning
community controls community or applied
map community they are really the
instance of one higher abstraction of
problem. So we can call scientific or
physics informed machine learning. And
when you look at each of these papers uh
they can be abstracted in the four major
components. Then the first one obviously
is is data. We need some form of active
sampling or data acquisition to sample
our u parametric uncertainty scenarios
or or gather uh the time series data for
system identification. We have some
machine learning function approximator,
some surrogate model that approximates
our unknown relationships in the model.
And then the critical component is a
domain prior. That can be either your
known differential equations or it can
be the structure of your state space
model or it could be constraints in your
optimization problem. Then you embed in
this computational graph.
And the last component is physics or
domain informed loss function where
those quantities that you cannot enforce
as a hard structural constraints or
treat as a implicit layers you enforce
as form of soft constraint penalties
through residual learning and there is a
again whole field of collocation based
um methods um in in dynamical systems um
that can cover these type of approaches
and I would also argue it's nicely
linked with stoastic optimization in O.
Okay. So to give you a quick uh walk
through of the major approaches uh in
scientific machine learning, everyone
knows physics inform neural networks or
pins in short. They have been used for
both forward and inverse modeling mostly
for uh scaling uh inference for PDS. Uh
so they come with several advantages.
They are mesh free. So you don't need to
uh construct your finite discretization
beforehand. You can sample with finer uh
samples for offline training and then
query your solutions only at the spatial
temporal points when you need um and at
the inference time you're typically
getting orders of magnitude acceleration
because you are uh approximating the
solution in the learned function
approximator typically neural network.
So how do these components look
specifically? Well, the data set are
collocation points in spatial temporal
coordinates. So here simple example you
have temporal domain spatial domain and
you sample these points uh that you
query your neural network model to
generate candidate solution that aims to
satisfy your partial differential
equation. There's a neck layer. So you
embed this PD as a layer uh in your
computation graph. For that uh to
represent the PD that is dependent now
on the neural network solution, you need
to compute these partial derivatives.
But thanks to uh wonderful and scalable
automatic differentiation tool kits, we
can compute them rather efficiently. And
now you construct your pin loss function
which is nothing else as empirical risk
minimization on this PTE equality
constraint. and potentially some
supervisory loss function that you
typically impose on your initial and
boundary conditions. So this is a
vanilla pin and there is a lot of
research in advanced architectures. Uh
how do we sample these collocation
points? How do we quantify errors? how
do we uh weight the relative um terms in
this multi-term loss function? But here
I just want to like show you this
vanilla approach and show you that
conceptually it's very similar or
basically the same as learning to
optimize in self-supervised setting that
is really
emerging AI and operation research power
systems optimization that um has a huge
potential in u um improving our
real-time decision- making. Of course
when we are talking about power systems
these are safety critical systems. So if
you are having some residual errors in
pins in for PD solutions they don't they
they don't cause like in catastrophic
failures but any errors or potential
constraints violations in power systems
can cause catastrophic failures. So a
lot of research in this domain is in
so-called physibility restoration
layers. So how do we correct uh the
solutions generated by this neural
network to satisfy hard constraints?
And conceptually the method is again
very similar than pins. But here instead
of spatial temporal coordinates we
sample some parametric space that can
represent initial conditions or um some
stoastic uncertainties in your problem.
And your neural network now tries to
replace your numerical solver by mapping
these parametric uh scenarios into the
primal solutions of the optimization
problem that in general form um is
described by some cost function over
your primal decisions parameterized by
the the uncertainties and some general
inequality constraints.
Um so how do we embed uh the domain
awareness in this self-supervised
learning to optimize? Well, if your
objective functions and constraints are
differentiable, ideally smooth, so you
can embed them as a layer and evaluate
their violations in the loss functions
through the same empirical risk
minimization that we use in pins. But if
you want to have further hard constraint
guarantees again a lot of research is in
these feasibility restoration layers
that can be done either through
differentiating through optimization
solvers through implicit function
theorem or differentiating to unrolled
fixed point operators um projections or
Newton type solvers. So a lot of
exciting uh new research done even in
this community here uh in this uh
learning to optimize method.
The next category of uh models that I
would argue is again related and could
be formalized on the high level as the
same class of problems is nonlinear
system identification with constraints.
And here instead of sampling
uh some parametric scenarios or
uncertainties or special temporal
coordinates, we assume some time series
data which we from which we want to
learn. And
uh one methodology that is really
standing out is neural differential
equation that have been being used
extensively in generative AI. But here I
want to uh think about neural
differential equations from the
perspective of engineering applications.
Can we utilize these methodologies in
modeling engineering systems subject to
constraints and again apply them in
safety critical systems like power
systems or or heat transfer energy
systems modeling. Um
so how do we think about constructing
those data sets? Uh there are typically
batches of trajectories which we assume
over finite horizon typically on
discretized u time samples. And now the
uh combination of your function
approximator with the domain prior comes
in different shapes and forms. There's
there is a lot of uh nonlinear system
identification methodologies in the
literature that utilize either neural
networks or polomial basis functions in
differential programming setting in
different shapes and forms. So in the
neur blackbox neural OD setting you
right hand side is represented by neural
network and you differentiate through
the OD solver either by unrolling the
operations of the numerical integrators
are like RK4 or using a joint
sensitivity method. On the other hand,
operator based approaches like deep
coupman operator, they uh embed the
observables into the latent space
through neural network encoding and in
the higher dimensional latent space they
evolve the linear operator and then
project it back uh to the observable
space with this type of approximate
inverse encoder decoder architectures. A
lot of interesting theory and
interesting properties for for control
in this space. um other approaches like
sparse identification of nonlinear
dynamics or CID for short um are also
used for model discovery. So what I'm
arguing here we can train all of these
uh with stoastic gradient descent based
on this empirical corros minimization of
the trajectory matching uh for dynamical
systems as as well. And now when you
have capability for modeling dynamical
system when you have ability to handle
constraints either structurally or
through these implicit layers you put
them together and you can train closed
loop dynamical systems to solve certain
control task and this is the methodology
that we have been developing my
colleagues at the Pacific Northwest
National Lab that we call differential
priority control that uh combines this
idea together and again we are based on
sampling based collocation approaches of
the parametric scenarios in optimal
control problem and we represent a
closed loop system with some function
approximator for the control policy most
commonly deep neural net and system
dynamics representation either with
family or state space models or known
differential equations or learned neural
differential representations.
Of course there needs to be some
assumptions on on the the well
conditioning of the system because now
we are unrolling this system which can
create rather deep computial graphs. So
uh conditioning of this dynamic system
is very very crucial. But from the
higher level methodological perspective
you're solving again empirical
minimization by sampling the scenarios
in your parametric space that can be
initial conditions of this problem or
there can be uh conditioning of your
constraints or objective functions like
different desired reference trajectories
to solve this parametric optimal control
problem approximately
uh by training this deep neural network.
So for those of you who are familiar
with control theoretic approaches like
model property control um it's uh
approximate approach to solve explicit
model pretty control that traditionally
is being solved with multiparametric
programming but unfortunately the
multiparametric programming approaches
don't scale very well because they blow
up in complexity of all possible
combination of active constraints. So um
how you can think uh structurally
between this differential operating
control and traditional implicit MPC. So
it is simple example on uh linear model
printing control when we have linear
state space model and quadratic cost
where we want to match our desired uh
reference trajectories with our state
trajectories and we can conveniently
represent the state system state
evolution over finite horizon uh with
this type of like lower triangle matrix
where a matrix is our my state
transition matrix b is the my input
dynamics matrix
So when you think about it structurally
is nothing else as a recurren neural
network. Yeah. When you unroll it as a
computation graph and if you replace the
decision variable uh to be your control
sequence like it is done in online model
property control with explicit control
policy. Now we have this closed loop
neural dynamical system where the
policies represented by the the neural
part and encodes the explicit control
policy approximately and it can be
trained in a batch over distribution of
desired reference trajectories and
initial conditions.
Okay. So that's a high level overview of
different methodologies in scientific
machine learning that uh my I'm arguing
that are family of this high level of
abstraction that we can call scientific
or physics for machine learning. they
come with these four major uh building
blocks and because of this abstraction
it allows us to build uh user friendly
software tools and that's what I have
been doing for last uh already 5 years
together with my colleagues at Pacific
Northwest National Lab by developing the
library that is called Neurommancer
which is built on top of PyTorch and
really the vision is to enable a
software toolkit that is integrating all
of these advancements and the focuses on
modularity
um simplicity and user experience rather
than on performance.
uh we chose PyTorch as our back end
consciously because of the large
community and uh robust support uh from
the hardware accelerators and from the
front end the API is modeled based on
algebraic modeling languages that we
commonly use in controls and
optimization like jump or cvxpy or yip
that allow you to formulate the highle
constraint optimization problems or
optimal control problems in uh
convenient symbolic abstractions by
defining the variables and on these
variables you symbolically define your
objective expressions or constraints and
then you plug them in together in a
problem and in traditional algebraic
model languages this problem is parsed
into solver specific form and then you
solve it with interior point or or or um
Gurobi or other solver skip baron but
here what we are doing is that we
combine this with these machine learning
components that are being trained
through stoastic gradient descent uh in
PyTorch and through our problem
constructor we generate this custom
computial graph of scientific machine
learning components whether it is for
pins or learning to optimize for
learning to control you have the same
standardized API and really the vision
is to be interoperable so once you train
a pin and you have approximation of the
PD and you want to do PD the constraint
optimization you can embed it in in in
the learning to optimize.
Um okay so that's the software
capability that has been developed by my
wonder with my wonderful colleagues at
PNL uh funded with US department of
energy. So want to acknowledge all of
their hard work and uh commitment to
making this tool open source and
maintainable.
Um next I want to highlight two
applications that we have been working
on and buildings has been something I
was been working for 10 years which has
been already a long time and we are
still not really like solving these
problems in in real life but I hope that
these type of new tools and capabilities
could um mitigate some of those
engineering problems uh in in the
practice because we don't really have
problems with theory uh we have problem
in making uh the theory and wonderful
numerical tools to be easily usable and
scalable in in practice. And that's what
we are trying to demonstrate in our more
applied research where we want to show
that we can now train these uh control
policies through scientific machine
learning with surrogate models um at the
fraction of the time investment and also
expertise investment because if you have
engineer that now is capable in the
scientific machine learning uh
functionality
you don't need to have one expert in
modeling you don't need to have one
expert in optimization control and then
expert in ML and stitch all of their uh
software solutions together in
functional mockup units and or in other
ways. So that's that's the argument here
and in uh the building space
specifically we know a lot of physics
and we can exploit this in these uh
datadriven machine learning uh
surrogates these physics informed ML
models. We know the buildings are
thermodynamically stable systems. They
are dissipative. they want to get to the
equilibria with the the environment. So
we can encode those properties in um our
neural ods or neural taste models. We
also know um that their partial
derivatives need to satisfy certain
properties uh um with with the
environment. So if I'm increasing the
temperature in in this room uh the heat
transfer to through the walls we also
increase temperature in the in the other
room or not other way around. So there
are a lot of uh physics constraints that
we can embed in these models to uh
reduce the degrees of freedom and allow
us to learn from uh smaller and less
excited data because that's also one of
the big problems in industry when a lot
of your data is coming with missing data
points uh low fidelity data and
operating really close to steady states.
So how do we how do we solve this
problem without physics? Well, we need
we need to really utilize a lot of
physics in order to have any like
datadriven modeling here. So, it's more
like data tuning of the physics models
rather than uh large data set machine
learning. And uh one of like very early
prototype uh type of applications which
we are exploring is uh learning to
control learning to optimize for power
systems where we want to reuse all of
the software infrastructure that we
built for the buildings application and
uh applying in a different context. So
here is again small scale example on
night bus system where we know some
physics we know uh the the stability
conditions that we can embed in our
model. In this case, we have chosen this
deep coupman operator that was uh
physics inspired and uh constrained to
to be stable operator um to allow us to
train this uh explicit control policies
offline with this empirical ro
minimization. Um from the computation
perspective what you are getting uh is
that you are basically offloading your
computational effort from the online to
offline. So it takes some time may maybe
you require some GPUs to train these
models offline but at the online
inference we are typically getting
orders of magnitude faster acceleration
and in our papers and others we are
getting up to five orders of magnitude
acceleration compared to uh nonlinear
optimization solvers like uh inferior
point so that's very very exciting
um but a lot of problems remain um I
will talk about two specific problems
today. Um there are many many more
including differentiability, well
conditioning and convergence
um of these methods but I want to
highlight two more of a of the
structural problems that uh uh are
common in applications whether it is
power systems or uh HVAC systems in
buildings. The first we have um
differential algebraic equations
describing the system where the
algebraic equation can represent some
energy or mass conservation property
very common in power systems and and
buildings here like very simple example
when you have the reservoir and then you
have a pump and now the mass is
distributed through this three three-way
valve into two tanks. Well, there needs
to be some mass conservation at this
point and that's represented by this uh
algebraic uh constraints on on your
dynamical system. So how can we train
these models and discover their uh
components from data?
That's uh was the question that we asked
uh with the colleagues at PNL and uh
took inspiration from a lot of recent
advances in neural differential equation
especially structured differential
equations and and learning for what is
called universal differential equations.
I believe this is term coined by Chris
Rock here from MIT um uh who has been
working on these methods uh for a while.
So here uh we
uh asked the question that if we can
represent our dynamical system in a
operator splitting uh scheme which is
typically used for large scale uh
systems uh we can apply these
traditional fractional step or what is
called operator splitting schemes by
first solving the uh one part of the
problem get the update on on the dynamic
system state update and then use it as
initial condition for another initial
value problem for the second operator B.
So that's like standard operators uh
splitting scheme and what we ask like
okay can we think about this uh
differential algebraic equation and
apply the same operators splitting
scheme uh in this context uh the answer
is yes but only for certain type of
systems of course so uh the type of
systems is index one differential
algebraic equations uh where uh you can
reduce these das into odes by
differentiating your uh algebraic
constraints exactly wants and for that
we have this pickar lend theorem that is
telling us what properties do you need
to have in order this problem to have
unique solution. So basically um your uh
differential equation is smooth and uh
the algebraic equation is invertible. So
if this holds then you can apply this
relatively simple explicit scheme this
operator splitting where we uh introduce
algebra solver H that takes your
differential states algebra states and
some potential exogenous inputs to get
you update on the algebra solution.
This can be either Newton solver or it
can be uh trained as a soft constraints
with pins. And then you take this
updated algebra state and plug it in in
your forward OD.
And that's it really like super simple
trivial kind of
solution for uh having this neural OD
with algebra constraints that you can
think from the computational graph
perspective. you get uh some initial
condition control action that first sol
goes through the algebra solver solves
the algebraic update and then this
algebraic update initialize the OD
solver to get you the uh differential
state solution and this can be trained
again with the same empirical risk
minimization on the trajectory matching
for both uh differential on algebraic
states.
um lot of different uh and exciting
extensions are already in the literature
where instead of this explicit scheme
you can have semi-explicit scheme where
you first solve the OD solve and then
you project uh on the algebra or
reformulate the whole problem as a
nonlinear optimization problem and solve
it with IP opt so u different direction
exist the one is worked by Chris Rockos
group and another another one with
Lawrence bigler CMU um so We are seeing
a lot of exciting opportunities in
learning for differential algebra
equations tremendously important for
industrial applications.
Um so toy example uh to illustrate uh
the idea where we have this two tank
system and the three-way manifold and
the pump from the reservoir.
We don't need to represent everything as
a black box. We know a lot of structure
from this problem and uh the underlying
differential equations are described um
by the ratios where this fi equation is
basically height area function that we
may not know. So we want to approximate
these uh and then we have this basically
conservation laws um on the three-way
valve and we know that the tanks are
basically at the same level so their
levels needs to like uh level up uh
because of the gravity. So what we can
do we can uh enforce a lot of those
structural constraints just by knowing
the problem. Uh like this conservation
law can be represented by a simple
convex uh uh combination and uh by doing
so we can enforce some of the
constraints as a hard architectural
constraints rather than uh soft
constraints in the penalties. And this
allows you to not only fit uh the
measurement data but also to respect
those conservation laws which is really
helpful for extrapolation out of
distribution data where you can change
uh different design parameters but uh
your model still respects those physical
constraints.
So yeah, this is uh something that I'm
uh very excited for the universe
modeling uh and really practical
applications in energy systems.
Yeah, acknowledging all my wonderful
collaborators and again founding of US
department of energy that enabled this
research on neuro differential algebraic
equations. And now I want to pee to the
second uh challenge that we have in um
energy systems optimization and it's to
handle mixed integer decisions because
uh all of the scientific machine
learning is mostly uh focused on
uh continuous spaces for natural reasons
because we are using automatic
differentiation as a workhorse to
compute our uh gradients. Um but a lot
of practical problems in power systems
like unit commitment problem or uh data
center cooling chiller plant
optimization HRA systems in buildings
have integer decisions switching between
different modes um or dispatching
different units. So what are the
challenges in current uh landscape of
machine learning based optimization? The
first one is um many of the methods
particularly in the machine learning for
mixed integer are based on super
supervisory signals. So the supervised
learning requires you to generate a lot
of training data by solving a lot of my
problems which are expensive. So uh
that's that's the first problem. So for
this reason we we said okay let's focus
on self-supervised learning approaches.
Um second problem is when you are using
neural networks as a surrogate policies
for solving constraint optimization
problems um they are continuous uh how
can we enforce hard integer constraints
without losing differentiability. So we
have been focusing uh on this question
how can we come up with mixed integer
surrogates uh for these control policies
that retain uh differentiability through
smooth gradients and the the third one
is like how do we guarantee feasibility
once we train these models
important for any safety critical
applications so yeah he'll be focusing
actually on extension of uh gradient
based projection that had been proposed
by Priya in her paper in DC3 three um
have been really great inspiration of
this particular work and I want to walk
you through the pipeline of this
self-surprise learning to optimize for
mixed integer um programming. So we
assume again empirical risk minimization
of some nonlinear objective functions
where x is my primal decision variables
and xi are those uh scenarios of problem
parameters that I'm assuming I'm
sampling from some known distribution
and if I know let's say operation
constraints of my energy system then
this is relatively um cheap uh thing to
do. uh the constraints we assume general
nonlinear constraints smooth and
differentiable and for the policy
representation let's have a mapping um
fi that maps these problem parameters to
primal decisions so this is up to now
standard learning to optimize that you
train on this uh empirical corros
minimization of your cost on and
constraint penalties
how can we embed these mixed integer
constraints And so what we introduce are
two components. One is called integer
correction layer that does the integer
rounding while retaining the phys while
retaining the gradients for end to end
trading and the second one is this
physibility projection that utilizes the
gradients from the integer rounding in
the gradient based updates.
So let's focus on these uh integer
correction layers. Um here the
inspiration comes from primal heristics
in mixed integer programming that is
called relaxation and force neighborhood
search or rens in short. And in rens
what we do we have mixed integer program
and we first solve continuous
relaxation. Then we obtain these uh
continuous primals and we get uh the
nearest integer bounds lower and upper
bound to tighten the subsequent myip
solution. So what we ask here is can we
come up with trainable end to end ren
type layers in learning to optimize and
um short answer is yes and basically
what these differentiable integer
correction layers do they are learning
to round up or down for some fractional
value and they are learning with respect
to this empirical cost minimization of
your optimization problem that includes
the constraint penalties. So what what
happens that you are basically learning
this uh conditional rounding uh
mechanisms for specific uh formulation
of the parametric mix integer program.
So how do we do it technically is okay
we assume that uh we get initial relax
solution that can come from continuous
neural network or other means uh the
parametric instance and the second
neural network this delta that is taking
those instances and gives us these
hidden states and these hidden states
basically acts as a corrections
um for the continuous variables they add
basically as additive term to correct
those continuous variables in the
forward pass and For the the integer
part, we first round down the fractional
value and then treat this uh integer
hidden value through two mechanisms
either what we call rounding
classification or learnable threshold.
They are you know practically
equivalent. They are just trying to um
get us this threshold for these
indicator functions to decide whether we
should round up and down. So one is
implemented through a scaled sigmoid
layer and another one with a gumball
sigmoid that introduces a little bit of
stoasticity. But the good thing about
these functions is that they are smooth
and we know analytically they're lip
shits uh constants which is will be very
important for like theoretical analysis
of these uh integer layers in in
projection mechanisms.
Good. So that's uh integer correction
layer allows us to round forward in the
pass uh with this hard rounding and
retains differentiability uh thanks to
the smooth approximations uh of the
rounding threshold and how we deal with
this indicator function we just ignore
it in backward pass through straight
straight to estimator we basically treat
it as identity so that's kind of a trick
for differentiability has been used in
machine learning for a long time
okay uh some small example to illustrate
uh how these layers would work. Let's
say you have some parametric problem
where a and b is a parameter for
objective function and constraint and it
is feature for your uh first continuous
relaxation of the problem that gives you
this relaxed primals and then you take
those relaxed primers together with
those parametric instances in the second
neural network that gives you these
hidden states. And the hidden state for
the continuous variable you just use for
directly updating the continuous
variable. And the hidden state for the
integer variable you either run through
this gumball sigmoid layer or scaled
sigmoid layer to give you the the
threshold value for rounding up and
down. And you train this end to end with
this uh empirical risk minimization of
your objective and constraint
violations. So that's like kind of
learning this uh conditional rounding
for this class of problem. So it's not
like general rounding for any problem.
You will train the rounding mechanism
for your specific problem to um favor
feasibility but there are no physibility
guarantees as such in this integer
rounding with empirical risk
minimization training. So the question
is how can we enforce this physibility
and here is the inspiration from the DCT
tribe projection that we can also uh
think as
uh alternative to physibility pump
heristics that is used in uh mixed
integer programming that again
alternates between rounding and uh
projection. So again you solve a
continuous problem you round to the
nearest integer if it is invisible you
solve projection problem again on a
continuous space uh and you you youerate
yeah u until convergence. So here we
again ask questions how can you utilize
this integer uh correction layers that
ren type mechanism in the context of uh
gradient base updates and the mechanism
is very straightforward. We um okay
assume that we have this initial relax
solution. We have the parametric
instance and we have this pre-trained
correction layer. So that acts acts
basically as a transformation of this
relax solution to the mix integer
solution and then we use this mix
integer solution to evaluate uh our
constraint violations and it can be done
with L1 L2 penalties you get basically
this scalar energy function for the
constraint violations and if it is zero
okay you terminate if it is non zero you
basically run gradient descent on this
function but on the continuous variable
not on the integer var variable here. So
basically um you have this composite
function this uh penalty and the integer
correction layer that you you're
differentiating through to update the
continuous variable. And this this was
really like important from empirical uh
perspective uh to get us
um robust uh performance from this
algorithm. We are still like trying to
theoretically understand why it is so
and um one of the potential explanations
uh could be um our um um convergence
analysis that um is based on on some
assumptions of course. So if you assume
that our constraints are uh l smooth and
um they admit the
lipshits gradients then we can use
standard descent lema on this but of
course this will be approximate uh uh
convergence guarantees for less uh
stringent structural assumptions we can
use this cordika lawyer sherich
inequality as again these are standard
tools in nonlinear optimization we are
which we are borrowing here in the
context of this uh gradient based uh
optimization.
Uh so a lot of interesting uh
theoretical advancement that we can
still uh say about the approximation
error of our uh smoothened um uh
gradients of of the integer correction
layers with with respect to the hard
integer rounding and how this
approximation uh layer um interplays
with our approximate uh physibility
guarantees. So we with assumptions on
smoothness you can also obtain one / k
complexity um um
non asytotic convergence guarantees but
these are still again approximate uh
convergence guarantees u lot of space
for improvement in this theoretical
analysis but thanks to family gradient
based uh structure and and moodness
approximations that really like opens
door for some uh more rigorous
visibility uh analysis here. So how
about empirical performance? Um we are
aiming to solve large scale optimization
problems where traditional solvers fail
or too they are too slow to be
implemented in in in practice and in
those settings even for like modest size
problems like 100 decision variables uh
they're integer and 100 constraints for
quality cases. um state-of-the-art
solvers like Gurobi or skip for
nonlinear optimization over time they
will find better solution than than
these approximate algorithms but by
pre-training these parametric solutions
offline we are really offloading a lot
of cost for the online inference because
now we can in milliseconds obtain a high
quality solutions with feasibility
guarantees on inequalities um that can
make a difference between real-time
implementation so that's what is what we
are really arguing here and empirical
ally we are getting up to five or
magnitude acceleration which can be
really massive
>> yes to ask
>> please please yeah
>> yeah question one is like how do you
choose lambda I mean the term balancing
>> that's that's a crucial question so uh
in
next slide yeah so we did lot of um
ablation studies empirically to analyze
the effect of uh the penalty weight And
of course like if you are putting high
penalty weight on the constraints you
are favoring feasibility versus
optimality. And for instance um these uh
full full lines represent uh just
training the policies with integer
correction layers without uh physibility
projection. So in order to get
empirically high degrees of uh
feasibility where feasibility uh goes up
on on the y-axis uh we require high
values of of these lambdas. Yeah. High
penalties but that kind of significantly
degrades our our objective values of
course. Um so after applying these
physibility projections we can train
with way smaller penalties and get and
kind of uh get the the physibility
projection handle uh the physibility
part and if we are combining them
together we are getting comparable and
sometimes better solutions especially in
the mix integer nonlinear programming uh
case than uh state-of-the-art solvers.
So there is this type of trade-off which
we are still trying to understand
theoretically. Um but empirically we are
having very interesting results on kind
of large scale uh optimization problems.
I think the largest one was 20,000 mix
integer decision variables that we are
still able to train on on the CPU within
two hours and we train these policies
and we still have um subsecond inference
time. So that's
uh that's something that I'm uh really
excited about. Uh lot of opportunities
about theoretically answering these
tuning questions also can come from
applied math community especially the
residual learning in pins. They're
they're putting a lot of effort in uh
adaptive uh weights tuning uh based on
analysis of your gradients of the loss
functions and and the loss function
residuals and adaptive sampling of your
parametric scenarios in regions that are
of a high error and we can really
interpret this also the regions of like
when the active constraints in
optimization become um are become active
basically. So
the the the this kind of generalized
view of scientific machine learning that
brings the ideas from applied mod
operation research and controls I think
can create nice opportunities for new
methods and theoretical development on
those intersections.
>> Yeah good. Yeah I think I have another
question like I think if I understand
correctly uh I mean the rounding part
going to deal with the uh integer part.
Yes. And then the physibility going to
deal with like continuous
>> um like
>> yes uh we are updating the continuous
variable in the physibility but because
you have this hard integer rounding in a
forward pass. So you are actually you
are actually embedding that rounding in
the physibility projection layer.
>> I see. So like mean the fability uh part
can also change the integer variable.
>> Exactly. So like um this uh energy
function like there's a uh the penalty
on the constraint violations where the
integer variable is represented by this
integer correction layer and thanks to
this smooth approximation of the
gradients it allows us to compute the
gradient of uh this function to update
the continuous variable. But the
continuous variable is a pass through
the the rounding layer in a forward
pass.
I see I mean it's it's true that all
together you know
>> well actually in our experiments what we
have done we trained the integer
rounding without projection and then we
use the projection as a post-processing
you could do that um but from the
perspective of the stability of the
learning and avoiding exploding
vanishing gradients we kind of separated
these two so offline training of the
integer correction and uh
post-processing of uh projection layers.
>> Yeah, thank thanks for question really
good uh and um really relevant for this
wonderful work that has been done with
LS Khalil and Bangk
will be joining your group soon. So yeah
um really there was one of my uh great
collaborations I had in last two years.
Um that brings me to the end of my talk
where I was arguing for scientific
machine learning as really potentially
unifying
um methodological advancements that can
bring together communities from applied
math, operation research, computer
science and controls to develop this
type of toolkit that is interoperable
and can be practical for important
applications in sustainable energy where
we are dealing with large decision
spaces. u mixed integer decision
variables and hard constraints that are
necessary for stability and safety of
these systems. So um a lot of challenges
remain that I have been just talking
about two today but uh lot of work on u
backends on effective automatic
differentiation dealing with exporting
vanish ingredients illition problem
which many of them are ill conditioned
and require careful tuning and modeling
um computational cost of guarantees
there are a lot of interesting methods
for verifying this machine learning but
uh yeah they're cost for uncertainty
quantification and hard constraint
guarantees is still u largely
prohibitive for online um inference. Um
but I want to end on the bright side on
the opportunities where I was not
talking about potential of solving PD
constraint problems or optimal control
for PDS that I know many people in the
community are start looking at through
neural operators uh the University of
California San Diego specifically and
other areas and what I'm passionate
about is not only developing new methods
and theories but working on software
tools so we can really transition this
into practical viable applications that
um can really
enable the change the transition in in
applications that are you know important
more than ever and uh hopefully we can
enable that by cutting the cost of
technologies and making the economical
case uh for sustainable energy. So here
I want to yeah thank you very much uh
for being here and uh thanks for all the
questions.
[Applause]