Hello, I'm E. I'm first year post fellow
at the Shimi Center. Uh we are delighted
to have Dr. Anu Kandaji for our next
speaker. Uh Dr. Kandaji is a associate
professor of genetics and computer
science at Stanford University. His
research uh focus on developing machine
learning and computational framework for
regulatory genomics. His work has
transformed our understanding of
regulatory element, regulatory
interaction and genomic variation in
general. Um before joining Stanford, Dr.
Kaji led the computational effort of the
inco project and the road map epigenomic
project. His contribution has been
recognized with numerous honors
including the Hugo Chen award of
excellence uh the NIH doctors new
innovator award and every um and many
else. So please join me to welcome Dr.
Kachi.
[Applause]
All right. So, just want to start by
thanking Caroline and the organizers for
this really nice meeting. Um, I'm
excited to tell you about how uh we've
been using base resolution deep learning
models uh to decipher uh syntax of
regulatory DNA and non-coding genetic
variation. So hopefully this bridges
some of the themes you've seen you know
with the molecular data and genetics uh
using uh machine learning models.
So just to orient us um yesterday uh
Mark gave a really nice uh overview of
how genomewide association studies have
identified thousands of lossi associated
with diverse traits and diseases and as
you know uh vast majority of these lossi
end up being non-coding. So they are not
disrupting protein coding sequence but
uh lie in the non-coding genome. highly
enriched and regulated DNA elements. But
uh just knowing that is not sufficient
because it's still very hard to pinpoint
the precise causal variants, the causal
genes, cell types of action um you know
due to various reasons. Um so this is a
major challenge of trying to identify uh
causal effects and mechanism. Um if you
move to the rare disease case um again
you have again huge catalogs of of rare
and denovo variants now from whole
genome sequencing of patients of rare
disease and again there's a large number
of variants of uncertain significance
that actually end up being
non-coding. So to to address this
challenge uh I think you need at least
two components. First you need to
profile regulated DNA. You need to
actually understand which parts of the
genome are involved in gene regulation.
And uh this is a very multimodal problem
because there isn't a single assay that
gives you all information about
regulatory DNA. Um so people use a
battery of assays to profile uh
regulatory activity. So for example, you
can perform chipsseek experiments for
hundreds of transcription factors in
some cell line or cell type of interest.
Uh or you can perform uh attack seek
single cell attack seek DNA seek
experiments that'll give you chromatin
accessibility landscapes. or you can
perform other kinds of experiments
procap and histone chipsseek and so
forth. So it's extremely multimodal
data. Uh with these data sets we can
start mapping regulatory DNA but if you
really want to understand uh you know
how a variant might affect activity you
do need to understand how DNA sequence
encodes this activ activity patterns. So
what we're interested in trying to use
this data to decipher you know how the
DNA sequence encodes this this sort of
function. And for that over the last few
years we've built these uh class of base
resolution deep learning models. Uh the
basic idea here is you're building a
supervised model that's taking sequence
as its input and trying to predict uh
literally coverage profiles across the
genome at single base per resolution. So
no data no data processing at all. It's
literally taking the raw coverage
profiles and trying to map sequence to
uh uh to uh coverage profiles. And uh
throughout this talk today, I'm going to
focus on uh what I'll refer to as short
context models. These are models that
will only capture about 2 KB to 5 KB of
DNA sequence. Uh obviously this is a
simplifying assumption. The genome is
vast. There's lots of long range
interactions and ideally we would want
genome scale models and there are genome
scale models but I will show you that
many of them actually do not outperform
local models. So our goal uh sort of
from a purely u uh you know design
perspective is to first conquer the
short context uh zone of of models and
they will not be as predictive or
accurate as the ultimate long context
versions but you know if you can't uh if
you can't conquer the short context you
probably don't have much hope of going
long context.
Um and we've built a series of these
models corresponding to various kinds of
readouts. And uh one nice thing is we've
converged on a um uh an architecture
that's that's uh a common backbone for
all our models. So we don't do as much
architecture engineering. We've done
that for a few years, but we ended up
with an architecture that may not be the
ultimate delta optimal like you know you
get an epsilon improvement in
performance, but it's extremely stable.
And we've done lots of tests on it in
terms of uh interpretation stability all
of those important aspects and these
models really work beautifully out of
the box. Uh so the first model we built
was in 2021 called BPnet. This was
designed for transcription factor data
at base resolution for chip exo chipseek
and cut and run. We recently put out
chrome bpnet which is a similar model
that's designed for tax DNA seek and
pseudobulk single cell tax. Uh we have
procapnet which is designed for nent
transcription. uh uh and uh you know TSS
assays like procap cage and rampage and
we have upcoming assays for uh upcoming
models for report assays his own
modifications so so on so we're building
um series of models that are really
specialized for each readout and I'll
explain to you why you just can't take
the architecture and just apply it uh
because it seems like it should just
work out of the box it takes us about 6
to 8 months to optimize any model for
any specific readout and I'll explain
why that's really because of the assay
specific ific technical artifacts and
biases. Um once we have these models, we
can use them to do exciting things like
uh we can take the predictions of the
model for any sequence genomic or
synthetic. Uh we can back prop through
the model. We can use a variety of
different feature attribution methods to
infer for any query DNA sequence um for
a specific readout in a specific cell
type. What are the base pairs that are
likely driving activity? This gives us a
a very high resolution view of the
underlying nucleotides that that
regulate activity. Uh and again this is
very context specific. So if you take
the same sequence and push it through a
model that's trained in a different cell
type or a different readout, it'll give
you a different interpretation of the
exact same DNA sequence. Um you can do
this for every sequence in the genome.
Our models are small. Hence we can scale
them for interpretation. Um, and then
let's say you you run this model over
the entire genome and you get these
kinds of attribution maps that tell you
from the perspective of the model which
base pairs are important over millions
of DNA sequences. Uh you can then you
know identify regions of high
importance and then do very rapid
alignment and clustering to summarize or
distill out uh motif patterns uh
recurrent motif patterns that uh sort of
capture the lexicon that the model has
learned for predicting activity. Then
you can do more interesting experiments.
Uh this is sort of just capturing the
first order patterns but the neural
network is capable of learning much more
interesting syntax. And so we can use it
as again as insilico oracle. So we can
do lots of counterfactual predictions in
silico using synthetic sequences. So
example let's say you're interested in
the spacing syntax between two motifs.
You can generate random DNA. You can
insert motifs chain spacing. Use a model
as oracle to make predictions and see if
it has learned some interesting spacing
relationship. You can do this also for
uh genomic sequences through
combinatorial incilico crisper-l like
experiments. And again a small model
allows you to do this at scale at very
high throughput. And of course then you
can also use a model to do
counterfactual prediction of variants.
Uh you know genetic variants you may
have seen or you would like to query.
And we can do this for common rare
variants SNVs and short indels. All of
works pretty well. So let's jump into
what these models look like. I'll
explain uh the chrome vpnet model. Uh
it's it's actually remarkably simple.
It's not it's not a complicated model.
It just takes 2 KB of local sequence and
maps it to 1 kilobase of base pair
resolution coverage through a simple
convolutional architecture. There's one
convolution layer. There's eight dilated
residual uh blocks. They help you expand
receptive field rapidly. And the model
makes two complimentary predictions. One
prediction is the total coverage over
the entire sequence. That's a scalar
that just captures a total number of
reads over the entire sequence. And the
second head of the model learns to
distribute that total coverage over
every base pair. So it learns a
probability distribution over every base
pair. And this these two loss functions
are simultaneously
optimized. So what we can do is then you
know compare observed versus predicted
on held out chromosomes. Uh this is uh
performance in peak regions for the
total coverage over thousand base pair
peaks. Uh you can see it's pretty good.
You know correlation of 084. Again this
is not replicate concordance. You
shouldn't expect it because we're using
only 2 KV of sequence, but it's still
really high. And if you look at the base
pair resolution probabilities of of
reads across the sequences and you
compare with the observed uh uh
distribution of reads, uh you know, you
see this is replicate concordance. The
Jensen Shannon distance between observed
and predicted query distributions. This
is the distribution of GSDs. Uh you
know, closer to zero is is very
accurate. Uh this is the replicate
concordance. This is our model versus
the observed data. You can see there's
pretty good overlap and these are sort
of baseline pseudo uh sorry um
randomized profiles or the average
profile across the whole genome. So the
model is pretty accurate and you can see
this even at base pair resolution. If
you zoom into any particular uh
regulatory element, this is the observed
data at base pair resolution. Uh this is
the predictions at base pair resolution.
And like I mentioned, we can interpret
the model and try to figure out which
base are driving activity. And in this
case, the model says that there is a
something right here that looks like a
motif. This in fact is a well-known
motif. It's the CDCF motif. One of the
most uh the Chuck Norris of the genome.
Everybody knows CDCF. Um and then there
are all these other base pairs around
it. Uh which are weird. I mean the
predictions of the model are very
accurate, but the base pairs don't make
any biological sense. So this is for a
single enhancer, but we can go across a
genome and aggregate these motifs. What
we realize if you naively train this
model which appears to predict the data
very accurately, it not only learns
transcription factor motifs which you
expect it to learn but it learns the TN5
enzymes sequence bias and that actually
dominates the model very significantly.
So this is uh you know the first uh
important thing to note that if you
naively train models on genomic data any
kind of biological data and you're not
careful about correcting for technical
biases uh you will rapidly run into this
problem that the model will learn the
biology and the technical biases.
There's of course a drawback of not
pre-processing the data. So we have fed
in the raw data. Often people will do
complicated uh statistical processing to
remove these artifacts and then train
the model on that. That's also a
reasonable approach. But maybe we can,
you know, do both at the same time.
Let's see. So now we know the model has
learned all these biases which of course
we would like to correct. So the nice
thing about the human genome is you get
a control experiment for free because
you have three billion base pairs and
only about 2% of the genome actually has
signal these peaks of activity. So the
rest of the genome is basically
background, right? Uh the background is
is not being is directed by
transcription factors. is is it's either
going to be completely random if there's
no bias at all or it's going to be
entirely directed by the TN5 enzyme
sequence bias. Right? So what we can do
is we want to learn a model that only
learns bias. We can train it on the
background regions. There's regions that
are not peaks, right? And when you do
that, you actually learn an incredibly
accurate model. It learns the profiles
exactly accurately in background. That
means sequence can predict the
background profile of TN5 transposition
outside regulated DNA very well as well.
And if you interpret that model, you see
that it learns many variants of the TN5
bias motif. So now what we have is a
model that's confounded by bias and it
has bias and biology built in and a
separate model that has learned only
bias. So there is a very simple trick
that you can use to correct the data
which is you regress out the bias and
you fit a new model to the residual.
That's exactly what we do. So you fit
this model in two phases. You have the
frozen bias model. We now use it to
predict bias in peak regions which were
confounded and then we regress uh that
out and we effectively fit a second
model that learns to fit the residual
after you remove bias.
you get the same exact performance
globally, but you've now routed the bias
through one component of the model and
hopefully the biology through the other
component. So let's see what happens
here. Let's go to the same enhancer.
This is the same region again confounded
by this kind of spurious bias. You can
predict what the bias would look like in
this region using the bias model. And
you can see it actually is remarkably
similar to the observed attack. You know
these spikes you see are really captured
by the bias model. You can see where the
protein binds there's actually
protection in the attack seek data
whereas the bias model is predicting
spiky transposition there as well. You
can interpret the bias model and you see
the base pairs driving the bias are very
similar to these base pairs in the
flanks but the bias model is not
learning the CDCF motif which is exactly
what you would want. So once you can
regress this out and look at the
residual signal it is this beautiful
latent footprint which was hiding in the
attackic data which was confounded by
the TN5 bias. So we can we can back out
this latent footprint and then when we
interpret the bias corrected component
of the model uh you can see it learns
the CDCF motif and these little ZBTV 7A
repressors which were in fact uh hidden
in the original model. And just to take
you back to the uh other approaches
which actually do the bias correction uh
in pre-processing there have been
methods that have done this before. If
you fit models to the bias corrected
data from these pre-processed uh
approaches, you can see that they in
fact do not fully correct bias. They do
partial correction but not completely.
So the key point here is that uh a
neural network trained naively on the
data it learns biology and bias but you
can train the best possible bias model
with a neural network by simply training
it on background or a control data set.
You can then regress out the bias, fit
the residual and you get really
beautiful uh bias correction, right? And
once you do that and you look at the
motifs across the genome or the patterns
learned across the genome, you see that
the TN5 bias is completely gone and all
you learn is transcription factor motifs
as you
would. Now um we can actually do
additional experiments to make sure that
you haven't overcorrected because you
may correct for bias but you may easily
overcorrect for things. Um luckily we
have two assays DNA seek and attack seek
that both profile chromatin
accessibility but use different enzymes.
So the claim would be that if you have a
method that corrects biases very well
after bias correction DNA seek and
attack seek should be very similar much
more similar than they were uh before
bias correction. So uh this is a region
in the genome uh you can see the smooth
attack seek data. This is typically what
people you know call peaks at base pair
resolution. This is what the data looks
like. If you train a model naively on
this data and this is a held out
chromosome, the predictions of the model
are extremely accurate. They mimic the
data exactly as you see it. Here's DNA
seek for the exact same cell type, same
region. Again, the peak, the smooth peak
overlaps very nicely with the attackic
peak. The base pair resolution profile
is completely different from the attack.
Doesn't look anything like it. Uh if you
again train a naive model on it without
any bias correction, it replicates the
DNA seek. If you correct the attackic
bias, it predicts this bias corrected
profile which is quite dramatically
different from the observed data. You
can start seeing it. It looks quite a
bit more similar to the DNA's data. You
can see the footprints aligning quite
nicely. And if you do this for the DNA's
data, you can again see partial
correction. The DNA's you know enzyme
has less bias than the attackic enzyme.
So the correction is less dramatic. But
you can see that after correction the
footprints align very nicely and more
importantly the underlying sequence
syntax the model claims is driving
activity is identical from the two
assays. So the model is able is able to
exactly pull out the precise base pairs
that drive activity from two assays with
very different biases that originally
looked very different. And this is not
just for one locus. You can do this
genomewide and you can see this kind of
dramatic improvement in concordance of
the DNA seek and attack experiments
before and after bias correction and
similarly for the feature attributions
the sequence attribution scores if you
compare the DNA seek and attack seek
attributions you can see this dramatic
improvement uh in in concordance as
well. So we can show how you can use
neuronet networks to correct biases and
reconcile experiments that appear to
look very different originally but are
capturing the same biology.
We've done this at scale now at hundreds
and thousands of data sets and uh of
course we want to validate this. You
know we're calling all these motifs uh
these high contribution score motifs.
Are they real? Is the model
hallucinating this stuff? So luckily we
collaborated with Len Panakio's group
and they did this pretty amazing um
block mutagenesis experiment. This is
actually taking DNA sequences and block
mutagenizing each piece one at a time,
putting it in mouse embryos and
measuring uh report activity. So you get
a whole body uh scan of the embryo to
see uh not only whether the enhancer is
active but also which cell type or
tissue it's active in. This is an insane
experiment. They've done tens of
thousands of these sequences and we've
trained models in humans and mice. This
is done in mouse embryos. So we can
actually test the generalizability of a
model trained in human cellotypes in the
mouse. So the sequence is it's a human
sequence. It's put in the mouse and
you'll measuring activity. So I won't
show you millions of plots. You can look
at the paper. There's there's extensive
validation. But very broadly all I will
say is that even though you're training
the model on chromatin accessibility and
you're testing it on gene expression of
reporters in mice, uh there's pretty
good sensitivity and specificity. We're
getting about 88% specificity for 65%
60% sensitivity. And more interestingly
uh we can take the actual block
mutagenesis results and we can use a
model to interpret why a particular
block increases or decreases activity.
So we get a very nice explanation. Oh,
it's this cryptic motif. It's these two
things happening at the same time. This
mutation creates, you know, this motif
and so forth. So we get the explanation
power for free. Uh so we we've done
other large scale validations as well.
Uh but this is just one example of a
pretty difficult validation experiment.
Again the readout is chromatin
accessibility. The model's trained on
the effect sizes are being tested in uh
a mouse reporter essay which is
measuring expression. So it's pretty
good
generalization. We can also discover
novel things. So motifs people think
motifs who cares you can just run me and
get motifs. Well, let me tell you that
the lexicon that we know about
regulation the human genome is extremely
incomplete and we will have a catalog
coming out soon where we've collated uh
neural network learned lexicons from uh
tens of thousands of models and I will
just say that the motive landscape is
non-trivial and here's one example you
know foss is a well-known transcription
factor is has this AP1 motif TED is
another transcription factor with its
well-known motif u in the IMR90
fibroblast test the chromeb9 model for
taxi learns this composite element. It
is a force and a tad that is exactly six
base pairs apart. Now usually when this
happens is very interesting. It usually
indicates a cooperative interaction. But
just the presence of two motifs six base
pairs apart doesn't tell you that
something's cooperative. It just tells
you that two things are six base pairs
apart. They could happen due to many
reasons. We can use a model in a
counterfactual setting to test
cooperativity. So how do we do that? We
can take a piece of random DNA. It has
no activity. You can see the black line.
We can push it through the model. The
model predicts flat signal. We can take
the false only motif, put it inside the
sequence and it predicts mild activity.
We can put TED only. It predicts mild
activity. You can compute the additive
effect of TED and FOS six B pairs apart
as if they were independent by literally
adding up their signals. That's this
this signal right here. And then you
have the joint effect of the two of them
together. There's this amazing
amplification. This is classic
cooperivity, right? And you can also
test for the spacing. Is the six base
pair an artifact or is it real? Well,
from the perspective of the model. And
you can see that again you can play with
the spacings in silicone and predict
effects. And you see this massive
amplification only exactly at six way
pairs. And we've done this for many
other known uh composits as well. This
is a novel composite that's never been
seen before. And uh we haven't validated
this experimentally but we can fit
another neural network to chipsseek data
of FOS which is one of the partners
right here and it's a completely
different model trained on different
data. It's chipsseek data not attackseek
and we can replicate the exact syntax.
So you can do the same incilico
experiment and you can see the same
amplification and you can see the exact
same uh strict spacing. So actually a
bioarchy paper just dropped today
morning from uh my lab and Will
Greenleaf's lab. We've done this at
scale for a big fetal atlas of attack
data and we've discovered hundreds of
these composite elements many of which
are very novel and the lexicon is
substantially more complicated uh than
we think. Um we can also use the models
for interpreting genetic variation. So
um here's an example. This is a a
quantitative trait locus. It's a variant
that has been shown to impact chromatin
accessibility uh through uh genetic
profiling and chromatin accessibility
profiling. Uh we can again use a model
counterfactual setting. You put you take
the reference sequence. It has a C alil
at this position. You switch the C to a
G. You see this really nice beautiful
amplification. But you can interpret the
model and understand how it's doing
this. And you can see that the C alil
has this weak signal due to this kind of
low affinity spy 1 motif. When you swap
the C to a G, it creates a very strong
spy 1 motif that cooperates with this uh
other motive nearby to amplify activity.
So you can get a very nice explanation
for this. This is of course one example.
We can do this at scale. So we're going
to now um you know validate against um a
chromatin QTL data set. This is
basically a taxi done in hundreds of
individuals of diverse African ancestry
in lymphoblastoid cell lines. So using
this you can associate genetic variation
with chromatin accessibility. We
identify 11,000 CAQDLs that are in
peaks. And now we have this uh chromant
model that's trained in a reference
individual of European ancestry. So it's
it's a different ancestry group. It's a
reference individual and we've trained
it on the reference genome. we've not
even seen the personal variants. We're
going to try to see if we can
counterfactually capture these effects.
Uh so we just simply take all these
variants, we push them to the model just
as I showed you before and we correlate
the uh observed betas on the x-axis
against the predicted betas. This is not
0.9. Again, it should not be 0.9. Uh
actually replicate concordance if you do
the QTL experiment twice, the
correlation is about8. So we're not that
far from a local model that's only
seeing 2 KB. And what's more important
is we are very directionally concordant.
So what that means is like the effect
sizes are not only correlated but when
you have a positive effect the model
predicts a positive effect. When you
negative effect you predict a negative
effect. Now let's see how this does
against these uh large long context
models. So we contrast again I I showed
you the results of a of a small model
with six million parameters trained on
one data set uh on a reference genome.
Uh the opposite end of the spectrum is u
a very large multitask transformer
model. This is Enform from 2021. Uh
we've also benchmarked against Bour
which is the bigger version of this. Uh
Enform has 385 kilobase receptor field.
Bour has 554 kilobase receptor field.
This is trained on uh literally 30,000
tracks on human and mouse. So obviously
should be learning much better than us.
But actually it ends up doing not that
great. Um in fact if you take the
predictions from the informer paper uh
the same correlations I showed you right
here you know um and we can uh compute
these correlations as a function of the
CAQTL threshold just so we threshold
independent because you can always you
know play around and cheat with your
thresholds to get something that looks
good. So on the x-axis is all possible
thresholds on the y-axis is correlation
from the model versus the observed
betas. If you take Informer's uh
predictions from the paper, it is
actually remarkably poor, which you
know, our models are great, but that
didn't make sense to us. So, we went and
tried to figure out what was going on.
And we realized that they um for some
reason were predicting the variant
effects using 100 kilobase of uh profile
that they're predicting. So, you can
imagine a variant has a tiny effect at a
peak, right? It destroys a peak
completely. The rest of the genome stays
intact. when you compute the delta, you
end up swamping your own signal, right?
So, actually they are much better than
they think. So, we recomputed them. We
did them a favor. And when you do that,
you actually get this nice boost in
performance, which is the green uh
triangles. But if you compare it to our
models, we are still much better for the
exact same match depth. And if in fact,
if you increase the sequencing depth of
the experiment, not the size of the
model, just crank up the read depth.
Tell your collaborators to create, you
know, 10 times more reads if they can.
uh you actually get a nice boost there
as well. Okay. And this is not just for
effect size prediction. You can also
compare binary classification. So here
we're looking at CAQLs, right? The
significant QTLs and we're comparing the
actual effect sizes. We may also want to
classify, can we identify CAQLs against
background variants, right? And these
are well controlled variants. These are
background variants in peak regions. So
you can't cheat. They're not in
background. They're actually in peaks.
And the classification of a random
classifier would be about, you know,
average precision would be about 05. So
it's a pretty hard problem. Again,
Informer's original scores look pretty
bad. After we correct them, they are
just maybe slightly better than us. But
again, if you increase readth, you get
this nice boost. Okay, so model size is
not everything. Uh read depth can
actually give you a lot of power over
the number of parameters in your model.
We've done other such benchmarks
including uh with Jesse Angritz. They
have this paper recently out. They have
this variant flowfish experiment which
is sort of like the block mutagenesis
experiment I showed but this is in
genome you know crisper with effects on
the target gene. Here we're looking at
the promoter of a gene called PPIF. Now
you would have expected a model like
inform which is trained on gene
expression. Uh it's a long context model
to have learned a very good model of at
least the genes promoter.
uh this is the predictions of enirmer
against the the actual crisper
experiment it's quite low it's about 042
if you use infirmer's expression head if
you use infirmer's chromatin head it's
actually quite a bit better 62 and if
you use chrome bpnet's uh predictions
it's 65 so we are actually quite a bit
better even on promoters using
accessibility to predict expression
effects of target
genes and the other class of large
models we have are these DNA language
models and these are pretty hot right
now. Many of them are absolutely massive
and they take months and months to train
and we've tested them against um we had
this publication in Europe called Dart.
It's a series of of tests we we suggest
of uh trying to decide if discover
whether a DNA language model has learned
uh very basic things like you know has
it learned motifs to the more
complicated tasks like counterfactual
prediction and we test these models in
zeroot probed and full fine-tuned okay
and uh these are all the latest models u
we have EVO and EVO 2 as well and they
don't perform much better than this um
random classifier would have an AUC
5 zeroshot probed fine-tuned you know
just slightly better than random here's
chrome bpbnet uh and the fine-tuned
model sees the exact data that chrome
bbbnet sees okay so it's not like we
seeing anything more and these are two
different QTL data sets and we
substantially outperform them so we can
do this for QTLs but we can also go to
gwas you know the first slide I showed
you and we can see if we can actually
recover fine map variants uh from go
slow size so here what we're doing is on
the X-axis we're looking at uh posterior
probability thresholds for fine mapping
for coronary artery disease lossi. So as
you increase the posterior probability
you're getting more and more confident
in terms of identifying the causal
variant. This is a genetic approach to
fine mapping. And on the y-axis you're
seeing the overlap enrichment of chrome
bpnet's predictions against the uh the
fine map variants. And you're looking at
enrichments observed as expected. You
can see that as you increase the PIP
threshold, you see these nice
skyrocketing enrichments and you see the
enrichments improve as you increase
Chrome BPET's prediction performance as
you would expect, right? And by the way,
this is a model that's trained on
uh taxic data from smooth muscle cells,
single cell attack data from mice, and
we're using it to start to predict
variant effects in the human genome. And
interestingly, the mouse model does
better than human smooth muscle cells.
The reason is because we have the mouse
data coming from a mouse model of
atherosclerosis where we feed it highfat
diet and we track it over time and we
get all these unique cell states uh as
the cells you know the vasculature in
the in the in the in the mouse is
actually uh getting fibroic right so
you're getting these very unique cell
states which you don't capture from the
human vascule that you just pull out
from patients. So in fact in this case
the mouse model does slightly better
than the human model for fine mapping.
uh we can interpret LOSI. So uh this is
a very exciting uh result and we
actually see this in many LOSI. It's not
one causal variant often sometimes it's
two inside the same enhancer. So here we
have two variants right next to each
other. Uh it is a fine map variant. Uh
the model predicts it exactly as having
the effect in smooth muscle cells. The
two variants right next to each other
and you can see this beautiful interplay
between them. Uh this variant uh on this
hletype has the AL. The A al creates an
AP1 motif, an activator. The G alle
destroys it. Uh this other variant right
next door in perfect LD, the C also type
in fact destroys a Z1 repressor. Whereas
the T alle creates the Z1 repressor. So
on one HLO type you're creating an
activator and destroying the repressor.
On the other halfype, you're creating
the repressor, destroying the activator.
So you get this massive effect size. You
see like the enhancers completely off on
one hloype and highly on on the other.
So there's really interesting variant
coordination going on. And we can also
do this for rare variants. So this is an
example of a patient from the DDD
consortium very severe
neurodedevelopmental disorder. We've
trained uh these single cell attack
models on um fetal tissue fetal brains.
So all kinds of cell types from fetal
brains. Um, we are able to prioritize
tens of thousands of these rare disease
variants. We not validated all of them,
but this is one we did. This is in a
gene desert. It's really far. It's 384
kilobases from CD83. It's 748 kilobases
from Jared 2. Uh, if you push it through
all the different models, this
specifically scores only in glutamic
neurons. You can see it's a pretty
complex enhancer with complex syntax.
The A alle creates the high activity.
the Gal creates low activity and it does
so by creating a NR2F1 repressor. So you
have the mechanism as well. Now we take
these two constructs and put it back
into our mouse again thanks to Len
Panakio's lab Michael Kosiki and if you
put the reference A al you can see
activity in the brain specifically you
put the G alil and you see exactly what
you expect.
Um I'll just end quickly by saying that
uh there's an additional problem with
these large kitchen sink multitask
models and that's if your goal is to
actually do causal inference and design
uh they in fact we have very strong
evidence and we have a paper coming out
soon that they're learning pervasive
features spurious associations which are
not causal. I'll just show you one
example of this. This is enforce
predictions for a particular locus.
There's a strong peak here in
fibroblast. Um, you can just take this
GRL motif and you can insert it in
fiberblast to see what it does. And if
you insert one instance, you see some
decrease in activity. If you insert two
instances, you see a little bit more. If
you insert three, four, five, six, you
can shut down the enhancer by inserting
this GHL motif. And uh, what's really
interesting is um, is that GRL is in
fact not expressed in fibroblast at all.
So the model has learned a spurious
association. It has learned a fake
repressor which when you put into these
cell into this into the system it
actually predicts um false effects. So
I'm out of time so I won't summarize.
Hopefully uh my talk gives you an
overview of how basically lightweight
single task models can actually perform
quite well and you can use them for
interpretation. And I'll just stop there
and thank my lab and my collaborators
and funding sources.
Um let's have one question.
Uh hey Anel, very nice talk. Um one very
common sort of epigenomic assay that I
don't think you you mentioned you've
developed a model for is is histone
chipsseek. So you know these are very
widely used. Um are there unique
challenges there or or what do you think
about that? Yeah, we actually have
pretty good histori models. They are
corrupted with a new kind of bias. So
we've been spending the last year trying
to figure out how to correct that bias.
We have models that work really well,
but I think it's basically nucleosome
positioning bias. So that's not a like a
technical bias. It's actually a
biological bias. But if your goal is to
figure out what syntax drives histone
modification versus nucleome
positioning, you would want to again
reroute that bias in a specific way.
Otherwise, when you interpret a
sequence, you get these haze of GC80
frequencies which are basically
nucleosome positioning signals and you
you want to be able to distinguish that.
So it's mostly an interpretation
challenge right now, but we do have
pretty good histo.
Okay. Oh, let's thank our speaker again.