If you have a couple economist friends,
you know that they don't get excited
very often. But one of the very few
things that gets economists excited is
the appearance of not just any
technology, but a general purpose
technology. And this is a high bar.
These are the technologies that
interrupt and accelerate the normal
march of economic progress. And examples
of these are the steam engine which
kicked off the industrial revolution.
About a century later, we started to
electrify things. The internal
combustion engine also merits this
category. And most recently, the
appearance of the computer probably
qualifies as a general purpose
technology. So, here we are. It's very
early in the history of generative AI,
but I think it's pretty clear that this
technology is going to be very
pervasive. We're going to see it in I I
believe every industry.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu. edu.
[Music]