hello everybody I want to explain a
little bit on how we can visualize music
using music 21 or other tools and how
important it is to be able to see what
is happening in a piece of music rather
than going through Jupiter notebook the
users guide to music 21 chapter 22 which
there's a link past into the page that
this is on has a good introduction to
some of the things that you can do with
graphing and
plotting we can go ahead and start by
importing everything from Usef 21 we
really only need the Corpus and there's
one piece by the Italian 19th century
opera composer JP Verde from his opera
roletto called Ladon Mo which we can
load in using the Corpus parse function
and store its variable Verity let's just
look at the first 10 measures and we can
show
it you probably may have heard this
before so it's a little piano score
version and so let's just get the vocal
part and if we go ahead and call on this
exerpt oh by the way I don't know if we
fully explained you can extract a
measure range
with these two numbers uh this is
inclusive uh unlike Python and so this
will include measure one and measure 10
and these are the numbers according to
how a musician would think of them okay
we can go and plot them and by default
it creates sign we usually call a piano
roll because it kind of looks like how
if you're going to punch the rolls um
outside of things like this um you can
go ahead if you know map plot lib or
another plotting software in cre these
things on your own but there's a couple
things that music 21 will take care of
for you if I zoom in oh there it goes
oops um and some of
them but there are some things that
music 21 will take care of for you for
instance uh the pitch will have octave
marks just on the C's or wherever
something is it will have correct flat
signs or sharp signs and choose the
right accident for what's happening here
and things will be plotted by measure
even if uh the measures are difficult to
deal with for instance uh here's a
here's a little example where we use
some pretty weird
accidentals the only C really is a dble
flat or so on and it will put out you
can barely see it but it will put double
flat there and if your measures are
different lengths it'll do it so it's
probably a decent thing to go go ahead
and call the Misa 21 plot if you want to
visualize
something we can load on another piece
uh this is uh Arnold schernberg uh early
late 19th and early 20th Century
composer from Austria who is uh
considered one of the creators of a
total music it will load his piano piece
opus 19 and will load movement too this
is just another way of loading a
specific movement for a piece and we'll
excerpt measures 1 through 4 and show
them there's a couple little problems
here you can kind of see this piece um a
lot of bum bum bum bum bum bumps in it
and what we can do is in the plot
command we can give it other things so
we're going to do a scatter plot we're
going to map quarter length to pitch and
we'll give it a title see the G and the
B and if we zoom in
here we can really
see oh yeah um we're doing a scatter
plot and we're making it darker the more
times things appear and we can see the
quarter length log two um so they're
equally spaced between 16th notes eighth
notes quarter and half note and see the
various pitches
here the other thing we can do is we can
do a histogram of uh pit of octaves and
we'll hide little ticks for anything
that doesn't appear and put the number
of pitches here and we can really see
these two uh the G and the B showing up
a lot or we can just restrict it to
specific pitch classes and see the pitch
classes of g&b without the octaves still
dominate on this
piece uh you don't really need to
install Matt plot web anymore um because
it's now included music 21 but you will
want if you're using
um if you're using Jupiter notebooks to
put this magic command at the beginning
and that will uh allow you to view
everything in
line you can go ahead and see what kinds
of things are there um horizontal
bars we can plot measure number and
quarter length against the pitch and so
on um various pitches SC Scatter
Plots counts of how often various pitch
and note lengths appear we can uh we'll
say how this happens later but we can
look at uh what the range of the piece
is how big it how far apart it is
various places or what the keys that are
being detected in various parts of the
piece using Carol Kel Shucker's key
analysis um we can look at when various
parts are playing and I believe this is
how loud they are um some silly 3D
graphs which can be kind of helpful
maybe uh but maybe not and it can also
plot against Dynamics and you'll kind of
notice that it says met Forte Forte
Forte pianos sportando fortisimo so that
there's built in um places for various
Dynamics we can see what kinds of Atlas
qualities there are and so on so what we
can do is we can look at how various
composers such as Robert Schuman a mid
19th Century composer how he uses his
pitches in a particular um string
quartet versus how chopan uses his in
one
Missoura then always important to go
back sorry it's all distorted for the
video but uh and look at how the piece
actually
works in chapter 44 of the music 21 you
this guide completely optional it'll
tell you a little bit more on how you
can customize plots with their title
change the size of the
figures change
colors and uh go ahead and um make other
plots highlight particular
data and um
remove data substitute other things in
there
not too much else these are pretty
Advanced things going on but um we can
look at offset versus cardinality well
you know what cardinality is now how
many pitches are sounding at once notice
this a little nice pickup measures at
the
beginning and um maybe you want to plot
how the frequency in hertz goes against
pitches but show um white and black keys
or this case red and black keys over
tie and you can use this to make um some
various other graphs that might not come
from data these are all kind of
interesting things uh smoothing out how
box motion Works in a particular
Crow there's a lot still to be done with
plotting but this is a great way to
start I'm also going to put in a link to
Edward Tufts or tufty I'm not exactly
sure visual display of quantitative
information which is a book that has
absolutely shaped how I think of what
are good ways of creating graphs why we
want to create graphs and how do we make
the data stand out and still be
beautiful thanks a lot for listening and
hope to see some beautiful graphs in the
future