Next, I'd like to welcome, it's a
pleasure to introduce co, excuse me,
Corey Walrip of Sublime Systems. Sublime
Systems is transforming data center
infrastructure by developing lowcarbon
cement solutions that reduce emissions
and support more sustainable, energy
efficient facility construction.
Welcome, Corey.
>> Thanks, everyone. Uh, thanks Trisha. Um,
happy to be here at this event. Um, we
are a company that actually came out of
MIT. So we spun out in 2020. Um came out
of uh Professor Ying Changeng's lab. Um
and our co-founders are Leia and Yet um
and Leia was a at that time she was a
member of the lab at at Inette's lab. Um
so we uh are commercializing a
technology that produces uh lowcarbon
cement uh for um the data center
industry as long as well as many other
industries. So why does that matter?
cement um as a whole uh produces about
8% of global CO2 emissions. Um one ton
of the ordinary Portland cement that's
produced today represents about one ton
of CO2. When you put this in perspective
in the data center industry, if you look
at a lot of the hyperscalers um and
their um emissions profiles and their
sustainability reports over the past few
years, most of those increased emissions
are coming from the capital goods
category. as they build more and more of
these data centers, their capital goods,
the emissions from those capital goods
um are increasing exponentially and
that's coming from steel and concrete.
So, we're providing a a solution here
that can address the emissions related
to the physical materials um that go
into these data centers. Our
breakthrough technology of course avoids
CO2 and I'll get more into the metrics
um that around that. Um so, we are not
providing any sort of carbon capture. We
are avoiding the emissions at the
source. um we are able to achieve cost
parity when we produce our materials at
the existing scale of uh industrial
cement production. Um we're also
producing a better cement um in terms of
durability features and aesthetic
qualities. Um we are a more
energyefficient process and in the
process of making our cement blends
we're also unlocking additional critical
minerals in terms of magnesium um
aluminum materials um and and also iron
products.
So uh fundamentally what Sublime is
doing is replacing the uh the existing
process for ordinary Portland cement
production which takes limestone which
is a carbonate material and then you put
that limestone in a rotary kil which is
fired at very high temperatures by coal
or natural gas. So you're getting two
sources of emissions the limestone
decomposition and then the use of fossil
fuels in that kiln. Sublime is taking a
different approach which is a low
temperature process that uses
non-carbonate materials. So when we use
clean electricity, we are basically
removing both emission sources from the
production of cement. The product that
we're producing is a drop-in hydraulic
cement. So this this material is is a
cement powder just like you would use in
the construction industry today. And it
can store, pour, and perform just like
ordinary Portland cement. So it drops
into the existing construction value
chain. And ultimately when it's mixed
with aggregates and water it forms the
same calcium silicate hydrate harden
phase that existing concrete uh uses
today.
So uh what's most important uh the
reason why I joined the company uh and
and many of the folks at Sublime um are
are still here is because of this uh we
have the potential to be able to produce
a cement um that is over 90% uh
decarbonized versus today's Portland
cement. Um this is a step change in
terms of what uh any other technology um
could produce um outside of you know
giant carbon capture installations on
existing cement production.
So we've uh scaled up quite quickly over
the past uh 5 years. Uh as mentioned we
started in a lab at MIT um at R&D scale.
Um we've now been operating our pilot
facility which is just located down the
road um in in Somerville um for the past
three years um where we produce material
for internal testing, external testing
and then also product demonstration
pores which I'll talk about. Um we're in
the process of in final engineering
design and expect to break ground on our
first commercial facility um which will
uh which is expected to be operational
in 2028. This will be in uh western
Massachusetts in Holio. Uh and this will
eliminate much of the scale up risk
associated with our product and uh and
the process technology. Um lastly, we'll
scale up to the full industrial scale.
So we call these mega plants or megaton
scale plants about 1 million tons of
cement produced per year. Um and we
expect those in the 2030 plus 2030 plus
time frame. Uh we are partnered with
some of the largest uh strategic cement
players in the world. So, Amise, CR, and
wholesome um partnered in terms of a
deal that provides uh offtake for our
materials. It also provides uh a a
partnership framework to be able to
build those full-scale plants in
coordination with them.
And we are also working directly with
the data center industry. So earlier
this year, we signed a binding forward
offtake agreement uh to to provide
material as well as environmental
attributes to Microsoft. Um so this uh
spans the material produced at our first
two commercial facilities. The facility
was mentioned in Holio, Massachusetts as
well as our first full-scale production.
Um so we're very uh looking very much
looking forward to being able to be a
supplier to the data center industry at
mass scale and we're repeating the same
agreement template with other
hyperscalers and data center developers.
Ultimately what's most important is
getting our material in the ground. Uh
we've done that with the material from
our pilot facility over the past few
years. So starting at a at the slab um
and then moving all the way to a data
center loading dock. So we are
specifically working in the data center
industry um with construction
contractors with developers and the
hyperscalers themselves. Uh and so you
can see our most recent applications um
are in different applications that you
might see in a data center. Eventually
of course we'll be moving to this lab on
grade application that would be um you
know underpinning uh most of the racks
uh where all these GPUs are sitting.
So uh very much looking forward to
conversing with you all after the
presentation later on and learning about
how we could partner with you all in
terms of building uh these data these
infrastructure uh that this data center
rely these data centers rely on. Thank
you.