So last time
uh last time we talked about the basic
algebraic operation for limit of
sequences. We talked about the mono
convergence theorem. So the mono
convergence theorem was that you had a
sequence
that was increasing or it could be
decreasing. So either it was increasing
this meant that the next element was
bigger equal to the previous and then
they were all assumed to be bounded.
If you had such a sequence or similarly
if you had a sequence so this was the
increasing case
then there was a similar decreasing case
where the the the
previous is bigger equal to the next one
and then they are assumed to be bounded
from below.
So this was decreasing.
So monotum convergent theorem was that
if you had a bounded increasing sequence
or a bounded decreasing sequence in
either case
uh uh the sequence is convergent
and it's converging in the first case in
this case here a
um it's converg to the soup
of the xm to the in case Okay.
And in the case B it converts to the in
case case B. So that was the mono
convergence theorem.
And the third thing we talk about and
that's where we will continue today is
uh is cruise sequence. So we talked
about push sequence.
So let me and we prove a few things
about cruise sequence but we want to
examine that all today. So let me remind
you what a cruise sequence is. So a
sequence
is said to be
Uh if for all epsilon greater than zero
there exist
there exist n such that
if little n is bigger equal to the
capital n then Um sorry if little n and
little m.
So if n and m m and n are big or equal
then they are
epsilon close together
xn
and x m the distance between them.
So this was a cus sequence and it just
meant quis sequence just meant that the
tail right of the sequence bunchs
together.
Now, uh, let me just prove I think we
maybe talk about this, but let me but
I'm going to let me
just a little theorem here.
Um if
if uh xn
is a cruci sequence
then uh xn is bounded
and so the proof of this is a proof.
So now in the definition of it being a
frequency you can take epsilon to be
equal to one. So if you take take
epsilon equal to 1
in the definition
of being
accuracy sequence.
So this means that there exist there
exist
there exist some n
such that
uh if little n and little m are bigger
than this n then the difference between
these two
is less than one. Right? This is the
definition where I just apply it to
epsilon equal to one. We have this but
of course in particular
in particular we can set say m equal to
this
and then you have that x all the other
ones. This means that for all
then for all
um little n bigger than capital n if
you're looking at this
difference here then this is less than
one I'm only applying this now I'm just
choosing just one single m and I'm
choosing it to be equal to that capital
so you have that And so this means that
that now you see that if you take now so
so if you take
uh x so now suppose that little n
so so for
little n bigger than capital n if you if
you look at little n
then you have this
so or
for or little n big or equal to capital
n. Then you have that the norm of little
n. Well, you can write little n as as um
as a difference.
You can write little n
like you can subtract it first and then
add it again. So this is clearly the
same.
And now you can just
So you have the sum of two things. You
can think about this in here as one
number and this is another number. So
this is now less than x n minus x
capital n plus the norm of x capital n.
And this here was because little n was
bigger than capital n. This here is
bounded by one. So this is less than one
plus the norm.
this.
So you see that for all the the little
ends that are bigger than capture all of
those there is a uniform arch right and
so this means that if you're now just
taking them the maximum
of uh the norm of x1 the norm of x2
up to the norm of xn
uh minus uh sorry xn minus one
and then x capital n
+ one. If you take the maximum of this
and call this m then clearly for all n
for all n
clearly you have for all n
you have that x n is lesser equal to n
right because if n little n is bigger
than capital n then it's bounded by
capital M because it's it's a maximum in
particular of this and on the other one
that's sort of obvious.
Okay. So so it means that if you have a
cushy sequence it's automatically
bounded. Okay.
Now we have the
convergence theorem. So next we want to
discuss
is
convergence.
So this is the following that uh any
any precision principle
is convergent.
Okay. So remember that last time we
proved the following. So so recall
that last time
we showed the converse
So namely we prove the following
theorem.
to prove that if
that any
convergent sequence
is a cushy sequence
and so the cushy convergence theorem is
to
Now uh so we'll come back to the proof
in just a little bit
but before that let me talk about some
applications
and so the first one we we sort of
started talking a little bit um last
time and this is uh the contracting
mapping the so contracting And that in
itself have a number of applications. So
contracting
mic
and for that I need some I need to uh
call some definitions.
So,
so a map
a map t from r e to r
uh is set to be
a contracting map.
If there exist
some constant C positive C is positive
and the key point is it's it will have
to be positive. So that but the key
point is that this constant has to be
strictly less than one. And then
contracting mapping just means that if
you looking at the difference
between the images
then they are closer together. This
they're strictly closer together
than than the points that they are
images of.
Okay. So this is a contracting map
right then. So the contracting mapping
again this here inequality is it say
that under the map the images are
squeezed more together.
So now
that's one concept. The other one we
need is that for fixed points.
So the other concept is fixed point.
So So X here is a fixed point.
for MF.
See if if it is
if under the map the the points uh
remain unchanged. So T of X is equal to
X. So this is what it needs to be. Yeah.
>> But that it's not the same C for X and
Y. It is the same scene. It is.
>> Yeah, it's the same scene.
>> And we'll come back to this in just a
second, but but it but it it is supposed
to be the same scene.
You can weaken that a little bit. Uh but
essentially, I mean, you sort of, you
know, at least we'll talk about this in
just a second, but it it's important
just think about it that it's a
requirement that it's the same seat for
all. And the key point is that this C is
strictly less than one. Okay. So this is
a fixed point.
And now um so now the first
little
that.
So we have a lema here.
Uh if t
uh is a contracting
then
then um there's at most
at most one
there cannot be more than one fix. Okay.
So let's prove that. a pro.
So yeah, so I'm going to So suppose
X and Y are fixed points
and I want to show
that X is equal to Y.
So I'm looking at the
images.
So
uh
Let's continue.
So I'm looking at the images under F. So
I'm looking at So I take T of X
and I'm looking at the difference
between T of X and T of Y
and I want to estimate that difference.
Well, on one hand T X is supposed to be
a fixed point. So T of X is the same as
X and likewise for Y. So this here is
the same. So T of X is the same as X. T
Y is supposed to be the same as Y. So I
have this. On the other hand, it's a
contracting map. So this here is less or
equal to C
times the norm of X - Y.
Right? But now C here remember C is
strictly less than one.
So you can only have an inequality like
this, right? If this number here is
zero, right? when c is strictly less
than one. So this here implies that x -
y
the distance is zero and so of course
this means that x is equal to y.
>> Okay. So that's what we want to prove.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. I'm sorry that was uh yeah it
should
because otherwise you know it's it
wouldn't be if x is equal to y would be
so should be let's change
okay so a contracting map have at most
one fix one
okay now let's
uh so so so let me Just so you're going
to do this. So um
um I have harassed the graders to give
you back the homework. I uh it should be
back today. I mean otherwise they're in
trouble. So hopefully but but but and
the assignment for next week is already
posted.
And and here's
here's um
so this is on the next so I I will
so here's um here's something on pet
stream
and I think it's uh
okay uh yeah I forget which one it is
but anyway on on the third pet
You will be asked to prove the following
that if uh t here
is a contracting map
and
and x here is any point
any point in the domain of this
Then if you form the sequence a n so a1
say that's just x
a2 uh let's let's call it a sorry let's
let's call it a z is x
uh a1 here
is t of x t of a is zero so this is t of
and a2
is t of a1. So this is the same as t of
this. So this is t
* t of x which I'm will write like this
and uh a3 so we continue this way a3 is
t of a2. So that is
t applied three times. So t g
t g t g t g t g t g t g t g t g t g t g
of x and I'm going to write this as g c
2 of x
and and so on. So a n is going to be t
of a sorry it's t
a n + one
is going to be t of a n. So that's the
same as uh t to the power n + one
of x.
Okay.
So if you have a contracting map and you
just start with any point you want and
now you form a sequence that is based on
that point and uh and the nth element is
just where you have applied the map n
times to the original point. So if you
form that sequence then you will prove
uh you will show
that uh
in the homework you will show that this
sequence so this set
three and I I will just do a
special case of it that you will start
with but we'll just do this now
and then the rest to you to you know I
leave you for the homework but but on
piece of three you prove that this a is
a secret
and what is the the key starting point
starting point for this
so now
because you're there you know you're
already uh well started on on p three is
a key starting point for this is to
prove that it's a cruise sequence so I
want to estimate
so this is not enough right I mean I
need to prove what I need to show is
remember I need to prove that when
little m and little m
are sufficiently large then I want to
estimate the distance between these two
and show that they're bunched together,
right? That's what we need to prove.
Prove this precision. I I won't quite do
this, but I do a special case that is a
key starting point. And that is the
where I'm looking at this thing here.
I'm looking at two consecutive element
in the sequence and I'm estimating the
distance. That's not enough to prove
that C sequence, right? Because I need
to prove that for all n and m
sufficiently large. And I'm just proving
here that for any ns sufficiently large
if I'm looking at the neighbor then that
this is very small but but but you can
use the estimates that we will now prove
to prove that it is in fact a sequence.
So in order to estimate this right I'm
can think about this thing here
as t as a to the n + one this here is
just t of a to n and a n itself this is
t of the previous element right this is
how we define them so this means that
this thing here so again I could just
write this in here. So this thing is
equal to a n minus t of a n minus one
and now I can use that contracting map
right because now I have these two gez
here so I can use that contracting map
so I get less or equal to and then a n
minus a n minus one
and so you see that that's the Next the
distance between the next pair is
because C is strictly less than one. It
has decreased with some factor. Right?
And so now the the the key starting
point is that if you just iterate this.
So now if I iterate this, so I'm looking
at a n + 1 minus a n
and I now have that this thing here is
less than c a n minus a n minus one. But
now I'm writing forget about the c for a
second. I'm just writing this thing
here. So I do the same thing again. I
write this here as the image of a n
minus one and I write this n minus one
as the image of the previous one. So n
minus two right and now so I write this
so c here I just have to carry along for
the right and then I have t a n minus
one minus t a n minus 2.
And now forget about this just use this
contracting mapping. So then this is
less than equal to and then the C here I
to carry along. But then there's another
C that pops out. Right? So this is times
C that pops out because of the
contracting mapping and then a N minus
one minus A N minus 2. And so you see
that you have written this as c^ squ a n
minus 2 - one minus a n minus 2. And so
now you continue it and so you see that
the further out you get right. So you
continue this all the way down to that
you're getting that this element is the
initial point and and this one is the
first ele you know a1. This is a z and
this is a1 right
and so you see that you're getting
something which is like a a c to some
power n times the distance that you
started with right so this is bounded by
uh something like c to the n * a 1 - a z
something like that
and so that's a key starting point. So
if you going very very far out remember
that this number is smaller than one. So
this here will become incredibly small
when n is large. Right? And so this is
the key starting point uh to prove that
to prove that if you take a contracting
map start with any point and you form
this sequence here then it's a sequence.
So now
so and I leave the rest for the
homework. Uh
now let's prove the
contracting mapping theorem
using the cush convergence.
cushion
will not prove the contracting Not going
to serve.
Okay. So what is a contracting mapping
theorem? The contracting mapping theorem
is that if t here is a contracting map.
So T g from R to R
maps R into R gives a contracting map.
Then
then T has a fixed point.
We already know that such a fixed point
is unique, right? We already proved that
it can at most be one fixed point.
Okay, so let's try to prove that. So
we're going to use like this result from
PC.
[Applause]
So I start with I start with any point
X. You pick any point you want and then
we form the sequence
where you apply this uh uh end time to
X.
Now we have that. So, so then we have we
have so this is this pie set from P
three
that a
is a sequence.
[Applause]
Okay. But then the but then from the
from Kushik convergence
we have
that
uh we have that am
is converging right that this here is
this here is a cushy sequence but the
cus convergence I'm saying that any
cushy sequence is actually convergent so
this here converts to some a
okay and now the idea is that we want to
show so want to show
that
a is a fixed
So that's
this is a kind of uh it's a you know
it's it's it's the contracting mapping
is actually extremely powerful
uh it can be used to again can be used
to solve
uh you know uh what's called o ordinary
differential equations.
And we talk a little bit about that at
some later point in the class. And but
it can also be used to solve uh PDS
which is more complicated partial
differential equation and in all kind of
other areas of math. Um and um
okay so now we want to prove that this a
here is a fixed point.
So
I
have and and we we will come back in
just a minute we'll through something
um related to this but but let me just
very simple uh so I talking about a n
here I know that it's converted to a I
then look at the sequence t of a
Well, t of a n that was a n was wrong,
right? It was just one further out of
the sequence, right? But so since a
converge, this means of course that
since
since a n converts to a n, this means
that this here will also converge to a
n. So since this here a n + one as n
become very large for converge to
okay
now
if you're looking at t
of a n
so you want to estimate now
uh so what I want to prove is right so
now I'm looking at this distance so I
want to show
So want to show we want to show
that C of A right is equal to A. That's
what we want to do.
And so if I'm looking at T of A N,
right? T of A N, this here was A N +
one. And so if I'm looking at t of a n
plus uh a n minus uh t of a
right because it is a contracting map
this thing here is bounded is lesser
equal to c a n minus a
and this is also equal to a n + 1 - g of
That was just the definition of the a +
one.
So now I have that a m converts to a. So
this means that this here converts to
zero. Right? Since so now since
a n converts to a then you have that a n
minus a you can think about this as a
sequence that converts to zero.
But this inequality here say that since
this goes to zero this in here must also
go to zero. So you see that therefore
a n + one minus t of a
goes to zero. Right? So but this but
that this here goes to zero. This just
means that a n + one this much converge
to t of a
right.
But this sequence already converts to a.
There can only be one limit. Right? So
we already had that a m + one converts
to a. But then these two numbers must be
the same. Right? So the conclusion here
is that that a must be equal to g of a.
Okay.
So from the cus convergence theorem
then you get the contracting mapping
thems
and and we already proved that there was
you get a fixed point and we already
knew that there was at most one fix
point
and so so and so this is a very powerful
idea because for many things
it's almost impossible to find the
actual
fix point. But what you do is that
you're starting with some right. So in
this case you just said you pick any X
and then you just apply the map enough
times. Right? Sometimes you would start
with a you can't
find a fix point but you can find
something pretty close to the fix point
and then then you iterate from there on
and we'll see we'll see just in a
second. which I already talked about
that this applied to the existence
of solutions to OD and to PD. And now
let me illustrate this last point.
Another example and this come backs to
your question uh about you know is this
the same but but do think about it as
being the same for all X and Y. But you
could have some kind of local statement
where it was true for X and Y in some
small range and that would be enough to
guarantee you a fix point. But but but
in general just I mean it's the same in
the definition it's supposed to be the
same for all x and y but so let me
explain that
in what's called Newton method.
So this is Newton measure
and so the idea is that you have a
function you have some function here f
maybe it doesn't look like a function
but it's supposed to this is f ofx
and you want to find where this or you
want to find points where this function
vanishes. Okay.
And so so the method is sort of a
numerical method to find such a
you know just you know if if this
function was very simple like a linear
function or quadratic function then of
course it would be easy to find but
maybe this is a very complicated
function and so you wouldn't be you
wouldn't necessarily be able to say
exactly what the point is
and so
the idea is that so Newton method
Newton method is that Newton's methods
require that you start with a good guess
and but this is the idea of the Newton
method.
So here's the idea
that we're looking at a function like
this. I'm going to assume that this is
um that is not zero. So it's actually
monotom is either increasing or
decreasing.
So I I'm assuming that there's nowhere
where the the fractional vanishes.
And then I defined a map t of x to be
equal to x
minus uh f ofx
frime of x. This seems kind of uh quite
it seems uh yeah seems far away from
now. But if you define it like this.
Now let me take the derivative of this.
If I take the derivative of this now
then I get that this in here the
derivative of x that's just one. The
derivative of this in here
um it's the this is a closing. So it's f
prime
uh times
my derivative of this time frime and
then f prime squ minus
and then uh f fp prime like that right
that's a quotion for taking
and so you see that you can write this
if you split this up into two this has
one you split it up to two this has
frime
2 / frime squ and then this here becomes
plus and then I'm writing it as f f
prime
fr
and so you see that this here cancel
with that so these are cancel so you
have that the derivative of this map
is just f of x
uh frime prime of x frime of x²
that's the derivative
and now of course
if I'm using the mean magnet
Then I have that uh derivative.
Then I have that t of x minus t of y. By
the mean man theorem say that this thing
here is the derivative
it's actually like wer theorem or
whatever but but you can also think
about this is the derivative at
somewhere in between x and y times the
difference between x and y
so We see that if we already knew. So if
we can show if we knew
that the derivative
was bounded everywhere was bounded by
some C little C that was less than one.
If you had that then of course then you
just take absolute value of this. So
then you had the t of x minus t of y the
absolute value was was equal to t prime
in this intermediate point x - y but in
this intermediate point we're assuming
that everywhere the derivative is lesser
equal to c. So this here is now this is
lesser equal to c. So c x - y and we're
assuming that c is strictly less than
one. So you see that this here if we
knew that the derivative of t was
strictly less than one everywhere then
we would know that this map was
contracting that.
Okay. But but of course you know what we
have for the derivative is we have this
in here.
And so now but now the idea is that if
you start with a really good guess
so if you start with a so so the idea is
so so idea
the idea of with Newton method
is start with a good this
like this and I'm not going to make that
too precise.
I'm putting it in quotation marks but
the idea is that you want to so good
guesses remember that what we want is we
want to find a point we're interested in
this point here where this function here
we're interested in a point where the
function vanishes right so starting with
a good guess means that you're starting
you may not start where the function
vanishes but you're starting somewhere
where where the values is really small,
right? That would be a good guess,
right?
And so start with a good guess meaning
that f at that point
is is is small
is is very small.
Now, of course, you're going to ask what
do you mean by very small? So very small
here is going to mean that the value.
So so now we have right from this here.
So we have that we have that the
derivative here of this map here
was equal to these two terms cancel out.
So this is f of x f prime of x
uh frime
of x².
So starting with a good guess means that
this thing here is really really small
and in fact I want it to be small
compared with this. Right? So if this
here is really small compared with that
then I can guarantee that the absolute
value of this is smaller than one.
Right?
And so you see that if you start with a
really good guess then it would be a
contracting mapping right and then of
course you need to prove that so you're
forming the sequence right and you need
to prove somehow you need to estimate
that you need to be able to say that
that once you form the sequence you you
know the next thing that is spitting out
is also a good guess right so that you
stay in this range of good guess, right?
And if it has this property, then it
would be a contracting map and you would
guarantee to get a fixed point, right?
But and but that's all the Newton
methods say, right? So you need to kind
of justify why if you start with a good
guess, why you keep as you're iterating
this process, why you keep in the range
of good guesses.
But but but you know the news method
doesn't doesn't tell you anything about
that but but but it require that to be a
part
and so okay so it's a contracting map
this T is a contracting map right if if
I can start with a good guess and when I
do this when I form so I start with this
good guess and then I'm looking at that
the next thing is this t of x and then I
t^ squ of x
right then and I want all of these to
also be good guesses and then I'm saying
that as n goes to infinity this here is
cons
is going to converge to this fixed point
I guess I called it x well this is the
fix point
for for t
Now,
so now we we we started with a function
and what we were interested in, we
wanted to find a root. So, x0 where this
function vanishes, right? And I
constructed a contracting map. But now I
need to relate this contracting map or
the fixed point for the contracting to
the original problem. So, what is a
fixed point for the contracting map?
So the map here
the map we defined
was g of x is equal to x - fx
over frime of x
but a fixed point fixed point. So if x0
is a fixed point
then this means that uh this here is the
same as x0 minus f of x0
frime of x0
and now you can just write. So therefore
this implies that f of x0 minus f of x0
over frime of x0 this here you subtract
x0 on both sides and this is equal to
zero but that of course means that
denominator must be zero.
So a fixed point is indeed a point where
f of x0
is equal to zero.
Okay.
Now,
um, so now we want to prove the C
convergence,
but we're going to cheat just a little
bit because we are going to deduce it
from another theorem that I will prove
next time.
So,
so to prove the component
and that's we'll prove next time.
So, what is a bosano?
So the person theorem. So the person
theorem says that every bounded sequence
has a convergent
substitution.
So that's a coal is
okay.
Now let's try to so I assume this again
I'll prove this next time. So let's but
let's
This is to prove the cush
from the
from the device. I show
kids.
>> That's fall off.
So remember the cushy convergence here
I'm saying that if you have a C sequence
then it is converted. So suppose
XN is a C.
Okay, I want to prove that it's
convergent.
But I already we already showed we
already show
we already proven
show that any C sequence
uh any C sequence
shown that XN any C sequence is bounded
right this is this earlier.
So now by therefore by the biosium
by the pano biosium
there's a subsequence
a converted subsequence
So there's a converted subsequent x and
k.
So So now
So you have
you have that uh you have that this
subsequence here convert to some x
and now I want to show that the original
sequence converts to x.
So uh so give so since
xn is accus
given
given uh epsilon greater than zero.
There exist
there exist uh capital n. So that so
that if
m and n are bigger than capital n then
uh x n minus xm
is less than epsilon
using the epsilon
in the definition of being
but now I and this let's call this the
exist n let's call it n1
So now since
x and k
converge
to x there exist
for that epsilon there exist
uh n2 uh k2 n2. Yeah. So that if uh if k
here is bigger than n_sub_2
then uh x n k - x
is less than ep 2.
Okay.
So now,
so now you just take, so now we take um
we take um n to be equal to
um the maximum
of uh n1
and n sorry and n
two. This is the one that corresponds to
right. So this is where where k is
taking equal to this n2.
So if we take n like that and you're
looking at uh n bigger equal to n and
you now want to estimate this thing here
then you can think about this difference
here as x - x n2
plus
uh sorry x n
like this minus plus uh x
x n
uh x uh x n - uh x
uh n / x terms like like that
and this here is now in this. So this is
now in this uh subsequence and so one of
them this is less than epsilon / two and
this here is less than epsilon / two and
so you get that this difference here was
less than epilon. Okay
now so this is why the balsano vastra
theorem implies a cush convergence.
Okay. So now the next thing is that I
want to give another
uh application of so of the kus
convergence. So here's another
application of the cus convergence.
Right.
So one one application was to the
contracting mapping theorem. But here's
another application of the of the cushy
convergence
theorem.
So this is the extreme value theorem.
them.
Now before I I um before I explain that,
let me
introduce uh this notion of a function
being continuous
in a rigorous way. So what does it mean
for a function to be continuous?
So a function
f say from r to r it could be a subset
of r
all of them is set to be continuous
to being continuous
at x0 at some points x0.
If
for all
epsilon greater than zero there exist
there exist delta greater than zero such
that
if x minus x0
is smaller than delta then the images
are
within epsilon.
each other.
So if you think about it, so if you have
like the function, this is a function
you you
to say that it's continuous at some x0
means that if this thing here is this
here is now f of x0.
If you take a little interval around
here, this is a epsilon interval around
here. Then there should be some delta
interval around here. So that if you're
looking at images here, then it will map
into here.
Right? That's what it means to be
continuous.
Okay? So this is continuous at a point
and a function is set to be continuous
if it's continuous at all points.
So,
so a function
is set to be continuous.
If it is continuous
at all.
And so now we have a little theorem here
and this is often useful way of thinking
about continuity.
So if
f is continuous.
So let's say f let's just say it doesn't
need to be all of r. You just have to be
careful that everything that you talk
about is in the domain. But let's just
say that f is a function from r to r is
continuous.
So if f is is continuous
uh and
xn is a sequence that converts to x
then
then the images so f of xn this is
another sequence those converge to f of
x
this is this This is a usual way of
thinking about it being continuous.
Um,
and so now so now why is this the case?
So,
so
since
f is continuous,
the only leaf that is continuous at is
x.
So since it continue at x, this means
that for all epsilon you're given
Given epsilon greater than zero there
exist
there exist delta greater than zero such
that
if
uh x - y
this is this this x here that you think
about fixed if x if you have another
point that is within delta
And uh the images f of x - f of y
this is just that is continuous at that
one point x. Okay.
Now since
since um xn converts to x right since xn
converts to x this means that if you use
this delta here in the definition of uh
convergence then uh there exist
there exist
capital n such that If x if sorry if
little n is bigger than capital n then x
n minus x
is less than delta.
But now you see that if little n is
bigger than capital n then these lies
this close to x. But then this say that
the images. So therefore the images
f of xn
minus f of x
is less than epsilon. And this was just
as long as little n was bigger than
capital n. That's exactly proving that
this sequence converts to that. Right?
So that's okay.
Now let's prove the extreme value. I
need to state that first.
And there's two versions
uh of it.
So extreme guys.
So you take a function f on some
interval a and b a real number.
They're both included.
And f here is continuous.
It's continuous at all points.
It needs to be continuous at all points
and this interval needs to contain the
ins.
So if this is continuous then
the soup of f is achieved
at some
uh x.
So meaning that soup
of f over this interval
is equal to the value
um let's say let's call it x capital m
yeah capital m for max
at some point in particular the soup is
finite right the soup is finite and it's
not really a soup it's a max Right? And
so likewise it also said that moreover
just the same thing and you could in the
usual way you could obtain it from this
by looking at the function minus f if
you wanted or you could just prove it
directly with the same that we're going
to give here. Moreover, uh the in
of f over this interval
is equal to the value at some point. So
it's not, you know, it's not just a in
it actually is a minimum where x little
m is.
And so now let's try to prove that. And
so this is going to use this theorem
that we proved this theorem and then
it's going to use uh the kushi conver
So um okay so and I'm just going to
prove like just because the two the two
there's two parts to the extreme values
the this with a soup and that's this
with in but the proof uh you know with
obvious modification
they're same
okay so I'm just going to focus on the
soup.
So, so I so I want to prove so looking
at the soup of this function I pro the
soup could be infinity. Okay. So,
usually we like soup to be finite but
let me allow this that if if there is no
upper bound then I will write infinity.
So in any case I um there exist
there exist
xn
so that xn
so that f there exist a sequence
in this domain here so that the f of xn
converge to this
of
Okay.
>> Okay. I'm allowing here and we don't
usually like this but I allow this here
to be infinite. If it's infinite then I
just mean that there's a sequence where
the value of these become larger and
larger than
right.
So I have that but now you see this here
is in this range. So this is a bounded
this is a boundary. So note that xn So
note
that xn is a boundary sequence.
So then I'm using not kushi conversion
but I use the banana vas. So it's a
bounded sequence. which I know that they
exist
a convergent
subsequent
it's a good exercise to see that this
sequence in itself you know you can just
draw a little picture and you'll
convince yourself that it this sequence
it in itself may not be convergent. But
after you pass to a subsequence, you you
can find a converging subsequence.
So it converge. So this here converge
and it converts to something in this
interval, right? And that's important.
So it converts to some to some x and I
call this x capital m.
Okay. So converging and the key point
here is that this thing here is lying in
this interval and and the function is
defined
in particular at this point. Right? So
if this had not included the end point
it converts to one of the end point but
the function would not be defined there.
So you wouldn't be able to conclude the
extreme direct but anyway. So should we
include the end point here?
Then now we have
now we have that from this theorem that
is right here we have that since this
sequence converts to that we have that
the images
converge
to sorry to the image of
X capital N right
but on the other hand this sequence here
was a subsequence of a sequence that
converts to the soup. Right? But if you
take a sequence that converts to
whatever number, then any subsequence
will convert to the same number. So this
here also
converts to to
the soup
to soup.
And so this means that these two numbers
here must be the same.
And so you should just you know it would
take you just a second to convince
yourself that everything is fine if you
know if a I didn't know that the soup
was a finite number but infinite right
that it's that is still fine but but
it's that should also take a minute to
convince yourself about that. So that
that proves the extreme value theorem
right that the if you take a function
that is continuous
and defined on an interval where the
interval include both end points then uh
the s the soup is achieved. So the soup
is really a max and the in by very
similar proof the inom is also achieved
and so both the min and max
Sorry.
>> Okay. So that was the So yeah, that's
right. So you're saying just so it was
clear enough that it was a boundary
sequence because it lying in this
bounded interval, right? So it's a
boundary sequence. Are you asking why
such a bound sequence exist?
>> So okay. So, so I just so
you have you have this function,
right? So, so like this. So, you you
take the soup of f over this in term
and so this means that that if you take
any any epsilon and you subtract it from
the two, right? Then actually there must
exist a x depending on this epsilon
there must exist so that the value at
this x is larger than this right and so
you could imagine instead of epsilon
here take looking at a sequence like
this and then this gives you a sequence
like that
and so right so that would be how and
the same when you do
and so once you have it it's bound
sequence because it's lie between A and
B, right? You're using the Banana Vest
theorem that we prove next time to get a
convergent subsequence and then you
apply the theorem this theorem here to
get that in that case the maximum and
likewise for the minimum that they
achieved.
Any questions?