Hello, everyone.
My name is Asu Ozdaglar.
I'm the head of
electrical engineering,
computer science
department, also
the Deputy Dean of the
Schwarzman College of Computing.
I'm delighted to introduce the
session on AI and the health
and life sciences.
It's a very exciting
time for this initiative
and its intersection with AI.
Advances in AI and
machine learning
are transforming not just
every aspect of our lives,
but also the fundamentals
of academic inquiry.
And life and
medical sciences are
very much at the
forefront of this
with the promise of accelerated
scientific discovery
and personalized
treatments in medicine.
While the opportunity
is clear and present,
realizing it is
absolutely not trivial,
it really requires a two way
exchange between biologists,
chemists, chemical engineers
and health care professionals
on one hand, and those at the
forefront of AI and machine
learning on the other.
And this session aims to
contribute to this exchange
by highlighting early
innovative advances from MIT
and how we can make this
aspiration a reality.
I'm delighted to introduce
our four amazing speakers.
First is Joey Davis, Associate
Professor of Biology.
Joy will focus on
structural dynamics
of multiple molecular
machines that
are essential for performing
critical cellular functions,
including synthesis and
degradation of proteins.
He will present his
recent groundbreaking work
that develops a novel
computational method called
cryo DRGN and leveraging
deep learning to analyze data
from cryogenic electronic
microscopy, which enables
to image millions of
single molecules rapidly,
but also extending this
method to determine
dynamic structures of protein
complexes directly in cells.
The second speaker is Caroline
Uhler, Andrew and Erna Viterbi,
professor of Engineering
in the Department
of Electrical Engineering
and Computer Science,
also core member of
Institute for Data Systems
and Society and Broad Institute,
and the director of Eric
and Wendy Schmidt Center.
Caroline will highlight
the big opportunity
coming from rapidly growing data
sets in biomedical sciences.
Of course, there's great
promise in understanding
programs of life, but also a
phenomenal opportunity for AI
and ML in creating
inspirations and problems
for the foundational techniques.
Of course, I think the
interesting part about her work
is that she's going to
highlight that, AI applied
to biomedical data
will require focusing
on causal mechanisms rather
than simply correlations
and forecasts, where-- which is
the focus of machine learning
in several other domains.
And she will actually talk
about the roadmap that
combines causal inference
and machine learning
to understand various key
questions in cell biology.
Our third speaker
is Marzyeh Ghassemi,
Germeshausen Development
Professor in MIT Electrical
Engineering and Computer
Science Department,
as well as Institute for
Medical Engineering and Science.
Marzyeh focuses on decision
making in health care.
And she's going to highlight
the importance of evaluating
not only model
performance, but also
the heterogeneous
performance of these models,
including biases when
a model is applied
to specific demographic groups.
She will investigate whether
the AI models currently in use,
use demographic
information as shortcuts,
and whether biased decisions
follow from such shortcuts.
But of course, with
a positive spin,
she will also tell us
how to actually de-bias
these outcomes in
a way that sort
of calibrated to each
distinct input and query.
And last but not least,
our fourth speaker
is Dimitris Bertsimas, the
Boeing Leaders for Global
Operations, Professor of
Management and Operations
Research at Sloan School,
as well as the Vice Provost
for Open Learning.
Dimitris will
conclude the session
focusing on precision medicine,
providing personalized care.
How do we provide personalized
care to every patient?
Of course, the key
here is to understand
the variation of
treatment effects
across patients, meaning how
the same treatment will affect
different patients differently.
Gold standard approach is to use
randomized controlled trials.
But of course, this
is very costly.
And we have tons of
observational data.
So he's going to present
a terrific approach that
enables the use of observational
data by removing unobserved
confounding as if
they were randomized,
thus opening really the road
to true personalized medicine.
With that, I'm a very
delighted to invite you.
[APPLAUSE]
All right.
Thank you for that
wonderful introduction.
So I thought I would
start with some slides.
Oh, do I need to advance them?
I wanted to start with a
historical perspective.
This is a quote from renowned
physicist Richard Feynman.
And he's sort of describing the
interesting biological problems
of the day.
Things like how do cells
deal with DNA mutations,
how do they perform
translation, that
is, how do they
synthesize proteins,
how do things like
photosynthesis work.
And he says, "It's
very easy to answer
many of these fundamental
biological questions.
You just look at the thing."
And I really love this quote.
It sort of captures the
promise of structural biology.
That is, if we could
determine structures,
we could inspect
those structures
and use them to infer sort of
chemical mechanisms of action
to really understand
how these machine works.
He goes on to say, and
lament, unfortunately,
"The present microscopes," and
here he's talking about electron
microscopes, "they see that a
scale that is just a bit too
crude.
If we could make
them more powerful,
many of these problems
would become easier."
And so when we think about what
he was describing at the time,
we can go and look at a
micrograph from around that era,
this is a human cell.
And it turns out all
these little black dots
you see are ribosomes.
These are the machines
that are performing
synthesis in the cell.
And when you look at
them, it's quite obviously
it's very difficult to figure
out chemically how are they
working.
What are the atomic
contacts that allow
them to perform translation?
Because the microscope
was so crude.
If we flash forward roughly 20
years, microscopes got better.
People were able to infer sort
of low resolution structures
of ribosomes shown here.
They sort of look
like clay pottery.
We got a general sense of
the shape of the molecules,
but we really still couldn't
see the important details.
So the subsequent 40
or so years of research
led to huge advancements, both
in hardware and importantly,
in software, that now allow
us to routinely determine
structures to high resolution of
important biological molecules.
And just sort of capstoning
Feynman's predictions,
I've pulled a couple
of recent papers.
Here's a complex that was solved
determining how this protein
complex repairs DNA mutations.
Our group and many others have
used cryo electron microscopy
to look at the
process of translation
and understand how these
ribosomes work in atomic detail.
And there's a
recent study showing
how one of the
photosystems involved
in photosynthesis works.
So how does this actually occur?
When we perform cryo
electron microscopy,
we're going to take a sample
of interest, typically highly
purified in one state
that you're interested in.
You'll apply that to an electron
microscope grid shown here.
And then you're
rapidly going to freeze
the sample in a thin
layer of vitreous ice
that sort of freezes the
molecules in whatever
conformation they were in.
And then we're
going to image it.
So this grid is about
3 millimeters across.
An electron microscope allows
us to magnify it up to 100,000
fold.
Here I'll show you a
30,000 fold magnification.
This is a copper grid.
You can see the grid bar sort
of separate these into squares,
and in these squares there's a
thin layer of carbon into which
we've etched small holes.
Suspended across these holes as
this thin layer of vitreous ice.
And as you actually
look into the holes,
you start to resolve,
miraculously,
individual molecules.
So these are single protein
molecules directly imaged.
How do we use them?
We're going to use very
typical machine learning tools,
such as convolutional
neural networks to isolate
the particles of interest.
We can extract those
from the micrographs.
And now we have this
sort of ensemble
of data, which is
tens of thousands
to millions of particle images.
We're going to use
computational approaches
to then align all these images.
And once we align
them, we can average
across them, which reduces
the sort of noise increasing
the signal to noise ratio.
And that allows us to now
solve these high resolution
structures.
Now inherent in this
notion of averaging
is the basic assumption
that these molecules are,
in fact homogeneous.
That is that they're all
in the same conformation.
They all have the
same composition.
Anyone that has kids realizes
realize that biology is not,
in fact, static.
It is highly dynamic.
And so we start to think
about, say, drug development,
trying to understand
what types of pockets
we might want to dock a ligand.
We can think about kids.
So here is a small
molecule docking problem.
The task is to get the
ligand into the binding site.
If you look at a
static structure,
this looks like it
should be an easy task.
And when you look at the
dynamic version of it,
there are all sorts of motions.
There are all sorts of dynamics
that complicate the problem.
All right.
So what we really want to do is
look at the dynamics of this.
[APPLAUSE]
So how are we going to do that?
We began to think about
other ways to use this data.
So typically you would
take your set of images
and infer a single structure.
We thought instead we could use
these images to learn a mapping
function.
So this mapping function
at its base level
is going to take
these images and learn
to map from some position
in Cartesian coordinates
to some density at
that same position.
We first showed that
one was able to do this.
And then later,
we realized, well,
we could modify this
function to now take
as a second input
some condition.
Say, where is this molecule
in a low dimensional energy
landscape?
How do we do this?
So this is the work [INAUDIBLE]
that also introduced.
This was done in collaboration
with Bonnie Berger's group
in CSAIL, and led by my
first student, Ellen Zhang.
We built a variational
autoencoder,
consists of two parts.
There's a decoder network
that does exactly what I just
showed you.
It's going to predict the
EM density at some position.
The way it learns to do that is
it generates these model slices,
compares them to
the input images.
If they're the same, the neural
networks stay left alone.
And if they're
different, that's a loss
that we can backpropagate
to that decoder network.
We couple that to
an encoder network.
That will map these particles
into a low dimensional space,
and you can think about
them as sorting them
based on their structures.
So the particles
get sorted based
on what they're similar
to, and the decoder can
generate structures from those.
So how do we use this?
Here's an exemplar
data set we analyzed.
This is a spliceosome.
So this is a machine involved
in splicing mRNA together.
If you look at the
static structure,
there's regions of it that are
highly resolved shown in blue.
And there's other regions that
we weren't able to resolve.
Those are shown in red.
We hypothesize that those
are likely in motion, which
made it hard to resolve them.
When we pass this
through Cryo Dragon,
we can now start to see
this molecule in motion.
You see these
dancing motions that
help you understand the
dynamics of the molecule.
So with this in hand,
we began to think, well,
if we can resolve sort of highly
purified molecules like this,
perhaps we can push
this further and begin
to resolve sort of
heterogeneous structures out
of say, cell lysates.
And we turn to translation
as a way to test this.
It was well known
that ribosomes go
through all sorts of
conformational and compositional
changes as they perform
their functions.
And about 20 years of work,
using primarily cryo-EM
has resolved key
states within this.
And we said, well, if
these states are important,
they should be
populated in cells.
And if they're
populated in cells,
then we should be able to
just put sort of cell lysates
directly onto grids,
image them by cryo-EM,
sort the particles with
something like Cryo Dragon,
to resolve each one of
these individual states.
And so I had a series of really
wonderful students and postdocs
that worked on the
technology to do this,
and I'm excited to say this
actually worked quite well.
So we can go through that
whole set of translation states
that I just mentioned.
We can see initiation
sort of building up
more and more factors
joining to the particle.
We can look at translation.
We can see tRNAs in different
states within the ribosome.
We can see these
ratcheting motions.
And again the remarkable
thing about this
is that there's no
purification upstream.
We're just putting lysates
directly onto a grid.
And we can fill out this
diagram and basically
one or two weeks of work,
versus these decades of work.
What do we really want to do?
We want to understand how
these machines work in cells.
So how do we go about that?
There's a related technology
to electron microscopy called
electron tomography that
allows us to look at structures
directly in cells.
And so Barrett Powell,
a student in my lab,
applied some of the
similar approaches
to Cryo Dragon and
particle picking
using convolutional
neural networks to try
to apply this to tomography.
And so what I'm going to
show you here is a movie.
This is a bacterial cell
imaged by tomography.
As we slice through that cell,
you'll see the sort of membranes
on the right side of the image.
All these white
sort of speckles.
Those are ribosomes.
We can then segment all of those
out to populate the tomogram.
We can then extract
all of these particles
and use Tomo Dragon
to try to find those
that are in similar states.
And there was a
little trick here.
We had actually
treated the cells
with a small molecule
named chloramphenicol
that binds to the
ribosome and inhibits it.
And what we were
really excited to see
is that the resolution of
the maps that came back
were high enough for actually
to see the small molecule
drug bound.
Oops, jumped ahead there.
So this is a small
molecule therapeutic
bound to its functional target
image directly in cells.
With that, thank you
so much for your time.
[APPLAUSE]
I'm super excited to be here
and see this establishment
of this HEALS Collaborative.
I think it's really exciting to
see all this vibrant community
come together here and see
all the collaborations that
will actually come out of it.
So I'm here to talk to you
about the unique opportunities
that I see at building this
two way street between machine
learning, AI, and the
biomedical sciences,
and why I believe that the
life sciences are not only
uniquely suited for
being one of the greatest
beneficiaries of research
in AI, but actually also one
of the greatest
sources of inspiration
for foundational
developments in AI.
So in the life sciences and
the biomedical sciences,
we've seen a huge
data explosion where
we're now able to
measure the same system
in many different modalities.
Think of single cells where
we can, in one experiment,
measure the activity
of all genes
at the single cell level in
a million cells at a time.
Or all of the
imaging data where we
can image at subcellular
resolution, cellular resolution,
tissue scale, organ scale,
even whole body scale.
And we have all
these biobanks where
we have access to
health data of millions
of individuals combined
with genetics data
of these individuals.
So I think the real
power here comes
from thinking about
how to integrate
these different views
of the same system
into some joint space.
And so that's really where
representation learning,
the field of representation
learning in AI
comes in, where you're trying
to identify information
about all of these
different modalities
and combine them into
one view that is most
informative about the system.
And so that has
unique opportunities.
You can think of multimodal
biomarkers that better capture
a disease, because
it can combine
all these different views.
Or you can think about
the opportunities
for experimental
design to think about,
what is information
that is actually
captured by different
types of measurements?
Say a cheaper measurement,
easier to obtain measurement
like a heart ECG, or a
much harder to obtain
and more expensive
measurement like a heart MRI.
If you have shared information,
I could just translate from one
to the other.
Or what is information that
is really only contained
in a particular measurement,
like a particular protein
stain, where you really need to
get that measurement in order
to get that information out?
And maybe you can
go even further.
In the life sciences,
generally, we
care about getting at the
underlying mechanisms,
moving from just
associations and biomarkers,
actually moving on to
mechanisms and causality.
So maybe multimodality can
actually help us there.
And so that's the question
I want to talk to you about.
But before-- let's
make the case.
And I think I
probably don't even
have to make it
here-- for why we
need mechanisms and causality.
So let's take a simple example
of fibrosis, where it's still
a disease that actually has
a huge effect on mortality.
And there is still no drug
that can revert fibrosis.
Now, how do we think about
identifying drug targets
in this setting?
Well, we need to identify--
and I should say, fibrosis
is when the tissue stiffens.
And so what you want to
identify are genes proteins
that are upstream.
So causal of tissue stiffening.
And not genes,
proteins, that are
associated with
tissue stiffening,
but are downstream of it.
Because these would be
very bad drug targets.
So it's really critical to
understand what is cause
and what is effect.
For example, for identifying
a drug candidate or protein
candidates in this case.
However, if we're thinking
about the current AI models,
they generally fail
miserable in causal tasks.
And so here I just want to give
you a very, very simple example.
So we all know that good
warm weather and sunshine
is a cause of increased
ice cream consumption.
Right?
But if you now go out and
you have a gloomy cold day
and you give out a whole
lot of free ice cream,
well, you're increasing ice
cream consumption artificially.
That doesn't change the
weather, because weather
is upstream of it.
However, if you ask Dall-E so
OpenAI's model for generating
images from text, and you
should all do this experiment,
you ask it to draw an
image of an ice cream stand
where they're giving
out ice cream for free.
It always puts good
weather in the background,
because there is a really
strong association between ice
cream and good weather.
And these models are trained on
learning based on associations.
They are not trained on
trying to identify what
are the causal relationships.
But that's critical,
as I just showed you
in the previous example.
We need AI models that can
actually reason causally.
And that's exactly
the types of questions
that we're working on in my lab.
So how do we?
What does it mean to fully
understand the mechanisms
in a biological system?
So I guess
traditionally we would
love to get to these pictures,
these amazing pictures here
by Davidson, for example, of
really understanding fully
how one gene protein turns
on another gene protein,
maybe even knowing all the
differential equations above it,
and really having this
full causal picture.
Now, the framework for thinking
about these regulatory networks
causally has been already
developed in 1920s by Sewall
Wright.
And so that has been like--
the field of causality has been
a very, very vibrant field
basically since the 1920s.
Now, in causality, actually,
until now, basically, there
has always been one very
important assumption.
That we know what the
nodes of the network are.
So say we assume they are genes,
and we have data on the genes,
like the activity of all genes.
And we would like to infer
the regulatory relationships,
these causal edges
between the genes.
But I'd like to argue that in
all modern problems in the life
sciences, we actually
don't even know what
the nodes of the network are.
Like let's take the example
of cholesterol, for example.
Where for a long time we
thought that total cholesterol
was one causal variable.
Well, now we know
that's not the case.
We actually have two causal
variables, LDL and HDL.
And they have different
causal effects.
So we don't actually know.
We have to learn what
the causal variables are.
Similarly in images, pixels
are not causal variables.
We have to learn what
the causal variables are
in any of the imaging data
sets that we're collecting.
Is it the shape of
the cell nucleus?
Is it a particular protein,
and where it is localized?
Is it how much of it is
So we have a really more
fundamental or really new
foundational
question in AI, where
we have to first learn what
even the causal variables are,
and then from there go
on and actually learn
the causal networks among them.
So over the years, we've
taken on this problem
and really thought
about how, or identified
that actually having
access to multiple views
of the same system, so
different measurements
or different data modalities
on the same system
can really help us understand
the underlying latent
causal structures.
So why is that?
Well, so let's think about what
is hard about understanding what
are causal relationships
is you need
to sieve out all kinds
of spurious associations.
So multimodality can
help you do that,
because we're looking for--
or a causal relationship
in the system
as an intrinsic relationship
should be there,
whether you're
looking at the system
from the left, meaning
with measurement type 1,
or from the right meaning
with measurement type 2,
or from the top or
from the bottom.
So in order to
really identify what
are these causal relationships
or causal features,
you should be looking for
what is invariant to how
you're looking at the system.
So trying to understand which
information or what information
is really shared between
different modalities
can actually help
you get at causality.
And so that's really
exciting because we
have all these
different measurements
of the same biological system.
And so we're always thinking
about, well, how can
I identify what
is actually shared
between these
different modalities?
And then actually
learn from there.
And so I just want to end with
one example that we're currently
working on in ovarian cancer,
where we can, for example, think
about, well, what is shared
among abundant pathology images
that we have access to, and
newer and much more expensive
spatial transcriptomics
data, and actually
see that there is a lot
of shared information.
It's actually possible to
translate between them pretty
well.
And you can not
only identify what
is shared among
different modalities,
but also what is shared
or specific to particular
individuals or patients.
Now, that's a really
important problem.
Anyone here who has worked
with, say, transcriptomic data
or basically any
patient data knows
that if you look
at these data sets,
you have such big batch effects
that basically every patient
always looks its own Data Cloud.
So it's very hard to see
what is actually shared
and what is specific to
a particular patient.
But if you just use these
multi-modal causal features,
you can directly identify, in
this case, cancer niches which
are specific to a
particular patient,
and other cancer niches
that are actually shared
between different individuals.
And identifying these
cancer niches, as we know,
is really critical for
informing therapeutic strategies
down the road.
So I hope I was able to give
you an example of showing why
I think it is so important
to build this two way
street between AI and
the life sciences.
I think that like RA
Fisher, was motivated
to develop modern statistics
based on applications
to agriculture and to breeding,
I think here we have the life,
the modern life
sciences is really
going to be a driver for new
foundational questions in AI
that will really inspire maybe
even deeper types of questions
that we have seen so far.
Certainly that's the case
in the field of causality.
So thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
Hi, everyone.
I'm Marzyeh Ghassemi,
and I'm going
to talk to you today about the
pulse of ethical AI and health.
My lab is the Healthy
Machine Learning Lab at MIT,
and we focus on
evaluating whether there's
a need for machine learning
in a health care setting.
Developing a robust private
and fair model if there is,
and then potentially
deploying that model,
understanding how people
might use that model for good.
What I'd like to
start out with--
and there will be a
quiz later, so remember.
You're all going to--
its final season at MIT.
What I'm going to start out with
is the first learning, which
is at this point, maybe based on
the presentations you've already
seen, you should know
that with some caveats,
we can predict or
generate almost anything
if we have the right data
and the right models.
These are two really
fantastic examples
of AlphaFold for
protein folding,
and robust prediction
of breast cancer risk.
And in both of
these cases, these
were tasks that we
weren't very good at.
And that machine
learning really improved,
transformed the practice in.
That's really exciting.
How do we do that?
Well, the way that
we do this now
is by following this pipeline.
This is pretty well established.
We choose a problem, collect
some data, define an outcome,
develop an algorithm, and then
potentially deploy that model.
And if I walk you through
this for another prospective
application, let's
say that I want to do
X-ray triage at a hospital.
So if you're healthy I
want to send you home.
How would I do that?
Well, I already
picked the problem.
And so I would go out
and get some data.
There's three really large,
publicly available chest X-ray
data sets in the US.
Over 700,000 images.
I would train a model.
Here I'm training a type of
convolutional neural network
to predict no finding,
which means you're healthy.
And then I would look at what
the performance of that model
was.
And here I get an AUC of 0.859.
That's really high.
Random is 0.5, 1 is perfect.
So this is a really good score.
And many people
don't just stop here.
They go all the way
to FDA approval.
And in fact, there's now many
hundreds of FDA approved devices
with AI/ML in them
that are being
deployed across a wide range
of clinical subspecialties.
This is really exciting.
But the second thing
to keep in mind
is that predicting or
generating something,
well, for the average,
especially in health,
is not good enough.
Why?
Let's go back and
pick on my own work.
That performance
right there, 0.859.
That's really good.
But that's one number.
What happens when I see
the individual performance
numbers for different
subgroups of patients?
When I do that audit, I find
that this model underperforms
in female patients, young
patients, Black patients
and patients on
Medicaid insurance.
And actually, if you exist in
an intersectional identity,
if you're a Black or
Hispanic female patient,
then you do significantly
worse than if you
were a part of a larger
aggregated identity.
And this is happening in part
because medical data is really
complex, and you can
infer just by looking
at somebody's medical note
or their medical image what
their demographics are.
What their biological sex is,
what their self-reported race
would be.
And this is even when you
don't give this information
to the model.
This is also in situations
where we've tested doctors
and they can't tell based
on the medical image
or the medical note.
And so what this means is that
it's actually pretty complex
to make a model optimal
in a high dimensional,
multimodal setting.
How hard could this be?
Well, let's take a look.
Medical imaging is one of the
spaces where AI is applied
to most frequently in health.
And so we looked at
a couple of settings
where it's frequently applied.
This would be for a chest X-ray
based diagnosis for dermatology
and for ophthalmology.
And in each of
these cases, we're
trying to predict an
important clinical outcome.
And we want to look at
how poorly these models do
in different subgroups depending
on how we optimize the model.
The first thing we found is that
the more that a model secretly
learns in the layers to encode
your demographics, for example,
that you are
female, the worse it
does at predicting the clinical
target for that subgroup
that is minoritized, in
this case, female patients.
Put another way, if
you're training a model
to predict pneumonia,
and it learns who is male
and who is female, it will
predict pneumonia worse
for female patients.
We then tried to
fix this, and we
found that if you take data
from hospitals in Massachusetts,
train the model and
force it to be optimal,
meaning all the way on
the bottom right hand
part of that plot, very,
very performant on average,
and on the bottom,
very low fairness gap.
Then when you test the model
on patients from Massachusetts,
it does really well.
And so that means modern
machine learning strategies
can be locally optimal,
if you deploy them
in the settings at
their trained in.
But that's not how we train
machine learning models
right now, even when
they're approved by the FDA.
We train them in Massachusetts.
They get approved, and then we
invite the world to use them.
And when we take this model and
we throw it over to California
and ask them to
test on their data,
we actually find that optimal
fairness doesn't transfer.
And this has important
policy findings for the way
that we audit models
and evaluate them
before they're approved in a
local setting, for example,
state to state.
And this gets even
harder when we
think not just about
deep learning models,
but vision language models.
Everybody's used a
vision language model,
I would assume at
this point, for fun.
As Carolyn said, they can give
you really interesting results.
And they're really good, not
just at image generation,
but they have been
used in medicine
and clinically adjacent tasks
for zero shot classification
and zero shot retrieval.
And they're very
good at these tasks.
But it's also been
pretty well established
that they have these
problematic human biases in each
of these settings.
For example, they always tend
to generate male doctors.
And one of the reasons
it's really hard
to de-bias these
models is because we
have a really simplistic
approach to thinking
about their mind space.
And so here, if I wanted to
de-bias a vision language model,
much of the existing
work assumes
there's a direction for male,
there's a direction for female.
Draw a linear projection
and collapse that down.
It's fair.
But actually these
models are reasonably
complex and non-linear.
And so maybe the direction
for male and female doctors
is very different than the
direction for male and female
pilots or managers.
And so in order
to get past this,
we actually have to
think about doing a more
complex, non-linear approach.
And so in recent
work, what we did
is looked at a zero
shot retrieval example
where we want to get
a picture of a doctor,
and we want that to be unbiased
between male and female image
generation.
So when I ask for a
doctor, maybe my query
gets embedded right
there at the star.
And if I did a
traditional de-biasing,
I would just project a line,
find this middle point between
these two spaces, and
say, "Now I'm fair."
But you can see here, because
it's complex and non-linear,
I'm still closer to all of
these pictures of male doctors
than female doctors.
So I would still just generate
a picture of a male doctor.
Instead, we propose an
approach to bend your debiasing
in the direction of the
complex non-linear space.
And so don't stop here.
Move along this
surface until you're
at a place where you're
equidistant from male and female
images, in this case.
And this is nice because
approaches like this
require no fine tuning of
your vision language models.
So you can just use a
vision language model
as it comes to you.
And they can be
tailored to de-bias
for existing or new
queries that come in.
The last thing I
want you to remember
is that good models,
even if we de-bias them,
they don't necessarily guarantee
that we'll have good outcomes.
And so we have a lot
of work in the past
that's shown that the
losses from poor AI
can be larger than the
gains from good AI.
And so we have to be really
careful that these models are
trained well.
We know that doctors are
susceptible to poor advice,
even when they have expertise.
Here we showed radiologists
incorrect advice
for X-ray images, and they
were still fooled by it.
And finally, we
have work showing
that the way that you
deliver bias content
is more convincing sometimes
than the bias content itself.
So if you tell somebody to call
the police on minority patients,
they're much more likely
to listen to it than if you
say there's a risk of violence
at an equal rate for minority
patients.
So we need to pay
careful attention
to how we deliver
advice from models,
not just the advice we give.
And so the four things you need
to keep in mind as you build
models along this pipeline
are, we can predict,
or generate anything.
But doing well on average
is not good enough.
We need to know that making
models optimal as complex,
otherwise they already
would be that way.
And good models won't
improve outcomes.
Instead, we need to move
forward with creating
actionable insights
in human health.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Thank you and good afternoon.
Very glad to be here.
What I would like
to talk to you about
is an area that occupied
my thinking for many years.
And recently with
two of my colleagues,
we have made some progress
that recently appeared,
meaning recently in the
last month in nature
digital medicine.
So what is the story?
As many of you
know, of course, is
that the golden standard in
medicine and many other fields,
of course, is to do
randomized clinical trials.
For more than 100 years, this
has been the name of the game.
However, RCTs are very expensive
and often last very long.
Also, while RCTs,
the conclusions
are suitable for
the average patient,
they may be not appropriate
for not the average patient.
So there is a need
to identify a way
to understand what is
called heterogeneity
of treatment effects,
namely more personalization.
In contrast, observational
data are very widely available
and inexpensive.
One would argue that the cost
of developing a new drug,
which currently is of the order
of between one or two billion,
is definitely affected by the
fact that we have to do RCTs.
So what is the
challenge on this idea?
The presence of
confounding bias.
Confounding exists, especially
in observational data.
This is exactly the topic
that RCTs try to address.
At the same time,
RCTs, while strong
in identifying whether a
treatment works or does not
work, they do not define
effectively patient subgroups.
In other words,
they don't typically
personalize treatments.
There has been some
progress of what
is called one
variable at a time,
but I would say quite limited.
So what is the purpose
of this effort?
That we propose and
demonstrate using
one clinical example,
and later on many,
but I only have time for one.
A framework to reach
clinical conclusions
based on observational data.
And this is data that
we used in collaboration
with Memorial Sloan Kettering
that one of my collaborators
is from.
So in other words, we
can now have an approach
that can lead to medically
valid conclusions
based on observational data.
The second is that even
if we insist to use RCTs,
we have a way of
personalizing the RCT.
In other words, from an
RCT, you can actually
get personalized information
of how treatment should
be appropriately personalized.
So in my view, this
leads to a way of--
which is, in my
opinion, something
I have tried for a long time
to utilize observational data
than RCTs for
precision medicine.
So let me tell you, get
you a sense of the story.
We have some patients that
have a particular cancer,
of a particular type
of tumor, what's
called GIST,
Gastrointestinal Stromal
Tumor, that MSK specializes
in the observational data set.
So these patients have
already undergone surgery.
And the question
is, are we going
to give them a particular
chemotherapy called imatinib?
By and large today
in the world, we
offer imatinib as
a way of doing it,
even though there has been some
studies that suggest that there
are patients who don't need
it, and therefore would
have benefit by avoiding it.
So what is the data
that we do have?
So for each patient we
have some covariates,
or what is called
[INAUDIBLE] count
the tumor site and the tumor
size potentially others.
And for every one
of these patients,
these are observational data.
We also know whether the
treatment was applied,
whether imatinib
was given or not,
and whether or not
the patient recurred.
So we have the
data, the treatment,
whether the treatment was
given, and whether reoccurrence
happened.
Of course, there is confounding.
What is the notion
of confounding here?
That the treatment was
not randomly assigned.
So patients who were predicted
to have worse outcomes typically
tend to get the treatment.
So these are not--
this is not a randomized trial.
So the very act of
having the treatment
has a higher baseline
risk of recurrence.
So which is the key difficulty.
So what we try to
do, I will briefly
tell you, the key idea
of how to overcome that.
There are two components.
I will only have
time for the first.
But the key here
is to take a model,
take a machine learning model.
Take only people who did
not receive the treatment,
and build a classification
model of whether they
are recurring or not.
Notice that this is
only based on people
who did not get the treatment.
Then apply the model for those
who did take the treatment.
So now for every one
of these patients,
we have a probability
of recurrence
for both types of patients.
But the patient was only
developed for those patients
who did not--
I'm sorry-- did not
get the treatment.
Put them in buckets.
So now let's say we put them
in 10 buckets between 10%.
So within these buckets,
we have patients
that have similar
probability of recurrence.
Some of them got the treatment.
Some of them did not.
And then at the same
time, we try now to
in each of these buckets,
there are say 10 of them,
we try to make them in
each particular bucket
so that they are as
if it were randomized.
And how do we achieve that?
We try to use optimization.
We try to match the
characteristics from the data
that we have so that
patients within every bucket,
that includes both
treated and untreated,
are similar in these
characteristics.
And we use
optimization for that.
The specifics that, you
would not follow it.
I would not have followed
it if I were you.
So key here is that we
have a methodology now
that we, in each
of these buckets,
we are able to match
their characteristics.
Just to demonstrate the
process of confounding,
the process of the left.
The data on the left
shows the survival
among those who took
the treatment and those
who did not get the treatment.
And you observe that people
who got the treatment
are faring worse than the
people who did not get,
because they are healthier.
After the matching, after
this optimization process,
there is still confounding
involved, but it has decreased.
So there is remaining
confounding even
after this optimization.
So what we do as
a second step is--
and to demonstrate
the effect is that,
so this is the graph on the left
shows the percentages of people
in each of these
buckets who have
similar probability
of recurrence,
but who took the treatment and
who did not take the treatment.
What the optimization does
is on the right, in which we
have the same number of people.
So we actually delete patients
from the observational data,
but we don't delete
random patients.
We delete those patients so
that the remaining patients
are very similar in their
characteristics, as well as
the probability of recurrence.
And then as a final step, we
also, because as I mentioned,
there is a confounding
left, we actually
train a model where
we artificially
increase the weight
for those patients who
received the treatment who
did not have recurrence.
So the model tries to
make better predictions
for those patients
with a larger weight,
since this yields
greater improvement.
And when we are-- so in a way,
we clean the data in such a way
that we try to subtract
confounding from the data.
And then as a final step, we
apply machine learning technique
called optimal policy trees,
that was developed in my group,
to be able to personalize
the treatment.
And here's the effect
for patients from MSK.
So you can see that
although you might not
see the exact
personalization, you
observe that when you
look at a particular,
let's say the mitotic count,
if it's above a certain level,
you prescribe the treatment.
If it's is below a certain
level, you do other things.
So this is definitely
a personalization story
on the observational data.
So how do we know that
it has some benefits?
We actually took completely new
data, unseen data from Poland.
And in that particular
data we have observed
that while the sensitivity
of the trial data and ours
is similar, we were able
to actually find 7%--
the personalization
helped us spare
7% of the patients who
would not have benefit
from unnecessary treatment.
While the result is
relatively modest,
it shows that there is a
benefit by the personalization.
This is just on-- and
this is unseen data.
I mean, a completely
different study.
My final point is how to
now personalize trials.
So this has been so the benefit
of radiotherapy for patients
with what is called
truncal sarcomas
has been demonstrated
in two major trials.
So MSK, as many
other institutions,
utilize a radiation
therapy after surgery.
So that's more or less
the key therapy today.
However, it has been
reported that many patients--
some patients might
not benefit for that.
So applying a
similar story-- this
is now not observational data.
This is randomized
data for which we
don't know how to personalize.
So this data does not have
the effect of confounding
because it's randomized trials.
So we do the optimization
and this other part.
And we also find a
personalized treatment
on the randomization data.
So this is a general purpose
randomized clinical trial
that allows personalization.
And then we try this
approach for data from MSK
that are different from
the clinical trial.
The original-- the methodology
was trained by the randomized
clinical trial data in that
happened in the early 1980s.
And then we utilized the data
from MSK observational data
over 16, 17 years.
We have found that the
approach is equally
effective in
protecting patients,
but spares 15% of the
patients that need not--
they didn't need radiotherapy.
And therefore, the
personalization
helped in improving that effect.
So of course, since then
this was the original paper.
We have tried it in about
10 different studies,
from cardiology to oncology,
to other areas of medicine.
And we have found
across the board
that a benefit by the
personalization in studies
outside of the data we have.
So in summary, what I would
like you to remember from
this is that the area
of trying to find
an approach for personalization
just on observational data
is, in my opinion, a very
important aspect in medicine.
We hope that the approach is
definitely-- would definitely
help how to change
medical research,
and also perhaps improve and
decrease the cost of developing
therapies around the world
in a way that provides
a road to precision medicine.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]