Hi everyone and welcome to the AI and
open education and initiative speaker
series.
Again, you are here at professional
education and the judicious use of AI
which is part of the AI and open
education initiative speaker series.
Welcome.
My name is Sher Seagull and I am the
collaborations and engagement manager at
MIT Open Courseware. I am also one of
the planning committee members of the AI
and open education initiative at MIT
Open Learning. In order to meet the
moment of remarkable growth of
artificial intelligence and to examine
its benefits and challenges to the field
of open education, last summer, MIT Open
Learning solicited rapid response papers
from stakeholders around the world to
articulate how generative AI might
accelerate or hinder the promise of open
education. An international jury of AI
and open education experts reviewed 147
submissions and published nine
thought-provoking papers by 32
researchers on the open platform pub
which you can find via the link in the
chat.
This initiative and today's speaker
series webinar is generously funded by
the William and Flora Hulet Foundation.
We want to thank Huelet for their
ongoing support.
Today's session is the first of two
webinars in the initiative speaker
series. Today's topic is professional
education and the judicious use of AI.
Our next webinar on May 12th is on AI
literacies and evaluation and we'll put
the registration link for that in the
chat.
Please note that today's session is
being recorded and will be openly
licensed as an open educational resource
that will be openly available to people
around the world. We invite you to shape
the narrative we are having about AI and
open education and help us navigate the
terrain for new directions and new
questions. So, please add your voice and
let your critiques, concerns, and
enthusiasm be heard. You can do so
through the Q&A function throughout
today's session. Put your ideas in the
Q&A as you have them. Rest assured that
we will circle back to your comments and
questions later in this session. You're
welcome to let us know your name, role,
or affiliation in your comments. If you
do not want your name referenced in
today's recording, you can post your
questions anonymously.
An overview of today's structure is as
follows. First, I will briefly introduce
today's speakers. Then our respondent
will contextualize this moment for us.
Third, the authors of the two
spotlighted papers will provide a
high-level overview of each of their
papers. This will be followed by a
discussion with the authors led by our
respondent. And finally, we will open
the discussion for your comments and
questions.
I'm thrilled to introduce today's
speakers and papers. Clint Loland is
today's respondent and he is the
director of open education at BC campus.
BC Campus is a government-f funed
nonprofit organization that provides
teaching, learning, educational
technology, and open ed support for the
25 publicly funded postsecondary
institutions of British Columbia. In
2013, Clint was instrumental in the
launch of the BC open textbook project
and currently oversees the operations of
the provincial open textbook repository
and their open publishing platform.
The author of our first featured paper
is Dr. Aarim Aya Sheili Bakova. She is
an associate professor of strategy and
the founding director of the center for
teaching excellence at University Canada
West. She's also a PhD candidate in
edtech and learning design, pursuing her
second PhD at Simon Frasier University.
She's a multilingual educator from
Kazakhstan whose research focuses on AI
powered instructional design, inclusive
faculty development, and knowledge
mobilization in diverse linguistic
contexts. She's the author and editor of
numerous policy papers and four books.
The links will be in the chat. Her paper
is addressing challenges in faculty
professional development UDL training
through AI enhanced OEER in a
non-English context.
One of the co-authors of today's second
featured paper is Dr. Royce Kimmons.
He's an associate professor of
instructional psychology and technology
at Brigham Young University. In his
work, he seeks to end the effects of
socioeconomic divides on educational
opportunities through open education and
transformative technology use. He is
also the founder of edtechbooks.org
and other sites focused on providing
free highquality learning resources to
all. The other co-author of today's
second featured paper is Dr. Tori Trust.
She's a professor of learning technology
at University of Massachusetts Ammerst.
Her work centers on the critical
examination of the relationship between
teaching, learning, and technology, and
how technology can support teachers in
designing contexts that enhance student
learning. She has written and designed
several open educational resources, many
of which have had millions of views. She
is also the author of five books
published on the edtechbooks.org site,
and we'll put those links in the chat
for you. Now I'll pass the baton to our
respondent Clint Loland to contextualize
this moment for us.
>> Thank you very much Sherah and thank you
for inviting me to participate in this
event today. Uh I am joining you from
the traditional territories of the
Lquangan speaking peoples of the Songhes
and Esquyimal nations also known
colonally colonially as Vancouver uh
island Victoria British Columbia to be
exact. Uh thank you also to MIT open
learning uh for sparking these
discussions and launching the rapid
response papers looking at the emerging
relationship between open education and
generative AI. Uh as Sarah Schwetman
says in her preface for the collection
of responses we are at a moment where
quote AI is entering the public
consciousness in a big way and reshaping
how we learn, communicate and
collaborate. Uh end quote. Uh and as
with any new technology, there is both a
promise and a peril. Or as media
theorist Neil Postman famously said,
every technology is both a burden and a
blessing. Not an eitheror but a this and
that. And this means for every advantage
that a new technology offers, there's
always a corresponding disadvantage. Uh
the disadvantage may exceed the
importance of the advantage or the
advantage may well be worth the cost.
Generative AI may be a new technology,
but the reality is it's no different in
this regard. There are both burdens and
blessings, promises and perils. Uh which
is what the rapid response papers
address. Uh in the papers we can see
both the promise and the peril, the the
fouian bargain of technology as Postman
calls it at play once again. uh and it's
this tension that we're hoping to
explore a bit today uh and in this
speaker series in our discussion of the
papers. The collection of papers is also
quite unique in that they specifically
speak to Gen AI within the context of
open education. And now there's been a
lot of discussion about AI and education
in general, but there's been maybe less
so looking at the specifics of AI within
the context of the unique affordances
and consideration of open education and
open educational practices. Um so for
those of us who are deeply committed to
open education and open educational
practices
uh uh and and the values that are
embedded in those practices things like
fairness and equity social justice
access autonomy for both students and
faculty uh critical digital pedagogy
collaborative practices knowledge
construction and co-construction I think
these papers are are very welcome and I
think a much needed addition to our
field. Uh, and if you haven't done so
already, uh, I would urge you to take
some time to explore all the papers in
the collection. Uh, I'm going to hand it
back to Shar. I'm going to be back after
the authors have done their
presentations and facilitate a Q&A with
the authors and I hope you enjoy the
next hour.
>> Fantastic. Thank you so much, Clint. So,
I will now pass the baton to Dr. Sheili
Beova uh to discuss her paper um
addressing challenges in faculty
professional development UDL training
through AI enhanced OEER in a
non-English context.
>> Thank you. Hi everyone. Thank you Shira
for a kind introduction and Clint. It's
great to have you as our respondent. Um
and warm thank you to the MIT open
learning team Sarah Hansen and Sarah
Schwedman and to the HLET Foundation for
supporting this initiative. Um, it's
been a quite a learning process for me.
Before I begin, I want to acknowledge
that I'm joining you today from the
traditional and unseated territories of
Seyamu First Nations here in White Rock,
beautiful British Columbia and grateful
to be here. Uh, today I'm presenting a
paper that actually grew into the core
of my doctoral research. uh a localized
AI enhanced UDL based open educational
resource created for non English Kazak
speaking educa educators. When my
daughter heard this title for the first
time, she was like mom what a coded
language you are talking what is UDL o
so many abbreviations we'll talk about
that today. Uh next slide please. Um
this work began through the reach
project. So I want to contextualize um a
bit. Um it's a multi-country initiative
led by Dr. Robert Williamson at Simon
Fraser University. It was funded by
Canada's Sherk and a reach focused on
inclusive education for displaced and
refugee children with disabilities
particularly in Jordan, Turkey, Canada
and Kazakhstan.
uh Kazakhstan joined from the start this
project but not because of a formal uh
refugee population they had but because
of this unique humanitarian situation.
Um back in 2019, Kazakhstan government
launched a humanitarian Jusan operation
that repatriated around 600 citizens
including 413 children from former ISIS
controlled territories and refugee camps
in Syria. and um 19 of those children
were resettled in the western Kazakhstan
Ataro region. Um although I had moved to
Canada back then, I remained closely
connected to Atrao State University
faculty and colleagues where I had
previously served as vice president for
strategic planning and international
relations. And earlier in that capacity
I initiated this um platform kids
university a community-based open
learning uh for rural uh children like
from rural regions and uh it became a
sort of an early form for me um of
localized open education grounded more
in social connection and institutional
support. I had to study different
experience of different kids
universities around the world and try to
localize those practices. So when this
reintegration of repatriated children,
displaced children from Syria, that
support was needed, the faculty, the
team at at university naturally turned
to this space to kids university because
it was safe, it was working, it was
trusted and we included them into the
reach project to support that inclusion
um to the um children with disabilities.
But as the reach project progressed, it
became clear that the real challenge
wasn't the children in the first place,
but was the readiness of the people
trying to help them. Faculty were
committed um but lacked some training,
digital fluency, um no English language
skills to be using the resources in
English. So there were no resources,
open resources in Kazak. So um I began
offering some fragmented workshops
mostly around UDL framework and um
artsbased strategies but I saw that we
needed more of sustainable um solutions.
Next slide please. So that's when the
idea took shape. We saw that well we've
developed a UDL based open resource
asynchronous course in Kazak that would
educators learn from about inclusion and
how to um adapt it. So um a resource
that they could use flexibly in their
own language and at that stage there was
no AI. I was translating myself using
sometimes Google translate to help but
it was not really helpful. So we had to
adapt um again culturally pedagogically
uh considering Kazak traditions of
pedagogy as well. I reflected in my
paper that much of the global literature
on UTL and open education is in English
and embedded in western assumption about
technology and access and that
disconnect made localization not just
important but essential and critical.
Next slide please. So in early 2024 I
began exploring generative AI tools a
bit cautiously. Um and actually the main
excitement was could they help
accelerate that localization
um save my time with translation uh
generating some visuals um but with
cultural care. So I experimented with
Chad Gupt for drafting D for um visuals.
Yes chat there was a Kazak GPT chatbot
that saved a lot of time as well. I was
inspired partially by the Ludia it's UDL
plus AI chatbot also and I saw the
potential there to make it more
accessible. So um this re overall the
course uh that uh we've I've designed
and um piloted with Ataro University was
not generated by AI but it was designed
with this instructional design model
successive approximation model um and
SAM as its author Michael Allen reminds
us is not just about speed being fast
being reiterative it's about listening
so um that's what this project became
became uh a sort of act of pedagogical
listening through language design and
response. Next slide please. So we chose
UDL and um I just quickly want to share
the anecdotal part about translating
actual concept into English universal
design for learning. Um and it proved a
bit difficult. It's always tricky with
those concepts. Um so machine
translation gave us ambabo
and here ambab which is more of
convenience store type of universality
and uh balao is more about um to pro
projecting um or outlining or drafting.
So after consultation we had with some
of the doctor in philology at that state
university. Um I we made decisions. So I
I kind of was my decision but um I
relied in on the feedback as well to
keep uh universal part univers as it's
an international term and also design
part because we also have that term in
Kazak. So uh universal
design uh but yet as you see uh I kept
UDL in English abbreviation in brackets
in English and that also another was um
another strategic decision here. Hard
one um because um I thought that it
would be a hybrid that preserved um both
local clarity but also global
recognizability.
So faculty could recognize it in English
language, conferences, resources or
books UDL and um use AI tools to
translate those resources because they
now know that it's about UDL. So uh I
would call it conceptual bilingualism,
the way to build both sort of
familiarity and fluency across that
academic scholarly context. Next slide,
please. I will probably skip it. is just
another example of the translation and
localization. U it was quite a
challenging part as well. Another
resource that we used was this again
Kazak GPT that saved so much time
because I started designing my own Kazak
Jet GPT and then thought well let me
check maybe some other smart people
already done it before me. So uh and
voila there was this free resource. Next
slide please.
So uh the course had 95 completion rate
uh among 25 faculty and um it was
unusually high to be honest. I was
surprised um for asynchronous
professional development which is um
like nobody really tracks the progress.
Uh so far we had the precourse survey
and after course survey anonymously and
knowledge scores again we've seen
increased 60% were those faculty who
attended my previous fragmented
workshops during the reach project so
they knew something about UDL that was
really also um like rewarding to see
that uh and the increase was to 85%. And
so there is a lot more to work on and
faculty actually shared that it
reflected their realities. They felt
that it was not translated or decoded
from other language. So here I felt like
localization doesn't just increase
access but it's also about connection or
um to the content. Finally, next slide
please. The lessons I drew actually a
lot more but I I thought the most
important ones I would share today is
that localization is um foundational
um not optional. It's important that we
um start with the design uh on mind and
it shouldn't be an afterthought. Um
second AI integration requires critical
human guidance. Yes. Um AI accelerates,
it supports localization but it cannot
lead it. And finally inclusive design
requires institutional support. Um I
mean we had to get support from the um
Atra State University's um
administrative level also to have access
to their IT resources so that it is
hosted on their platform as they helped
us with the access to articulate rice
platform where we designed the first
interactive uh elements of this course
and um it's important that professional
development isn't only inclusive but
also available and institutional support
is the key. And last slide, please. Um,
so that was a rapid response paper. It's
still going on. Uh, it was my first
pilot project I was excited about. At
the moment we have two more uh
universities in Kazakhstan who are
interested in hosting this uh course and
uh I assume for my doctoral dissertation
I would want to have a larger sample of
respondents and so um look forward to
include more but this time um the
platform sustainability is um
challenging and it's quite expensive
sometimes in those areas so we are
exploring now simpler tools like Moodle
maybe or Google sites
uh to keep resources open and replicable
and in future I hope uh it will grow
into sort of community of practice among
Kazak educators whose this course
actually um brought together and thank
you for your time and listening to me if
there is one takeaway from my talk today
it's this inclusive design does not
begin with AI or frameworks it begins
with the people and the language we
choose to design for and if open
education is truly to open then AI must
serve as a bridge not a gatekeeper uh
enabling educators to build resources
not just in many formats but in many
voices as well. Thank you so much.
>> Beautiful. Thank you so much. Uh we
really appreciate it. As you um are
thinking of your questions and comments
um and ideas, please do put them in the
Q&A and we will come back to them near
the end of this session. Uh so I would
like to pass the baton now to Dr.
Kimmons and Dr. trust who will talk
about judicious AI use to improve
existing OEER.
>> Thank you Shar and I'm delighted to be
here today and what an incredible first
presentation by Ya that I really
enjoyed. I am presenting alongside uh my
co-author Dr. Royce Kimmons and on
behalf of our other co-author Dr. George
Valencianos
today and let's go ahead and jump in.
Next slide please.
So, generative AI technologies are
powerful tools, but they come with
significant costs in terms of financial
costs. Just last week, a CEO of Open AI
said using nicities like please and
thank you, cost the company upwards of
tens of millions of dollars. and
thinking about the environmental costs
of these tools, which are quite
substantial. Unfortunately, many of the
developers of AI technologies aren't
very transparent or clear about the
environmental impact of these tools.
However, when looking at Google's 2024
sustainability reports, it showed that
there was a 13% increase year-over-year
in greenhouse gas emissions since
totaling 48% uh since 2019. and they
attributed that to increase in um data
centers and need for power in those. The
same report also noted there was a 17%
increase in water use uh totaling 6.1
billion gallons of water which is more
than 9,000 Olympic size swimming pools
um and water in that case is often used
to cool down data centers. Some
researchers have also tried to make some
estimates about the environmental cost
of these tools. One group of researchers
found that generating an AI image, one
or two AI images, takes as much
electricity as charging your smartphone.
Another group of researchers found that
getting AI to provide medium length
responses, about 10 to 50 of them, takes
about 16 ounces of water, which may not
seem like a lot, but then when you
multiply that by the hundreds of
millions of users of these tools data
daily, it's a quite a significant cost.
and also the fact that many of these
data centers are housed in towns that
they are now taking electricity and
water and other resources from the
residential supply. Uh these tools also
have several other ethical issues in
terms of their accuracy um you know
hallucinating information and have
exacerbated the digital divide um
between those who have access to these
tools and know how to use them and know
how to think critically about them and
those who do not. So, I'm gonna hand it
over to my co-author here, uh, Dr. Royce
Kimmans to talk more about judicious
uses of AI.
>> Thank you. So, um, as has already been
mentioned, AI came into kind of this
critical consciousness of everyone or
um, for the vast majority of people with
the advent of specifically chat GPT um,
but chat bots specifically as an as a
type of AI. And for that reason,
whenever we talk about AI, whenever you
hear a new presentation about AI, most
of the time, uh, it's going to be about
chat bots. And that's true in education,
it's true in every field. Um, and so the
kind of knee-jerk reaction that we've
had to AI and across lots of disciplines
is, oh, we can use AI now to do some
exciting things. Let's throw chat bots
at our problems and see what happens.
Um, the problem though, well, one of the
problems is that chat bots require a
high level of literacy as Tori
mentioned. They also require a lot of
energy. um more than a lot of the other
kinds of AI or uses of AI that we often
deal with. And so what we what I would
what we would refer to as a
non-judicious use of AI um specifically
when it comes to OAR is to um embed a
chatbot or to throw a chatbot at a
learner and just expect the chatbot or
the learner to be able to interact with
the chatbot in a way that is beneficial
to the learner. Like going back to Ya's
example, um giving a learner a chatbot
and asking them to localize OAR for
themselves, right? Um, now there are
other options or other ways of thinking
about this. And so what we're framing
here is what we refer to as a judicious
use of AI. And what this means is that
instead of putting the a having the user
or the learner interact directly with
the AI, are there high value things that
we can have AI do that we then store, we
save the results of what the AI has done
and then we distribute those to learners
at scale. So this requires three steps.
First, we identify impactful
improvements to existing OEER that can
be accomplished with AI. And I'll sh
share some examples in a second. Then we
use AI to enact and store those
improvements in a finite typically
one-time manner. So if we use AI to
localize some content, we store that.
And then the third step, we release what
we have done under a new as OAR
themselves. So we efficiently serve
those improved materials to learners at
scale as OEAR. Next, next slide, please.
So our context for doing this is um
edtechbooks which is an open textbook
publishing platform. Um just a couple of
a little bit of information about the
background for this. So this system um
is very intentionally open. It's very
intentionally available to everybody. Um
there are no log in or access walls.
Currently we serve our content to over
one and a half million users across the
world every year. Um we have over 200
published books about 8,000 published
chapters. All content is automatically
converted into PDFs and Microsoft Word
documents as well. So they can be
accessed offline and all content is also
converted to high-quality audio books
using AI. Um and that audio is stored so
that people throughout the world can
access um audio versions of these this
content as well. And so when thinking
about how can we use AI to improve this
kind of an OAR resource, well, if we
have one and a half million users
accessing our content, we don't want one
and a half million users using chat bots
to to get content that they need. Why
can't we just figure out what our users
want, use AI to to create that and then
re-release that to them as OEER in a way
that is more efficient and more
sustainable. Next slide, please. So
we'll give uh four examples of of how
this plays out. So one is simple
glossery. So if we want learners to be
able to define terms that they come
across, we can use AI so if someone
clicks on a term, AI will define it. But
what we don't want is AI to have to
define this term a million times. So if
a million people don't know what an
abduction is, for instance, we don't
want AI to be called upon a million
times to define this. Instead, what we
can do is we have the author decide what
they want defined. So they create a
glossery. They use AI to create an
initial um an initial definition for
this. And then we serve that definition
up to all users. So that makes it more
sustainable, makes it lower cost and
also allows the human so in this case
the author to have control over uh have
a quality assurance control over that
definition. So that uh for instance
we've come into we've had examples in
the past and you've seen many papers
written about this about hey how AI is
biased, how AI replicates even things
like racism and sexism in and what it in
what it provides to people. So by
allowing a human in this case the author
to come between the what the AI
generates in terms of the definition and
what is provided to the learner it
allows the the author to take control of
that and to ensure that content that is
being provided is unbiased and and so
forth. Next slide please. Another
example
is in the form of learning checks. So um
we can have an AI go through content and
maybe after every couple of paragraphs
it it discerns what is the core content
of this paragraph and it creates a
multiple choice learning check that then
is stored as static HTML and with some
JavaScript layered on top that is then
efficiently served to all learners. So
you don't have to have an AI to ask so
that every learner doesn't have to ask
an AI to help me find what are the key
points of this of this content. We do it
once and then we provide that to all
learners so that all learners can can
benefit from that learning check whether
or not they have access to an AI. Next
slide please.
Um the audiobook example that I already
mentioned audiobooks doing high quality
audio with an AI actually takes a ton of
energy um and it takes a a lot of time
even with a high-powered machine. So if
you were to have uh a learner for
instance in the Philippines click on an
click on a chapter and have AI translate
it into audio for them that would be
hugely expensive, use a ton of bandwidth
and um just not be sustainable. Um so
what we do with audio is whenever a book
uh a book a chapter is edited or updated
we have AI go through and create a an
audio version of that. And some of these
chapters the audio ends up being um an
hour and a half long. Like these are
huge audio files. Uh it takes a ton of
energy to create. But we generate this
once we store it in efficient storage
with like Amazon S3 that then can be um
mirrored across multiple sites across
the world so that it can be easily
accessed um at multiple points across
the world. Um and so we're generating it
once but we're able to deliver it to
thousands or millions of learners at
scale. And next slide please.
And one final example is translation.
Um, so instead of having learners have
to have like a an account with chatgpt
or something like that to translate
content for them that they come across
in an OEER, why can't we bake that into
the o the the system itself so that in
our case we're translating all of our
content into English, Spanish,
Portuguese, Chinese, and then those are
made available to all learners who come
to the content. So it's translated once
by AI and that initial translation is
costly but once you scale it across
thousands of us owners who are accessing
it the cost per user is is negligible it
the and so the return on investment is
is it approaches infinity because at
some point you create this resource and
then it's available to everybody and
then last slide. So um to compare these
two, non-judicious use tends to be very
expensive to scale versus judicious use
is inexpensive. Um judicious use uses
less energy um and has resulting in much
lower economic or ecological and
economic impact because learner AI
interaction is visible. Uh so like in
like the case of the glossery, the
author can see what the AI is providing
before it's provided to the the learner.
So the author can step in and make do
quality assurance on it. The so AI
responses can be audited, verified and
checked for quality. Those AI responses
are available to everyone. So it's there
isn't an there's no equity concern where
only some people have access to enhanced
resources because they have licenses
with specific AI tools. No, because the
AI uh results are generated and stored
and then shared with everyone. They're
equitably available to everyone and it
requires low bandwidth and can be made
available offline. And so if we create
like for instance an audiobook version
of a chapter or um generate other like
translations of chapters, learners can
download those and access them offline
without having to have persistent access
to like chat GPT for instance.
>> Fantastic. Thank you so much. Um so I'd
now like to invite Clint to have a
larger conversation with ya Royce and
Tori. Um and that will last probably 10
15 minutes or or so 15 minutes and then
we will um come back to your questions.
So do make use of that Q&A function uh
and let us know what questions or
comments you have as you are thinking
them.
>> Great. Thank you Shar. And I I uh I want
to start with you and your project
because uh the localization work that
you did reminds me a lot of the
localization work that we did in the
early days of the BC open textbook
project way back in 2013. Uh one of the
one of the challenges we had when we
started our open textbook project here
in British Columbia was taking US-based
textbooks and contextualizing them and
localizing them for a Canadian context.
And I can tell you it was difficult work
and I really wish we had access to some
of the tools that you did when doing
this kind of uh local localization work.
But I you know as you note um using AI
was not without its challenges to do
localization. And the one I want to hone
in on is the linguistic barriers with AI
translation as I think this might be a
good example of a type of uh cultural
bias that we might find in AI tools. uh
in your paper you noted that um
translating resources while preserving
pedagogical integrity requires more than
direct translation. I wonder if you can
expand on that a little bit. Why was the
direct translation inadequate and how
did you work around that?
>> Yeah, thank you so much Clint. I really
appreciate you naming that experience
with textbooks localization. It
resonates deeply with what we
encountered. But we had AI and all those
tools that supported this process that
made it way easier even fun. Sometimes
we were um juggling with different
dialects and terms um and um in sort of
educating and training AI as well. So
one of the most consistent challenges we
faced was um not just linguistic really.
It was more cultural um and um AI and
machine translation tools. Um Google
translate that was the first thing they
used. It was uh more familiar to faculty
uh involved. Um they often carried more
of that implicit cultural assumptions
already embedded in the source material
whatever they were using. So as I
mentioned in my um today's talk um
universal design itself like seemingly
neutral brought up some unintended
associations with translated directly
into Kazak like ambib which more used
like in my childhood we would say ambib
store which is universal store uh
convenience store. So technically it
worked but culturally it undermined the
integrity of the concept. Um that wasn't
also the translation issue exactly as
you said um around the cultural bias the
idea that uh what is neutral in English
may carry different weight in other or
tone or authority in another language
when it translated um directly. So all
these biases um um magnified by this
machine translation at the same time uh
if used without reflection or review
from um human judgment um may lead to
sort of um not even confusion but
misrepresentation or worse unintentional
um reinforcement of cultural
hierarchies, right? what we call through
this geese of open access but yet we
wanted really to that it sounded
natural, respectful and pedagogically
coherent. So educators do not learn
something new but rather review what
they have been doing with these new
tools or new approaches. So we brought
really I've involved um a lot of
feedback from uh faculty at at
university. I'm very grateful to them
here. Um uh we even asked some of the
educators from different regions of
Kazakhstan where we would have some
dialect. So we wanted the term would
resonate with someone in western
Kazakhstan as well as in south
Kazakhstan where I'm from. So we uh
wanted to we had to actually to think
about those uh pecularities there and it
was not only about clarity. I think for
me it was more about credibility.
Thanks. So to get around some of what
you were finding, it sounds like you
definitely had humans in the loop kind
of reviewing the work that was coming
out and the importance of having people
still involved checking the work I think
is something that I also picked up on in
uh Royce and Tori's paper too. The
importance of humans in the loop and
having oversight. I think you mentioned
uh human quality assurance is essential
to correct AI hallucinations, errors and
misinformation. And so Tori and Roy, I
want to bring you into the conversation
here and just maybe tell us some of the
ways that you're thinking about how to
address this in your work to ensure that
there are humans in the loop. I can
start briefly just from an author
perspective. So I have written several
books on the edtech books platform which
are open educational resources OEARS and
along the way Royce has been adding in a
lot of different features which I always
love to try out in my books. Um, and at
one point there was like an AI generated
abstract and I'm talking one of my books
has like 700 pages cuz I have a
co-author who just loves to write
nonstop.
Um, and so,
you know, I don't have time to go
through and write an abstract for every
single one of those chapters.
But when I had the AI generated version,
I was like, ooh, this is not like fully
capturing what happened in this chapter.
Um, but it's a starting point. And so
for me, I found it helpful that it like
it put text on paper for me then to work
around and revise and figure out what is
the most important part of this chapter
I want to include in this abstract
rather than starting from a blank page.
Uh, and I do think that helped speed up
the ability to include abstracts. And um
but I do think there had to be a human
in the loop in that process because the
AI I don't think ever created an
abstract that was fully accurate and
correct for any of the chapters um its
very first try. And that's we know how
these tools work. They're they're
predictability machines guessing which
words go together. Um so you have to
have that human aspect and that's what
Royce has really built into the
edtechbooks platform.
>> Yeah, just to build on that. So it's
it's it's accuracy, it's quality, it's
speed, but it's also contextualization
too. Um that's one of the things that AI
struggles with a bit. Um I mean if you
especially if you're not providing it
with deep understanding of the context.
So if I'm writing to elementary school
teachers for instance, that context is
going to be very different from writing
to a group of professional engineers and
and what I convey, how I convey it. And
so, um, allowing the a using the AI to
create kind of a boilerplate or a
beginning, uh, kind of outline of what
this looks like. Just getting something
on the page is really, I don't know,
encouraging as an author because then
it's easier to edit. It's easier to go
and adjust than it is to just stare at a
blank page. And so, that that applies to
abstracts. It applies to like glossery
terms. Um, and and and even beyond that
too, that to things that are more
strictly created entirely by the AI like
audio books. um you know just being able
to go and listen to it and make sure
that you know you're you're happy with
the way that it sounds um is is an
important step. And I guess translations
as well translations are a bit tricky
because um if when we like for instance
if I translate my content into 10
different languages I I don't know all
10 of those languages. So um we have
built in the ability for the author to
go in and edit what the the AI has
generated and is now providing in those
different languages. But unless I also
collaborate with people who speak those
languages or that can help me um uh
engage in quality assurance with those
languages um then even though I I'm
there as the author I'm not able to do
much or I don't even know what to do. So
so there is so part of it is how we
structure our relationships with the AI
by by putting the author between the AI
and the learner but part of it too is
thinking about what resources and
literacies are needed to the author so
they can can actually engage in quality
assurance. the AI has generated results.
>> I want to circle back to that literacy
piece in just a moment here, but first I
want to I want to talk a little bit
about the environmental aspects uh in
your paper uh and the environmental cost
of using generative AI because your
paper raises the environmental cost as
really being a serious social justice
issue. Uh and I think there's a real
tension especially for us in education.
I mean we're feeling this pressure to
perhaps use these tools. we're seeing
some of the benefits of using these
tools, but we know that there there are
steep costs to actually using them. And
and this is kind of a big question, but
I mean, how do you think we go about
reconciling that tension between the
benefits of generative AI and the
environmental costs that you talk about?
>> Well, I think Tori brought brought to my
attention just uh recent research on
even how youth are using AI, right? So,
they use it for information seeking
primarily. So, for instance, if they
don't know what the word abduction
means, they'll go to chat GPT to ask it
what abduction is. Well, doing that
using a a chatbot, specifically like the
the newest versions of the chatbot, like
if you're using a 4.1 or something like
that, you're going to use more 10 times
more energy than if you did a Google
search, which is going to use 10 or 100
times more energy than if you just went
to Mariam Webster and did it and
actually typed it in there. So, um, or
had had a dictionary in your operating
system that you're using. Um, so I mean,
super easy. I'm I'm on a Mac. Just hit
command space and type in a word and it
uses the built-in dictionary to define
it for you. But youth do not know how to
do that. So, that's a literacy question
which we can talk more about later. But
I think part of what it speaks to is
just that we don't understand what our
tools are good for and what they're
efficient at and what is like because
there's cost associated with everything
that we do with them. We don't know what
is what is a legitimate cost. Is it it's
is it really um desirable to use this
much energy to define a word that I
could just easily find a definition to a
different way? And so I think so much of
it is, you know, there's the literacy
aspect, but there's also just like for
those of us who are creating tools or in
positions to um provide resources to
people. Hopefully, we're not falling
into that same trap where we're not just
throwing a you know, oh, I need to
define terms. Let me throw the newest
version of chat GPT at it which I know
is going to be super resource intensive.
Um there are lots of different large
language models out there. Lots of them
are more efficient than others. So for
instance in our current onet books in
our current use of the glossery and the
abstract feature we're using llama 3
point I think it's 3.2 but we're using
the the three billion or the three
billion parameter model which is much
more efficient than than the the the
kind of flagship llama is 70 billion.
And I and I don't know know what the
chat GPT model current GPT models are
right now. If you're not an AI person,
what that just basically means is a
three billion parameter model, you can
run it even like on a pretty, you know,
mid-range like laptop. Um, if you wanted
to, it's not a super intensive model to
run versus if you're running cutting
edge models, uh, you need a super high
performing machine that it's going to
use a ton of energy. Um, I actually have
a super high performing Mac Studio uh
under my desk here right now that is
constantly running stuff in the
background because I'm analyzing data
and I can feel the heat coming off of
it. Um, uh, and so I have to have the
air up higher in my office. So, I'm
creating an ecological concern here
within my office just using how I'm
using how I'm using AI. But, um, but
using more efficient models and I think
using models that are that are kind of
that are designed for the kinds of
things that we're after. I don't need to
throw a 70 billion parameter model at a
simple definition task. Um, and by not
doing that, I'm I'm drastically saving
cost. I'm drastically saving um
ecological impacts.
>> It's interesting that you mentioned
that. I mean, one of the things I I use
a large language model, but I've been
working on a locally hosted large
language model. So, I've been using a
tool called LM Studio and running models
just on my desktop because that's one of
the ways that I kind of feel okay about
the environmental impact of of using
large language models is if I can at
least run it locally on my laptop, then
I'm not, you know, relying on huge data
centers uh to power the the work that
I'm doing. And it has been it has been
one of the ways that I've been kind of
managing that environmental concern and
I think maybe holds out a little bit of
hope for uh uh for you know the the sort
of more basic queries that we tend to do
or that that as you mentioned youth tend
to do on uh on the large language
models.
Um, I want to stick on the technology
piece a bit and just talk a little bit
and and I know uh Rory, you talked
Royce, you talked a little bit about um,
Lama and I I do want to come back to
that, but I mean the I want to talk
about the technology choices you made
for both of your projects because I
think the technology choices kind of do
paint a complex and really a very
realistic picture of the kind of mix of
open and proprietary tools that we often
have to use in open education projects.
So a let me start with you here. Can you
talk through some of the rationale for
your technology choices for your project
and and is there anything that you think
you might have done differently with
your technology choices?
>> Um yeah that was the tricky part. Of
course the easiest one was chachi as uh
our colleagues at other university also
had started experimenting that um but
let's say for translation like Google
translate was the first um intuitive way
like to go exactly for English the ma
matching the um terms. So when um I
started to explore AI tools, I think um
I looked for those who had free access
in the first place. So uh faculty back
in uh Kazakhstan context wouldn't or
university wouldn't have burden like to
pay for those things. Um I didn't have
special funding for that. So it was all
voluntary pro uh like a volunteering
project for us. So um it it should be
free uh at least for a trial period for
a couple of weeks or months that even
would be helpful and uh because it was a
very um speedy process we wanted to be
fast and um prototype fast based on this
SAM model that I followed for
instructional design. So and a
technology that um at that moment was
mainly accessible uh was through the
open AI platform definitely uh we've
tested with PO uh another platform where
we looked specifically for um their like
approaches what kind of data um they use
or how they process it um
in that context what's interesting um
not the um like ethical or privacy
issues they pop up later on with the
faculty as they started to learn more
about the technology. So um and we
didn't have a clear criteria for which
would be the best or how even to access
or assess that uh technology um uh I
think uh the start was the very simple
like free accessible easy to use in any
language um and helpful. So
>> wonderful. Um, if I may interject,
there's a handful of really juicy
questions in the Q&A. Um, so we're going
to go ahead and start with Vikram Singh
who asks how to use judicious AI in the
case of dynamic content.
>> Yeah. So it's a great question. Um, the
short answer is we have to build systems
that allow us to do it. And it's similar
to uh just modern web approaches. So,
um, if, uh, so, so going back in time to
when we first did when I first built the
the alpha version of edtech books, I had
nonAI tools that I built that would
generate PDFs of all the content on the
platform. And so, the issue was, yeah,
dynamic content like authors are
adjusting content continually, but we
want to provide a static version of it
as a PDF. And so, my brilliant thought
was, let me just have the the web server
generate the PDF every time someone
wants to access it. But the problem is
the amount of energy to generate a PDF
out of that dynamic content is it's
really heavy. And so when you have a
hundred people try to do it at the exact
same time, your server fails very
quickly. Um and so but it's a similar
kind of thing with AI in the sense that
yeah, you have dynamic content, you want
to create like static snapshots of it at
different times um that then you provide
efficiently to people. But so you just
have to figure out when is it
appropriate to take one of those
snapshots. You don't want to create a
snapshot every single time. Like say
someone wants a translation of your
chapter. You don't want to create a
snapshot every single time someone asks
for a translation. Maybe when you when
you edit the content, you make a
significant edit, then you flag it, and
then it creates um then it creates a
snapshot of it that is that the AI uses
as to create a translation that it
efficiently serves up. Um but you have
to create kind of what those milestone
stones are. Decide how much of a change
to the dynamic content uh merits
regeneration with the AI or or or re
reinvolving the AI. Um, so that's always
challenging. Yeah. So like in terms of
like the audio like very concrete
example in terms of like the audiobooks
that we generate, if someone goes on and
corrects a typo, I'm probably not going
to regenerate the entire audio book for
that for that chapter just because a
typo is changed in the text. But if
paragraphs are added or something like
that, then yeah, we'll we'll initiate a
rebuild.
>> Wonderful. Thank you.
Our next question comes from Muhammad
Sed and the question is in the context
of professional education, how can
institutions ensure that AI tools used
for assessment and feedback are fair,
transparent and free from bias,
especially when serving diverse learner
populations?
>> Yeah, thank you Muhammad. Um that's um
really critical question um especially
in the context of professional education
definitely where assessment shapes often
shapes access to opportunity and if
institutions want to ensure that uh AI
tools used for um assessment and
feedback are fair and transparent
especially for diverse learning uh
population the first step at least what
we've learned and observed from our
experience igrants is to recognize that
bias is not a technical error there and
it's often a reflection of uh whose
language norms um learning behaviors uh
the system was trained on. And one of
the lessons um that specifically um
stood out uh for my colleagues um there
is that fairness requires human context.
We discussed that um specifically at the
level of design um and it's not enough
to translate just rubrics or adapt
instructions
um institutions here we really wanted to
um
prompt them to think were these models
trained with us in mind right um no
obviously in the beginning so um we
recognize that culturally relevant let's
say expression of knowledge that's
something that um even The feedback when
the feedback was given um the um we we
we should be aware that the feedback was
maybe um based on western assump
academic writing conventions or
unfamiliar terminology or a different
logic of argumentation that is um alien
to that cultural or context. Right? So
um and that feedback will not be
actionable. So therefore um for us um
was to get the feedback and again
translate it quote unquote to the um
management of the university who were
observing the project in a way that um
it also um supports that learning and
helps them to improve. So um here that
building human uh in the loop validation
I think it's very important um being
able to interpret AI uh behavior or make
AI behavior interpretable. So faculty
and um staff should be able to see that
what's the model is evaluating or and
why. So the clear explanation reasoning
um is important and um have a feedback
again not as a design opportunity not
just a measurement output if it's a good
project or a good course or a good um so
uh we need to u not to guide learning
across uh context um like not only
through that direct feedback again so
for institutions to be aware of that
it's important Beautiful.
Thank you.
>> Um, our next I just want to get as many
questions in as possible, but please
Rice, go ahead.
>> Um, I just want to mention just
auditability is super important for
this. So, one of the big problems with
AI is that you put in your input and
then you get output and there's just
this huge black box. You have no idea
what happened, right? Um, and so one of
the ways to help alleviate that, so like
I'm in a former life, I was a a high
school English teacher. So, if I wanted
a AI to give me feedback according to my
rubric that I've created for student
essays, if I say, "Here's the rubric.
Here's a student essay. Give me
feedback." Well, the essay has lots of
different components to it, right? And
so, the feedback I'm going to get is,
you know, it's just this really messy
black box. I don't know why it's saying
what it's saying in all these different
ways. It may not even remember all the
criteria that I gave it. Um, and it just
gets lost very quickly. Um, and so one
of the kind of the general best
practices that that I've uh uh come to
realize is that when you're working with
AI, it's better to be it's best to be as
discreet as possible and what you're
asking it to do. Um, so instead of
asking it like one omnibus prompt like
do this thing and it does this huge kind
of blackbox thing in the background and
you get the results and you have no idea
where this came from. Ask it more
discreet things. Ask okay instead of
like feeding in my entire rubric, feed
it one element of my rubric. how did it
rubric how did it do on this specific
thing and then you get that feedback
because it's easier to audit on very
specific small black boxes than on a
huge black box right and so by
separating it out like that it allows
you to audit and to do quality assurance
more effectively
>> ties into some of the other questions I
think the next question is from Jessica
Glla and her question is I appreciate
the examples of judicious use could you
recommend where to find data on learner
interactions with AI to help anticipate
learner needs and preferences and
support the judicious use of AI with
open educational resources.
Um, I'll just say most of what we do
comes out of um kind of op priori
assumptions that we're making about
learners based upon instructional
design. Um, so like what do we already
know students going to want? So that's
one way. Another way is using learning
analytics um and and just UX um like
gorilla research with with our learners.
So um as learners uh read through a
chapter we have a quality assurance
rating at the at the bottom where they
can rate this in five stars or one to
five stars and then we get feedback from
them like what what would they want or
as authors request things what would
they want um so there's no like single
place to go but I think that yeah
looking to UX research on like what what
are high impact things we can do for
learners to help them looking at
instructional design research to do that
as well but then also having some kind
of a mechanism for feedback back to help
us to know what is it that our learners
wish that they had or maybe our learners
are going through all of our OEER and
copy pasting all of it into chat GBT to
get a cliffnotes version of it. Even
just knowing that they're doing that is
super valuable because then we know okay
that's a use case that would be use that
that we should be able to provide to
them that would um eliminate a lot of
this waste and redundancy of if if we
have multiple users doing this.
>> Fantastic. Thank you. Um, I think we
have time for one more question and it's
actually from another one of the authors
from the rapid response papers and I'm
not going to pronounce their name
correctly but I will do my best. Um,
Joel Alberto Arantes do Amaral asks,
"The environmental impact is one of the
unintended consequences of AI use that
is largely overlooked today. How can we
make these impacts more visible?"
So, this is
this always continues to surprise me, I
guess, because I'm in the the AI and
education world and early on learned
about the environmental impacts. And so,
when I talked to someone about it who
said, "I had no idea." I was just
talking to a reporter last week. It was
like, "I had no idea there was
environmental impact." Um, and then on
the other side, there's people who
literally won't use AI because of the
environmental impact, and there's
everyone in between trying to figure
this all out. I want to contextualize
this really quickly in the last minute
or so. um right now like the you know
global impact of of data energies um
data center energy uses is like 1.5% of
the global energy. So it is a it is an
impact and it's expected to double but
it's not like um
massively huge in destructing our
environment just yet. Um, I do think
though it is something we need to pay
attention to and I would love for chat
GPT to say before you prompt this might
take this much water, this much energy.
I don't think any of these companies
will do that because that will ruin
their profit margins. Um, but maybe an
an AI tool will come out. Um, just like
you know Eosia for internet searches can
show you how much like trees it's
planting or carbon dioxide it's reducing
from the environment. So, I would love
to see that more, but right now I think
it comes down to AI literacy. A lot of
this comes down to AI literacy and
preparing people who use AI to think
critically about what are the unintended
consequences of these tools. Um, because
that's really important impact on
society.
>> Well, that's the perfect transition for
me to thank you all because our next
webinar is actually about AI literacy
and AI evaluation. So, um, deep
appreciation and thanks to all of our
speakers today, uh, for joining us, for
writing your papers, for doing your
work, and for having this public
conversation. Um, we're really eager to
continue the conversation. Um, and thank
everyone for I just want to thank
everyone for attending today. This is
really exciting. Um, and you can sign up
for um, for updates of the initiative.
And, uh, and we'll sign off uh, here at
3:00. So, thanks so much everyone and
we'll see you next time.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Shar. Thank you everyone.