my name is Sunan I'm glad to present
efficient multimodel large language
model on edge devices so on the right
hand side is a data center with a lot of
GPU uh servers the image is not real
it's generated and we are proud to U be
able to run this uh model on a laptop
the model is called
s so we need efficient AI Computing uh
we see on the left figure uh this is the
supply and demand of computing uh the
green is the GPU memory the red is the
model size the large language model size
is growing much faster compared with the
uh amount of GPU memory we have on the
right hand side is showing the advanced
technology noes design cost from 65
nanometer all the way to 5 nanometer the
the proportion of software is just
getting more and more expensive software
is important the cost is very high so
our research focus on using software
approach to make Hardware more
efficient this is some of my prior work
including deep compression which can
drastically reduced the model size by an
order of magnitude with pruning and
quantization these techniques has become
industry standard and a standard lexicon
in our field widely used um for
efficient air Computing industry these
days uh later I designed this efficient
inference engine which is a hardware
accelerator toward this spars and
compressed neural networks without
having to decompress it we can directly
run infuence on the compressed model so
that is the one of the top five most
cited paper in the 50 years of isca isca
is a flagship conference in our in our
field from 1953 to
2023 and recently model compression
about pruni and sparcity is gaining a
lot of momentum with a lot of
Publications uh since deep compression
was published
so our efficient ml project Bridges the
gap between the supply and demand of
computing from the following aspects uh
we co-design software and Hardware from
Tiny ml which is uh in my early days at
MIT versus large language model which is
my recent work at MIT we focus on both
dce model and also sparse model in in
fact there's a lot of opportunity to
exploit sparsely to accelerate and
compress neuron make it run faster a lot
cheaper um including using both full
precision and quantization uh from not
only 8bit to even 4 bit like nidia's
recent GPU uh the black well GPU has
this amazing feature uh fp4 using only
four bit floating point to represent the
numbers so we are showing very Pro
promising results to go with low
Precision to uh decrease the cost of
inference and decrease the cost of
training using fp8
uh we focus both on inference and
training um as the skating law continue
to um to to scale with not only on the
training side but also inference time
scating is getting super popular um in
uh recent releases from CH
GPT uh we focus not only on
discriminative model but also generative
models Genera images we we have already
done we're also working on generating
videos which is super computationally
heavy and which require a lot of gpus so
if a startup recently raised $10 million
it can purchase only a few hundred gpus
and that's it it's super expensive in
the field so making AI more um more
efficient can reduce the cost and we'll
make democratize AI to diverse field of
lives and improve the um efficiency for
the practitioners previously we have to
take a long time to train a model but
with such effic efficiency techniques we
can greatly reduce the time and improve
the
productivity and finally we focus on not
only a single modality like text but
also multiple modalities including
images videos
Etc to start with I will first talk
about large language model
quantization so quantization can map a
floating Point number into a integer or
even low bit floting Point like ip8 or
ip4 uh the challenge of applying
quantization to large language model is
that there's a lot of outliers making it
difficult to quantize we designed a very
smart idea mathematical eal approach to
migrate the quantization difficulty like
these three channels of outlier we
migrate the quantization difficulty from
activation to the weight so the
activation becomes much smoother to
quantize and the weight is also uh is
harder but still relatively easy to
quantize compared with here as a result
we can reduce the serving cost from
eight gpus to only four gpus by
switching from fp16 to in8 reducing the
memory by half while the latency is even
shorter and the principle is that 100 *
1 equal to 10 by 10 so using this way we
can equalize the quantization difficulty
between activation and
weights not only 8 bit we went one step
further for forbit quantization using
awq activation aware weight quantization
for large language model uh quantization
so we want to deploy large language
models on mobile on edge devices like on
the cars on AI PC like here we can
deploy U this coding model locally on a
laptop to write a c sort an array in a c
program and it's reading pretty writing
the code pretty fast even give you the
uh the Cod
per so the idea is that when quantizing
the uh weight we should not just look at
the weight distribution and this
activation awareness is the primary
focus uh we find by not quantizing only
1% of the channel can greatly improve
the accuracy but increasing um but using
ip16 introduces mixed Precision so we
avoid that by just multiplying scating
this channel by a larger number so
scating by two if actively can increase
the number of bits by one so for example
0.5 and one they cannot be distinguished
they both will be quantized to one but
if you multiply them by two they become
one and two now you can distinguish them
so that's the fundamental principle and
it's mathematically equal so we can have
very good accuracy while maintaining the
accuracy while accelerating the
inference by about three times the
theoretical saving is about four times
that has been adopted by Nvidia chat
with RTX to chat with RTX
laptop we also built this CH tiny chat
computer to realize uh the algorithm so
we 3D printed the compu uh the the tiny
CH computer and it's asking about the
attractions in Boston is giving Museum
of Science Harvard Square Freedom Trail
Etc and in the back you can see it's
powered by a very small Json AR Nano in
the
back so we believe such power and
quantisation techniques can enable
expensive large language model to be
deployed on resource constrained low
power uh
devices uh so these quantization
techniques smooth Quant awq has been
widely adopted by industry it has more
than 17 million downloads on huging
phase so if you're interested in
applying T awq in your products we come
to check out our uh code base is fully
released under permissive license so you
can grab it for free and there are many
companies using these techniques
including nvidia's tens RT which is a
flagship inference library for large
language model Intel neuro compressor
and Q8 Chad we collaborate IBM the
integrated for the grite also Berkeley
integrated tiny chat huging face
Transformer make St standard package and
also several startups adopted awq
now let's switch gear from large
language model to multimodel large
language model we want to handle not
only language but also Vision okay so we
want to deploy them also locally on edge
device like chess and or for example
here we can ask what is unusual about it
scene any safety concerns and the model
can understand the image saying this is
a person hiding from a rope attached to
a wind the turbo turbine engine um
there's risk of falling from a
significant height
and this is also a um in the factory
scenario we train the model and can
answer how many cars are jacked up um
there and also what color is the gloves
such kind of QA in a real time manner
running just locally on a media just
orent a mobile
GPU and what we how we achieve that is
we convert all the modalities into
tokens so everything can be tokenized
now not only language but also images we
convert image into patches and feed it
into a vision encoder plus a projector
such that we have both visual token and
text token we feed such kind of tokens
to L fine-tune the L um and make the
final
prediction and this is a homogeneous uh
approach all the techniques we invented
before like awq quation can immediately
help uh to increase efficiency to make
it Deployable on the edge so here are
some examples so how according to these
two images how much should I pay for all
the beer on the table I'm going to say
the beer on the table is a Magna which
is priced $6 each right here two bottles
on the on the table so the total should
be
$12 what's the implication of
temperature between these two images it
says Arctic eyes decreased so global
warming warmer
temperatures in healthcare it can check
the patient status it's just one model
we can do diverse
tasks and for driving scenario again the
same model that's the beauty of
foundation model you just need to tr one
model and then generalize to different
scenarios well previously we have to tr
separate model for driving inside the
car outside the car so this is inside
the car we can check the driver if the
driver is distracted is is on the phone
how many many people in the car where's
the passenger seating and the same model
can be applied to Smart Manu uh
manufacturing to check how many chip
bags are picked and uh how many how how
long does it take to pick up one chip
bag
Etc we also make this Deployable on a
laptop so we can here ask what is the
name of the painting is running locally
on a MacBook uh this is just running on
the CPU the name of the painting is
Portrait of Mona Lisa with GPU it might
be even faster and who drew this
Leonardo
DaVinci and here we ask it describe uh
the painting in
details so this is without internet um
showing the model is so lightweighted
you can have a local copy of that on
your laptop say if you have proprietary
data for your company for anything uh
this is
safe all right so so now let's switch
gear from language um to image from
image understanding to uh to image
generation which is even more
computationally heavy since we want to
gener generate each pixel okay now just
predict what is the image we want to
generate the image pixel by pixel that's
very computationally heavy especially
you want to generate these high
resolution images like here you see the
eyes you see the makeups you see the uh
the lips everything has a lot of details
like the first right here lot of details
right so high resolution image
generation consumes a lot of uh
Computing right so there are two
approach um conventionally the approach
to generate image is using the diffusion
model so using diffusion model you start
with a noise and then you directly
predict what is the noise and then you
Den Noise by subtracting the noise from
the noise and then the image will get
cleaner and cleaner finally you get the
final output that is it ative process
which is very slow we use a different
approach okay we use we didn't use
diffusion model but use the auto
regressive model which is similar to the
uh large language model when large
language model is predicting the words
Tokens The Language tokens here we
predict the image tokens so what is the
image token you can think of it as a
patch patch by patch we PR predict them
patch by patch
um but in order to achieve this we we
need to
discretize the image patches just like
language our words is discretized we
have like 10,000 words in the English
vocabulary for example that's sta usable
um such that we can use this cross
entropy laws to supervise it but image
is not is continuous right so here we
use discrete token discret tokenizer uh
such that we can pred prct uh token by
token uh and apply all the optimizations
we did before for large language model
now we can apply it to uh image
generation however directly applying the
discrete token uh will hurt the accuracy
you can imagine um everything in the
world can be tokenized the images in the
world can be tokenized into like a
vocabulary uh that's very uh coarse so
we also designed a very small
ridu token predictor using a very
lightweighted model to predict the regu
from the discrete token okay so that is
a very small model to predict uh The
Continuous ridu to help uh fill in those
details such that uh we can even surpass
some of the um diffusion models with
respect to the Quality right here by the
speed is about 7.7 Times Higher faster
compared with diffusion model here are
more examples this is a boy and a girl
for in Love on the left hand side is our
heart model it's Auto regressive model
heart for hybrid Auto regressive
Transformer and on the right hand side
is the diffusion models uh playground
pixel art act stable diffusion is right
here second image full body shot of
French woman photo photography French
streets and this is ours it's a blurred
in the back very good artistic style uh
versus this is playground pixel art
stabil diffusion
XL last one is drawn views of waves
crashing against the rugged cliffes in
the BX sir again it's showing very good
quality and the most amazing thing is
that we make card so small such Auto
regressive model is very friendly to run
on the laptop compared with iterative
diffusion models so it can run a 4090
mobile GPU uh just in seconds we can
also change the
prompt uh to draw something an astronaut
riding a horse on the moon in fungal
style and here is a dog that has been
meditating all the time it takes just
seconds to generate un images it can be
applied to different scenarios and uh
for example for uh advertisement for
Branding for anything that require image
generation
uh feel free to try the demo at heart.
it.edu uh we make it fully open sourced
under permissive license so feel free to
grab it for
free all right so another technique is
the auto encoder which is a very
important component for image generation
using diffusion models so here we go
back to also acceler diffusion models
and we find conventional model have a
very poor quality when the compression
ratio is high and here we not only
compress the model but also we want to
compress the images remember the image
will be converted into tokens right so
in the future uh you plug in electricity
and token will come out right token in
token out but token is a very important
resource the more the tokens the more
the computation and the more money you
have to pay so compressing the token is
super important but compressing the
token will lead to very poor quality so
here is a very important very uh
effective token compressor called Deep
compression Auto encoder that can uh
compress the image by 64 times um in
each side so 4K 64 by 64 is 4K
compression ratio Al together while
conventional work can only compress to
eight times f8 indicate eight times on
each side well we can well maintain the
perplexity of the rfad all the way to 64
or 128
times and this is by applying uh deep
compression Auto encoder to diffusion
model uh we can accelerate it here from
very slow like 17 images per second on
the right hand side um it's 19 times
faster 335 images per second and we
compress the token so you have a much
smaller uh latent space compared with
previously a 64x 64 large lat space you
have to generate a lot of tokens now you
can generate only a few tokens more
lightweighted um compared with the
original uh
tokenizer and we applied uh this
tokenizer to build this saana a high
resolution image generation model so we
very proud to generate 4K resolution
photos um and make it about 100 times
faster compared with the flux flux is a
very popular probably the most popular
model these days for image generation uh
we accelerate by 100 times with a deep
compression Auto encoder using a linear
diffusion
Transformer uh with cural fusion and
flow based DPM
solware so these are the images
generated by S of only 1.6 billion
parameters it'll be open source very
soon so stay tuned
uh these are more images generated by
S all right so given the limit of time I
will uh conclude my presentation today
finally I want to mention all the
techniques we discuss today is
incorporated into my course called
efficient
ml. covering efficient inference
techniques pruning quantization NE
architecture search distillation
efficient training techniques and also
application specific optimizations for
large language models and generative AI
feel free to check it out it's also uh
on
YouTube and finally here are some
library of our lab uh photo gallery of
our lab uh including the mcet on my
microcontroller awq on device LM and
sping chips and many mobile uh
demos thank you
[Applause]