[Music]
I'm Carara Miller. And I'm Rob Stoner.
And from the MIT Energy Initiative, this
is What If It Works, a podcast looking
at the solutions for climate
[Music]
change. Today, we're going to examine
how the world's most populous country,
India, is thinking about clean energy
and how policy shifts in the US might
affect their trajectory. But first, a
story about environmental degradation
versus well, cold hard cash and the
kinds of experiments you have to do to
understand how to alter human behavior.
One thing that development economists
think about a lot, but maybe not
everyone else does, is just how the
nature of market frictions might change
what the optimal policy is. That's
economist Namrathakala. She's an
associate professor in applied economics
at the MIT Sloan School of Management.
And a few years ago, she and some
colleagues decided to figure out how you
can best incentivize farmers to stop
setting fire to their fields at the end
of the season. Every year farmers in
North India and also other parts of Asia
burn their fields to clear it for the
next crop because that is the quickest
and cheapest way to prepare your field
before the next season. Except the air
quality implications of doing this are
very large and very negative. And so
there's work in epidemiology that shows
that it's responsible for about 20% of
New Delhi's air pollution during the the
burning season. I don't need to tell you
but New Delhi air pollution levels
extremely high, most polluted capital
city in the world and so on. Experts
have estimated that burning this crop
residue causes more than 60,000 deaths a
year. So the incentive was high for Kala
and her colleagues to figure out how do
you convince farmers not to do this? A
reasonable answer might be, well, check
their fields at the end of the season
and if they haven't burnt them, give
them some money. And what we found is
that because of market frictions like
liquidity and trust, that actually
performs extremely poorly. In fact, that
leads to no additional emissions
reductions relative to not paying
farmers at all. So, just to underscore
that, researchers say, "I'll give you
money at the end of the season for not
burning your fields." And it doesn't
move the needle. People go ahead, they
burn them anyway, regardless of the fact
that they have a contract to get paid.
What instead works is paying farmers the
same amount of money but giving them a
small amount 25% upfront before the
season as a sign of trust and to
decrease their liquidity issues. And
that doubles compliance relative to the
control group and in fact it performs
much better than doubling the total
payment that you give them. Right? And
so this is sort of just one example
where understanding market conditions
allows you to design an effective policy
that then achieves these emissions
reductions at a lower cost relative to
kind of this higher more expensive less
effective contract. So in essence the
bottom line was not the bottom line.
increasing the payment didn't work. But
understanding that these were not
wealthy people and having some money
upfront mattered well that turned out to
be crucial to convincing them you were
serious. We tested a payment that said
800 rupees per acre everything paid at
the end 800 rupees per acre 200 now 600
later if you comply. And then we tested
a version that said 1,600 like double
the amount but all at the end of the
season and the 25% upfront is where we
see all the compliance or the 50% up
front the upfront contracts are where we
see all the compliance happening. Kala
says that India is moving towards clean
energy quickly but in a place where many
people are trying to make sure they've
got enough to eat every day there has to
be a balance between economics and the
environment. And so like a lot of the
developing world in the 90s and 2000s
thanks in part to uh trade reforms and
other types of reforms extreme poverty
fell and worldwide I think the number is
about 2 billion people escape poverty
and in India as well as I mentioned that
said this has been reversing in the
developing world in about the last 10
years and so these tradeoffs of poverty
reduction combined with emissions
reductions I I think will continue to be
salient for developing countries uh
moving forward. Right? And just to kind
of put some numbers on this, the per
capita income in subsaharan Africa is
about $1,600
uh right in India it's something like
2500. Uh in the US it's like
$82,000. Kala says that people who
haven't visited India for five or 10
years tend to be shocked by the rapid
rate of change. Indeed, her own
childhood is reflective of that change.
When I was younger, my family did not
have an air conditioner, and that was a
source of kind of great joy and comfort
when that arrived. And I was about, I
think, maybe 7 years old, and there was
one. And so, you know, everyone sort of
crowded in to to sleep at night in the
in the same room. And then there was a a
lot of kind of managing uh because it
was a big energy consumer and we wanted
to manage the bills. There was a lot of
like it's been on for an hour now shut
it off, right? And there was also a lot
of uh which is I think emblematic of a
lot of experiences dealing with outages
and trying to protect your appliances
from these uh outages that might hurt it
and the inability to use all your
appliances uh that you wanted all the
time especially because when it's hotter
you know is correlated with with demand
and also outages. So I think personally
a lot of what I see in the data and what
I do in the fieldwork resonates with
just like my experience growing up. But
India has been ramping up the
reliability of its grid which has made a
huge difference and so I think there's
been a massive electrification program
over the last couple of decades and I
think hundreds of millions of people
have benefited from that. I think
there's been a large increase in
appliance use and I think it's kind of
just sort of correlated with with my
experience that in a country of you know
1.3 billion people when you go from 65%
electrified to almost 100% that's just
order of a magnitude increase in in
comfort and welfare. Meanwhile, India
has also embraced clean energy. Kala
says and that doesn't seem likely to
change even as American policy on energy
shifts dramatically. A lot of Indian
policy on regarding clean energy I think
and Chinese as well has been in my
opinion quite pragmatic and innovative.
Right? So if you look at cost reductions
around solar energy, India is such a
large market. It really is right. It's
the fourth largest wind market in the
world and renewable capacity just last
year grew by about 35% in India and I
think in in China solar capacity grew by
over 40% uh last year. So these markets
are large and they are growing fast and
India has electrified I think almost all
of its uh railway network which is a
system that carries 20 million people
every day. So these are like large
system and I think a lot of it has been
based in terms of whether it makes sense
of the economics along with you know
does it make sense in terms of uh the
emissions. So the railways running on
say diesel are are costly and and
variable in terms of cost.
Electrification can can be more reliable
if it's done well. So I think that's
sort of the this combination of what I
consider pragmatic and innovative has
been one kind of the first principal
component as I would call it of uh a lot
of these energy policy decisions that
that I've been aware of. So you made a
really interesting point there about
about the railroads and the
electrification displacing the use of
diesel. You know, I I think of India has
been sort of emblematic of of many
developing countries in that fuels are
very expensive there. That's right. You
may not experience that because
sometimes they're subsidized by the
government to sort of provide a buffer
in the middle. But India doesn't have
large primary energy supplies apart from
coal. They don't use coal on the
railways anymore. And and what that
means is that that renewables have an
advantage there because you've got to
import natural gas. And unlike us who
pay $3 per million BTUs, Indians pay 12
to$14 per million BT use, three or four
times the cost. And so suddenly solar
starts looking pretty good in India and
with pretty good sun that's really a
help and I think that's helping to sort
of propel this rapid adoption of of
lowcarbon energy. Not because it's low
carbon energy, because it's the best
deal. Yes, I think that that's going to
be, as I said, like just given the the
really salient trade-offs about growth
and poverty reduction. Uh most clean
energy policies will likely be driven by
economics. Let me go back for one
second, Namra, to this. in some sense if
you have a lot of poor people the
question of can people eat next week
maybe I don't want to put words in your
mouth maybe tends to subsume the
question of like are the glaciers
melting right and so people go to the
pools in India so the issue of energy um
even the issue of climate change is it
something people care about or are they
kind of like focused on other things I
think you know like everywhere in the
world I think the economy matters a lot
and jobs matter a lot. I have in the
most recent elections there has been
mention of air quality and I think
that's important. I think energy is
really important and I think electricity
and quality of life are very important
for sure and I think people value that
and I think people would reward that
electorally and uh so on. Is there an
explicit trade-off that you think of? I
mean, you know, how much of an increase
in emissions can India accommodate in
order to deal with poverty? How do you
think about that? So, I you know, I'm
very much like uh like smart policy
matters and by that, you know, by that I
mean one of my favorite papers that I
read in the last year was this paper in
science. The lead author was at the Potm
Institute and essentially what that
paper does is it takes 1500 policies,
climate policies that have been
implemented across the world and uses
really datadriven methods to find out
which ones were effective, right? And so
in some sense this is not a binary
version of should any country, you know,
India included have climate policy or
energy policy or not. It's so much more
a question of like what is the right
policy that has productivity co-
benefits and emissions reductions and
they find successful examples and they
show you right so in the developing
world the pricing policies matter a lot
more they have like examples of these uh
etc you can do the same thing with cost
benefit right and so I think that the
way that I think about the like is there
an emissions gap or is there like that
that we need to achieve our growth
targets I think thinking about these
kinds of policies is much more high
return because it's more like when
you're in it's not that I want to invest
in a tech firm yes or no it's like which
tech firm am I going to invest in is
really important for my returns and I
don't think policy is any different so I
think that's kind of thing one which is
why as I said I've been very heartened
by these large growths of an already
large renewable market that don't show
signs of slowing down and partly again
it's the economics partly it's the
demand but partly it's also the learning
by doing. So there's work that shows
that both in solar and in wind the more
you produce the more your average costs
go down and you can have policies that
induce lower costs over time by having
like R&D uh subsidies or or output
subsidies. So there's like really nice
paper by Robin Burgess and co-authors on
China solar experience. There's work by
Rich Sweeney at Boston College on
learning by doing in the wind industry.
So I think like these are all things
that make me think that you know there's
momentum in terms of the economics. I
think there's a portfolio of policies
many of which are not a trade-off some
of which might be a trade-off and we
should think about and so on. It's a
little bit from a US perspective, but I
wonder there's been an argument, there's
long been an argument here, that there's
really no point doing a big energy
transition in a place like the US if
much larger countries in terms of
numbers of people i.e. China and India,
you know, are going to keep their
appetite for energy is going to keep
increasing and and you could even make
it it's even more salient for small
countries like a a France or a Denmark
or whatever. You can get pretty small
like what's the point in making these
little shaving things off here and there
if like China is building coal fired
power plants. I think there's kind of
like a particular amount of carbon that
you can put in the air and that's going
to increase the temperature by x degrees
and kind of increase the likelihood of
extreme events by a certain amount. So
when you scale that back, how do you
allocate the scale back? I think is a
good question, right? And I think that
there's
certainly merits to to saying something
like of course it won't matter if you
know I think the top 10 countries have
76% of carbon emissions right so if like
nine of them keep going maybe it will
matter less for sure at the same time I
don't think it's superfluous to consider
the fact that the US has like 29% of
cumulative historical emissions
you know India has 3%. So when you're
thinking about scale back, I think
that's potentially useful information
and does not at all in my opinion
preclude a reasonable solution, right?
And I think that if you just kind of
look at policy actions, the policy
actions are indicative of many
developing countries knowing that
there's benefits to investments in clean
energy, right? Like that's why now from
what I understand, China's emissions are
set to peak in 2030.
if they have this large renewable market
that's again growing like 45% relative
to last year for solar like I think
there's they're making gains in in
emissions reductions and so on. So for
me, you know, I think that's right.
There's a certain amount of carbon you
can put in the air that's going to
increase the degrees by a certain
amount. How should the scale back be
aortioned when, you know, they have
there's like the the poverty reduction
goals that I that I mentioned and the
per capita emissions are 14 tons per
capita for the US and two for for India.
And I think for subsaharan Africa, it's
probably less than half. That's not
superfluous information. I think that
really doesn't preclude a solution and I
think that the last couple of decades of
like renewable energy investment in fact
indicate to me that there is a feasible
solution at at hand
at least at a in an initial level. I
mean I think something that's lost in
the the climate discussion is often just
how much we have to do. I mean we really
have to massively reduce our emissions.
I mean was it somebody somebody uses the
the the phrase you know if if we each do
a little we all do a little if you add
it all up we have to do a lot and and
unfortunately India will have to be part
of that story. Absolutely. But I think
but that's why I think you know I I'm
heartened when I see these kinds of
year-on-year growth numbers from a large
market. And I think part of that again
like I think it's it has to be the
economics at play in to to some degree,
right? Like you have these I think the
the wind turbine paper that I was
mentioning earlier said something like
you manufacture twice the turbines and I
think your your costs fall by about
15%. It's pretty
[Music]
big. It sounds like you think people are
adopting these technologies because
they're cost-ffective like not is that
right? Not because they're clean.
I think it's both. But I think there
have been good concerted policy actions
from a lot of countries like the EU,
like China, like India to to mention
some and of course the US as well to
sort of understand that you're kind if
you're at a higher cost point, what does
policy need to do to make that
competitive and then do that, right? And
and so the a lot of the gains that we
are seeing are partly like the private
sector responding to policy certainty,
price signals, a large incoming market
and doing its part and getting us these
cost reductions that that make the
economics look better. Yeah, I think
it's pretty clear from what's happened
and the numbers that you know solar plus
batteries in India which are becoming
cheaper all the time actually
economically displace coal as coal
plants age. You know, you're not going
to rebuild those coal plants. You're
going to build solar and batteries
instead. That doesn't mean that the
whole power system can be replaced by
solar and batteries. But I think Indians
are being very realistic and pragmatic
about recognizing the opportunity to do
this and it's it's it's economically
driven but it's I think they're also
aware of the benefit that that has for
them as well. Absolutely. And Rob, no
concerns about intermittency and wanting
something that you can do 24/7 and the
sun doesn't shine all. I mean, does the
the batteries fully solve that problem?
No, they don't. Okay. No, they solve it.
You know, they saw that in when we're in
the regime at which we've got some of
the generating capacity from old coal
plants rolling off as those as those
plants age out. And you can replace
those with batteries and and wind to
some extent. But you're taking advantage
of other flexibility that still is
available within the generation system.
A lot of which comes from more modern
coal plants, but also from hydro, okay,
that um you know you can you can take
advantage of to deal with that
intermittency. But you get to a a
certain point where that's no longer
really feasible without adding a lot of
batteries and that starts to affect the
economics negatively. Now, of course,
we're hoping that we get cheaper and
cheaper storage technologies over time
and that that threshold just keeps on
moving up and and India can continue
down this path and you know they get an
economic benefit from it. Another way of
looking at that economic benefit is that
it's it's freedom from having to import
fuels in many situations that that um
would otherwise have to be used. So it's
it's win-win. India is really leading
the way in in showing how far you can
push a lot of these things. I think
Namroth I wonder what the impact if
there is any of the shift in US policy
has been on India. So, you know,
obviously very early in the Trump
administration, we saw the president
dismiss the Paris climate accord and
obviously the the approach is super
different from what the Biden
administration had been. Does India sort
of like we have a different policy? We
just keep on going. I think the it's a
little early to say you're right. So I
think the one thing that that I will
point out is that these renewable
policies and these kinds of growth rates
had been happening even prior to the
Biden administration right so there is
some broad trend of countries deciding
that for economic reasons for other
reasons like this is this thing to do
what does it slow down the rate perhaps
because you know there's market
conditions that have shifted there might
be like less technological
conditions that are favorable etc. But I
don't know how much of that is going to
affect this kind of broader trend of of
increased investment and and growth.
This is getting uh veering into your
personal experience. But I wonder if you
also see the
possibility clearly there's a lot of
people in the US who are Indian who've
either come here for school or come here
after school very technically capable
people. I wonder if at all in your own
like in the trajectory of your own life
you've seen more of those people return
to India versus stay in the US
indefinitely. I I don't know I don't
know if
you see any like balance shifting there
because I know that can be a sign that
like there are very good opportunities
at home maybe I don't want to stay in
this other country. Yeah, I think it's a
bit difficult to say also because like I
you know sadly I know more economists
than I know other types of scientists
really you know it's like um I'm a nerd
I don't get out much and so a lot of my
kind of personal experience is like
seeing my friends and co-authors and
things kind of make these career
decisions but only in one field and I
know a little bit but much less than
about other fields India has had this
influx of private universities that have
tried to value cutting edge research and
I think that's kind of been a heartening
development in the last 10ish years or
so and so you do see more people kind of
get PhDs in the US and then and then go
back and do cutting edge research there
so there's been I think a little bit of
that pull factor relative to kind of
these other macro factors I can't really
say if it's a big deal you know the Tata
had a lot of Indian PhD students at MIT
who were working on a variety of
technologies that found their way back
to India and I we you know we got to I
think 10 of them became Indian faculty
members over a period of four or five
years. We stopped counting at one at
some point but you know a lot of Indian
really really highly trained Indian
scientists and engineers certainly were
returning through that program to India
and I think they're having a big impact.
Absolutely. And you know similarly as I
said in in economics I think there's a
lot of it's a field with a lot of uh
depth of talent and so there's been like
more dispersion across space as well.
Namatha when you think about clean
energy going forward in India I wonder
what sort of gives you the most hope and
what also gives you the most cause for
concern or what you feel like the
biggest hurdles are going to be you know
as I mentioned kind of the the trend
gives me a lot of hope. It's a large
market. I think a lot of the recent
policies have helped the growth of clean
energy. At the same time, I think
there's more that you could do to really
make sure that you're getting the the
maximal returns to these policies. So
that's thing one. Uh so Nick Ryan at Yel
has a very nice paper on counterparty
risk in the solar market in India. And
so trying to understand what market
frictions, what contracting frictions
you should mitigate to make sure that
when you put in a policy in place,
you're getting the most private entry,
the lowest cost entry, and you're
targeting the consumers that you want to
be targeting. I think be be great to
see. The other thing which is kind of a
broad point about industrial policy and
green industrial policy is no different
is some of this ends up being countries
competing for the same slice of the pie
rather than making the pie bigger.
Right? So it's like the same thing can
be produced in country X or country Y.
So country Y tries to get subsidies in
earlier and become lower cost faster
with the learning by doing. But then if
both countries start that then in terms
of like aggregate welfare you don't get
uh as much as you would if they
specialized. So I think for countries
broadly thinking more about comparative
advantage and then how to target the
resources best that you want to target
towards these clean energy goals would
be great to see like just broadly across
the board versus let's it sounds like a
race to the bottom with who has the
cheapest solar cell. That's right. If
we're if if we all have exactly the same
advantage in producing a commodity and
it's just a question of who gets there
first then you know starting together
and trying to race might not be optimal
for the world right but uh figuring out
what your comparative advantage is so to
Rob's examples about uh India's recent
advances in the solar industry is a is a
great example so really thinking about
targeting within the industry to like
those resources I think is likely to
yield the maximal cost benefit. Well, I
think this this discussion has had an
interesting academic character. You
know, we're talking to an economist
rather than an engineer. So, it's, you
know, thinking and it begs the question,
what's the role of universities in
helping countries like India to advance
faster? Is that something we want to
talk about? I mean, how much time do you
have? Yes. Yeah. I mean, how do we do
But I mean maybe if we could talk from
your personal experience of how you
engage with the Indian government or
Indian companies to help them find their
unique path. So I think collaborations
are pretty key have been pretty key at
least for me and that's like
collaborations with economists in India,
collaborations with firms, state
governments and so on and that's a lot
easier when you have these ongoing
research relationships and so so you
know here I really want to give a shout
out to JPAL which is a center housed at
MIT but has offices all over the world
where you have these these educated
researchoriented professionals that are
forming these relationships, conducting
research and facilitating a lot of this
uh research and disseminating it as
well. And I think that's been really
helpful as well. So what is the role of
universities? I think you know the way
that I think about it is we we need to
produce knowledge. we need to kind of
collaborate in the production of that
knowledge because at least in my field I
think it's better when it's done in
collaboration in knowledge of what the
context is how you improve things when
you understand what the frictions are
that's thing one and then I think two is
again helping figure out what policies
what firm strategies uh are the best out
of a portfolio of strategies and that's
difficult experimentation for a single
firm firm to do by itself. It's costly
or by you know for a single government
with uh maybe a year of lead time trying
to make a difference to do but having a
store of knowledge and having multiple
collaborations for people to learn is I
think a role for a university and I
think you know at least in my experience
MIT has done a lot of that. You you make
a really important point too. It makes
me think of like everything we have
talked about in this conversation has
been nobody lands in India and like
immediately knows who these farmers are,
who you're going to talk to to do right.
So you've got to like start to get to
know people and you have no ongoing
relationship that you know it's hard to
then get to the truth of what even would
work. Exactly. And then just figuring
out what the right thing to try is like
that's going to be like the steeper
learning curve and and all all of the
above. Yeah. We're also in a world in
which people are trying to move quickly
and and you know there are lots of
actors out there promoting their ideas.
They strongly believe in them or you
know maybe they have companies that sell
products that that align with those
ideas. You know people are saying well
you know solar is the answer or or green
hydrogen is the answer or LPG is the
answer and of course none of them is the
answer. there's there's a combination of
those things as an answer and it's very
contextual and it might not even be the
same in different parts of the same
country uh and it might change over time
and so I think universities also have a
role to play in in helping governments
to understand what's optimal and what
are the trade-offs that they have to
make in setting policy and and we've
seen that play out a number of places. I
spent a couple of days this week with a
bunch of oil and gas executives in uh in
Houston who wanted to get involved in
ending energy poverty and and I have not
the slightest doubt that they're earnest
in wanting to do that. Um and and you
know their perspective is well I think
people are overlooking fossil fuels as
part of the answer to ending poverty in
these countries and we're
overemphasizing
um climate as a as a a guiding light.
And you know I have some sympathy with
that.
Being poor is something that that people
experience right now and and ending it
is is uh important but that doesn't mean
the answer is natural gas or oil. It
just means that we need to be uh mindful
of the impacts outside the energy sector
on personal economy of people who live
in these places. Absolutely. And I think
that is the university like universities
can play that neutral research
datadriven role and and we should.
Namratha Kala is an associate professor
in applied economics at the MIT Sloan
School of Management. Namratha, thanks
so much for being here. Thanks again for
having me. This was really fun. Thanks
Nanra.
What if it works is a production of the
MIT Energy Initiative. If you like the
show, please leave us a review or invite
a friend to listen. And remember to
subscribe on Apple Podcast, Spotify, or
wherever you get your
podcasts. You can find an archive of
every episode, all of our show notes,
and a lot more at
energy.mmit.edu/mpodcasts. And you can
learn more about the work of the energy
initiative and the energy transition at
energy.mmit.edu.
Our original podcast artwork is by
Zitler Design. Special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible. I'm Cara Miller. And I'm
Rob Zer. Thanks for listening.
[Music]