Hi everyone and welcome back to the uh
introductory series for the obesity
machine learning competition. My name is
Julie Laffy and I'm a post-doal fellow
uh at the Broad Institute in the Eric
and Wendy Schmidt Center. uh and my
research there uh involves taking
approaches from computation uh and from
interpretable uh machine learning and
applying this to uh biological context
to understand disease and I'm
particularly interested in uh cancer
immune context.
So I'll be taking you through uh the
remaining two lectures of this
introductory series lecture two and
lecture three. Um and today we'll be uh
in this lecture talking about uh
technology.
So in the first lecture you will have
heard from Thiago um and learn about
adipose tissue um and the adiposite
cells that make up this tissue um and
then also how when things go wrong um
this can lead to uh metabolic diseases
like obesity.
And uh in this lecture we'll be talking
about uh two revolutionary technologies
um that will allow us to uh both probe
uh and profile individual uh adiposite
cells uh so that we can better
understand um how um as I mentioned when
they go wrong this can lead to uh
obesity.
So um we've broken down this lecture
into three parts. uh in the first we'll
learn about an important concept um of
gene expression programs. You can think
of these uh like the uh functional uh
units that cells use to have specific
functions. Um and then in parts B and C
we'll talk about these two key
technologies uh to profile and to probe
uh cells that I mentioned on the
previous slide. So in part A, gene
expression programs. So just to take a
step back uh and remind ourselves uh
what a gene is. So uh a gene is the
fundamental unit uh of inheritance. Um
and uh our genes live inside uh the DNA.
Um and so they're encoded by this uh
four-letter code uh where the four
letters are adinine, thymine, cytosine,
and guanine or ATC and G.
Uh and these genes carry uh all uh the
traits that make us up. Um so both uh
physical traits like our height uh and
our eye color uh and maybe our hair
color uh but also uh biological traits
um and uh often traits that are also
associated with uh disease.
And so from these genes, you can get
what is a really incredible uh diversity
of cell types and tissues um in the
human body. So um here I'm just showing
you a few examples. You can see uh cells
in the skin, the epithelial cells, uh
cells in the small intestine, cells in
uh that make up your blood vessels, uh
and also um the cells in adapose tissue.
So the adiposite cells that we we're
talking about today.
And um there are really two uh things
that are quite incredible I think when
we look at this. Um the first is just
the sheer diversity of cell types um
that arise from our genes. Um and the
second is um the fact that every single
cell has the same uh set of genes or the
same DNA. Um and so um how is it that uh
this can lead to cells looking like they
do in the small intestine in one case
but like they do in the adipos tissue or
in the skin epithelium in another. And
so um the answer to this is gene
regulation. Um and so um what actually
happens is that uh the genes which
encode these traits um and as we
mentioned which uh are encoded in the
DNA they uh undergo a process called
transcription um which produces RNA and
uh the RNA is like a um copy that's made
um of the gene. So for every gene you
get some copies of RNA. Um and the key
point here is that uh different genes
are switched on in different cells. So
in a cell in um adipose tissue for
example in an adiposite cell we would
see the adiposite gene switched on and
so we would produce a lot of RNA that
corresponds to those adiposite cells. So
now we've spoken about the genes and
gene regulation and how this allows
certain genes to be switched on in some
cells and others in other cells. Um and
so here you can see a schematic of this.
So this is um an illustration of a um
what we call an expression matrix where
every row is a different gene and every
column is a different cell and um the um
red boxes represent when a gene is uh
switched on or is active uh in a
particular cell. And so what we see is
that um actually rather than individual
genes representing uh different cell
types in those different tissues that we
spoke about that actually um it's a
group of genes um that define these
different identities. So for example, we
have these first three genes here which
are switched on in epithelial cells. And
so this would be maybe an epithelial
gene expression program.
And then we have uh these next two genes
that are uh switched on in blood cells.
So this is uh perhaps a blood uh cell
gene expression program. Uh and then
finally another two genes which are
specific to uh the adiposite cells. Um
and so this would be an adiposite gene
expression program.
Um, and so, um, measuring, uh, the
amount of this RNA in every single cell
will allow us to tell, um, which gene
expression programs, uh, are present in
the different cells and by that means
really identify what these cells are,
uh, and hopefully, uh, learn what
they're doing.
And so um we spoke a little bit about
gene express gene expression programs uh
and how these define uh cell identity
and um here we're looking uh at the
zoomed in version of what uh I showed
you um a couple of slides ago. This is
adapose tissue. Um and you can see um
that the gene expression programs uh in
adapose tissue um create this phenotype
whereby the cells are very big um and
they have lots of fat stored inside
them, lots of lipids um and so as a
function of that they have this really
thin cell membrane and they also have
the nucleus which are these little
purple specks that are pushed off to the
side. Um so this is to um permit the
main function of the adiposite cells to
uh produce and store uh lipids uh
leading to this phenotype. But even
within adapose tissue uh and within
adiposite cells you actually can have uh
different gene expressions uh that lead
to different functions of adiposite
cells. And so uh in this uh tissue which
is also adapost tissue um we see a very
different phenotype um that actually
represents um particularly uh
metabolically metabolically active uh
adeposites. And so um the reason for
this uh different uh phenotype is um one
these cells produce um a lot of
mitochondria um and are very
mitochondrially active. And so the kind
of pink tint that you see here is
actually coming from the density of
these mitochondria.
Um and they also have uh much smaller
lip lipid droplets which are the um
white blobs as opposed to just uh the
very large version of those droplets
that you see um in the classic adapose
tissue.
And so um if we kind of dive in um we
can think of this uh classical adapose
tissue as being made up uh principally
of these adiposite cells. Um these are
actually uh generated uh via what we
call a differentiation pathway from this
earlier uh much smaller cell um called
uh priiposite.
And um in the metabolically uh active uh
tissue um this is actually specialized
uh functions uh that um that these
adiposite cells perform. Um and so these
are still adiposices. Uh but there may
be adiposytes that are particularly
concerned with the formation um and
generation of lipids. Uh or uh
particularly concerned with actually
using up fuel and breaking it up to uh
release heat. So we typically uh refer
to these um as differentiation programs
uh that define these uh particular cell
identities um and to the lipogenic and
thermogenic as uh metabolic programs.
And um one reason that we're
particularly uh interested in these
programs is because um of their
association uh to obesity. Um and so
what we know is that uh skewed
proportions of some of these uh cells in
particular uh for example a high
proportion of adiposytes uh or a high
proportion of lipogenic adiposites or a
uh low proportion of thermogenic
adiposytes um is linked to obesity. And
so the hope is that uh by really
understanding these different cells um
we can uh do a better job at treating uh
patients with obesity.
So we do know uh some things already. Um
so if you remember uh we introduced uh
that uh gene expression programs are
made up of uh genes that go up and down
together uh depending on um which cell
they're expressed in. And so um I've
highlighted just a couple of the genes
that we know to mark these different
cells. Um and so you can see here for
example PDGFRA.
PDGFRA uh is a gene which allows the
padiposite population uh to proliferate
and divide um and lead to this uh
diversity of adiposite cells um that we
can see here.
Um and in the adiposite cell um adipo Q
is a hallmark gene. Uh this is a gene
that allows um adipose tissue to signal
to other tissues um and do things like
uh regulate insulin activity.
Um and so that's great. We already have
some uh information and uh some ability
to kind of identify these different
populations. Um but really what we would
like um is uh first of all uh to to
understand not just a few genes um that
are switched on or off in each of these
um each of these different cells. uh but
actually to be able to measure uh all
20,000 genes um that are in uh the human
genome uh and understand what their
relationship is to each of these
identities.
Uh the second uh problem here is that um
we know for specific genes within these
programs um what they're doing like I
mentioned PDGFRA in the uh priiposite
and um adipoq uh in the uh
differentiated adiposite um but what
about all other 20,000 genes so if we
delete PDGFRA the cells uh won't be able
to proliferate as well uh What about if
we delete all 20,000 other genes in the
human genome? Will we be able um to
understand better what they do?