Thank you for coming to the very last
session and our moderator for this
session is Nick Fry.
>> Hi, thanks everybody. So, uh, just
gather in and we'll get into some case
studies next. Uh, the first speaker is
going to be Carrie Smith joining us
remotely. I believe we're going to have
his video up. Okay. Uh, so Carrie Smith
is pretty well known in the industry.
He's an AE fellow. Uh, and he's had
about 30 years in ground source and, uh,
subsurface and almost another 30 years
before that doing other things. Uh then
we'll have uh Mark Metzner uh who you'd
heard from earlier and Jay Egg and Susan
Merkott to follow. So uh if we can ceue
up Carrie's video.
>> Hello, my name is Carrie Smith. I hope
you're enjoying the conference. Uh thank
you for letting me present my portion
the about ATL systems. My presentation
will give you an overview of one pipe
ATLs.
Depending on uh how you classify
multi-building projects, we have between
20 and and 30 ambient temperature
systems operating at at this time. Uh
our first system was started in 2002 in
SEU Springs, Colorado. Other projects
include housing projects, a 40 acre
heavy equipment dealer service center, a
see a NASA track, seven school campuses,
and of course uh additional uh
university campuses like Colorado
University and Weber State University.
I'd like to uh describe what uh these
the configuration of these uh uh ATLs
and stuff. First uh we have a
configuration that basically is a hair
pin. two pipes going up and down uh the
street uh which uh connected two
connected pipes going up and down the
street which are connected primary
secondarily to these loads sync sources
uh and buildings. The second would be
the perimeter or runaround system which
basically goes around the block or
around the campus. These two loops can
be uh two configurations can be combined
together to form a multi-ist uh
multi-asset uh uh system where we have a
central loop that basically connects
them. Uh and then we have submicro
district coming off that central loop.
We could also connect directly to
another central loop system. Uh
theoretically these are quite expandable
uh over a large area.
You know, nothing's more efficient than
off. Uh, an ATL uses an independently
large diameter HTP pipe
uh attached that uh that uh pipe or or
hydraulically separated independent surf
circuits serving buildings or system
assets.
Uh these assets may be but are not
limited to really uh graywater and
blackwater systems
closed loop and phase change materials.
Uh that's for storage or sync source uh
use solar thermal systems or PVT energy
for energy addition or rejection.
um open loop sources or sinks, high to
mid temperature geothermal resources,
CHP waste and conventional uh boilers
and cooling towers for emergencies or
peak loading.
This system uses heat pumps and
diversity of loads to heat and cool.
Bore hole and phase change storage is
dinural for load shifting or time of day
power reduction or or seasonal for
heating and cooling. All sequences are
birectional
central loop to building or building to
central loop.
Uh to give you an example of the control
of these systems, we have a building up
here that's uh running between 55 and
85. If it gets out of range, uh what
happens is uh it turns the central loop
pump on and goes to the central loop. Of
course, we started with the uh first
thing we had this central loop is
idling. So, consequently, other
buildings and assets are available to
this building. Finally, uh if uh the
central loop and the buildings that are
on it can satisfy the load, that's
diversity.
uh then uh we will go to green systems
or like uh loop fields and PV and so
forth. uh when the temperature is under
50 or over 85.
And finally when uh the system
uh gets above its uh set capacity and is
no longer able to uh uh to maintain this
50 to85 and it has all the green assets
on will go to boiler cooling towers uh
the for additional energy or to reject
basically under 40° or over 95 degrees.
This is a a uh picture of the front end
system of Colorado Mesa University. Uh
it uh the central loop flash fluids
building the heat pump systems. We have
about 3 and 12 miles of 18in central
loop pipeline in the five micro
districts. We have currently 19
buildings uh on the system itself and uh
13 1.3 million square ft. Uh these five
five micro distances are interconnected
and they can uh be operated
independently or as one system.
Let me see. There are over uh 250 van
gallons of transport fluid in the system
and there are distributed assets around
campus. This system uses loop fields,
irrigation water and some potable water
at this time. Uh except for a small
number of hours, we have not fired the
boilers to maintain temperature in the
system since 2012.
So what we've got uh here we've got loop
fields. This is district number one.
We've got loop fields. We've got a
pumping station. This is a main pumping
station uh for the central loop. It's
sized to uh to handle about 4,000 tons.
And south district 2 is down here. It's
a set of dorms is mostly heating. Of
course, it's isolated primary secondary.
Uh district three is the Maverick
Center. Uh in the center here, we have
mixing valves and so forth. So we can
direct and redirect uh the fluid and uh
uh throughout any of the micro
districts. Down here we have a a
classroom building dorm complex when we
have a second uh pumping station. These
pump two pumping stations by the way um
when they're used together are in a kind
of a
parallel series configuration.
And you know, most of the time uh uh we
only used one or two pumps to start
with. Uh as you might be able to see,
it's kind of small here. This estimate
right now, the central loop temperature
is 82 degrees. And if you notice, we
have none of the assets on. This is
purely run on uh uh building diversity
at this time. So, you know, uh it's uh
oh, oops. you know, we do have, by the
way, several buildings on at the uh at
the same time. So, uh,
as we go through this, um, we're
currently planning on this campus
another 1.3 million square foot
addition, which is going to be a sixth,
uh, uh, and probably seventh micro loop.
This is kind of a nice cartoon. What it
does is tell you a little bit about uh
gives you a little broader perspective
of what uh we have buildings on the
loop. Uh they can be commercial,
residential or industrial. They're
cooling dominant or heating dominant. It
doesn't matter. They could be balanced.
It just depends. Uh then on top of that
we have uh a system we're able to build
solar PVT uh do heat exchange panels so
forth. Uh we can uh use air source uh
pumps built into made as multissource
heat pumps which basically either uh use
uh air as a source or water as source
and of course ground source heat pumps.
We may have chillers on the loop. We may
have wastewater heat recovery and heat
heat exchangers or we may have
industrial us industrial waste and of
course we have ground heat exchangers,
thermal storage and water source heat
changers exchangers.
Uh all of the systems can be interfaced
with the electrical uh grid and uh and
also in PVT uh panels and so forth. But
uh what we do is we operate the loop in
such a way that we can uh uh shift loads
and and or take care of take advantage
of time of day rates and and so forth.
Uh and then also on top of that, you
know, we might be turn around have
another source of electricity, river
run, wind, whatever have you.
And finally, you know, we can go with uh
additions like conventional CHP, cooling
towers and of course boilers for
emergency. Uh the interesting thing is
uh we can attach micro uh other micro
grids to the loop. So consider that to
be opponent. This system is emissions
free uh uh and uh uses electrical power
and in some cases we're starting to
interface with the telecon uh with with
grid enabled monitoring automated uh uh
uh sequences above the general
management system and monitoring and
intelligent control. uh for example
mapping the uh the flow of people back
and forth across campuses uh in and out
of city buildings and so forth.
So that concludes my uh presentation. Uh
I hope you enjoyed it and if you've got
any questions, please submit them.
[Applause]