Hi everyone, nice to meet you. My name
is Idol Levy. I'm the founder and CEO of
Safe Mode. My co-founder, Professor
Muelli, our chief scientist, is the
connection for MIT. Came out of the
media lab and now is the head of big
data lab in Tel Aviv University. And
we're helping tracking companies and
transportation delivery companies to
prevent accidents. And you have a lot of
uh products in this market. But we are
focusing and developed a behavioral
modification engine. We focus on
changing behavior not on only on
monitoring behavior but how we can
actually take drivers and make them
drive more safe, more efficient um and
more
sustainable. So our mission is to focus
on the driver. We want to be the most
driver ccentric company out there. And
the reason that we are focusing on the
driver is that these are the guys that
sitting behind the wheel for 10 12 hours
a day. Now most of the industry products
are focusing on monitoring how driver
behave with dash cams, GPS, many
different hardware. But these let's call
it stick products are not really
changing behavior. They are overwhelming
managers with a lot of data. But
eventually when you have 200 drivers or
2,000 drivers, it's impossible to manage
and analyze the data and more important
you don't really able to coach the
drivers or enforce them to drive better.
We have an incentive programs the carrot
to incentivize drivers to drive better
and make a win-win situation between the
driver that earn more money based on
safe and efficient driving the company
whether if it's Amazon or trucking
companies and even the insurance
company. These are some of the case
studies. One of them is with Uber rental
car company. The other one is with
Amazon delivery company. We help them to
lower accidents by 30% on top of all the
advanced solution in the market like
dash cams and GPS and telematics and
also save 5% of fuel. All of that is
because of better and safer and more and
less aggressive driving behavior of the
drivers. So how we actually do that? We
collect a lot of data from existing
devices in the vehicle. We are
completely software platform. We don't
have any devices of safe mode. uh we
integrate uh seamlessly with whatever
fleets already have. Then we analyze the
data and eventually we engage the
drivers with a gamified app that push
them to coach themselves to drive
better. Every day they can see how they
drive and more importantly as you can
see in the left screenshot they actually
get cash reward based on their
performance. So on a daily basis we
coach drivers we push them to see how
they perform and it's trigger some
circuits in the brain that releases
dopamine on a daily basis. This is how
we are trying and actually affecting
their behavior. We have a lot of science
behind that. My other co-founder is
professor for behavioral economics. So
we have a lot of research on what are
the different incentives that we need to
incentivize and how to incentivize
drivers. Um, I mentioned the seamless
setup and the plugand play. The way that
it's working, we integrate with whatever
fleets have. And then we have two AI
models. The first one is how we score
the driver behavior. Driving in San
Francisco, Boston and New York in
winter, summer, day and night is very
different. Nobody in the industry focus
on the drivers but us. And we in order
to make it fair and make the drivers
play the game, we need to make it um in
a very dedicated way and fair way that
drivers will understand that if they
drive in different atmospheres, they
ranked in a fair way. The second model
is how we incentivize the drivers. If
you are the best driver in the fleet is
great. We need to maintain you the top.
But if you are the worst driver, this is
the lowhanging fruit. This is how we
prevent 30% of accident. Um and
eventually these are the models that
make it happen. Our partnerships ask we
want to have more customers. So if you
have any customer with a fleet or
trucking company, delivery company, we'd
be happy to partner with them as well as
with insurance companies or telematics
providers that have the customer reach
of
any transportation company. So we'd be
happy to meet with them. So thank you
very much. And we have the booth as
well. So stop by and say hi. Thank you.
Thank you, Ido.