My name is Luis Perez Breva and I teach
the MIT class on how to move
technologies from lab to impact. It is
called innovation teams and it's the
longest running course at MIT in
technology innovation. In it, students
learn to solve problems with technology.
This series of videos is an introduction
to a whole new mindset for innovation.
We can help you think the way the most
creative engineers do. There's 40 years
worth of technology sitting and awaiting
for individuals with a new kind of
problem solving skill. I will share with
you the MIT way to solve problems with
technology. Many of the ideas I will
share with you in these videos and more
can be found in my book, Innovating AR's
Manifesto.
[Music]