So here the way to think about modular
arithmetic is that it's about
relationships between numbers. So some
of these you've already seen before and
are pretty familiar. So for example, if
I take an even number and add an odd
number to it, then I definitely get an
odd number. And if I take an even number
and add an even number, I get an even
number. So even though these things are
familiar even from elementary school,
you know, we're going to talk about
generalizations and go a lot further
with these ideas. Really, the way to
think about this simple example is it's
what's called arithmetic modulo 2. So by
that I mean you're doing arithmetic, but
you're only keeping track of the
remainders when you divide by two.
So, you know, for today's lecture, we're
going to have the following key
definition that's going to take this
idea much further, which is we're going
to say that two integers A and B,
well, we're going to write the following
expression A congruent to B mod N.
So, this is pronounced as A congruent to
B mod N. And we'll write this expression
if and only if A and B differ
by a multiple event.
So that's it. That's our key definition
that we're going to explore today. But
we're going to see that there's a lot of
meat to this in terms of you know
understanding how to work with modular
arithmetic.
So another way that you'll sometimes
hear module arithmetic described is as
clock math. So I'll explain what that
metaphor means in a minute. But let me
tell you the you know key result that
we're going to use to reason about uh
you know modular arithmetic. And this
will also be something that's you know
familiar from long ago.
But we're going to state this a little
bit precisely. This is really a
corollary of you know what you learned
in elementary school namely long form
division. So what I claim is that you
know for any integers
a
and n where n is
strictly positive because it's our
divisor. What I claim is that there is
a unique pair
of again integers
Q and R and these are suggestively
chosen because Q is the quotient and R
is the remainder with the following
property.
We can write a as q * n plus r. And the
crucial thing is that this remainder
r is between zero and n and cannot be as
large as n. So it's really between 0 and
n minus one. So this is really the
correlary of what we learned in you know
elementary school about long form
division. I can take any integer a and
some divisor n and I can write a as q
multiples of n and then whatever I have
left over and the crucial thing is what
I have left over is an integer between
zero and n minus one. Though these are
just the basic facts that'll help us
make sense of modular arithmetic.
And you know let's go over some you know
basic facts about you know digesting
what this expression means. you know
what are all the equivalent ways to
think about what this expression is
saying that a is congruent to b. So what
we're going to do is we're gonna you
know learn the language of modular
arithmetic. It's a little bit like you
know relearning arithmetic from scratch
but trying to remember what rules you're
still allowed to do and what rules
change. So you know let's be careful
with this. Uh let's prove our first key
fact and this will be an extremely
powerful fact.
So what I claim is that this expression
a is congruent to b mod n.
Well, we know what this expression
means. A and b differ by multiple of n.
I claim that this is true if and only if
the remainder
of a divided by n equals the remainder
of b when I divide by n.
So this is a very intuitive fact right
this is what was going on right here is
that um you know we think about evens as
being a set of numbers that are
congruent mod 2 and that's if and only
if the remainder when I divide by two is
zero and something is odd if and only if
its remainder is one when I divide by
two but this is true for modular
arithmetic even more generally than this
so this gives us you know a powerful way
that we'll use this fact later uh to
great effect for talking about the
uklitian algorithm but for right now
let's just make sure that uh we're on uh
the same page and that we can understand
why this fact is true. So we can prove
both directions of this implication. So
let's prove the backwards direction. So
let's suppose
that you know a is equal to qn plus r
and that b is equal to q prime n + r. So
r is their remainder. So I'm just
assuming that the remainder of a / n is
the same as the remainder of b / n
because they both have the same extra
term for the remainder.
And now you know what we can do is we
can just remember what this expression
means right we can look at a minus b the
difference between a and b and we can
write this as q - q prime * n and the rs
cancel. So this gives us what we're
looking for, right? The statement that a
and b are congruent mod n is equivalent
to the statement right here that their
difference is an integer multiple of n
and q minus q prime is an integer. So
we're good. We proved one direction. Uh
so this proves you know the first
implication that if the remainders are
the same then they're congruent mod n
and we can prove the converse direction
too. So conversely
let's suppose that a is equal to qn plus
r and b is equal to q prime n + rp
prime.
Now you know since
a a is congruent to b mod n we know that
a minus b is supposed to be equal to an
integer multiple of n. And then we can
remember what a and b are by assumption.
And we can write this out as q - q prime
* n plus r - r prime. Right? And so now
we can just focus on this expression. We
know that a minus b is a multiple of n.
And we can write the expression
alternatively this way. But the key
point is what's happening right here.
That this term right here r - rp prime
is an integer that's strictly larger
than minus n and strictly smaller than
n. So if k you know if uh a minus b can
be divided through by n, we get you know
some integer multiple. The only choice,
you know, n divides evenly here and we
get an integer. The only way that a
number that's between minus n and n and
is strict, these inequalities are strict
and it divides through and gets an
integer is if r - r prime equals zero,
in which case the two remainders are the
same.
So that's our you know key fact right
here is just that we can use the
division algorithm to connect very
nicely with modular arithmetic. The
statement that you know two numbers are
congruent mod n is really a statement
about you know what happens when we run
the division algorithm on a versus b. We
might get different quotients but they
better have the same remainder. So are
there any questions? Does this make
sense?
Yeah. Okay. All right. So now, you know,
let's think about how we can uh,
you know, visualize what's going on.
So the visual to keep in your head
is of a clock. So we can think about
something like 12, which is congruent to
five mod 7. And what's really going on
is that we take the integers 0 to six
and we put them evenly spread out along
our clock.
And now what's going on is when we take
an integer like five, we start off at
zero and we go around the clock until we
hit five. And if we take an integer like
12, we go around the clock, but we're
going to loop one full time around and
we'll end up at the same exact place. So
that's sometimes why you'll hear it
referred to as clock math is because,
you know, unlike ordinary integers here,
we're not actually distinguishing
between 12 and five. These are in the
same equivalence class because they land
on the same position when we go around
the clock.
So this is you know the basics of
modular arithmetic but so far we've only
talked about addition. So the other
piece we should talk about is you know
multiplication
and then we can get to some action. So
when we think about modular arithmetic,
we already know how to uh you know add
and we can also ask how we multiply
modulo n.
So it turns out that you can kind of
just do it. So if I have something like
10 is congruent to three again modulo 7
I can multiply this by 12 which is
congruent to five modulo 7. And one
thing you can check is that you can just
you know do multiplication as usual
right you can multiply 12 by 10 and I
get 120 and on my right hand side I get
15 right but really 15 is congruent to
one modulo 7 because I can take away two
multiples of seven and get back down to
one. So basically when you're doing
addition and multiplication
you can always just you know multiply
and add the way that you're familiar
with just at the end after you're done
you take out as many integer multiples
of you know the modulus as you need to
to get back to an integer that's between
zero and n minus one. So a lot of things
work out you know very nicely. But you
know the way to think about this really
is you know um if you were to try and
unwrap what's behind this notation the
statement that uh you know 10 * 12
modulo 7 is congruent to one right is
really the statement that a number
with remainder
three all happening modul
7 times
a number
with
remainder
five modulo7
gives a number
with remainder one
all modulo
So it's good to not get confused by
what's happening in terms of this
expression, right? What this expression
really means when I take any number like
some number like 10 whose remainder is
three modulo 7 and I take any number say
12 whose remainder is five mod 7 and I
take the product of those two numbers I
get this number on my left hand side 120
and that number should have remainder
one when I take it with the modulus 7.
So that's really what's going on is it's
the same, you know, generalization of
what I wrote down right here is that you
can forget what the actual even number
was. All that matters is what its
modulus is, mod 2. I can forget what my
odd number is. All that matters is that
it has remainder one modulo 2. And I can
still tell you something about the
remainder when I add up those two
numbers even though I've forgotten the
rest of the action of like how many
times around the clock I've gone. So
that's the key way to think about it. So
you know if you've seen it before this
is very easy. Uh if you haven't seen it
this is, you know, takes a little bit of
wrapping your head around. So are there
any questions about modular arithmetic
or does this make sense?
Good.
Okay.
So, you know, I'm trying to give you a
lot of different ways to think about it.
Uh, I'll also mention that you can think
about these things abstractly too,
right? So, we'll talk more about this in
the next lecture, but when I'm working
modulo 7, then I can really think about
it as uh something called a group that
we'll talk a lot more about. And really,
I can just think about the elements of
that as being all of the possible
remainders. And I have this table of how
exactly to add up two numbers that
belong to this set. Because when I add
up remainders of zero, I get back to
zero. When I add up two with two, I get
back to a remainder of four. But see, I
have interesting things happening here.
When I take four and I add four, I go
back to the element one because that's
the new remainder I would get when I
take it modulo 7.
And the same type of thing happens here.
This is our multiplication table. You
know, when I take something like 3 * 3,
that'll give me 9. And when I subtract
off the multiples of seven, I'm going to
get back to two. So, really, what's
going on is that uh we're just redoing
our addition and multiplication tables
just in the context of only keeping
track of what the remainders are.
Make sense?
All right.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
tell you some more basic facts about
modular arithmetic and then we're going
to do a demo
um just to give you a bit of a hint
about why modular arithmetic is
important.
So you know as I promised many of the
things that you're used to with ordinary
arithmetic go through just the same and
I'll point out the things that don't. So
one of the properties that we know and
love is associivity. If I have some
number you know modulo 7, I can add two
numbers B and C modulo7
and then I can add to their result A all
happening mod 7 and I claim that that's
the same thing as parenthesizing the
expression in the other way. It's the
same thing as you know a plus b and then
I add c all happening mod 7.
Um a lot of the other basic facts we're
used to go through as well like
commutativity.
So in particular a + b modulo 7 is equal
to b + a. You know, that's the same
thing as like even plus odd. It doesn't
matter what order I add them up, I still
get the same thing, which is an odd
number.
And, you know, last but not least,
we still have the distributive property,
which tells us, you know, how
multiplication and addition interact. So
if I'm multiplying over Z7, a * the
result of B + C, that's the same thing
as A * B plus
A * C. So almost everything works
exactly the way that you're used to,
right?
All right. So, you know, before we go
too far into modular arithmetic, because
we're going to be doing a lot of it
today, I wanted to give you a little bit
of a teaser for later about why we care
about modular arithmetic. So, it's not
totally obvious, but you know, modular
arithmetic is a great way to accomplish
a lot of things, especially in computer
science. So, we talked a bit about, you
know, areas like cryptography in a
previous lecture. Um, you know,
cryptography is based on modular
arithmetic. So this will be a very
important application for us later in
the class. There are also some other
really fun applications that uh also are
from other areas of cryptography which
have to do with things which are
actually invented here at MIT about zero
knowledge proofs. So uh I'm going to
need some help from the audience for
this one. But you know let's imagine
that uh you're home on a weekend and you
want to watch an embarrassing movie with
your friend. Now you have some favorite
movies you might want to see, but you
don't want to admit to, you know, liking
that movie unless your friend likes it
too. I mean, this is a common problem,
right? You know, maybe if you both like
the same embarrassing movie, you would
then watch it and that's fine. But
otherwise, you know, if you don't both
want to watch the movie, you want some
kind of plausible deniability, right? I
don't like that movie, right? So, what
are some examples of embarrassing movies
that uh you guys actually like that you
might be a little embarrassed to admit?
Don't be shy.
You guys don't like any embarrassing
movies.
What? [laughter]
We can't move on with the lecture until
you guys give me something here.
>> I don't have any.
>> Okay. What are embarrassing movies? Your
friends like
your friends might like
>> Shrek.
>> Shrek is good.
>> Shrek's okay. All right.
>> Barbie maybe.
>> Barbie. Okay.
>> Barbie movie is great. [laughter]
>> All right. We're going to have a fight
breakout.
>> Like this is just the correct answer. I
think
>> Morbby. I have no idea what that is.
>> It's like constant. [cough]
>> Okay.
>> Because it's so bad.
>> Okay. MorbiiUs.
>> Oh, wait. The room.
>> The room. Okay. The room. Uh, I was
gonna go with what's this? Uh, okay. I
don't know. [laughter]
Um, all right. Let's go with Morbius.
So, uh, can I have two volunteers from
the audience and then I'll explain the
game?
Who's going to come up here? Don't be
shy. Yeah. All right. One more. Let's do
it. All right. So, let's explain how,
you know, modular arithmetic and clock
math is going to help us, you know,
answer this question. Uh, what I'm going
to do is I'm going to take five cards.
Three are red, two are black. Let's
pretend that I don't keep track of like,
you know, the fact that it's a two, and
I just know the color of it. So, what
I'm going to do is I'm going to give
each of you uh one black and one red
card. Okay? And then what's going to
happen is I put down this one red card
in the middle. Now, what they're going
to do is they're going to decide whether
they like the embarrassing movie or not,
which they want to see on the weekends,
which I guess is MorbiiUs, which I
should look up after class. And if they
like it, what they're going to do is
they're going to put their red card
closest to the red card in the middle
and their black card on the outside. And
if they don't like it, they're going to
put their black card next to the red
card and their red card on the outside.
Okay? And so what I'm going to do then
is I'm going to stack up the cards on
top of each other. And then I'm going to
have them both cut the deck randomly. So
that way it's a random cyclic shift when
they put it together. And then what I
claim is that, you know, if they both
like the movie MorbiiUs and they want to
see it, what's going to happen is we're
going to have two red cards in a row
cyclally.
And if either of them doesn't like it,
right? Then we will not have three red
cards in a row. We will have two red
cards in a row. But even the person who
claim who liked it and the other person
didn't, they'll have plausible
deniability because all of those, you
know, after the cyclic shifts, it'll all
look the same. So, let's try it out. Do
you guys want to see MorbiiUs over
spring break? So, I won't look. Put down
your cards and then we'll see if uh
we've got a match.
All right. And just for security
purposes, I'm going to ask each of you
just to cut the deck. So, just take up,
you know, some number of cards and put
them on the bottom.
Perfect.
And then cut the deck randomly. We'll
pretend we didn't see how they cut them.
And what I'll do is I'll put them out in
order.
And unfortunately, we don't have a
match. So, uh, can you tell me what you
guys answered?
>> Oh, I answered no.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Yes.
>> You put yes. It's okay. So even though
he put yes, he can save face and say I I
never like that movie anyways. So this
is what's called the zero knowledge
proof. Thanks for your help. Um and you
know it uses just clock math types of
things. So it turns out that you know
once we have the basics of modular
arithmetic there'll be some amazing
things we can do with it like being able
to privately compute functions, be able
to execute cryptographic schemes. But
for this lecture, what we're going to be
doing is we're just going to be building
up the basic mechanics before we can
apply it in action in some of the later
lectures in class.
Okay, so now um let's roll up our
sleeves. You know, all of this stuff was
pretty natural. Um you know, it it works
kind of the way you would expect it to.
But now we're going to get into, you
know, one piece of the puzzle that, you
know, makes it really interesting and
different than ordinary integer
arithmetic. So, let me tell you the key
question which we're going to spend a
few minutes answering.
Um, you know, what I claim is if I look
at that, uh, you know, table, I'm going
to have some examples of, you know,
elements that have multiplicative
inverses.
I'll tell you what I mean by that. But
my key question is going to be when I'm
working say mod 7, does every element
have
a multiplicative inverse?
So let me be concrete. So let's say
we're working mod 7 for you know the
time being. We can take two and four and
we can multiply them. And as usual, the
way we do modular arithmetic with
multiplication is we just kind of do it
and then subtract off the multiples of
seven later. So when I take the element
two and I multiply it by the element
four, what I get is I get the element
one. Right? So that's an example of a
multiplicative inverse.
Because what's going on is if I have a
number multiplied by four, I can get rid
of it by multiplying the whole thing by
two, the two and the four will cancel
because they multiply to one and then I
get back the thing I started with. So
this is the key to a lot of what we're
going to be doing later
cryptographically
is because you know multiplying by a
number in modular arithmetic serves of
jumbling up the numbers you started
with. So I might have some secret
message and then I want to jumble it and
I could try multiplying by some other
number like four. But then I have to
have some way of unjumbling and in this
case that's a multiplicative inverse.
Now that scheme is not literally going
to work but that's the intuition behind
what's going on. So in this case you
know I got lucky or maybe I didn't that
you know when I multiplied by four there
was a multiplicative inverse which is
two. Does two have a multiplicative
inverse?
What is it?
>> Four. That's right. Because of
commutivity, it doesn't matter what
order I multiply them in. So two and
four are each other's multiplicative
inverses. You know, I could look at my
table and write down the full table of
all of the elements, right? And I could
check that, you know, every number has
some kind of multiplicative inverse,
right? like five has a multiplicative
inverse of three and if this table
continued three would be the
multiplicative inverse of five but when
I get to larger and larger moduli it's
not always possible to write down this
gigantic table and verify that in each
row there is some column where it's got
a one right and so what I can ask is you
know whether every element and by this I
mean just to be clear I mean every
nonzero element
zero won't have a multiplicative
inverse. But does every nonzero element
have a multiplicative inverse?
So this will be a key question which
occupies us for um a little bit of the
rest of the lectures answering this
question because we're going to build up
some mathematical theory of not only why
does every element have a multiplicative
inverse when we work modulo a prime but
how exactly I would find it without
actually writing down the entire table.
So that's our plan of action and uh you
know let's go back to
uh we're going to use this fact I
mentioned the fact that a is congruent
to b mod n if and only if the remainders
are equal. We're going to use this to
great effect. So let's just uh start
with some very natural definitions and
um it'll lead us to the answer to this
key question. So first of all I'm going
to define another key quantity which is
called the GCD the greatest common
divisor.
So if you give me two integers a and b
well the greatest common divisor is what
you think it is. It's the largest
integer
that divides both.
Okay, so it could be one for example if
there's no integer larger than one that
divides both. But we'll take this as you
know our definition the GCD.
And you know really it's not so obvious
right now but um you know the following
question is going to help us answer this
problem about multiplicative inverses.
So you know I can ask the question how
can we compute the GCD?
So there's a terrible way to do this
which is I could just take the smaller
of the two integers. Let's say it's a
and I could try all the integers between
one and a and check. You know that might
work for small numbers but that's you're
going to have a very hard time once you
start working with gigantic numbers
things that are like 32 digits because
I'll just have to try too many things.
What I claim is that there's a very fast
algorithm for computing the GCD. In
fact, it's one of the first algorithms
that was ever discovered. So, it goes
back to the ancient Greeks. And we're
going to build up to, you know, this
algorithm with a few key structural
lemmas about how the GCD works. So,
let's start with the first lema. So,
let's assume that B is at least as large
as A without loss generality otherwise
we just switch them. What I claim is
that the GCD, the greatest common
divisor between A and B is actually the
same as the GCD
between A and B minus A.
So this is our first notion of progress.
We start off with two huge integers A
and B. We want to compute their GCD. And
I claim that their GCD is the same as,
you know, two not quite as huge integers
because now, you know, potentially I've
made one of the integers smaller.
So this is our first notion of progress.
Uh once we have this lema, we'll be able
to make a ton of progress. But let's
start by proving this lema and then
we'll prove a souped-up version of this
lema.
So the proof for this is very simple. Um
let's suppose
that K divides A. This is the expression
for K divides A evenly into an integer.
So A is a multiple of K. And let's
assume that K also divides B.
Then um you know what I claim
is that K must also divide B minus A.
Why is that true? Well, what does this
mean? When I take A / K, I get an
integer. When I take B / K, I get an
integer. And so then if I take K, if I
take B minus A and divide it by K, I get
an integer minus an integer. So I
definitely still get an integer, right?
But let's think about what this means.
What this means for us
is that the GCD
of A and B is a lower bound for the GCD
of A and B minus A.
So this part is easy. I know that K
divides B minus A. How did I get to this
statement right here? How does you know
interpreting the statement tell me that
the GC whatever the gcd is for a and b
the gcd of a and b minus a is at least
as large? Can anyone help me out?
So you're up to here. How did I get this
statement? How did it follow from this?
Any ideas?
Let me give you a hint. So mechanically,
you know, I'm not telling you I know
what the GCD of A and B is. I'm telling
you whatever the GCD is, let's suppose
it's some integer K. That the GCD
between B and and uh between A and B
minus A must be at least as large.
How can I guarantee that fact
or ask a question? So either give me an
idea or ask me a clarifying question.
But this is important.
>> Prove that anything.
>> Yes. Perfect. So one way to think about
this is what am I saying here? Whatever
this GCD is, let's imagine that it's K,
right?
Well, then I know that K, you know, from
the statement, you know, if K divides
both A and B, then K must also divide A
and B minus A. That's literally what I
just proved. So that means that K also,
you know, is a candidate for a divisor
for A and B minus A. So whatever the
greatest common divisor is, it must be
at least as large. it must be you know
maybe there's something even bigger than
K but I know it's at least K so are
there any questions about that does that
make sense now right so this is really
yes
>> K is the GCD of everyone has this
>> uh you know I said that this is so this
is you know even though this is just
three lines it's a bit subtle right so
here what I said was that if you give me
any integer k that divides both a and b
it also divides B minus A. So in
particular now when I set K to actually
be whatever the GCD is
then I know that that same K had also
divi better divide B minus A. So it's a
candidate for the GCD of A and B minus
A. So even though this is just a couple
lines the logic is a bit subtle. Okay.
All right. So this proves one direction
but really we want to prove that these
two things are equal. So let's prove the
converse. So conversely
let's suppose that K divides A and
K divides B minus A.
Well then what I claim
is that K divides B. And that's the same
proof as before what happened here,
right? So if k divides a that means I
take a divided k get an integer. b minus
a divided k I get an integer and b is
just b minus a plus a. So that is the
sum of two integers when I divide by k.
So the statement is true. And now this
allows me to prove the inclusion the
other direction. Right? So what this
implies is that the gcd
of uh a and b minus a is a lower bound
for the gcd of a and b. Why? Because
whatever this integer k is the largest
integer that divides both a and b minus
a. I just proved for you that that same
integer had better divide both a and b.
So it's the same logic as above, right?
All right. So this is one of the key
proofs for today. So again I will ask
are there any questions about this
proof?
Good.
Speak now or hold your peace until the
next office hours or something. Okay.
All right. So let's do a souped up
version of lema one because once we have
lema one and we understand this logic uh
we're off to the races.
So [clears throat] now we'll be able to
get a lot of cool things immediately.
So you know lema one didn't make that
much progress at the in the grand scheme
of things because I started off with you
know two integers a and b and I made b a
little bit smaller because I turned b
into b minus a. That's not a huge amount
of progress, but you know, let's take a
leap instead of a step, right? What I
claim, same assumption. So B is at least
A. Then what I claim is that the GCD
of A and B is equal to the GCD of A and
the remainder
of taking B and dividing it by A.
Okay, so now I made a huge leap. I'm not
just subtracting off, you know, one uh
multiple of a. I'm actually making, you
know, b way smaller potentially because
I'm dividing by a and just taking
keeping track of whatever the remainder
is. Does anyone have any intuition for
why this kind of statement should be
true? And my hint is the division
algorithm that's very conveniently right
above it.
Let me give you a hint. So let's say
that we write uh B as equal to Q * A + R
because that's what we get when we do
the division algorithm. And so what I'm
saying is that I can replace
B with R. Right? So what I'm doing
really is I'm not subtracting off one
copy of A, but I'm doing something a bit
more aggressive. So does anyone have any
hints about how this proof ought to go?
How should I do it?
Yes.
>> Repeatedly used.
>> Perfect. That's exactly right. So it's
just a repeated application of lema one.
Perfect. So by the division algorithm
which is conveniently
right above.
Well, what I can do is that the GCD
of A and B is equal to the GCD
of A and B minus A, which is equal to
the GCD of A and B minus 2 A all the way
down to it's equal to the GCD of A and B
minus Q A which is of course the same
thing as R the remainder.
So it's just a repeated application. So
why do I keep subtracting off one
multiple of a per time? Instead I can
just jump to the end and do division,
right? And now I make a huge amount of
progress, right?
Because you know we won't prove the
progress bound, but it's very easy to
prove. Um, you know, the point is that
if A and B are like really close to each
other as integers, then I'm going to
make, you know, a huge amount of
progress in one of my two steps. If A
and B are very far from each other, all
of a sudden, the larger of the integers
goes down to being as small as a. So
either way, what ends up happening is
you get this gigantic speed up in the
algorithm. But you know let's think
about uh just a numerical example to see
what this algorithm looks like. And this
numerical example you know is really
just the uklidian algorithm in in
action. So you know
so the ukitian algorithm
works as follows.
Um all you do is the GCD of AB
is equal to the GCD
of uh A and B1
where you know B1 is equal to the
remainder
of B and A
and then this is equal to the GCD
of A1 B1 1 where a1 is equal to the
remainder of taking a
and dividing by b1. So we just alternate
back and forth. We divide one of the
things by the other. Take the remainder
and now we take the smaller of the two
which now in this case you know is b1
and we take a divided by b1. And that
gives us our new a1. So we just keep
alternating back and forth until the
end. Okay,
so let's actually see a numerical
example of this just to make sure that
we're on the same page.
So, you know, in action, let's do it for
some
large uh integers. So, we could look at
something like the GCD of 46 and 360.
kind of hard to do in your head, but um
you know if I were to do out the
division algorithm,
well the first step is to take 360 and
divide it by 46,
right? And what I'll get the remainder
is going to be 38.
So I replace B with its remainder when
it's divided by A. And now I just divide
things the other direction. So if I take
36 of 46 / 38, I'm going to have 8 left
over. So I'll get that this is equal to
the GCD of 8 and 38.
And then I'll divide things the other
direction. I'll get the GCD of 8 and six
because I'll have six left over when I
take 38 and divide it by eight.
And then I'll take the GCD again and
I'll get two and six. And now I get uh
no remainder. The GCD between two and
zero.
So my uklidian algorithm stopped. But
what's my answer? Two. That's exactly
right. Because the key point is that
what lema one lema 2 tells us is that in
each step we're not changing the gcd.
And what is the greatest common divisor
between two and zero? It's just two.
because zero gets divided by everything
perfectly fine.
Okay,
so that's the ukitian algorithm which we
now understand.
And what I claim is that it's actually
going to help us answer that key
question. It's not totally obvious why
it does and what it has to do with it.
The key is really taking this algorithm
and doing more bookkeeping
and that's called the extended uklidian
algorithm.
So, you know, the key point behind this
algorithm is we're going to keep track
of how we got here.
So, for example, when I start off with
the state 46 360, right? Because I want
to compute the GCD between these two
things.
Instead of just replacing 360 with its
remainder, I'm actually going to keep
track of, you know, what integer
multiple of 46 I subtracted off to get
the remainder. So that's the key point
is that my next state in this
transition, 46 stays the same, but
instead of just having 38, I'm going to
keep track of it as 360
minus 7 * 46.
Okay.
Why am I doing that? We'll get into that
in a second. Uh but now same thing
happens here, right? So when I had, you
know, this number which is 38 and I knew
that I had to subtract off one copy of
it from 46 to get my remainder 8, right?
So I'm just going to subtract it off
wholesale, subtract off, you know, this
entire expression. And what this will
give me is it'll give me 46 minus
minus 7 * 46.
Right? And then on the other side I
still have 360us
7 * 46.
So this seems kind of strange because I
just took a beautiful algorithm that's
very simple to understand and analyze
and I just made it a lot uglier by
keeping track of all of these things.
Right? But the key point is if you look
in these steps the intermediates that I
have are all integer linear combinations
of the two things I started off with.
Originally I have 46 and 360 and all of
the numbers that I get in between are
some kind of integer times one of the
numbers 46 plus an integer times the
other number 360. So, at the end of the
day, when I get the answer of two, what
I've really done is when I keep track of
these integers along the way, I found
some integers s and t so that 46 * s
plus 360 * t is equal to two.
And my extended uklidian algorithm
window will not just compute that the
gcd is two but it'll find the integers s
and t that make that be true right and
so what's really cool about this
expression if you think about it right
let's say you didn't trust me you know
maybe I'm certainly prone to making
algebra mistakes like everyone else
maybe I made some algebra mistake along
the way here and I just tell you the
answer that I got two. One thing you can
do is you can check that two actually is
a divisor of the two things I started
with. Right? So if I have, you know, two
as my uh candidate answer, I can check
that it really does divide both 46 and
360.
But how do I guarantee you that there's
not a bigger divisor of both of them?
Right?
And so the key point is right here.
Imagine there were a larger integer that
divided both of them. You know, four,
six, something like that, right? Imagine
I had some integer k that was larger
than two that divided both 46 and 360.
I claim this expression proves for me
that it cannot be a divisor of both.
Because if K really did divide both of
these things, 46 and 360, when I take
the left hand side and divide it by K,
I'd get an integer time an integer plus
an integer time an integer. That's an
integer. But my right hand side is not
an integer. So this is actually a
certificate that your answer cannot be
any smaller. So you don't even have to
trust my work because at the end of the
day the S and the T I find are the proof
that I found the largest possible GCD.
Does everyone understand that?
Okay.
So now let's connect it back to our key
question. Right? And I'll just state
this as a lema first.
This is really the thing which came out
of our proof
is that you know given
any integers a and b
what I claim is there exist integers s
and t
with the property that sa plus tb is
equal to the gcd
of a and b. And that's just the abstract
version of what we just did in this
specific example.
But now we're in good shape to answer
this question, right?
So, you know, let's return to this,
right? And let's ask, you know, why
does
four have
a multiplicative inverse
mod 7? Okay.
Well, let's think about it in the
context of the uklidian algorithm. So
the GCD between four and seven is what?
One, right? Because seven is prime.
Now I can use this lema. You know if the
GCD between four and seven is one, what
it means by lema 3
is that there are integers s and t so
that 4 s + 7t is equal to 1.
Okay.
And what I claim is that this implies
that four has a multiplicative inverse.
You know we know the answer is two. But
from this expression,
what I claim is that my multiplicative
inverse of 4 is s.
When I take 4 * s, I'm going to get 1 -
7t. So it's actually 4 * s is congruent
to 1 modulo 7 because all of those
integer multiples of seven go away.
So that's actually the proof of why not
just four has a multiplicative inverse
mod 7. Why does every number that's non
zero have a multiplicative inverse mod 7
is just because for any other number B
here I know the GCD between B and 7 is 1
because 7 is prime and I know that means
there's an expression 4 B uh sorry B S
plus 7T = 1 and in that case S would be
my multiplicative inverse right so even
more generally the GCD between B and 7
is one This is true for any nonzero B.
And this would then imply by lema 3 that
b * s + 7t = 1. And that means that uh
you know this expression right here s is
b inverse.
Okay.
So this actually answers all of our
questions, right? So we had this
question. Does every element have a
multiplicative inverse? That's true as
long as the modulus is prime. Right? I
had this question. How could I compute
the multiplicative inverse? So if I gave
you some large prime P and I gave you
some nonzero element A, how would I
compute the inverse of A mod P? Does
anyone have any ideas?
The answer is on the board. some place.
>> Yeah,
>> you can use the
>> perfect that's right. So I would use the
extended uklidian algorithm. I would
apply it with not 46 and 360 but a and p
and I already you know my point of doing
this isn't to compute the gcd. I know
the gcd is one. My point is to find this
expression the S and the T and then that
S that I find will be the multiplicative
inverse. That's exactly right. So this
answers you know basically all the
questions we could uh want right
um in fact there's even a more subtle
question which we can answer too.
um you know if I have a uh modulus
that's not prime like you know six it
turns out that five has a multiplicative
inverse mod 6 because the gcd of five
and six is one so you'll actually have a
multiplicative inverse you know when you
don't have a prime modulus just for the
things that don't share a common factor
Okay, so this was the main part of
lecture.
But uh now what we're going to do is
we're going to do one last
cool application of modular arithmetic
in the last you know few minutes of
class.
And this is another really important
topic.
uh tons and tons of applications. So
I'll tell you you know the math riddle
and then I'll tell you some applications
of this uh you know once we solve it.
So let's just start off with a riddle
about modular arithmetic.
So, let's say we've got a treasure chest
and it's got gold coins.
And let's imagine I promise you that if
this treasure is divided into
groups of five,
I'm going to have four coins
left over.
And let's imagine same thing if it's
divided up into groups of
seven. What I'll have is I'll have one
coin left over.
So there are many possible answers to
how many gold coins there could be, but
what I'll be interested in is what's the
smallest number. So what is the smallest
number
of possible coins?
So that's our key riddle for the rest of
lecture.
Of course, this riddle is going to lead
to, you know, a very interesting
statement in its own right that's
powerful.
Um,
and what I claim, you know, what's
really going on here is that we have a
system of equations.
But the key point which is different
than like the system of equations you've
seen you know before is that these
system of equations are really in
modular arithmetic right so you know
translating this
so whatever we we want to solve for n
which is the smallest number of coins
that could be the answer. So we know
that n is congruent to four mod 5.
That's literally just using the
definition, right? Because you know what
that means is just that four is the
remainder when we divide n by five.
And the second statement is that uh you
know n is congruent to one mod
7.
So it turns out that we can guess the
answer here. But I'll tell you more
formulaically how to find it. So if you
take for example 29 then this works. You
know it solves the system of two
equations in different moduli.
Um but actually there's a much more
general result. I guess today is the day
we're doing ancient results. So this
similarly like the uklidian algorithm is
you know one of the oldest algorithms.
Um this is a fairly old uh statement
too. It's uh due to a Chinese
mathematician son Zushwan
in the 4th century
and what I claim and we'll prove this.
So suppose a and b are relatively prime.
By that I mean you know they don't both
have to be prime but they share no
common factors besides one. Their gcd is
one between them. So imagine that a and
b are relatively prime. You know a and b
will play the role of five and seven
here.
>> [clears throat]
>> So just to be clear, this means gcd of a
and b equals 1
and
we have
some unknown n that's between zero and
ab minus one.
Then what I claim is that if we think
about the system of equations, n is
congruent to r mod
and n is congruent to s mod
b. Then what I claim is that there is
exactly one solution.
So this is somehow exactly what you
could hope for, right?
You know, I'm only telling you one out
of a possibilities here, right? I'm only
telling you one out of b possibilities
here.
So at most I can uniquely determine
integers between zero and ab minus one.
But I'm claiming that every such integer
is, you know, uniquely determined by its
pair of residues modulo a and b.
So really this is a bjection between all
of these AB possibilities of the
integers here and the possible pairs R
and S of what this modulus moduli are.
So are there any questions about the
statements?
All right. So let's prove this. Uh the
proof of this is clever.
Um usually this is called
the Chinese remainder theorem.
uh
[clears throat]
and let's prove this fact. This will use
a lot of the properties about the
uklitian algorithm and modular
arithmetic that we've been developing
for today's lecture. And then if we have
time left over, I'll tell you a cool
application
uh just to get you know some intuition
for why this Chinese remainder theorem
is so powerful.
Actually,
I guess I could have kept that. All
right.
So, let's prove this.
So you know as I told you already there
are
AB choices
for N
and similarly AB choices
for the pairs ST.
Right?
So you know what we want to show
is the following that for I'm going to
call this statement star. I want to show
that for any
uh choices of x and y that are between
zero and ab. So any possible answers xy.
Well, what I want
is that their pair of remainders are not
both the same. I take the remainder of x
/ a. I look at the remainder of x / b.
That pair of remainders had better not
both be equal to the pair of remainders
I get when I take y and divide it by a.
And similarly I take y and divide it by
b. Okay. So maybe I have pairs xy that
are different. I'll assume you know x
not equal to y.
Maybe I have pairs xy that are different
that have one of their remainders match.
But I cannot get different x's and y's
which have both of their remainders
match. So that's the key property. Okay.
So let's show this. Um so we're going to
show star
by assuming it's not true
and creating a contradiction.
So this proof will be short but the
logic is pretty clever for this.
So you know let's assume that we have a
pair XY that are different that are
between zero and AB which have both of
their pairs of remainders exactly
identical and let's produce a
contradiction.
So you know if we have such a pair XY
then what I claim
is that uh you know X minus Y
uh wait which way do I want to say this?
Oh sorry other way around a divides X -
Y.
Uh why is that true?
So we're assuming that this statement is
false. Why is it true that uh a divides
x minus y?
What does it mean for these two things
to be equal? Definitely their first
components have to be equal.
So if remainder of x / a is equal to the
remainder of y / a then that means that
they differ by an integer multiple of a.
So a divides their difference. Right?
This is the same type of thing we did
before. And similarly we know that b
divides
x minus y as well. Right?
And now here's the key, you know, idea.
We somehow have to use the fact that A
and B are relatively prime.
We know by assumption that the GCD of A
and B is equal to one.
And what this tells us
it means that AB
the pair of them divides x - y.
So this is the key thing. This isn't
always true. You know if I had two
things I had like um
I don't know uh six and nine. If I knew
that six divided my integer and nine
divided my integer, it would not imply
that 54 divides my integer because maybe
I only have two powers of three sitting
in there. But the key point is that
because both a and b are relatively
prime, the only way that they both
divide xus y is if their product divides
xus y as well. So you can think about
this in the case where like a and b are
not just relatively prime but they're
prime. Like our in our example with five
and seven. If five divides your integer
and seven divides your integer, there's
no choice. 35 has to divide your integer
too. That's basically what the statement
is saying, right? And this is the key
step because now we're in good shape,
right?
And so you know if AB divides X - Y I
claim this is a contradiction.
So someone make me happy tell me what
the statement contradicts. See the the
you know the statements I've made are
not very complicated but the logic is
subtle. Right? I wanted to prove that
star was true. So I assumed it's not
true. I assumed that there was a
different pair xy
where uh there were both between zero
and a minus and ab um where a divides
their difference and b divides their
difference. And I concluded that ab must
divide their difference. But now I claim
I'm done and I've actually contradicted
something.
Um, if X and Y are different, then they
will then they have to be off by at
least AB.
>> That's exactly right. That's right. If X
and Y are different and are between zero
and AB, they cannot differ by a multiple
of AB. That's impossible.
It's the same type of logic we used
earlier. So this contradicts what we
started off with. And what this means is
that you know hence the Chinese
remainder theorem is true.
So very very clever proof.
Okay, make sense.
And if you have any questions about
these things, you should sit down and
make sure that you can reconstruct the
logic yourself. You know, this proof and
the proof of lema one are not hard, but
really, you know, one of the things of
doing proofbased math is it's one thing
to be able to verify line by line the
steps as someone is giving them to you,
but to really understand, you know, it
in, you know, uh, deeply, you have to
check whether or not you can reconstruct
these things yourself. You know, these
types of things often happen on tests
where you think that you understood
something, but when you're forced to
come up with it yourself, it's much
harder. So that's just a piece of
advice. Yeah.
>> Okay. So the solution exists at all. Um
so the point is that uh you know every
pair that's a good question, right? So
we know that uh you know there are n
there are ab choices for n and there are
ab choices for st.
Now if every choice of n gets mapped to
some choice of st right and what we just
proved is that they don't collide ever.
So what this really means is that we can
draw this bipartite graph right here
where these are all of the values of n.
These are all the different possible
pairs st and every n gets mapped to some
value st just by taking the remainder
modulo a and modulo b. And so what this
proof just showed is that there are no x
and y that map to the same thing. If
there are no X and Y that map to the
same thing and they're the same size,
there's no choice, but everything maps
to exactly one thing and that means
everything has a solution and we can go
back and forth. Good. Very good
question. There's also another way to
answer your question which is the way
that I will do next. So, thanks for the
segue. Uh that'll be our last math topic
for today before I tell you an
application.
Um, see the same way like you know it
was one thing to ask this question about
whether or not every integer has a
multiplicative inverse modulo prime and
then we asked for more because we not
only wanted that the answer was yes. We
wanted to actually find what that
multiplicative inverse is. Right? And
you know the even stronger thing we
could ask for is okay the Chinese
remainder theorem is true. Hooray. But
maybe we can also ask whether we can
find the solution.
So how can we actually find n? In our
case, n was you know 29. So how can we
find n, right? And so here's you know
the stepbystep procedure for how we
would do it. So first thing
is that we write
n is equal to k b + t right so this is
just the statement that if I take n and
divide it by b the leftover will be t
and I don't know what k is so this just
captures you know one of my modular
equations the second one right and we
know that
A
is going to be between zero and A just
because we know that our answer, you
know, is supposed to be at most AB,
right?
And so what we can do
is we can take this expression which is
just an integer expression. There's no
modulus here. And we can take the we can
take mods on both sides. We know that um
this implies that uh k b + t is
congruent to s
mod a. This was our first equation and
now this was our second equation and
these modular constraints right because
this unknown integer n we know it should
be equal to t mod b and same thing it
should be equal to s mod a right and so
what this implies now if we just
rearrange things is that kb is equal to
s minus t mod a. So, you know, just to
emphasize, we know S and we know T
because those are the constraints in our
system of modular equations. And what
we're looking for is what K is, right?
So, now does anyone have any ideas how
we might uh solve
this equation to figure out what K is?
So, what's the key idea? How can we
solve this equation?
Perfect. That's right. We can just
multiply by the multiplicative inverse
of B which why does it exist? Because
the GCD of B and A is one by assumption.
So we know from the extended uklidian
algorithm that the multiplicative
inverse exists and we can find it. So in
particular we can solve this equation
and we get that K is congruent to B
inverse S minus T and this all happens
mod A right
we know B inverse exists and because K
is between zero and A well K is actually
equal to its remainder so this just is
the answer right here right so we can
actually compute K using this assumption
that uh you know k is between zero and
a.
So in the last four minutes I'm going to
tell you a really cool application.
Um this is somehow like a baby version I
made up of like a more real application.
Um
but let me tell you about it.
So, last time for my demo, I asked you
guys, "What are embarrassing movies you
like?" And I got, you know, much less
exciting answers than I usually get. So,
you guys got to work on that. But, uh,
how many people here stream stuff
online?
There are people who didn't put their
hands up. [laughter]
How many people stream stuff online?
How many people stream stuff illegally
online?
Oh, I saw you. Okay. [laughter]
Okay. So, let me tell you about a cool
application which has to do with
streaming, which is something related to
fountain codes. Surely fountain codes
are a whole topic in their own right.
And this is a hugely simplified version,
but imagine I've got some giant file n
and I have not just uh you know I'm I'm
representing the contents of the file as
some gigantic integer. So this is a
truly huge integer, right? Not one I'd
want to compute its factorization for by
hand or anything. But now I have not
just one person but many people
streaming, right? Maybe it just came out
like a new season of Stranger Things or
something and everyone's trying to
stream the same same thing. And you
know, one of the ways that you can
reconstruct the file is imagine, you
know, I'm just going to sit out there
broadcasting a bunch of snippets of the
message. So what my snippets are going
to look like is it's going to look like
some modulus
um you know A1 and then I'll take the
remainder of N divided by A1 and I'll do
this for a whole different choice of
these AI. So I'll choose a whole bunch
of primes AI. I'll tell you what the
prime is and then I'll tell you the
modulus. you know what the file contents
look like as a huge integer modulo uh
a1. Okay, so you know how can you
reconstruct the file?
So once you have you've received some
set of the uh messages these are what
you've received
as long as the product of the ais is
larger than n. That's really the
generalization of the Chinese remainder
theorem where I just had two factors a
and b. But as soon as I have the product
of these ais is larger than n, then the
same type of thing works and I can use
the Chinese remainder theorem to
reconstruct what n is. But now the
really cool thing about it which
explains like fountain codes is you have
all these people streaming and you know
maybe it's like a one gig file but
they're all not streaming at the same
time. So what you can do is you can just
broadcast these messages perpetually.
It's like a water fountain that's, you
know, um, always spraying water and
everyone comes there and as soon as they
fill up their one gig of data, they can
reconstruct the file, it doesn't
actually matter which one gig of data
they get. So these kinds of things are
very effective ways of sending one thing
to many parties. when those same
parties, you know, are listening in and
getting different uh snippets of the
code, they'll still be able to recover
it because they've all filled up their
ngene bottle with the one gig. So, this
is a very simplified version of what
fountain codes are because really you
care about things like errors in the
messages, but you can already see why
things like the Chinese remainder
theorem and modular arithmetic are
extremely powerful. So next time on
Thursday, we're going to be starting uh
group theory and we'll talk a little bit
more about, you know, modular
arithmetic, especially the parts we need
for crypto. But uh see you all then. All
right.