okay so our next speaker is U Professor
uh Antonia May and uh she's a
Chancellor's fellow and the senior
lecturer or um assist associate
professor in the school of chemistry at
the University of Edinburg and she will
um okay let's wait a little bit for the
slide to pull up um but she has done a
lot of amazing work on drug drug design
and um today um yeah we will hear a lot
from her about her work good afternoon
everyone uh first of all thank you very
much to the organizers for inviting me
and giving me the opportunity to speak
here today um second of all maybe a bit
of a controversial uh talk topic uh it
wasn't quite what was in the program I
think it never made it into the program
so um basically hopefully in the next 15
minutes 20 minutes I'm going to talk
about what my group's been doing in in
the space of both sort of generative
modeling and um machine learning and how
we've been using Lang anguage models um
or how useful language models are in in
this um area all right thankfully um
we've already had a nice introduction in
terms of um drug design so we can do
high through pit screening we can do
fragment based drug design um in the end
what we want is some kind of compound
that works well in our Target protein
and of course we can optimize various
different properties um adme properties
but also binding Affinity so we kind of
want some in silico scen screening way
of being able to elaborate either a
fragment or uh find a good hit molecule
from our high throughput
screening so what are the methods you
can do this with so one of the things
we've been looking at is active learning
um Active Learning particularly looking
at sort of compound libraries that are
similar so you can use things like uh
relative binding free energy predictions
and you can iteratively label your
library of lians you want want to score
and then figure out which one might be
the best
compound another way of doing it is if
you have a generative model you need to
somehow figure out how good that
molecule is binding into your binding
pocket so typically what we've been
doing there is just looking at docking
scores um and as we've just learned from
the previous talk they might be slightly
dodgy and we'll see similar results in
in in a few slides
so because we're kind of looking at a
different ways of uh model
things looking at libraries but also at
generative design I thought I'll give a
brief highlight in terms of what we've
been doing in terms of fragment uh based
design for generative modeling so this
is work done by Nicholas runi who is in
my group um as a master student and
things that are being picked up now by
uh Oro patnik who's uh been working on
this and the idea is that we're using a
diffusion model um so typically in a
diffusion model you train um on on a
data set by adding noise and then you
learn the reverse process to generate
samples so we train a model and then we
generate a bunch of samples
unfortunately cats can't quite cure um
diseases yet so we probably want to
sample molecules instead of cats um but
still we have a problem because now
we've just generated a bunch of
molecules most of them are probably
going to be garbage cannot be
synthesized as we've learned um so this
might not be a super gen genius strategy
to actually do things in in in this way
so is there way in which we can actually
refine our model such that we can
generate something we're actually
interested in and want so again uh image
uh machine learning uh to the rescue we
can use things like refinement so we can
actually post um training refine our
model to kind of guide it in the way we
want it to go so here's an example of
generating caffeine uh using a diffusion
model so that is fueling uh the
scientist but still not quite a drug uh
but it means we have fairly stable
control over how we are interacting with
the diffusion model and what kind of
molecules we can
get so in terms of um fragment based
design what can we do in this setting so
here's an example of two fragments um
bound to imbh and the question is how
can we link these fragments so we're
using this refinement approach for uh
our pre-trained diffusion model and we
can actually generate linkers quite
easily uh you could also use a genetic
algorithm to do that uh but I guess the
whole fun part about machine learning is
trying new tools and see if they do
better than existing tools um so what we
can do well in this case we actually
took a very conservative sample of a
th000 molecules that took about 22
minutes so we're still not super fast
with sampling uh then we can do a bunch
of filtering um and we end up with 112
molecules that are good in the sense of
they fit The Binding site there's no
weird strain they are sensible molecules
based on a set of filtering criteria um
now I don't have a massive wet lab where
I can go and test things but the nice
thing is we took this example from the
literature and in these 112 molecules we
actually recovered two compounds that
were tested in the lab and they had nice
um affinity so one of the things we're
trying to do now is actually use this
prospectively not just retrospectively
but at least it's quite promising that
in this particular case we managed to
recover something that people medicinal
chemists had come up with and tested in
the lab and had good Affinity so that's
kind of where we're there where we're at
now so that leaves us with
well if we can't afford to go in the lab
can we actually use um a model that
allows us to predict how well our
generated compounds or compounds from a
compound Library can bind and this is
kind of where my my background comes in
so I came into all of this from a
molecular Dynamics angle so we've been
looking a lot at these alchemical free
energy types of calculations we're
running MD simulations and then try and
figure out from these MD simulations how
well a protein and ligan binds so that
is a fairly costly method it works well
with uh con generic series if we have
non- congeneric series we learned
earlier today there are new methods that
that are great but in general MD takes a
bit of time and you might not be able to
score I don't know a billion compounds
so um you could do docking um as we've
just learned docking isn't necessarily
super reliable um or you can use machine
learning and now there's the question
are these machine learning models that
have been coming out actually any useful
and this is kind of um similar in the
veins of what Pat Walters has been
saying this morning we can test whether
the way we think about it is the same
way you think about it in terms of how
we should be assessing these models
because what is happening is we have a
large set of data um we evaluate the
model on the data and then we have a
nice table and then go okay we have a
great performing model but that doesn't
really get us to the point where we're
like hey I have a particular Target and
I want to know how that works so so
here's a non-n naming and shaming table
you would typically find um and if we're
just looking at some of the the data
entry so all of these rows are different
machine learning models for binding
Affinity predictions and you've got uh
High correlation low root means root
means square error but how different are
they really does the Bold number
actually mean anything there's no error
bars on this so we have no way of
actually telling whether one model is
better than another they're all
evaluated on pdb coret well that's great
but the test data has many different
targets in there so is that really the
kind of question we're trying to answer
so if we're trying to answer I want to
pick my favorite machine learning model
I want to score my compound library and
I want to score it against a particular
Target am I going to get there with this
because based on that I can probably
pick any of them and they should all do
really well right so how well do they
actually do well here's an example of
one we've looked at um this is just out
of curiosity if we try and generate a
model ourselves how how good does such a
model work uh how well does it work so
um these are three variants of the model
we get high correlation uh that's all
great now You observe here I say random
here at the bottom so that's a random
test training
split that's fantastic but it doesn't
help us with my particular Target
example so if I've already seen the
Target in the training data then
probably I'm going to do quite well uh
so if we do different splits like cold
Target cold drug cold scaffold you end
up losing your ability to actually be
predictive um so you need to be careful
in which way you actually work with a
data um so and that is true for all the
the metrics and also observe now because
I've put some error bars on these I can
actually distinguish my different model
and go like there's a significant
difference between them and whether they
are useful or not is that the way to go
probably still not quite so right now
we've Amalgamated all of our protein and
liand binding Affinity data and
effectively what we've done is plotted
this plot and worked out the pierc and
correlation coefficient so we have
experimental PKD versus predicted PKD
and then based on that we can work out
our spearm and correlation coefficient
great so that's what we've done does
that help us with the Target no
um if we look at one target we can we
can look at the scatter that's kind of
similar so that's great but if we look
at a different one we might actually
have a negative correlation and it's not
very uh predictive in terms of rank and
we might have another one so really
looking at just the scatter of this is
not going to give us anything useful
instead we should look at a different
way of combining uh our individual
Target predictions using a Fisher
transform and that fisher transform
basically basically allows us to get a
much more reliable error estimate on how
how good our spread is in the data
versus just looking at the overall
scatter this is nothing new in fact Pat
has written a blog post about this in
2019 uh particularly looking at the sort
of free energy community at the time
where people were compain comparing um
Affinity predictions across many targets
and benchmarks and um I think this is
still true and we're not doing
for for
here so what is the model I've been
showing you well this is now the uh
language models uh so they're not large
language models what we're looking at is
uh protein language models so we have
protein sequence uh and then a um
embedding or protein encoding that that
results from from from this embedding
using a language model and we have smile
strings and the same thing and then what
the model is doing is we're basically
projecting onto a a cosine uh space and
looking at distances between protein and
Lian space uh that means if a li uh has
a good binding Affinity it kind of moves
closer to the protein space if you think
of it in that way whereas if it has a
bad binding Affinity it moves away uh
how does this work in practice so the
architecture is using um an esm2 model
and the Keta model and then we've
actually put some um parameter efficient
fine-tuning adapters on each of them so
we actually can individually fine-tune
our language models in order to be um
getting better at actually capturing
capturing this um so now what are the
different bars I've shown earlier the
the parameter efficient fine tune model
plus this balm binding Affinity uh model
is is the dark bar this is a baseline
model the the Grays basically just
concatenating our protein and ligin
Coatings and using uh multi-layer
perceptron in order to get your readout
for the affinity and then the middle one
is just the balm without the fine
tuning Okay so we've generated a new
model it's another black uh box uh no a
black number in in in our table um well
I want to know how good is this model in
a sort of real scenario so uh we now
look at a different
uh set of splits so the the training was
done on this leaky pdb bind um and now
we're actually looking at different
Target families so how good does it
perform across different Target families
and how good does it perform in
comparison to docking so if we learned
that docking is random uh well maybe
this is also random we'll see but
effectively um what we now see is the
the blue dots are the the language model
the trained language model the the um
orange ones is the docking for this
particular family of proteins then
chapon targets again the the B model
seems to be doing quite well but then
there's also again examples where
actually docking seems to be doing
better so you really can't just put
everything into one pot and get a
guaranteed working model they will work
differently across uh different targets
so now um if I want to look at my
overall correl coefficients and root me
square error um I need to average over
them not by just adding them but using
my Fisher information so now I can look
at my Spearman row or my person R versus
the the different um tools we're using
so we've got done docking with Vina and
arock um and then uh the model we've got
is this model better than these
models I I don't know because we're not
looking at the same things am I going to
rerun all of this no probably not um but
I think at least in this way I've now
can convincingly say I know for
particular T classes this model will
probably do quite well for other ones it
probably will not do well um is it
learning the right thing maybe um
something to look into so the last thing
I want to mention is zero shot learning
and few shot learning so um very briefly
I talked about Active Learning so you
can use active learning to score here uh
we were thinking what if we could use
something like this in in an active
learning situation so here is a usp7
target that was not in the training set
at all and we actually get pretty
reasonable statistics if we look at the
the scatter but if we now take 10 or 20%
of the data and do few shot learning we
actually get a much better uh
correlation the interesting thing is if
we now take the same data and train a
gan process um we get almost better
correlation so what does that tell us
well in some cases the Gan process is
better in some cases it isn't because
the gaan process requires you to make um
a decision about the embeddings and
depending on the embedding you choose
you get similar performance to the model
we've been training if you choose a bad
embedding it actually is worse and you
can't know this a priori so it depends
it's not the same across all Targets
it's going to be different across
targets so yeah future toning can
improve performance um but gausian
process models perform similar in
certain situations so this kind of gets
me to the end if you're interested in
how this works all of uh that model is
online um and can be tried out it would
be great to kind of hear what you think
about it um I think in terms of what
I've talked about so we can do fragment
link in with diffusion models uh getting
meaningful data splits is important um
and language models can be used to uh
predict affinities so kind of like a
scoring function um the last thing I
want to mention before acknowledgements
is if you work in this field and you
have interesting um best practices
tutorials Lessons Learned please
consider the living Journal of
computational molecular science uh I'm
an editor for it if you want to know
more please come and talk to me about it
if you do open source software consider
Joss uh another nice uh Journal both of
these are diamond open accents so
nonprofit and ultra low cost for both
reader and author with that I would like
to acknowledge Rohan and AO who did most
of the work and my group and you for
your attention thank
you great thanks for the awesome talk uh
any questions uh you can come to the uh
mics I have one we have um maybe two or
three minutes uh but I have a question
on have you tried uh with more like
decoys because I feel like a lot of
times we have um different scenarios
right we um in the lead optimization
stage we care more about correlation
because we want to boost up the Affinity
but in the kind of the virtual screening
case when we have a lot of negatives um
have you looked at more example for
example like the top hit rate like
enrichment type of thing um
um so so I mean I mean the the the data
set has both binders and non-binders in
it right so in that sense um that
information is there we've not
specifically looked at this no um I know
there's work out in that direction but
no we have not okay okay there's there's
please go ahead thanks it's a wonderful
talk um you at one point differentiated
between large language models
and I guess just language models could
you elaborate on that a little more it
seems like that there's a lot of
resources being poured into large
language models as we know yeah okay so
so I I think maybe my uh terminology was
a bit wishy-washy so I guess large
language models typically we think of
chat jpt um those kind of type of models
Lama whatever Gemini you name it so
that's trained on um language um and
text that is widely available uh here we
look at um
um language models that use similar
architecture to these larger language
models but are trained on sequence um
and um smile strings so the idea there
is that we we have much more information
in sequence databases and smiles
databases than 3D structural information
so
um we wanted to see what if we fine tune
based on then um Affinity data can we
get a signal out or is it all garbage
effectively but yeah and and is there a
difference then between say tuning a
large language model on the exact data
set you say in and starting yeah so so
basically the the so we do two types of
fine-tuning so we have these uh PFT
adapters which are basically taking the
pre-trained model and just um optimizing
it a little bit in the training process
and then we have this uh F shot training
where basically we leave the most of it
intact and just look at the projection
layers and unfreeze some some weights
there and retrain that bit so there's
different parts where you can basically
unfreeze and and and retrain depending
on on your desires but yeah thank
you nice talk with these language models
and F shot techniques I think it's
difficult to not fool yourself and just
create a really elaborate similarity
search so so did you do controls on this
and did you say great instead of zero
shot I'm just going to do KN andn with k
equals 1 and do the lookups and just do
the
comparisons so so we looked at um
molecular weight comparisons effectively
um I don't think we have the the plots
that really show this but I think we
should do that yeah I mean I think just
doing a a simple similarity search
comparison and convincing yourself that
you're not just creating a very fancy
lookup table yeah no I think there's the
I think this is why we looked at the
gussian processes because to me that is
already like a slightly fancier version
of a lookup table Yeah and because they
seem to work surprisingly well
um yeah no that is a concern 100% okay
thanks thank you yeah uh with that let's
give our speaker one more round of
applause