Good morning everybody. Welcome to the
MPG primer. We have Raymond Walters
talking about heritability of common
complex traits. Uh he is an instructor
in investigation in the analytic and
translational genetics unit at MGH and a
group leader in the Stanley Center for
Psychiatric Research here at the Broad
Institute. He joined the Broad in 2014
as a postoc with Dr. Benjamin Neil after
completing his PhD in quantitative
psychology at the University of Notre
Dame. Dr. Walters has extensive
experience in large-scale analysis of
human genomic data sets including as a
lead analyst in the psychiatric genomics
consortium and multiple projects
investigating patterns of heritability,
missingness and late infecture
structures across the UK bio bank. Um,
thank you Raymond.
Thank you. Um good morning everyone. Uh
going to dive in this morning to the fun
topic of heritability. Uh mostly in the
context of uh complex common complex
traits the oh at least the initial
things we talk about generalized to kind
of all traits. Um but gonna spend the
time this morning kind of starting from
just kind of as a theoretical concept
what do we mean by heritability and then
spend a fair amount of time talking
about how we actually go about
estimating that quantity um and some
results of what that looks like in
practice. um and then a little bit of
time at the end to kind of further
motivate like even if this quantity I
introduce of heritability isn't
necessarily of interest to you itself
the ways in which it informs kind of
other directions within genetics
research. Uh so kicking off the the top
on just what do we mean by heritability
kind of the the very old and kind of
very qualitative observation is simply
that children resemble their parents.
This kind of continues over generations
within families. So some idea of there
being inheritance of traits and so that
trait is heritable. You can inherit it
from your
parents. and kind of early statements
about thinking about this as a more
quantitative idea go back to kind of
like the earliest concepts of regression
and work by Golton and others kind of
just making the statement more formal
that for example if you look at the
height of a child relative to the
average height of their parents that you
do see a relationship there in this kind
of regression style and then thinking
about what that means for how much of
that trait is inherited versus coming
from other sources.
And so to kind of formalize that into a
mathematical quantity, at least in some
intuitive sense, we can think about any
given human phenotype as being some
combination of a genetics piece and an
environmental piece. Uh and then the
heritability from that simple model is
simply saying how much of that overall
variation in the phenotype comes from
that genetic piece as opposed to that
environmental piece. So kind of
splitting up that pie chart of the kind
of total variability in that observed
trait. Um and that very simple
conception that everything else we'll
talk about rests on makes a lot of kind
of simple intuitive sense until we have
to start dealing with a lot of kind of
the mathematical things that pop up out
of this being an
oversimplification. And so to maintain
that definition of heritability, we have
to make decisions about what do we do if
that genetics risk for the phenotype and
the environmental risk for a phenotype
are correlated or if they interact. And
so we could choose to take this in a
direction of that genetics piece being
just some sort of causal definition of
the genetics
um and thinking about some kind of true
underlying causal effect sizes there. Or
we could think about this in terms of
the maximal variance explained by a
genetic risk
prediction. Um, and essentially the
environment then becomes the residual
the for what could be explained by the
genetics regardless of kind of the
underlying causal mechanisms there. And
we'll we'll see that pop up as we get
into actual methods for trying to
estimate this quantity.
The the other thing that emerges just
from looking at this definition is that
these are quantities that aren't
necessarily stable across time and place
or even how you measure a given
phenotype. Uh in that if the environment
changes if suddenly there is like an
increase in the variability of
environmental risks towards a phenotype
that'll shift the heritability because
now as a proportion of that total
variability the genetic contribution has
shrunk. Similarly, if as population
demographics shift over time or you look
in a different population, the
variability of that genetic component
may differ due to drift and al
frequencies, selection, assorted mating,
all these kind of population genetics
forces that will also change that
heritability. And so what we have is a
like parameter that describes a fraction
of a trait that might be attributable in
some way to genetics, but that is very
much going to be attached to a given
population at a given time and place.
And so uh while it's easy to fall into
the idea of thinking about like there
being a heritability of your favorite
trait, so like the heritability of
height is 80% or something like that,
that is very much a contextual statement
rather than some fixed statement about
the trait.
Um the another thing we'll run into with
this definition is and you may already
be catching on to if you've seen
discussion of heritability before. I've
written this with a capital H. Uh but
most of the times you'll see
heritability kind of the notation with a
lowercase H. This reflects that we have
to make a decision um about what all is
captured in the types of genetics we're
going to include in that numerator of
this fraction. And as especially in the
Goss era but even before that um often
we talk about heritability in a slightly
narrower sense than what is this broad
sense
heritability and so in particular
there's kind of a range here starting
from that broadest sense where when we
say we're going to say genetics means
all of genetics but we can quickly kind
of subset that to well all of genetics
is computationally hard and there's some
benefits to simplifying it too. We'll
just talk about additive effects of
genetics because that's easier to
estimate. And so that's that's what that
the lowercase H square comes from is
that narrower sense of just the additive
contribution of
genetics.
Um getting below that and is as we've
gotten to being able to do genetics
directly off of measured genetics as
opposed to inferring it from things like
family structure.
uh we can think about the the genetic
contribution that is coming just from
common varants and uh or or common snips
and so the kind of standard notation
that's emerged in the field for that is
this H square subg
um just to note that kind of common
genetic piece and so leaving aside that
like we're going to get to estimation
methods that are using GWS data and so
don't capture necessarily CMVs maybe
aren't capturing the contribution of
rare variants or especially denovo vari
variants which are kind of in this weird
space of like they're a genetic
component but they're not inherited so
do we want them in the definition anyway
um so that kind of shift and then if you
go back
to some of the early days of G-W was
there was also some discussion of these
later two uh quantities thinking of kind
of the variance explained by a PRS or
the variance explained by top
significant lossi energy was as kind of
a heritability like quantity
in the sense that they very directly are
this kind of ratio of like what's
explained by that more directly measured
observable genetics relative to the
phenotype but now less a theoretical
quantity about kind of overall
contribution of genetics and more a
directly observed quantity off of some
specific attempt at measuring genetic
risk via PRS or from uh some individual
let's say and so I I ordered them this
way in part because there is a strict
ordering of these quantities and so the
heritability will range between zero and
one because it's a fraction of that
total variability. But the narrow sense
heritability has to be less than or
equal to the broad sense heritability in
that either all the effects are additive
or there are some additive effects and
then there's some fraction beyond that
from dominance effects or other such
things um that would make the broad
sense be larger than the narrow sense
and that kind of continues them this
chain. Um, so those are all different
versions of how to define the
heritability. There's another problem
that arises for many of the traits we
care about in that this kind of idea of
separating the variance into a genetic
piece and a non- genetic piece doesn't
immediately translate to the variance of
a binary phenotype just because a binary
phenotypes variance is a function of its
mean and doesn't have this natural
partitioning in some like additive
linear model kind of sense.
And so the classic solution has been to
imagine uh as kind of already exists for
things like logistic or probit
regression that there's some underlying
continuum of risk that is a continuous
value that we refer to as the liability
for that phenotype. Um and then we can
talk about the heritability of that
continuous liability as reflecting the
heritability that we care about. Um
rather than the heritability defined
directly off of the
uh directly off of the the observed
phenotype. Um and so kind of graphically
the the idea here is um uh starting in
that top panel. So if we have the
combination of a distribution that is
the environmental effect and the
distribution that is the genetic effect.
I'll just get the cursor so I can
actually gesture this. Perfect. So an
environmental piece and a genetic piece
that combine into some population
distribution that is continuous like
this. And the thing that matters to the
phenotype is the combination of them
here. And so, oh, if we had a continuous
phenotype, this might be directly the
observed phenotype. But for um a binary
phenotype, we'll imagine that this is
some unobserved underlying liability.
And then so for that binary phenotype
where the statement is that that same
kind of combination of environmental and
genetic risk combining into uh kind of
the observed phenotype, it still exists.
But now what we observe instead of that
smooth continuation is simply the
distinction between uh these points in
black and these points in red based on
uh cases being above some threshold in
that continuum. And so that kind of
mathematical slide of hand solves our
question about how to define
heritability uh for a binary trait. Um
the other way you can think about this
if you prefer the kind of equation
statement is that we do the swap to that
uh the phenotype that is genetics type
plus environment is uh the liability and
what we observe is a function of that
liability being above above or below
that
threshold.
Um, so putting all those pieces together
and trying to summarize like what is
what are you talking about with
heritability that we're focused on that
idea of a proportion of variation in a
trait that comes from or is explained by
genetics. This is again a population
parameter in that you know can shift
based on how we measure the phenotype
and who we measured it in and the forces
happening in that population. Um, and
kind of depending on our decisions about
how exactly to define that genetic piece
versus that environment piece, it might
make sense to think about this as like a
causal proportion of the the phenotype.
But it may also make more sense to just
think about it as the most you could
explain by the best possible genetics
predictor, possibly subsetting to say
common variance or, you know, observed
variance in some way. that is kind of
the population level observed underlying
like best possible prediction
level. Uh what that means for what it is
not is that it's not a statement about
how mutable the phenotype would be over
possible interventions or amount of
variability that could exist in uh
shifts in the environment.
Um, this was there's a lot of good
literature trying to hash out kind of
the theoretical statements of this,
especially out of the sociology
literature and especially around debates
over the heritability of things like
intelligence. Um, and perhaps the the
cleanest summary I've uh heard goes back
to this favorite from Goldberger who
remarks that we could find that the the
heritability of say eyes height maybe
approaches 100%. practice it probably
doesn't. But for sake of argument, we
could say it does. But that wouldn't
mean that we necessarily need to give up
on the idea of making glasses for
people. Like we, you know, just because
a biological phenomena has some
contribution of genetics and some
variability in the population doesn't
really speak to the opportunity to
intervene on it. It's simply a measure
of the variability as it exists at the
moment. The other thing is because it's
a population parameter, it doesn't tell
you anything really about the difference
between populations. Like you other than
that you could say that the heritability
in some population for a phenotype is
higher or lower than in a different
population for that same phenotype. That
doesn't tell you about whether observed
phenotypic differences between those
populations are due to genetics or not
because it's a within population
parameter rather than a between
population parameter.
Um so all those are statements about
kind of heritability as a theoretical
quantity. Um and now we can get into in
practice how do we actually go about
trying to estimate this
quantity. Um and that estimation
historically started in the same place
the observation about what we even mean
by this concept of variability did which
is with that resemblance within
families. Um and so in particular the
kind of quantitative way to get there so
keeping our same model that we're
talking about the phenotype that has
genetics and environment in it. If we
have a pair of people the similarity in
their phenotype should reflect the
combination of how similar their genetic
risk for that phenotype is and how
similar their environmental contribution
to that phenotype is. mathematical
arrangement gives you that the
heritability lives as coefficients on
kind of those pieces and assembling a
total
correlation. And for related pairs of
individuals, we don't actually need to
observe their genetics directly to know
at least in expectation how similar
their genetics are simply as a by virtue
of their relatedness.
This is a slightly easier statement to
make for like common complex traits
where we expect that the kind of overall
relatedness for a pair of individuals
should fairly directly translate to how
similar they are on the genetic
component for any given phenotype just
because polygenist exists. Um it gets uh
the the level of certainty of there gets
much less certain once you're talking
um uh mandelian phenotypes where like
the the level of expectation is the same
but the amount of variability and uh
between uh individuals with the same
level of relatedness
uh um how often they'll have that kind
of same amount of sharing will be yeah
assumption here is just that this is all
multivaried Gaussian right that goes
into this. So this is just like a large
locus large number of locus assumption.
Yeah, that same way works better in
complex traits. That's the assumption.
Yeah, that one it's a large number of
lowi that kind of central limit theorem
kind of mini loi contribution gets you
there. You don't have to make that
assumption because even in mandelian
inheritance in expectation that
correlation works out the same. It's
just that you don't have the kind of
nice law large numbers kind of behavior
for getting
there.
Cool. Uh so with that kind of intuition,
the kind of canonical example of how
this has been gone about is thinking
about
this within families or especially
within twins. And so the idea here is
that kind of schematically
um if you think about pairs of
individuals based on the nature of their
relationship is kind of drawn out along
the the x-axis of this this diagram here
kind of the more related you are
especially for for twin pairs. If a
trait is heritable, you should see that
that phenotype is more similar between
those pairs of individuals versus if a
phenotype isn't heritable, then kind of
regardless of how similar the
individuals are genetically, the traits
only being driven by environmental
features. And so, oh, you'll just have
some kind of average background of uh
similarity in phenotype that's
essentially null.
And so you could do this with the full
spectrum of relatedness, but turns out
you can get there fairly easily just
with twin pairs uh that are either
identical twins or uh fraternal or
dygotic twins. And so I won't belabor
stepping through all the math, but
essentially the idea here is is that the
identical twins will share all of their
genetics. The dygotic twins will share
half of their genetics on average um as
any siblings
would. We'll make an assumption that the
similarity in the environment between a
pair of twins is the same regardless of
whether they're identical twins or
they're zygotic twins. It's a rather
questionable assumption but is the
common assumption that gets us to the
easiest estimator. And so in that
scenario, the heritability emerges as
simply the difference uh as a function
of the difference in the correlation
between pairs of twins that are
monozygotic versus ones that are
digygotic. Um because you have that
difference and how genetically similar
they are, we can subtract out away that
kind of equivalent environmental piece
and get to just an estimate of the
heritability. And so kind of as an old
so simple version of getting there um
you get an estimate like
this. Um you know there's much room to
generalize upon that model and get more
sophisticated. Um so often this will get
represented in terms of something like
the the ACE model where we now have an
additive genetic component, a dominance
genetic component, a shared common
environment piece and a unique
environment or residual error term for
each individual phenotype and we can set
expectations about how correlated
between the individuals each of those
species should be. So the the dominance
piece will behave different than an
additive piece. which room to allow
variability on what that shared
environment looks like, especially as
you incorporate dzygotic twins versus
other forms of siblings versus cousins.
You can extend this with individuals
from those other forms of relatedness.
Um, and they, you know, essentially get
to more sophisticated estimation off
that same basic uh familial form of
thinking about
heritability. All that is done without
observing the genetic data though. And
so we now have many methods that work
with data that we can observe genotype
and attack this question of how much
genetic contribution to phenotype there
is in other ways. This list isn't
exhaustive but but is intended to just
give you a flavor of is kind of the
diversity of methods that that exist.
There's a wide range. Um, and so for for
today, I'm going to talk mostly just
about to these two that are probably the
the most common in circulation and kind
of provide a good reference point for
many of the other methods here. Um, but
what I'm talking about by no means is
exhaustive for the different ways that
have been proposed for estimating
heritability.
Um so starting with this method called
greml um which comes from it's a
restricted maximum likelihood estimate
using genetic relatedness. And so it
emerges from ex that exact same idea
that existed for our twin or family
based estimation that more related
individuals will be more phenotypically
similar proportional to how heritable
the phenotype is. but says instead of
working at the extreme of um like
perfectly related twins, can we do that
with nominally unrelated individuals
based on the kind of much more subtle
variation in people who are slightly
more genetically similar than average or
slightly less genetically similar than
average. Um, and when you play that idea
out, the the model that you kind of get
to is that you essentially say that the
that variation across individuals in the
phenotype. Um, and the similarity or
dissimilarity between those individuals
is a function of kind of a residual
error term that is I that is independent
across those unrelated individuals. And
then this genetic component that is
proportional to the gen observed genetic
relatedness between those people based
on a genetic relatedness matrix
estimated from you know estimates of IBD
and genetic sharing. And so
um while what the the literal estimation
of that VA maximum likelihood isn't
quite the regression shown here,
conceptually they end up in a very
similar place and that you have this
kind of narrow range of very small
genetic related assessments that are
slightly above or below zero and a
relationship to that for any given pair
of individuals to kind of how similar or
dissimilar their phenotype are on some
standardized scale. And the very very
subtle slope that does exist in that
line prod would give you an estimate of
heritability and conceptually that is
approximately what you're getting out of
the actual way that GCDA does this in a
maximum likelihood sense for fitting
that
model. And so, oh, kind of the key here
is as long as with your observed
genetics, you can make that estimate of
how genetically similar people are and
kind cross your fingers in the same way
we already discussed that you know,
especially for things that are polygenic
on average that you know observed amount
of little bit of higher or lower genetic
relatedness will track with the
phenotype because somewhere in that
estimate of the genetic relatedness is
the relatedness on the pieces of the
genetics that actually inform the trait.
Um and so this gives you um an estimate
off of that observed genetics of the
heritability.
Yeah. On the left that sorry
sorry on the left that that's the
variance coariance matrix in the
phenotypes or the uh in the equation.
Yeah the and the i that's is that's not
the identity matrix or it is the
identity matrix or just matrix of ones.
Uh it is the identity matrix.
So it's it's it's it turns into a
slightly weird statement. So the the
implied matrix on the left hand side is
n byn. So individual by
individual. In practice, the kind of
sufficient statistic observation there
ends up being just the crossroduct of
the two phenotypes between the two
individuals with some standardization
for for scale.
And so yeah, then you have a term that's
on that matrix of correlation in
genetics and a term of what is meant to
be correlation in environmental terms
that we take to be the identity matrix
and say that their environments are
independent since they're
unrelated. Cool.
Uh uh the other method I want to spend
some time talking about is called LD
score regression which takes a slightly
different tactic uh particularly living
within our GWS era and asks um so we
have G-W wases looking at the amount of
association of all of our common genetic
variants with a given trait here the the
example of the 2014 paper on
schizophrenia and so instead of looking
directly from how related individuals
are. Can we take our observation of the
amount of association signal in a G-W
was and turn that into an estimate of
heritability partially for the benefits
of being able to do this hopefully off
of just the G-W was results without
needing to refer back to the individual
level genotypes in a way that allows us
to keep up with say metaanalyses
um and maybe some lower computational
overhead. And so the intuition that
turned into LV scorecore regression um
was that if we imagine our our genome
here at toy genome of with 20 little
snips on it um and we we know that the
genome has this structure in terms of
blocks of linkage to
sigilum. Um and we'll we'll lay down
some blocks of that on our little toy
example here. Um and we have some snips
that aren't in LD with any of those
blocks. We'll call them lonely snips.
They have no friends. Um, and for sake
of illustration, we'll say that the the
snips in the LD blocks are all perfectly
correlated with one another. No
variability in that R square, just
perfect LD
blocks. Um and so we asked the question
of so if this is our toy little genome
and if polygenicity exists and there's
some set of causal variants that kind of
exist at random across her miniature
genome what might we observe in GWS
association and so if we play that out
we can say that well we had you know
there's a couple causal snips we'll say
at random they fall in these two
locations and so for GW was what we'd
observe is that for each of those causal
snips, all of the snips in that LD block
would show association in the G-W was.
We can't really differentiate which is a
causal variant because they're all
perfectly correlated. And so each of
those blocks would be fully associated.
The things not in those blocks would not
be
associated. But we're doing this kind of
at random. So, you know, you know, maybe
in a a different reality it look like
this or maybe in a different
equivalently structured section of the
genome. You see causal snippets in these
locations. And so again, you'd see their
corresponding LD blocks show
association. You wouldn't see
association elsewhere. We play this out
as kind of a random process that
continues to happen. Every once in a
while, we do actually hit one of those
lonely snips. And so, oh, it doesn't
show association for a block. We see
association just for that snip. Hooray.
But if we, you know, thought about that
process kind of happening at random at
large scale, what we'd observe is that
the likelihood that a given snip shows
up as associated with our phenotype in a
G-W was sense, would be proportional to
the size of the LD block it lives in or
how much genetic variation it's tagging
kind of equivalently there. And so it
turns out that that
observation with some simplifying
assumptions lets you derive a
mathematical expectation that the the
result in the G-W was represented here
kind of in the expectation of its
kaiquare statistic for a given snip is a
function of
uh some pieces that have to do with
confounding or population
stratification. But then a piece that is
related to that concept we just laid out
which is how much variation does that
snip tag. So in practice taken as the
sum of correlation of that snip J with
all all surrounding snips. And it turns
out that when you walk through that kind
of expectation that you have a piece
that is constant with respect to snip
because it is more about overall
inflation that's not a spec in the G-W
was that isn't related to LD and then
something that we you know if we think
of this as a regression equation would
be the slope attached to that
information about LD and that slope
happens to be a function of
heritability.
and sample size and number of snips
which are known quantities. And so we
can do this regression, get a slope and
turn that back into an estimate of
sniper
heritability. Um, and since the only
inputs here are G-W was information and
information about LD, which we could
pull from some reference panel without
needing to go back into individual level
data. We can do this just from the
information that's in the G-W was. And
it turns out that we can get this
estimator because there is a link
between that amount of signal in a G-W
was and the kind of and that overall
heritability under some
expectations. Didn't get good at time.
All right. So that's at least kind of
the main ways in which heritability
estimation has happened in the field.
What do these different approaches tell
us about heritability in our complex
traits?
And so kind of especially out of the
long history we have now of twin twin
family studies the kind of broad
takeaway has been the statement that's
uh you know been been described as the
first law of behavior genetics that
could probably also apply to kind of
human genetics at large which is that at
least as a first approximation all
traits are heritable.
um was kind of the rule of thumb that
people expected and kind of reviews of
the literature have upheld that idea. So
this is a review done about 10 years ago
now looking across about 50 years worth
of twin studies and meta analyzing as
much as possible within traits that have
been studied over that time. um and
found that kind of broadly across
phenotypic domains in these different
clusters of parts here that you see kind
of this moderate heritability often you
know either side of 0.5
um in the it's in the purple bars here
versus there's uh some information on uh
the kind of shared environment estimates
in those green bars can so kind of yeah
I had a question um earlier you
mentioned heritability as a population
level parameter. Have people made
similar plots for this for other
populations or should we assume this is
the white European
um estimates we're looking at? Yeah,
it's a good question. So, this
is the estimates in here include
estimates from multiple populations
going into these averages, but the
preponderance of those studies and so
the prepoundonderance of the weight in
the these values are coming from kind of
white European predominant populations.
[Music]
Um
the values do tend to be similar um up
to variations that are more study
specific factors but there's not like
broad differences I would say in terms
of the takeaways for different like
ancestral
populations. Um yeah so in these
different phenotypic domains you see
maybe some variability where some of the
more you know anthropometric or more
directly measured kind of phenotypes or
maybe slightly higher inheritability and
slightly lower for you know personality
or social values kind of phenotypes but
by and large strong heritability and
basically every type of measure we care
about in people.
Um and the same broad statement probably
applies to our estimates off of the
genetic data. So here looking at methods
with that LD uh estimates from that LD
score regression method applied to G-W
was in thousands of traits in UK bioank.
Uh the particular results here are from
an effort we did in the lab. Um but this
has been kind of replicated in kind of
multiple publications of different
domains of phenotypes as well. And so
kind of broad strokes, you can see the
distribution there and the significance
on those values stratified by kind of
our level of certainty in those
phenotypes due to sample size and
measurement scales and things like that.
But kind of broad statement, the middle
of that distribution is solidly away
from zero with an average heritability
of around 0.1 in this form of
estimation. Looking at this is a sniper
heritability as opposed to a family
based heritability estimate. It's in
theory at least all of the narrow sense
heritability. Um but at least for all
the things that are well powered for G-W
was and subject to some kind of QC we
see that the preponderance of things
that are well powered show signs of
genetic signal that align with having at
least some heritability out of our G-W
was results. Um so at least uh kind of
qualitatively concordant with the the
idea that everything is heritable.
Um that difference though between that
0.1 that exists in like an LD square
regression or other efforts that have
been made to quantify the genetic signal
in G-W was versus the like 50%
heritability in a lot of the historic
twin family
studies did has did at least for a time
was the kind of crisis of faith of
thinking about why are these estimates
in G-W was estimates so much lower than
what we observed in twin family studies
the so-called missing inheritability
problem. Um, and part of that goes back
to kind of thinking more carefully about
the different quantities that are being
estimated. So that twin and family
methods are really after that the all of
narrow sense heritability
versus GCTA or LD score are at least
somewhat attached to the observed
genetics and so are more in that sniper
heritability H squared G kind of
estimation. uh and some of the
statements about missing heritability
were more concerned about
difference differences down to the the
more PRS or toposai type uh variance
explained
estimates. Um but there are probably
other reasons that due to differences in
in methods that like are more than just
that they're estimating different
quantities. Um, so even between LD score
and GML or GCTA, we observe kind of some
variability where often the LD score
type estimates a little bit lower. Part
of this goes back to more subtle
differences in the quantity they're
estimating. But also there's a lot of
impactful decisions that exist there
about um kind of implementation details
particularly
around treatment of al frequency and how
that contributes to what is the presumed
model of signal in a G-W was um and how
that contributes as far as relative
weight that is captured in a genomic
relatedness matrix. And so you can see
wide variability, you know, in
simulation studies from different
versions of these methods that attack
these questions in different ways and
relative to different underlying genetic
architectures and distributions of where
the causal effects live and things like
that. Uh and so there is room in all of
these methods for different biases to
kind of percolate through and so not
only be estimating different quantities
but also be um
estimating and making different
assumptions about how to get there that
could have biasing effects in in either
direction. Um and this isn't a statement
just about like LDL score and GCTA. This
exists back in the the twin and family
studies as well because we had to make
that assumption about the similarity of
the environment between the identical
twins and the dygotic twins and so if
that violation is assumption is violated
will similarly have biases there where
that might contribute to those higher
heritability estimates as well. Yeah. uh
the estimates from chas data is that
purely additive
uh everything I'm talking I've tried to
summarize here yes there are uh
extensions of both the gcta and ldcore
that also get into dominance effects by
and large kind of searches across traits
with those have found very little signed
dominance effects and trying to do a
dominance g-was
um mostly things that tend to be at low
size that are already well captured by
additive effects and you're just looking
at the residual around that that's
dominance. But that is also in the low
frequencies represented in G-W was as
opposed to kind of more rare variant
studies where we might expect a lot of
more dominant or recessive recessive
acting variants to
live. Any other questions or
paused? All
right, cool. Uh so before I move on from
the topic of how we do estimation, just
like a quick highlight of some of the
ways that these things go wrong in their
respective estimation. Um there's kind
of a garbage in garbage out phenomenon
that just because you get to like rely
on somebody else's G-W was doesn't mean
you aren't now attached to the decisions
they made in terms of where measurement
error may have affected their phenotype
where the ascertainment
uh kind of aspects of the study design
uh contribute in
um ancestry and stratification are real
concerns for all of these methods in
terms of needing to different whether
they're ever going to try to differenti
iate ancestry liated signal from overall
genetic signal and if so how they're
going to accomplish that because genetic
similarity between individuals will
include the similarity of their ancestry
unless you do something to try and
portion that out but how successfully
that's done may
vary. Um, we've already talked a bit
about the assumptions that exist around
kind of the environmental piece. Um,
whether that's the shared environment in
related individuals or kind of just
treating it as a residual term that we
assume to be independent in a GCTA type
model.
Um, and then some of the kind of tricky
aspects that exist around things like
actually applying a correction for
getting to that liability scale amount
of signal off of having an observed uh
binary phenotype. It's easy to state
what we want and as a theoretical
concept generally, but actually getting
that in an unbiased matter uh can be
difficult. There's some standard
transformations that work approximately
fairly well, but how well they work
depends a bit on just how common the
phenotype is and some of the other
features
there. Uh, cool. So, the the last bit to
talk about is uh kind of where
heritability gets into um other related
uh kind of areas of genetics research.
And so without having infinite time to
talk about any any of these in great
detail, kind of a few places of interest
that I thought were worth mentioning
starting with polygenic risk scores. And
so when I introduced early on, I made
the note that kind of uh heritability or
particularly at least a sniper
heritability kind of exists as a
theoretical quantity that would be the
variance explained by our best possible
genetic predictor. uh including all of
those kinds of variants. And so, you
know, for the sake of thinking about
polygenetic rest scores, this exists as
kind of the in the infinite data limit,
we might expect that like we could reach
that level of predictive
power, never more than that. And so, how
that informs on where we think, you
know, all polygenic horror may or may
not end up being able to be useful or
how much it'll contribute at least has
this kind of theoretical bound on it
provided by heritability.
Um, in a more direct sense, even before
you get to that infinite limit, you can
derive expectations for how well a PRS
should predict as a function of
heritability and the available sample
size for the the G-W was that V's used
to create that PRS.
um which uh generally comes down to a
function of heritability as well as uh
so this um this row G term has to do
with the correlation between the
discovery sample that was used for G-W
was and the target sample where you're
actually applying the PRS. So if there's
some difference either that you're
predicting into a different phenotype or
just there are differences in that
phenotype that exists between cohorts
that'll attenuate your prediction and
then as a function of kind of the the
the sample size and number of snips
contributing to that PRS. Um so you can
get actually the expectations about kind
of future forecasting of how well a PRS
should be behaving that come out of
heritability. Um and even in the
construction of polygenic risk scores a
number of the kind of polygenic risk
scoring methods now uh kind of
incorporate heritability as part of
setting priors for expectations about
the distribution of effect sizes to more
robustly estimate the effect sizes that
should be used as the coefficients for
constructing a polygenic score. So the
example equation here comes from LD
prred um that I won't belabor the
details on but are basically getting
expectations about those effect sizes
that depend again on sniper
heritability. Um another place where we
see heritability pop up as kind of
conceptually related is thinking about
enrichment testing for various
enrichments of signal across the genome.
And this kind of follows from the idea
that our null hypothesis for most
enrichment testing is some idea that the
genetic effects that exist for a given
phenotype are kind of uniformly
distributed across the genome. Um, and
we're looking for places where that
doesn't actually follow and that we have
some enrichment in some place. And so
one way we can formalize that and get to
the quantities of estimation is if we
can estimate heritability in some subset
of the genome whether that's you know
separate regions or snips that have some
annotation or some concept like that and
get heritability that is specific to uh
that category these C's here and
relative to um kind of the the size of
that annotation or how many snips are
present in that that relative signal in
that category to the overall
heritability in kind of a uniform
expectation across all snips gets a
natural statement as far as what we mean
by this quantity of
enrichment. Um and that you know enables
all the things we see in terms of
talking about enrichment in uh signal
and GWA studies. So things like looking
at enrichment of signal in conserved
regions or in regions that are
associated with um expression or open
chromatin in particular cell or tissue
types um and all those kind of secondary
analyses of G-W was to try and pull out
this kind of signal relative to a
baseline measure of how much overall
signal there is that is showing up in
different places.
Um, heritability is also stepping to
stone towards other kind of genetic
architecture parameters. They kind of
live as extensions of that same kind of
model of a phenotype is simply genetics
plus environment. And so, oh, one common
direction of that is genetic correlation
where we say now we have that same model
but exists for two different
phenotypes. And then our genetic
correlation is defined kind of by the
correlation between the genetic
component of crate 1 and the genetic
component of crate 2. And to estimate
that it often is you know occurs that
we'll have some estimator for the
covariance of those two terms and
standardize that relative to the
heritability of the two phenotypes. And
that again gets us to our genetic
correlation. So kind of extending from
that one phenotype
um that one phenotype variance parameter
now to a coariance parameter and getting
these now these statements about
correlation across phenotypes extending
that idea. Um and so wrong direction
there. And so again this is has been
done increasingly across phenotypes uh
and observing kind of pervasive genetic
correlations in various domains.
Um, and it turns out that like even
beyond genetic correlation, um, other
kind of moments of that distribution of
effect sizes that live kind of in that
that same space of ideas are also
informative about aspects of genetic
architecture. Um, so this pair of papers
from Luc Connor and Alcus Price kind of
get into how some of these quantities
also manifest in asking questions about
polygenicity or about causal
relationships. again coming from uh
these same kind of extensions of
parameters of
architecture. Um and then lastly in
thinking about kind of uh selection or
population genetic forces, heritability
also lives in expectations about the
kind of relationship between strength of
selection on a phenotype and how much
impact that'll actually have in shifting
genetic drift over time um and how much
the the phenotype will actually be able
to move in response to the selective
pressure on the the phenotype. Um so
kind of the these fundamental quantities
just connect in many ways um kind of
across our landscape of genetic
research. Uh so just to kind of wrap up
again the rundown here. So again
heritability is conceptually this
proportion of phenotypic variance uh
that can be attributed to genetics in
some form or another but is very much a
population parameter and not a statement
about our ability to intervene. We have
a multitude of methods for uh estimating
this from those old twin and family
studies into methods using G-W was data
that each come with kind of their
various hiccups and things to be
concerned about um in how we estimate
them. But by and large the takeaways
have been that we observe lots of
heritability across the human genome. Um
and this is informative both for those
estimates directly and in the ways those
estimates inform uh uh everything else.
And so the the slides will be
distributed and also has an appendex
full of kind of related resources and uh
publications. Um but hopefully that you
know it's covered the space as far as
getting introduced to the idea
here. We are almost well we're at time.
Um if anyone has a question they can
come up to the mic. Um I do have one
from online uh from anonymous attendee.
There's one there's a question about is
um are there any problems if we are
comparing heritability across
populations?
Yeah. So
the for comparing comprehensive across
populations conceptually it's possible
um but often the thing that emerges is
that matching all of the features of the
studies to actually make that an
applesto apples comparison can be quite
difficult and so like I mentioned that
even things like measurement error will
affect this and that is that like if you
have measured a phenotype comparatively
worse and just have more measurement
error in there the that'll lower the
heritability as an overall proportion of
that variance. And so by no statement
about how much genetics actually
contributes to some like true trait
there, um you'll observe differences.
And so getting those kind of features
comparable is quite difficult. Um so
even while in principle that kind of
comparison should be possible, in
practice it's quite difficult.
Thanks for beautifully clear talk. Um,
early on you mentioned that there's this
fundamental ambiguity of interpretation
between kind of like direct causal maybe
mechanistic style effects versus ability
to predict. And I just wanted you to say
more about your views on that if you
view that as something that the field
needs to grapple with and help
disambiguate by I don't know introducing
more concepts or or if it's something we
should live with and if that's dangerous
etc. Thanks. Yeah, it's a good question.
Um I think there are there there's a
place in the world for both versions of
thinking about that
estimation and most of the challenges
arise in the fact that we are applying
the same name of heritability to mean
possibly either of those concepts and
thus implementing methods that attack it
in different ways.
Um the the version that is best possible
prediction is certainly easier to get at
because then you can think of the
environment is solely the residual piece
and it also gets you out of some of the
problems that also exist in GIWAS about
you know well whether it be
stratification or effects that are the
environment that comes from your parents
and so is correlated with the genetics
but has nothing to do with how the
actual inherited genetics are acting
that will show up in G-W bus signal
unless you're doing within family study.
All those pieces are much harder
to practically deal with. But there's,
you know, there is still value to
wanting to think about the quantity that
is the like true underlying like causal
effect of the genetics and having a name
for that and thinking that in concept.
Um, it's just a a practical difficulty
in terms of making sure that we are
thinking clearly about what we've
estimated and what that actually says
versus what we might wish we could get
to and like thinking about where the
pitfalls are. If what we want to think
about is the causal effect version.