All
right, we'll get started. Um, we're
going to continue our discussion of
principal components analysis.
And what I want to uh emphasize with
principal components is that we're
dealing with a random vector x
that's in m dimensional space
and it has an expected value
of
alpha say and it has a covariance matrix
given by sigma
which is m by m.
Okay, this kind of setup uh can be used
for modeling returns on stocks or assets
that may have a mean return over some
holding period and a variance covariance
matrix.
And so um in working with financial
data, principal components analysis can
be quite useful. Um essentially what
principal components does is it
transforms
our x vector to a p vector of principal
component variables.
And the definitions of these is
we subtract from X the mean vector
and then we
rotate the coordinate axes
of this M vector by this gamma uh
transpose
uh matrix.
And so um this gamma transpose
can equal gamma 1 transpose gamma 2
transpose down to gamma m transpose.
And so the first component
um P1 down to PM the first component
corresponds to using this uh gamma
vector which happens to be an igen
vector of the covariance matrix
corresponding to where with associated
igen value lambda I and in this
representation.
Um we uh basically have sigma gamma i is
equal to lambda i gamma i.
Uh and
we can order our ien values
from largest to smallest.
And the first principal component
variable
corresponds to
lining up or looking at a coordinate
system where we're looking along the
dimension of greatest variability in the
data. So um so this
sort of covariant structure it's
actually useful to think of a special
example
which is the multivariant normal
distribution in m dimensions with mean
vector alpha and covariance matrix
sigma.
And so
if we think of X1 and X2, we'll just
consider a two-dimensional case as an
example. There could be an alpha one,
alpha 2 here for the mean of X1, first
component mean of X2.
And with a bariate normal distribution
the uh we basically will have contours
of the density the joint density of x1
and x2 that are given by ellipses
centered at the mean vector and the
degree to which the components are
highly correlated ated. If it's a
positive correlation, then we have
ellipses that are tilted up. If it's a
negative correlation, it would be tilted
down. Now, um what principal components
analysis does is it basically
this step here corresponds to shifting
the coordinate axes to say x1 star and
x2 star. So we reenter our space at the
point with the origin being at the mean
point of the outcomes. And then we
consider
rotating these axes
in such a way that
the first principal component axis with
the largest corresponding to the largest
value. Um it will orient along the
principal axis of the ellipse.
And the second principal component
axis will be orthogonal
to the first
and it will um well in two dimensions it
will you know have variability along
that dimension that's that's smaller
than P1 when we extend from a
two-dimensional case to an M dimensional
case.
So suppose we have 500 stocks or a
thousand um then if we apply a
multinnormal model to those to that case
then our principal components will be
identifying
uh coordinates
basically coordinate um system variables
that line up with
different orthogonal dimensions of
variability.
And so what's ends up being very useful
is that um at least when we look at a
market of stocks or asset returns
um some of those may be highly
correlated with each other. Others may
be in a sense orthogonal or uncorrelated
with each other. And with principal
components analysis, we can actually
identify
uh we can identify different directions
in the space which uh basically have
decreasing levels of variability but
that are also orthogonal to each other
or uncorrelated with each other. So when
we want to specify
factors underlying factors say in joint
distributions of returns and markets
principal components can be very helpful
and trying to identify those and later
on we'll talk about factor modeling and
see how uh close or how effective
principal components can be. um and uh
but there are also general factor models
that that we'll introduce later. So with
these transformations as noted here um
these principal component variables have
basically a mean that's zero and a
co-variance matrix that's diagonal.
So these principal component variables
are uncorrelated with each other. And if
we order the igen values from largest to
smallest, the first principal component
uh variable will be the uh sort of axis
with the greatest variability. Now
what's interesting to highlight is that
in the transformation from the original
x's to the principal component variables
the only thing we've done is shift the
origin
and then rotated
the coordinate axes in an orthogonal
way. So we're maintaining
right angles between coordinate axes
and that's all we've done. So, so if we
have outcomes
of X,
so if we have X is a random variable,
but then we may have realizations
realization say
X I don't know a XB. I don't want to
have integers uh referring to these
because I don't want to confuse the
components. But we could have different
realizations for different days
or different analysis periods and we
would get different points of
realizations of the outcomes of this
vector. And so principal components
allows us just to view the data in a way
that hasn't
um transformed the data in an unusual
way. basically the configuration of
points is the same before and after uh
the construction of these uh PC
variables. So um
let's see okay there's uh this sort of
version of principal components where we
consider splitting the first k
principal components into uh sort of a
gamma one matrix and uh the remaining
ones into a gamma 2 uh portion. And so
one can then think of there being a
linear model for our outcome X variable
which might be simplified to just a mean
vector plus a matrix
times
the first K principal component
variables plus error. Um, if this in
fact were sort of an effective model,
um, you know, it might be the case that
the last M minus K principal component
variables essentially have no important
information in them. And so this could
be a very simple model for our uh, X
variable. And importantly the if this
were the
mo an appropriate model for an M vector
X then the co-variance matrix of the uh
the coariance matrix of X
um is just given by uh
or or let's see or the yeah the the
coariance matrix of X in terms of the
off diagonal entries which represent the
correlations are all due to common
loadings on these different principal
component variables in P1. So the
interesting question to uh think about
is you know how can we model
uh random vectors with some covariance
matrix and are there simple structures
to the covariance matrix that explain
all of the intercorrelations.
Uh now when we uh perform
empirical principal components analysis
then what we do is we say we have an x
uh matrix
which has columns x1 through x sub
capital t that are all m vectors. Then
we compute the row means
um we subtract those row means from uh
the uh from the matrix row by row and
then with this xstar matrix that's the
demeaned matrix
that matrix times its transpose
divided by the number of columns in X
capital T that is an estimate of the
coariance matrix essentially the sample
coariance matrix and we then can perform
an Igen value vector decomposition of
this coariance matrix and then use these
results to define
um the empirical principal component uh
coordinates of our data and it
corresponds responds to just taking our
estimate of the gamma matrix transpose
the demean matrix. So this is very
simple to implement
um
and let's see there the singular value
decomposition
um is also uh a way of obtaining these
principal uh component uh
transformations.
If we look at v durpose being the
singular value decomposition of our
xstar demeaned matrix. Then um
we have our lambda
estimate just being the square of the d
diagonal matrix divided by t. The
estimate of the gamma matrix is simply
the v. and our principal component
variables or our data transformed to
principal component coordinates is
simply given by d u prime. So um
principal components analysis is very
easy to implement and the lecture that
was originally scheduled for today uh
Stefan Andrev um he's going to go
through a number of examples of applying
principal components in uh equity
markets and in uh bond markets. What's
really useful to anticipate is that
um well one of the examples that he's
used in the past is where the X vector
corresponds to index returns in
different European markets on a daily
basis
and
attempting to understand
sort of the joint variability across all
of the markets. markets, but also to
understand where there are sort of
different geographical
um clusters of uh countries like
northern European versus southern
European those tend to uh be separately
highly correlated with each other. Um
another example of principal components
analysis is looking at interest rates
in uh the fixed income market. Uh it
turns out that for different maturities
of bonds ranging from say one month,
three month a year to uh five years, 10
years, 20 years, 30 years. The interest
rates
can be uh uh measured in terms of their
yields and the yield curve will vary day
by day. And it turns out that uh the
principal components analysis of yields
um is uh has a very strong uh structure
to it.
um the uh so uh I'll let him introduce
those when he when he comes in a couple
of weeks. All right. Well, um with
principal component variables, it's
important to
understand
uh that there are alternative ways of
deriving or defining principal component
variables. One is to define the first
principal component variable to be the
linear combination
defined by weights W1 through WM
that maximize the variance of that
weighted sum subject to the sum of
squares of the weights equaling one. So
we're looking at a unit vector
W
and trying to find the
vector W that maximizes
the u variance of the linear combination
in that direction. So um when we get to
sort of the transformation of the data
u or the random variable by demeaning it
then if we look at
w vectors that are unit vectors
in this space
then we're looking at which sort of w
vector is pointing in the direction of
maximum variability. ability. Then the
second principal component variable is
defined as the next
W vector now V which maximizes the
variance subject to having length one
but being orthogonal to the first.
So you know it's a rather nice way of uh
characterizing principal component
variables. Now, um, with principal
components analysis, one of the really
neat things is that,
let's see, we often focus on the first
few principal component variables
because they explain most of the
variability.
But the last principal component
variable is defines the linear
combination of the components that has
the smallest variance.
And sometimes that smallest variance can
be zero in which case we're identifying
sort of a linear dependence in the uh in
the return. So um let's see my first
sort of example uh of this case was uh
before the euro existed. So I'm really
dating myself. U but the uh German uh
Deutsch mark and the French Frank were
very very highly correlated uh before
the euro came out and in looking at
currency returns
um the principal components analysis
actually sort of identified that
empirically in a nice way. All right. Um
let's see. Okay. Mathematically
with um
principal components analysis we can
talk about a decomposition
of the total variance. So if we have
this covariance matrix sigma we could
talk about the total variance
is equal to the sum one to m of sigma i
jj. So the J diagonal
entry of the coariance matrix is the
variance of the J component
and the sum of that is the trace of
sigma.
um we can decompose that total variance
as the sum of the igen values.
And so uh principal components analysis
provides a decomposition of variability
and we can see sort of what proportion
of variability is explained by the first
or the first few principal component
variables.
All right. Um these lecture notes uh
finish with just reminding you of some
important statistic or dist important
probability distributions in statistics.
Um
the ki squared distribution arises again
and again and the ki squared
distribution with one degree of freedom
is
equal in distribution to the square of a
standard normal distribution.
So this is a useful thing to remember um
in different cases. Um and uh let's see
if we uh
well here's its density function. Um it
turns out to be a special case of the
gamma distribution
and uh here's this moment generating
function. It turns out that if we um
take independent
normal
01 random variables, square them and sum
them, then the sum of n independent ones
is a kai squared with n degrees of
freedom
and we can prove these results uh using
moment generating functions and get
densities for those. Um importantly, uh
t distributions often are um
uh let's see arise especially in the
study of a regression models and the
significance of regression parameter
estimates. Um but basically with a t
distribution
um if we take a standard normal
and then divide it by the square root of
a ki^ 2 divided by its degrees of
freedom where the ki squared variable u
is independent then this will give us a
t distribution with our degrees of
freedom. And so uh
let's see with t distributions um
t distributions are examples of
distributions that are heavier tailed
than a normal distribution.
And so if you think of
taking a normal Z variable and dividing
by this ki squared distribution divided
by its degree of freedom
and square root we're basically dividing
a random normal by something that's
random but around one.
and uh the randomness of that factor
leads to greater variability than the
normal. So it's sort of obvious that
that could be the case and it's u indeed
uh true. Um and uh let's see uh the F
distribution turns out to be the ratio
of two kaiquare distributions each
divided by their respective degrees of
freedom. And in uh classical statistics,
we often are interested in measuring
variability of data and variability due
to different driving factors. And so F
distributions arise commonly when we
have estimates of variance um given by a
ki squar divided by a degree of freedom.
And if we have two different estimates
of variability, um then uh if those
distributions sort of have common
variances, then the uh F distribution
applies.
Um some of you may have heard of uh
analysis of variance in statistics.
Anyway, the analysis of variance methods
work with studying uh f statistic
distributions.
Yeah.
>> Are nonentral distributions used a lot?
Or is that are they mainly just like the
centered ones? Well, the uh
non-entrality
um or when you have null hypotheses in
analysis of variance that are true then
the F statistics will sort of be be fs
with zero non-entrality and if the null
hypothesis is false then um you'll have
a F distribution with a non-entrality
parameter. So the non-entrality
uh parameter comes into specifying the
distribution of the test statistic
when the null hypothesis is false. So
>> is that used sometimes then like when
when the ho is false?
>> Yes. Um the uh actually uh the next two
lectures after today will be on
regression analysis
and testing in regression and so we'll
see those come into play there.
>> Yeah. Um
all right. Um what else? Oh, okay. Just
the weak law of large numbers and the
central limit theorem are the remaining
topics here. Um
if we have
sample data um realizations of say n um
or n realizations of a random variable
and here we say iid for independent and
identically distributed.
um if those random variables have mean,
meu and variance sigma squared, then
the sample mean xbar
will converge in probability to that
mean. So the larger the sample size
in the mean, the closer the sample mean
will be to the uh true mew parameter.
But what we what's important from
probability theory is how do we
characterize convergence of random
variables. And so the convergence in
probability to a constant
means that the probability that the
deviation the absolute deviation from mu
exceeding epsilon that that goes to
zero.
And um this theorem or this result can
be proven with chbbyev's inequality.
And uh it's sort of a neat example um
where
if we want to look at the variance of
xar n
which is equal to what the expected
value of xar n minus mu uh
squared.
Then
if we were to draw
sort of xar n
and here's mu
and then have the graph of xar n minus
mu
squared.
If we were to transform our scale to xar
n minus mu,
then this
mu value goes to zero.
And if we were to look at
um the epsilon value for xar n minus mu
um we can consider
a function other than this parabola
which is zero
up to this epsilon away from mu point
and then is simply equal to epsilon
squared
beyond and do the same at minus epsilon.
So zero up to there
and
the variance which is the probability
weighted average of the parabola over
the distribution
has to be greater than epsilon squar
times the probability of exceeding
of being further away from u than
epsilon. So the fact that this function
um
is greater than or equal to epsilon^ 2
times probability that xar n minus mu is
greater than epsilon.
This gives us uh the result and um
we basically have um that we're
basically
giving a positive bound for
for this uh
or we have an upper bound that decreases
with n for this uh probability. So that
gives us our nice result. Um
let's see if you really like probability
theory um
one can actually extend this result to
the case where um we don't have a
variance existing we just have a mean
existing
and that's a rather strong result that's
uh that's neat um at least it's neat in
terms of how the mathematics can uh
handle um more complex cases. Now
finally we have the central limit
theorem
which uh tells us what the asmtoic
distribution is of a
sum of independent and identically
distributed random variables is. And so
if we have
variables x1 to xn that are mean zero
variance sigma squared,
it turns out that the
sum of the x i divided by the square
root of the sample size uh converges to
a normal distribution with mean zero and
variance sigma squared. So um so we have
what zn equaling 1 / roo n sum 1 to
n of the x size converges to a normal
mean zero and variance sigma squared.
And if we were to think of um
xbar
which is equal to 1 / n * zn
this basically is converging in some
sense to a normal with mean zero and
variance sigma squar over n. Now, I put
quotes around this
arrow here because
it's not really legitimate to talk about
a limiting distribution
that depends on n. But this is sort of
the way the um
this is the way we approximate the
distributions of sample means. basically
they converge to the mean of the
distribution in this case zero and the
variance is sigma squar over n. Now
what's neat in this proof is just to
highlight the use of moment generating
functions.
And so if we say let's calculate the
moment generating function of ZN,
we're going to show that the moment
generating function of ZN converges to
this moment generating function, which
in fact is the normal with mean zero and
variance sigma squared. So the theorem
that says moment generating functions
are sort of unique and if the limit of
moment generating functions um exists
and equals some function we can identify
the distribution by that limiting moment
generating function. Well, if we
calculate just the moment generating
function of ZN, we just plug in ZN
within the expectation.
Then noting that the X's are independent
of each other. We basically are taking
the expectation of a product of
independent terms.
And so that expectation of a product is
the product of the expectations.
So we have the product of the expected
value of x i * t over root n. And this
expectation here is actually the moment
generating function of x
evaluated at t over root n.
So it's the nth power of that when we
take the product of all n of those. Now
this is where it gets interesting.
If we look at our moment generating
function of t over root n, well we don't
really know much about the distribution
of the x's. We know it has a mean. We
know it has a variance. The mean is
zero. The variance is sigma squared. If
we expand the moment generating function
into a tailaylor series, then we get 1 +
the expected value of x * t / roo n
plus the expected value of x^2 time / 2
* t / roo n^2 + an order term that
is given by the third power of the
argument.
And so as n gets large these higher
order terms are of smaller order. And so
we finally have that this in the limit
is 1 + this multiple over n plus a small
o of t ^2 / n. And if we take this
expression to the nth power,
then it converges to the exponent
of the argument sigma^ 2 t ^2 / 2. So um
let's see if we have 1 + r
let's see 1 + r / n to the n power
um this converges to e to the r
and villi used this argument
uh in the first lecture to talk about
sort of continuous compounding and what
the limiting value is of uh continuous
compounding at some interest rate.
Anyway, that same exponential
result is true here. So this actually
proves the central limit theorem using
uh the identity theorem for MGFS. Yeah.
>> Is is CLT actually used in practice
because obviously And like in finance,
nothing's going to be IID or at least
they're not going to be independent. So
like is it actually still useful in a
practical setting?
>> It it can be very useful in a practical
setting and it right now it's specified
in terms of
identically distributed X's. um it
actually generalizes to um x's that are
uh independent but with um different uh
distributions as well. So, um, also, uh,
what's, I guess, really important is
that
if
a variable we're working with
corresponds to the sum
of
independent or uncorrelated uh terms,
the sum can approach a normal
distribution well.
And um if one
uh
looks at I guess linear sort of
projections
of uh
multi-dimensional
vectors x's
um if you had sort of a random direction
in the mdimensional space
the projection onto that random
direction will correspond respond to
sums of
close to sort of identically distributed
random variables but we'll very likely
have a uh a Gaussian distribution as
well. Um the uh I this will come up when
we talk about regression modeling. Um
but um when we look at sort of the error
vector from a regression
the um feasibility of the error vector
being close to Gaussian is uh plausible
and reasonable given the way it's
constructed sometimes.
Okay. Well, let's uh move on then to
this note on probability theory for
asset pricing. What's really neat about
this uh note is that we're going to
introduce you just with basic
probability theory to one of the more
important models in uh
quantitative finance or at least in
early quantitative finance which is the
capital asset pricing model. And so um
let's consider
a simple
uh
context where we have one risky asset
like a stock and we have a one period
model where
we have uh
the beginning of the period
is
t not and the end of the period is t1 I
guess. Um and so
and
there's this risky asset A. So there's a
risky asset
A.
Um, and
we'll consider
a market agent having QA shares
of
the asset
and
just Q units of a risk-free asset.
Now, the risk-free asset
is like putting money in the bank and
being confident that you'll get it back
with interest. Um, and uh we'll assume
that the risk-free asset costs uh a
dollar.
So, a dollar per unit.
and the uh risky asset will be of price
pa per share.
So this market agent has a wealth at
time zero. So W0 is going to be equal to
Q A PA
plus Q
times$1.
Um and okay so maybe we'll put an F here
just to indicate that it's sort of the
risk-free asset. Um now at time t1
um
so this is the uh the t not prices
are given here at t1 the risk-free asset
is going to be worth 1 + r
f
and the price of the risky asset.
We'll assume that it's a random variable
given by f tilda.
And um
for simplicity,
we'll assume that it has some mean mu
and variance sigma squared. Well, now
right away this is maybe a bad
assumption to make because Gaussian or
normal distributions can be arbitrarily
large negative but we'll assume that the
likelihood of impossible values is very
close to zero. So that this is a useful
model. Um all right. So this is the time
t1
uh
state of the uh market which has sort of
certainty for the uh
risk-free
investment but uncertain outcome for the
risky asset.
Well, um,
one could consider
the agent being able to
buy
X units of the risky asset at the
initial time point
T0
and then have end of period wealth that
reflects that trade of buying X units at
t not. So at the end of
the period T1
time there will be QA plus X shares with
value F tilda
and
the X shares will have been bought by
paying PA the T0 price at time zero.
And so there will be money invested in
the risk-free asset earning uh the
interest rate or at the absolute return
of 1 plus RF. Now
what we want to do is consider what is
the optimal choice of X
the number of shares to buy for this
agent. And in order to
make that choice, one can apply
um sort of the uh decision theory under
uncertainty
um and associate a utility of the end
period wealth given by some utility
function U.
And we can choose the x value to
maximize the expected utility of wealth.
So importantly
um if we have u of w as a function of w
and there's basically a um
w0 value here um
utility of w0
there are some standard assumptions one
makes as to what the utility function is
like. Um, and we might assume that the
first derivative and second derivative
exist.
So we'll assume
that these exist.
And so well the first derivative
is likely to be positive.
More wealth is preferred to less.
So we sort of have a a better direction
being up and to the right. And the
second derivative,
this actually could be less than zero
if there's a decreasing marginal utility
to more wealth. So this function might
go
and look like this with a u prime
greater than zero and u doublep prime
less than zero. Um
so these kinds of assumptions are
reasonable to assume and
the theory of sort of decision rational
decision making under uncertainty. If
this is indeed your utility function is
to find the action X that maximizes
this. And if we are lucky, we might be
able to solve for X by satisfying the
first order condition, the derivative of
the expected utility equaling zero at
the maximum value.
And uh yeah,
>> why would you use anything other than
the identity function for you? Because
surely you just want to maximize your
end period as well.
Um
the uh let's see if you use the identity
um
uh then
there's sort of well it it will turn out
there's no penalty for risk that you're
undertaking.
And so with this decreasing marginal
utility of wealth, you end up having a
penalty for taking risks.
And so um
the uh
yeah um
okay so I'll I'll leave it there, but
it's a very good question. Um and uh
let's see there there's actually some
well there's some really interesting
discussions and uh about how to
optimally uh sort of invest
um as as this case and uh there was a
controversy between Claude Shannon and
uh um I think it was I think it was
Milton Freriedman.
um about uh sort of maximizing
um the
exponential or the the the expected log
return of investments uh just period and
that being optimal. So anyway, we'll
return to that discussion later as well,
but for now, let's just assume that this
is a reasonable thing to do. And um in
order to
solve this problem, we're actually going
to use a lema called Stein's lema, which
is
a curious mathematical result dealing
with
normally distributed y variable
and uh yar, they're jointly distributed
with each other and Gaussian. If we look
at the expected
value of g of y times y minus mu
and u
the expected value of g prime of y if
both of those exist then we get these
simple formulas for essentially the
covariance between g of y and y and the
covariance of g and y and y star. So the
this is a mathematical theorem that is
sort of abstract
as it's stated but it ends up being
applicable in our problem. Um so if we
define our wealth at the end of the
period at time t1 to be given by this w
tilda vector. Um then
if the outcome of the asset price
filda
if this is Gaussian
then uh this
wealth at time t1 will also be Gaussian
because we're just taking a multiple of
that plus a constant.
So that note is simple. Um then if we
look at the expected utility and try to
take the derivative of that with respect
to x.
Then under certain conditions we can
take the expectation
of the derivative with respect to x of
the u integrant with the expectation.
Now under what conditions is it feasible
to differentiate sort of underneath the
integral sign when you're doing
computations in calculus
I mean
I mean basically what we want to do is
take the expected value of U of
um
W tilda plus delta
and subtract the expectation of U of W
tilda
and divide by delta and take the limit
as this
goes to zero.
So that's sort of the formula for
computing the derivative.
It turns out we can do that if the first
derivative of u
is bounded or has bounded expectation.
And so if that's possible to do then we
can take the derivative underneath the
integral sign and we have basically the
derivative of u multiplied by
the chain rule the derivative of w tilda
with respect to x. So if we take the
derivative of w tilda with respect to x
we get f tilda minus p a * 1 + rf. So
this is just the chain rule of
differentiation there. Now um with this
expression in black
um we can use the uh
well let's see we we can express this as
the expected product of two random
variables is equal to the co-variance
plus the product of the expectations.
So here we have U prime and F tilda
minus PA1 plus RF the co-variance
between those two plus the product of
their expectations is equal to that
expected product
then um by Stein's lema
one actually can simplify or reexpress
this covariance
as the expected second derivative
of u
times the co-variance of w
and f.
And so we can then substitute this
expression
into this last expression here and get
zero equals that co-variance plus the
product of the
first expectations there.
And um so we're substituting in this
expected second derivative of u times
the co-variance in that formula. Now
with this
um
expression here
um we have this co-variance of w and f.
Well, the coariance between W and F is
simply the co-variance of U f with a
multiple of F. So it equals that
multiple times the variance of F.
And so we plug that in to this coariance
term.
And what's curious
and sort of is the punchline is that
this final equation
gives us a formula
for
um how we uh solve
for um
how we solve for x.
And so the value of x that we should
choose
um will basically satisfy this equation.
Um and uh
so our x value will depend upon what the
price of the asset is. And um it
actually is equal to
a discounted value of the expected
price
plus this other term here.
And this other term here, the second
derivative is negative.
First derivative is positive. So this is
actually a negative factor here. And so
we end up getting that
um
we have a formula that
sort of depends upon
that ratio of second derivative
expectation to first derivative
expectation of the uh utility function.
Now in economics classes maybe some of
you have come across the constant
absolute risk aversion utility function.
Has anybody come across that in an
economics class? Maybe maybe not. Um but
that function which is a constant
minus
a constant minus e to the minus a uh w.
Um this is the constant
absolute risk aversion utility function.
And so it basically um
you know has has the right shape
um for u in terms of marginal utilities
decreasing and
utilities always uh increasing. And so
with this particular
utility function we have the up prime /
u prime um those actually uh giving us
just the factor a here. So we have our
price of the asset should equal the
discounted expected cash flow minus a
risk adjustment.
Um and so and the risk adjustment in the
price that's like the fair price for the
asset um varies depending upon what the
risk aversion coefficient is of the
agent and uh also the magnitude of the
shares of the risky asset
that are obtained and the variance of
the uh of the price outcome. So, so the
fair price
for um the market agent basically is
balancing all of these factors.
And uh let's see if um
okay um well with this result for a
single asset what's really neat is that
we can um
generalize from one asset to many
and set up the whole problem with almost
the same notation.
So we consider defining a Q vector of
shares of
assets one through N
A1 through A N and QF units of the
risk-free asset
and we can go through the same logic of
the initial wealth being
the Q shares per asset times the price
at time z t0 of the assets plus the
value of the risk-free investment.
And we can assume that the random prices
at time t1
are jointly normally distributed.
Um and so we then can think of the
market agent uh basically adjusting the
initial
shares Q by the X vector
and choosing the X vector to maximize
expected utility.
And
we can uh
just plug everything in now with vectors
instead of scalers
and the same arguments apply.
And we end up getting at the end of the
day different sort of equilibrium prices
for the different assets that are sort
of discounted
expected values of the price
plus a penalty depending upon the sort
of risk aversion of the agent.
Um and so uh we end up getting
this uh final result here. Now, um
what's
particularly interesting um from this
uh setup is to then say well
what
uh prices should be holding if this um
market model is in equilibrium.
And so
if the market
is in equilibrium,
then we should have expected returns
of risky assets
that satisfy
um this formula here.
And
if we look at
a
an initial endowment sort of of no
shares at all and
define the X allocation
to be an equilibrium investment
in the market portfolio.
Then
our market portfolio defined by X
will have a market value of F tilda M.
The sum of the X size
shares times F tilda I. The price
initially of the market portfolio will
be just the sum of the XI shares times
the initial prices P AI.
And the return of the market portfolio
um will just be the change in value
divided by the initial value
which corresponds to a weighted sum of
the asset changes
or percentage returns. So the percentage
return R tilda M is simply the weighted
returns of the individual assets
and this is our expected return of the
market portfolio when the underlying
assets satisfy these uh pricing
conditions.
Now um
if we expand this expected market return
uh
expression,
we can successively derive
that
it equals
the risk-free rate
plus this blue factor times the
co-variance
of the initial
uh sort of W vector with RM.
And uh this
blue expression
can be solved for as the sort of excess
return of the market portfolio divided
by the co-variance
term here.
And so we end up getting that
this
co-variance of
W and RM end up being simply uh PM times
the co-variance of RM or the variance of
RM.
And plugging this in,
we finally get that the expected returns
of different assets
are simply a beta factor times the
excess return
expected return of the market portfolio
over the risk-free rate. And so this
expression is actually
the expression for what's called the
security market line
where we have the expected return of
asset I is the risk-free rate plus a
beta factor times the excess return of
the market over the risk-free rate. And
this beta factor
is the ratio of the co-variance
of
asset I and the market portfolio divided
by the variance of the market portfolio.
And so
this beta I is equivalent to the
regression coefficient of the excess
return of stocks regressed on the excess
return of the market.
So in this model um we end up having
that different assets will have
different returns
and those returns
are sort of bounded below sort of by RF
but then are
increased by having a higher beta factor
multip multiplying the excess return of
the market. So you may be familiar with
um issues of betas in equity markets and
there being low betas or high beta uh
stocks. Um in this model we have that
the way you get higher expected return
is to have a higher beta.
And uh so um so this
um also just uh leads to
understanding sort of what the
equilibrium prices are of individual
assets. If we take those expressions for
returns and then uh reverse them into
expressions for the equilibrium prices,
we have that the equilibrium prices are
sort of the expected
terminal
price divided by a discount factor that
discounts by the discount rate of the
risk-free investment.
but adding to that um a uh penalty based
on the level of risk that's being taken.
And here are just some uh references on
this topic that
you may want to uh check out. Um the uh
the development here was actually uh
taken from the first reference by Frank
De Jang and Barbara Rindy. Um there are
other important citations. One of them
that's of interest is uh John Lintner
the valuation of risky assets. Um
the capital asset pricing model was
actually um uh formulated by John
Lintner and William Sharp uh back in the
early 60s and I distributed one of the
articles of Lintner um in the Canvas
site and it's actually nice to be able
to read a very technical paper
um in an accessible way. And so I think
that you'll enjoy checking that paper
out. Um
okay. Um well, let me turn then to
the sort of main topic in our syllabus
for today, but uh it's sort of the tail
end of today. um to talk about uh
stochastic processes uh concepts and one
of the most important concepts in
stochcastic processes is the u concept
of a martingale process.
And so if we
have a stochcastic process
given by a sequence of
random variables xn,
we can define
a related process mn
which is defined as functions
of the first n x's for each n.
So if we
have uh mn depending only on the first n
x's in some well- definfined way given
by a function fn then we will say that
this mn sequence
which is random because of its
dependence on the x's it will be a
martingale
if the expected value
of the nth
m
given the first n minus one x's is
simply equal to the n minus1 first value
of m
and we also are going to require that
the magnitude of the mns as has a finite
expectation for all n2
now um
let's consider perhaps the simplest
example of a martingale which is
basically ally a random walk.
Suppose the XN sequence is just
independent random variables that each
has mean zero
and Sn is the sum of the first n X's.
Then
this SN is a random walk with steps
given by X. and it's going to be a
martingale with respect to the original
process of XNs.
Now, we can make this example even
simpler by assuming that the X's are
independent and identically distributed
and maybe that they're discreet with
just a plus one or minus one step
increment with equal probability.
So these X's have expectation equal to
zero
and variance equal to one
and the process SN has expectation zero
the sum of the expectations and the
variance of SN it's the variance of a
sum of independent
steps increments and so it's just the
sum of the variances so that's in.
Well, here's a random walk realization
of this model with a 100 steps.
And
so it basically starts at zero at time
zero and then as steps occur increments
up or down uh plus or minus one. If we
increase from a 100 steps to a thousand,
this is what a realization uh looks
like. And then here's an extension from
1,000 steps to 10,000 steps. And what's
rather significant is the general shape
of this random walk process. As we
increase the number of steps, it becomes
this very sort of jagged uh path
and it actually corresponds to
brownie and motion models that we'll
come across. Now, if we were to realize
10 different paths of length 10,000,
here are
examples of that. And so one can see
that for
low number of steps there's not very
much variability. It increases as we
increase the number of steps. And here
we're just drawing bands at plus or
minus multiples of the standard
deviation of the random walk value. And
so um these
standard deviation
levels uh basically apply just through
you know the mathematics of uh
calculating
uh one or two standard deviations of the
sum.
And what you know we know from
uh our central limit theorem is that the
sort of distribution of possible values
at any given time step will be closely
modeled by a Gaussian distribution
because of the central limit theorem.
There we have a stop. Okay, I'm going to
take two more minutes just to show you a
more not a more interesting but a
related but very interesting uh
martingale.
Suppose that
once we've calculated the random walk
SN, we look at the square of Sn and
subtract N sigma squared.
It turns out that this is a martingale
as well.
And here's one realization
over 10,000 steps.
And here are 10 realizations.
Um, and so these look very very
different from the simple random walk.
But these as well are martingales.
And so one of the uh what we'll see next
time is how martinales
have very special uh properties which
can be used to solve challenging
uh probability problems. And just as a
closing remark um does anyone here know
uh where the term martingale comes from?
Do we have any uh equestrians?
There's a bridal in a horse called a
martingale bridal that keeps the horse
straight looking straight. So it sort of
is a a bridal that sort of has
pressure on both sides of the mouth to
keep the horse looking straight. And
what's true about a martingale is that
the expected value in the future is
always a constant level equal to the
last level of the series. So that that
property will end up being very very
convenient and we'll see examples of
that uh next time.