How does the brain give rise to the
mind? To answer this question, we need
to start with the mind. If we're going
to understand how does this thing
produce a mind, we need to first figure
out what is a mind. Last year was the
first time I taught this course. So in
my valves, student 50458 offered this
comment. This class was not sold in the
correct way. It should not be called the
human brain because it was basically
just a cognitive science, not a brain
class. I expected to learn very
different material. So I don't know who
the student is. I wish I could apologize
to them, but I will say to you, sorry I
didn't make that clear. The fundamental
reason the brain is cool is that it
gives rise to the mind. And that means
that studying, you know, the biological
properties of the brain without
considering the mental functions it
implements, it would be kind of like
trying to study the physical properties
of a book without considering the
meaning of its text. So, we're going to
spend a lot of time doing cognitive
science in here.
>> For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe, or follow.