okay so maybe we can get started hello
everyone and thank you for joining us
this uh late afternoon on behalf of the
MIT swartzman College of computing I
would like to welcome you to this
event um which is part of the Circ
Workshop series now dealing with cir
social and ethical responsibilities of
computing uh is a core mission of the
College of Computing here at MIT and
with these events our goal is to bring
the broader MIT and scientific
communities together to engage in
discussions uh on the responsible safe
and ethical use of AI and Computing now
with that in mind uh we are delighted to
have with us today uh an industry and
thought leader in this area Eric
horvit and among the very long list of
things that um Eric does he serves as
Chief scientific officer at Microsoft
and at the president's Council of
advisors on Science and
Technology Eric is also a distinguished
scientist he has been at the Helm of the
research Enterprise at Microsoft for a
few years now has served as director of
Microsoft research Labs Eric also leads
efforts on the responsible use of AI not
just within Microsoft through the The
Ether committee uh but also industrywide
through his involvement with various
organizations including partnership on
AI we're also very fortunate to have
with us today the inaugural dean of MIT
swartzman College of computing Dan
Hatten Locker Dan is going to moderate
and engage um in today's fire side chat
with uh with Eric now before I pass on
the Baton to to Dan um I want to extend
a very big thank you to Corey Harris for
helping organizing this event and Terry
and Eric and everyone else who helped
couple of
logistics uh we're going to have the
fireside chat uh followed by a
Q&A uh please use the QR code and we are
a little bit uh trying to fix the
transitions here but if you uh follow
this QR code you should be able to
submit your questions throughout and
then Dan is going to move
moderate uh and second after the event
we're going to have a reception at stata
Center across the
street um so please join us for that as
well okay so without further delay
please join me in welcoming Eric horvit
and Dan hutten
loer thank
you ER Eric it's great to have you here
I should say that some of the questions
that I have here are also audience
questions because many of you submitted
questions online and Eric and I were
sort of going through some of those
questions uh beforehand and we decided
that we might start calling on people in
the audience also so we might run this a
little bit like a like a MBA class
where where everybody participates in
the answers and not just the questions
but but Eric has uh you know tremendous
uh experience and leadership as Nico
said but but um but really beyond that
he's one of the few people I think of
who has combined his own deep
fundamental research in this area uh his
research leadership leading research
organizations his leadership of one of
the Great American companies Microsoft
and his incredible government service
and in fact um Maria Zuber is is on
pcast with him and she keeps me on my
toes yeah and she she but she also says
I can't believe how much work he does on
P
she says she says it wouldn't be
anything without you Eric
so um so so let me let me start with a
couple High Lev things and we'll go on
and uh uh and feel free to turn
questions back at the rest of us but uh
but in what ways do you think Ai and you
know particularly this sort of machine
learning uh instantiation of AI since
you and I have both at this been at this
game long enough to remember various
other iterations of AI uh is likely to
change our society and and and in
particular what are impacts you think
that are not appreciated enough right
now or that might be being
overlooked um and you know what should
we be excited about and what should be
should we be worried about in those
things that might be being overlooked
well what a big question
so I think we're in truly uh a
remarkable time I think we all know that
deep down uh one of my Reflections is
that
500 years from now people will look back
and the next 25 years from now will be a
recognized period of time that will
probably have a
name uh because of the transformation
that will be coming from computation in
particular um technologies that uh read
on uh Reflections actions inventions
that have been monopolized to date by
human cognition as as machine start
playing a a significant role uh
collaboratively and
autonomously uh what does it all mean uh
What will what will the history books
show when when you open up that chapter
and look at what happened
um first uh I can guarantee to this
audience that there will be surprises we
can't predict uh and that to me is
mostly positively exciting uh of course
we have to be concerned about rough
edges um I think some of the surprises
will come in areas we now recognize as
being likely areas for big impact like
like in the biological sciences in
healthc Care Medicine Material Science
the the shape of skyline is changing
because of how we do design architecture
materials uh looking at it how New York
City skyline or Boston will change over
35 years 40 years um even though we know
this these technologies will have great
influence in those spaces we will be
surprised by the by the by the the way
and the extent of the
influences in areas that I think we
don't think deeply enough about or
expect because it's hard I
think uh it's an unfair question what
overlooked what yeah what comes to mind
for me is what I call the category in my
mind that I the word I use is deeper
currents like deeper currents of the
influence of Technology on society um
what comes of human
dignity human
agency uh how it feels for a human being
to
create um to celebrate their own
intellect uh when machines um are doing
this I don't know in the last couple
weeks how many people played with that
uh I know what the application was
called that M new music app that went
viral on on the web you know people were
writing uh you know show tunes to their
spouses complete orchestration and
chorus with a with a simple prompt you
know it made me think and it brought to
light a this a prediction I made in
2018 uh that was an AI magazine AI
magazine ran a prediction Market article
and I was asked for some predictions and
I made a bunch uh most of which people
said oh that's not going to happen you
had to give a prediction by a certain
date and I said oh by by 20
35 AI will be so ubiquitous in how it
does Artistry art music literature that
human beings will certify that their
creation was human soul authored and
they'll get more money and payment for
that like on the wall in a home people
will
say that was done by a human being this
is an original horbal no AI right even
even a label and a stamp now what but
again I mean what what does it all mean
for how we feel about ourselves as
people now there was an article that
came out um maybe three years ago now
that said it was in in the Journal of
radiology that said uh fears about the
this was before the current ERA you know
like different different realm three
years ago it's amazing to say that right
um that in the realm of radiology
there's so much fear among medical
students that are graduating um about
about Radiology being overtaken by AI
systems and therefore being devalued as
a specialty that it's changing decisions
about residency programs as's a study of
this what does it mean as AI becomes
more obviously um Central in taking on
key tasks that were celebrated or
enjoyed in other in other areas so I
think it's that's one area I like to
keep my my my eyes on and then other
areas come to mind like how education
might change um what does it all mean
and I'll mention one one little story
here which I thought was very
interesting which gives you a sense for
like maybe the tangent about what we are
right now I was at a a yoga retreat with
my wife she's a yogini uh and uh at
esselon and at the at the uh at the at
the one of the breakfasts I was talking
to a to a a um a middle school teacher
from San
Francisco and AI came up and I said so
aren't you can I mean what's going on in
your classrooms and so on she goes oh no
it's not a big deal she's a literature
literary Arts which I guess is the new
phrase for English an English teacher
and she said well you know it's okay I
just tell the kids in the class like for
this what assignment you could Google it
for that one you can AI it and they and
they know what this means so so so for
now maybe there are some packaging and
tools but what does it all mean in the
future is going to be a big question I
think
so the words agency and dignity I think
are which are almost the first words out
of your mouth
uh or at least to the first one they
were early I'd love love to just dig in
a little further there because I think
you know
we're we think about sort of you know
kind of immediate possible risks and
potential harms of AI and we focus on
things like uh you know bias and
algorithms in an AI which are very
important but but they're they're quite
localized and when you think about
something like a term like dignity or
human age
it's such a
general PHR like it's hard to even
characterize what like we all have some
sense of what it means to have human
dignity or human agency but we can't
Define it like you know this algorithm
isn't you know exhibiting racial bias in
hiring or in recommending Medical
Treatments how do you think we're going
to start to develop these more precise
characterizations of what
constitutes the things that AI should be
enhancing in in agency and dignity
instead of depriving us
of let me get to that in my next couple
sentences but let me first say given
your use of those terms just now um my
my sense that
um we have to really think deeply about
about how important it is to people
today uh because we don't really
understand what it's like to not be at
the top of the pyramid in when it comes
to intellect we celebrate that about
Humanity about ourselves it's unclear
how much we need to have that be true to
have a sense of wonder and um to Value
human life way we do I hope it's
irrelevant but it could become an
influence
um
uh and I'll say one more thing and in
the rise of
automation my optimistic side says is it
possible in a sea of
AI that will'll come to celebrate and
value even more deeply human touch human
caring you know I was talking to a uh to
a actually a well-known um psychologist
in the Cambridge area uh about the um
excitement about automated therapists of
the future oh they'll be less expensive
and they'll be available you can kick
back and talk to a therapist whenever
it's uh you know be automated you know
how much let's say you have a and this
is a kind of an interesting assessment
you have access to a fabulous proven
automated therapist who's like the best
in the world the system at handling
depression how important is it that
there's a human being at the other end
that's actually there to listen that's
the question to ask ourselves right now
goes beyond efficacy go the fact that
there's a human being there that will
never go away I think um back to your
question now um agency
um you know a few years ago actually
1999 I wrote a paper some of you may be
familiar with it's one of my higher
cited papers a mixed initiative
interaction and we had principles for
how a human being works with a comp with
an AI system um and they're all very
balanced about when the AI should should
take an action and when the human should
take an action given competence icies
and given the the pace and the flow of
the conversation where it's
conversational around a pro conversation
around a problem solving task and steps
not language but a a problem solving
session and it was all very balanced
back then made a lot of sense I just
wrote a paper with Abby selin who's
director of our Cambridge lab um that's
that's all about celebrating the Primacy
of human agency in our interaction in
our interaction model and some of the
reviewers wouldn't say complain but they
said well why are you changing the tune
from this equal mixed initiative human
machine depending on who can do what
better and so on and we sort of changed
we make wein this is would be in cacm
the summer this piece we refined the
article to call out that with the
ubiquity of AI and the role that it's
playing we need to start thinking deeply
about a decision and a value a value
assertion
that humans are basically on top they're
making the decisions they do the guiding
today in uh I I see David Sant here uh
one of his fabulous students we just did
a PhD thesis I'm here primarily for a um
PhD committee today and celebrating
Hussein's passing and he did he did a
fabulous job uh but um we talked in the
in the in one of the sessions after the
after the after the uh defense you know
about
clarifying the different areas of study
there's AI assisted human decision
making and human assisted AI
decision-making and there's very
different perspective you can have on
those two things they both would
probably work well and you might even
say in certain
designs for fail safe and so on maybe
the human gives an input to a automated
AI system and it does that's the best
thing to do but I think more generally
the design principle for the first time
in my life I started thinking about we
needed to sort of think about the
principal agent and I'm using the phrase
in a decision analytic way the principal
agent of decisions decision should be
humans it should be the humans that are
accountable some human if it's a if
people are are worried about lethal
autonomous weapons there's no such thing
as not having a human accountable for
every single thing those weapons do so
that human who pushes that button and
guides those
weapons better know that he or she is
accountable and better understand
understand how that weapon works for
example super it actually reminds me I'm
completely not following my script here
because keeps reminding reminds me of
something we were just talking about
right before this and then I'm going to
go back because there were some
interesting things on the script but uh
just before when we were talking about
uh you know
whether sort of metrics for evaluating
performance and looking at whether the
on a given task an AI system
or a human or a human and an AI system
together what their relative performance
are and that we're sort of in this state
at the moment where because in general
machine learning is optimizing for the
AI alone it's not surprising AI alone
usually does the
best uh how do we move beyond that sort
of world the the example I just gave we
were talking up in in Dan's conference
room was I was just helping with a study
at Stanford of clinicians they did a
very intensive study I mean involving
like you know tens of Physicians uh a
the the control group were just doing
their thing with some case diagnostic
case studies challenging hard problems
in clinical medicine and the the
intervention group were given GPT for to
you know ask questions and to help with
the diagnosis and the bar the bar graph
was like gp4 alone clinicians alone
together and so we all looked at this
and and it was done really well very
careful carefully um and it just
suggests that there's a huge Headroom in
I think Headroom in like maybe three
three three triple on Tandra but there's
huge Headroom in figuring out like how
to design these systems to work well
with people and because you know uh and
I think Usain had a slide about this
today and he's done work in this space
uh our new our almost new PhD going off
into the world that you can you should
get a bigger bar uh out of the
combination and we just haven't been
investing enough in that
yet and how do you think we get focused
more on that investment either wearing a
uh you know an academic hat or a
corporate hat or or you know does
government have a role here or well I
think I think human AI collaboration if
you will call that that call that out of
the field is especially given the
advances in AI is a severely
underinvested area and um look I mean I
I I'm on The Advisory Board also at the
the Hai program Sanford's human centered
Ai and I I've called the map by saying
you know you're human centered AI but I
don't see very many people in your
department working on the technology and
the psychology and the in depth on this
this actual
interaction uh and and so I'd like to
see more of that not just there but here
and everywhere um it's Challen
challenging work and I think in part
because you need to involve in a deep
way cognitive psychologists to know what
the gaps and the capabilities are you
know the biases and blind spots in human
cognition and if you look at the 100
Years of cognitive psychology that's
exactly what what that those groups have
studied um that could be very helpful
then there's the whole design you know
like the the interaction the
conversation with an AI system
um the idea of of a general purpose uh
oneline input uh as the you know choice
or the uh the standard of practice for
talking to large scale language models
well I'm sure I hope a decade from now
seem like an old Franklin stove approach
in the old days we have new kinds of
innovative ideas in fact be to think
about with this group to check back with
this group in 15 years like what's the
human AI
collaborative uh state-ofthe-art and
best practices across fields to see
people doing all sorts of interesting
things with gesture and and engagement
with different different kinds of
modalities would be very interesting we
have to get you to MIT for a slightly
longer time period than this visit
because uh
um I I'll I'll publicly go on record and
say that uh we will be working a lot lot
on human AI collaboration here and we
already are um partly with faculty that
we already have partly with a number of
Faculty we've been hiring including a
co-author of
yours and uh uh and uh I couldn't agree
with you more it's incredibly under and
just to call this out people are hearing
different things when they hear human
collaboration some people are thinking
design some people are thinking you know
uh you know uh psych psychological
advances it's really it's the whole menu
going to core computer science up up to
cognitive psychology uh to human factors
so it's it there's a soft design aspect
to it that takes a lot of interesting
effort and then there's also getting
down pedal to the metal you know methods
for grounding and confirming and and for
the Baton passing which get into really
um you know in some applications um your
millisecond
controls I can give examples of those
things
so you have this very broad view from
the multiple organizations that you're
involved with in you know in government
and Industry consortia at Microsoft um
and I guess in
particular um you know you've been
involved in the responsible AI
initiatives in that office at Microsoft
and in the the safety board the
deployment safety board at Microsoft and
I just you know are there examples of
how uh you know either at Microsoft or
in other organizations you're working uh
uh in these kinds of questions on
about how you frame these considerations
and maybe trying to tie broader safety
considerations because I mean I know
when you look at safety it's not like
just turn it off it's how do we balance
the like so how do you frame these
things and then maybe a specific case or
too so there's kind of the broader
Framing and the
specificity we I ask easy short
questions yeah so in 2016
um just had the sense that we needed to
get going on at
Microsoft uh on stating a set of
principles when it came to systems that
were starting to read in the open world
on in the realm of human intellect human
decision- making um and Brad Smith and I
uh went together formed what was called
The Ether committee um we got
representatives from across Microsoft as
well as experts from Microsoft research
and legal team policy people um and one
of the early things we did was we
defined what what are now called U
Microsoft's AI principles and there are
six of them and they they they they've
been standing the test of time but maybe
even more interesting because there are
principles everywhere there's like you
know 10 principles oecd four principles
U you know and so on and they offer
quite equivalent these all these
embracing uh value statements but one
thing we found interesting we said we
defined we wanted to Define what a
sensitive use of AI was we called it a
sensitive use and we came up with a
definition or a set of attributes that
have also stood the test of time and
I'll just say what they are I mean and
so at Microsoft any AI application has
to be reviewed per policy and compliance
with whether or not it pings on one of
these attributes and you can look at it
as Rings starting with a human being
first Circle does this application that
we're going to ship or create and then
ship uh somehow um put someone at risk
for physical or emotional
harm and I can give you examples of
those including apps that we haven't we
we we we've stopped we halted at
development the second ring is um does
this application put someone at risk for
losing access to a consequ quential
service like health care loans education
and the third ring is does this
application put Society at risk does put
Microsoft at risk for its commitment to
Human Rights civil liberties privacy um
uh and
democracy uh and it's an outer ring um
and we have impact statements that
require an analysis of all our
applications and so on now we first
rolled out this program and said you
know and Sai actually was I always
people say how' you get how' you get it
to work at Microsoft well Sacha nadela
sent the whole company a note about this
we have The Ether committee here's what
we're doing here's the link and so all
of a sudden we we had incoming cases um
I my my first reaction was you know what
we're going to have maybe I don't know
seven to 12 cases and we'll have
precedent and we'll automate well here
we are you know like nine years later
eight years later or so and we're over
600 sensitive uses reviews all very all
different and nuanced and precedent is
still there we can point at other cases
and so on uh and uh and it doesn't seem
to be any any simple way to summarize or
generalize on these
cases U one of the first cases that came
to that I I I have I give a recent case
and an older case one of the first cases
that came to us was uh there was a
project called project aware and this it
was built by our Consulting teams that
build custom tailored apps that run on
Microsoft services and I think the first
one was done for New York City and it's
always kind of a cool system it helps
triage 311 calls and it it it it does
some proactive work about where police
should go you know it helps helps manage
Emergency Services all sounds really
great well it was you can imagine sales
and marketing teams around the world say
we have uh on the menu we also have
project to wear you want to buy this
thing and I'll just won't mention a
government but but but a military
government in the Middle East
said we'll take that uh and it came
through sensitive uses and that was the
first time we had to Think Through okay
what does it mean to take a Microsoft
product and and and think deeply about
who the user is and and who and what
does this mean for the for um the first
second and third Loops of that sensitive
uses uh a definition um and that went
back and forth and in the end uh um we
ended up defining our policies when it
comes to um um who gets access to these
Technologies AI Technologies in
particular um and so we told the
disappointed salesperson who had a huge
contract on his hands no uh they came
back and they said well well how about
for this Museum of Antiquities they just
for the museum and so they we got back
together again and thought about what is
this mean a museum can we keep the
object code in in just one place can we
uh and so we have this beautiful
statement that we've never had before at
the time which said yeah you can have
this system for the museum but and it
was a statement about you cannot it had
statements it had assertions like you
cannot do facial recognition you cannot
detect gender or race you cannot predict
future events with with any kind of
add-on so had a an AI statement about
things you could not do with the system
that was an example of like trying to
Define borders and things have gotten
way sophisticated since then in terms of
how we deal with countries and different
governments and
Technologies another um uh example that
came a little bit later was um when a
large uh Sheriff Department um in
California got excited about facial
recognition this was before the recent
police actions where Microsoft now says
will not even even uh um distribute
facial recognition to to police agencies
and it was really excited the police
department they said we have three use
cases uh stopping some somebody in the
wild you know like a camera on on the
vest uh a traffic pullover we also want
to have it on the way into into into
jail because we don't know who these
people are this would help us ID
somebody who's done who's been observed
performing a crime and the third was in
inside the jails apparently people pass
around these cards for the you know when
they when they go when they when they
buy and sell and they want to you know
people want they want to certify who's
who when they see people using resources
and cards and whatever they do at the
canteen for example and so each case was
examined very carefully by the by The
Ether committee sensitive uses review um
uh very clear set of requirements were
were made including education to the
police department this stuff doesn't
work very well there's a false positive
false negative rate we will work with
you in fact we will be willing to first
of all it was absolutely no for open
world case for the second case in the
third case it was like okay listen
here's what we have to do community
engagement uh reporting every six months
uh impact of false positives and false
negatives tracking um uh Community uh
you know hotline for complaints that we
requireed before we chip the technology
and the police department is very
interesting the police the sheriff's
department said we've reviewed the
technology we look at what you're saying
and what you've asked us to do we've
decided this technology is not for us
it's not ready to be used uh just by
educating them by the process we went
through as an example
uh um just as you were saying that I was
thinking about you know the widespread
use of fingerprinting technology in the
criminal justice system and it has all
of those same problems even though it
you know it's not an AI technology so
it's not really getting reviewed and if
you and if you look at the what and we
can get to this later but the European
the EU AI act now will forbid certain
biometric uses of
AI so one of the you know uh when people
signed up uh they many of them there was
a spot for them to put a little question
in one of those questions so this is
pre- audience questions uh one of those
questions was very relevant to this
because it said you know Microsoft seems
to be taking a thoughtful approach to
responsible uh uses of AI uh compared to
many
other uh companies out there um many
other actors
uh how do we go about trying to we know
more broadly socialize these kinds of
approaches you know is it something that
you know you're seeing being able to
happen just with sort of you know
industry consortia and collaborations
and Industry groups is it a place for
governments to be uh getting involved
how do you how do you think about how we
you know take best practices um and uh
you know yours or others and and and
really make sure that they're getting as
broadly applied as they can sometimes I
think about where we are today as kind
of being akin to you know if anybody's
ever visited the the original Con Edison
Consolidated Edison electric power plant
in Manhattan that Tom Edison built to to
basically light up the light bulbs he
was selling he like well I have
generators here I'm going to sell you
light bulbs and it's going to be a
service and I often think well was there
a government regulatory body dealing
with like you know ground
hazards and electrocution and there was
no UL laborat there was no Laboratories
to do standards and so I'm hoping that
the need for companies and I can talk
about our motivations like Microsoft to
do this intensive work and reflection
about what do we build and what what
what are the benefits and harms will
pass to society more generally and we
won't rely on companies to do this kind
of thing is I think it's transitional I
think we're we have we don't really have
regulations just yet we have this
incredible executive order from
President Biden and the administration
and ostp that and other agencies that
came together with report out starting
very soon I think on Monday we'll be
hearing a few uh 120 days I guess that
was um and um but I think we'll be in a
world almost by necessity within a few
years where societies who have come to
especially democracies where that people
have spoken and leaders will take take a
take a a point of view where regulations
will come to hold in best practices and
it won't just be you know we won't rely
on industry but instead will enforce and
require industry to do certain
things when you talked about Edison and
light bulbs it reminds me of an example
that some of us have been using who are
working on AI policy issues which we've
come to refer to as the fork and a
toaster problem
uh which is you know today we have very
good Norms about uh you know when you're
misusing a device like a toaster and if
you get electrocuted it's probably your
fault versus uh but if if you go back
and look at in the 1920s the ear the
first electric
toasters they they look like they were
designed to electrocute
you well it it's interesting and and so
as the the the EU AI act so the Norms
you know the industry sort of develop
Norms then regul regulation came in
exactly following but if you look at the
a AI act it was interesting to see um
Europeans who's responsible comes up and
and that created lots of questions as it
was coming to as it was yelling there
was like you know the there was they
called out roles of the general provider
of the services of the general AI
Services then the application Builder on
top then the consumer and the industry
shipping these things and like they they
kind of call out like who's in you know
who's on the hot seat for something that
goes wrong at any of those
levels I agree
so so this is whyu or should I try to
okay good yeah no so so just to react
um this is one reason I feel
particularly passionate about the
responsibility of people in this room
technologists academics people who know
the technology IND desists who are have
their fingers in the technology who get
a sense for where things are going for
their role both to Think Through
Solutions technically soci technically
and even policy and communicate them out
to others uh and this is why i' I've
been excited about Microsoft's um policy
teams in DC for example that have really
weighed in with with with uh
Congressional staffers and um other
agencies you know in ining waston State
um when it came to facial
recognition uh we didn't want to compete
to the bottom with our competitors
wanted to sort of raise the bar so we
worked directly with uh staffers to help
with Washington State facial recognition
legislation we're very proud of that
that we got you know sort of it's
communicated out and then and so on in
other areas things are so are moving so
fast so we all know and we're all
worried I think in this room what's
going to happen with democracy and
elections even coming in the next 18
months I think a a billion people are
voting in the next 18 months on the
planet and just look at what look at
what's going on I get reports daily from
our internal uh security analyses around
the world and it's amazing how fast the
latest uh synthetic uh media
Technologies are being used by you in
adversarial ways to to impersonate uh
and to persuade um if anybody saw the
latest coming out of mic Microsoft
research you know it just put a chill up
my down my from our from our from our
from our China lab is incredible I mean
to take a a still picture uh and to
completely synthesize a just a beautiful
uh um rendition of a fluid conversation
a person talking where the voice is
synthetic the face is synthetic and even
even the content is synthetic uh means
we have to do something so folks have
taken dramatic efforts our team
sat together and said we're creating
something called media Providence and
we're going to use cryptography and show
how that works with manifests we're
going to go to the BBC and talk to them
and get them started this thing called
project origin with the New York Times
we helped to co-found ctpa the Coalition
for Content Providence and authenticity
and then thinking through what are the
soot technical issues with having this
stamp of of authenticity will people
trust it will they distrust it and
understanding all that comes along with
it so this is these are initiatives
going on by people who just happen to be
in the know and see what's coming down
the bike I mean let's say synthetic
media deep fakes I saw my first demo at
Stanford in
2016 it was a cvpr paper people were
really proud they said watch I I can
make Donald Trump he was he was just a
candidate back then make his mouth move
in certain ways and make him say things
and the same with Obama at the time and
it was it was fun and it was a demo and
it was a it got into cvpr uh great it
was a science fair project I gave a
South by Southwest talk and I showed
this and I said remember this moment as
2017 as South by Southwest here we are
today it's it's common parlance you know
a deep fake and it's they're persuasive
and it's it's a problem we need to get
ahead of it somehow and by the way
staffers in Congress are talking about
legislation now not just requiring
certain kinds of stamps of auth
cryptographically signed but making it a
penalty to remove them a penalize
offense so we probably need all of that
while respecting civil
liberties an interesting
balance I wanted to come back to this um
point you were making
about sort of the different levels of
responsibility kind of you know a
foundational model provider application
provider
Etc um
I was
uh POS positively surprised when uh
pretty much all of the uh large
providers of llms decided that they
needed to
indemnify their paying customers
against copyright
infringement uh both claims and
judgments uh positively surprised in the
sense that just you know when we think
about the software industry and its
history it tends to be caveat empor
right you know there's a long end user
license agreement that pretty much says
you're the human you're responsible
essentially back to some earlier
conversation uh so it was you know I
think different do you
think as we start to think about sort of
responsibilities of layers that's
essentially a layer dayi thing right I
mean it's it's like there's a provider
but the end user is going to use that
work product and some way and they don't
really know the provence and so if you
didn't take responsibility you probably
would have any customers it's clear the
Dynamics are different in some of those
things than conventional
software how do you think about how
those things might uh might pan out over
time it's interesting Dan I I have um a
general response to your general
question but also on the specific case
this this whole area of attribution and
uh generation of people who provide
content or artists who have a specific
style that you know worked most of their
life in a world where they didn't uh
have a fear that their style would be
scooped up and then regenerated uh
without their name on it um these are
really interesting questions I just um
spent time on a National Academy of
Science committee uh that met at
sunnylands uh and there'll be an article
coming out in pnas
entitled uh protecting scientific
Integrity in the era of generative Ai
and part of the what's called for is
like how do we deal with attribution a
scientist is using a system doesn't know
where ideas are even coming from as
they're being mixed for example so it's
even more General than copyright it's
like you know how do we back to human
agency and human dignity if you know how
do we we reward folks for their
creativity if we even if if the in the
mill of an llm
all identity is lost as things are
created and provided to somebody else
um and it's been interesting to see
companies uh buying up now in in in the
frame of lawsuits digital rights for
corporate x for use in model y uh and
price is going up all of a sudden
because oh I didn't realize that I could
charge so much for my big medical
journal over the last 30 years of
content that's great let's negotiate now
so that's happening what does it mean
more generally
um you know I think because of the way
current models work um where we haven't
really cracked attribution yet besides
kind of back tracing with reference
creation and trying our best to put
links and so on that's one solution sort
of retrieval augmentation and those
kinds of those kinds of approaches yep
and matching uh hashing and so on I I
think that we're going to be in a world
where companies who want to sell the
service will have to be indentifying end
users and I like the idea of that even
becoming a costly thing to do because
it'll Force Innovation and even Force
policy
eventually like I said it was a positive
surprise to me so it sounds like maybe
not a surprise to you because you were
closer to it but uh but but a similar
kind of kind of view there um all right
so now uh
um we covered a lot of things here uh
kind of out of order um all right so I'm
going to go to some of the things that
kind of came in in advance um and uh so
uh um as the chief scientific officer at
Microsoft how do you find a balance
between sort of constant Improvement the
industry is sort of rushing forward at a
at a rapid P Pace you a lot of
competitors out there um or or Coop
petitions with you you have both
competitions and Coop petitions uh you
know how how do you find that balance
between an industry rushing forward and
maintaining the highest possible social
and ethical standards in your own
company but also encouraging that as
part of how the industry does things
well there's definitely a tension there
um some people might know notice that we
shipped something called open model
called 53 mini this week um that was
held up because of safety concerns uh
and it was sent back by the deployment
safety board like back to the lab you
can't ship uh on the earlier date um
even though it was considered a
competitive thing want to get it into
hugging face get it into the hands of of
end users
because it hadn't passed some metrics on
safety we have a certain set of
requirements and a bar to be reached
happy to say that it did but but it was
wasn't going to go forward until it did
the the there's
um there's a commitment uh called the
responsible AI standard of
Microsoft that
um is is uh in some ways was overseen by
the board of directors of the company uh
for the an audit committee that reported
to them so in some ways
uh
the the the promise and commitment is
firm about what Microsoft does when it
comes to its standards that said you can
imagine there's lots of gray areas and
there's pushing and tugging going on and
one reaction to this is Can Can
Microsoft stay ahead on
the where it's advancing the technology
as fast as anybody else but also is
putting enough investments into the
responsible AI aspects so that it can
either
uh uh learn something and warn the
planet warn governments warn uh
colleagues or come up with the right
kind of constraints uh guard rails
filters and so
on yeah well it's
amazing the scale at which you all have
been able to do that so far I think that
uh um so there are a number of questions
that came in beforehand and then I'll
start going to some of the ones that are
coming in uh now uh there are number
questions before that were uh something
along the lines of you know what's the
path to
AGI uh you know are llms the path to AGI
or um what do you think about first of
all what AGI
is and is is it something that you know
is a little bit like uh you know
um in our lifetimes Quantum Computing
has always been somewhere between the
the the time period is getting shorter
I'll give it that but it's always
somewhere on the horizon right uh well
the the the old joke uh in AI used to be
through most of my career was AI stands
for almost implemented uh and things are
changing now and that on that front I
think now with AI is an interesting I've
had an interesting relationship to that
concept over the years I think probably
we all have you know mainstream AI
researchers always looked a scance at
that term and go what does that mean I
mean AI for us was AGI we were looking
for general principles I think that the
terminology came from largely at least
as amplification from outside mainstream
AI research in that people were
seeing um actual great advances that
were in narrow domains you know it's
like you know like from the point of
view of AI it's like first things first
AI research but it's like no no no we
don't mean that we want like humanlike
intelligence and then some people have
to find it like Shane leg as you know
doing anything a human can do I think is
a is a short definition of that um so
stepping
back you know I came into this field I I
came to Stanford as
mdphd in
neuroscience and my because my primarily
my primary motivation has been like what
the heck is going on with neurons and
vertebrate brains I said I'm just blown
away I understand physics to my level of
curiosity and maybe more you know
biology chemistry but when I went into a
into I spent a two years in a in a
undergr as a biophysicist biophysics lab
as my major with biophysics playing with
rat sticking rat neurons with little
electrodes as an undergrad I was
completely mystified and so I said I'm
going to study that when I go to grad
school and my first three or four months
at Stanford I said you know what I'm
going to shift to AI because there's
like no way we're going to make progress
with sticking single neurons or even
sets of neurons for a thousand
years um and I had hoped that we get
some insights about how brains work um
and I got very excited about probis
graphical models and understanding every
Arc and Link in these models and
understanding the mathematics and what
basine updating is and how to apply it
in exciting applications but I never
really had the sense that we were
getting anywhere near what vertebrate
Minds were
doing and I have to say and I might be
completely off here but my conjecture is
whether it's close or not to what what
biology has discovered with human
nervous systems the magic we're seeing
and we still can't explain and we have
the most you know seasoned AI
researchers completely stunned by what
these large scale language models are
doing is something there will read on
human intellect and how vertebrate
brains work it's unclear what yet but
the power of
composition synthesis AB raction
generalization that seems to be emerging
in these systems might have some
relevance is it the pathway forward no
but I think it'll frame questions and
and and and provide answers that might
lead us to The Next Step so do is that a
piece of this next 25
years will have a name I think like what
when when I heard you say the next 25
years will have a name looking back I
was thinking at the time you said it in
the conversation that was about the
kinds of impacts on you know sort of our
daily lives but this is more a potential
sort of intellectual and human
understanding impact do you think that's
also an important part of this era we're
in or do you think maybe it'll be
outside the 25 year time frame or can I
say for the sake of this video
that for me that's an expected
surprise so people will be able to come
back and test you on it that's good uh
so um back to psychiatrists here okay so
there's a a
um question here about how Joe Eisen bam
argued around 1970 I can guess a few
people in here who might be writing
about Joe in 1970 uh that a super smart
dolphin would not be acceptable as a
psychiatrist could would not have had
comparable experiences to its
clients so when you were sort of talking
about the AI psychiatrist and you know
does there need to be a human in the
room was that sort of
human you know sort of Flesh and
embodiment was it Human Experience is it
both how do you think well when I used
that term earlier I was trying to Define
a simple notion of being listened to by
an actual mind who understands and
understands what it means to be a human
directly that is a form of experience
form of experience but it like actually
someone who's there who's home versus
potentially an algorithm that doesn't
have that kind of of sensient or or
maybe human form of sensient
um I
I
I'm amazed at and I know this is
controversial right now among people
studying this um but I've done Bunch
myself with a team I think the theory of
Mind capabilities of even the current
largest large scale language models are
just mind-blowing the ability of these
systems to have a good sense for what
people are thinking about others at
least how they they express it in
language um the ability for example I
mean I and this was was an example I I
actually created for my colleagues at
ostp say well give me an example of how
these back when it was kind of a newish
thing dpt4 and I created an up thology
case um an actual you know sort of
anonymized case but at the end I said
what are the patient's questions now
that she received this diagnosis and the
system is brilliant at writing down um
the questions that a patient would ask
so in some ways when it comes to
psychology don't ask me how but through
sifting through and learning from
corpora of fiction and non-fiction large
scale Corp this the idea of the systems
are actually learning a remarkable
amount it seems of psychology
even without being embodied in a
relationship with a human and so on they
just seem to be that's the kind of thing
that we write a lot about I
think so yeah I was really assessing the
how it felt I'm puzzling over that one
yeah but no but but I just been
seriously wanting to talk to a human for
the humanness not the
competency I I tried to remove that from
that
assessment so so one um
in this AI era are we going to be are we
going to lose human skills are we going
to become less effective than we are
today how do we how do we ra how do we
raise the the human capacity in addition
to the the capacity of these systems or
at least not diminish the human
capacity so you talked about agency and
dignity I mean for those of us who sit
in rooms like this maybe part of our
agency and dignity is also our
intellectual capacity but that's
probably not universally true how how do
we how do we make sure that you know in
addition to agency and dignity there's
we continue to drive the human
intellect I think it's a really good
question I mean I'd like to It's that
kind of question like to take credit for
it but it was here from from the
audience yeah no I think it's a really
good question I think many of the
questions you've asked today I would
feel more comfortable sitting in a
multi-party stakeholder setting because
it's it's not really my answers I have
my intuitions but your answers have been
remarkably
informative but I've learned from
colleagues this disciplines and and this
is one reason we set up the the
partnership on AI to hear from different
people and learn from different
perspectives Microsoft recently uh made
a deal a deal an arrangement with the
aflc IO um where we agreed to like three
different major steps to keep each other
informed about influences of AI on jobs
in the economy to work together on
Skilling uh and uh to stay in touch um
and I think we need those kinds of links
between people on the ground people that
represent uh professionals uh blue
collar White Collar academics to
understand how things are going to how
these technologies will
influence uh people's daily lives and
their professions and their jobs and
their choice of jobs if they're younger
um in the paper that I mentioned that
Abby selin and I wrote It's on archive
right now um it's called the rise of the
AI
co-pilot um we talk about
co-pilots as covered in the human
factors literature you know plane
co-pilots and there's a lot that's been
written about the loss of
skills uh and
the ability the need to train and rigor
that Pilots must go through but to not
be dependent on their on their on their
co-pilots or their uh in you know their
autopilot in the plane I mean
um and
um I think it's a great area for
scholarship to understand uh loss of
skills um people are saying in the in
when it comes to the Sciences right now
that we haven't seen genius yet in these
systems um and it could be that for a
long time to come there's something
remarkable about human beings ability to
think out of the box and these tools
will just bolster their abilities to do
science uh it's interesting when I first
um uh was was testing gbd4 out I think I
took it to FR Maria I had Francis Arnold
play with it at one of our breaks a
pcast in a noisy bar I was there you
were there too so so we so Francis
Arnold was like okay let me see this
thing I had heard about this and he
started you know challenging the system
with uh various silicon Centric
chemistries and after we were ready to
move on to dinner and we had closed the
laptop she said yeah it's kind of like a
seconde grad student now now imagine
hearing that 10 years ago where someone
will
say yeah second year grad student as if
that's like a failure of the ice system
um so here we are with a new bar but
still it it hasn't blown the minds of
scientists yet and and sa prometer and I
as part of another pcast project we're
looking at we worked with a physicist at
Princeton looking at the origins of the
the um universe and some questions about
cycling versus Big Bang vers models and
there different models coming to into
Vogue now into into into um awareness or
or review and I think what I got back
from Saul after he engaged with uh his
Princeton colleague was kind of like a
seconde grad student so it's interesting
will we go beyond that someday it could
be that the Sciences are a place where
we don't lose our skills and we just get
bolstered and push ahead with our human
creativity so I wanted to change gears
to a different kind of topic here um
which is there's a lot of concern out
there about the energy usage and demands
both of the training of these large
language models and then uh or large AI
models generally and then even though
the individual inferences aren't
necessarily that expensive when you
integrate over all the inference for
doing so how how are you thinking about
that how you you yourself how's
Microsoft thinking about
that so um I think we just discussed
this earlier in your conference room so
on Monday on Earth day uh I and several
colleagues had our a paper published in
nature it's a comment piece where we
spent months it was an interdiciplinary
group we spent months looking at Power
projections and analyses for AI and the
paper is all about is AI going to help
us or or hinder Us in getting to into
Net Zero on carbon um and we talked
about the need to do research and
scenarios but one interesting finding
that came out was you know a credible
projection is that we may need 10 times
the amount of compute for AI in four
within four
years and and as I said in my little
tweet when I was you know roll the paper
out on Monday uh to my to my colleagues
to my network I said scary sounds very
scary but do you realize that will bring
that power uh amount up to the quantity
of power used by Americans watching
television so so so I don't I'm not
concerned about global power in carbon
right now I also see interesting trends
like 53 mini that was just shipped can
run on a cell phone on a client without
the cloud for example certainly the
training of the largest models is taking
quite a bit of uh impressive amounts of
electric power uh that's amortised over
time when it's when these models are
used um but
uh when it comes to the scenarios I
personally fall on the side of AI being
a boon in leading to some breakthroughs
on the chemistry's catalysis and
thinking about how
to the and designs for how to address
sustainability challenges um but we we
should keep an eye on it for example for
we know it's a thousand times the
confute yeah well great I want to thank
the audience but I want to especially
thank Eric for joining us and for your
incredibly thoughtful observations and
willingness to take such a crazy wide
range of
questions thanks for the questions
everybody thanks for the questions
I'll just like this to you I want you
get sick BL your
hand so please do join us across the
street in stada uh for reception