thank you for the introduction and thank
you for the opportunity to share some of
our work with you here so the actual
title is a little longer than what's in
the program that's because for analog
energy efficient Hardware I'm going to
share with you our electrochemical
devices as a biop plausible Hardware
platform that can enable energy
efficient brain inspired
Computing so this is what I'm going to
share with you is a collaborative effort
between myself my group as well as my
colleagues asella Lama and Julie on
materials and devices as well as with
Michael fee in connection to
Neuroscience in the longer term and of
course the results that I will share
with you are the product of the work of
our current and past group members PhD
students and postdocs who have been
working with us that we are very
grateful to so as the theme of this
session AI we are for a number of years
aware of the exploding energy need of AI
training and and use contexts and it's
growing very fast and the data that was
shown to you earlier by Tomas that shows
projection of compute energy by 2045
thanks to AI is supposed to consume all
over world's electricity production
which is of course not sustainable and
the CO2 emissions associated with that
energy cons consumption using the
current grid is of course a big concern
and we have been aware of this for a
number of years so as you have heard in
the introduction I'm also with the
nuclear science and engineering
department and until this year I would
joke at the beginning of my talks that
you need a small modular nuclear reactor
to go with each data center or to train
major machine learning models but it's
no longer joke so as of last month
especially these big tech companies
Amazon Microsoft Google have been racing
with each other in buying and investing
in nuclear like Microsoft bought a
recently closed nuclear reactor to
reopen it just to power their data
centers Google and Amazon have been
investing in new nuclear reactor
technologies that they're trying to push
as fast as possible just to power their
data center so this is um huge issue
extremely fast growing energy demand of
data centers and Ai and of course one
way to reduce the CO2 emission pain is
to buy nuclear in the near term but
there are of course bigger efforts in
the field both from hardware and
software perspectives to reduce the
energy consumption of
computing and one approach that we are
involved with in includes physical
neural networks that combine processing
and memory in one unit in order to
reduce energy consumption associated
with data shuttling in our current
Computing architectures and in such
Hardware physical neural networks the
connectivity of the array is to emulate
the connectivity of the neurons but the
cross points are essential and they are
supposed to be trained and represent
node weights in a physical neural
network and at the same time emulate
some functionality of the synapses both
for near-term and long-term application
so there
conductance should be programmable by
voltage pulses that we apply by voltage
history that we apply at these cross
points and at least for the hardware
deep neural network applications there
are some industry targets that we should
keep in mind which of course includes
very fast programmability on the order
of nanosecond time scales programming
with low voltage order of one volt
storage capacity up to 100 or 100 States
conductance change change order of
tenfold and a constraint on the high
resistance that should not be lower than
about 110 Mega ohm variation should be
low enough so that the network can be
trained reliably and the target there is
less than 30% and of course it has to be
low energy with a target of less than
ftoj per programmed state so those are
numbers we can keep in mind for the
nearer term Hardware DNN application and
I can tell you from the beginning that
no current device technology at those
synaptic connections at present address
all of these targets simultaneously so
we are working in with those Targets in
mind okay and before I show you what we
are working on let's look briefly at a
higher level at the biological synapse
where we know the synaptic connection
strength so the signal transmission is
depends on the electrical history at
each synapse
we can obtain long-term increase or
decrease of that synaptic connection
that's referred to as potentiation or
depression so that's simple conductance
change but there are also very
interesting dynamics that that takes
place in the biological synapse where
the extent and sign of this conductance
change can depend on the relative timing
of signals that come to the synapse from
the Press synaptic or the post synaptic
neuron that's referred to for example as
Spike timing dependent
plasticity and to do this changing
conductance and also Dynamics the
biological synapse has small cations
that it transmits through the synaptic
connection under voltage difference so
you can see this as a chemical or
electrochemical cell that transmits
small cat like sodium pottassium calcium
that then triggers certain chemical
reactions to change the conductance of
the synapse so small cat involved but in
liquid medium and organic material of
course so the question for us has been
can we be inspired from these ionic
processes to emulate these synaptic
functions or potentiation and dynamic
changes in the potentiation but using
inorganic materials that we can make
devices out of and the ions that we can
work with can of course include the
biological ions but also others like
smaller ones for example proton or
lithium and we do so the type of devices
that we work with do use these type of
ions and we refer to them as
electrochemical ionic synapses or
electrochemical Ram whose goal is to
serve as the synaptic devices in those
physical neural networks in a low energy
and as biop plausible manner as possible
and these devices are nothing but
miniaturized batter batteries in fact
the thermodynamic and kinetic working
principles are the same as batteries but
we want these to be low energy and low
capacity unlike the batteries you want
for your mobile devices or for your cars
so we have a reservoir where we store
the iron and if this is a metal this can
also be the Gate of the device that's at
the top shown on the sketch the bottom
is the target material the channel that
we are trying to
tune and separated by an electric
electronically insulating but ionically
conducting electrolyte and as you apply
a positive potential at the gate or the
reservoir you oxidize the stored ion so
in this case we're working with the
smallest ion proton we store it as
hydrogen and it becomes proton migrates
through the electrolyte under potential
difference and the electrons take the
outer circuit if you have chosen the
channel material appropriately the
electron brought together with the
proton can be done ated into electronic
states of the material and serve as
anend type doping and tune up the
conductivity so for example Tung noide
is um semiconductor that we are working
with with about 2.8 EV band Gap the
electron brought together with proton
gets donated into ingap States
associated with tungsten and form
polaronic carriers and increase
electronic conductivity so after such
right if you open the circuit you can
obtain ultimate nonvolatility because
electrons cannot go back and therefore
the ions cannot go back but there are
other more practical ways of getting
nonvolatility from these devices too so
the range of wies we can work with is
Broad but everything I will show you is
with protons because protons are the
smallest ions in solid state which allow
faster diffusivity faster speed and
lower energy in doing
so so the layers that involve the St
storage of proton in the form of
hydrogen is metal hydrides so we are not
relying on water or some or organic
hydrogen Source but a practical metal
hydde that we can work with padium
hydrite the channel can be a number of
different semiconductors which
intercalate small cations and the
results that I will share with you are
from Tung noide and the electrolytes we
started with our polymeric just to
demonstrate the concept like nepon and
then we move to inorganic materials to
be able to downscale the device
Dimensions such as silica zironia and
havia that I will show to you so the
behavior that I exemplify here is that
the conductance goes up after each
positive voltage pulse that's sent to
the gate and that's because we are
inserting protons and electrons in a
nonvolatile way way into the channel and
we are not limited to only few pulse
pulses you can apply thousands of pulses
and the example on the right is showing
this potentiation depression Behavior
with a number of pulses that brings
protons in in going up and takes protons
out as well as the electrons out as we
go down in the depression side of the
curve so this is the behavior you want
for being able to implement this in the
training of Hardware DNS as fast as
possible and while we started with
naphon as the um very fast conducting
protonic electrolyte this is not
conducive to scaling down so it's
interesting that we can run these
protonic devices with other thin film
oxides that function as electrolyte like
silica hnia and
zironia and these thin film oxides as
the electrolyte layer actually allow us
to run these devices very fast down to
four five nond programming speed
with very low energy consumption on the
order of 10 or tens of atj per
programmed State just the
electrochemical energy consumption part
and so it's that being extremely low
energy is very
encouraging and what's intriguing that I
will note here is that these oxides like
silica havia zonia they are actually
insulating dial electrics they don't
pass ions or electrons in their bulk if
we just rely on their bulk lattice but
we have to make them in low density at
the verge of
nanoporosity so that they can absorb
humidity or absorb water and O groups
that allow to conduct the protons
through this internally percolated path
so it's like internal surface
conduction so because the mechanism
relies on intercalation of the ions into
the lattice of the channel it's a
uniform non- filamentary
mechanism and unlike the filamentary
resistive switching mechanism in the
field like metal filament formation or
oxygen vacancy filament formation in
dielectrics it's much more repeatable
and therefore more reliable for training
so what I'm showing here is the cycle to
cycle variability of a Tung snide half
pelium hydde device showing 800 Cycles
with very good repeatability and if you
quantify the variability it's about 1%
over more than 2 million uh right pulses
across about 800 Cycles spanning the
right conductance regime so staying in
the low conductance regime which is very
encouraging and the target is actually
30% or less for variability so cycle to
cycle is already well achieving that
even with devices that we make in our
labs in in the
University when we compare device to
device variability of course this is
more challeng in but even in that case
when we are looking at channels that
have different micr structures channels
that have different sizes still this set
is above the Micron scale regime the
variability on average is about 10% so
this is standard deviation of the
conductance change over the mean again
staying in the very low conductance
regime this is a very challenging thing
to do in fact and that 10% may look high
just as the number but again for this
this application Hardware DNN the target
is 30% and it was actually not possible
to achieve this with state-of-the-art RM
to date and if you look at the data on
the right that's from literature even
though the conductance regime is much
higher 100 fold higher conductance
regime the variability device to device
is 10 fold or more which is not
acceptable so this ion intercalation
approach giving us a uniform nominally
uniform mechanism to to change is much
more controllable and repeatable that
should improve the reliability of the
training of networks with them so that's
all let's say quantification of certain
specifications for near-term Hardware
applications where we want the
conductance change fast low energy but
we don't care about the Dynamics so if
you think longer term there are
interesting dynamics that take place in
learning rules such as the example I
gave at the beginning Spike timing
dependent plastic City and because we
are also working with ions and charge
transfer reactions which are actually
very nonlinear with voltage can we
emulate some of these nonlinear
processes also in the biological synapse
so for this we constructed a simple
circuit around the electrochemical
device which allows us to overlap the
pre synaptic and the post synaptic
voltage
pulses and apply app that at the gate
and also design the voltage pulse form
so that we can emulate some of these uh
nonlinear uh types of potentiation at
the synapsis so what we are essentially
sending to the gate of the
electrochemical device becomes um linear
superposition of the press synaptic and
the post synaptic voltage pulses at the
at the neurons that come to the
synapse and I won't go into details but
again using the simple circuit and
designing the voltage forms
appropriately we can emulate different
types of sdp that takes place in
different places of our brain so the
leftmost one is the most commonly
referred Spike timing PL Spike timing
dependent plasticity and that takes
place in a particular uh part of our
brain that's um qualitatively sketched
in the top row but the other three that
come from hippocampus or pyramid
hippocampus or entorhinal parts of our
brain they all show different Dynamic
learning rules at the synapse so they
are all referred to as stdp but the
functional form is different and there
are others also in fact and the key for
us has been to come up with that simple
controll circuit and Leverage The
nonlinearity of our electrochemical
devices and deterministically designed
voltage forms that can give us that can
allow us to emulate these different stdp
functions in in our inorganic devices so
these can be then integrated into
spiking neural networks for even more
energy efficient um AI applications
longer term than
DNA and of course the biological process
is in the milliseconds but we can tune
down this stdp response also to the nanc
time scale both by increasing the
voltage which is really a nonlinear
effect but also by changing the geometry
in particular making the electrolyte
thinner and that can give you a wide
time scale to play with that connects to
neuroscience at the millisecond time
scale but also can get things much
faster at the nanc time scale and again
if we compare this stdp behavior and its
controllability to other attempts of
stdp in the literature we can see much
lower variability of the data using
these deterministic electrochemical
devices across the whole time scales
that we could program even down to the
nanc regime the variability that we
quantify from this stdp function with
our electrochemical device is much lower
than other attempts with resistive
switching or phase change materials or
ferroelectric tunnel Junctions or fero
electric fats that attempt to do this
but with much less controllability
so controllable stdp functions fast
programmability and low variation better
reliability are all
possible so very briefly even longer
term what else can we do with these
ionic devices so we talked about
Hardware DNN potentially stdp but when
we talk to our Neuroscience colleagues
they of course know much more than us
and we were very motivated to connect to
one of them Michael Fe who has been
working on deducing a learning rule that
describes how baby birds learn to sing
and I won't go into the details but the
mechanism involves three signals and
first is the stored Melody that the baby
bird listens and stores at a certain
part of his brain and the variability
that it generates so vocal exploration
and first as it generates this
variability there must be a context of
the song that is coincidence So Random
variability but there is good match so
that's not enough if there is good match
between the variability and the stored
context of the
song before too late if a third signal
the reward comes in then the
corresponding synapsis that control the
vocal cord for the right Melody can be
strengthened so you need three of these
signals to be coincident at different
time sequences and therefore it's
referred to as three Factor learning
room in particular this first
coincidence between the vocal
variability so vocal exploration and the
stored context of the song is extremely
important and if there is coincidence
then what's produced is something called
eligibility Trace which makes that
coincidence eligible for being
rewarded and it's a nonlinear signal in
time also it increases and decays over
time time and the question for us is is
this possible to also generate by ionic
devices and indeed we can do this so the
devices that I introduced to you can be
nonvolatile if you open the gate or
float the gate but they can also be
volatile depending on the voltage form
they apply as well as keeping the gate
not
floating and so pretty much we use a
volatile version of the same device to
serve as this and coincidence and delay
weight operator to generate the
eligibility Trace that is defined in
neuroscience and very quickly I can
because I'm showing this to you it means
we are actually able to generate this
signal so the eligibility Trace
generation with context and variability
signals being coincident gives us this
lower experimental data which indeed
looks like the functional form of the
eligibility Trace discussed in
neuroscience and if the two signals that
are not coincident the output of that
volatile device does not give us the
non-zero eligibility tra and if on top
of the generated eligibility tra we have
a third signal the reward that comes in
before the eligibility Trace completely
decays then we can obtain different
extents of strengthening at the ultimate
synapse that's the second
device and even if there is eligibility
even if there is reward but no
eligibility Trace so the context was not
matched then even if you have reward
it's random and the output actually does
not generate strengthening of the
synapse we are very excited about this
because it becomes an all ionic circuit
not only the synapse but also the
control circuit around it and it's a
very simple um footprint very low energy
in capturing this essential building
block of a biop plausible learning rule
that can be applicable to other
mechanisms as well so with that I will
stop and end by repeating that we are
very excited about these ionic
electrochemical devices that are
deterministically controlled in their
electronic modulation mechanism gives us
the ability to do very low energy
processing and very fast down to atle
and nanc regime still there are
challenges that I have not told you
about and I'm happy to discuss during
the break so we have to work on coming
up with better materials for these
devices in fact and Beyond um near-term
Hardware DNN context they can also be
enablers of energy efficient Hardware
building blocks for brain inspired
Hardware such as spiking neural networks
or these biop plausible learning rules
that I have exemplified you from
Neuroscience so with that I will stop
here and hope you have some questions
and interest either now or during the
break
thank you Professor yudi uh let's see
whether we have any questions from the P
hall no yeah anyway since uh we have um
limited time today uh so you're welcome
to submit questions either you can talk
to Professor yodis during the break or
you can send uh email to Professor
directly or you can contact LP as well
uh thank you very much thank you thank
you professor