(upbeat music)
- When I was a child,
we got Scientific American every month,
and I read a lot of the articles in it,
but one thing that really fascinated me
was this column by Martin Gardner called,
Mathematical Games that
he had every month.
And I was really very taken by it.
As an undergrad at Caltech,
I took a lot of quantum physics.
It was either two or
three semesters of it,
that's because I was thinking
of becoming a physics major,
but I did not like lab
courses enough to do it.
So I became a math major instead.
But you know, that really,
I guess, introduced me
to quantum mechanics,
and got me thinking
about quantum mechanics.
And when I got to MIT,
I took a lot of different courses.
I took Algorithms and Cryptography,
and Number Theory,
really, you needed all of these courses
to discover the factoring algorithms.
So you needed some
things from mathematics,
some things from computer science,
and some things from physics.
I was taking courses because
I was interested in them,
not because I thought they would be
ultimately useful for something,
led me to discover this quantum,
this quantum factoring algorithm.
The first time I started
thinking seriously
about quantum computing
was after I saw Umesh Vazirani
give a talk at Bell Labs,
and I started thinking about
quantum computing at that
time, I didn't tell anybody.
And then the next thing that happened
was I saw Dan Simon's paper about
his algorithm for solving Simon's problem,
which is another contrived problem
that quantum computers can do faster
than classical computers.
But this one was really,
I wanna say this was really
kind of like a blueprint
for the factoring algorithm,
then figured out how to
do Fourier transforms
over Z mod P,
where P's a smooth number
on a quantum computer.
And then I think I got up
in the middle of the night
and scribbled some stuff down,
and that gave me a discreet log algorithm
for primes that are one larger,
where P minus one is smooth.
And so a smooth number is one
that has a lot of small factors.
So I had a factoring
algorithm for smooth numbers.
This algorithm was so different
from the classical algorithm
that I think I, you know,
it encouraged me rather
than discouraging me
I played around with it quite a bit more,
and I figured out how to use
the Fourier transform
for P when P was smooth
to factor to find the
discrete log for any number.
I mean, that was great.
That was, I could solve something
with a quantum computer
that you can't solve with
a classical computer.
And it was, you know,
a very important problem,
because discreet logs are
used for crypto systems.
I used to work on algorithm for
problems in computer science
and now I work on quantum computing,
so it's changed direction.
I still kept working
on traditional computer science algorithms
for a few years after
the factoring algorithm was discovered.
But then I started doing more and more
just quantum computing.
And I guess the first thing
I did after quantum computing
was quantum error correction.
Without error correction,
you can't get very far
on a quantum computer.
My algorithm has completely
changed cryptography
because cryptographers
now know that the RSA
and Diffie-Hellman,
and the old crypto systems
is based on discrete log and factoring
are not necessarily going
to be secure for ever.
So they're trying to come up with
quantum resistant crypto systems,
and this has been an
immense area of research.
We would really like to
make these crypto systems
as efficient as possible without,
you know, compromising them,
and I really don't think
they know how to do that yet.
So there's going to be a
lot more research on these.
This is my office.
I do a lot of things here.
I work with students, I meet students,
I work on my computer,
writing papers and doing calculations.
I'm going to describe the steps
in the factoring algorithm.
I'm not gonna explain why they work,
because that would take
a really long time.
But, so what do you do?
Well, there's a part that
you do on a quantum computer,
and then there's post-processing
that you do on a classical computer.
And the factoring algorithm,
you want to find
P x Q = N.
So you're given N,
and you wanna find two primes
that multiply to N.
And start with
two quantum registers.
(chalk scratching on board)
And these are just basically registers
that are supervision of numbers.
The first one,
so the first one has 2L qubits
and the second one has L qubits.
And you start the first register,
well you start them all
in say zero.
So every qubit is in the state zero.
And now what you do is
you apply a transformation
that takes this state to
one over two zero plus one,
to the 2L.
And now this is the same as
summation over I = 10 through two
to the 2L - 1.
I'm sorry,
I with one over two to the L
normalization factor
in front of it is zero.
Now the next thing you do
is you choose a random number X.
Well, I choose random X
with zero less than X, less than N.
And now you compute
X to the I
mod N in the second register.
(gentle music)
(chalk scratching on board)
And now what you do is you take
the quantum Fourier transform
of the first register,
(gentle music)
and you measure the first register,
and this will give you,
well this will give you a number,
but the wonderful link of the number
is that you can then take this number,
and do some post-processing on it.
So basically you do
continued fraction algorithm,
and it will give you
the factors of N if you're lucky.
Do I have any hobbies outside of work?
I like writing poetry,
and I posted a few of my poems on the web.
I like walking,
but we have a dog now
that I take on walks, generally every day,
she needs like two or
three walks each day.
And I like to read a lot.
I like science fiction especially,
but really I like pretty
much any kind of book.
I've had a very successful career.
Part of its success
is that I've chosen some very
difficult problems to work on
and I haven't solved
anywhere near all of them.
Maybe I've solved a third of
the really difficult problems
that I have worked on,
and you know, a third is actually enough.
But if I was giving advice
to a young researcher,
I would say,
don't spend a hundred percent of your time
working on really difficult problems,
because if you don't solve them,
which is a very likely thing to happen,
then you have nothing to
show for your time.
But there's always a chance
you will solve a really difficult problem
and those are really,
you know, good for your career.
We keep finding new areas of mathematics
that can be used in quantum computing,
so don't hesitate to get
a really broad background,
even if you think it's
going to be irrelevant.