well good morning and welcome every time
I see that video I'm always inspired and
almost giddy that I'm the luckiest
person here to be working in this uh in
this ecosystem right I love uh what I do
and I'm so excited to uh welcome you
here to hear all the ground baking work
that's going on at MIT today's
conference is going to be focusing on
gener generative Ai and how it will help
um reshape and reimagine
and you know business and business
futures um with that today's conference
is going to have 12 different uh faculty
members talking about their research six
industry panelists and 11
startups moving on to um a lot of you
may know about MIT a lot of you may know
something about MIT I'm going to just
give you a snapshot about what is MIT
MIT has 177,000 plus uh employees has
almost 1100 uh faculty members has 11 uh
almost 12,000 students out of which 4500
are undergraduates and 7,500 are
graduate students and um 29% of the
student body is
international it comprises of five
schools and one college you have the
School of Engineering School of Science
uh management um School of Management
SLO School school um School of
humanities arts and social sciences uh
School of Architecture and planning and
the College of
computing but what does it do in terms
of all these things comprise in terms of
65 re 6 65 plus because we can never
keep track of exactly how many they are
um research Labs centers and programs um
$840 million on campus sponsored
research 20 % of those come from
industry sponsors and many of which
comes from members uh of the ILP program
um 592 us patents filed uh in 23 fi23 uh
362 uh patents issued uh in fi23 $4.2
million in licensing revenue and 23 MIT
companies startup uh started up using
MIT um uh intellectual property
this is of course MIT is doing wonderful
groundbreaking research in many many
areas but these are the three areas
where our president is you know for you
know forging a path ahead for us to
focus on changing world problems and US
solving them so that is climate and
sustainability life sciences and
AI how do we do this we do it by
innovating we do it by our
groundbreaking research but Innovation
right and of course when you talk about
Innovation Innovation means different
things to different people but how do we
Define innovation we at MIT Define
innovation as the process of taking
ideas from inception to impact and the
word impact is so important and that's
what we do every day each person at MIT
in our own ways try to make ideas um
from you know uh ideas from inception to
impact
now what do we do we are the industry
Leone program and what do we do we we
try to bridge the gap between industry
and academic research at MIT and so how
do we do it we have the way of thinking
about it in four brackets one is
research Innovation students and
education but how do we Bridge those
gaps is through understanding and
learning for our ILP member companies
and how they can learn learn about The
Cutting Edge um research happening
through webinars conferences through
executive briefings through um uh
professional education through exec Ed
and many other opportunities happening
through open learning you can learn and
discover Pro problems or discover new um
ideas and opportunities and you can we
can facilitate that through faculty
meetings meetings with labs and centers
strategic Executive Education for your
uh executive leaders assistance with
identification of opportunities for
sponsored research Consortium membership
visiting Scholars and IP licensing and
lastly we do it by networking and this
is an opportunity where you can network
with your colleagues with MIT faculty
with MIT students you can also network
with startups in uh the MIT ecosystem
and many more opportunities beyond that
and I want to leave with a thank you but
at the same time I want to also uh alert
you to the fact that none of this
happens with me standing up here it's it
starts with a lot of hard work from our
teams and I just wanted to give a shout
out to um the events team sitting there
um events and communication team and
also if you want to learn more about the
ILP program many of our program
directors are sitting amongst you in the
audience and would be happy to answer
any questions thank you so much
[Applause]
enjoy thank you gri for the wonderful
wonderful introduction for MIT ecosystem
and uh coroporate relations including uh
the overview of uh today of uh this
conference over the next couple days uh
good morning good afternoon and good
evening welcome to
MIT we are so excited to have you with
us uh both in person and
online over the uh over the over these
two
days MIT faculty members industry
leaders entrepreneurs will share their
insights on how emerging technology
strategies
particularly generative AI can help you
drive your digital transformation or
business transformation and shape the
future of your
industry I want to say this is a unique
opportunity for you to engage learn and
network for those who are here in person
you have a wonderful opportunity to
connect with our faculty speakers
through your program
directors to explore solutions to your
specific
challenges and also thank you for
joining us I hope you enjoy the
conference during the Q&A we use pugun
Hall life to submit
questions and vote on questions interest
you and the p p life information is on
display on both
sides uh the the passcode is 24
digital and uh for those who are online
you can also submit questions