hello can people hear me in the
back yeah thumbs up
okay uh so today we're going to be
continuing our discussion of uh
probability uh in the last lecture we
saw uh how to compute probabilities
using the uh oh dear uh using the uh
tree method and this lecture we are
going to uh you know see how some of the
tools that we learned in the last unit
for
counting uh for for reasoning about the
sizes of sets and things like that can
also carry over naturally into the uh
into the realm of probability okay uh
and we'll also learn how to express
mathematically uh statements like uh if
you recall I was saying things last time
like you know if the prize is behind
door a what is the probability that uh
Marilyn selects door b or or something
like that okay so we're going to uh you
know see you know more formally what
these statements are are trying to
express and how to reason about them
okay so uh recall how we Define the
probability of an event a so an event is
just a set of
outcomes uh our probability function PR
is a function from uh the set of
outcomes the sample space uh to the
interval 0 to 1 and we can can extend
this naturally to events by saying that
the probability of an event is just the
sum of the probabilities of all of the
outcomes in that event
okay so an immediate consequence of this
definition or several immediate
consequences I suppose are the following
so first we have the sum
rule so if we have two events uh A and B
and they're disjoint so A and B are
disjoint of
events this tells us that the
probability of the Union of A and
B is what what do we think that
is any
ideas
yeah yeah the sum of the probabilities
so probability of
a plus the probability of B
okay so very similar to what we saw with
sets if you have two disint sets the
size of their Union is the same as as
the uh sum of the individual sizes the
same thing happens with
probability okay uh we also have the
complement
rule so if we have some event a what do
we think the
probability of the complement of a is so
the probability that a does doesn't
occur oh I should
probably
yeah what's the probability of not
a anybody
yeah yeah one minus the probability of
a
okay right because uh a and not a are
disjoint and one of them must happen so
you know with certainty uh one of a or
not a happens so the probability of
their Union is one so this kind of just
follows from the sum rule
okay what else do we
have uh the difference
rule okay so in this case suppose we
have uh again two events a and B and
this time we'd like to look at the
difference a set minus
B what do we think that might be in
terms of the probabilities of A and
B yeah
exactly so the probability of
a minus the
probability of the
intersection
okay and why is that well a is just the
disjoint Union of a minus b and a
intercept B
okay uh we also have an analog of
principle of uh inclusion exclusion
so the probability of
uh a union B for more General A and B so
you know they're not necessarily
disjoint
anymore just like we had with sets this
is going to be the probability of
a plus the probability of
B minus the
probability of the
intersection okay
and we have a couple of um new uh rules
that don't really have analoges in in
the case of uh uh like in the case of
counting
sets so first we have the union
Bond
oops
so probability of a union B it's less
than or equal to probability of
a plus probability of b or I suppose I
shouldn't say it doesn't really have an
analog but we didn't really look at the
analog
okay and why might that be the
case yeah oh
yeah uh so uh the question is what's the
difference between the sum Rule and Pi
so so in the sum rule we assume that A
and B are
disjoint okay so if a and b are disjoint
then their intersection is is empty so
the intersection has zero probability so
Pi is just a way to generalize uh the
the sum rule okay to to the case where
they're they're not necessarily disjoint
anymore they may have a non-trivial
intersection okay good question any
other
questions no okay so can anybody give a
reason why the union bound might be
true
yeah yeah so the answer was the
probability of the intersection is not
negative right so uh you know if we just
take PI right so this holds you know
with
equality and now if we just you know get
rid of this negative term here we can
only increase the uh the probability
because all probabilities have to be
between zero and one
okay uh we also have
monotonicity again I don't think we uh
you know saw an analogue of this with
sets but uh you know
if a is a subset of B what do you think
that tells us about the uh probabilities
and
ites I'm I'm seeing some uh hand
motions
so as you might expect from the
name if a is a subset of B then its
probability should be smaller than the
the probability of
B
okay so do these make uh do these make
sense to everybody
okay so just as we saw with uh with
sets uh both the sum rule the union
bound and uh principle of inclusion
exclusion can all generalize to you know
arbitrary numbers of of uh events uh or
even you know countably many okay uh I
suppose principle of inclusion exclusion
you should probably only think about you
know finite cases but the other two are
you know they fairly naturally
generalize to uh to countable sets of
events okay so do these rules make sense
to everybody he'll probably be using
them quite a lot so uh you know make
sure you're familiar with
them any
questions
okay so in that case let us move on to
the main topic of today's lecture
conditional
probability okay so if you recall on
Tuesday when we were talking about the
Monty Hall problem when we were drawing
a tree diagram right um we were making
statements such as you know if the car
is behind door one what's the
probability that we picked door two or I
guess it was you purple gold and green
uh purple gold silver silver
yeah uh so how do we express this
mathematically uh so that's where
conditional probability comes
in we're going to make use of the
following definition okay so if we have
two
events A and
B uh we Define the conditional
probability
of a given
B
okay uh which we denote as the
following so we' say uh you know a
conditioned on B right we denote that
with a vertical
bar we Define this to be
the
probability of a intersect
B divided by the probability of
B
okay so intuitively you can kind of
think of it a little bit as uh you know
we're trying to scale our probability
space so that you know B becomes our
entire entire sample space okay so we
kind of want to divide out this this
probability of B uh so that you know we
still get a a probability space all of
the probabilities sum to one okay does
that kind of make sense to
everybody and then you know the analog
of a right we're you know only looking
at everything that that's already within
B so we're looking at the intersection
of A and
B
okay now if we rewrite this we can get a
product rule
right so if we want to know the
probability of a intercept B we can kind
of just move this probability of B over
to the other
side and we end up with probability of a
intersect
b
equals probability of a given
B times the
probability of B
okay and as you might expect you can
extend this to multiple
events or I guess this is already kind
of multiple events you can extend it to
more than two
events so you can also have
EG the probability of a intercept B
intercept
C
equals
probability of a given being
T times the
probability of B uh or maybe I should
write this out more
explicitly B intercept C okay and then
if we apply our uh apply our binary
product rule again we can kind of expand
out that uh this
term as the probability of a given B and
C probability of
B given
C
probability of
okay so that's basically what we were
doing on Tuesday you know written out
more formally right so
uh like probability of C corresponds to
you know what is the first Edge we chose
you know the the first Edge going away
from the root okay and then conditioned
on reaching a particular vertex like
conditioned on you know Monty hiding the
prize in the gold
box you know what's the probability that
Marilyn chooses the silver one okay so
that's the conditional probability of
choosing the Silver Box conditioned on
the the prize being in the gold box okay
and then you know as you continue along
the uh uh along the path to a
leaf uh all of the edge probabilities
that you're looking at are secret like
they were secretly just you know basic
additional probabilities okay does that
make sense to
everybody any
questions
okay so another extension of this that
you may find
useful is the
following a intersect B
given
C is going to
be
probability of a given B intercept
C
probability of B given
okay so can anybody see why that might
be the case
well first maybe we should look at you
know what exactly is it saying okay so
if you kind
of squint a little bit and get rid of
the C's
right it kind of looks a little
bit like the product rule right a
intercept B is
probability a given
B times probability of B
okay it it looks kind of like that right
but we've added a bunch of C's
everywhere so basically what we're
saying here is this is the product rule
in the probability space where we're you
know assuming C like it's it's the
product rule conditioned on
C okay does that make sense to
everybody and we can you know obtain it
from the from the previous line just by
dividing out by the probability of C
okay do people have questions are we
happy to move on to some examples yeah
sorry uh okay so the question was are we
talking about sets or events uh yes uh
so remember that uh events are defined
to be sets of outcomes right so uh you
know we're talking about events but you
know events are sets and we can treat
them as such so that's why we're using
uh lots of notation here that you would
typically associate with sets like Union
intersection
Etc okay any other questions oh yeah
ah uh so these are not nodes in the tree
um some of uh sorry question was if we
have an event that's like a union B
Union C or something uh are these
General sets or are they nodes in in the
tree um that is a good observation some
of the nodes in the tree kind of
naturally correspond to events right
like uh you know if we draw out our tree
diagram this node here fairly naturally
corresponds to this set of events like
or sorry this set of outcomes those
those two uh leaves in its sub tree uh
but not every event necessarily
corresponds to an internal node of the
tree like that like for instance you
could
have these two uh outcomes
right uh if you you know consider the
set of those two outcomes that's still a
valid event but it doesn't really
naturally correspond to a a a tree Noe
in the same way
does that make
sense oh that that is quite
possible okay um so asking about the
conditional probabilities as they appear
in the
tree uh
yes oh I see okay uh so I guess the the
way that I like to think about uh a
given B um it is an event in a different
probability
space so you can kind of think of uh you
know if you limit uh the scope rather
rather than you know talking about your
entire sample space s if you limit the
the scope to just C so you like scale
all of the probabilities down by by the
probability of C you you end up with a
different probability space so now the
probability of or sorry the event you
know be given C is an event in that
probability space does that make
sense okay yeah
sorry thank you for the clarification
okay so why don't we move on to some
examples then if uh if this makes you
know reasonable amount of sense
hopefully it'll make more sense after
examples okay so uh you know suppose Ash
and Gary are having a bunch of Pokemon
battles against each other and you know
they're doing like a tournament the the
first to win two battles uh wins the uh
the or I guess the series the first to
win two battles wins the series okay and
uh you know the the probability is of
Victor are not you know entirely uniform
so for the first match you know maybe
it's a toss up okay Ash wins with
probability one2 Gary wins with
probability one half okay uh but after
the first battle there's kind of an
advantage to whoever won the last battle
like you know their their their morale
is high or something they they do better
so they now have probability of 2/3 uh
of winning the next battle
okay and there aren't there aren't any
draws uh they're bitter Rivals they will
fight to the death
um
okay so let's define a couple of events
we'll say that a is the
event Ash
wins oops the
series and
B is the event uh Ash wins
the first
battal
okay so now we can ask for the
probability of a given
B
okay so does does the problem setup make
sense yeah okay so how could we compute
this any ideas where do we want to
start should we just throw some numbers
out there oh
yeah yeah let's draw a tree diagram nice
one okay
so drawing a tree diagram what's the
first you know random thing that happens
what's the what's the first source of
Randomness
yeah yeah so F could win or lose the
first battle so we can actually label
these as
B and not B
okay what's the next random thing that
could
happen
yeah yeah that's right so actually maybe
it's better to call these just W and L
so we can use the same thing
everywhere so win lose win lose
regardless of uh whether he wins or
loses the first battle you can still
either win or lose the second one Okay
now what's the third layer going to
be
exactly yeah exactly okay so if he's one
two or lost two those are just leaves
now we don't do anything more the series
is over okay but if he's won one and
lost one in either order we can now
split
again oops that's a little bit long but
oh well WL
WL
okay so now what are our outcomes again
let's look at the uh uh paths from from
root to leaves and just you know label
with a uh a string of edge labels so
this is going to be W comma w w l
w w l
l l w w l w l and l
l
okay now what are the probabilities on
each of the edges
so in the first layer what's the
probability that Ash wins the first
game first match
yeah2 so each of these say probability
one2 okay now the second layer we said
are now conditional probabilities so
conditioned on winning the first match
what's the probability of winning the
second
match what's the probability on this
edge here
do we
remember 2/3
yeah and so the other branch is going to
be the complement of that so
1/3 okay and then for the bottom Branch
it's going to be exactly the opposite
okay it's going to be one3 chance of
winning 2/3 chance of
losing okay
now conditioned on winning the first
match and losing the second match what's
the probability of winning the
third
yeah one3
yeah so 1/3 win 2/3 loss and uh this
will be uh exactly the opposite so 2/3
win 1/3 loss
okay so now we can assign probabilities
to all of the outcomes
okay what's the probability of winning
twice how do we compute these
probabilities anyone
yeah uh oh so that this was uh just you
know what we assumed in the problem
right
if uh if it's not the first game uh you
win with probability 2/3 if you won the
last game or with probability 1/3 if you
lost the last
game okay so the the first branch is
50/50 but the subsequent ones are going
to be 2/3 1/3 in One Direction or the
other depending on the outcome of the
previous game maybe I shouldn't use
outcome depending on the result of the
previous
game okay
okay so how do we compute probabilities
of outcomes does anybody
remember
yeah yeah so you multiply probabilities
along paths two outcomes okay so for
this top outcome right we've got uh 1/2
* 2/3 so this is probability
1/3 uh win loss win has probability 1/3
by/ 12 by 1/3 so that's
118th uh when loss loss is probability
1/2 * 1/3 * 2/3 so that's going to be 1
nth uh and then these all
reverse 11 18th and
13 have I done that
correctly yes that looks
fine if I make an error please shout at
me uh okay
so we've got all of the uh we've got our
tree diagram we've got our sample space
we've got our our probability
function uh what's the next thing we
need do we remember
so we've got step one the
tree step two the uh
probabilities three right was the events
of
Interest
okay so what are the events we care
about here
yeah
pardon okay winning the tournament and
winning the first game okay
so uh a was uh y a was winning the
tournament B was winning the first
game uh is that
all are there any other events that we
care about
yeah yes exactly so we also
want a intersect B okay we also care
about the event where you win the first
battle and the series why is
that would you like to explain
or yeah exactly so ultimately we want
this conditional probability right the
probability of a given B and if we go
back to our definition right the
probability of a given B is the
probability of a intersect B divided by
the probability of B okay so as it turns
out we kind of don't really need a right
the two probabilities we really need are
these two or the two events I suppose
okay so finally for answer
what is our
answer well probability of a given
b as we just said is the probability of
a intersect B divide by probability of
B
okay what are each of these
probabilities well which events or sorry
which outcomes are in the event a
intersect B
it's ww in a intercept
B
yeah win loss win also yes okay win loss
loss nope and all of these he lost the
first game so these are also not in it
so we care about these two uh these two
outcomes okay so this is going to be by
the sum rule 1/3 +/ 18
that doesn't look much like an
eight oh well
okay now what's the probability of
B yeah yeah it's just one half right
either by symmetry or you can actually
look at what those outcomes are right
it's these top uh these top three
okay and if we do this arithmetic we've
got 7/8 divided 12 which is 7
nths
okay so the probability that Ash wins
the entire series given that he won the
first battle is going to be
79ths okay so so far this is pretty
straightforward right fairly routine uh
mathemat well
arithmetic but what if
instead we ask for the probability of B
given a
what is that
probability well numerically right we
can compute it in exactly the same way
right it's going to be the probability
of the intersection divided by this time
the probability of a rather than the
probability of B but still by symmetry
that probability is going to be2
okay so this is also going to be 7
9ths but what exactly does it
mean
yeah yeah so the answer was you know
given that you already won the series
what's the probability that he won the
first
battle okay now this might sound a
little bit weird to some of you right
like you know if we know that he's won
the series right everything's already
happened he either won the battle or he
didn't right but uh you know when we're
modeling probability questions you know
we don't really care about any sort of
temporal relations or anything like that
or even causal ones right like uh you
know we're just uh like it it's all just
you know numerical right you can kind of
think of it a bit like an inference
right like you know you've got some
uncertainty right like you know maybe
you're told that he won the battle you
want to or sorry you're told that he won
the series you want to update your
belief that you know maybe he won the
the first battle maybe he didn't uh and
maybe you're not entirely confident in
it uh but you'd like to estimate you
know how confident you should be uh that
might be one way to think about
it um
so in a sense it's kind of like looking
at a backwards probability that you know
something in the past has happened given
that we observed something in the
future uh so you know in general you
know they they won't always be the same
like this like you can kind of relate
the probability of B given a to the
probability of a given B they won't
always be equal okay let's see how to
relate
them it just so happens that in this
case right these two
things
oh these two things have the same
probability okay so that's really the
core reason why they were
equal but more generally we have the
following okay this is called base
rule
okay uh you can kind of think of it is
you know it's just the product rule in
disguise right so the
probability of B given
a equals the probability Oops why don't
I split this into two
lines probability of a given
B probability of
[Music]
B divided by probability of
a okay so in the example we just saw
these two are the same so they just
cancel uh but more generally you want to
multiply by the quotient okay and you
can kind of think of this as the product
rule in disguise right like if you just
move this probability of a over to this
side right uh now you're just Computing
the probability of the intersection of A
and B on both sides does that make
sense but uh it can often be useful uh
you know even though it's not really
saying anything new it can often be
useful to think about it in this way
okay if you kind of want to reverse the
direction of an
inference uh you want to multiply by the
quotient of the two event the two
probabilities of the events that you
care about
okay
uh and one particularly useful
uh consequence of this is the following
so suppose we have two events B and C
and we're kind of trying to condition
them both on the same
event
okay
so what is the probability of C given
a no B given a divided by the
probability of C given
a
okay and in particular often we would
take C to be the complement of b or
something like that and that will then
help us to compute this probability of
being given a
okay so as it turns out this is going to
be the probability of a given
B times the probability of
B divided
by probability of a given
C oops
probability of C
so does that make sense to
everybody and the reason that this might
you know this in particular might be
useful uh in order to compute the
probability of B you know if we uh use B
complement to C
right this right hand side here
does not depend on the probability of a
right like we don't have to compute the
probability of a so maybe if a is some
really nasty event right and we don't
actually want to compute its probability
but we can still condition on it we
might still be able to use this formula
more easily than we could use this
one okay does that make sense to
everybody
okay so let's take a look at a couple of
applications of BAS
R uh or actually
first first maybe I should uh give you a
brief lesson in
statistics uh so
terminology the probability of uh a
given
B uh this would often be called the
likelihood
of a given
B okay so if any of you have ever seen
like maximum likelihood estimations or
anything like that that's where this
comes from or this is where that comes
from
sorry uh probability of B
we call the prior
probability of
B and the left hand side the probability
of being given an
a is the posterior
of
B uh actually we don't usually specify a
with that
oops
okay so this is how you would normally
talk about it like in statistics or
something like that uh the the
likelihood of a given B the prior
probability and the posterior
probability because basically what
you're doing right is you're starting
with some prior right if you don't know
anything like this is kind of what you
think the the probability of B should be
and now you make some uh some
observation a right and so now you
update and you got a posterior
probability of B you know condition on
that that uh uh observation does that
make
sense
okay so why don't we take a look at a
couple of examples then
uh
here hopefully everybody is okay with
those okay so first example suppose I've
got two
coins okay uh I've got one Fair coin
right I toss this coin and it'll come up
heads with 50% probability tails with
50% probability okay and I've also got a
trick coin right it's uh you know double
heads I flip it I always get
heads
okay uh suppose I pick one of these
coins uniformly at
random I flip that
coin and it comes up
heads okay what is the probability that
I picked the far coin to begin with as
opposed to the biased one
any ideas does anybody have any guesses
as to what the probability
is who wants to just dra draw the tree
diagram few people people aren't as
enthusiastic about it as as they were on
Tuesday that's uh that's slightly
unfortunate let's do it anyway uh no
let's let's first uh you know let's make
precise the events that we care about
okay um so let's let H be the event
uh that we flipped
heads uh and uh f is the
event picked the fa
coin
okay so what is the probability that
we're trying to compute
in terms of these two
quantities
yeah probability of f given H
yes
okay so how might we compute
this people didn't seem too enthusiastic
about the tree diagram so what else
could we do instead
does anybody see a way to use base
rule yeah or just a stretch
sorry
yeah yeah the probability of H given f
is easy right that's that's 50% okay so
that's that's an easy known quantity so
if we use base rule right that that
might make it easier to uh to compute
okay
so uh actually why don't we use the uh
you know slightly more complicated
version of Base rule so let's compute
the ratio of the probability that we
picked the faircoin given that we
observed a heads versus you know the the
probability of the of picking the biased
coin given that we observed a heads
okay so the
probability of f given
H over probability of not F given
H so what was that
so right base rule is about you know
flipping the uh flipping the order right
so instead of f conditioned on H we want
H conditioned on
F multiplied by
what yeah yeah probability of f
okay and on the bottom we can do the
same thing probability of H given not
F times the probability of not
F
okay so this expression is much easier
to work with right what's the
probability of H given f
yep2
yeah okay what about the probability of
H given not
F yeah
one and probability of F and not
F those are each one half by assumption
okay
okay so those just cancel and we are
left
with2
okay so
now what is this
probability we computed the ratio of
this probability to its complement
right so what does that tell us the uh
probability
is yeah one3
yeah
okay so OB serve here that uh if our
prior changes right if the if the chance
that we are you know picking the fa coin
to begin with
changes uh this posterior probability
also
changes okay
so you know if if I if I originally
picked the Fair coin with very high
probability
right uh and then I observe a heads
right do you think the uh probability
that a the the posterior probability
should be the same higher or
lower oh yeah how did we get a third oh
question how did we get a
third uh so the ratio of this to its
complement is 12 right they sum to one
right so they're 1/3 and 2/3
okay
yeah the numerical values of h and
f uh so h and f are events they're not
uh they're not numbers
exactly right so you know H is the event
that you know whichever coin I flipped
uh I got a heads on
it right
and F is the event that the the coin I
picked was the Fair
one okay so they're not really numbers
they're just you know sets of outcomes
that could have
happened okay
yeah oh the assumptions right so um you
know pick uh
fair or
biased uh uniformly
and then uh flip
it so fair means it comes up with 5050
you know heads or tails biased it's a
two-headed
coin
okay
yeah uh explain where the one/ third
came from again okay so uh the
probability of f given H over not F
given h
right these are complimentary
probabilities they should sum to one
okay so we figured that the ratio right
is
uh2 okay so you know if we want them to
to sum to one then then they should be
1/3 and
2/3 okay does does that make sense
yeah
okay yeah
sorry oh question if it's biased do we
care in which direction it's biased uh
yes
absolutely so if it's you know a double
tailed coin instead of a double heads
coin right you know if I observe a heads
it must be the Fair coin right because
the the double Tales coin cannot get a
heads right so then my probability is
just one
okay are people reasonably happy with
this example shall we move on to a
second
one
okay second example Co testing woohoo
everybody loves Co testing right oh I
suppose you most of you probably weren't
here when there were those like you know
daily or near daily nasal swabs right
well those those were fun times okay
um so in the next next couple of
examples we're going to see some you
know rather counterintuitive behavior
that uh arises from base rule okay
so you know you just as we were
discussing last time you kind of want to
throw away uh intuitive reasoning and
you know just go with the numbers okay
so suppose
10% of
MIT has
Co
okay uh and everybody has to take a
covid test okay uh they have a false
positive
rate uh uh of uh
30% and false negative
rate of
10% okay so false positive rate means
you know uh if I'm am healthy and I take
a covid test there's a 30% chance that
it's going to be wrong and it's going to
say that I'm I have Co okay okay so it's
it's falsely reporting a positive
positive result uh and false negative is
the opposite so if I'm sick and I take a
covid test there is a 10% chance that it
does not detect it and it reports that
I'm
healthy okay do does the setup make
sense
yeah oh uh question was are the false
positives included in the 10% or is the
10% when you actually have it uh so this
10% is you know conditioned on being
sick okay the conditional probability
that it gets it wrong is
10% and the false positive rate is
conditioned on being oh sorry false
negative is conditioned on being healthy
false positive is conditioned on being
sick
no no positive positive is sick yeah it
was right the first time sorry I'm I'm
confused uh yeah so these are both
talking about conditional probabilities
okay conditioned on being healthy or
sick what's the probability that the
test is accurate or wrong
okay so let's define some
events let's say that H is you know
healthy uh and S can be its
complement
sick uh plus is going to be positive
result and minus is going to be a
negative
result
okay so suppose I take this covid test
and it comes out
positive okay what's the probability
that I have
covid so first what is the probability
that we're trying to compute
yeah probability of
s
unconditionally yeah so s given positive
right the unconditional probability of s
is just 10% by assumption okay what
we're actually looking for is the
probability of uh probability that I'm
sick given that I tested positive okay
because that's the observation that we
made okay so how would we compute
this well let's do the same thing we
just did over
here let's look at the ratio of this
probability to its
complement
okay and and applies apply base
rule so we're going to flip this uh
conditional
here positive given sick times
probability of
sick divided by probability of positive
given
healthy times probability of
healthy
okay now those four probabilities are
probab that we know okay what are
they what's the probability of plus
given that I'm
sick
yeah yeah
90% so let's write that as 0.
n what's the uh prior probability that
I'm sick
yeah 10
10% and now what's the probability of a
positive result condition on being
healthy
yeah yeah that's the false positive
rate3 times and what's the probability
that I'm healthy the prior probility of
I'm
healthy well that's just going to be the
complement of the uh the event that I'm
sick so that's going to
be.
n okay so these NS
cancel this is going to be
1/3 okay so I am 1/3 as likely to be
sick as healthy so the probability that
I'm sick condition on getting the
positive result is actually only one and
four
okay
so probability s given
plus equals
1/4 does that make sense to
everybody so it might seem a little bit
weird right like uh uh you know this
this test is a pretty good one right
like it's usually giving the right
answer but you know I took the test I
got a positive result but I'm still
probably healthy why is
that can anybody explain what's going on
here
yeah yeah exactly so that there's a very
slim chance that I'd Co to begin with so
it's actually much higher now that I've
got a positive result but the uh the the
prior was kind of overwhelmingly in
favor of being healthy and so it's still
you know very likely that I'm healthy
just you know slightly less
so okay so often people kind of
underestimate the uh uh the impact of
the prior in this way okay uh of course
in the real world you generally don't uh
do this so if you get a positive result
uh you can be more confident in it
because you know normally you only test
when you have symptoms right so the
probability that you uh uh that you're
sick given that you tested positive and
you have symptoms that's probably going
to be much higher than
1/4
okay are people happy with
that yeah
okay why don't we look at another
interesting application called Simpsons
paradox
okay so there's actually kind of a funny
story behind this one uh so about 50
years ago uh Berkeley UC Berkeley got
sued right because uh you know that it
was claimed that they were being very
sexist in their admissions
policies um and
uh you know the
claim was that the admissions rate was
much higher for men than it was for
women right so you know that's that's
clearly bad right but then Berkeley
counter claimed by saying that if you
look at each individual Department it's
actually the opposite like women are
being admitted uh with much higher rates
than
men right so
um what's going on was somebody lying
can these both be true
any
ideas
yeah yeah exactly so the uh the the
observation right was that the sizes of
the Departments could be very different
right and what
else
yeah yeah so the the the admissions
rates like the the the overall
admissions rates for the Departments can
also be very different right and so you
know maybe you know there's some
departments like you know let's let's
take a look at a very simple example
okay so suppose we have two departments
e and
CS
okay right uh and you
know maybe both of them mildly favor
women okay but uh uh you know one of
them is much more popular with men one
of them is much more popular with women
and they have very different admissions
rates you know
generally
okay so
maybe uh we have a 100 men and 100 women
applying to you know this two Department
UC
Berkeley
okay and uh maybe we have
99 uh women and one man apply to
Cs and in we it's the opposite one woman
and
men
okay and
maybe
uh in CS we're a bunch of snobs right we
we hate everybody we take one
applicant okay so maybe we take you know
one woman
is
accepted everybody else is rejected
okay uh and dou on the other hand has no
standards at all they'll just take
anybody with a pulse uh but
unfortunately one of these men is dead
so uh you know they take one woman and
men
okay so now if you look at the
individual Department's admissions rates
right
uh CS has accepted a woman right so
their their admissions rate for women is
you know nonzero they haven't accepted
any men so they've got a zero admissions
rate for
men so it's higher for
women right and in E they've accepted
all of the women but not all of the men
so again it's higher for women but if
you look at what's happened overall
right we've got two women being accepted
and 98 men
right so you can kind of argue that you
know rather than being a problem with
the
university uh or or the Departments it's
kind of more of a systemic problem like
uh you know maybe they're you know
encouraging men and women to apply to uh
different departments at different rates
and uh you know it's all a bit messy and
uh you know also this is 50 years ago so
you know they only really considered men
and women women didn't really you know
consider anybody who you know identified
as anything else but you know we're not
saying anything about that this is just
kind of uh to illustrate the math so
hopefully it's not terribly
offensive but yeah uh even though for
each department the the women are doing
better than men the men are doing much
better overall okay so that's what we
call simp Simpsons
Paradox does anybody have any question
questions about
that
okay so last
example has anybody seen the dragon
prins couple of hands okay well so last
example uh suppose a cake has gone
missing from the bakery and and uh you
know barus the baker has has a prime
suspect right he thinks that Prince ezin
stole the
cake
uh and you know he wants to present
evidence to the
king he would like to tell the king that
you know this this uh this deviant is
always stealing jelly Tarts from my
bakery you know that makes it much more
likely that he stole the cake right like
jelly tart thieves are you know 10 times
as likely as randos to to steal cakes
okay it seems Seems fairly reasonable
right does does anybody think that this
is a good reason to uh admit the jelly
tart thevery into uh into
evidence who thinks that it's not a
compelling
reason well who has no
idea morans okay so uh maybe Prince
cen's counter claim
is well if you look at you know all
jelly tart thieves you know only one in
say 2500 of them actually go on to Steel
cakes so like you know even though the
probability of you know being a cake
thief has you know increased
dramatically from from the the Baseline
in terms of like a multiplicative Factor
it can't actually have increased very
much because you know it went from 1
125,000 to 1
12500 right so the uh the probative
value here is you know essentially zero
right you're you're trying to prove
guilt Beyond A Reasonable Doubt
right and so a 1 in 2500 chance increase
is kind of negligible but on the other
hand you know if you admit this into
evidence the king is going to be biased
against ezren right he's going to be
like oh this kid's a thief this is
terrible we got to punish him right
regardless of whether he stole the
cake so uh so who's right is is the
baker right or is the uh is the suspect
right who thinks Baker is
right who think suspect is
right who thinks
[Laughter]
neither yeah I've got a few HS
okay so
um well both parties here are trying to
reason
about uh a conditional
probability okay what is that
conditional
probability
anybody well maybe we should start by
writing out some
events
so let's let J be the event
suspect
[Music]
steals jelly tarts
uh C can be the event suspect steals
cake and X can be the event cake was
stolen
okay so both the Baker and the suspect
we making claims about conditional
probabilities what specific conditional
probability in terms of these events
were they making claims
about
yeah
sorry uh repeat the assertions oh the
assumptions uh so the assumptions were
right that a cake has gone missing from
the bakery the baker has a prime suspect
okay and the the Baker wants to admit
into evidence that this suspect is
always stealing jelly Tarts okay and the
reasoning is that uh you know jelly tart
thieves are much more likely to steal
cakes than you know random other
people okay and the suspect counters by
saying well sure but like only one in
2500 jelly tart thieves is actually a
cake thief right so you know the actual
increase is less than 1 in
okay so what are the probabilities that
they're reasoning about what are the
conditional
probabilities yeah
yeah well you're both right sorry it's
um geometry they're both trying to
reason about probability of C given J
right you know so we're conditioning on
the suspect having stolen jelly Tarts
and they're both trying to make claims
about you know what is the probability
of C conditioned on
that okay
so well the baker is arguing that
probability of C given J divided by
probability of C given not
J is
high
right so you know because this is you
know about 10 J is very relevant to the
case so it should be
admitted okay uh the suspect is saying
that
probability of C given
J is low
right so J cannot actually uh
dramatically increase the
probability right the increase is going
to be less than this
probability yeah
yeah so that's a good point um so the
the point was that we're we're talking
about you know one individual suspect
one individual cake one individual case
right so kind of as we were saying
before when we first uh started looking
at rule like you know either it happened
or it didn't right like you could say
that it doesn't make a whole lot of
sense to talk about probabilities right
but you know you're trying to convince
you know the king or a jury or somebody
right um so this is kind of you know
similar to when you present DNA evidence
in court or something like that uh like
the fact that there's a match means that
there's you know overwhelming
probability that the uh the suspect was
at the crime scene or something like
that right so like you you do kind of
still talk about
probabilities uh but you could think of
it as like you know how confident are
you in the inference that uh that the
suspect did something does that make
sense
okay
so so if you were the judge in this case
determining what should be presented to
the
king what would your verdict
be do do we allow jelly tart thievery
into evidence or
no pardon draw a tree diagram draw a
tree diagram uh well that's not actually
necessary anymore we've already figured
out what the uh probabilities are the uh
question is um you know is the probative
value good enough to justify you know
putting it into evidence or is the
probative value small enough that the uh
bias is going to be more more of a
factor
yeah oh
yeah so it it it will not you know
generally capture the full story and
this is why you know lawyers in a
courtroom are you know trying to find
all kinds of evidence to uh to bolster
their cases so yeah like something like
that might be something that the uh the
defense would want to uh would want to
present um or the prosecution might be
like oh but even though it's an MIT
student like it's an it eecs student who
do steel cakes all the time
so I'm getting some uh some nods That's
mildly
[Laughter]
concerning so uh you know like yeah it's
going to be very difficult to capture
the entire picture um for right now
we're just trying to limit the scope to
like these are these are the things that
are known right we we know that a cake
is stolen we know that this suspect
steals jelly Tarts uh but that's it like
we we want to try and figure out you
know what the the probative value of
this evidence is uh just based on
those does that make
sense so who thinks who thinks the jelly
tart should be
admitted who thinks
no okay I'm I'm I'm getting more hands
this time less extensions okay does
anybody want to say
why yeah
mhm yeah so the the observation rate was
uh you know the probability of C given
not J is also very low right and in fact
it is much lower than than C given J um
so that's kind of where this this uh the
the ratio there probability of C given J
over C given not J is coming from right
like uh probability of C given J is 1
and 2500 probability of C given not J is
1 and
25,000 right so that's where you're
getting this factor of
10 so you you agree with the uh the
defense that this should not be ad
admitted into evidence okay does anybody
have any Contra
claims
yeah
yeah yeah so that's a good point we've
uh we've kind of forgotten about
something
right a cake was stolen right we don't
care that the probability of cakes being
stolen is low it it
happened right
so you know we we we don't really care
about these probabilities at all what is
the actual probability we care
about what we really want is is
probability of C given
what
yeah well not that they stole a cake but
that a cake was stolen yeah so C given j
and
x okay so that's what we really care
about right uh that the fact that the
cake is stolen is really important right
like if
uh no if you don't know whether the cake
is stolen right why are you even having
a
trial and as it turns out this
probability is something like
80% jelly tart thieves founded bakeries
with missing cakes usually they're the
guilty
party um
so yeah I've kind of made this a little
bit more palatable but uh this is uh you
know based on an actual courtroom case
um like this this is the kind of thing
that that people uh you know like people
try and use and you know end up misusing
probabilities and conditional
probabilities all the time this was
actually from a very high-profile case
the OJ Simpson case um where both the
defense and the prosecution attorneys
like you know they're supposed to be
experts uh but you know they were both
making bogus claims about uh about
conditional
probabilities uh you know it's it's very
easy to make these kinds of mistakes so
you know fall back on fundamentals uh
when you're an adult fall back on the
fundamentals even if you're not it's
probably a good idea anyway okay uh feel
free to come up if you have any
questions and uh otherwise we will see
you next week