okay so now you know about the clinical
samples and how the data derived from
those is structured so now let's get
into the really exciting part which is
what you're going to be working on what
are the three crunches you're going to
be kind of tackling here so let's start
with the first crunch so here we're
going to be asking you to predict gene
expression from tissue pathology images
so your training data is going to be
paired data where we give you the h&
image and the spatial transcript omix
data and we're going to provide you 460
genes that were measured in the spatial
transcriptomic data and then in the test
we're going to hold out patches of uh
tissue that are outlined here in a gray
box and in this patch we're going to
give you the h& image but we're going to
hide from you the spatial transcript
omix data and we're going to ask you to
take that h& image and predict this uh
transcript omic data for the cells that
are in that tissue patch so in this
cartoon here we have a through F and
we're going to ask you to predict the
expression of Gene 1 2 3 all the way to
Gene 460 and then we're going to see how
well you do because we actually know the
underlying ground truth because we've
carried out the spatial transcriptomics
experiment for this entire tissue so
again starting with the h& image can you
predict spatial transcriptomics data for
all the cells in this heldout tissue
patch so that's the first
crunch the second crunch we make things
more difficult for you and that we are
going to ask you to predict the gene
expression for genes that were never
measured by the spatial transcriptomics
experiment so we've chosen 20 genes that
were not measured by spatial
transcriptomics and we are going to ask
you to predict their expression so the
structure of this is pretty similar to
Crunch one and then we're going to
provide you with pair data and we're
providing you with the h& image and the
spatial transcriptomics data for 460
genes and we are going to hold out
tissue patches and from the h& image
we're going to ask you to predict the
held out spatial transcriptomics data
but in addition 20 genes they were never
measured by spatial
transcriptomics so you're not going to
just be predicting genes 1 through 460
but also genes 461 462 all the way to
480 and now you're asking well how would
I know anything about those 20 genes
this is where all our background about
single cell transcriptomics comes in we
are going to provide you with single
cell transcriptomic data from ulcerative
colitis patients and that data has all
20,000 genes measured so it has the 460
genes we provide you in spatial
transcriptomics it has the 20 genes that
we would like you to predict and it has
all other
19520 genes uh provided so can you use
the single cell transcriptomic data to
tell to tell us what are the uh gene
expression levels uh for those 20 gen
that we're really interested in so
that's crunch 2 it's really an out of
distribution problem because we're never
providing you spatial transcriptomics
data for those 20
genes okay so that's crunches one and
two and the final crunch is focused on
detecting cancer earlier so the focus is
on this really special uh aler of
colitis tissue section where there's
both a non-cancerous region and the
colon mucosa and this displasia region
and remember displasia is this sort of
abnormal growth of epithelial cells
that's precancerous and what we would
like is to find genes that differentiate
or that Mark the displasia region from
the non-cancerous region so what are
genes that are more highly expressed in
this displasia region compared to the
non-cancerous region and these are genes
that can maybe tell us what's going on
in these early cancer events so there
are many ways to go about doing this but
if you've done crunches one and two you
will have built models that can take the
AG
image and predict gene expression and so
one very reasonable way to proceed is to
take the h& image here and predict the
gene expression in the different regions
in the displasia region and the
non-cancerous region and so we can make
those gene expression predictions in the
non-cancerous regions here for cells
here and in the displasia region for
cells here and get all these predicted
gene expression vectors and one thing
I'll point out is that you actually have
zenium spatial transcriptomics data for
the non-cancerous region but we never
provide you any zenium spatial
transcriptomics data for the displasia
region so for the left half of this
tissue image you're really predicting
the genes beyond the 460 that have been
measured already by spatial
transcriptomics but on the right half
you're really predicting all 20,000
genes you do not have any spatial
transcriptomics data directly from that
uh piece of the tissue and again how do
you predict you know genes that you were
never you know given uh any information
about we are going to provide you with
single cell transcriptomic single cell
RNA sequencing data for uh displasia
regions so this is the data set that we
had introduced earlier and it's single
cell transcriptomics and it's going to
tell you what do epithelial cells with
dysplasia look like in terms of their
gene expression so you can use that
single cell transcriptomics data to help
with your predictions of what's going on
with the displasia regions and now once
you've kind of made these predictions of
you know gene expression in the
non-cancerous region and gene expression
in displasia regions it's a relatively
simple task to just compare the two and
say what genes are you know marking this
population of cells that in the
displasia region versus genes that are
marking the non-cancerous region so can
you look at these and say what are the
genes that distinguish these two regions
once you've made these predictions and
so this is a pretty ambitious crunch
it's pretty exciting and cool um and the
like one really really exciting part of
this too is that we're actually going to
experimentally test your predictions so
when you predict a gene that marks
dysplasia we're actually going to go in
and use that to design a new panel of
460 or 480 genes and we're going to use
that panel to measure a new piece of
colon tissue that has dysplasia and
we're going to see if the genes that you
predicted as marking displasia are
really being expressed in the dysplasia
region compared to the non-cancerous
region and so this is really an ultimate
test we're taking your predictions and
applying them to a piece of tissue that
we haven't measured before so this is a
really exciting opportunity you know
most machine learning competitions uh
there's not really an experiment
associated with there's not really you
know something new that you're really
doing and here we actually have a chance
to really go into patient specimens and
see if we can really get better at
predicting uh cancer in these tissue
sections okay great so now we've gone
through all three lectures in this crash
course thanks for listening along if you
need more information you can go to our
website we're really excited to see what
you come up with as you tackle these
crunches and to interact with you uh
along the way so good luck and have fun
[Music]