hello and welcome to another footnote
episode of energy reads my name is Kelly
Travers and I am your host I'm excited
to introduce today's guest Kristoff
Reinhardt Kristoff is a professor of
architecture at MIT working in the field
of Sustainable Building design and
environmental modeling he leads mit's
sustainable Design Lab and is the
director of The Building Technology
Program he is also the head of several
spin-off companies with products used in
practice and in education in over 90
countries we recently shared some of his
research in the audio article titled
cutting Urban carbon emissions by
retrofitting buildings while reading
this article I was surprised to learn
that buildings can be responsible for
more than half of a city's carbon
emissions new buildings are now
typically designed in ways to minimize
energy use in carbon emissions but there
are still a lot of older buildings that
need to be cleaned up Kristoff and his
team are working to help this effort
they have launched a publicly accessible
website called .io that provides a
series of simulation tools as well as a
process for using them to help
neighborhoods and cities calculate their
current building energy use and
resulting carbon emissions and then from
there what initiatives they can take to
reach their carbon reduction goals
Kristoff I've been looking forward to
this conversation and learning more
about your work so thank you for joining
thank you for having me one thing I've
been wondering your bio says that you
you are a building scientist what does
this mean exactly that is a good
question and I get get asked that quite
a lot um building science is the the
study of buildings as the name suggest
and it has various subdomains so first
of all how do buildings function and so
that has a lot to do with the physics
like the heat flow going in and out of
the buildings the buildings being
physical manifestations in the world so
how do we actually keep the temperature
comfortable in place
now there are of course other components
to building science like how do people
operate buildings how do they accept
their thermost how do they decide uh to
um turn when do they decide to open
their windows turn on the lights so that
moves then from physics into the areas
of Psy psychology and sociology who is
living in this building what can they
afford then there's of course also the
big question how are buildings designed
so what's the process of putting them
together and that puts us to
architecture and then even as buildings
are maintained uh facility management
real estate and so for so generally
building science is a pretty wide field
uh most building scientists used to be
engineers and physicists so the focus
has really for a long term been on the
physical manifestation of buildings and
understanding how they work but as a a
wonderful new trend of field has uh
become a lot more diverse in terms of
what people are in the field as as well
as their interest and the reason for
this is really uh two drivers one you
already alluded to the recognition that
in the age of climate change buildings
are globally responsible for uh 40% of
carbon emissions so this is obviously a
huge opportunity and problem that that
we have to deal with and then the other
component is that um over the last 50 60
years uh we've all started to spend more
and more and more time in buildings
where I think the average people still
think is 90% but during Co many of us
probably spend more than 90% of our time
in a building so the conditions that we
are generating building and the impacts
on our well-being are enormous so hence
this uh ever increasing interest in the
field so it's funny that you mentioned
physics a couple of times because I
understand that was your original
background so what sparked your shift to
architecture yeah physics uh the reason
that I laid out uh that's my initial
passion and still my passion and it's
useful to have that in building science
but uh as I already alluded to there are
so many other aspects important for
Building Technology and I always want to
be and aspire to be at the table where
decisions are being made and when you
look at the face of buildings that's of
course architecture and the people that
work with the general public to make and
maintain and renew buildings so that
prompted me towards this ship well
speaking of decisions and you know to
talk more about the article that we had
read recently on the podcast um how
important do you think it is for cities
to really encourage these building
retrofits I mean
worldwide uh we know that by 2050 our
expectation is that the global build
area is going to double which is
actually quite staming if you think how
many thousands of years we have spent
building the buildings that we currently
have that the projectionist that we
might have twice as many buildings in
under 30 years at the same time that's
wild that it's it's a scary and amazing
fact means it's good to be in the
construction sector because you're not
going to run out of work but uh of
course it also means that we really have
to focus that are already existing we
new buildings generally uh tend to be
more efficient because we have more
stringent building codes in many parts
of the world so we really want to uh f
focus on the main carbon emitters the
existing building stock and in the case
of the us about 2/3 of the buildings
that we currently have well they will be
they will make up twoth thirds of our
building stock in 30 years and about a
third half of our current building stop
we are adding to our buildings so
overall retrofitting buildings are inici
old buildings are inefficient and they
constitute the majority of buildings
that will be around by 20 so do you
think making these retrofits are
actually going to make a difference to
these carbon reduction goals retrofits
are enormously efficient especially the
ARs is really and this is where our tool
is focusing on what are the lowest thing
foods for different types of buildings
to reduce carb and sometimes these are
surprising facts so one of the things
that actually saves us a lot is for
example if you get more efficient
appliances say at a dishwasher or
um washing machine then these systems
use a lot less electricity energy at the
same time they use uh a lot less water
you can half your water consumption and
water nowadays is energy in many parts
of the world so you have this this
double dip instantly and um and of
course it pays for itself
relativ uh so yeah doing retrofit and
buildings can be enormously efficient
you can on average with offthe shelf
technology reduce the carbon emission of
a city's building stock by 60 70 80% wow
so do you feel like there's kind of one
sure place where a city can start when
considering what retrofits to prioritize
or is this kind of really City dependent
that is a good question I would say have
several answers when we think of how we
are approaching cities right now we are
basically we have developed this app
that takes cities by their hand and
allows them to explore various
upgrades that they can take for their
buildings let's say we are focusing on
all the old single family homes we're
doing some insulation we make the
buildings a little tighter where does
this get you to and uh very often well
nobody has a real sense from that before
and how this is going to translate at
the city level we know that certain
things in certain climates work very
well
but I think one of the advantages of us
working in workshops with City and their
sustainability Champion to go through
these processes is they own the results
more it's one thing if I come and I tell
you have to do this this this and this
and it proba g acrost an enormous amount
of money and they might not be that
interested in that technology for
various reasons they might not even
believe that this is the right thing
sometimes this is counterintuitive so I
think going through this really as a g
gamification type for this process of
personal um Discovery can be very useful
and ultimately I think it also helps to
develop a very good carbon emission
reduction plan so General cities city
mayor City governments mean any
government is very good at coming up
with outrageous goals anybody heard okay
London or New York or Boston want to be
NSO or near Neto in 25 50 then the
chances if you are the municipality
anywhere you're going to say I want to
be the same thing so we're going to tell
anybody that's all go without really
having a clear uh mind how are you
actually going to get there and I think
this is uh leads to the situation that
you have right now where the
administration in a lot of cities don't
really even know how what to communicate
on what what to do whereas with these uh
reduction PL it's becomes very concrete
we can basically tell every citizen if
you do this this and this to your
building if we are all doing this then
we reach our goal and in a way that
liberates the policy maker because
ultimately it's not them but it's the
the owners of the building that do this
work so I think these um uh tools are
very useful for uh building consensus
around a cent goal well so you mentioned
um a moment ago that you created an App
for this um that's u.io okay so I know
um part of that analysis that you do on
these different retrofit policies you're
using something called an urban building
energy model which is ubm can you tell
us how this model works exactly so maybe
it's worthwh going a step back if you
are in the business of designing an
energy efficient building then for the
long term we've been relying on
something that's called a b a building
energy mod which is basically a
physics-based model that can be linked
to an architectural model of the
building which basically calculates
based on physics engineering based
equations and on a local climate file
the energy use of this particular
building and then for a long term what
we've done then is that there has been a
specialty consultant working key
ambitious project with the architect to
run these models and say we are
designing the building in this way it's
going to be very efficient now the
models typically take quite some effort
because it's one building it's one
architect I mean the costs are pretty
high so we couldn't just repeat that
process with every building in Boston
because it would be too expensive so
this is why we started 10 years ago to
develop this Urban building energy
modeling which is basically a
combination of big data so G data
lighter data anything that we have
available in our time which we can scra
and get for all buildings in the city s
and what the buildings used for how old
it is so and that we are combining bya
in the cloud with um with our physics
based models we of course have to take
certain shortcut simplification but we
figured out ways especially for these
early stage you know policy decision
tools to create a good enough digital
representation some people might call
this a digital Twi of the city to be
able to say okay we can reproduce what
goes on in the city right now and once
we have that and it's based on the
underlying physics we can do any upgrade
you're interested anything you would
want to come up we could basically say
what would happen if we applied that to
the city and this is how these we models
function now maybe one thing that is
interesting to just show the trajectory
when we first came out of this in 2016
we built the first PR model of a large
anywhere that was in Boston and that was
of course worked with the Boston R
Development Authority that was a really
expensive project it was great that we
did it we explored what could be done at
the same time similar activities
happened in other major cities around
the world but this is not something that
a small
place would do would would be able to
afford even though of course most people
live in smaller places that don't have
the front so this new web app
particularly focuses on the idea rather
than having like an expert expert user
who has to be a consultant and an energy
modeler and a big data person so
something that is barely affordable or
trainable we kind of broken this up into
little little pieces we need a
sustainability Champion somebody that
cares which just about any town in
municipality PA we need a GIS manager
and that nearly everybody as especially
in the US because our property taxes are
linked to the digital GS model so this
is usually somebody that's the financial
bloodline of most cities so this person
exists as well and then energy modelers
are pretty common so we bely in this
case go through this eight-step process
where we bring the three parties
together and we can dramatically reduce
the cost that's the the idea behind so
this is kind of this question is a
little off the rails but um I'm really
curious cuz I was reading the story out
loud and so the model and your website
are spelled Ube M why is it pronounced
ubam instead of ubam because ubam just
seems like the obvious
choice I love it well as you might have
GED from my accent I'm German and I made
up that term together with Carlos ceso
who is Spanish maybe B it was natural to
say UB and we called it UB think it's
like an ubot I don't even though know
the that op me that so blame it on my
accent that we call and I guess that uh
people never questioned how we called it
maybe some people in the world say you
them and uh there we go I don't know
that's a great I love it yeah one of
those things where I never would have
thought of it except I'm was you know
wanted to get it right for the podcast
and when I was watching videos to try to
see you guys talking about it and how
you're pronouncing it I was like wait
what I have to like double check on this
so anyway I had to
ask all the Americans at the lab nobody
have a question that maybe you know my
they probably all have somewhat German
exence after the time that leave MIT
with me well thank you for being good
sport on my question so to test the
website that your team created you held
a 3-day workshop with policy makers from
eight different cities around the world
what surprised you the most about the
results from this Workshop there were a
few surprises and uh what was really
nice from the GetGo how enthusiastic
these cities were to participate when
you look at the list of cities it's in a
way quite remarkable we had
hirro Singapore Dublin he in Germany
Montreal like Flor nocus in Brazil um
some small place is in middleb in
Vermont and part of this was by Design
we just contacted people that we
somewhat knew in different parts of the
world and we wanted a variety of planets
and we wanted a variety of sizes because
we wanted to demonstrate that this works
everywhere but these are not like
long-standing
collaborative so I mean I was stunned
actually we uh contacted a whole bunch
and nearly everybody says yes so that
was the nice surprise before we started
because we felt this is really we hadit
a Nerf there which was very good right
so that that is something that we know
City want cities want to do it yeah I
think another component that was uh nice
for us to see is these three uh roles
that I talked about the sustainability
Champion the G manager and the energy
modeler we had kind of made this RS up
in a paper before when we laid out the
concept and suddenly remember this
people for example some uh group in uh
Sandi Springs in Atlanta who actually
had these titles and I had never met
anybody with this title so again it was
maybe a a happy coincidence but it was
again it really showed us that this mold
that we created fit actually to where
cities are going and we had tried a
couple of times to find the right angle
for this technology so that was that was
really postive another thing when when I
go three days later after the workshop
was done I would say one of the key
things that only after the fact done to
us that we had somehow forgotten to talk
about domestic hot water why is that
important uh so domestic hot water is
the hot water that you use in your
buildings when you take shower and the
application where you need hot water and
we know that uses a lot of energy and
actually if you go back to the 80s a lot
of our effort has really been focused
about the solar water systems and so
forth but right now we are so focused on
energy star appliances and that's all
good and on photo voltic and he comes
for eating that we found that once you
start modeling the cities and all these
things were done nobody had talked about
water so we have this significant
remainder that including us I would BL
that well on us nobody had ever talked
about anymore and so that was maybe one
of this this little things that where
people knew for a long time it's
important but we just are all choosing
to ignore it yeah I think um I started
thinking about hot water this past
winter when I was thinking my home is um
on natural gas and so thinking about the
fact that you know how much hot water
I'm using in my shower or to wash dishes
is actually making such an impact so a
low shower at half the water that you
use during your shower I'm not sure if
you have one 15 bucks or so it's quite
amazing what it does and one of these
things like solid state lighting which
most people not have we should all at
the stand our low hanging technolog
absolutely that's a great one I'm
definitely putting that one in my back
pocket so you said that there are cities
that were from all over the place how
big of an impact did these different
locations and their climate have on the
results climate is of course heat well
first of all if you're in a very extreme
hot or cold climate then the technology
is completely different that people are
using I mean if you're in Singapore it's
Cooling and dehumidifying Air to be
comfortable if you're in Montreal it's
heating the air and in between there
there's a mixer of good one Technologies
so climate is very important now I think
what we sometimes look to be
self-evident is that that culture and
local interests are really important
well and so culture has several levs it
has just hold people traditionally put
together a building and in what building
techology do you live when you live in
Middlebury Vermont in Montreal the CH
are maybe you live in a single family or
home or you live in a triple DEA then
you live in Cairo or singapo you're more
likely to live in like a mid to
highrise and these buildings be
very differently and then another key
cultural uh component is how people want
to live so in a way there is especially
I noticed and I share that in uh in
Europe and here in the US in the
Northeast uh people like to live in Old
buildings that are renovated so usually
when you say I live in this building and
people near brag about if their building
is over 100 years old and and then kind
of the Assumption is that it's we uh I
think in many parts of the world that is
not desirable people want to live in a
new home and of course when we want to
be in the business of selling retrofit
that's a lot easier year than if you
would think I don't want to live in a
retrofitted building I don't want to
live in any Lo building let Al Lo
something that's like a secondhand show
repared right so I think those
components is really something that I
just me starting to understand that and
that of course has nothing to do with
what we've been traditionally building
on this is really more like really
fundamentally rethinking how do we how
do we acknowledge these cultural desires
and operate with them and so I know part
of the results you found were that these
initiatives that these cities had
already decided on it kind of revealed
that they actually weren't going to get
them to you know that reduction goal
that they had in mind and that you kind
of later looked further at what
decarbonizing the city's electric grid
would do what sort of impact does that
decarbonization make so there's a lot of
Focus right now on using more
electricity than fossil fuels so the
idea is when you use electricity with a
heat pump to heat your building then one
day we going to have all electricity
being generated from renewable energies
and then that makes sense because once
we have wind farms and solar in
sufficient quantity then our grid would
in principle one day be so clean that us
having switched everything towards
electricity works very well and so now
depending on where you are uh different
countries have different plans more or
less concrete how they're going to reach
this in the United States there's
actually a pretty concrete cancer plan
and you have pretty good predictions of
where how much carbon is in a kilowatt
hour of electricity right now and how
this is going to change and usually go
down over time so that helps you to
decide is it really a good idea to put
in a heat pump and depending on where
you are in some cases today you might
temporarily use more carbon or generate
more carbon by switching to a heat pump
if you happen to be in a state that
burns a lot of coal to create the
electricity but the longterm goal in all
cases is that this is going to disappear
so what we did for these cities we uh
looked at these plans and basically
wanted to see how these two uh effects
work in tendons so on the one hand
you're reducing carbon emissions uh from
the grid that's something where the city
doesn't have to do anything this just
happens to them not through them and
then on the other hand when you update
your buildings then hopefully you pick
electrically based uh technology so that
you fully benefit from this de one thing
I thought was interesting in the article
was that you noted that one of the
Cities you worked with owned both the
utility and the natural gas that it
burned and that this actually affected
their retrofit choices can you speak a
bit about that yeah absolutely so a lot
of cities I would say primarily in
Europe but in different parts of the
world own their local ities and the way
that often works is they might have a
power plant but usually they're
purchasing electricity or natural gas in
bulk but they own the distribution
system and generally that's something
very good because uh utility makes money
by definition there's a monopoly there
and if people use electricity they make
money and a lot of these cities then use
this Revenue to for example find public
transportation but on the other hand of
course there are situations where when
you do this you invested in certain
Technologies in a way one of the
technologies that are harder to deal
with is if you have a district heating
system that is fossil fuel powered so
that would mean you have basically a
fossil fuel a huge natural gas boiler
where you burn natural gas to create
Heating and you distribute that to a ton
of buildings that has its limitations in
the long run due to what we said earlier
that if you want to Electrify your
heating you're stuck to a natural gas
boiler so there was less appetite to say
hey how about we are exploring getting
heat pumps for everybody because that
would undermine the financial model of
the of the utility now interestingly
that actually changed uh pretty
dramatically in the last year this was a
central European um City because uh of
the unfor warn Ukraine there not enough
natural gas anymore so now it's uh it's
an interesting we come out of
availability necessity yeah and so I I
know like a key limitation even Beyond
you know the city level is that for many
different Clean Energy Technologies and
policies is just getting that buy in
from consumers can you speak a bit about
how you took this into account for your
research and for ubam doio yeah the B is
absolutely key and in our first
iteration of the tool and this is what
we've been talking about we focused on
the kind of technical potential if you
do certain things how much can you
reduce carbon but of course you have to
very very quickly people are not
interested in kilowatt hours people
might be interested in carbon people are
interested in money so without uh
putting some D tax and payback uh
numbers to this analysis that's
very the analysis won't get you very
so we have been working on models just
to estimate costs involved and this is a
complicated moment uh right now to
evaluate because we are trying to ramp
up this retrofitting activity so fast
that our labor force is lacking behind
we just don't have enough people that
put in these Technologies right now in
many parts of the US and I would say in
the world and that of course lead to
Adit to shortterm distortions because
the few people that are able to do that
are overwork and that drives up highs uh
but I think that we can understand how
this develops in the long run so then
the final component is where we've been
working on through the MIT energy
initiative with some uh Utility Partners
here that we started to work on
willingness to pay model so that's where
we ask people uh how are you willing to
pay $500 $1,000 5,000 25
$50,000 to upgrade your home and how
much would you expect to save each month
what is the uh the payback time and we
asked to several thousand people
including knowing how much they care for
the environment
self-reported like General income level
ownership of the building and so forth
so that has actually greatly helped us
to have now this we call it the Deon no
Deon model we we at least know when
people say oh it's too expensive for me
like you probably have two-thirds of
people when you tell them uh would you
spend $50,000 to upgrade your building
they're just going to say no that number
is just I'm not interested so that helps
us kind of lay out this this complex uh
um relationship between how much do I do
people care how much money do they make
what do they expect so that we can start
fine-tuning incentives better right now
is um to kind of get this retrofitting
Market rolling in the US there are a lot
of pretty blanket pretty high
incentives and in a way this is similar
to what we've done through photo
voltaics they were really heavily
subsidized at the beginning to get a lot
of people to get Buy in and then we're
slowly tuning down the support because
we know that technology gets more
efficient that works to a degree now the
question is how much how fast can we get
lower
there's of course also an unintended
consequence that when you do that you
tend to um get higher income household
to do this first if everybody gets the
same money the person who has more money
is more likely to say yes because for
them it's a smaller commitment to
certain things so the questions of
equity and how we have to break this
down this is really where our activities
are currently at to just help cities to
understand these relationships better
well so and I know MIT right now is
actually currently retof fitting the
Metropolitan storage Warehouse which for
those familiar with the MIT campus is
the huge Warehouse on the corner of
massav and Vasser Street um it's an
iconic Cambridge building it opened in
1895 as a storage facility it's now
being renovated to house MIT School of
Architecture and planning have you
played any role in this project or your
model a role in the sense that of course
as MIT faculty we all try to be very
involved in and to my old that here with
several colleagues we've been involved
in the architectural process and trying
to give our advice with the
Uber software or Uber no I'm going to
say U uh
the the uh the UB software is really for
larger scale so we would use what I
mentioned earlier the bem the building
energy modeling software to look at that
building specifically and a lot of this
uh work has happened using these tools
for this building I would say well
larger scale work really came in is
thinking about the development of the
electric Rd so right now MIT is very
similar to a lot of uh emphasis in the
Northeast is that we are using natural
gas with um with a complicated campus
utility plant to
create uh heating chilled water and our
own
electricity and that has been one of the
drivers for decarbonizing the Grits
generally in nor New England and it is
also economically a a good model which
is why a lot of campuses are are doing
that now we are at this interesting fine
moment where fortunately we are pushing
so much renewable energy that we are
soon reaching the point at which
actually the electric grd the grd the
public GD in Massachusetts might be
cleaner than our own Electric
and for us at a school of architecture
that was really really important we
didn't want to move in a building that
is basically dependent on a source that
might not per se have an immediate
future so there was a lot of lobbying on
our behalf to say well we would really
like to have an all El electric ready
campus buil and that is not necessarily
the most economic decision but it's a
future and uh it has was actually a
fabulous experience that um you know our
facilities onland campus uh the
administration everybody was really
receptive to the arguments that we made
and in a way uh committed to spending
more so what we are doing right now is
that might be a little complicated it's
for a physicist a really beautiful thing
so what we are doing we we are
basically on our campus we have two
Loops we have one loop with hot water
and one with chilled water and every
building just comes in and takes
whatever they they need right and so
what we are doing is we're using what is
called a water source heat bump in that
building so we are taking the cold water
that all buildings share and we make it
colder and that colder that heat we are
using to heat our building so the
Metropolitan Warehouse will be heated by
making the chilled water chilia coder on
campus which which is cool as a idea
it's a very efficient idea it also kind
of ties us on as a campus more together
physically speaking so there are a lot
of ideas of basically having these Grand
Loops that start connecting buildings
and the buildings take and give from it
heat in order to benefit from this so
this is something that uh that we've
been fortunate all as a team to uh get
implemented right now in the building
we're really excited about that and it
has direct carbon savings for the
buildings I think it was an extra 15% of
the over T were safe to that and it's
also something that I would think that
was um motivated through this work I'm
thinking our cities the campus is like a
mini City so that help so to close I
want to ask a fun question um if you
could become an expert in anything
instantly download all the skills and
knowledge instantly into your head even
if it's not related to what you're doing
now what would it be if I if I'm selfish
I think the most exciting Fe field if I
wanted to just learn something from
completely new right now it probably
would be biochemistry and Gene
sequencing I think the co pandemic
taught us just how incredibly our
advances have been in the field given
that the technology for the vaccine was
we in principle available that we could
do this so I think it's an incredibly
exciting field and my daughter enters
into this field where now and this is
one of the topics where I always feel
completely
ignorant and so I think it's an exciting
new feeli that I would probably where I
see a lot of innovation coming up next
uh otherwise when I look at something
that is kind of related to what I'm
doing maybe I would want to become like
an influencer YouTuber because I think
if you want to
really get to a lot of people and get
them exciting about retrofitting that we
me need the Mar Roba type skills I think
to make building science is already a
little out of the basement of nobody
caring about building science but we
still have to bring it more make it a
part of the public
imagination I love that answer Kristoff
thank you so much for speaking with me
today thank you that was a lot of fun
great thank you and to our listeners
thank you for joining I am Kelly Travers
and this is energy reads