good afternoon everyone so it's already
already 405 um and we successfully kick
off kick out the previous class um so I
think we should get started because we
have amazing talk ahead of us uh I will
keep my introduction short um Professor
Philip holer it's a program leader at
MRC laboratory of molecular biology in C
UK Phil graduated with distinction from
space uh Swiss Federal Institute of
Technology uh in other name cth at
Switzerland and then he came to UK did
his PhD with Noel lawat Prof uh do sorry
sir gray winter uh during which he
started uh really amazing work with
nuclear acids and synthetic biology and
uh he did a very short pass out there
then start his tenue check at MRC lmb um
and got his tenue in 2005 so uh his lab
aims to better understand the
foundational principles and chemical
logic that shape our genetic system
mostly DNA and RNA um I don't know like
maybe once a once in a while you may
wonder why we have DN RNA as our genetic
M materials why it has to be reel so why
it has to be four bases if not more or
less so uh to us that questions um
Philip slab is really doing amazing work
to try to recapitulate what happened
initially how the first life on Earth uh
emerged and why um this whole
replication system is possible with
simpler chemical structures to begin
with uh without further Ado I just want
to welcome our speaker today again uh to
deliver the talk thanks so much
thank you can you hear me thank you sh
for the introduction and for the yeah
for inviting me here and giving me the
opportunity to tell you a little bit
about our work um so this being the town
of Jack shostak and David Bartell I'm
just going to talk about polymerize
riboses and actually not talking much
about the xnas so really what we start
with is this um central dogma kind of
diagram introduced in the 19 70s to sort
of summarize the idea that information
flow in biological system is mostly
unidirectional from um okay from uh from
DNA into RNA into proteins but then
immediately people recognize there's a
sort of strange dichotomy uh to this
system in that you know we need nucleic
acids to make proteins but then we need
proteins to make nucleic acids so how do
you get a system like that started up
you know how do you boot up life
and and this is over 50 years ago Les
Francis Crick Leslie Orel and coose and
also Alex Rich here at MIT sort of
proposed an idea which was pretty
far-fetched at the time uh which was
that there was a primordial biology
which was much more primitive and where
RNA was doing most of the sort of heavy
lifting both catalysis and and
information and although that's you know
still kind of you know there is no sort
of concrete evidence for such as it
became known an RNA World um ever
existing there's a lot of compelling
circumstantial evidence maybe the
Smoking Gun is really the structure of
the ribosome sort of central Hub of
protein synthesis in all cells which is
mostly RNA including the peptidal
transfer center and really a
Cornerstone of this idea of an RNA world
is is this that it must have started
with maybe an RNA that gained the
capacity to co make copies of itself to
self-replicate
and uh so many people such RNA does not
exist in in nature so many groups have
been searching uh you know to build such
an RNA uh replicas in the lab to maybe
study the um the properties of life's
first genetic system by proxy by
studying a molecular doppelganger and we
sort of joined this effort um um you
know you you know starting from this
truly amazing kind of polymerase uh
ribozyme that was discovered this
polymerus ribosy discovered in David
bartel's Lab at the white head and it
still sometimes blows my mind that such
a uh simple molecule which is this is
about an RNA it's about bit over 200
nucleotides long can carry out such a
sophisticated uh molecular function
which is to read out the sequence of an
RNA template and synthesiz its its
complementary sequence you can see it
doing its job here so just
um sorry just to to just to introduce
these type of gels you're going to see a
few of them this is a primary extension
gel is a nice semi-quantitative way of
measuring polymerase activity where you
enlabel a primer you let the polymerase
do its job and then you separate the
products on a polyacryamide gel and you
can see each sort of band denotes an
incorporation step so this uh polymerase
RNA polymerase ribosy can do about 14
incorporation steps and then it's SP
um so that's not quite ready for
self-replication but we thought our
first talk should be this ribosy is
about 200 nucleotides long can we
acquire can we engineer this further can
we evolve it to acquire the ability to
synthesize rnas that are at least as
long or ideally longer than itself but
you know before I start with this there
is something that always bothered me
about the RNA world I mean I don't know
how many of you have worked with RNA
it's a pretty fragile molecule if you
expose it to alkaline pH to high
temperatures or to divalent metal ions
in par in particularly um uh transition
metals or God forbid combinations of
that kind of it quickly degrades now
that's all very well in the lab where
you can control conditions in nice clean
Endor tubes but on the surface of the
early Earth with sort of meteorites
raining down hot Boiling Springs come on
RNA is a pretty perverse choice
um as a primordial genetic material now
other people have proposed a pre RNA
world uh that would then be based uh on
a much more resilient genetic polymer
which then transitions to RNA but it's
worth saying that there's zero evidence
for that so we wondered if we could
think of environments where RNA would
make more sense and on the face of it
the answer to that is pretty obvious
because what do you do both in the lab
and at home if you you're dealing with
sort of perishable things that's right
you put them in the freezer but we also
need the uh RNA to be an enzyme and
certainly protein enzymes don't take
kindly to being frozen so this is RNA t7
RNA polymerase you can see it happily
synthesizes RNA at 37° but when you
freeze it it's dead but the polymerized
ribosy is very different you can see not
only is it active um um not only is it
active in the ice but if you just wait a
little bit long enough it pretty much
shows the same activity as at ambient
temperature so it retains it activity
when Frozen and in fact if you kind of
adjust the conditions just a little bit
you know it can synthesize rnas that are
actually quite a bit longer than it can
do at ambient temperature so it is a
little bit like the toris and the hair
it's a bit slower in the ice but it just
keeps going and going and making more
and more
RNA um and reason for that is and this
wasn't discovered by us is that it would
be wrong to to think of um uh ice as a
sort of homogeneous solid medium because
what really happens is when you freeze
an aquous solution that doesn't just
contain water but contains RNA and maybe
magnesium and some nucleotide
triphosphates the water freezes out
first and excludes the solutes into a
liquid uh uh brine phase the so-called
tic phase which surrounds the ice cre
crystals and actually stays liquid at
subzero temperatures and this is
accompanied by a tremendous
concentration and dehydration um effect
which sort of compensates for the low
temperature and accelerates the the
synthesis reactions so this really looks
like a you know a nice environment for
RNA to do its job and in fact all the
reactions you see from here on are done
in ice um in in our lab so as a next
step we try to do evolution in ice and
we selected a new variant of the
polymerase
ribosy and um to to adapt it to the Ice
phas uh a bit better and this one I hope
you can see this here this is a about
206 nucleotide synthesis band so it can
now synthesize rnas that are longer than
itself because it's about 23 this is 206
so we've been we've there we're there it
can synthesize RNA as long than itself
but can it synthesize itself no it can't
so that was really frustrating so why
can it synthesize this rnas that are
longer but it can't make itself and um
to to figure out what's going on we fed
this ribosy simple simple pool of random
RNA sequences and asked asked it to to
copy them and just see which ones can
you copy which ones you
can't and when you analyze these I'm
sorry these sequences the ones it can be
copied they behave like strings they're
unfolded but the ones that it can't copy
the moment you have a little bit of
secondary structure in the RNA this RNA
polymerized ribosy uh can can cannot
read through those uh
structures and and really this um this
brings us to this dichotomy of RNA that
it has to be as what Larry gold called
it has to be both a string and a thing
and it needs to be both be able to fold
up and then on fold again to become a
template and and and really you you'll
encounter this sort of theme throughout
the talk but the fact that it cannot
that this polymerized ribosy cannot copy
structured rnas now leads us to what is
uh an apparent Paradox because the RNA
needs to fold into a three-dimensional
structure to be a polymerase ribosy but
then once folded rnas cannot be
replicated by the polymerase ribosy so
how do you get around this and um one
solution I'm going to tell you a lot
about that we came up with involves that
we rethink the the substrates that the
polymerase uses so so far the polymerase
riboses that I shown you they all use
the mononucleotide triphosphates that
are also used by natural RNA polymerizes
but really it was always a bit
optimistic to think that at the origin
of Life you'd have a nice clean pool of
you know ntps kind of like ready for you
so there would be a mixture of things
maybe dinucleotides trinucleotides
tetranucleotides Etc and the question is
which one of these would be good
substrates so we did a a number of trial
experiments and eventually settled on
trinucleotides uh or specifically
trinucleotide triphosphates as as
substrates with with with good
properties that is they would were
Incorporated well by the polymerase
ribosy but they also maintain the
Fidelity of interaction which you lose
when you actually go to longer r
oligomers and just to make life a little
bit easier instead of saying TR
nucleotide triphosphate each time and
from now I'm going to call these
triplets so um this shows the problem
again so this is a sort of series of RNA
templates this is the primer and you
know they have an increasing tendency to
fold back on itself now with the old uh
the mononucleotide polymerize you can
see it can copy the first one but then
it's pretty much stumped kind of like
with each of the others but if we now
switch to trinucleotide triphosphates
again to Triplet substrates you can see
we can copy through all of them and
what's even
better when you sort of um plot the
curve of uh the amount of RNA you
synthesize as a function of tripet
concentration on the unstructured
template you get a sort of saturation
curve which is what you expect of an
enzyme as you increase uh the substrate
concentration but if we do this on the
structure templates we get a sigmoidal
curve you just get a sort of transition
at about 10 micromolar triplet
concentration uh where suddenly kind of
like synthesis increases kind of to a
much greater extent and our
interpretation of this is that actually
you know that the triplets it's the
triplets that invade the secondary
structure so there's a sort of
ratchetlike progress of synthesis where
the triplets at a certain
concentration uh are become able to
invade the secondary structure leading
to a Cooperative unfolding of the
template which then can be
copied so at this point we became really
interested in you know evolving this as
a triplet polymerase ribosy and this is
our result which we came up with we
didn't ask for it the enzyme became a
heterodimer a mutualistic heterodimer of
an active and an inactive subunit we've
recently managed to solve the um crym
structure of the APO enzyme and you can
see here there's the catalytic subunit
in red and in blue you see the non
catalytic subunit which actually derives
from the catalytic subunit but in just
kind of you know a few mutations kind of
completely rearranges the structure and
sort of provides a scaffold to hold the
catalytic subunit in place as you can
see this this polymerase ribosy the what
we from now I'm going to call the
triplet polymerase ribosy has
substantial triplet and sort of oligomer
uh polymerize
activity um and it can really synthesize
some pretty tricky substrates so this is
the broccoli RN aper which binds this
chromophor become fluorescent it's a
sort of pretty much stay all together a
hairpin structure all the way but now
you know the triple polymerase ribosy
can synthesize them and the broccoli is
active because if you add the chromophor
to the gel you can see this is made with
uh t7 RNA polymerize this is made with a
ribosy you get a sort of an extra
triplet added to the end but they are
nicely fluorescent and active and what's
better you can do both strand so you can
actually replicate kind of both strands
of this uh broccoli aptamer and just to
show you again what sort of structures
look like this is a structure of the
related chili uh fluorescent timer and
you can see this is really a hairpin
structure all the way with a sort of
interrupted G quadruplex in the middle
which binds the chromophor I don't think
you could come up with a much harder uh
uh substrate uh to to to
replicate what's amazing is that the
triplets now also unlock kind of um uh
replication modes which are not
available in nature because all RNA
replication in nature proceeds in the
five Prime to three prime Direction but
because the triplets bind to the
template there's no reason why they
can't go in the reverse provided you
give it a primer which is phosphorilated
at the three prime end and indeed that
works so this is the forward uh reaction
you give it a normal primer you give it
the triplets happily synthes Siz is RNA
now we give it the reverse primer
phosphorilated at the five Prime end and
you can see it does uh the same reaction
and what's better if you give it both
primers it can do both reactions at the
same
time because the triplets bind to the
RNA template they can now act as primers
themselves so you can see in lane two
this is the re primary extension
reaction with a primer and in lane four
where we give it no primer at all just
triplets and you can see you can make
exactly the same product and you can use
that synthesized product and prime it
again just using triplets and again make
both uh strands of the
RNA now initiation from triplets has a
number of consequences and one of them
is that there's now a large
combinatorial number of Pathways by
which the ribosome can make the full
length so this is um this is a a 24mer
RNA
template
okay this is a 24mer RNA template and
these are all the potential
Pathways now if you had the normal five
Prime to three prime synthesis you would
expect a sort of a clockwise Arc to
appear if you had the five the three
prime to five Prime Direction you would
expect an anticlockwise arc and using
Next Generation sequencing we can now
take a snapshot of the reaction and find
out what actually is
happening so each of these dots
represents a product of the reaction and
the sort of size of the dots represents
kind of how much there is and you can
see there is a nice clockwise Arc here
kind of starting from here with the
synthesis but as you can see up here
there's other products so what's
happening there is actually the first
kind of uh after the first kind of d uh
triplet liation the enzyme likes to
connect to the second second kind of
dinucleotide and form a second Arc so
there's two arcs kind of going to the
full length product and you can see what
we conclude from this there's two
independent initiations from two
triplets um and uh independently
extending now let's look at a different
slightly longer at 27 more template now
already just looking at the pattern you
can see this is very different so this
uses a very different
pathway you have this time quite a nice
developed anticlockwise Arc but you can
see you have all these other kind of
arcs here as well and you know just took
a long story short if you try to
reconstruct the pathway you come up with
four at least four independent
initiation events both in the forward
and the reverse Direction so what's
really exciting is the system as we ask
it to replicate RNA can now find its own
way it can initiate where it wants fill
in the gaps and sort of find the low the
PA path of lowest resistance to find uh
to make the the final
product okay now another really
important aspect of um RNA catalyzed RNA
replication is if we want to go to
self-replication this reaction must
preed with a certain Fidelity that which
is defined by the uh famous error
threshold of Manfred igen because if you
do not operate above the error threshold
a the the majority of the sequences you
generate will be basically inactive you
will have destroyed the phenotype and
there can be no inheritance and no
Evolution now one way to um enhance the
Fidelity of RNA
replication and obviously Fidelity is a
problem that is also occurring in
biology and one way to enhance the
Fidelity is to not just rely on the base
pairing but to actually read out the
hydrogen bond donor and accept the power
patterns in the minor Groove and this is
done both by DNA polymerizes and uh in
the decoding center of the
ribosome and in fact my colleague Wy RAR
chrishan sort of speculated on the basis
of the structure of the ribosome
decoding Center that really the
Primitive replicas the RNA replicas that
we're looking for if it was able to read
out minor Groove hydrogen bondona uh
patterns its Fidelity would be much
improved and which would potentially
allow much more accurate uh uh
replication and more complex systems to
evolve so we thought we should really
try to select for Fidelity and how do
you do this so we started by feeding now
the main source of error of these RNA
replication reactions are geow wobble
pairs so we um we presented the the
ribber with two triplets the correct one
and a sort of a terminated triplet with
the wobble pair so the terminated
triplet but cannot be extended so if the
polymerase incorporates it wrongly it
cannot synthesize to the edge of to the
end of the Strand and as you can see
during uh selection initially the Wubble
the wobble triplets actually
Incorporated slightly better but as we
as we keep going eventually it's its
incorporation
disappears and at the end of this
replication experiment if you look at
the Fidelity of the triplet polymerase
so this is for the first the second and
the third position of the triplet you
can see initially the Fidelity overall
wasn't very bad and it was particularly
bad for the for the the third uh base of
the triplet but after Evolution both the
second and the triplet have much
improved although there's still wobble
pairing uh uh in the first base triplet
but the overall Fidelity has now
improved to about
97% now to find out if this really is
based on hydrogen bond pairing um going
to show you some some cool experiments
done bya raguram who is who is um I
think a group leader now here at the
broad and and was in Cambridge briefly
kind of for a summer intership did some
cool experiments by testing essentially
if we could prove kind of that minor uh
that the minor group hydrogen bond donor
acceptors were were um were re read out
by replacing the urine where the car the
the the keto group is like a uh often
used as a hydrogen bond donor except the
replace ing this with two cou which
can't form a hydrogen bond and also
replacing the two prime hydroxy of RNA
with a floro group which again kind of
abolishes hydrogen
bonding and you can then measure the
impact on Fidelity if you have this mod
modification present or not and the
experiments he did sort of clearly
showed that at the third tripet position
um the minor Groove is definitively
engaged because if if you for example
replace urine with two th iDine the
Fidelity uh drops back to the Baseline
uh while at the first position there is
very little
effect now how does this work now
unfortunately the cryoem structure that
we have only um only is of the APO
enzyme so we don't know exactly how the
triplet polymerase ribosy engages uh the
primate template duplex and the incoming
triplet but we can build a model based
on the structure of the class on Lio is
ribosy and if you do that if you fit the
primer template into our structure you
can see you can see in red the active
site and the the the sorry the catalytic
site in green and the a minor kind of
interaction Motif in red and in blue you
can see this P10 Loop which emerges
during the Fidelity selection which is
sort of poised to interact uh with with
the primer template duplex and in more
detail you can see it is sort of
perfectly positioned to to actually
hydrogen bond to the incoming uh Tri
triplet here in red and this is the P10
Loop and this I think what gives us the
High Fidelity in the forward reaction
because in the reverse reaction the P10
Loop is in the wrong place and it's
positioned over the primer and can't
contact the triplet incoming triplet
here in red and this may explain kind of
why the reverse reaction has a much
lower Fidelity uh back to
Baseline Okay so there's another way in
which um in which triplets kind of seem
to influence Fidelity and this is
completely unexpected and is based on
the sort of systems level properties uh
of the triplet pools so the first hint
we got from that is when we looked at
the Fidelity of two triplets so this is
Prett pretty much the worst case
scenario the the ribos sign really
discriminates those very very poorly
that in 30% of the cases the wrong the
wobble pair triplet is actually
Incorporated but um
before I do this just just to to to
notice if we have a pool of 64 triplet
for each triplets there is also its
perfect anti- triplet in the pool now
what we did is if you give if you
provide those those to those two
triplets they're anti-
triplets the Fidelity actually improves
by over three fold now this is totally
unexpected because those triplets have
nothing to bind to in the template the
template just codes for uh ACC
incorporation now if you use the same
template and you give it all 64 triplets
another weird effect pops up because if
you increase the triplet concentration
again normally would expect with
increasing triplet concentration for the
Fidelity to drop but in fact the
Fidelity increases let's look at another
example here the Fidelity phenotype
isn't so bad but again if you provide
the anti-t triplet it gets almost four
times better on the same template you
use the NN pools again the Fidelity
increases so what's going on now if you
look
at basically all the triplets and you
look where the Fidelity effect is the
most pronounced you can see only above
50% GC is where you see a significant
shift and you can um we can look at this
here where you look at the Fidelity
effect at High versus low concentration
of nnn triplets and all the a triplets
behave as you would expect at higher
concentration the Fidelity drops but for
all the GC Rich triplets the Fidelity
increases at higher concentration so
what's going on now we think kind of
because this KD range is exactly in the
sort of range that has previously been
shown to promote dimer formation among
trnas between codon and
anticodons I think our hypothesis is
that these triplet anti- triplet
interactions in the pool of a Tri of
triplets they occur uh between
selectively between the GC triplets and
so what really happens is the pool sort
of normalizes these interaction networks
increase the Fidelity by normalizing the
triplet substrate pool against base
pairing strength all the strongly
pairing GC triplets form diers and
they're the concentration of those free
triplets drops uh as a function of their
base pairing strengths while the more
weakly interacting a triplets don't form
diers and stay their concentration is
increased so overall this is the same
effect as you if you would deplete the
most mispairing triplets selectively
from the
pool okay so here's another uh RNA
replication problem whenever you make R
whenever you replicate RNA the product
is invariably an RNA duplex and RNA
duplexes are insanely stable and these
double stranded dup r are basically in
they cannot be replicated by the RNA
polymerase ribosy they just are not
substrates and I just show you this here
two two strands this is the plus strand
this is the minus strand you can copy
them happily but you give it the duplex
you you preform a duplex of the plus and
the minus strand there is no RNA
synthesis whatsoever and this is uh
known as The Strand separation
problem so clearly we need to unzip the
Strand so let's see how we can do this
now as I told you before RNA doesn't
like to be heated up and particularly
not in the presence of
magnesium um um which we need for
ribosome activity so
how how can we um dissociate those super
stable
duplexes now one idea is uh came up uh
my colleague John Sutherland came up
with this idea to to actually use acid
RNA is is surprisingly stable at acidic
pH
uh and uh the base pairs uh begin to
protonate around ph4 and obviously this
destabilizes the the
interaction unfortunately to really kind
of U
separate um the sort of duplexes we like
to replicate especially in the presence
of magnesium which further stabilizes
them you have to go back down to to
maybe um
pH uh pH like you know 2.5 uh to to
really get good dissociation and you
also have to to elevate the temperature
so uh RNA duplexes can be dissociated
but it's hard and you need to use
conditions um that are not compatible
with ribosy activity so you then need to
neutralize again to do synthesis but
what if you do that you see the duplex
can't be synthesized now we melt the
duplex with acid and neutralize and add
the
ribosy now you can do it now you can
synthesize both strands with somewhat
reduced that uh yield but it can be done
so double stranded RNA can be
dissociated by acid pH and high
temperatures and the dissociated strands
can be replicated so now we have a way
to actually do some sort of ribosy PCR
now we can go through multiple cycles of
replication um and I should say that if
you don't uh uh replicate it the strands
rapidly zip up together again and we can
measure that the half life is about
three minutes in about three minutes all
the RNA has for reformed the duplex and
um and that is
unfortunately too fast for the ribosy to
to to to copy it because the ribosy is
really not a fast
enzyme but again triplets come to the
rescue because if you dissociate the
strands and then add the triplets before
you
neutralize um the um the strands can no
longer anal so the triplets actually
attenuate they connect ically and
thermodynamically stabilize the
dissociated state so to enable
replication and this just shows you sort
of a sketchy Delta G diagram where you
dissociate um the single stranded state
is a sort of high energy state which
wants to go back to a low energy State
um which is the duplex but because the
triplets bind to the dissociated strands
this this a becomes a um a a the
stabilizes a thermodynamic and because
you now have to strip all the triplets
off before you can zip back together it
also slows it down kinetically so this
really stabilizes the single stranded
State and slows down stranded
kneeling and uh this does not work with
the mononucleotide triphosphates so when
we do this with the old RNA polymerase
ribosy and the mononucleotide
triphosphates you can't copy the duplex
even if you have dissociated it with
acid okay so now we've got a scheme that
we need to do we need to dis dissociate
the strands with acid neutralize at the
triplets and the rivy and replicate and
go through these Cycles but there is a
problem for dissociation we need low PH
high temperatures and low concentrations
of everything in particularly RNA for
synthesis we need you know actually
mildly basic pH we need low temperatures
and obviously we need high
concentrations ideally of everything so
these are sort of really opposing
conditions but uh again something I told
you before earlier comes to the rescue
because we can now kind of have this
tremendous concent take advantage of the
tremendous concentration effect of ice
and also to bring the temperature down
so if we now
combine uh hot temperatures and low PH
with freezing sorry with freezing and
high pH we should be able to uh by free
by coupling free cycles and pH Cycles we
should be able to decouple the Strand
separation and the synthesis steps this
is just a little cartoon which shows you
how this should be working you know you
start with a duplex you move it to ph3
heat it up they come apart you add the
triplets you move it to ph9 and you
freeze and add the ribosy and now it
copies it we move back to ph3 they come
apart and so on and so on and you should
be able to get exponential RNA
replication and I would say this C T is
a little bit optimistic because it shows
a doubling in fact um it's not so good
you only probably double in the best
case scenario every five Cycles but you
can now use this kind of if you want
acid free cycle PCR kind of to to to to
to really kind of replicate and amplify
double stranded
rnas now what's more interesting than
this is what happens when you feed the
system not a defined sequence with
primers but actually a random sequence
library and a random sequence template
um uh with um with with with primers
with defined primers
attached um now I think this is really
weak but this is the original length
template and you can see in the first
five Cycles this is sort of synthesized
you can see a little bit of the full
length template but as we keep going
through more and more Cycles um the
system sort of shifts to a different
sequence pop population and you can see
these strong product bands emerging
which are truncated from the full length
and these actually grow exponentially
over many
cycles and these sequences when you
analyze it it's quite a diverse pool but
these sequences have now been selected
by the ribosy for being nice to copy for
what I would call replicability so the
system itself actually syn uh uh selects
for highly replicable RNA sequences they
emerge spontaneously from a random pool
and then act amplify exponentially upon
continued RNA replication and you can
pick out some sequences uh from this of
the different lengths and you can see
they nicely grow over uh five Cycles um
and and and keep
amplifying now I've told you before
about primer free replication now what
happens if you do this without any
primers so in this experiment all we
feed into the system is an 20 seat
sequence uh all 64 triplets the ribosy
and we just let it go as you can see uh
initially it begins it copies the N20
seat but then very rapidly a sort of
ladder kind of of products appears which
grows in intensity as we keep going um
now what is really interesting is we
also do a control where we don't add the
N20 SE sequence seat sequence which
initially you know shows a sort of very
weak p pattern but then the sort of
banding pattern appears and then the
minus the the sequence which the the
reactions which had no template input at
all they actually begin to overtake the
ones which had an RNA template so what
goes on so we analyze these Pools by
Next Generation
sequencing and what you find is that
actually a large number of these
sequences are actually homologous to the
ribosy so this is now in the pool which
had not had template sequence added so
essentially in the absence of a template
uh what the ribosy does it uses itself
as a template so it first kind of
synthesizes uh you know pieces of the
minor Strand and then uh uh these
eventually become used later on as
templates to be to synthesize the plus
strand so these are all sort of small
fragments I would say these are not
contiguous sequences but this is all
sort of small pieces of the ribosy that
are being
replicated uh and uh and
churned um so really the primary free
RNA replication in the absence of an N20
SE yields an expanding population of
ribosy minus and plus strand fragments
which are being continuously
replicated um but the polymerase also
does something else you know you can see
this sort of red a section which
increases as as a replication goes on uh
there was no temp plate uh added to this
reaction so this is not homologous to
the ribosome this clearly must represent
the denovo generation uh of replicating
RNA sequences so the polymerize sort of
dreams of RNA sequences and begins to
sort of doodle and create new sequences
which then get replicated um and we
think this is probably through the
addition of these uh GC kind of triplet
pairs now when you sequence um
specifically these sequences you also
notice something interesting because
they have a highly uh biased sort of
triplet code and if you superimpose that
on the genetic code what is quite
striking is that this matches you know
very well with the so-called family box
codons which are shown here in Gray
which some people think is representing
the primordial genetic
code now this may simply be um one has
to be aware of if you want confirmation
bias because it's likely that this is at
least partially just a function of
thermodynamics because the family box
code on triplets also tend to be the
triplets which uh are bound most stably
kind of to the template but what
certainly is true is that this type of
open and ended and unbiased RNA
replication generates sequences which
are inherently biased to be translatable
because they have they use uh uh codons
which may have been present and
certainly contain no
stops okay so everything I've told you
so far was sort of based on this
ribosy which I've shown you the cryoem
earlier on as I said it's a mutualistic
heterodimer with a um um with a inactive
subunit blue and here the catalytic
subunit it's an advanced phenotype but
it's complex it's a it's really kind of
you know quite a beast and you know it's
288 nucleotides long so this is going to
be challenging kind of for
self-replication if for each cycle we
have to make nearly 300
nucleotides and also if you think about
the idea that such an RNA needs to
emerge spontaneously from a pool of
random sequences it really the
probability is Vanishing is small so
here comes another Paradox you need
complexity for function but actually for
emergence what you want is
Simplicity and you know we we sort of
avoided this issue for a long time but
eventually we decided we had to to
address it and we tried to um start
again and do a denova selection for
triplet polymerize activity and this
time which just very small kind of RNA
libraries uh selecting for tripet
incorporation and what we got is these
sort of three small RNA motifs um which
emerged really from a very small kind of
random sequence library and show some
polymerize activity we chose we picked
one of them and evolved it further um
it's not an enzyme with an amazing
catalytic turnover but it actually has
very robust uh polymerize activity and
particularly if you compare it to the
original ribosy and this is all now
encoded in this really small domain of
just about 50
nucleotides and Eduardo the postto
working on that kind of like making fun
of sort of British understand and sort
of like called this the quite tiny
triplet polymerase ribosy so from now on
I'll refer to this as the QT
ribosy and yeah so this real a small 50
nucleotide RN motive with robust
polymerize
activity okay amazingly this can be
truncated it further although you start
to pay an increasing price in polymerase
activity but the sort of
qt4 is still has very accessible sorry
very acceptable uh polymerize
activity and you can now use this to
make other ribosy so this is just shows
you the synthesis of a mini Hammerhead
ribosy both with the the sort of defined
tripled substrates and with a sort of
random all 64 random substrates you can
cut out that band on the gel isol at and
you can show that this these ribosy made
Hammerhead riboses are actually active
they can cleave um um an RNA substrate
and they are synthesized with you know
really it's not such a good Fidelity
under those conditions but actually
they're very matching fidelities between
the QT and the more complex 5tu
polymerase ribosy so really the QT
ribosy is able to synthesize an active
mini Hammerhead ribosy and it has sort
of General um polymerize activity on a
number of sequences I haven't shown you
those kind of always with the same uh
Fidelity of about
94% okay so now we've got a polymerize
ribosy which is small which is actually
has robust polymerize activity um now
the question is now can it make
itself and really those are the two um
uh component reactions of
self-replication you need the minus
strand synthesis where the plus strand
the folded QT plus strand uses itself
another plus strand as a template to
make another minus strand that's the
minus strand synthesis and then for the
plus strand synthesis you need the plus
strand the folded QT to use its
complementary strand the minus strand to
template the synthesis of another plus
strand uh copy so I'm going to first
talk
about the minus strand synthesis now if
you think about it here's another
paradoxical requirement this is now you
need the QT plus strand to use itself as
a template so in this reaction the plus
strand needs to be both ribozyme and
template at the same time so how can you
how can you affect this that it is both
a string and a thing again is it's both
folded and unfolded at the same time
again the triplets come to the rest
because as I told you before the
triplets can invade secondary structure
so you can have this state where it is
both unfolded unfolded as part of an RNA
confirmational ensembl which is um which
is essentially affected by triplet
concentration so at low triplet
concentration you can see you have two
copies of the plus strand they're both
folded nothing happens but as you
increase the triplet concentration an
increasing population of Plus strands
unfolds and becomes coated by the
triplets um and then can be used as a
template to synthesize at the minor
Strand and if you go too high with the
triplets eventually all the strands are
unfolded and there's no more activity
and you can see this on this gel this is
a sort of a polymerase ribosy activity
as a function of tripet concentration
you can see there's quite a sharp
transition where all the strands begin
to unfold and and and where you lose all
activity
so really the triple concentration
allows you to control the confirmational
Ensemble to shift the equilibrium from
ribosy active to template inactive
confirmation and if you're at the right
position you have a sort of a population
which contains both folded and unfolded
plus Strand and then you can synthesize
a copy of the minus strand you can see
this here this is the full length band
and again you can sequence this and
again we get about 94% % Fidelity so the
first component reaction of
self-replication can be preceded so the
qt4 ribosy can synthesize a ful length
minus strand copy from a plus strand
template using random
substrates now we come to the plus
strand synthesis now here's the same
problem now the ground state of you know
incubating a plus and a minus strand
together as I first told you before is
an RNA duplex this is incredibly stable
so we need to dissociate that and as I
told you before the triplets allow us to
stabilize the dissociated state and at
the right sort of concentration you have
um um you have in the dissociated state
you have some minus strands coated with
triplets obviously also some plus
strands coated with triplets but also
some plus strands folded that can then
use the minus strand as a substrate to
synthesize more PR Strand and again if
you go too high everything gets coated
by triplets and there is no
activity but unfortunately there is an
other equilibrium going on and that is
what happens is if the polymerase if the
polymerase ribosy the plus Transit
concentration here is just a little bit
too high it the the ribosy can compete
effectively with the triplets to strip
the triplets of the minor Strand and
everything kind of goes back um to the
dlex which is inactive and kills the
reaction and this is sort of shown here
that by increasing the plus uh
concentration you get less and less
product
formed and this sort of shows this
equilibrium as the plus strand
concentration increases um you more and
more effectively compete with the
triplets until you basically fold just
plus Strand and the uh the duplex so we
thought that one way to fix this would
be instead of using triplets we need to
use a substrate just in this case that
where that competes more effectively
with the plus strand for binding to the
minus Strand and we um and this is
particularly the case for the uh an au
kind of appical loop in the ribosy that
um where the triplets kind of do not
bind very stably to the template and
therefore this is single stranded and
sort of prone to Invasion uh by the plus
strand and yes if we add a hexamer that
sort of blocks off this vulnerable site
we now can get full length plus strand
synthesis so again the tripet
concentration allows controls of the
Strand confirmations and the hexamer
substrate complementary to the appical a
loop reduces the duplex formation and
now enables the QT 45 plus strand
synthesis this is kind of coming to the
end of my talk just to show you here
it's a weak band but we can also make
the plus strand synthesis so really the
QT can complement can complete sorry uh
both of the component reactions of
self-replication and we're sort of you
know excited kind of you know to take
this to the next step and go hopefully
to a fully kind of self-replicating
system that can begin uh to evolve so as
a summary kind of like I've been you
know trying to tell you kind of like how
triplets really have some very favorable
properties to enable RNA catalyzed RNA
replic ation to promote it by opening up
template secondary structures for
replication by attenuating strand reing
after duplex melting so it really solves
the Strand separation Problem by what I
would call substrate assisted strand
separation it enables these
non-canonical RNA replication modes I've
shown you the reverse and the primer
free but you may appreciate that with
triplets you also potentially have three
different registers in which you can
synthesize RNA
it improves replication Fidelity by the
sort of systems level triplet anti-t
triplet interactions in the pool and it
enables this open-ended primary free RNA
replication and the noo generation of
RNA sequence
pools and then the small QT ribosy
really now achieves the complex RNA
polymerize ribosy phenotype in a much
smaller motive just 45
nucleotides
um and is a able to of General RNA
templated RNA synthesis with good
Fidelity at
94% and is able to complete the two
reactions needed for self-replication
and really for the QT we're just at the
beginning because we've only done about
18 rounds of evolution and this is
exactly where Dave bartel's uh ribosy
was it's called r18 it it was at this
stage right at the beginning of the talk
so this takes us
back and finally I'd like to end with a
with a sort of a plea to take ice
seriously as a potential Prebiotic
primordial medium where RNA could have
made more sense because really if we
think of our solar system as potentially
a typical planetary
system in the cosmos of which we now
know there are many it's very noticeable
that while liquid water is only found in
any quantity on One Planet Ice is
abundant ice is everywhere there's whole
celestial bodies in the outer solar
system made from Water Ice
which would have substantial tic uh
phase kind of like
zones okay and I'd like to to to end by
thanking the amazing people kind of
who've done this work pretty much
everything I showed to you was done by
two amazing posts Jamie Atwater who's
now left the lab and running his own uh
group at University College London and
Eduardo janni who's still uh with us uh
in Cambridge and and also with help from
Sam quar Kevin GOI and uh Bryce Clifton
in the lab and actually also some very
very able uh L&B interns which
contributed to this like Joe keran
aditia raguram and Teresa who are both
here and I'd like to thank Ebe Anderson
at arhus kind of for some great
collaboration on the
cryo um these bodies for giving us money
and you for listening thank you
so um thanks so much for the amazing
talk uh any questions we prefer to give
chance to students and po STS to ask a
questions first so any questions uh you
can either work to the microphone or I
can just hand this to you
are you guys interested at all at
looking at quadruplet
substrate codons for we did right at the
beginning and I I I mentioned it briefly
but it probably went over it too quickly
so what happens is that you know when
you look at the sort of progression from
dinucleotides tried to quadruplets Etc
as you go longer they get Incorporated
more and more effectively because they
bind to the template more effectively
but when you then measure the Fidelity
there's a very sharp drop as you go from
triplets to
quadruplets uh with quadruplets
basically one of the base pairs no
longer matters so that really kills the
Fidelity so I think triplets is a sort
of Sweet Spot uh at ambient temperatures
and uh
yeah there there are various clinical uh
situations in which patients are treated
with protein and giving them injections
of proteins in order to um supplement
whatever is deficient and sometimes they
become resistant to that because they
make antibodies to the protein right um
have you considered trying to um make an
RNA that would have the specific
activity of a given Protein that's used
clinically where that might be a
substance Institute for the kind of
situation that uh I just articulated
yeah I mean I think um I think pure RNA
is probably wouldn't be a great clinical
substitute because it's not stable in in
you know in the body kind of in the
serum gets rapidly rapidly degraded
modified rnas kind of can form into
three-dimensional structures and you
know potentially you know act as ligans
like
antibodies um they can also be Imes for
a sort of limited set of reactions um
but I think in most cases what happens
is that so for example apers have been
explored with chemical modifications in
clinical trials to potentially replace
antibodies but the antibodies just tend
to win out um sort of tend to be better
so I think it would depend very it would
very much depend on the protein you're
trying to
replace actually I have a lot of
questions maybe I'll try to ask three to
begin with if no one has a questions um
so the first one is uh regarding the
evolution of the um ribos do you think
um the template free replication is
actually its own invidual Evolution
system which means if you begin with a
PO R polymerase that relatively AO prone
and then if it's replicating itself then
whoever most catalytically potent
will be the final products yeah no I
mean this is this is what we would like
to do we would really like to begin the
self-replication process so you know the
system should become self-optimizing and
this has been literally proposed you
know as you acquire mutations you know
you select for better and better
self-replication yeah they should self
like emergence uh as the mostly
efficient and the Fatal system that that
would allow you emergence but but I
think the the problem with the
fragmentary replication is that you that
you keep losing the connection between
the pieces so even if you had you if you
replicate in fragments and then assemble
them and then select for function um and
then you you would go back to the open
end to to the randomly primed
replication you then break the
connection again between the mutations
so I think the small ribosy we think is
the way to go cool uh and my second
question is um just generally do if this
is indeed the true that's how things
begin on Earth um do you imagine there
will be another ribo synthesizing the
triplate um well I mean we we had I mean
I'm not sure I fully understood the
question we had three motives which had
triplet polymerized ribosy activity so
this clearly loads there's probably that
was a small RNA Library so I think if we
keep selecting we would I think
emergence of these small motives is
really easy because they're small
they're simple and the there's probably
loads of
them I see um and then uh regarding the
potential possibility of uh the
evolution of ribosome uh ribosome in the
end do you imagine there could be some
Co evolution of R and pipe ties to
extend they self replicate uh now
actually synthesizing some pipetite
products like I feel the triplet is
already the precursor of TRNA
yeah I think
um I mean the in a way the evolution of
translation is almost more mysterious
than you know the sort of original kind
of origin of life because you need at
least three different subsystems to sort
of come together to give you translation
you need you need a reader like the
small ribosomal subunit that tracks
reads the sequence you need a decoding
um adapter like the trnas and you then
need the
the you need you need the the peptidal
transfer um now some people have
speculated that the s30 subunit of the
ribosome that's the old replic case that
has become repurposed for
translation uh but I I really don't know
if you know I would like to speculate
too much but what is very interesting is
that you know the ribosome the genetic
code um is a triplet code with one
wobble position and that's exactly what
we have as well with our triplets we
also end up with one wubble position
it's at the other side of the triplet
but it's the same sort of idea yeah I
think it's quite amazing because they go
from either direction but then still
they have this triplet like the effects
at the wble position so I in fact Jamie
I think has some interest in you know
building simple uh models um of how
translation might have evolved kind of
in his lab so you know you should ask
him maybe in a few years time
any more
questions uh sorry you do we have more
time okay thank you uh great talk do you
have any idea of how ribozymes can bias
towards self-replication rather than
replicating other uh RNA template yeah
so so what you're asking is like if you
have the ribosy in a soup of sequences
how does it recognizes its kin yeah yeah
I mean I think I haven't included this
here but I think the the answer to that
is the same as in Biology you need to
compartmentalize so you need to have
some sort of
um um you know you need to sort of
enclose the replication reaction into
some sort of compartment which means
kind of that the ribosy and its kin sort
of stay together and these type of
compartments could be many things you
know they could be simple by layer
membranes vesicles but and there's all
kinds of pockets that you can have in
fact I haven't shown you this but if you
set up the TIC ice phase in a particular
way instead of getting these channels of
tic phase you actually get little
inclusions so these could be even the
TIC phase could be some sort of
primitive you know protocellular medium
and of course you can hit pockets in um
sort of if you mix kind of like you know
oil phases kind of unwatered type of
emulsions um some people are interested
in aerosols kind of that you get let's
say an Ocean Spray which form like
little droplets and so on so I think
there's no shortage of um enclosing
compartmentalization modes that one
could explore but I think what we we're
sort of focused on getting the
self-replication process to work and I
think once it's working I think we'll
definitively think about exactly that
problem hey there um I was curious if
you could speak to any structural
similarities you SE between the the
smaller um ribozymes and the any larger
ones or between the smaller ones I don't
think we really kind of see any and I
mean what is interesting is we ma the
way the two riboses interact with the
primer template and they seem to contact
exactly the same positions on the primer
template but when we try to look at the
structure I can show you a slide that I
sort of um have excluded um from this
this is you know when we sort of try to
figure out what the
ribosy looks like by footprinting and
sort of Fitness landscape analysis um I
mean you can see it really kind of just
looks like a hairpin and we have some
preliminary cryoem data which also
suggests kind of it really it's just
kind of you know there's
nothing nothing that looks you know like
the other structure at all it's just
just um you know a hairpin structure uh
and we we definitively you know want to
figure out how this thing does its job
because at the moment it's completely
mysterious thank
you any more
questions okay if not thanks everyone
for coming and let's all thank uh Dr
holik is great talk okay
[Applause]