so now let's talk about how a medical
doctor can make a diagnosis of
ulcerative colitis so first thing that
happens is uh your doctor takes your
medical history and does some blood work
then there's a colonoscopy which again
is just a tube that's inserted kind of
into the gastrointestinal tract into the
colon and there's a camera on it and we
can look uh at the inside of the colon
and assess the level of inflammation and
finally uh a pathologist can do
hystology on the colon tissue so let's
introduce hystology so how this works is
a biopsy is taken from the colon and
that's just a small piece of colon
tissue and that tissue is cut up into
smaller pieces and put on a slide and
then examined under a microscope to look
at uh cellular and tissue features from
that piece of the colon so uh
Pathologists have many Tools in sort of
their toolkit for studying uh tissue and
one of the most common tools they use is
this stain called h& this stands for
hematoxylin and Ain and these are two
stains that when mixed together can
provide contrast to a tissue uh section
so here we're looking at a uh colon
tissue biopsy and it's been stained with
this hematoxilin and Asin stain and the
hemx hemotoxylin stains the cell nucleus
uh this blue purple color and the Ain
stains every other part of the cell pink
so here you can see individual nuclei
and then everything else is pink and
what this does is it gives you this
really nice view of the tissue so here
we're looking at colonic Crypts which
are intestinal glands made up of
epithelial cells that line your entire
colon and this is a really common
structure that we see all over the colon
and it's really important for the colon
function now the colon itself has a
somewhat complicated organization so
let's walk through it so here's the
colon tube and it's made up of multiple
layers and these layers are the mucosa
the sub mucosa and the muscularis
propria so the mucosa is the innermost
layer and this is where uh food or
partially digested food gets pushed down
the track and there are colonic CPS that
line the mucosa then below the mucosa is
the sub mucosa and this is a dense and
sort of irregular kind of connective
tissue and then finally uh there's the
muscular propriate which is a thick
layer of muscle which is involved in
peristalsis which is pushing uh food
down the gut tube so now if we cut a
crosssection through the colon and then
have a pathologist do an h& stain of
that colon tissue uh piece we get this
nice cross-section and now here is the
inside of the colon where food and
microbes are kind of living and then
here's the outside of the colon and the
h& stain reveals the three layers so
here we have the mucosa which is made up
of these Crypts which are these circles
you see all along the surface and then
below that is the submucosa and then you
see the muscle layer and what you can
see is that the h& stain really reveals
the structure and organization of the
tissue so now let's go from the outside
in with the colon starting with the
muscle layer so here's a zoom in of h&
of colon muscle and there's two layers
this longitud layer and the circular
layer and again this is important for
pushing food through the gut and then in
between the layers there's this nerve
fiber or myenteric plexus and this does
a lot of things in the colon but one of
the things it's doing is kind of
controlling again that peristalsis the
movement of food through the gut now
let's go one layer in into the sub
mucosa the sub mucosa is this dense and
irregular connective tissue that has fat
cells blood vessels immune cells and
nerves here is a blood vessel
highlighted and you you can see it's
very red there are red blood cells in
there uh here's a nerve cell that's been
highlighted and then finally let's go to
the innermost layer which is the mucosa
and the mucosa has a somewhat
complicated structure the first layer of
the mucosa is the epithelial layer and
that's made up of these glands here or
the colonic Crypts and they're shown
here and here and this is a really
fascinating layer um at the base of
every single colonic Crypt there are
stem cells and these are are
regenerating the entire lining of the
colon every 5 to 7 days so the colon is
one of the fastest regenerating tissues
in the body and that's needed because as
food goes down the colon it's basically
sloughing off a lot of the cells in this
epithelial layer so this layer needs to
be regenerated constantly below the
epithelium in these colonic Crypts
there's the lamin propria which consists
of many immune cells and connective
tissue and then finally there's a layer
of muscle called the muscularis mucosa
which separates the mucosa from the sub
mucosa and this is important for local
motions of the colonic Crypts
here so in ulcerative colitis there are
dramatic changes to the normal uh colon
histology we see so in this cartoon on
the left we have healthy colon and on
the right we have ulcerative colitis and
there are sort of three big changes that
happen histologically one is cryp
distortion
so we go from these normal look colonic
crys to distorted ones or crys that have
these
abses um there's also epithelial changes
that happen uh such as metaplasia so
metaplasia is the appearance of a new
cell type that's not normally found in
that tissue and then finally we also
have immune infiltration so immune
infiltration means that immune cells are
showing up and this is because you know
ulcerative colitis is a disease with
chronic inflammation and these immune
cells are showing up and causing
inflammation in the mucosal layer and so
this could be neutrophils which we
talked about earlier which are kind of
responding to the bacteria in the colon
uh also other cells such as plasma cells
which is a type of B cell okay so here
we're looking at a histology image of
ulcerative colitis and on the right for
comparison we see healthy colonic Crypts
so there are several tissue features
that a pathologist can immediately spot
when looking at this h& stain of Al sort
of citis uh first they might say that
okay there's these Crypt abses where if
you look at the Crypt it looks like
there's some cells in the center of the
crypt and those are neutrophils which
are these immune cells that are
responding to bacteria that's
infiltrated into the mucosa uh the
pathologist will also spot that there's
ulceration so the formation of these
ulcers in the mucosa and this is where
ulcerative kitis gets his name and then
finally uh pathologist would point out
that there's basil plas cytosis so what
this is is the accumulation of plasma
cells which are a type of immune cell
and they are in the base of the mucosa
and they are these small blue cells that
have been stained by the h& and they
have very prominent blue nuclei as
another example here we're looking at
CPS that have undergone Distortion and
branching so you see this sort of
branching structure and again you can
pair this to the healthy colon you just
see these dramatic changes we also see
things like panth cell metaplasia so a
panis cell is a cell type that lives
near your intestinal stem cells and it
protects the stem cell against microbes
and normally these cells are not found
in the distal colon but during uler of
colitis you get this metaplasia where
the cell type appears and you can see
this if you look very closely in this
bright pink color that's a Telltale sign
that there's a pan the cell there