my name is Noah Trish and I am going to
be presenting the first part of the
primer on
using uh Advanced molecular Dynamic
simulation techniques or MD uh to
characterize large scale confirmational
Transitions and
Transporters that includes both uh
confirmational Dynamics uh and also uh
energetics um
so before I get into that say that cells
are surrounded by membranes membranes
protect the cell from their external
environment um they're mostly
impermeable to most substances but it is
necessary for substances to cross the
membrane in order to support the all the
functions that happen uh within the cell
um and one of the main classes of
proteins that facilitate transport of
primarily small molecules across
membranes are
Transporters um
Transporters uh the substances that
Transporters transport are called their
substrate um and they at a fundamental
level operate through the alternating
access
mechanism um in the alternating access
mechanism Transporters go uh the
accessibility of bound substrate is
accessible from only one side of the
membrane at a time um Transporters
undergo transitions from inward facing
or high F states to outward facing or o
States Transporters can be bound which
is this subscript b or APO which means
nothing is bound to them is this
subscript a and it can also be partially
bound um in between these
two um because of their Central role in
cellular function transporter
malfunction is often associated with
disease and they also are common uh
targets of pharmaceutical drugs
the Transporters are very diverse uh set
of proteins they realize the alternating
access mechanism varies widely from
transporter to transporter this
schematic is uh showing uh most of the
common classes of realizations of the uh
an alternating access
mechanism
um it's not important to know the exact
details of each of these mechanisms
right now we'll introduce uh more about
the details later on when they become
more important um but what I will say is
that uh common feature of all these
different uh transport mechanisms is the
involvement of large scale structural
changes um in order to switch this
substrate accessibility from one side of
the membrane to another There is almost
always some sort of large- scale
structural change and uh this is what we
want to uh probe understand uh with the
uh approach that I'm going to that we're
going to be talking about uh the
particular technique that we use to uh
look into this is called molecular
Dynamics
simulations um or
MD uh within a molecular Dynamics
simulation it's a physics based approach
where you first Define a potential
energy function which we call a force
field there are various terms within the
force field that represent uh as meant
to empirically represent the
interactions between bonded sets of
atoms and non-bonded sets of atoms um
and uh the idea is to represent all the
interactions between all the atoms
within the system uh with all these
interaction all these interactions
defined uh we can determine all the
forces that uh are exerted on all the
atoms in the system and then uh
iteratively numeric ly integrate uh
Newton's equations of motion to
determine how the positions of the atoms
change as a function of
time um these Atomic Dynamics
collectively give rise to molecular
Dynamics uh you can end up with
simulations uh that visually look
something like
this
[Music]
um MD simulations have been around for a
long long time they've been maturing
over time uh and it's been there's lots
of examples out there of them having
success in predicting and capturing uh
what the Dynamics of molecules look like
um but uh they also have their own
limitations and the most important
limitation for the purposes of this
presentation is the time skills that are
accessible to molecular Dynamics
simulations um as algorithms have
improved and especially as Hardware has
improved uh longer and longer time
scales are accessible to MD simulations
nowadays it's pretty common place to uh
find MD simulations uh that run for uh
on the order of
microseconds but um this still is not
long enough to capture in in general uh
the spontaneous transition of
Transporters between inward facing and
outward facing
States um these uh transitions can take
usually on the order of milliseconds
they can also last all the way up to
minutes and this is just not something
that uh we can access with uh vanilla
and
these and so with this problem in mind
uh in the lab ofad PID where I'm
currently a postto um we there was a
method that was developed that put
together um a series of advanced
molecular Dynamic simulation
techniques uh in order to specifically
probe uh the confirmational Dynamics of
these large scale transitions within
Transporters within the modou cores lab
there was a method developed to tackle
this composed of multiple Advanced
molecular Dynamics simulation
techniques um we're going to go in the
rest of the primer we're going to go
through each of these steps in more
detail uh right now I'll say the overall
approach um just to give an overview uh
within this approach we start by
identifying structures that represent
the end States of uh the transition of
Interest usually representing an inward
facing and an outward facing State we
Define uh Collective variables which are
mathematical mathematical descriptions
of reaction coordinates uh that capture
are meant to capture the all of the
major structural differences between uh
the two states of
interest uh using these Collective
variable definitions we run a series of
driven MD simulations uh to explore
different pathways through uh the
collective variable
space uh after we've identified a
sufficiently optimal transition pathway
uh we can uh relax it structurally uh
using a technique called the string
method with SWS of trajectories or
smws um then uh we to enhance sampling
along the transition pathway we run a
simulation called bias exchange umbrella
sampling or
be uh and then finally from that
simulation we can extract a free energy
profile using techniques like the
weighted histogram analysis method or
Wham or the multi-state vet acceptance
ratio M
Bar um so before I start talking about
those steps in more detail I just want
to say a little bit of little something
about where this uh technique comes from
it was developed by Mahmud Madi and Imad
Tash kid when uh off mood was a postto
in a mods lab um this approach draws on
previously wellestablished techniques
within the MD field uh namely driven MD
string method umbrella sampling and Wham
um and then it develops them further and
uh targets them towards specifically
understanding uh these large scale
structural Transitions and
Transporters um I'll also say that this
approach is imp imped in using the MD
engine namd uh and also makes heavy use
of the collective variables module which
is uh externally
developed um namd was originally
developed in CL schuon's lab uh but
since he passed away it's continued to
be developed in aad Tash Cori's lab so
there's always been a close
collaboration between uh the research
scientists in these Labs uh which we've
always shared lab space um and the devel
developers of Nami which is also uh
contributed to the development of this
uh method
overall okay so with that I'll start
going into each of these steps in a
little bit more detail starting with
identifying the uh start and end states
of the transition of
interest um so transport Cycles in
general are composed of a series of
transitions U between major functional
States like uh the inward facing and
outward facing State generally we're
interested in these types of transitions
you can also uh generalize the approach
a little bit to apply it to uh binding
and unbinding events uh sometimes
there's also um a transiently stable
intermediate State that's relevant for a
particular transporter and you can look
at uh transitions between these major
States and that uh intermediate as
well um so first you have to pick which
transition you want to look at um once
you've done that you need structures to
represent uh both of the end States of
transition of interest uh the best uh
source for structures is our high
resolution structures that come from
experimental techniques like x-ray
crystallography or cryoem uh but it's
also an option to use modeling uh
techniques from a variety of sources
like alphafold standard topology
modeling and also or specialized
modeling that are specific uh to
Transporters I'm also I will also say at
this point that in order to uh do the
advanced MD simulations we also need to
build an MD simulation system that
includes uh the protein lipids water
ions uh and everything that want to
include within the system um there are
standard tools within the field for
doing this uh charm GUI is particularly
popular for uh preparing uh simulation
systems for M uh MD simulations of
membrane uh proteins like transporters
and then sometimes there are
also uh there are very um established uh
parameters for standard amino acid
residues nucleic acid bases lipids water
ions but small molecules are much more
diverse and so if you want to look at
transitions involving uh substrates or
bound Inhibitors that might be drugs
then uh you will need to generate
generally need to generate parameters uh
for those and there are standardized
tools to do that as
well okay next step is defining
Collective
variables um Collective variables as I
said before are mathematical
descriptions of reaction coordinates uh
these Collective variables that you
defined are meant to uh fully capture
the major structural differences between
uh end states of your transition of
interest um this example which is coming
from the paper that uh established the
approach uh you have uh Collective
variables representing the angles uh
between major protein domains like the
red and the blue domains and two
different uh viewpoints and also the
yellow and green domains and then a
distance as well between these yellow
and green domain there are many
different uh kinds of collective
variables that are defined within the
collective variable module used by namd
um
and I want to say a little bit of
something about two of the most common
ones first distance distance is very
simple it measures distance between the
centers of mass of two selections of
atoms so in this example Center of mass
of this green domain and the yellow
domain uh you can either use the full
distance it's also common to project the
distance along a particular user
specified um U axis of uh of
interest um and then orientation is the
second common Collective variable that I
want to comment on um there is
established theory that says that uh
when a any kind of rigid body moves
throughout space tumbles in any kind of
way um at the beginning if you have um I
think the reference at the beginning of
that tumbling motion at and at the end
of that tumbling motion you superpose
the uh centers of mass of the rigid
bodies you can find and calculate a
rotation about a particular uh amount of
rotation about a particular rotation
axis that passes through the center of
mass of that rigid body um and this idea
of having particular uh rotation a axis
and rotation amount um allows you
relative to reference coordinates allows
you to represent any General orientation
of a collection of atoms in a protein um
throughout your
simulation
um I will also say because it comes up
in literature and also in our
presentations that um the collective
variables module represents orientation
using a quaternion format that looks
like this uh there's nothing special
about this representation scientifically
it has some convenient mathematical and
computational properties which is why
it's used um but and it's also not
exactly straightforward to understand
what's going on uh from a human
perspective in this format so usually
people will convert it to something that
makes more sense in the physical world
like in this example angles between
these uh individual
dos okay next is step of running driven
MD simulations
um the way that this works U from the
perspective of MD you go back you to the
original formulation you still have the
same uh potential energy force field um
and then when you want to add biases you
end up adding uh an extra biasing term
uh to your total potential energy
function for Collective variables that
are scalar uh this takes the form of a
harmonic uh
and for quaternion the situation is a
little bit different um and then once
you have this definition of the
collective variables and of the harmonic
uh restraint you go through the same
steps of calculating the gradient of the
total potential energy function forces
then uh iteratively
demeric um for static restraints you can
have a moving Target which is this uh Z
not of I
um uh but for driven MD simulations this
target value moves as a function of time
and so you have a moving harmonic
restraint and with the uh by applying
movement to these harmonic restraints
you can induce uh processes to happen uh
at time scales that are quicker than uh
they happen in nature
oops uh so I'd like to say that the
process of defining Collective variables
and running these driven MD simulations
is inherently
iterative um there are a lot of uh
considerations and options that you have
when you're defining Collective
variables and also biasing protocols um
you have to choose your Collective
variables carefully like I said there
are a lot of them that are defined in
the
module uh you have to make choices about
which atoms to add to your Collective
variables for example you could uh do
the oh one sec um you can select the
entire uh domain here or you might want
to exclude certain Hees there as
well could you uh describe just
basically what's happening in the
animation in terms of driving a
transition yeah so uh there are two
Collective variables defined here which
are changing this orientation drawn it
schematically on left uh changing the
orientation of the trans for of the uh
this blue domain relative to the purple
domain then also inducing a a drive um
in changing the center of mass uh it's
depicted schematically as uh straight up
and down it's a little bit more
complicated in three dimensions but
those are the two things that are being
driven in order to uh create this movie
uh could you further uh elaborate how do
you make the decision like which part of
the transporter to use for Collective
variable and like which Collective
variable to use like how do you make
this position yeah so that that's
um that comes with experience is what I
would say U we say in general that it's
an empirical definition um and uh this
is also where this iterative process of
trying so you have an idea of what start
and end looks like you want to get from
point A to point B um and you want to do
it in a way that's um not perturbing the
system in an unnatural way these are
these uh criteria that I'm looking I'm
listing over here you don't want the
protein to unfold you don't want water
pores to form you don't want membrane
deformations to happen you want the
final state to match the end State and
so um you when you're starting out you
sort of draw from the literature
uh when you have more experience you
draw from your own experience to say uh
which Collective variables to choose and
how to uh combine them to
uh to induce what you want to
induce last thing I wanted to say on
this slide was a lot of these options
are straightforward to um see if there's
an issue and uh iteratively refine what
you're doing um the only one uh based on
uh analysis of the the trajectory that
you get up get out at the end the one
that is not so
straightforward um is choosing a path uh
to take through the collective variable
space and so to explain why that is I
think it's helpful to switch to an
analogy um what we're doing here uh in
especially in the later parts of of the
overall uh approach is trying to find an
optimal pathway
uh through a rugged mountainous
landscape the mountains representing are
representing uh barriers within the free
energy surface
um and uh sort of north south east west
is representing uh the collective
variables that you chosen um uh to
represent the uh the differences between
the inward facing and the outward facing
States
um starting from
an initial uh or a a direct drive from
the inward facing state to the outward
facing state it could be the case that
uh this is pretty close to the optimal
pathway uh for this particular
transporter but you don't know that and
uh the next step in this uh uh protocol
string method is um a local structural
refinement uh algorithm and so if it's
if the direct drive is close to the
optimal path pathway the string method
will turn out a relaxed pathway that's
close to that optimal pathway um but you
could be in a situation with your
transporter where this uh direct drive
from the inward facing to outward facing
state is kind of pushing you right over
the top of a mountain a really high free
energy barrier the string method will
still uh relax this pathway for you but
it uh will not be uh close to the
optimal pathway through this Collective
variable space and so So within the
traditional uh method the way that we um
approach this is we run a lot of driven
MD simulations to uh cover a lot of the
important Collective variable space and
we evaluate these different Pathways for
uh their degree of optimality to
identify which pathway we want to
proceed forward uh with relaxation with
the string
method um the way that we evaluate
optimality of Pathways um with driven MD
simulations is using work profiles that
look like this work being um a measure
of how difficult it is to induce
transitions along the particular chosen
Pathways um and this is showing the
example that I showed previously uh from
the paper that established uh this
approach overall um and in
this
uh um approach oh the question yeah are
these work profiles a kinetic barrier or
are they
energetic
thermodynamic
work like if there's a a a steep hill
that prevents things from going down One
path even though it's the lowest energy
path will that will that kinetic barrier
still uh cause a lot of work in
this it's thermodynamic
okay um okay so in this
example
uh the different Pathways that were
chosen were uh corresponding to driving
changes in different Collective
variables for this particular
transporter in different orders
um uh it's important that these uh work
profiles represent averages over
multiple MD simulations um because work
values can vary significantly based on
what's happening within the environment
of the M
simulation um and so uh by exploring
different Pathways we're able to look at
these work profiles and identify um a
pathway uh which is uh the most optimal
um that you can find in the the end of
the day and uh for this example uh this
particular order of changes in
Collective variables were the one that
uh require the least amount of work and
was selected for um additional
refinement um with string method and so
with that I'm G to pass it over to ashon
who's going to talk about the second the
uh next steps also talk about uh
comparisons to other methods um uh that
are exist within the field and also
generalizations of um and uh
perspectives on the overall approach
thank you so much uh thanks Noah for
your excellent talk my name is Ash and
I'm a post stock at theoretical and
computational biophysics group bman
Institute University of Illinois and I'm
also a visiting scholar at University of
arkans I'm going to talk about the
second second part of our strategy to
study confirmational transition mainly
focus
on um string method and the path
sampling part string method and free
energy
calculations uh I will a little bit into
the details technical details of this
approach and also try to bring up some
alternative ones and uh talk about my
own
perspective uh proteins are uh
confirmation hetrogeneous if you want to
Define design a drug for them you have
to consider it and their confirmational
space is very complex uh there are many
uh midle stable St States local call
Minima and go from one state let's say
this state to this state we uh need to
consider different pathway and uh a
great tool here is molecular dyamic as
Noah mentioned molecular Dynamic has uh
uh time scale
problem and uh what is known as sampling
problem to resolve that sampling problem
we use statistical physics based
approaches uh I saw of divide these two
techniques to two different
categor uh let's imagine that this is uh
the projection of the
previous the confirmational landscape on
uh one uh Dimension this is the reaction
coordinate our pathway and this is the
free enery our system is fluctuating
here we want to go from here to here
this free energy is not known priority
and we are trying to reconstruct this
one in
our uh as I mentioned there are
technically two different
strategy uh first one are the one that
they use
force uh potential force or potential
external force of potential to uh bu a
sample and these are the one that we use
and I will talk about them in the next
couple of slid there are other methods
that are uh basically try to uh disturb
our sampling Direct I call them
statistically bios for in or sometimes
people call them adaptively uh sampling
method it's like uh let's imagine we
have we run several different
simulations here some of them they move
to the a little bit different State uh
with some approach we duplicate the one
that they are able to pass and kill the
other ones and repeat this approach
until we go to the
other each one of these approach has
their own advantage and
disadvantage uh here and the main
problem as you guess is using force uh
makes our system to go to the states
that are not natural to our system
uh but we prefer these these set of
approaches because uh they increase our
chance to go to the others exponential
because we use force or uh potential so
of the example for uh these set of uh
methods are steered MD uh or targeted MD
these are group of I group them in a
non-equilibrium work the deren MD that
Noah was talking about is in this Set uh
here let's say that we push our system
with some Force go to the others we
calculate the amount of work the work
that Noah was showing in in his part and
convert that work to free energy uh this
approach is not very common these days
for calculating the free energy uh
because to get something accurate we
need to do several different
simulations another class of method is
uh the gradient based me the one that an
example of them is adaptive biasing
force uh let's say that uh We've be in
this
space our simulation is here our system
is here uh we calculate the force that
is um experiencing by our system
um export exactly opposite force on our
system and push it a little bit forward
and then uh we convert this Force to uh
derivative of
freeer and taking the uh integral from
that derivative we get the free energy
another class is histogram basement
umbrella sampling and metod Dynamics are
two example of this class umbrella
sampling is the one that we use in our
uh uh sampling in our confirmational
transition uh technique uh it is
basically works by restraining our
simulation to different region um making
sure that we are sampling all the this
difference barriers and then combining
all of them together to get the fre
another popular method is metod dnamic
um metad dnamic is working by adding uh
small external potential to our system
usually in form of gaan bringing our
system up to pass the barrier and go to
the others and then inversing that
potential to get the free energy I have
used meod dnamic during my PhD a lot uh
it's a very good approach but the main
problem with metod dnamic is when we
have a lot of Collective variables is
very slow and this is the case for
studying uh meming
transport uh yes uh can you comment on
what type of sampling methods are
suitable for different types of protein
I understand that the topic here today
is the transmembrane protein but then
there are disordered proteins there are
more folded proteins do you recommend
different type of sampling for different
types of protein yes it it really
depends on your system and accuracy that
you want uh I generally suggest uh the
first two for small system like DNA
peptide and that kind of but for larger
systems I recommend umbrella sampling
and metod dnamic even for metod dnamic I
I think uh it's not generally a good
approach because it uh for large system
you need uh to consider a a large number
of collective Vari Ables and it makes uh
your computation pretty
slow uh sorry uh so as Noah mentioned
our uh strategy is to combine these
biing sampling methods with pth sampling
Al and uh the reason behind that is uh
probably can see better here in this um
uh toy model this is a
from potential a 2d
potential uh let's uh assume that this
is the uh the free energy that we don't
know and it's related to that uh system
I showed in the first slide uh we can
try to sample the whole area the red
area is correspond to high energy
barriers the blue one is the low energy
barriers we can try to sample the whole
area or we can focus on some important
part and the interesting part the
transition go from here to here and uh
this is the procedure this is known as P
sampling um pass sampling
um as Noah mention we generally use der
MD to go from one state to other state
and then uh to try to refine that path
we cannot generally generate many paths
sometimes we do have to but um our
approach is to focus on the most
important the one that we think are more
important for our case
uh to refine or relax that path we use a
technique called string method uh string
method uh like other past sampling
algorithm has routine transition p
through it was introduced around 20
years ago and it works by um
uh discretizing an initial path who uh
set of let's say images that are full
copy of our system these images that are
in equal distance from each
other and we can identify them with a
set of collective variables let's say
these are our Collective variables and
uh they are related to our each one of
our system then we refine this path in
iterative manner According to some rules
until we end up with something convert
and the main rule here is that we assume
our systems are evolving according to
this over damp
langine uh equation that has diffusion
and also free energy diffusion and
free
uh uh we want the final pass
um we want to end up with a pass pass
that doesn't have any drift at the end
except along the path if our system if
we start the system um somewhere here um
our system only can evolve along the
pass it doesn't move orthogonal to these
paths and this is called Zero D path a
string method tries to identify these
paths it's not necessarily the minimum
free energy path that um we are ultimate
looking for it or the most popular path
that our system are going to take it's
just uh a path that we think it's
important for us there are different
version of a string method zero
temperature string method was uh the
first one it was not considering the uh
temperature and
entropy uh then final temperature uh
string method came up the one that we
use is string method with swarms of
trajectory and it works by by
um assigning T tens of copy to each
image each copy of our system each
system that we have
um the algorithm conceptually is simple
it's like uh we disc criticize this
path uh then we
um um assign copies to it uh restrain
those copies to be close to the images
then uh release uh um our system to move
a little bit in a short time let's say
they for this image they move here for
the other one they move here calculate
the average distance move them to the
new places and then next step is to make
sure that they have equal distance from
each other this is particularly
important because close to the minimum
they tend to get very close to each
other otherwise uh everything goes
inside to that minimum so we keep the
distances equal from each other and we
repeat this procedure until we
converge this animation shows uh how the
string method works the pass the initial
pass was starting from here and it is
getting uh converged to this new pass
after some number of
iterations the important thing here is
that our string method the passes that
we get from string method are not unique
and they are really depend on the
parameters that we use for our uh
approach for instance if we go with a
short number of images um we end up with
a pass like this let's say the initial
pass was from here to here and if I go
with only five images I lose a lot of
information for uh my calculation this
example is for 20 the the path seems to
be reasonable if I increase the number
of images to something very large uh I
end up with that pass that has a lot of
inks and loops and it's not a real pass
for or another problem here is that uh
if I start with the initial pass that is
um just um from here to here I I cannot
sample and go here my pass is just uh a
refin pass locally and this happens a
lot in our cases because particularly
when we work with experimental people
they come up and give us some structure
some endpoint structure they say okay
this is your structure here and they
gave us this structure after a little
bit they come and say that okay the the
actual structure was this one so we need
to repeat this one more time and go from
um for all of these steps one more time
and uh my point here is that this method
cannot give us some final struct we need
to have uh the end point for our
path uh now let's say that we have the
path the next step is to uh calculate
the free energy along that path uh the
method that we use for calculating free
energy along the path is umbrella
sampling umbrella sampling is uh
probably the oldest method for free
energy calculation but yet in my opinion
at least the most successful it works by
uh biasing our
system and uh through different Windows
um getting fire sample from our system
beaning those fire sample to and getting
distribution of Bio uh samples
converting those bio sample combining
and converting them together through
different reweighing techniques the
conventional one is called weighted
histogram analysis spam and then
calculate our fre energy uh one problem
here is
that calculating free energy with
umbrella sampling it's like when we are
uh on our path it's like we don't have
any
diffusion one way to resolve this uh
problem is um pass the information
between this different different Windows
a technique for that is called uh
replica EX
change it passes information any kind of
information between two windows every uh
couple of steps and sort of through this
we sort of make our uh pass our
information to diffuse and we have some
sort of
diffusion uh we call this one this
approach bias exchange umbrella sampling
uh again works by considering set of
Windows images that we got from the
previous step assigning them different
copy piece and uh calculating the uh
free energy for that one this is my
converge path
um with 20 different windows or images I
do umbrella sampling for each one of
these and when I'm converg my
simulations are converged I combine them
through a little bit different approach
called a nonparametric approach uh and
calculate my free energy uh we use this
non-parametric approach
because uh it allows us to not only
calculate the free energy along the uh
Collective variables that we initially
bias our system but also other
Collective variables that uh we think we
have sampled them enough this would be
uh the free energy from these path along
these path this minimum is corresponding
to that point along the path when we go
little bit higher we have a barrier then
we have sort of a middle stable State
here and then my final minimum is uh
would be
here okay now having all the different
part of this puzzle together um putting
them all
together I sort of uh
summarize our sampling we start with a
identifying a set of collective
variables for our system this is
basically knowledge based and sometimes
data deriv based and then uh we steer
our system we induce the transition to
go from one state to other state but
since we use force uh we try to refine
and relax our system through a string
method
um yeah here for instance for the first
step um this is the collective variables
for distance the other one is uh Theta
for the angle the schematic is showing
that the The Next Step was calculating
the amount of work and then refining the
path and finally calculating the um free
energy along the path and when we have
all of these we sort of try to detect
the area that did not sample
and we sometimes have to go through this
step uh again we have to for instance go
from here back to the previous step but
the whole procedure is something like
this
uh having those now I want to talk about
some of the recent advances in our
approach uh the package that we use namd
for our molecular Dynamic
simulations uh now supports gpus it
improves our uh simulation performance
of our simulation uh let's say from uh
almost from my experience 10 times from
like couple of nanc per day to couple of
100 nanc per day sometimes on the other
hand for free energy calculations we use
cold bar modules these two now can work
together and improve our um sampling
approach
uh another uh Improvement here is using
uh data deriven approaches I already
said that there are methods at least for
toy model uh they they use time like
Auto encoders to reconstruct better
Collective variables but as I mentioned
one problem here is that uh to define a
good Collective variables we need to
have good trajectory initial inputs and
for having those initial inputs uh we
have to bias our system and this is kind
of like a um
um iterative procedure here that we need
to go through it uh over the years
different flavors have been added to
these sampling techniques for instance
people combine bias exchange and string
method uh bias exchange with a string
method or they come up with adaptive
some sort of adaptive umbrella
s uh I want to now talk about about one
of the newer approach that we uh are
using and to not only calculate the
thermodynamic but also
kinetic and one problem that we had one
problem that we had from our approach
was uh that we only consider a single
pass everything end up with a single
pass we can instead of a single path
calculating everything along a single
path we can consider a tube of path let
say uh we we end up with this converge
path from here to here and then run some
equilibrium
simulations um and then count the number
of transition between different images
from that we can build a transition
Matrix having that transition Matrix we
can calculate the free energy and also
let's say rate of transition that is
experimentally very important uh but and
this usually is not really good for
continuous model like
molecular uh systems
and uh for instead of using this we
suggest using a different Matrix called
rate or uh generator Matrix which is
based on this previous transition Matrix
but for instance it's La time
independent the time that we save our
information and resolve some of the
problem from this one when we have this
approach it's like we use some
estimators to go from this one to that
one when we have that one uh we can
calculate the
diffusion and also free energy having
diffusion and free energy both we can
calculate the mean first passage time
the time that um it takes an average to
go from here to here and then uh
converting that one to rate of our
transition
um okay finally I want to summarize the
main feature of our
sampling uh our approach is by
definition an ad hog man we uh search
for Collective variables iteratively
improve our approach we start with a
deran MD steered MD targeted MD to
induce a transition refine that
transition calculate the free energy
along that uh transition pathway with bi
exchange umbrella sampling our method
works on high dimensional
Collective uh on unlike other methods
that are uh they are limited by number
of collective variables we can consider
High number of collective variables that
we we're going to talk about them in the
next part and uh you will see uh the
number of collective variables that we
use for our system uh they are efficient
for sampling high energy barriers this
is particularly the case uh because we
are we using Umbrella sampling and
restraining our simulation even to high
barriers and our approach uh scales
efficiently because both string method
and bias exchange umbrella sampling are
loely coupled multicopy
approaches and finally they are suit
this approach is suitable for larger
scale confirmational trans and the
reason behind that is we have tested on
several different system there are many
many different methods uh available
currently and they are they work
perfectly fine on to models but when you
apply them to real model you will see
that they do not work uh here we have
test arm uh approach or sampling
approach on three different system the
top ones are the one that we already
have some result or uh already published
or uh the one that um
are um in know a good uh stage and the
bottom ones are the the one that we we
are currently working
on hello back uh for seminar part one uh
which is going to be talking about uh
applying the approach that we introduced
in the primer to uh a transporter called
na um Na
is uh well is a metabolite transporter
specifically transporter of citrate um
and it was first uh became interesting
for the most part to researchers uh in
2000 when experiments on a related
transporter in
flies um well the researchers performed
experiments where they mutated uh this
trans the gene that encodes this
transporter to make the transporter
function less efficiently and when they
did that the mutant
organisms uh were shown to uh live
longer than the wild type uh
organisms um following that follow on
experiments uh on the na transporter
within mice showed that knocking out uh
Na and mice causes the uh mice to store
less body fat and also become less
resistant to
insulin and so since these experiments
were performed na has been uh thought to
be a potential drug Target for treatment
of obesity and type two
diabetes um Na operates through the
elevator What's called the elevator
transport mechanism uh in the this
mechanism transport is achieved when a
transport domain shown in blue rotates
and translates relative to a stationary
scaffold domain in order to change
accessibility of uh the substrate from
one side of the membrane to the
other
um uh this protein is called a homodimer
so it's composed of two uh subunits to
completely independent proteins actually
that form oblate diers um
um yeah uh so there's been a
longterm uh collaboration between the
Tash corid labs and uh the Wong lab uh
that works on these uh this family of
Transporters
uh within uh our lab focuses on running
MD simulations uh and then the Wong lab
focuses on uh doing structural biology
so solving structur of these related
sets of
Transporters uh both using X-ray
crystallography and cryoelectron
microscopy uh they solved the first uh
structure of Na in 20 2021 in an bound
inward facing State and uh more recently
they came to us and said that they had
additionally solved new structures uh
which are currently unpublished um of an
APO inward facing stage so so completely
Unbound inward basing State and also uh
an APO outward basing State and so with
this set of structures we're now primed
to apply the uh approach that we
introduced in the primer uh to look at
this APO transition in N
act um so I'm going to rest of my part
of the seminar uh I'm going to talk
about the application of each of these
steps to
na um
this is an active project it's a work in
progress I have not uh gotten through
all these steps yet and so what I want
to do is talk about some of the
considerations that I've went through
when I in the application of these uh
each of these steps to sort of give you
a flavor of what it's like to actually
apply this uh technique to uh in the
real world to an actual
project so with that start with the
first
step um first step as I said before is
choosing uh transition to study and
having structures available for that
that transition of interest uh we have
these
highresolution uh structures of the
inward facing outward facing state so
that um makes it a prime candidate for
uh for study and application of that
approach um you'll notice that in this
schematic both I have BR both transport
domains in uh symmetrical inward facing
or outward facing States um but this
structure is in a mixed state uh there's
a large uh body of evidence um that from
multiple different kinds of experiments
performed on multiple different
Transporters that
um uh indicates that elevator
Transporters like
na uh the individual transport domains
within the transporter operate
completely independently of one another
um and additional experiments have
indicated that the transitions uh for na
happen uh quickly and then the or
relatively quickly and then the uh
transporter
um dwells in individual if or o States
for a far greater amount of time what
this means is that uh a transition of a
single transport domain is more common
to happen in nature than both of them
exactly at the same time um and for this
reason I decided to uh only induce the
transition look at the transport uh in
in one protomer at a
time okay next step is defining
Collective variables running driven MD
simulations
um in past work which has been published
a collaborative work with the Wong lab
um I had established a biasing protocol
for uh Rel ated bacterial um
transporter um and so this was
immediately generalizable to
na uh so did that generalization applied
the biasing protocol this was the result
resulting um MD simulation that I
obtained uh within this biasing protocol
I have two Collective variables uh the
transport domain rotates um about um a
particular defined axis uh and then it
also a transition is
vises are added to induce a change in
the position of the center of mass of
the transport domain relative to the
scaffold
domain um within this uh uh this driven
MD simulation there were some things
that I saw as I looked at the simulation
and analyzed it further uh that I didn't
think
were
ideal
um these Transporters are thought
to uh have the transport domain move as
a rigid body relative to the scaffold
domain this is supported by the actual
cryoem structures of the O and if States
for
na um structural superposition is shown
here uh in our field we use uh a metric
called root mean Square displacement or
rmsd uh to measure overall structural
similarity the formula for this is shown
here it's root mean Square displacement
of um Atomic coordinates within a uh
selection of atoms relative to a
reference set of atomic coordinates um
so aristy is low for the pair of cryoem
structures within the initial protocol
that I used uh you can see visually
structural uh similarity is not looking
so good higher armist value and so this
was straight forward to correct uh what
I had to do is add arsd uh restraints to
the arms
um both internally within the transport
domain and also within the scaffold
domain um by adding those restraints was
able to get at the end of the
transition um transport domain that uh
matched what I was hoping it would look
like the second issue that I saw was
that um both the position and
orientation of the transport domain at
the end of the uh transition was not
matching what it was supposed to the
ideal cryoem Target that I was looking
for this was confusing to me for a while
because this is what my Collective
variables were specifically designed to
do um I thought about it for a few days
and uh eventually figured out that while
I'm inducing a rotation specifically
about this rotation axis and a
displacement specifically along this
displacement access axis um I wasn't
restraining
um sort of wobbling of the transport
domain around other uh axes of rotation
wasn't preventing um drift of the
transport domain well um sort of around
laterally around this uh this placement
axis um and so I had to change the
collective variables I was using um so
that these uh off- pathway uh movements
would not happen anymore uh when I did
that uh the result of the protocol ended
up getting a final state that matches
the desired crym or outward facing
structure okay so I did these
refinements applied The Driven ND
simulation uh this is a result of what
this looks like this is a direct drive
from the inward facing state to the
outward facing
State um direct drive within the
collective variable space um this this
is the point of the uh method where
ordinarily I would start looking for
testing other uh Pathways throughout the
collective variable space try and find
um more What U might be the most optimal
pathway through the space but my
particular excuse me circumstances um
allowed me to sort of approach this a
little bit
differently um so as ashon mentioned in
the
primer um there's a new uh meth mode
within computation mode within namdi
that allows most computation to happen
on uh a GPU um previously uh
namdi most of the computation would
happen on the CPU GPU was only used as a
co-processor um so these computations on
the GPU are inherently faster um then
Additionally the recent uh
Improvement in uh GPU performance has
also increased uh sampling quite a bit
um and so what this means is that uh
with the same Hardware that we've had uh
all along we can now get a lot more
sampling with nami uh at the same time
uh the Taj cored lab was awarded a large
uh allocation on Summit uh which is
housed at Oakridge National Lab it's one
of the largest supercomputers in the
world um um and so this improved
sampling by namdi combined with a large
allocation means that string method
simulations umbrella sampling
simulations which historically have been
really expensive uh from the perspective
of uh standard MD simulation uh
practitioners uh they're actually really
cheap in the context of this uh large
allocation and so what I decided to do
was to run a string method simulation
from this initial uh direct drive
Pathway to see what would come out of
that and try and use that to inform uh
how I was going to try and explore uh
the collective variable
space um so uh the within the driven MD
simulations I had two Collective
variables um but the uh position and
orientation of two rigid bodies relative
to one another like the transport domain
relative to the scaffold domain uh is
inherently six dimensional there's three
rotational degrees of freedom three uh
positional degrees of freedom um and I
wanted within the string method to be
able to account for all six of these
degrees of freedom um so I set it up in
that way uh when you're setting up a
string Methods uh simulation you also
have to choose um certain parameters
um for a couple of them I uh selected
parameters based on uh other simulations
similar simulations that have been
performed in the literature um but uh
this is as you recall is an iterative
approach um and
so uh I decided to increase the amount
of time spent in each duration uh
compared to what's been done in the past
this is newly possible because of the
increased sampling time within DD um and
it also has benefits
algorithmically uh longer uh iteration
times has been shown to up to a
increasing uh these iteration times up
to a point has been shown to uh speed up
uh iteration of the algor or uh
convergence of the algorithm um it also
reduces the amount of communication
between individual replicas which allows
the algorithm to run more efficiently on
the supercomputer and also reduces the
amount of uh data that you need to store
um from the
simulation so these are the results so
far of the string uh simulation applied
to the direct drive um from the inward
facing state to the outward facing State
uh you can see the evolution of the
pathway in all six of the degrees of
freedom that I talked about
previously
um interestingly uh there are three
degrees of freedom where I you could see
that there was a large change from the
inward facing state to the outward
facing State uh the other three the uh
start and end states are pretty similar
um but interestingly you see that there
are large uh features um that are uh
relaxation features that are uh
happening in these uh degrees of freedom
um which is saying that all six of these
degrees of freedom seem to be important
for uh this particular transporter um
and you can see how these six degrees of
freedom work together uh within the
simulation um over in this movie over
here it's showing the transport domain
sort of behind the scaffold domain so
you're looking through the scaffold
domain and uh it's coming together in a
complex
uh um
transition
um I haven't analyzed this simulation
fully because it hasn't converged uh yet
uh you can look at convergence by
looking at uh the evolution of the
centers of the Swarms as a function of
iteration um so these plots over here
are showing uh the evolution of the
Swarm uh near this dip here this plot
and the same point uh in this degree of
Freedom it's continuously moving down
continuously moving up uh we want to see
for convers we want to see for all these
swarm centers uh stable values that are
remain the same for several
iterations um so that's still running
but it did what I wanted to tell me
something about um how I wanted to
explore the uh uh Collective variable
space with driven MD
simulations uh what I ended up deciding
to do was to induce a series of uh
transitions along circular arcs um
between the inward facing and outward
facing State uh within this original two
uh
two-dimensional um with these original
two Collective variables so this is
forming a two-dimensional dis within the
uh six-dimensional space um what you're
seeing in this plot are uh data points
along these driven uh from these driven
MD simulations along uh these Target
Pathways represented by the dashed lines
um you see that the simulations are
overlapping with one another so um
they're sampling quite a bit of this
space these simulations are also
currently running on Summit um you see
sort of at the ends here along these
longest Pathways uh there's not sampling
here because these simulations just
haven't finished yet um so but in the
meantime while we're waiting for them to
finish we can look at the work profiles
uh like I talked about in the primer to
see which different what it says about
which Pathways may be more or less
optimal uh relative to one another um
this is breaking up those work profiles
into equally spaced segments and they uh
the values of uh the amount of work that
increases or decreases uh within each
segment segment is represented by uh the
colors the plot and so what this is
saying is that it looks like uh inducing
translation uh before any kind of
rotation of the transport domain
relative to the scaffold domain uh
that's disfavored there's higher values
of work over in these
parts um of the uh driven MD simulations
similarly if you do all most of your
rotation first followed by translation
that also seems to be
disfavored um and so actually starting
from this direct drive from the inward
facing to outward facing state is
looking like a reasonable um starting
place for uh refinement with the string
method was forms of trajectories um the
relaxed
pathway uh from that uh direct drive
from the string method applied to that
direct drive is uh overlaid with these
white and red dots on Top This is a
projection from the six dimensional path
taken uh with by this relaxed pathway
back onto that this two-dimensional disc
and then the colors are representing the
uh distance um that that uh relaxed
pathway relaxed away from that dis uh in
units of uh the length of these
individual segments that are that each
have a different color with plot and so
this is saying that uh the distance that
the pathway is relaxing away from this
dis is pretty far um and it calls into
question just how relevant
uh these work profiles actually are for
what uh a natural pathway for what the
optimal natural pathway might actually
be um so this is as far as I've gotten
right now uh my plan going forward is to
relax more of these Pathways using the
string method with forms of trajectories
uh maybe all of the pathways
um and then continue on with uh the the
application of the approach so running
uh driven additional driven MD
simulations eventually running umbrella
sampling simulations getting work uh
free energy profiles and then connecting
this back to the original structure of
the protein to understand what the
connection is between structural
Dynamics and function of n
act um also interested in looking
at this transition under different
conditions so this is uh the APO
transition nothing is bound be
interesting to see how binding of
substrate and ions affects this uh
there's also a published structure with
a drug-like inhibitor bound um it'd be
interesting to look at how that affects
the transition as
well and so with that I'd like to
acknowledge my adviser and M tou kid uh
my collaborators Donnie Wong and Yan Lee
and all the members of the nah resource
for macromolecular modeling and
visualization um both pass and present
uh special thanks to mahm moradi who
taught me this approach and he was still
postto in mods lab acknow I'd like to
acknowledge funding and uh Computing
resources that allowed me to complete
this work and with that I will toss it
over to ashcon for second half of the
seminar my turn for um the seminar
part
uh here I brought two examples uh
similar to what Noah mentioned they have
a little bit different stories I thought
that they are useful one of them is a
glutamate transporter for this one uh we
did a 2d two-dimensional free energy
calculations um the other one glycerol 3
fosfate transporter this one um we use
this model for calculating the kinetic
the uh very last part of our strategy in
my previous section that I discussed we
tested on this
model uh let's start with the first one
gluto
transporter um glut toate Transporters
let's talk a little bit about the uh
importance of this model are the
glutamate Transporters or excitatory
amino acid Transporters are responsible
to transport
glutamate uh an important
neurotransmitter in our neural cell
their disregulation cause different
diseases such as Parkinson Alzheimer and
depression uh glutamate Transporters are
secondary active Transporters they
transport glutamate and or aspartate
with three sodium ions the pottassium
inside the cell they take one uh sorry
one proton inside the cell and uh one
potassium outside the cell at the same
time they work as a coloroid
Chanel uh I'm currently working on this
type of system the ones that are known
as eats but for today I want to focus on
the Aral homologue of the system gltph
gltph is a little bit simpler than and
eats the glutamate Transporters actual
glutamate Transporters it just transport
glutamate and
aspartate uh with three sodium ions
doesn't need proton or
potassium uh the this is the structure
of gluto Transport there it's a
tri has three protom three units that
are kind of similar uh these Brown parts
and the green part the green part is
known as a scaffold domain it doesn't
move a lot uh the brown part is the
transport domain that is moving trans
transporting the substrates and
ions it has been uh the uh crystalize in
three different form outward facing
inward facing and intermediate
State uh the transport mechanism in this
type of Transporter is sort of like
elevator it is known as elevator like
alternating access uh mechanism it's
like uh ions and substrates get into
this BR part the transport domain
transport domain moves translate moves a
little bit down and rotate and then ions
and substrate leave the transport
there this is sort of a complex picture
our strategies is to break down this
kind of complex movement to different
pieces can consider a cycle like this
it's like ions in um substrates get into
into the transporter these are uh
helical her pin that sort of acting like
a gate and then the transporter gets
full fully bound and then we have the
translation confirmational change and
releasing the ions and substrate
uh we focus on the vertical part of this
cycle uh from outward facing empty or
aole to inward facing
aole uh in other cases when we have one
ion we wanted to know if uh this
transition is possible or the uh
transporter has to go through a cycle
like this and the third scenario is when
we have the full
one uh there are other scenarios here as
well that let's say we have two ions or
we have substrate with ions as well but
uh for this case we just focus on these
three conditions this one this one this
one we start with equilibrium simulation
we put our system in a explicit membrane
environment uh try to see if we see
anything interesting generally
equilibrium simulation just provide us
with some uh local changes it does not
give us the actual information about the
transport itself for
instance uh we know that if we're on
equilibrium simulation one of the ions
is done the stable inside get released
then this Gates this gate it opens and
then soft releases as
well this equilibrium run uh was
interesting provide us some information
but not too much information about the
transport itself so uh we went through
our procedure to study the largest
Square larg scale uh confirmational
transission uh to go from this outward
facing inward facing we consider uh two
sets of collective Val one of them was
related to the distance of these uh
transport
domain going from up here to down move
translating a little bit and then
another one is angle uh for rotation and
uh similar to Noah's case for rotation
we use uh coion Collective
variables uh for the quion uh we
consider the quion that are unit um
coion have four components um since they
are unit three of them are independent
three degrees of freedom there plus one
degrees one degree for this one four for
each unit time 3 12 degrees of freedom
so our Collective variable space is 12
degrees of freedom has uh is a has 12
degrees of comparing outward facing with
inward facing we noted that uh we need
12 degrees 12 angr translation and 32
Dees
orientation having these Collective
variables we induce the
transition uh with d MD and this
animation shows this translation we were
able to do this
translation uh now this slide shows the
whole procedure of our
sampling um this is sort of Step by Step
uh on sble base uh enhan sampling
strategy the story starts here uh
outward facing inward facing with a
targeted MD or steered MD we ran six set
of simulation with different Force
conent to induce a transition noted that
for all of them the amount of work that
they generate is pretty high so we
decided to sample the whole confirmation
on the space in terms of those two
Collective variables the translation and
orientation uh this provided us with a
2d free energy that I'm going to show in
the next slide but here i' like to pay
your attention to the number of replica
number of simulations copy of
simulations that we are
doing um after doing the 2d3 energy we
went to uh calculate the path from going
to outward facing to inward
facing
uh we generate a path uh based on the
information that we had from bias
exchange umbrella sampling the 2D bias
exchange umbrella sampling an initial
path with a method called post uh post
hawkk string method it is just having
the information from the
translation and generating an initial
path for us then having that initial
path we use a string
method to refine that pass e stage
everything up to here was related to one
of our cases the very first one the
fully bound one this is probably similar
to the question you mentioned um
Somaya that sometimes we have different
conditions for our system having the
initial uh or a refined path for one of
them we use that path for the other
cases the AIL one and uh the the other
case that we had one only single ion The
partially bound
one having all of these passes these
three passes we calculated free energy
along each one of these paths and uh we
got the free energy from
that the total aggregated simulation
time for this the whole procedure was
0.1 millisecond which is as far as I
know in terms of uh memory transporter
is probably the largest amount of
simulation uh here uh I mentioned in
this part was a little bit complex we
did a 2d I want to now focus on this
part the 2D free energy
calculation this is translation and this
one is orientation the outward facing is
here this is is my inward
facing as I mentioned we started with uh
six different of six different set of
simulation from going here to here let's
say different path from here to here
from this path and the other path would
be this one all of this generated very
large amount of work so we decided to
branch of new simulation from these and
Sample the old space here this made for
us a two 32 by 32 gr Point space this
step we repeat this step to make our uh
samples prepare our sample and cover the
whole
Space having these uh samples initial
samples to cover the whole space with
did a 2d bi exchange umbrella
sampling uh and this is the free energy
for that uh case the outward facing is
somewhere here the inward facing is
here we can see that the outward facing
has a minimum but the inward facing is
basically is missing its minimum so we
repeat this stage one more
time and made our um points closer to
each other made a our sampling refiner
did another set of fire Exchange
umbrella samply end up with this um map
that is showing the inward facing here
and outward facing here and you can see
that seems our system is going from sort
of this path the green one is the
initial pass that we generated with post
HW shring method and running uh actual
simulation string method with swarms of
trajectory with up with this
um uh black one and as I mentioned this
was just for uh fully bound the
condition that uh we have the ions and
substrate everything all
together we repeated the simulation for
the apole in uh the the one that only
has one ions one ion and uh did the free
energy calculation along these path and
these are the maps for the free energy
for each one of those cases let's focus
on uh the first one this says for the
fully bound one outward facing inward
facing is here now we have some minimum
for inward facing there's some sort of
intermediate State here uh the scenario
for AO one is sort of similar to fully
bound
one uh a little bit different moved a
little little bit for right but the
interesting thing is here the partially
bound one uh this is the outward facing
inward facing is missing it seems the
transporter doesn't want to transport
one single iron it doesn't want to waste
the cycle for just transporting one
ion and this is the uh GRE energy uh
projected in One D here it's the outward
facing inward facing is here the fully
bound one our transporter is taking a
path going through these barriers in our
free energy and then going back in APO
form empty from sort of a separate pass
having this barrier this two different
barrier it is clear that or it's a sign
that um our transporting is taking two
different paths and we find an
intermediate State correspond to this
one that we think is important
particularly that the uh experimentally
we cannot we we do not have this
state having the free energy and the
path to go from outward facing the to
inward
facing uh we uh characterize that path
and and try to find the interesting
things some of the interesting things
here are for instance we noted that
going from outward facing to inward
facing this scaffold domain is sort of
moving like a pistone
um sorry I don't know uh why this movie
is not showing and
the uh scaffold domain is sort of
getting uh dis this engage from the
transport domain and the salt bridge is
breaking during this
transport now I want to talk about the
second example the glycerol three
phosphate transporter
glpt this is a transporter from a
bacteria and transport phosphates
transport and uh organic phosphate with
in organic
phosphate uh and in absence of that
organic phosphate is just exchanged to
inorganic phosphate this structure was
only crystallized in out inward
facing and the transport mechanism for
this was a little bit different from the
previous one like a rocker Su it's like
it's
taking one uh it's anti porting uh the
the organic phosphate with the inorganic
phosphate again uh breaking down this
one to Pieces we study this cycle indeed
this structure was previously study in
our group um with Dr moradi when he was
a postart and uh he uh found that by
pulling this two domain of the
transporter he can induce a
transition um
uh and then uh this is the free energy
landscape for this one going from inward
facing to outward facing when it's April
the pass it seems to be having some
barrier it's difficult to pass through
these barriers here but for the case
when we have only
um uh the trans uh we have the phosphate
in it barrier is kind of lower and the
pass is uh kind of easier for uh the
transporter for this case uh having this
we wanted to test our new
strategy calculating the kinetic and
thermodynamic with the method that I
mentioned uh through uh studying a tube
of pass instead of a single pass for
this part for this one we focus only on
translation from going to from here
outward facing to this inward facing
which would
be correspond to these points in our
free
energy we having the images from or uh
structures from that pth we run
equilibrium
simulations um for 40 different images
between different copies for each one of
them count the number of transition
between different images for a
particular La time and build a
transition Matrix having that transition
Matrix we build our rate Matrix and
having that rate Matrix we calculated
the free energy and the fusion and here
in this slide I'm comparing these two
methods the green one is the one that
uh we got it from our new method
calculation along the path unbiased
equilibrium simulation along the pass
and the green one is the one from enhan
sampling the bias
one the interesting thing is that both
meals are providing a similar for energy
uh profile like one of them is just a
scale of the other ones just going a
little bit down the minimum are the same
place
uh only the barriers are different and
these are the structure corresponding to
those
um interesting or difficult part here is
to um have the right uh lack time the
time that we save our information and
the radius for the distance of our
images how we measure that a particular
structure is corresponding to which
image
these are the
um different life time and rce of uh our
images the distance from uh our images
and showing that they all are providing
similar result but with a different
barriers
um if we make our
um radius very small like we end up with
a single pass the one that we already
had for um bias exchange umbrella samply
if we make our pass or our tube the
radius of our tube pretty large gets
very far and our data gets very noisy
and our approximation are even
wrong and this is the yellow one is for
the case that it's um the LA time um and
the radius is very large and other one
is for the other case and they are
smaller one parameter here is time the
other parameter is distance we need to
play with both of these uh the
experimental activation energy uh for
this case was 8.4 the one that we got
from bias exchange umbrella sampling the
method that uh we usually take was
giving us
9.6 our newer method is giving us
only
s and the experimental value seems to be
somewhere near there so we need to
improve our methods a little bit to get
closer to
that uh but the thing that is
interesting here is the transition rate
the time that it takes to go from this
state to this state on
average uh this time depends on La time
but the value that we converge is
59.2 uh which is seven times larger than
the experimental value uh this one is
only for transporting the inorganic
phosphate the experimental one is for
the organic phosphate but they are at
least in order of magnitude similar to
each other we still need to work on this
and improve
it and uh finally this is my
acknowledgement page um this is my
supervisor similar to what Noah showed
and this is Dr Madi uh I'm currently
working with Dr moradi in his lab
collaborating with him and this is a
picture of our group I'm not there and
uh these are the source of uh phone that
I'm using to do my calculations