so today we are going to learn about
electrostatic shielding and why it's not
such a bad thing if you're in a
lightning storm as long as you're inside
a car here we have Benjamin Franklin and
he is about to be in a thunderstorm look
at what's happening to Benjamin as the
lightning bolt hits the grounding rod
Benjamin is not happy so now what we're
going to do is we are going to have the
same thunderstorm but we are going to
put Benjamin in a faraday cage same
tinsel skirt that he had before but this
time he is in a cage let's turn on the
lightning now if you look you can see
that there's that lightning bolt going
from the vandag graph right to the cage
here but now look inside at Benjamin in
there and his tinsil is completely
motionless I just got shocked but
Benjamin is completely safe this is the
phenomenon of electrostatic shielding
and this kind of a cage is often called
a Thad cage for more MIT moments from
MIT open learning like subscribe or
follow