so today our keynote speaker is Tom
fredman uh have a story Tom doesn't know
uh I first heard him speak uh at a
graduation ceremony his daugh I think it
was his daughter and my son were
classmates uh and it was the graduation
ceremony at Yale and I recall him giving
this the graduation speech and
it was truly a tour to force of both
deep insight and personal commentary
about their Futures and it occurred to
me then my Universal answer to the
question when you were in a meeting and
you were planning an event now who
should we get to come speak it made it
real simple I just kept saying Thomas
fredman and uh and I continued to do
that for several years in a row uh and
guess what we finally got it to work uh
so it's my honor to introduce Tom Frey
who actually needs very little in the
way of introduction but uh being polite
I will give you some of the highlights
of what's an extraordinary career um he
is one of The keenest Observers and
commentators on the issues around
globalization he's a world-renowned
author and a journalist his foreign
affairs column which appears twice
weekly in the New York Times is
syndicated in over 700 newspapers around
the world he's one that pullit surpriz
three times and he's the author of
several books the most recent book is
the World is Flat through 3.0 a brief
history of the 21st century with that
I'll turn the Podi over please join me
in welcoming Tom
Freeman thanks so
much thank
you well it's a it's a treat uh to be
back here I feel a certain proprietary
interest in the open course whereare as
an and Chuck vesto I was wasn't here
quite at the creation but uh shortly
after they uh got me to come up and
Susan I think you were just starting
then and um so we were all kind of
present at the creation and I gave one
of the very first lectures I ever gave
about the World is Flat and they put it
up on the open courseware site and it
still sits there today I think it's been
downloaded 70,000 times or something
like that and um I now use it when
people want me to speak and I just can't
and some people you know um from far off
places I can't get to I just say go to
open courseware download it it's yours
for free
and um uh it's been a great vehicle for
me so it's a it's really a treat to be
back here soon thank you for having me
um what I thought I would do as Steve
said I've gota I got to update my site
my open courseware site so that's really
why I came you know um and uh we're
filming this and so um uh what I thought
I'd do is share with you um what is now
the 3.0 edition of The World is Flat
gone through a couple more iterations um
my kind of latest thinking on that
subject um I know some of you have read
the book those of you who haven't I know
who you are uh know where you teach
where you go to school um and uh so
there'll be a little you know repetition
to just sort of start from ground zero
and then try to take it forward and then
uh uh I'd like to just spend a few
minutes talking about my new book which
will be out in August uh called Green is
the new red white and blue um which is
about en energy environment because the
two books are actually uh very much
connected I I I hope it'll come together
every time I try to do this I'm always
reminded of this story when they were
digging the Chunnel under the English
Channel you know connecting Britain and
and Europe they uh they put it out for
bids and they got bids of $3 billion
from Beckel and 3.1 from halberton all
these big industrial engineering firms
got one bid from Goldberg and Cohen firm
on the upper east end of London for
100,000 pound and for fiduciary reasons
they had to check it out so they sent A
team out to Goldberg and con knocked on
the door con answered Goldberg was on
the road and they said um Mr Mr Cohen
how can you possibly dig a Chunnel under
the English Channel for £100,000 he said
what's the problem uh Goldberg will
start on one side a cone will start on
the other we'll each have a shovel we'll
dig until we
meet and he said what if you don't meet
so you'll have two tunnels so so maybe
you'll have one lecture one maybe you
have two I don't know I I I I hope
they'll meet it's all at for the same
price
um the the first thing you really need
to know about the World is Flat is that
uh this book came about completely by
accident I wish I could tell you I was
as smart as a MIT Professor this was all
cooking in my head I unveiled it to the
world it was all an accident um I became
the New York Times Foreign Affairs
columnist in January 1995 I um spent uh
basically from January 1995 until
September 11th 2001 my column really
oscillated between what I call Lexus
issues and Olive Tree issues issues of
Finance technology trade and issues of
traditional geopolitics and ethnic
conflict and I was really going between
Silicon Valley and the Becka Valley um
in light of what happened on September
11th I really dropped the globalization
side of my column which had really been
a abiding interest and spent the next
three years almost exclusively in the
Arab Muslim world trying to understand
the roots of 9/11 I was really in that
mode right up until January of 2004 when
I started doing documentaries for the
Discovery Channel we had done one on the
roots of 911 we had done one on the wall
Israel had built in the West Bank and in
January of 2004 we were sitting around
with our Discovery team trying to figure
out what what should we do our next
documentary on and at the time the big
issue out there the obvious issue to
take on was why does everyone hate
America and that's how this all got
started because I had this crazy idea
that what we should do is go to call
centers all over the world and interview
young people foreigners who spend their
days imitating Americans on what they
think of
America that's how the whole thing
started and right in the middle of our
budgeting meetings while we were trying
to figure out which call center centers
to go to John krey came out with his
blast against Benedict Arnold CEOs who
engage in
Outsourcing and suddenly this issue of
Outsourcing just exploded onto the world
stage the front page of the New York
Times The Wall Street Journal Forbes and
Fortune I said wait a minute time out
why why why don't we just go to bangal
or India and let's do a documentary
called the other side of Outsourcing
where we try to explain this phenomena
from the ground up that's how it started
so we went off to Bangalore on February
15th 20 4 with our Discovery crew we
shot about 60 hours of film in in in 11
days and across those 11 days I got
progressively sicker and sicker uh it
was nothing I ate it was somewhere
between the Indian entrepreneur who
wanted to prepare my Maryland tax
returns from Bangalore and the Indian
entrepreneur who wanted to write my new
software from Bangalore and the Indian
entrepreneur who wanted to read my
x-rays from Bangalore and the Indian
entrepreneur who wanted to trace my lost
luggage on Delta lines from Bangalore
that I got this really sick feeling that
while I had been sleeping while I had
been off covering the 911 Wars something
really big transformative and
fundamental had happened in the
globalization world and I had completely
missed it and it all came together with
the last interview we did which with
Nandan liani the CEO of nasis one of the
crown jewels of uh India's high-tech
firmament n was an old friend we were
sitting on the couch outside his office
I had my laptop top in my lap he's
putting up a little plaque there now
where where where where the world's flat
was born and
um Nan said at one point Tom I've got to
tell you the the global economic playing
field is being leveled the global
economic playing field is being leveled
and you Americans are not
ready oh I wrote that down on my little
laptop the global economic playing field
is being leveled and you Americans are
not ready well after the uh interview um
I got in my Jeep went back to my hotel
and along the way I kept rolling over in
my mind as is my habit what nand said
the global economic playing field is
being
leveled and after a while it occurred to
me that what he was really saying was
that the global economic playing field
is being
flattened and then in the crazy chemical
way these things happen it just popped
into my head that wand dakani India's
Premier engineer entrepreneur was really
telling me was that the world is flat
and I wrote that down in my my notebook
The World is Flat I got back to my hotel
I ran up to my room I called my wife and
Bethesda I said honey I am going to
write a book called The World is
Flat she now says she thought that was a
brilliant
idea it's not how I remember the
conversation but Men Are from Mars Women
Are from Venus um uh but in any event I
did come home and basically call my
owners of the New York Times and say
ladies and gentlemen I need to go on
sabatical immediately I need to go on
sabatical media because my software the
intellectual framework through which I
look at the world is out of date I'm a
I'm a basic engineer and it's a Java
world and if I don't go on leave
immediately and update my
software I am going to write something
really stupid in the New York
Times it's a great way to get a leave I
I have to tell
you so I started this book in March of
2004 I turned it in in December do not
try this this trick at home kids um I
blew out my forearms along the way but
in a fit of energy and passion uh
produced kind of the core thesis of this
book and the core thesis sort of the
meta argument of this book is very
simple The Meta argument is that there
have been three what I would call three
Great era of globalization uh the first
I call globalization 1.0 it began in
1492 and lasted until the early 1800s
with the beginning of global Arbitrage
that year of globalization Shrunk The
World from a size large to a size medium
and that year of globalization was
really spearheaded by countries
globalizing that is you went Global
through your country nation states were
the dynamic agent of globalization so it
was Spain exploring the Americas Britain
colonizing India Portugal East Asia you
went Global through your country
globalization 2.0 began in the early
1800s lasted till the year 2000 that's
right it just ended it Shrunk The World
from size medium to size small and that
year of globalization was really
spearheaded by companies companies going
global for markets and for labor you
went Global through your company well
while you were sleeping or at least
while I was sleeping we actually entered
globalization 3.0 from the year 2000 to
the present it shrieking in the world
from size small to size tiny and
flattening the global economic playing
field at the same time only what's
really new really different really
exciting and really terrifying is that
this year of globalization is certainly
not spearheaded by countries and it's
not exclusively spearheaded by companies
anymore what's really new really
different really exciting is that this
era of globalization is spearheaded by
individuals we've gone from a
globalization built around countries to
one built around companies to one built
around
individuals how did we get here how did
we move down this progression to a point
where individuals can now compete
connect and collaborate globally as
individuals well we had to create a
platform really for that to happen I'm
not going to talk about the whole
platform what I call the 10 flatteners
but I'm going to talk about four the
four key ones basically that are
relevant both to open courseware and I
think to where we are today um basically
the first of these four key flatteners
was I'm going to do this really quickly
the PC and what the personal computer
allowed and this is really the beginning
of the whole individual nature of
globalization what the PC allowed was
for individuals
individuals to author their own content
in digital form it's great to be able to
talk about this at MIT where I don't
have to explain what those things mean
um uh what the PC allowed was for the
first time in the history of the world
for individuals to author their own
content in digital form now individuals
have authored their own content ever
since cave women and cave men etched on
Cave walls but with a PC individuals
could author their own content words
photo data spreadsheets video music in
the form of bits and bites in digital
form and once your content was created
in digital form it could be manipulated
in so many more ways by individuals and
dispatched so many more places that was
the first basic flattener second
flattener some of these are Technologies
others are dates second flattener is a
date 8995 August 9th 1995 which I
consider to be possibly the most
important day in your lifetime
um certainly in our kids' lifetime up to
now because on 8995 a small startup
company in Mountain View California
called Netscape went public and the
world has never been the same since
Netscape gave us two two basic
flatteners that changed the world the
first was netscape's invention this
simple pointand click device called a
browser and what the browser did
was actually give us a tool that brought
the internet to life it was really the
Netscape browser that brought the
internet to life because it allowed us
to illustrate on computer screens
everything locked away in Internet files
and thanks to Tim burners Lee soon to be
websites it was actually the Netscape
browser that made the internet this
incredible tool of connectivity that
Grandma and Grandpa grandson and
granddaughter not just MIT computer
scientists could all use together so
it's really the Netscape browser that
brought the internet to life but that
wasn't the only reason Netscape was a
huge flattener it's because netscape's
IPO Netscape going public on the morning
of 8995 at 9:00 a.m. is what actually
started the.com boom and that triggered
the dot bubble and that triggered the
crazy absurd ridiculous utterly
outrageous overinvestment of $1 trillion
dollar that's trillion with
T into fiber optic cable in five years
and what that crazy ridiculous absurd
massive overinvestment into fiber optic
cable in five years did was accidentally
wire the world with nobody having
planned it so all those individuals
authoring their own content in digital
form could suddenly send their bits and
bites anywhere in the world basically
for free
it was that fiber optic explosion that
accidentally with nobody having planned
it made Beijing Bangalore and Boston all
nextd door neighbors how did it happen
well on the morning of 8995 Netscape
went public priced at
$28 their investment bankers Morgan
Stanley wanted the stock to be priced at
32 but Jim barkdale the Netscape CEO at
the time said no no no if this fails I
want it to be remembered as a $20 stock
Netscape opened that morning at $71
closed the first day at 56 and we all
looked at that and we said Woo there is
gold over them their Hills and we went
out and we we bought every.com that boom
that moved yeah we we bought every doc
that moved called Global Crossing and
Nexel and JDS uniface oh you can't fool
me I know it's in your 401ks I was born
at night it wasn't last night um and
when we did we accidentally funded the
massive over wirring of the world with
fiber optic cable so every individual
authoring content on their PC could
suddenly send their digital content
anywhere for free third key flattener
was a quiet Revolution it was a
revolution in transmission protocols
happened across the 199s it was the
alphabet soup of tcpip and HTML and HTTP
and XML and soap and HX you don't need
to know even though most people here do
what all that alphabet soup meant it
just meant one key thing for the
flattening of the world critical to to
this phenomena it meant everyone's
computer and software became
interoperable we forget today what a
revolution that was we forget today what
it was like when mit's Administration
first got computers and the bookkeeping
Department got rid of the Abacus and
adding machine they had down there and
got a computer and admissions got
computers a very exciting day around
here at MIT when that happened there
there was just one problem though
bookkeeping got sap and administration
got uh windows and uh they didn't
connect they didn't connect any more
than you were on your comp you serve
could connect with your wife on
AOL well what happened thanks to all
those transmission protocols is that we
made everyone's computer and software
interoperable it was a quiet Revolution
I call it the workflow Revolution
because it truly allowed work to flow
and when that happened when you could
suddenly sit at your computer terminal
or someone in India and not have to
think for a moment what is the computer
and software that open courseware is
running on and what computer and
software do I have what it meant was we
could all suddenly become
collaborators so put it all together
first I could author my own content in
digital form then I could send it
anywhere in the world for free and then
thanks to the workflow Revolution
suddenly everyone could collaborate with
everyone else on their digital content
what we created right around the year
2000 right around the time of the
Millennium was this crude flat world
platform a global platform for multiple
forms of collaboration suddenly more
people could collaborate with more other
people on more different kinds of things
in more different kinds of ways from
more different places for less money
than ever
before that is built on this platform
now this flat platform then gave rise to
a whole new set of collaborations
Outsourcing offshoring to me the most
interesting one which again is critical
to open courseware I call uploading a
term coined by Kevin Kelly of wired not
uploading in the conventional sense you
see when the world was round you
downloaded as an individual
but when the world is flat individuals
can now upload and globalize their own
content globally uploading comes in many
forms open- Source software is uh the
most was the most early variant and
probably still the most popular open
course software you just uploaded your
University
online uh blogging GE in the old days if
you wanted an opinion on Foreign Affairs
you had to read a fuddy duddy like me
not anymore now I go to Iraqi bloggers
see what they're uploading as
individuals from Baghdad when I want to
know what's going on there YouTube
uploading video and of course the mother
of all uploads
Wikipedia the people are now uploading
their own
encyclopedia now it's not
perfect all you have to do is be a
subject of Wikipedia to know how
imperfect it is okay and anyone who
thinks the network will get it all
straightened out um uh doesn't have
their biography on Wikipedia but never
mind we won't go there
um but the fact is we're going from a
world where when I grew up in
Minneapolis in the 1950s I remember when
the encyclopedia branica salesman came
to our house with all those books he was
so excited put them down in the living
room and then we got the coolest thing
we got incarta and you could download an
encyclopedia I think in carda 2007 had
about 38,000 entries wow Wikipedia today
has about 1.3 mil 840
846 and they'll have 847 real soon so
people aren't downloading their
encyclopedia they're now uploading it so
uploading is an incredibly new form of
creativity that sprung off this
platform now basically what happened
around the year 20
2000 is that all these flatteners
converged as I said and they converged
into a platform that is what I talk
about when I say the World is Flat when
I talk about the World is Flat I don't
mean it's equal I don't mean that
there's no more terms of trade I'm
talking about a platform that allows
individuals more equal ability to Plug
and Play compete connect and collaborate
globally and that's really what open
course
is an incredible manifestation of it's
living on this platform so we've really
gone from a world where value was
created in vertical silos of command and
control to a world where value is being
created horizontally on this platform by
who you connect and collaborate with
we're going from vertical to horizontal
I think that shift which is happening in
a million universities a million
businesses a million governments all
over the world is going to be seen in
time as the mother of all inflection
points we are going to from vertical to
horizontal and it in time is going to
change I believe
everything now there's sort of three
things I'd keep in mind about this new
platform the first is what I call the
iron rule of business on the flat R
platform and the iron rule of business
on the flat world platform is whatever
can be done will be
done when the world is flat
whatever can be done will be done the
only question the only question left is
will it be done by you or to
you just do not think it won't be done
promise me if you have a good idea here
at MIT you will do it because I promise
you someone at IIT Madras will have it a
second later when the world gets this
flat and there are this many distributed
tools of Conn ity and creativity at the
individual level whatever can be done
will be done now I see this everywhere I
go now and I'm not sure economics has
fully been able to capture what is
happening far below the firm level at
the individual level I call it gross
individual product because individuals
on this platform are now doing whatever
can be done my wife and I were in Peru
last year we're on ecotour our guide
Alfredo FAS head of ecotourism in Peru
we're there with conservation
International we're down in Rio tomoa he
says to me one day he knows I like these
stories says Tom I've got a friend I got
to tell he's selling Peruvian dish wear
now from a village near Cusco on the
internet great The World is Flat proen
village then he adds this he's checking
to see if he can get his dishes made
cheaper in China now okay why not if it
can be done it will be done and if he
doesn't do it the Villager in Cusco next
to him will do it whatever can be done
will be done I was out in uh Budapest a
year ago they did a seminar on the World
is Flat all these European scholars
screaming at me it was really
interesting and um uh they gave me a
driver when I got there and and he
stayed with me for three days and he
took me back we're going back Sunday
morning to the airport and on the way
the airport he says Mr Tom Mr Tom I have
to tell you you know if you have any
friends coming to Budapest would you
please tell them about me I do
diplomatic driving tourism Business
Services I said oh that's great you know
sort of blur eyed Sunday morning I said
give me your phone number whatever and
I'll if I ever you know think of anybody
coming he said no no just go to my
website I said no no you you have your
own website I said yeah he gives me his
card soon as I got home I looked it up
it's in three languages magar German and
English all the pictures of his
different services multi-pages
with
music and suddenly I had this vision of
something secretary baker said to me
after he retired as Secretary State he
said how do you know you're out of power
in Washington DC Tom you know you're out
of power in Washington when your
limousine is yellow and your dri speaks
farsy okay um how do you know you're in
a flat world when your Hungarian cab
driver has his own website now in magar
German and English with music
I interview people everywhere I go so
I'm out in South Sous City Nebraska I
don't even remember I think I was
speaking at the University out there guy
picks me up at the airport so I like to
interview people wherever I am hi what
do you do he says well um I used to be
in the chocolate business imported
chocolates so you're from Nebraska but
Brazil could import them into this
country finished chocolates cheaper than
I could make them then we went into the
TAC business you know horses stuff China
came into that business wiped us out
what do you do now he says now what do
we do we import a machine from South
Korea that can be placed at building
sites that produces building sighing and
insulation together I don't know that
much about construction evidently
there's a great efficiency there we
import this machine we add a little IP
here from some folks in South City and
we reexport it to
Kuwait I said you're doing all that from
here yeah I said I said interesting I
mean how do you communicate with the
kuwaitis this is actually in the 3.0
edition of the book this is all I'm not
making this up folks um he says um well
you know we got the winnabago Indians
here in Wago Indian tribes and the
Winnebago Indians have a casino called
Winne Vegas and Winne Vegas spins off an
enormous amount of cash so the Winnebago
Indians from wnne Vegas created the
Winnebago Indian Development Corporation
which created an ad Agency for Winnebago
kids who went out and hired Arabic
speakers from the local University and
they write the brochure so we can import
the machine from South Korea add our IP
here they write the the uh the um uh
directions for it from the Winnebago
Indian Development Corporation and we
reexport it to Kuwait wait you show me
where that shows up in the economic
statistics I'm sure it does somewhere
but that is people doing whatever can be
done and so much of that is happening
today I see it everywhere I go which
leads to me the second rule of the flat
world platform and the second rule for
me is the most important economic
competition going forward in the world
today is I don't believe going to be
between countries and countries although
it's obviously still important it's even
going to be between companies and
companies although obviously still
important I think the most important
economic competition going forward is
going to be between you and your own
imagination because when you have a
world this flat and individuals are this
empowered to act on their own
imagination
globally what individuals imagine really
matters and therefore how well a
university a country a state school
inspires enables and empowers individual
imagination I think will be the single
greatest Competitive Edge in the world
we're going
into the third rule of this platform is
how well you
horizontalization learned this lesson
really right when I was starting to
write the book quite by accident I was
going to visit my daughter who was going
to school in New Haven Connecticut I
live in Bethesda Maryland to get from
Bethesda Maryland to New Haven
Connecticut is a complete pain in the
behind you have to drive almost an hour
to Baltimore Airport take Southwest
Airlines from Baltimore to Hartford
airport then drive one hour from
Hartford to New Haven I could almost go
to London quicker never mind I'm a
Southwest fan don't know many of you
have flown South sou Southwest but you
don't look like a Southwest crowd to me
but that's okay and Southwest Airlines
you know is El Cheapo Airlines you don't
get a reserve seat you just get a ticket
this is a b or c a's board first B's
Board second se's board last only thing
you need to know about Southwest
Airlines is you do not want to be a c on
Southwest Airlines especially if you
have two bags of spring clothing for
your daughter and you don't want to get
stuck in the middle seat no problem I'm
a hip guy did the E ticket thing ahead
of time but just in case I got to BWI
Baltimore Airport 95 minutes before my
flight because I was going to be an a
got to the machine took out my Visa card
stuck it in the southwest e ticket
machine out came my ticket and it said B
and I said Son of a this thing is fixed
this is rigged this is worse than Las
Vegas there is no way I'm a bee I'm here
95 minutes before this flight there is
no way I'm a bee o I was mad got my
Cinnabon and sat in the back of the
beeline
steing well 45 minutes went by and then
they called the flight and then I saw
it all the A's seemed to be getting
getting on caring what looked to me like
just crumpled white home printer
paper as if they had gone online at
12:01 a.m. the night before and
downloaded and printed out their own
barcodes and boarding passes well what I
didn't know back then was what Southwest
Airlines knew was that the world was
flat
and on this new platform they could
Empower their customers to go online and
download print out their own barcodes
and boarding passes and take up all the
a seats before Tom fredman got to the
airport oh I looked at that friends I
said fredman you are so 20th century I
mean really think you're so
globalization 1.0 globalization there
was a ticket agent I us to go down pull
the number thank you ma'am I'm going to
go to Baltimore then we got to eat
ticket machine we thought that was
cool and then while you were sleeping
you the individual became your own
ticket agent or to look at it another
way you the individual became an
employee of Southwest
Airlines or or look at it actually still
another way you the individual if you
value your own time staying up at 12:01
a.m. the night before are actually
paying Southwest Airlines to be their
employee have a nice day
okay so I get smart next time I stay up
till 12:01 a.m. I download my own
barcode and boarding pass I get to the
gate 35 minutes before the flight this
time because I've interacted with
Southwest Airlines horizontally now not
vertically and what happened I captured
60 Minutes of
productivity by interfacing with
Southwest Airlines on this platform
horizontally not vertically well that
move from vertical to horizontal it's
happening as I said on a million
campuses and a million businesses and
when we get to the other side of it and
the people who do it best are going to
capture enormous productivity think of
the productivity gains if you could
measure them of all these people
interacting with MIT horizontally not
vertically not getting on a plane coming
here to a lecture but interacting with
MIT horizontally I would be fascinated
if someone could actually measure the
incredible educational productivity gain
you've given birth to here so so those
are the to me the three rules of this
platform now that that means several
things I think for our society and how
we organize ourselves which makes the
current election campaign make you want
to really weep because it means it means
several things first of all I I I used
to be a free
Trader I'm I'm not anymore I have to
tell you I do not I'm not a free Trader
anymore now now I'm a radical free
Trader oh I'm a wild crazy paint on my
face radical free Trader because if
whatever can be done will be done and if
the greatest single Advantage is what
you can act on your individual
imagination who's going to win it's
going to be the most open society that
gets the signals first of what's being
done and empowers and enables its
citizens to react and do it before it's
done to them so just at a moment when we
have this incredible cultural Advantage
as a free trading Society we do not have
one single candidate basically in this
election campaign truly in a
full-throated way standing up for free
trade it is really in my view really
really dangerous I think the second rule
that you know I pull off this new
platform and um its new capabilities is
also what it means for
Education um I have to say I was a
always a fan of liberal arts um I'm an
even bigger fan of liberal arts today um
Lord knows what MIT does here on math
and science is irreplaceable um and is
one of the crown jewels of this
country but bringing liberal arts into
the equation is more important than ever
because we're in a world now where
imagination and mashups the ability to
mash things together through really
imaginative I think than you
is going to be such a huge advantage and
I don't know about you all but where my
imagination comes from is having two
different Specialties Arabic Middle East
history and globalization and technology
and mashing them
together I think educ inspiration
Innovation comes from having two or more
Specialties and applying the framework
of one specialty to the framework of
another and so it is great it is
essential it is critical we have people
who are expt exper at dots but we also
need as individuals and collectives to
be encouraging the connecting of those
dots and the mashing of them together
that is where inspiration comes from
Leonardo da Vinci was a scientist he was
an artist he was an inventor and that's
what made him special I always Point
people to Steve Jobs graduation speech
at Stanford a couple years ago where he
talked about where his own inspiration
came from for the max Steve went to Reed
College he dropped out like all Great
American entrepreneurs after one term
think about that Bill Gates Michael Dell
Steve Jobs all dropped out um but he had
nowhere to go so he hung around Reed
College and he had nothing to do so he
decided to take a course in
calligraphy and he learned the beauty of
typface of serif and San serif type and
10 years later he said it all went into
the Mac keyboard
the first Mac keyboard was exactly what
it was which had at that time the most
Innovative type face in Computing in
popular Computing because Steve Jobs
dropped out of Reed College and took a
course in
craphy I don't know if anyone's out
there looking for a job we are desperate
at the New York Times for engineers
they've asked me to actually make this
appeal we can't hire Engineers we no one
no one thinks we're cool we're not
Google I know but we're not that bad you
know but we would love if any of you
want to give me your card you're looking
for a job in engineering we'd love you
to come interview at the New York Times
but just one thing please don't come if
you've never read the New York
Times please don't come if you don't
read at least three newspapers a day
because we need people who can mash up
those things we can we can get Engineers
we can Outsource we can we can get
people to do programming we need people
who can really
imaginatively Mash those things together
so I'm these are the kind of things that
I'm really looking at now as as I look
at America as I look at our election and
as I look at things that we
need I I'm still a big believer that we
have culturally so many things that work
for this new world
but we've kind of lost our
groove since
911 you I go around the world now and
you hear it everywhere people say you
know the 19th century belong to Britain
the 20th century belong to America and
the 21st century will belong to to
China and what's happening in China
today is truly impressive and what makes
it impressive is it's it's from hard
work and it's from the ground up and you
just cannot go there and not be
impressed at what China is
doing but I I'm just not quite ready to
seed the 21st century to anyone yet
because you know we're we're not going
to win it if we don't get our act
together and be smart about these
natural attributes we have free trade
Innovative culture we don't need to have
an hour of creativity class in this
country
okay but we need to get our act together
we cannot go on being dumb as as we want
to be and right now that is the motto of
the US Congress dumb as we want to be
okay Washington today is brain dead I am
talking about beep there isn't even a
okay brain dead as far as I'm concerned
both parties both houses the White House
brain dead but I have to tell you if
someone who is a reporter who spends a
lot of time out in the country thank God
our country is
alive because all these individuals I
should show you my desk boy I got a pile
here from energy entrepreneurs come see
my flywheel it turns a duck it jumps up
it makes you know methane I mean come to
my class another pile from Educators
we're teaching young women how to do
science and math in these really
innovative ways thank God our country is
alive if we had a government that was as
alive as the country no one would touch
us so I'm not ready to seed the 21st
century to anyone just yet because our
culture of creativity it's hard to
duplicate my grandmother in Minnesota
had a saying Grand Grandma fredman God
bless her she used to sit in her rocking
chair in the data winter and she would
say to me you know Tommy I I have to
tell you remember one thing said Grandma
fredman never seed a century to a
country that censors Google it was it
was just a
it was it was just a little thing
Grandma used to say
and sitting sitting by the fire so I'm
not ready to seed the 21st century yet
to anyone but I think a lot of who is
going to own the 21st century and I'm
going to close with this is really going
to be defined by who addresses this
clean power challenge this clean energy
challenge first best and most
productively and that's really the segue
to my next book Because when the world
is this
flat what's happening is three billion
new players God bless every one of them
have come through through through
portals like this to the flat world all
with their own version of the American
dream a house a car a toaster a
microwave and a refrigerator if we don't
find a
cleaner more non-emitting way to power
their dreams we are going to burn up
choke up heat up and smoke up this
planet so much faster than even Al Gore
predicts okay so the flattening of the
world is critical to
this now everyone says you know oh but
but but Mr freedan there's a Green
Revolution going on there's a Green
Revolution ution going I read it in the
special green issue of my local magazine
my local newspaper special green issue
even of amra
magazine I say oh really really there's
a Green Revolution going on here just
you don't say really a Green Revolution
have you ever been to a revolution where
no one got hurt that's the Green
Revolution yeah the Green Revolution
we're
having is a revolution where nobody gets
hurt you get to consume your way out of
it oh that's not a revolution friends
that's a party we're having a green
party and it's it's great fun I have to
tell you I get invited to all the
parties it's great
fun I've never been to a revolution
where no one got hurt many of you here
attended drove and participated in the
it Revolution that was a revolution it
operated on the true business
revolutionary principle change or die
change or die Wayne computer data
General Burrows they're not with us
anymore they're in that great computer
company heaven in the
sky because they were in the middle of a
real Revolution change or die
the Green Revolution we're having is a
complete fraud as far as I'm concerned
because in this revolution everyone's
green yeah exxon's Green BP's green I
read there Beyond petroleum GM's green
now they give you a little yellow cap
you know on to put your flex fuel in
they don't tell you you're driving a
flex fuel car but never
mind that's not a revolution that's a
party and if we don't do what what it
takes to sparkk a real revolution in a
flat world the climate and energy
impacts are going to swamp
us I wrote about this a few weeks ago
some of you may have seen by accident I
happen to visit two cities you've
probably never heard of two weeks apart
I went to Iraq and on my way I stopped
in dohaqatar capital of Qatar a tiny
Peninsular State off the east coast of
Saudi Arabia and 10 days later I went to
dalan China now I have to have been to
Doan and dalen several times but I
hadn't been to either one for three
years I go to Doha and what do I find I
find I get off the plane I look downtown
and they have grown a
Manhattan a little mini Manhattan since
I was there last like a wildf flower
that sprouted from a desert rainstorm I
just looked I said that you you have a
Skyline now that's like that's like a
little
Manhattan two weeks later I go to dalan
10 days later I see they already had a
Manhattan they've added two more since I
was there so I'm really glad you changed
all the CFL your lights here from
incandescent to compact
fluorescent Doha and dalen ate that for
breakfast oh no you got a Prius God
bless you Doan dalen ate that for lunch
oh you added more insulation to your
home you did the 205 easy ways to go
green according to working woman
magazine Doha and dalen snacked on that
after dinner like so much
popcorn two cities you've never heard
of have grown Manhattans in the last
three
years the global economy today friends
is like a monster truck with the gas
pedal stuck and we have lost the
key and the only way we are going to
catch that truck is with a
disruptive
breakthrough and the only way we're
going to get a disruptive breakthrough
is with a completely different mix of
Standards regulations incentive and
taxes that will trigger that
disruption which is why my fundamental
rule is change your leaders not your
light bulbs oh it's great to change your
light bulbs but if you don't change your
leaders if you don't change the leaders
who write the rules who trigger The
Innovation we are
cooked so what I've been trying to do in
the new book I'm writing um
is
basically in my own little way to try to
reshape how we think about this problem
because we actually think we're having a
revolution and we're actually having a
party but one of the real problems in
getting people to rethink this
problem is getting them to rethink the
meaning of
green one of the big problems around
green is that I'm a big believer to name
something is to own it if you can name
an issue you can own an issue The World
is
Flat and the problem with green is all
these years it was named by its
opponents basically they named it
liberal tree hugging girly man
unpatriotic vaguely French just vaguely
French something about it vaguely French
okay well what I'm really out to do is
to rename green rename it geopolitical
geostrategic economic capitalistic
entrepreneurial patriotic green is the
new red white and blue thank you very
much
thanks well first of all thank you very
much for your marks um I'm glad you kept
you know kept them lowkey and and
certainly you they're really but thank
you very much for Extraordinary pres
we're going to take a 15-minute break uh
and I will be ruthless in bringing you
back uh but I shouldn't need to because
we have an extraordinary panel as the
next session so take a break come back
when the lights start flickering and I
start making noises and I'll see you in
15 minutes