the MIT energy initiative presents
Michael Howland gives wind energy a lift
written by Deborah
halber Michael Howland was in his office
at MIT watching real-time data from a
wind farm 7,000 M away in Northwest
India when he noticed something odd some
of the turbines weren't producing the
expected amount of electricity Howland
the Esther and Herold e agerton
assistant professor of civil and Environ
mental engineering studies the physics
of the Earth's atmosphere and how that
information can optimize Renewable
Energy Systems to accomplish this he and
his team develop and use predictive
models supercomputer simulations and
real life data from wind farms such as
the one in India the global wind power
Market is one of the most cost
competitive and resilient power sources
across the world the global wind energy
Council reported last year the Year 2020
saw record growth in wind power capacity
thanks to a surge of installations in
China and the United States yet wind
power needs to grow three times faster
in the coming decade to address the
worst impacts of climate change and
Achieve Federal and State climate goals
the report says optimal Wind Farm design
and the resulting cost of energy are
dependent on the Wind Helen says but
wind farms are often cited and designed
based on short-term historical climate
records in October 2021 Howland received
a seed fund Grant from the MIT energy
initiative Mighty to account for how
climate change might affect the wind of
the future our initial results suggests
that considering the uncertainty and the
winds in the design and operation of
wind farms can lead to more reliable
energy production he says most recently
Howland and his team came up with a
model that predicts the power produced
by each individual turbine based on the
physics of the Wind Farm as a whole the
model can inform decisions that may
boost a Farm's overall
output the state of the planet growing
up in a suburb of Philadelphia the son
of neuroscientists howland's childhood
wasn't especially outdoorsy later he'd
become an avid hiker with a deep
appreciation for nature but a nth grade
class assignment made him think about
the state of the planet perhaps for the
first time a history teacher had asked
the class to write a report on climate
change I remember arguing with my high
school classmates about whether humans
were the leading cause of climate change
but the teacher didn't want to get into
that debate Howland recalls he said
climate change was happening whether or
not you accept that it's anthropogenic
and he wanted us to think about the
impacts of global warming and solutions
I was one of his vigorous Defenders as
part of a research internship after his
freshman year of college Howland visited
a wind farm in Iowa where wind produces
more than half of the state's
electricity the turbines look tall from
the highway but when you're underneath
them you're really struck by their scale
he says that's where you get a sense of
how colossal they really are not a fan
of heights howand opted not to climb the
turbine's internal ladder to snap a
photo from the top after receiving an
undergraduate degree from John's Hopkins
University and M's and PhD degrees in
mechanical engineering from Stanford
University he joined mit's Department of
Civil and environmental engineering to
focus on the intersection of fluid
mechanics weather climate and energy
modeling his goal is to enhance
Renewable Energy Systems an added bonus
to being at MIT is the opportunity to
inspire the Next Generation much like
his nth grade history teacher did for
him hen's graduate level introduction to
the atmospheric boundary layer is geared
primarily to engineers and physicists
but as he sees it climate change is such
a multi disciplinary and complex
challenge that every skill set that
exists in human society can be relevant
to mitigating it there are the physics
and Engineering questions that our lab
primarily works on but there are also
questions related to social sciences
public acceptance policymaking and
implementation he says careers in
renewable energy are rapidly growing
there are far more job openings than we
can hire for right now in many areas we
don't yet have enough people to address
the challenges in renewable energy and
climate change mitigation that need to
be solved I encourage my students really
everyone I interact with to find a way
to impact the climate change problem he
says unusual
conditions in Fall 2021 Howland was
trying to explain the odd data coming in
from India based on sensor feedback wind
turbin softwar driven Control Systems
constantly tweak the speed and the angle
of the blades and what's known as yaw
the orientation of the giant blades in
relation to the wind direction existing
utility scale turbines are controlled
greedily which means that every turbine
in the farm automatically turns into the
wind to maximize its own power
production though the turbines in the
front row of the Indian Wind Farm were
reacting appropriately to the wind
direction their power output was all
over the place not what we would expect
based on the existing models Howland
says these massive turbine Towers stood
at 100 m about the length of a football
field with blades the length of an
Olympic swimming pool at their highest
point the blade tips lunged almost 200 M
into the sky then there's the speed of
the blades themselves the tips move many
times faster than the wind around 80 to
100 m per second up to a quarter or a
third of the speed of sound using a
state-of-the-art sensor that measures
the speed of incoming wind before it
interacts with the massive rotors
howland's team saw an unexpectedly
complex airflow effect he covers the
phenomenon in his class the data coming
in from India he says displayed quite
remarkable wind conditions stemming from
the effects of Earth's rotation and the
physics of buoyancy that you don't
always see traditionally wind turbines
operate in the lowest 10% of the
atmospheric boundary layer the so-called
surface layer affected primarily by
ground conditions the Indian turbines
howand realized were operating in
regions of the atmosphere that turbines
haven't historically
accessed trending
taller Howland knew that airflow
interactions can persist for kilometers
the interaction of high winds with the
front row turbines was generating wakes
in the air similar to the way boats
generate wakes in the water to address
this howland's model trades off the
efficiency of upwind turbines to benefit
downwind ones by misaligning some of the
upwind turbines in certain conditions
the downwind units experience less wake
turbulence increasing the overall energy
output of the wind farm by as much as 1%
to 3% without requiring additional costs
if a 1.2% energy increase was applied to
the world's existing wind farms it would
be the equivalent of adding more than
3,600
new wind turbines enough to power about
3 million homes even a modest boost
could mean fewer turbines generating the
same output or the ability to place more
units into a smaller space because
negative interactions between the
turbines can be diminished Howen says
the model can predict potential benefits
in a variety of scenarios at different
types of wind farms the part that's
important and exciting is that it's not
just particular to this wind farm we can
apply the colle Ive control method
across the windfarm fleet he says which
is growing taller and wider by 2035 the
average Hub height for offshore turbines
in the United States is projected to
grow from 100 m to around 150 M the
height of the Washington
Monument as we continue to build larger
wind turbines and larger wind farms we
need to revisit the existing practice
for their design and control Howen says
we can use our predictive models to
ensure that we build an operate the most
efficient renewable generators
possible looking to the
Future Howland and other climate
Watchers have reason for optimism with
the passage in August 2022 of the
inflation reduction act which calls for
a significant investment in domestic
energy production and for reducing
carbon emissions by roughly 40% by
2030 but Helen says the act itself isn't
sufficient we need to continue pushing
the envelope in research and development
as well as deployment he says the model
he created with his team can help
especially for offshore wind farms
experiencing low wind turbulence and
larger wake interactions offshore wind
can face challenges of public acceptance
Howen believes that researchers policy
makers and the energy industry need to
do more to get the public on board by
addressing concerns through open public
dialogue Outreach and education Howland
once wrote and Illustrated a children's
book inspired by Dr SS's The Lorax that
focused on renewable energy howand
recalls his really terrible
illustrations but he believes he was on
to something I was having some fun
helping people interact with alternative
energy in a more natural way at an
earlier age he says and recognize that
these are not nefarious Technologies but
remarkable Feats of human ingenuity