Hey, we're provocative. Um, we're
building an AI data center in
Somerville. Um, we actually already
built it. Um, it's over there somewhere
behind me. Um, our secret sauce is we're
totally vertically integrated. So, um,
we build we take over buildings, in this
case, a big warehouse. We put shipping
containers inside. We put a lot of GPUs
in those shipping containers. And then
the really magic thing is our cooling
system is actually a carbon capture
system that we made to suit our business
model. Um, and so as we run air and hot
and cold water through our containers,
GPUs, we actually are bottling up CO2
and selling it to local breweries and
bars and restaurants um for make benefit
earth and cash flow. Um, a lot of MIT
people on the team. I dropped out. I'm
sorry. Uh of undergrad, but I came back
and joined Sloan and the MECI department
on the faculty. Um I kind of sneaked in.
Not a real professor. Don't call me a
professor, but uh I taught classes. Um
co-founded this with Marty Cper, MIT's
Makers are helped build the engine. Also
does a lot of other cool stuff. And then
my co-founder Rob didn't go to MIT, so
he's dead to me. Um our first engineer
is Andrew Bulma, who does a had a PhD in
HVAC and desalination stuff. And so we
love MIT uh here. Um but we do hire
other people too, like my co-founder. Um
the big problem we solve is actually
AI's uh AI cloud's debt problem. Um if
you're a data center, you care a lot
about power and space and bandwidth
because you buy those things and you
rent them out on a margin. So power is a
big part of your cost. If you're a
cloud, only like two and a half to 5% of
your cost is actually power. So it
doesn't matter much. What matters is the
fact that for every dollar you make, you
spend more than 60%, sometimes more than
100% of your revenue, servicing your
debt load. So, that's called a bad
business. We like good businesses. Um,
this is a slide that says the same thing
I just said. Uh, and this also is a
slide that says what I already just
said, so I'm going to skip that. Um,
this is kind of a layout of our system.
This is an air cooled configuration. So,
we pull air in, run them through um
modular carbon capture filters we made.
They're vacuum chambers. Um we use a
temperature pressure swing process um
where we can actually leverage the heat
coming off the chips for disorption. Um
which is neat. And then we invented some
really cool vacuum chambers that are
extremely lightweight. So, they're
really big, but the shell of them is
very thin steel instead of really thick
steel. So individual humans can lift
them up and you don't die if one falls
on you, which is a really big deal for
building stuff fast. Um, so the air goes
through those, goes through the chips,
cools them. It's great. We support air
cooled or liquid cooled versions like
Sasha said in these extremely dense
liquid cooled environments where you
have a megawatt per rack. Um, the
configuration looks a lot like what
Cruso builds these days where you have
like one container surrounded by a bunch
of one container of really hot compute
surrounded by a bunch of containers
evacuating heat to the atmosphere. Um,
so it's really convenient for us. Um,
lots of financial benefits. We make a
lot more money. Um, and the main reason
being that because Coca-Cola and
Annheiser Bush buy our CO2 and they have
incredible credit scores, like better
than the US government, we can borrow
against those contracts, lower our cost
of capital by a massive amount, buy
chips with them, lever that up into tons
of cash flow, and be very profitable.
Um, which is cool. Um, we already have
tons of customers. We're actually
delivering beverage gate CO2 all over
the Boston area. Um, we're about to take
over the Boston Logan airport contract,
uh, major stadiums around here. Um, no
one has enough CO2. Supply chain is
absolutely horrific. Uh, it's so bad.
Um, California alone is under supplied
by$ 1.5 billion dollars a year worth of
CO2. Um, but it's got to be beverage
grade and beverage grade is hard to
make. So, we're sold out for forever.
We're doing almost, this is actually
outdated. We're doing almost 1.5 million
in revenue in only 9 months. Um, so
we're growing really fast. Uh, lots of
LOIs, lots of order purchases and stuff.
Um, and but we need to partner all over
the place. You guys are all great. I'd
rather I'm actually putting three
megawatts in right now. Our our
electrical engineers are here. Uh, I
have a problem. Um, uh, we use existing
buildings and we got to punch through
walls. So, running one conduit instead
of 16 changes my life. Um, and every
week that we're not making money, I'm
losing a million dollars. So, um, if you
haven't invested in Ver, you should
invest in them or something like it. And
I'm I would be a customer. I can't
believe we haven't chatted much. Um, I
have that problem today. They're here
right now. Um, but other stuff. We need
transformers, we need GPUs, we need heat
pumps, we need super. Ah, I already put
it on there. CO2 customers, content
delivery networks, AI companies. If you
need GPUs, um, if you want to give us a
building to build a data center in the
middle of a city, that'd be great. We
focus on um, like in the middle of
cities is where we want to be. That's
where CO2 is. Um, so we can partner with
lots of people and we're excited about
basically everything. Love you. That's
me.
>> Thanks, Nick.
Um, you need a stage. Um, okay. Let me
start with a question and again please
post your questions to the chat or the
Q&A tab. Um tell us a little more about
supporting liquid cooled servers.
>> Yeah. Um well I think uh everyone kind
of sees that liquid cooled's the future
in the news and that's that's
kind I think true generally especially
with these rack densities. Um it's a lot
easier for us to harvest the energy from
the chips in a liquid cooled system. Um,
we already for our carbon capture
system, we have to heat up the filters
inside to get the CO2 out of it. And so
we don't have to change much about our
system to kind of integrate into a
cooling loop. Um, and so we kind of run
that loop through the chips, let them
heat it, let it let the water heat up,
um, run that into the carbon capture
filter. Um, and then that helps us
release the CO2. We can harvest a lot of
that about 40% of the kind of energy
lost to heat we can harvest, which is
great. Um, and uh, it's actually we
possible that we can get more dense than
a traditional data center liquid cooled
cooling system because we've got
chemical reactions going on and things
like that. So, it's actually quite
efficient and cheap.
>> Okay. And I was going to ask about the
best spots to build your data centers,
but also Jose is asking on that line. Um
spot for the yeah you know for sec uh
compute size of smallmediumsiz data
centers in an urban environment.
>> Yeah. So this is counterintuitive I
think uh the news again generally the
hyperscalers you know the one to five
gawatt things in the in the middle of
nowhere which are very cool. Um but uh
the backbone of the internet and and the
internet exchanges are all in the top 20
major cities. It's where the all the
undersea cables come in. And there's a
lot of office buildings and factories
that are shut down that have three to
five megawatts. And we can make 200
to$250 million dollars a year out of a 5
megawatt office building. Like that's
why we're here. Um we'll make about a h
100red million a year out of this crappy
factory in Somerville. Um and we're
right on top of a fiber line. So um
where people live is where CO2 is sold
and consumed. So we we need that and and
it's also where it's most in demand and
hardest to get. Um, and it's also where
the internet lives. So that's where we
want to build for now.
>> Got it. Thanks, Nick. Thanks very much.