good morning everyone and welcome to
today's MPG primer and today it is my
pleasure to introduce U or reintroduce
Sarah Morton Sarah Morton has been a
pivotal um member of the mpg Community
having served as the co-chair of this
primary series for several years um and
has some interesting outlooks about what
she'll be doing next with MPG so hold
tight for that uh so just a little bit
about Sarah Morton she is a
neonatologist at Boston Children's
Hospital and assistant professor of
pediatrics at Harvard Medical School her
research group is focused on genetic
contributions to congenital heart
disease and Associated Health outcomes
she is also the director of the niku
biobank at Boston Children's Hospital
and is glad to talk to you today about
bio banking big and small thank you so
much Sarah thank you so much thank you
all for being here today desite despite
the rain and slush um and so I'm really
glad to share with you a little bit of
what I know about biobanks but would
love this to be interactive so if you
have questions or thoughts as we go
along um I'd be really really uh glad to
engage uh but I think the perspective I
was thinking of is you know if primer
series is for people who are you know
maybe earlier on and designing projects
and and thinking about our scientific
Community what is it that you might want
to know if you wanted to set up a
biobank what is it you might want to
know if you're accessing a biobank about
how the data are obtained and the
decisions that are are made uh in this
setting up and then I'll give you the
example of our local biobank which will
have the definite theme of everything in
Pediatrics is smaller but I also think
that sometimes our effect sizes are
larger uh so there's something to be
learned from kind of every every type of
of
cohort uh and so uh through the talk
today we'll talk a little bit about the
general principles of biobanking and
that's where the why what who comes in
uh I'll talk about some of the Exemplar
ones that I'm sure you're all familiar
with but what I'll be sharing with a
little bit is like what does the
protocol look like for all of us what
did they decide to do with samples for
UK biobank uh so that you can see what
are the tradeoffs between scale cost um
and kind of preserving questions that
can be answered in the future that we
can't even anticipate now um and then
I'll tell you about our our local one
over at the
ncu uh so what's a biobank what's a bio
repository we kind of all smoos the
words together uh what do is are there
kind is there a significance to the
different ones and I would say a bior
repository is a larger umbrella term
that is when there is a banking or kind
of a storage of tissues or samples that
come from any kind of living organism
and so often when people talk about a
bior repository it might include
bacterial cell lines or tissue culture
lines uh from non-human animals and so a
bior repository is the gener more
general term of which a biobank tends to
refer to bio repositories that only
include human uh human
samples and so the other thing that
makes a biobank is not just that you've
stored it so having a freezer is not
necessarily a biobank uh but that the
specimens were lit were collected for
the purpose of advancing uh medical and
health knowledge and that's important
because you can't just have a sample you
need to know who it came from what were
the situations in which it was collected
um perhaps even what has happened since
that person participated what are those
longer term outcomes and so what makes a
biobank is not just the sample but the
meta dat that come with it um and and
sometimes you might spend as much effort
uh and as much of your budget on getting
those Associated metadata as you do on
the actual processing and storage of the
samples
um the other thing that makes it
different is that there are kind of
standard operating procedures and a set
of govern in principles that you should
adhere to when having a biobank and so
there needs to be a standard operating
procedure for the acquisition of the
samples for the processing and labeling
of the samples um and for storage and
distribution and so if you are either
trying to access a data a biobank or
setting one up yourself knowing how to
enter each of those different phases um
and how to understand how a sample you
might be using was processed is one of
those things that you can really dig
into a uh in the metad data my favorite
thing about a biobank is always its data
dictionary uh because if you know what
they know uh then you can also start to
understand a little bit about what might
be um missing that you would need to
infer uh or or acknowledge as a
limitation in your own
study um biobanks are so exciting right
now right there's they're growing
there's National ones there's
International ones every hospital has
one they're adding metadata they're
adding EMR you can do natural language
processing uh you write on medical
records that are linked to biobanks and
so it really is an area where there's
been a tremendous amount of growth both
in terms of the number of biobanks and
the scope of their uh purposes may I ask
a question about that what do you think
are some of the reasons of why this is
sort of booming right
now um I like to think it's because
there's a lot that as we advance
genetics some of our animal models and
cell culture models which have given us
so many insights into the fundamental
biology underlying health and disease um
that we've come to realize that a lot of
the fruitful advances recently have been
very specific to the human genome and
very specific to human physiology and so
I think that um some of the Boom is the
focus on moving towards having
understanding our fundamental biology
but also moving towards having new
Therapeutics or new Diagnostics um uh in
the near term and so I think biobanks
are a nice opportunity to bridge our
basic science and our cellular and
animal models um as a nice demonstration
of applicability uh before you go to
like a phase one trial or something like
that thinking about developing
Therapeutics so I think of them as
having a nice role in making it's you
can kind of take all of your science and
you know make sure that it holds true uh
in a human
population um yeah and so you know this
is not a tough crowd to say population
genetics is important right uh but like
you know having these broad uh diverse
representative cohorts really lets us
interpret variance like when I think
about you know we do genetic testing on
on patients in the ncu regularly at
least once a week someone gets a genome
sent and our ability to interpret those
variants now because your Al frequency
can go down to 10 theg5 or 10 to the6 in
the general population right those those
kind of data come from kind you know our
in large part for efforts of our our
biobanks um
and also you know just having many
biobanks as we'll talk about will be
able to share with you cells and perhaps
even um the cells that can be made into
IPS cells and so that does let you look
at molecular mechanisms among people who
you might know their genotype as well as
their kind of medical history uh and
then you know again switching and
thinking about interventions it's a
great place to look at questions like
pharmacogenomics where we've come in the
past five years to understand so much
more about how our generalizations from
limited population are not really
representative to our entire uh patient
Community I just thought this was really
cool that's a picture of like the inside
of the UK biobank it's just from their
website um but really thinking about how
sophisticated many of these operations
are with um you know almost no one
touching a sample once it's been
collected right uh and having the
automation both to reduce our amount of
uh potential contamination and
differences in handling but also really
um to
uh allow a scalability that's not
possible without
automation I came up with my title
before I found this paper but I found it
very interesting that we had the same
kind of way of breaking down how to
understand a biobank right which is if
you're really thinking about using one
or thinking about starting your own you
need to figure out what your scope is
and to me these same sets of like write
the five W's plus how at the end uh is
is a great way to Define which biobank
might be right for you or or how you
might start your own if you needed to um
and so we'll go through these more in
detail but really why is obviously the
first one so either why would you access
a biobank sample um or why would you
start your own usually has to do with uh
as Nicole asked like what is that key
question that's where there's a gap in
your science where either having a bios
specimen having uh you know U metadata
or aggregated or single information from
a population would answer your research
question the what is one of the things
that changes the most uh so our we have
a biobank over at Children's right now
and they're just going through the
process of pretty much only keeping
white blood cell pellets so there had
been a lot of serum or plasma that was
stored for a long time and it turned out
those just hadn't been accessed by
researchers right people were interested
far more in the DNA uh and so as the
scale of the samples became large enough
to require expansion or selection of
samples they chose selection of samp
examples right so the what definitely
changes over time and a lot of the what
is electronic now right it's your
wearable device data it's questionnaires
filled out um by by participants things
like
that um the when part I think is
uniquely interesting in terms of
thinking we used to think of a lot of
our research participation as a single
event you fill out one questionnaire and
give one sample and that was your
participation in the research study and
now it's become much more long itudinal
and people are more willing to share a
lot of their personal information in uh
in an ongoing way than they were in the
past uh and I think though there will be
differences in who contributes data and
who has time to contribute data that we
always need to be cognant of uh it it
definitely has expanded the when um of
of interaction especially with passive
drawing of data from the electronic
medical record right so that requires
you to just return to care from the
place you enrolled
uh but that's another way to get kind of
longitudinal data from
individuals um we'll talk about the wear
especially when we talk about all of us
but that's been another place where you
know it used to be Hospital based or
institution-based but there's been a lot
more biobanks with a Community Focus in
terms of Outreach and enrollment um
where where that part has changed uh and
then I think the who the from a
pediatrician one of my my biggest
perspectives on this is everyone I
enroll because their parents consent I
would need to reenroll once they reach
age of majority uh and so from for me
most most of the who's people can always
opt out uh but one of the things to
think about When approaching pediatric
populations is there's actually an
active need to opt in once you reach age
of majority we don't just because their
parents said yes when they were a day
old doesn't mean that they um as an
adult will say yes themselves and so
that's one of the things I think about
most with the who is just making sure
that we you know not just passively
accept people's choices to opt out but
there is actually a need to to
proactively uh confirm
consent uh so if you think about why to
start a biobank why did I start the niku
biobank why did people start UK biobank
there's very different motivations right
depending on kind of your scale and your
catchment
um sometimes it might be started for a
specific project uh for example many
times there might be patient registries
that are associated with a clinic or a
uh an organization that represents
people who have a particular diagnosis
and so those Registries are now often
expanding to also include a biobank
those are often optional and that the
primary project is still the registry
and collecting um non-bio specimens but
sometimes biobanks are an add-on to a
project that's been going on for
sometimes decades uh but now collecting
bios specimens in addition and
especially with the advances in ility to
do nice genomic sequencing from saliva
samples this doesn't even require anyone
to see a needle or show up in your state
uh and so that can be a way that people
do expand uh bios specimens we're doing
this right now for a study of adults
with congenital heart disease who are
now in their 30s and had their
operations generally in their first week
of life and it's been amazing how they
participated in this research study over
decades and one of the ways that we've
gotten bios specimens for that study is
literally we just send them a SP kit and
they send it back and then all the
sequencing happens here uh and so it's a
it's a nice way to be able to expand our
data types on studies where we might
actually already have that longitudinal
information but we've never been able to
consider the genetics in the in the
questions uh uh sometimes there might be
a planned analysis I'll show you an
example of this later I tried to make my
uh our biobank such that you know I U I
last night uh when I was working the ncu
cared for two instants with tr me 18
right uh and that's not everyone's every
day uh so I am very privileged that I
get to meet a lot of families and
infants who are affected by diagnoses
that are rare in the general population
and to me it was always a tragedy that a
fellow might show up five years later
and want to study Tri 18 but we would
have no samples for them right there
would be no place for them to start from
even though we had uh you know some of
the most uh ability to to start
collecting those samples and so we've
made our IRB such that a fellow can come
with a question uh we will do all the
consenting and Sample collection and
they do a secondary analysis of
available research consent uh and so
there that process becomes much more
easy for them and then we also have just
you know the accumulated knowledge of
the years that it takes to get a
reasonable cohort so that's an example
of a time where there might be a planned
analysis but we're just kind of adding
on the specific data types uh that we
need uh then there's the more General
projects so these are the ones we're
familiar with the UK biobank the Japan
biobank all of us and so there's often
broad participant recruitment this is
where the metadata might be a little
more variable it might fit your study
but might be missing some pieces right
like in the nicku there's all these
things we collect about what were you
know what was maternal what was the um
health of the pregnant person during
pregnancy what was the what were the
incidents that happened right around
delivery birth weight it's amazing how
hard it can be to find someone's birth
weight uh Even in our Hospital sometimes
if they transfer to us two months later
it might never enter our medical record
um and so there is a lot of more details
that we catch in our targeted uh
metadata which might not be present in
the general projects uh and then there's
a lot of times where people come up with
cool new techniques like um right EP
signatures of different congenital
anomalies and all of a sudden we already
have this biobank and so we didn't know
that that's what we were going to be
doing with our samples but now that as
those technologies have progressed and
the research questions come to Encompass
our population uh we're able to then set
up the uh appropriate agreements uh to
be able to transfer those
samples um so who is in the biobank
obviously determines your ability to
learn from the samples in the biobank uh
and so one thing is always read the fine
print and so if you read what the
inclusion and exclusion criteria are for
a bio Bank you're thinking of accessing
that can help you know at the start what
the caveats will be to your
analysis
um there again I mentioned this before
but just anyone who's enrolled uh under
the age of 18 tends to need active
reconsent now that's a change in the
past three years or so it used to be
that people didn't really require that
reconsent um but pretty much everyone
now is making is having their uh IRB
protocols revised to uh include that
reconsent and then just a couple of ways
that we do in our biobank to be
representative um is we have all of our
research approaches be regardless of
preferred language um our Hospital
actually does not have any charge for
use of interpreter services for research
uh so there should be no barrier uh to
enrolling anyone or approaching anyone
for research who's eligible um and then
pursuing a consent if they are
interested in hearing more um and I
actually think that's a really important
part because many protocols that still
come to our IRB we'll say English only
or English Spanish only because it's a
pilot study um but there's actually a
really nice thing called a short form
consent and what that is is that there's
a much shorter form of the consent which
is uh translated by The Interpreter and
then the the larger consent is verbally
translated in the moment uh and so there
are ways to be able to not have to have
your documents in every single language
but still be able to provide a r a
robust consenting process um that
doesn't limit particip based on
preferred
language um uh things like uh so this is
again maybe a little more nicku focused
um but not everyone's going to be
available to stay an extra half hour
after their Clinic visit not everyone's
going to be available to 9 to5 uh and so
having things like off hours consenting
having um remote consenting which has
been it was were there any Silver
Linings to everything becoming remote
for a while uh you know being able to
have some online consents where people
can read at their Leisure uh there's no
one in the room uh they can take their
time to ask their questions but be able
to be as synchronist in some of that uh
can be another way to be more inclusive
um uh and then also I think helping I
know why I would participate in a
research study I dragged my kids around
to be people you know they had so many
of those like motion balls attached to
them for some study right uh like many
of us participate in research for all
kinds of different reasons and what
actually matters is not why I
participate but why other people who
have chosen to participate in that
biobank or that research study uh and so
I think as much as possible having the
voices of participants represented in
your brochures um in your Flyers uh even
you know like on the screens that are
around every place where someone might
wait for their consent um having the
voices of people who really participated
and why they did uh can be one of the
most compelling things uh and so I think
that's something that can also help you
have a more representative uh uh
biobank um and then just thinking about
again location uh you know if you uh if
you only recruit in our nicku you're not
going to get the average neonate right
and so we're really good in answering
some questions and terrible at others um
so just making sure that if you're going
to access a biobank understanding how it
was that people were approached uh
because it's uh again when it's uh
location specific people usually either
were there or not there for for some
underlying
reasons um so what is banked um
this uh talks about all the different
things there this was a the image is
talking about one that was an oncology
example uh and so I liked it because it
focused on the participant pathway so
this set their participant starting at
the bottom left um and so people often
provide a lot of things they'll provide
bio samples some of them are passively
collected like our biobank uh at
Children's Hospital we we're actually
really good at using not very much blood
for testing it's not quite thos level
but we do things on very small volumes
but they even save the rest of that very
small volume because they know that some
of our right some of my patients are 500
grams you can't take a lot of blood from
them um and so with that they'll
actually save whatever is left after the
test was run in case I want to add on
another test like oh I needed the liver
function but now I'd really also like to
add on you know my ALB men or my
electrolytes or something like that um
and so they already had this culture of
saving the remnants and so all you had
to do was say well after you've reached
that Remnant part for retesting how
about that just goes to our biobank and
so there are ways to participate that
don't require extra uh needle exposures
or extra bios specimen collections
similarly sometimes operative tissues
are the most valuable right because you
might be studying a condition that is
not easily accessible or or directly
studied from blood CSF or urine
something else that comes out of us more
easily um and so having that pipeline to
be able to access surgically um excise
tissues is also a high a high yield
place and so again those biosamples
might be population based in which case
you're grabbing whatever's left over or
generally taking blood uh or they might
be very disease oriented in which case
you really want that tumor tissue that
was removed right or you really want um
uh the cereal spinal fluid because what
you're looking for is really a central
nervous system process uh the
demographic data which is now more and
more passively collected from electronic
medical records but obviously can be
from a a survey also clinical data is
really interesting I spend a lot of my
time with ICD codes ICD codes were meant
for me to be able to bill for me to say
to the insurer this patient's really
sick or this patient's not that sick
right and that's how we communicate with
payers to justify the hospitalization or
procedures or whatever else there is
they were not intended for research and
the things I say match the current
condition someone might have respiratory
failure they need a ventilator but it's
because they just had surgery and they
had anesthesia and need to recover it's
not because they primarily have a of you
know failure of their lungs and so
there's a lot of things like that where
what you're actually getting in ICD
codes is secondary and not primary and
and those codes don't always discern
those things so my biggest lesson or my
biggest message about clinical data it's
like buy or beware for your ICD codes um
and we've looked at things like defining
ADHD or Autism Spectrum disorders using
ICD codes across nine centers of our
congenital heart disease study and the
diagnostic rate R ranges from 1% to 60%
and I don't think it's because the
people who are receiving care are
different right there's differences in
how the codes translate to words at each
Hospital
um there's differences in how many codes
people click uh and so that's one of the
things about clinical data is I was
always just kind of as much as you can
do a little bit of ground truth checking
uh even if it's at a single Center or a
couple of centers uh or use something
like natural language processing as an
orthogonal measure that that's one of
the important things to think about for
clinical data um there's often directed
study evaluations they might be you know
directed neurodevelopmental testing we
do a lot right so we'll do these tests
called the Bailey tests which is how
know someone's fine motor versus gross
motor versus cognitive performance um so
there can be directed study tests and
those are often the ones that are most
high quality because they'll many times
be standardized right where everyone
who's administering the test has gone
through the same training uh there's
some crosschecking where it might the
test might even be administered by two
different people for some period of time
to make sure that there's a lot of
cohesion so many times it's those
directed study evaluations that are the
most harmonious uh to use between
centers or overtime
uh and then the questionnaires which are
just lovely because many times that's
the only way you get the participants
experience of life right how do you know
someone's quality of life how do you
know someone's you know job satisfaction
or you know uh social satisfaction it's
not going to be from directed testing
right and many times those outcomes
aren't necessarily what studies are
designed to report uh but can be a
really significant thing especially
again thinking about Pediatrics it might
not be whether your IQ is 82 or 86 that
matters it might matter like are you
know what's your uh degree of completion
of your education what's your degree of
autonomy as you've you know become a
teenager things like that um so that's
where those questionnaires sometimes
actually do have better information than
or different and and more applicable
information than some of the
questionnaires or some of the directed
study
evaluations um and so if you do get your
bio sample there are really expensive
really fancy ways to handle bio samples
and there's really simple ways and they
just all have trade-offs and right it
depends somewhat on your your resources
and your scale uh so one of the when
you're running a large biobank people
have uh as many automated steps as
possible because that minimizes any
contamination spent a long time looking
at um like uh 16s sequences of samples
we had collected in Uganda transferred
to Pennsylvania sequence transferred
again to New York proteomics and there
was just so much decontamination you had
to do from every step that was handled
and we saw as many batch effects um from
each step of the handling as sometimes
we would see biologic effects right so
really automated handling um and uh
minimized repackaging is really
beneficial the most common things that
are stored are plasma serum and DNA uh
some people like the children's biobank
now are moving towards what's called The
Buffy coat it's just that it's white and
fluffy looking but it's basically the
white blood cells and that's because if
get blood the nucleated cells are the
white blood cells right and so that's
where your DNA is going to be you don't
need all those red cells they don't have
that information and so that's why
people are often now moving to just
saving the white blood cells um
sometimes the primary bone marrow cells
are also saved because those can those
if stored appropriately in liquid
nitrogen or colder uh can be turned into
IPS cells in the future so people like
those as like a way of being able to
access that particular genotype again
um other things can be urine which is
great because it comes for free cerebral
spinal fluid which we um which can often
be obtained in a slightly larger volume
during a routine procedure without any
injury as long as it's a small volume
and that's one of those ones that we try
not to miss when it's available um
because it does let you know um very
specific things about you know brain
metabolism infections things like that
um and then the big thing if you really
do have a biobank and are meeting all
the criteria is you have to have very
careful protocols about all the backups
uh and so you can't just have a freezer
and slap a sign on it that says biobank
actually as I'm sure you've all seen you
have freezers with monitors on them that
alert someone immediately if the
temperature is has changed and you also
have to have a plan for like if your
freezer goes down where do your samples
go immediately uh and things like
that um and so again this can be
anywhere it doesn't have to be a fancy
bio Bank it can be in a single lab um
all of our samples that don't go to the
main biobank just go to a shelf in my
freezer like it's it's fine they can go
there they just have to have the right
protections and and security uh
sometimes it's a collaborative biobank
within an institution of which we know
of many right there's the MGD MGB
biobank which is lovely children's has
ours um they're these National and
international ones uh We've accessed a
lot of these to be able to get cardiac
tissue right for first uh
transcriptomics because not everyone
saves cardiac tissue uh and so that's
where some of these big International
and and National Banks can be really
useful for rare samples uh that many
researchers can
use um and then just if you are a
biobank that's storing any intact human
cells you need to be in a facility uh
with a human tissue act license and so
that's why when you're filling out your
protocols for these things there are a
couple more requirements um but it's
actually not that onerous to meet the
the requirements there uh the major
things are you have to make sure you can
link your sample and your consent right
you can't keep anything that you can't
prove uh was was consented you have to
show that there's that tracking of
samples and fail safe measures and then
Security in the building as well as the
local
freezer um the metadata is one of the
most variable things we I just last
night was assigning Mondo terms to
everyone in our niku biobank of which
Mondo doesn't cover a lot of like
neonatal disorders I was learning uh so
there's all the right there's the ICD
codes we talked about which are billing
codes which are meant to talk to payers
and so some people have tried to Dev
other codes which are more designed for
research and better capture uh someone's
actual I don't know molecular mechanism
of disease if you think about grouping
in that way uh and so
the you know there's often raw clinical
data that goes in as well as these other
kind of like meta metadata labels that
kind of uh accumulate the information
from the chart there's some really nice
ways to use Red Cap to just capture data
directly from the EMR which is always
the most it's kind of like the automated
handling of metadata so instead of
someone typing something in and missing
a decimal point uh you can actually just
have it directly pulled they still might
have missed the decimal point when they
first entered it but it at least is one
step of less
contamination um there's many
deidentified research uh deidentified
portals where you can actually do things
on uh the EMR
directly uh the data might be RW might
be curated and knowing the level to
which it was curated can be be helpful
um um and especially if there's a
phenotype that's already been studied in
that biobank reach out to that group and
get their phenotype labels right because
you you hate to have a different result
from the same cohort only because you
had a slightly different definition and
so even if what you're going to do is
purposefully different understanding um
the difference in your your kind of
labeling of a similar diagnosis can be
helpful to contextualize why your
results might differ from someone
else's uh and then again this is where
sometimes disease oriented biobanks will
have very different clinical data
available and that can be the benefit of
maybe going back and forth between a
more specific biobank and a more General
one in terms of maybe the the power you
get from the increased metadata and
granularity versus the power you get
from a large population and so I think
the two can work together nicely and
then you always want to know about the
sample when was it collected like we're
collecting placenta right now if you
collect it more than half an hour after
delivery it's like the pancreas it just
degrades and so you want to know when
that sample was collected some things it
doesn't matter as much cardiac tissue we
worked with up to 72 hours after it
became available that it was collected
uh and that's been just fine uh but
really knowing for your sample what that
time was and then making sure that that
time was not a factor in what you're
measuring later uh to know for yourself
that there wasn't a quality difference
um any processing right RNA later was
all the rage and now it's terrible and
so knowing if it was stored in different
kinds of media even if that was later
removed can really impact your ability
to interpret any kind of sequencing or
other processing that you do after um
the amount many times there's a standard
standard allocation so after the sample
arrives it might be split into five Alo
quats uh and so just knowing like how
many Alo quats remain for that sample
can be important for making your plans
because often there's like a an approval
that's needed if you're taking that very
last Alo quat um and so that's often an
important metadata uh and then the time
between collect and
freezing then there's all the study
deriv data there's a lot of measurements
now and as I mentioned this is area
that's just exploding in terms of people
giving all their digital device data um
the sequencing and many times it's
actually a requirement of accessing
biobank specimens is that you return the
raw and process data back to the biobank
so that it can be generally available
sometimes there's holds where you get
exclusive access for one year or two
years um after a study period uh but
that it comes back to the whole
community and that's been a common way
for biobanks to be able to grow their
resources while still allowing the
researchers who are funding the
sequencing to have time to complete
their
analyses um and then all the the
questionnaires that we had talked
about um so these are just some of the
kinds of biobanks that I think about and
we'll we'll cover very briefly one of
the oldest ones are actually these human
umbilical cord uh blood biobanks right
so if you go to deliver your baby people
will ask oh are you planning to bank the
cord blood and so literally what happens
is right there's this long umbilical
cord that uh connects the infant to the
placenta and they can just put a clamp
on each side and it goes in a a freezer
container and off to the biobank um and
so there uh the public ones uh are then
accessed by individuals who might need
some sort of stem cell therapy in the
future and since you are usually unable
to donate to yourself it's these public
Banks uh that allow uh for uh for
appropriate cells to be found for
individuals in need it's also they're
also available for research and so this
was one of the first examples of like
large scale biobanking there's 28 public
ones in the US uh and so that's uh yeah
one and so this was just showing the
number of people per year who had a uh
who received a treatment uh using the
publicly banked uh Core Blood uh from
from deliveries that people had donated
so it's you know in 201 it was a th
people that year and just seeing that it
was benefiting a good number of people
over 16 as well that's the green part of
those bars so it's you know benefiting
not only children but adults too to have
done this banking um that's all
Anonymous and
public um this is just from the all of
us they have very lovely documentation
again if you're going to use a biobank
if you just go onto their websites they
have all their protocol documents there
so you can see like what's actually the
standard operating procedure how are
people approached what's the sample
handling um and so one of the unique
things about all of us um was just this
idea that there were uh there was not
only recruitment at hospitals but also
within the community and that was part
of how they made sure that their
participants were as representative as
possible um and then the other thing was
that this could be done a lot of it can
be done online so whether you were at
home or at one of these centers you
could go online create an account give
your informed consent uh contribute all
the data again you didn't have to sit in
someone else's room you could sit at
home and contribute all this data um you
would then go into your appointment
which I think I'll show you on the next
slide um and you can also uh view your
own data and results from that
too uh this is an example from the UK
biobank this was a little older this was
from 2007 I couldn't find their more
upto-date
protocols um but they specifically said
that they aim in their in everything
they did with bios samples was to
maximize scientific return within
budgetary limits um which I think is
kind of what all of us try to do all the
time um but they took 45 MLS of blood uh
from their participants and then they
separately processed plasma serum white
blood cells and red blood cells so that
those four sample types were available
uh and
so uh they also took 9 MLS of urine in
their protocol they talk about why they
they considered a lot of other things
right so and this here which I liked was
some of their reasons why they
considered um some sample types but then
excluded them and so you know hair
people think a lot about longer term
environmental exposures with hair but
they just didn't know how to get it Tu
like it just seemed like the processing
was higher than the the benefits at that
time um saliva they weren't choosing
then there are some salivary biomarkers
I think now we feel differently about
that knowing how much better our
sequencing has gotten um and so you know
it I it's also nice that these protocols
will often have some of that why so even
if you're thinking about starting your
own you can see how other um other
institutions made their
decisions and this was that all of us
study visit that I was telling you about
um and so there was all of that
participant provided information which
again that part could be at home and so
if you because we often think about like
what's the burden of participation and
definitely the time spent at a visit is
a high burden we're often in places
where you have to find parking someone's
had to be with the rest of your family
members
there's many things that come into an
in-person visit so reducing that time
can really increase the ability of
someone who's interested to participate
um and so really what they did in person
was the physical measurements you have
to sit for five minutes it's like the
white coat hypertension phenomenon as
well as if you were rushing there right
so there was there was the five minutes
of waiting so that you could get real
Baseline Vital sign measurements right
uh because if your heart rate is high
but it's because you just you know got
that very last parking spot but it was
seven blocks away it's different than if
you have a baseline risk of tacac cardia
um and so then they would do their their
measurements and their bio uh bios
specimen Collections and they very
specifically were making these visits as
short as possible in terms of the um the
interface
time uh they also had a special
pediatric protocol and so this is again
where you think about having a special
subset where they were actually
collecting different types of metadata
and so knowing uh I mean I think we all
know that there's lifelong impacts of
early Health exposures uh but sometimes
it can be more useful to have those data
if your overall participation also
started early in life so that you can
track the impact of multiple of those
different uh exposures and so they had
very uh specific questions about
environment about um uh early life
adversity that they collected as well
and so that was like a special cohort
with a larger metadata
set and so what's our niku biobank uh
it's a subset of our overall Hospital
biobank which actually means that we end
up having like three different versions
of our consent as I'll show you in a
minute uh because we try to kind of
optimize someone's participation to
maximize their potential benefit from
being involved um similarly to kind of
lower the the bar of of participation to
meet where people want to be we have
many different tiered levels of consent
so it can just be the excess samples so
no extra needle pokes you know not even
a saliva swab just whatever is in the
lab and left over will be
saved uh we can do a separate blood draw
so you can have a you know when there's
going to be a blood draw anyways we can
take one extra tube and freeze that um
sometimes parents give us samples we do
a lot of genome sequencing um for people
who participate in our our study and so
we'll often get parent saliva is what we
tend to do now but they can also give a
directed blood sample if they want um
and then all of those things are with or
without genetic studies and so it's
really that people can choose what's
right for them and it might change over
time sometimes people are not initially
interested in genetic testing but then
if they're still with us one or two
months later their their desire for that
type of information may have switched um
so we we do kind of check in with
families as they remain there um one
sample is stored for free by our biobank
with the caveat that I have to share it
with anyone who wants it which is fine
because that's why I got them um and any
additional samples come to our
lab um so first yeah I have a question
about your previous slide where you said
that um like over time they might change
the permission do you also have an
option where they might actually take
back permission and then how does that
like actually happen if people have
already started like working with those
samples or analyzing it like having to
backtrack um you have to kind of Mark
the moment that they with Dre uh consent
and then you do have to remove all of
their data from the we remove it from
the metadata we discard their samples
appropriately for biohazard uh and then
we remove all of their data from
anything you can't remove what's already
been published right um but you would if
there's anything that is not yet
published you would remove their sample
from
analysis it's one of the reasons to have
a really good consent right like you
want people to feel comfortable with
what they have agreed to and it's
another reason to have a really good
deidentification
right uh we recently did uh paper where
we looked at genetic causes of hypotonia
in infants um across five continents
right sounds so fancy um but it really
meant that we couldn't report anyone's
variant because though it sounds like
it's across a big population it was a
100 people and those variants don't
exist in Nomad they don't exist anywhere
right that we know of except for those
infant sometimes and so it's incredibly
identifiable uh and so part of it is
also thinking like what you report and
though it would be useful to have the
variants reported for scientific
progress and that's my inclination is to
want to do that um we did not in that
particular case because it was such a
small number of individuals um so it is
that that balance and I think always
making your best decision if you were if
you were a participant knowing the range
of participant opinions how do you kind
of best carry out what they what anyone
consented to through the entire scope of
the
project um yeah so we were luckily
already at an institution that was
accredited so we didn't have to do that
part um we did get IRB approval and then
every time you change something even if
you're changing your brochure they might
ask you to change other things too so
that your entire protocol is up to date
with current requirements because as you
know what's what's considered
appropriate with genetic data is
constantly changing um and so that's one
of the things to know is that she'll be
making lots of edits but it's all so
that you do the right thing um and
sometimes it's just lots of back and
forth um the other thing that goes so
there's a study protocol there right
which is like why we're doing it
inclusion exclusion criteria um kind of
what uh what someone's what what we're
going to do as the study team and then
there's the informed consent which is
the version of that that is captured but
for the participants to read you need to
represent what you're going to do you
need to represent what your aims are you
need to represent what the potential
benefits and uh downsides would be and
then actually everything up there
everything goes in the IRB like a
brochure if you change who's on your
brochure you need to put a new version
up there um if you're going to post on
social media to try to contact
participants you need to have that on
your IRB and you need to have your
posting um on the IRB also and so
there's a lot of things some of the
things that you might feel like are just
automatic after you've gotten your
approval um are actually still still
looked at uh by the IRB um and then
there's the things that don't
necessarily go there but it's the how to
do things right so it's the standard
operating procedure that says you know
Hannah my lovely ra who does all of
these consents like it's it's how Hannah
does it and when Hannah goes to medical
school it's she will pass it on to the
next person to make sure that they do
the approaches in the same way that they
consult you know contact interpreter
services in the same way just so that
it's consistent year a year and if we
make changes we try to be very
purposeful about it uh because small
changes in how you do things like that
might impact who's recruited and uh and
whatnot um and so why did we do it in
particular and I'll be I'll be brief um
is like I mentioned I just think that
there's a lot of a lot we can learn um
from our patient population uh it's for
both people inside our group people in
the hospital uh and then external
collaborations where it might be hard to
get together you know more than two or
three people with a particular diagnosis
at your hospital but if we all work
together we can actually get a um a
large group uh a lot of it with all of
these biobanks is to prepare for
research right we have these transient
contact opportunities uh and so we
wanted to to start that contact UM many
times funders will be glad to provide
your sequencing if you already have the
samples having been burned for years by
people who said oh it's great look at my
recruitment rate so far I will show up
with 5 million samples um and then those
samples never appearing right so people
often want everything to be in hand when
you're making your proposal and so this
is one way of enabling that um there
these very rare events uh and again I
think especially for trainees being able
to kind of maximize their impact in the
time that they have is good and then
there's just questions we haven't
anticipated yet um I get new questions
every time I go to the hospital and so
being able to kind of have those things
for the people who not just have the
question but are then going to act on it
um is is good and then as mentioned
sometimes it's just complimenting
ongoing research so you know uh the
Pediatric heart Network which has always
been a very clinical study oriented uh
collaborative by the NIH for congenital
heart disease they didn't used to
collect bios specimens but now they've
added to their kind of registry and
study cohort a bios specimen uh because
they have tremendous data about patient
outcomes and exposures and are now able
to genetic risks into that um sometimes
yeah and so that's an example of a a
clinical trial uh and then many times um
it can be just a useful a useful tool to
complement other kinds of bioinformatic
projects that are going
on so sorry this is so small but this
this is our triage in the NICU which is
basically that if someone we approach
everyone for participation in research
um and if there's kind of no no concern
for an underlying genetic diagnosis
they're in with RSV bronchiolitis I
don't think it was their genes that gave
them the virus it was probably they like
lovely but slobbery two-year-old sibling
right um we would approach them for the
biobank participation where we would
take excess samples or whatever they
would like to consent to um if someone
came in with um a particularly a
particular difference on their brain MRI
that makes us very likely to think that
it's a a genetic diagnosis um but let's
say it was five years ago and we only
did exome sequencing we then would have
consented them for research genome
sequencing right um but if they had a
very specific condition where perhaps
their genome sequencing now was negative
but they have a muscular distrophy and
we think that RNA sequencing is actually
going to be what shows us where the
pathogenic variant is then we actually
had them enroll in the man Center where
there's very prospective and purposeful
uh testing of things like you know blood
RNA um or doing long read sequencing to
look for those missing variants and so
that's where we try to have everyone
have the maximum benefit from their
participation so if they if it's a if
it's a diagnosis that the man Center is
going to go after we have them consent
there because I think there's potential
participant benefit um but if Manon
Center declines then we do our genetic
testing on a research basis um through
our
project um so yeah so we take any baby
uh we take anything they want to give us
um and then this was just our example
project and this is my last slide uh is
just that there was a fellow who was
really interested in the immune response
to viruses and we're one of the only ncu
in the state that will take babies
who've been home and babies who have
known uh infectious diseases right
that's us niku are usually like only if
you were born in that hospital do you
get to enter uh and so we're a unique
place to get to see babies who have
severe impact of respiratory illnesses
and so the fellow was able to use our
existing IRB uh we've been able to
collect the swabs that she would like
and store them in the lab um and that
probably saved her like a year of
regulatory applications um so that was
nice so uh I think biobanks are an
important piece of our biomedical
research there are some ex Exemplar ones
that have really transparent policies if
you're ever thinking of starting one or
just want to know more about how they
tick they have lovely documentation and
sometimes small local bio Banks might
still be useful for the particular
question that you're you're looking in
and whether this is a um you know a
Community Foundation that has made their
own registry and now has biobanks
biobank samples or whether it's at a a
hospital they could be nice resources so
thanks so
much thank you so much if we have some
quick questions just walk up to the
microphone thank you thank you for the
talk um given that these biobanks are
meant to last forever um how do you kind
of achieve the financial stability or
health of the biobanks yeah I think the
big ones do it as we saw right UK
biobank used to be um a application to
access and now there's fee for Access
right and so I think a lot of how people
are becoming sustainable is um using fee
for access to you know keep those lovely
uh automated machines going I think a
lot of biobanks are also partnering with
groups who pay for access to the data on
large scales right so if you're someone
who has a commercial interest in a
particular Gene um being able to have
access to you know do the proteomics to
go along with all the diagnosis I think
we've seen Partnerships like that right
like regeneron um uh has has you know
many ways in which they're able to
commoditize the data from their
sequencing cohort and bios specimens uh
to be able to make it sustainable um but
fundamentally there's no
you know like you could imagine any of
them collapsing and then it would just
be up to the community to find someone
who would be able to kind of take over
the the specimens that have value um I
think much of the
data right because there's the data
infrastructure and there's the the um
biological specimens infrastructure and
in some ways those are able to be
separated too um but it does seem that
in our current climate that there might
be some some changes either in requiring
access to do many of the experiments or
paid access to do many of the
experiments that we used to do um for
lower no cost um or some of them not
being sustainable like even at our
Hospital right we we downsized all of
our samples pretty significantly um to
be able to keep just the highest yield
ones great thank you so much that was
wonderful um and I think we'll stop
there for time thanks everyone thanks
Sarah