the MIT energy initiative presents
investors awake to the risks of climate
change written by Calvin
hanik poppy Allenby a senior Financial
executive and the former managing
director of Black Rock has been
analyzing the link between climate
change and investing for more than two
decades for a lot of that it was quite
lonely Alan B said during her December 1
address at the MIT energy initiative
fall colloquium
there weren't that many other people
looking at this field and over the last
3 or 4 years that's completely changed
increasingly Alan B said investors are
opening their eyes to the long-term
risks of climate change risks that
threaten not only the planet but also
their
portfolios and as more institutional
investors come to see climate change as
a threat to their beneficiaries they are
taking action to fight it still she
cautioned that much more work remains to
be done
various investors are at very different
stages in considering climate change
Alan be said once they realize this is
something they need to think about they
need to do a risk assessment then
develop a strategy when you look at
different institutions she said some are
just the very beginning of this
journey a changing
landscape although there is a compelling
moral case to be made for taking steps
to mitigate climate change alanb noted
that institutional investors such as
Pension funds are bound by a fiduciary
duty to their
beneficiaries that is to say they are
obligated to put their client or member
interests ahead of their own I talk
about fiduciary duty because one of the
things that has really changed in the
investment space is that more and more
investors are beginning to see climate
change and climate risk as impacting
their fiduciary duty said Alan B that
has been a shift in my mind it makes
total sense if you're a long-term
investor
and you're thinking about beneficiaries
that need assets over the next 10 or 20
years and thinking about risks that
might materialize and climate change in
particular then that makes a lot of
sense but that is not where we were 5 or
10 years ago Alan be spent more than 20
years at the multinational Investment
Management Corporation Black Rock for 17
of those years she was a senior
portfolio manager responsible for
managing multi-billion dollar funds
investing globally in companies across
the traditional energy sector and also
those involved in sustainable energy and
mitigating climate change most recently
she was head of the corporation's Global
product group on several continents
where she provided oversight for nearly
$1 trillion worth of assets and played a
critical role in developing black Rob's
sustainable product strategy where I
like to think the finance industry is
heading is integration she said this
means thinking holistically about pretty
much every decision you make as an
investor and thinking about how climate
risk is going to impact that investment
that is a sea change the mentality
around how people
invest divestment versus
engagement for many years activists have
pushed for institutions including MIT to
divest from fossil fuel companies by
keeping fossil fuel companies out of
their portfolios these activists argue
institutions and individual can exert
social political and economic pressure
on these corporations and help to
accelerate the shift to renewable energy
however alanb argued instead for ongoing
engagement with fossil fuel companies
reasoning that this better positions
investors to push for change my personal
view with divesting from oil and gas
companies is that's not very effective
Alan be said I think there might be
examples where you have very specific
companies which you don't think will be
involved in the transition to Net Zero
and investment might make sense or if
you've got an Institutional Investor
where it is imperative that their
investment is entirely aligned with
their values so certain Charities it
might make sense but if you really care
about change I think you need to keep a
seat at the table in a way Alan be said
divesting from fossil fuel companies
lets leaders at those organizations off
the hook reducing the pressure on them
to make meaningful changes to their
operations imagine a company that is
incredibly polluting and not sustainable
and they have shareholders that are not
happy but they don't do anything and
those shareholders decide to divest she
said what happens as a result of that
potentially is the company goes oh that
was easy I didn't have to do anything
and the activists have gone away and
potentially those assets end up being
owned by people who care less so that is
a risk when you think about
divestment challenges and opportunities
alanb outlined several challenges with
climate focused investing but also noted
a number of opportunities both for
investors looking to make money and
those looking to make a change among the
challenges for one some investors simply
still need to be convinced that climate
change is a problem they should be
working to solve also Alan be said
there's a lack both of a formalized
methodology and of specialized
investment products for climate focused
investing although she noted that both
of these areas are improving finally she
said it remains a challenge to encourage
investors to direct capital toward clean
energy projects in developing
countries investors can both set
themselves up for financial success and
mitigate climate change Alan be said
through Savvy investments in either
distressed or underpriced assets if you
can buy assets that are discounted or
cheaper because people have real
concerns about their environmental
footprint then you can work with those
companies to improve it and therefore
reduce the risk and improve the
valuation she said Alan be pointing to
the high cost of waterfront property in
areas that are vulnerable to rising sea
levels also suggested that the long-term
risks of climate change have not been
fully priced into many assets my view is
that we've really gotten our arms around
that she said from a purely investment
perspective that's also an opportunity
additionally Alan be noted the recent
rise of ESG funds which invest with
environmental social and corporate
governance guidelines in mind some of
these funds she noted have outperformed
the larger market over the past several
years when we talk about climate change
one has a range of emotions alen be said
sometimes it can feel like we're not
making enough progress and one of the
nice things about being here at MIT is
that whenever I'm here I always feel
hopeful about the future and quite
hopeful about all of the technology IES
and work that you are doing to
transition Energy Systems and move
things forward when you look at what's
happening in the financial services
sector there's still a huge amount to do
but it's also quite a hopeful story