Hello out there. Can people hear me? Oh,
nice one. People at least can uh
intuitive what it means when I wave at
them. Uh okay.
Uh so today we are going to uh you know
continue our discussion of probability
and in particular we're going to talk
about um a very naughty word uh what we
call random variables.
Um unfortunately a random variable is
neither random nor a variable. Uh so
like it it's just called this for
historical reasons. Um
it's very silly. I'm just going to be
referring to them as RVs through the uh
through the lecture. Um this is what it
stands for, but uh you know it's it's
it's a very silly name. It's it's a bit
of a misnomer. Okay. So
what is an RV?
Okay.
So basically what an RV is like it's
neither random nor a variable. It is a
function.
uh from our sample space to say the real
numbers. Okay, that's all it is. It's
just it's just a function. Um you can
have you know like the the co-omain r is
not particularly important. You could
have uh you know you could just easily
have co- doain n. Uh you could also have
complex valued rs but like you know we
won't we won't be looking at those in in
this class um for now. You can just
think of it as you know real valued
function. Okay, whose uh domain is the
sample space. Okay,
so for instance
suppose
our sample space or you know suppose uh
you know our our experiment is we're
we're flipping three coins. Okay. Uh so
we're going to assume for now that they
are fair. They're you know they're
they're you know normal physical coins.
They're independent. If you flip one,
it's not going to affect the uh the
outcome of any of the others. Uh so what
is our sample space in this case?
What does our sample space look like? Am
I giving the right lecture? This this is
61200, right? Okay. Uh
if we flip three coins, what are the
possible outcomes?
Yeah.
Yeah. each of them being heads or tails.
Okay, so if we flip three coins,
our sample space is going to be
so each coin can take either, you know,
it can be either heads or tails. There
are three of them. So we're going to be
considering, you know, ordered triples
of, you know, either heads or tails.
Okay.
And maybe we've got this function f that
maps uh an outcome omega to
the number of heads
in omega. Okay,
so that's one possible uh one possible
RB, right? We're taking an outcome
and we're mapping it to some number,
right? The the number of heads. Okay,
another one could be
uh maybe instead we just look at you
know is the first uh coin flip heads or
tails.
Oh, maybe I should not write it as uh
that just yet. So one
if and only if uh first flip
is heads and it's zero otherwise.
Okay,
so these are two examples of of RBs.
There are functions that map outcomes to
real numbers. Okay, does this make sense
to everybody?
We could have one more that's like h of
omega
is one
if uh all three coins match
zero otherwise.
Okay.
So these are just you know examples of
RVs that we could have.
Uh so G and H in particular
have a special property right they are
either one or zero.
So this is what we call an indicator.
So all that an indicator is is just an
RV whose co- doain is 0 and one. Okay,
that's that's all it is. It's just a
binary RV.
Okay.
uh and uh RVs and in particular
indicator RVs naturally give rise to
events. Does anybody see how
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly. So the answer was you
know in particular if you have an
indicator RB right you can look at the
set of outcomes where it's one right
that's an event or its complement is the
set of outcomes where it's zero okay so
uh more generally
if we have
an RBF
uh and a value x
uh we can define the event.
So a slightly weird notation here fals x
okay
uh by the set of outcomes
omega where uh f of omega equals x.
Okay.
uh or you know you may also have seen
the notation uh f inverse of x.
Okay. Um inverse here meaning inverse as
a relation not as a birectionraction. Uh
but if you haven't seen this notation
don't worry about it. Um this is what we
uh this is what we call it in terms of
probability. Okay.
Uh and uh you know vice versa. If you
have uh an event, you can define the uh
indicator of that event.
So if we have uh an event A
corresponds
to the event
here, this is the notation I was trying
to use before. Uh blackboard bold one of
a
Uh this notation here just means the
indicator right that is one precisely
for the outcomes in a.
So
if omega is in a and zero otherwise.
Okay. Does that make sense? Does this uh
correspondence make sense? Yeah,
question
explain the notation again. Okay. Yeah.
So, um basically we are taking an event
and using it to define an indicator RV.
Okay. Um this notation is just how we
write it. Uh this is called the
indicator of A.
Okay. And all it means is just the the
indicator RV which takes the value one
on all of the events in A and it takes
the value zero on all of the events that
or sorry all of the outcomes that aren't
in A. Okay. Does that make sense? Cool.
Uh any other questions?
Okay.
Or actually maybe maybe we should keep
that visible for now.
We can also define uh a different kind
of event
f greater than or equal to x
right. Uh so that one you know obviously
doesn't make sense uh for for complex
numbers but you know for real numbers or
any any subset of the reals this this is
perfectly fine. Okay as you might expect
uh this is going to be the event uh that
contains all of the outcomes
omega such that f of omega
is greater than or equal to x. Okay.
So analogous to what we just defined.
Okay.
Um
and more generally we could say you know
f in some set s or maybe t right because
s is our sample space.
This is going to be omega such that f of
omega is in t.
Okay,
does that make sense to everybody?
so as you might expect, we can, you
know, condition on these events uh just
as we can, you know, condition on any
other events.
uh we can also have you know
independence of random variables just as
we have you know independence of events.
Okay sorry
for instance
now we could talk about the probability
that uh uh what did we call them
uh f
= 2 conditioned on uh
h = uh 1.
Okay.
So what is this probability? What is it
saying?
Yeah.
Oh, is that a hand or just Okay, sorry.
Yeah. Exactly.
So we're looking at the probability that
we have exactly two heads conditioned on
all three coins being the same. Okay. So
you know we could think of these as two
events A and B. uh you know if we
actually you know write out what this
means this is the
probability that uh f= 2 uh and
h = 1
uh divided by probability that h = 1
right uh and this probability in
particular is zero
okay so all three coins are the same.
It's impossible for exactly two of them
to be heads.
Okay, does that make sense to everybody?
Like we're basically doing exactly the
same thing with these weirdly written
events as we did with, you know, any
other events. Okay.
Uh and we can also extend this to
independence.
But I should point out here that things
are going to diverge a little bit.
Okay.
Uh so we're going to say that two uh RBs
are independent.
If and only if
for all possible uh x and y.
Uh
probability that f = x
uh and
v = y
equals the probability that f= x
times the probability
that t equals y.
Okay,
so it's similar to what we had for
events,
right? How is it different?
Well, for events, right, we didn't have
this quantifier, right? We just said
that two events are independent if the
probability of their intersection is the
same as the product of their
probabilities.
Right? Now we have to quantify
everything. Right? It's not just enough
to say you know the the event that each
of them you know takes value zero is
independent. We kind of need that for
all possible pairs of values that they
could take. Okay. Does that at least
intuitively make sense?
Yes. No.
Some nods, tentative nods at least.
Okay.
Uh or you know just as with uh you know
normal events we could equivalent
equivalently say
uh for all xy
either
uh probability
uh that t equals y
equals zero. Whoops, not of or
uh
probability that f= x conditioned on p=
y
is the same as the unconditional uh
probability.
Okay,
so if you prefer you could think of it
in terms of uh conditional probability.
So we're basically saying that two
random two two RBs are independent if
and only if like all of the events that
they generate you know the events f= x
and gals y uh those are all independent
events
and you know intuitively it's saying
that uh if we know something about the
the value that that g takes for instance
it doesn't tell us anything about what
value f takes.
Okay.
So, example
uh where were they? FG and H.
Are those independent? So, are F and G
independent?
Who thinks F and G as I've defined them
over there are independent?
Show hands.
Yeah. Who thinks they're not
independent?
Few hands. Who's still fast asleep?
Oh. Oh, that's unfortunate. Um, I'm
sorry. Me, too. Uh,
okay. So, does anybody want to give me
an explanation one way or the other?
Presumably, somebody is not asleep. I
don't need an explanation for why you're
asleep.
Anybody else? No.
Yeah.
Yeah. Exactly. So
if g is zero right that tells us
something about the value that f can
take right it cannot be three.
Okay.
So the events g is zero and f and three
or f is three are not independent
events. So the rvs are not independent.
Okay. Uh or perhaps even more obvious if
f is zero right that tells us exactly
what g is right g must also be zero.
Okay.
Uh what about uh
f and h.
So f is the number of heads. H is one if
and only if all three coins match.
Who thinks those are independent?
No.
Who thinks they're not?
Few hands. Okay. Why?
Yeah.
Yeah. So f basically tells us everything
we need to know about about h right like
h is just a function of f and well
neither of them is is trivial. Okay so
if we know if we know f no matter what
it is we know what what h is okay so
these are also not independent. What
about G&H?
Who thinks G and H are independent?
Hans. Who thinks they're not?
Oh, nobody. Okay. Why?
Yeah,
sorry.
Yeah, intuitively that's what's going
on. The the first flip doesn't tell us
anything about the other two. And in
particular, it doesn't tell us anything
about, you know, whether the other two
match each other and the first flip,
right? Uh so we could, you know,
put it all into here and, you know,
figure it out. But uh you know I will
leave that as an exercise to the reader.
Okay. Uh basically you know no matter
what happens you've got uh uh one in4
chance that the other two coins are
going to match the the first one. Uh and
that matches the probability that uh
that they all match to begin with. Okay.
Okay. Does anybody have any questions
about uh independence before we move on?
people reasonably happy.
Okay,
so next topic is distributions.
Okay, so for those of you who have seen
RVs before, uh this is probably the
context or this is probably, you know,
the context in which you've seen them.
Uh historically, this is where they
started and
more or less where they got their name.
Uh but basically um the distribution
uh is is it's basically a fancy way of
you know talking about the RV without
the underlying sample space. Okay, it's
talking about the probabilities that it
takes each uh each individual value uh
in its range. Okay,
so there are kind of two equivalent ways
to uh to talk about it
uh at least for real valued uh RVs.
So
for an RV uh f
uh we define
the probability mass function
often abbreviated as PMF
uh
of omega oh sorry x
and this is just the probability
that f equals = x.
Okay.
So, does that definition make sense to
everybody?
Right. the the PMF of an RV is just
talking about the probability that that
RV takes each individual value in its
range.
Okay,
so you could think of this as uh you
know a probability space uh over R.
Okay, so that's that's how RBS
originated like you know talking about
probability spaces over R. Equivalently,
you could also define
the cumulative
distribution function.
CDF
as CDF
subfx.
This is just the probability
that uh f is less than or equal to uh x
which is the sum
y less than x of the probability
that uh f equals x.
Okay.
Uh so I should warn you that um you know
if you see like in many other
probability classes
uh a PMF would or something analogous to
a PMF would often be called a PDF
uh for uh probability density function
instead of probability mass function. Uh
and I believe in particular the uh the
text does this. Okay. So for the
purposes of our class, those are the
same, right? Uh if you see PDF, uh you
know, think to yourselves PMF. Uh we
prefer this notation because this is
what's used for uh discrete
distributions. But you know, if you have
a continuous distribution like uh well,
it's kind of hard to talk about the
probability that a uniform random
variable over, you know, the interval
from 0 to one takes exactly a particular
value, right? like that's, you know, if
you throw throw a dart at a dart board,
you're you're never going to hit one
particular point essentially, like you
you have null events. So it it doesn't
really make sense to talk about the
probability that you hit a particular
point because that's always zero. So
instead you look at the the density
function instead. Okay. But for discrete
distributions, uh you know, it does make
sense to talk about the the probability
that you hit exactly one particular one
particular value. Okay, does that make
sense to everybody?
So for this class you know PMF and PDF
are the same. If you see continuous
probability they won't be.
So often it is useful to talk about uh
RBs in terms of their distributions like
in terms of their uh PMFs or CDFs uh and
just kind of forget about the uh the
underlying sample space. Okay. So, a
couple of examples
um indicator
uh indicators like what does the PMF of
an indicator look like?
Well, it can only take two possible
values, right? So, it's going to be zero
everywhere except at zero and one. Okay.
And you know at one of those it'll take
the value P. At the other one it'll take
the value 1 minus P.
Okay. Uh and we call these uh we say
that these have a Bernoli distribution.
Okay. So
there uh PMFs like basically look like
this. you'll have you know two values
everywhere else
it's zero. Okay. And the uh
CDF
is going to look like this.
Okay.
Oh, wait. No,
should be at one.
Okay.
Uh, another useful one is a uniform
random variable.
Okay.
So a uniform RV right it can take uh you
know any value uh with with equal
probability. So in particular let's look
at uh
uh an RV on the set up to n.
Okay.
So here the PDF
of X is going to be 1 / n
if and only if uh X is in this set
and zero otherwise
and CDF
of X
what is that going to be?
Well, you're basically going to have a
peacewise function, right? So,
it's going to be zero up until one.
Then at one,
it'll go up to uh 1 / n. At two, it'll
go up to 2 overn, etc. Okay.
So, you got something that looks like
that.
So, uh yeah, question
Uh oh. Explain again how I got to this
graph. Okay. Um so
uh well the CDF right is you could think
of it as like a a sum of the PDF or uh
or sorry sum of the the PMF right. So
you know the CDF at uh at one right it's
the probability that this uniform RV is
no greater than one like how can that
happen well only if you you take the
value one that happens with probability
1 overn right so at one
you know we should get probability 1
over
Okay,
anything between one and two has that
same probability, right? The the CDF of
one and a half, right? The the
probability that we're no greater than
one and a half is the same as the
probability that we're we're no greater
than one, right? Because we can't take
any value between one and one uh one and
a half. Okay, so like all the way up to
two, it's going to be constant.
Okay. And then at two, it's going to
jump up by another one overn,
right? Because at that point, right, the
probability that we're no greater than
two is the probability that we take
either of these two values, which
happens with probability 2 overn. Okay?
So we kind of get this like pie-wise
step function that uh you know at every
integer it increases by 1 over n. Does
that make sense?
Is there any way that you can, you know,
beat random chance? Is there any way
that you can do better like win with
probability greater than 1/2?
Right? It's not really obvious.
Okay, so let's simplify the game a bit.
So suppose I guarantee that one of the
boxes has more than five candies and the
other one doesn't.
Can you then beat random chance?
I'm seeing some nods. Yeah. How
how do you beat random chance in that
case?
Yeah.
less than five.
Yeah, exactly. You you you pick either
box, you open it, right? If it has more
than five, that's that's the the box
with more, right? You stick with that.
If it doesn't have more than five, well,
the other one does, so the other one has
more. Okay? So, if you know that one of
the boxes is is, you know, has more than
five and the other one doesn't, then you
can win with certainty, right? Like,
it's still not probabilistic. Well, I I
suppose you could think of it as
probabilistic, but like you can
definitely do better than a half.
Okay.
Does this give you any ideas as to how
you might win with probability greater
than a half, even if you don't know that
one of the boxes has more than five
candies and the other one doesn't?
Any ideas?
Yeah.
Okay. So, uh your colleague's proposal
was do it anyway, right? Uh if you, you
know, open up a box with less than five
candies, you switch and hope that the
other one has has at least more than
than uh what you found. If you open up a
box that has more than five candies, you
stick with it and, you know, hope that
the other one has fewer.
Um,
does anybody see a problem with this?
What is the probability of winning?
Yeah.
Yeah. So,
let let me try and rephrase that. Um I
haven't given you any probabilities of
like you know uh what the probability is
that that I've put a certain number of
candies in in either box right so it
kind of depends on what I've done right
there are kind of two cases right if I
have split them like you know greater
than five and and and less then you win
with certainty if I haven't then you win
with probability exactly 1/2
right if they're both greater than five
right you you win if you picked the uh
the bigger one to begin with. And if
they're both less than five, then you
win if you picked the smaller one to
begin with.
Okay? So, you're still not doing worse
than a half, but you're not doing
better, right? Or you're not
guaranteeing that you're doing better
because, you know, I made no guarantees
as to how I was splitting up the
candies. I may put fewer than five in
both of them. Or, as I did this time, I
may put more than five in both.
But can you use a similar idea to get
greater than 1/2 probability no matter
what I've done?
What if instead you know that I've put
more than two candies in one box and not
the other?
Can you win in that case?
Anyone?
If if you know that I've put more than
two candies in one box and not the other
one, how do you win?
It's It's not a trick question. I
promise.
Like just as what your colleague said
with five, you can open up one of the
boxes and see whether or not it has more
than two candies, right? If you know
that one of the boxes has more than two
candies and the other one doesn't,
right? You can identify which is which
by, you know, looking at one of them.
Okay,
so
why don't I start writing some of this
down?
So
if one box
so exactly one box has uh you know at
least one candy
right then you know we open up our box
we see whether or not it has any candies
and if it does we take it. Okay so we
can win.
So if we know
that two boxes, sorry, if one box has
greater than or equal to two candies,
right?
If we know this,
we can win, right?
If we know that one of them has greater
than or equal to three candies, we can
still win.
Okay,
the problem is, you know, we don't
actually know any of these.
So, what can we do about that lack of
knowledge?
Yeah.
Yeah. Exactly.
So, we don't know, but we can guess,
right? like one of these uh 10 things
has to be true,
right? I I've told you that I've put
different numbers of candies in each
box, right? So there is some divider.
One of these at least one is true. Like
maybe I've put zero and one and 10 in
the other, in which case they're all
true, right? But at least one of them
has to be true. So if you randomly guess
one of them and just say like like
pretend that you know it, okay? and you
know adopt the strategy we were just
talking about, right? If you guessed
correctly, then you win.
And if you didn't guess correctly, as uh
your colleague in the back pointed out,
you still don't lose at least like you
still win with probability 1/2.
Okay, does that make sense to everybody?
So our strat
is guess the threshold
Okay. And then assume it's true.
Okay.
So what exactly is the probability of
winning if we do this?
Well, it's going to be we can use uh the
law of total probability. It's going to
be the probability that we win
conditioned on being correct,
right? times the probability that we are
actually correct
plus
the probability that we win
conditioned on being wrong
times the probability that we're wrong.
Okay,
so what are each of these probabilities?
What's the probability that we win if we
made the correct guess
or a correct guess rather?
One. Yeah, exactly. Okay.
What's the probability that we made a
correct guess?
Yeah,
one10enth. Uh, well, it might be
greater, but it's at least one/10enth,
right? So, it's at least 1 * 110th
plus what's the probability that we win?
Condition on being wrong.
Yeah.
12. Yeah.
Right? So if we guess wrong, you know,
say without loss of generality, our
threshold is uh is too low, we're going
to open up a box and we're going to
stick with it regardless of what it is.
Okay? So we win if and only if we happen
to pick the uh the bigger one. Okay? So
we win with probability 1/2.
And what's the probability that we made
the wrong guess?
Yeah.
Nine times. Yeah.
So, what is this going to be? This is
going to be what? 55%.
Okay.
So, it's not that much better than a
half, right? But it is better.
So, does that make sense to everybody?
So we we Oh, yep.
Yeah. So we we we don't actually know
that, right? Um so it's it's possible,
right, that I could have, you know, a
large difference in in the number of
candies in each box, right? Uh we do
know that there's at least a onetenth
probability that that uh you know, we
picked the right threshold. Like it it
could be more than that, right? Um
but like you know if there are say two
correct thresholds then instead of this
you have uh 1x 210 plus 1/2 by 8/10.
Oh uh because you know these are the the
thresholds that we're picking from
right. So like we we do know that there
are uh between zero and 10 candies in
each box, right? So we're going to pick
a threshold that's you know in that
range. Okay.
But yeah, if if I have uh you know put
you know
if I've allowed you to pick you know
more than one correct threshold then
that just you know increases by 5% per
you know candy difference between the
boxes.
Okay
are people reasonably happy with this?
Okay. So this is an example uh of a
problem where we've taken something that
isn't exactly a probability problem to
begin with but we've turned it into a
probability problem and we've given what
we call a probabilistic algorithm for
solving it. Okay. So, uh yeah, if you do
it deterministically, right, you know,
there's not much you can do, right? You
you pick a box and you know, if I happen
to feed you the correct one, then uh you
know, you you win. Uh but you can do
much better if you introduce randomness
into your algorithm and make random
choices. Okay? So, you will see a lot
more of this in uh in doub uh 61210 and
even more of that in uh 1220. And uh
Eric, do you remember 5210, 5220?
There are other randomized algorithms
classes there. There are some uh you
know higher level ones whose numbers I
forget that are you know entirely about
randomized algorithms. So it's it's a a
very powerful tool that that is
frequently used in computer science to
uh you know make your algorithms uh you
know more efficient or make them better
in in various ways.
Okay.
Uh,
so now that we've finished with our with
our candy boxes,
unless anybody has any questions
questions about candy boxes before we
move on?
No. Okay.
So
let's give another example of a very
common distribution
called the binomial distribution.
Okay.
Uh so this is a distribution that arises
very frequently in computer science.
Okay.
And in fact we've already been kind of
dealing with it implicitly in this
class. We just haven't you know named
it. Uh it's parameterized by two values.
So
bin of n comma p.
Okay.
And uh basically this models uh the
following experiment. So we have n
coins.
Uh these are all, you know, they're
coins. They're independent. Uh you know,
flipping one doesn't affect, you know,
any of the others. They're all mutually
independent.
Okay.
And they're biased, right? They're not
necessarily fair coins. Each comes up
heads with probability P.
Okay.
And then
the RV X which is the number of coins
that come up heads
is or has the uh binomial distribution.
Oops.
Run out of frame. Sorry. Okay,
so we've already seen this uh you know
in particular with with P equals 1/2,
right? Flip several fair coins and uh
you know count the number of heads. uh
we did that at the very beginning with n
equals 3. Okay. But more generally,
right, you can flip n coins and they can
be biased towards heads with probability
p or away from heads as the case may be.
You could also model different things
like you know maybe you've got a very
complicated device. Each component you
know may or may not fail. They're all
independent. fail fail with probability
P. Uh then you could also count the
number of failures. This would also
follow the uh binomial distribution.
Okay.
So can anybody tell me the uh PMF of a
binomial distribution?
Okay. So, sorry. Could you repeat that?
Nice.
Okay. Why?
Yeah. So if if you look at you know
sequences of uh of these coin flips
right um there are n choose x sequences
right that have exactly x heads
right and if you have a sequence with
exactly x heads right uh you know each
index which is a heads that's heads with
probability p and each index that's
tails of which there are n minus x of
them is tails with probability n minus
uh sorry 1 minus p.
Okay,
so product rule says that we can
multiply all of those together. We get p
to the x 1 - p to the n minus x, right?
And now each of those uh each of those
sequences, you know, they're distinct
outcomes.
Uh each occurs with the same
probability. So we just count them and
then multiply by that probability.
Okay, does that make sense to everybody?
Okay.
Uh, what about the CDF?
Can anybody tell me what the CDF of the
binomial distribution is?
Yeah.
Mhm.
Yeah. Exactly. So let's say from i = 0
to floor of x of pmf
of i.
Okay,
so that is frequently how you'll want to
compute a CDF in practice, right? Like
it it it is often, you know, easy to
figure out the uh the uh PMF
uh and then you can just, you know,
compute sums to give you uh to give you
the CDF. Um there are other cases where
it's easier to go in reverse, right?
Like maybe the CDF is easier to uh to
compute and then you can compute finite
differences to get back to the PMF.
Okay,
but uh you know the fact that that both
of these are equivalent ways of talking
about the distribution
uh means that you know you can use
either one of them and the other one can
be computed fairly easily from from the
first.
Okay.
Uh
okay.
So unfortunately right there are
summations involved though. So
that can be a little bit unwieldy.
uh so it is often easier rather than
dealing with the CDF you know exactly
to approximate it and this might be good
enough for you know whatever purpose you
you have in mind
okay so
let's see how we can do that or actually
let's um
For the sake of notation, let's
abbreviate uh the the PMF. Let's just
call it F. Okay. So,
and big F can be the CDF.
Okay.
So, how could we approximate
f of say alpha * n.
Any ideas?
Well, first why don't we write out you
know what exactly this says in terms of
factorials.
So this is going to be n factorial /
alphan n factorial
uh time 1 - alpha * n factorial
times uh p to the alpha n 1 - p uh to
the
1 - alpha
n.
Okay. Now, who remembers sterling?
Oh, hand. Yeah. Okay. How can we use
sterling to uh to simplify this?
Oh, was that not a hand?
Oh, sorry.
Well, we we've got a bunch of factorials
here, right?
If we approximate each of these
factorials using sterling,
then we're going to end up with the
following. So n factorial is going to be
roo 2 pi n
uh
actually let's um
let's kind of split up the terms nicely
over
2 pi alpha n uh 2 pi 1 - alpha
n.
Okay. Uh
then multiply this by
okay. So for the top we have uh n minus
uh sorry n / e
to the n. Uh on the bottom we've got uh
alpha n / e to the alpha n
uh 1 - alpha
uh n / e to the 1 - alpha
n.
Uh and then these p and 1 minus p terms
we can just uh keep as they are.
to the 1 - alpha.
Okay,
so a little bit unwieldy as it is, but
we can simplify it.
Okay,
uh how can we simplify this?
Well, those n's and e's over on the
right, those aren't really doing
anything, right?
We've got n / e to the alpha n e 1 -
alpha * n. And here we've got n / e to
the n.
Okay, so we can get rid of those.
This is just going to end up being 1 /
uh
is it uh alpha to the alpha n 1 - alpha
to the 1 - alpha * n.
Okay. And over here we have 1 /
2 alpha * 1 - alpha * n
And then our P terms remain.
Okay.
What next?
Well, let's try shoving these P's and
one minus P's in here. Okay, so this
carries down. We've got uh p / alpha
to the alpha n time uh
1 - p over 1 - alpha
to the 1 - alpha*
n
What can we do next?
Well, what happens if we take the log of
this and then raise two to that power?
It's going to be the same thing, right?
But as it turns out, that's going to
make our life a bit easier. So, this
continues to carry down. So, two to the
uh this is now going to be n times
alpha log of P / alpha
plus
1 - alpha
* log
of 1 - P
/ 1 - alpha
and parentheses
here.
Are any of you here physicists,
proficient in physics?
Does that uh exponent look familiar to
anyone?
Well, as it turns out, this exponent,
even though it looks kind of ugly,
uh it's always negative except for when
uh p equals alpha.
Okay,
so what happens when p equals alpha?
Well, we've got a log of p over alpha
here. That's zero. Log of 1 - p over 1 -
alpha, also zero, right? So the exponent
is zero there. And if p is not equal to
alpha, uh then you know because log is
concave, this is just going to be uh
it's going to be negative. So we've kind
of got this this bump right at P= alpha
and it's going to get exponentially
smaller everywhere else.
Okay, does does that make sense to
everybody?
So if we actually put in some concrete
values, so for the sake of uh
simplicity, let's say P equals.5
uh N equals
say 100, right? Evaluating, you know,
100 choose whatever is going to be a bit
of a pain, right? But if we just use
this approximation,
then uh you know, we can get uh we can
get actually some pretty good
approximations.
So if alpha also equals 0.5,
right?
What happens?
Well, as we've just established, this
exponent is zero, right? So, this this
term is is one here. We've got 2 pi
alpha * 1 - alpha * n, right? So this is
going to be 1 over pi uh sorry 1
over 2i * 12 * 12 * n.
Okay. So that's that's going to simplify
to pi n /2. It's going to be uh
f of 50
is approximately equal to uh 1 over
square of pi * 50.
Okay.
And as it turns out, this is about uh
0.08.
So pretty small.
What about alpha equals 0.25?
As it turns out when alpha is 0.25 right
like this you know it doesn't change too
much but this term starts decreasing
exponentially
so we actually end up with uh f of 25
is about uh 10us 7.
Okay. So if you flip a 100 coins, right,
the probability that you get exactly 25
heads is minuscule.
Okay.
Uh and I think the last lecture, right,
Eric, is about tailbounds. Do you
remember? Okay. So, uh yeah, last
lecture we'll we'll discuss how to get
bounds on the uh uh on the CDF uh
instead of just the uh the PMF.
Um, and
yeah, as it turns out, it's kind of
funny, right? The probability
that you get at most 24 heads, right?
How do you think this compares with the
with the probability that you get
exactly 25?
Turns out that this is actually smaller
than uh f of 25.
So because it's decreasing
exponentially, right? The CDF is also
decreasing exponentially. So it turns
out that it's it's more likely to get
exactly 25 heads than to get fewer than
25 heads, which might be a little bit
counterintuitive, right? like for larger
numbers that's that's definitely not
true, right? Like it's much more likely
that I'll get uh fewer than 50 heads
than exactly 50 heads, right? Because
the uh the probability of exactly 50
heads is 8%.
Right? So the probability of fewer than
50 heads is going to be, you know, half
of the complement of that, right?
So what's that? 47% 46% I can't I can't
math. 46%. Right? So, it's much more
likely that you get fewer than uh 50
heads than exactly 50 heads. But then
because it decreases exponentially as
you get close to the tail, uh turns out
it's it's more likely to get exactly 25
than fewer. Okay. Uh so that's all we
have time for today or sorry that's all
we have planned for today. We have a
little bit of time left over for
questions if you want to uh come up and
ask and otherwise we will see you next
week.