[Music]
one of the biggest breakthroughs in
generative AI has been the ability of
large language models to actually
generate code some of these models can
actually produce code that is difficult
even for humans to write however as we
prob deeper we find that they're
actually quite different from the way
programmers think about code they have
different skills they have different
capabilities and so what we find is that
they can provide substantial help if
working collaboratively with a person
and in particular when the feedback
comes from a human then there is a
really substantial difference in terms
of the set of problems that the model
can actually solve humans do get
significant productivity benefits when
using them to help them write code for
more MIT moments from MIT open learning
like subscribe or follow