All right. Well, last class we started
to talk about the forier method in
uklidian space in R2. And the big goal
for the class is to to digest the forier
method, finish that story, but also just
to digest it in general. Um and then
after that if there's time we'll start
to introduce civ theory which has a
extremely parallel story um that but
that was developed by a different group
of people and with with somewhat
different goals.
Um okay so to digest the 4A method I
wanted to go back for a second to the
finite field 4A method where everything
is a little bit cleaner and to make a
point about it.
Okay. So,
so our main lema in the finite field
case was like this. If you have a set of
lines um in FQ2
[Applause]
and then you add up their characteristic
functions
then it has a a big constant part and
then a small high frequency part.
And then the conclusion is that f is f
plus f high
where um fnot is a constant function.
It's the number of lines over q and from
that you can compute its l2 norm.
Um l2 squared is number of lines
squared.
Um and uh fi is has mean zero and we
have a bound for its alorm.
Okay.
So, um, so one thing that you can get
out of this is a bound for the L2 norm
of f. If you add these together, you get
a bound for the L2 norm of f. Um, and
it's worth saying that that bound for
the L2 norm of f has a elementary proof
that's really simpler than this. Um, let
me let me show it for comparison.
to help put this in perspective.
[Applause]
Okay.
So let's call this elementary L2 bound.
Okay. So there's a first lema that if
you have two different lines
and then you take the sum over x
l1 of x l2 of x uh this is at most one
could do that. Uh it's just saying that
two two lines intersect in at most one
point.
Okay. And we can use this to make an L2
estimate. So here's the L2 estimate.
Um
if f is the sum l and l of l of x
then
f l2 is bounded by the number the number
of lines squared plus number of lines
times q.
Um here's the proof.
So f L2^2
is the sum over L1 and L2 of sum on X L1
of X L2 of X.
Okay. And now each one of these sums we
can control with this lema. All right.
But we have to be a little bit careful.
If L1 is equal to L2, that's a different
situation. A line intersects itself in a
lot of points. So we're going to split
up this sum. So it's the sum L1 equals
L2
plus the sum L1 did not equal L2.
Okay.
So here we have um only L choices for L1
or only L choices appear in this sum and
each one of them contributes Q.
And then over here we have L squar
choices for the lines but each one of
them contributes one.
So that's the
all right so if you compare this with
this it looks something looks kind of
similar right we get an L2 bound up
there of L^2 + LQ that matches L^2 + LQ
that we get here with this quite simple
argument.
Okay, but the main lema has more
information than that. Um,
well, there's actually a really two
cases. If Q uh is bigger than the number
of lines, then this term dominates here
and this term dominates here. And in
that situation, the main lema doesn't
really have much more information than
this because the function fh is not that
special. But the other regime is that
the number of lines is much bigger than
Q. So this dominates that
and in that situation most of the L2
norm is coming from F knot which is very
special because it's constant.
Um so so the um
so the main lema has an important piece
of information beyond this that when we
have many lines this sum is almost
constant and and then it's a constant
plus something that's much smaller.
Okay,
so that uh that is also true in spirit
for the main lema in the real case, but
the main lemon in the real case is a
little bit more complicated. So I wanted
to do this first and then we could look
for the analogous thing in the more
complicated real case.
Okay. So what did the main lema say in
the real case?
[Applause]
Main lema in the real case.
So now we have t is a set of 1 by r
rectangles
and um uh s t is a smooth approximation
of the characteristic function of t and
the exact meaning of that is explained
in agonizing detail on the homework.
Um okay and then we have a function
which is the sum over all the t and t of
this smoothed characteristic function of
t.
Okay. Now our bounds are going to depend
on how these tubes are clustered.
So n subt of r
is the maximum where t tilda is a two
little r by two big r a rectangle or
tube of the number of tubes in there.
So picture is we have this tilda and we
see how many middle tubes are in tilda.
Okay so that those are the hypotheses of
the main lema and then the conclusion is
that you can write f uh you can break it
up into pieces of different frequencies.
So the pieces are labeled by a sort of a
width parameter little r which is a
diatic number between scale one and
scale capital r
of f sub little r
where the f sub little r has two good
properties. It has a frequency support.
The support of f little r hat is
contained in the ball of radius 1 / r
and it has an l2 norm uh bound f sub
little r l2 2 is bounded by um the
number of tubes times this
um packing clustering uh parameter at at
the scale little r um times big r
Okay.
Okay. Now, one thing you could take away
from this is you could take away from it
a bound for the L2 norm of F by just
adding up all of these. And like before,
that bound for the L2 norm of F has a
simpler proof. Um, and for context for
understanding this, I'm going to show
you this simpler proof.
>> Yes. FR is orthogonal.
>> The FRS uh the FRS are orthogonal. Um
yeah, the FRS are orthogonal. Um if we
didn't know they were orthogonal, we
would lose a little bit when we we'd
have to do Koshy Schwarz to compute the
L2 of F. Um but the amount that we would
lose would be like a log R, which is
relatively minor.
Okay.
Okay. So, let's do an elementary L2
bound.
All right. So, like before we when we
expand out the L2 norm, we'll have to
estimate the integral of one tube times
another tube. Um, but one tube times
another tube is a little bit more
complicated than one line times another
line. Two lines always intersect in a
point, but two tubes intersect in a
different amount of area depending upon
the angle between them. So, we're going
to keep track of that.
All right. So, let's make a definition.
the um width r in between t1 and t2
is the minimum uh r so that there exists
a two r two little r by two big r
rectangle tilda that contains them both.
So if this is t1 and this is t2
then um
that would be t tilda and that would be
r.
Okay.
So now
if I want to integrate t1 of x t2 of x
dx
that's going to be about big r over the
little r associated to these two tubes.
Why? Well the integral is the area of
their overlap.
And if I I'll sort of sketch their
overlap over here. Um not a great
picture. Um this is around one because
it's contained in one of the tubes. And
this axis here is uh like big r over
little r.
As little r gets smaller, they overlap
more and more.
Okay, good. Um so now we can make it L2
bound.
Let's say that the integral of f2
bounded by the sum uh sum over little
ratic
of
t * n subt of little r * big r over
little r.
Okay. And the proof is that we'll just
break up this sum as a bunch of sums
bunch of integrals like this. group them
according to the value of little r and
we'll see what happens. This is what's
going to fall out.
So here's the proof. Um so the integral
of f2 is the sum t1 and t2 in our set of
tubes integral of t1 of x t2x.
Now this integral here depends on the
value of little r. So let's group these
by the value of little r. So that's the
sum over little ratic
sum over t1 and t2 with that value.
So the r associated to t1 and t2 would
be about this r
and then I have this integral which I
can bound by the lema. So I get big r
over little r.
Okay. Now I need to know how many pairs
of tubes are in this list here. Well, I
can choose T1 and T1 as far as I know
could be anything. So I have number of
tubes choices for T1. But once I choose
T1, I choose need to choose another tube
T2 that fits into the same rectangle
with T1. So the number of choices for
that is about N subt R. It's what it's
measured.
So this is bounded by sum over r diatic
of um
number of tubes
and n subt of r big r over little.
Okay, great.
So let's compare this with this.
This is exactly what we get by just
adding up all those L2 norms uh for the
for the F subr.
Okay.
Um
so this proof is a lot easier than the
proof of the main lama that we did last
time. Um let's compare the L2 bound in
the main lama.
[Applause]
If I were to erase this information in
the main lema, then all that would be
left is the L2 bound.
But there is this information and this
is helpful. This is telling us something
more. Um, okay. Now, depending upon what
we know about this thing here, different
terms might dominate this sum.
If it so happens that the term little r
equals 1 uh has the biggest contribution
here um then we don't learn very much
because the our information about the
support of f1 hat is is the same as the
information we already had about the
support of fhat. So we'd have nothing
new. uh but it may well happen that the
that the the term where this is biggest
is has little r much larger
and then f little r has this frequency
support condition. It gives it some
structure some extra information there
that's going to help us.
So let's talk about what what does it
mean about the function f little r that
it's frequency is supported there.
Okay. So uh intuition
we call this the the locally constant
intuition
says that if I have some function g and
the support of g hat is contained in the
ball of radius 1 / r um then
the function g is approximately constant
on balls of radius plus.
So
um you know if the support of Ghat is in
the ball of radius 1 / r then ghat is a
combination of waves cosine waves where
all of the cosine waves have have
frequency at most one over r. So each
one of those cosine waves is not
changing very much on balls of radius R.
So it's sort of intuitively plausible
that after we add them up also we'll get
something that is roughly constant on
balls of radius R.
We'll come back in a little while and
make a precise statement about this.
Okay. So based on this, let me make a
picture illustrating main lama R
main
and then
okay. Um
so
okay so th this will be well so this
will be like a uh each one of those
lines is going to be a one by R tube.
So, I may have a whole bunch of them
over here, sort of like this. And a
whole bunch of them
over here, sort of like this.
[Applause]
And over over in this part of the board,
I might have some that are not uh so
clumped into thick tubes. It might look
sort of like this.
All right. So over here what the picture
I wanted to to give you is that I put so
many thin strokes of chalk one by our
rectangles that they sort of smooshed on
top of each other and they produced with
like a thick stroke.
Um and so this part over here might be
dominated by f of r. So maybe this scale
might be R and F subr
be sort of the sum of this blob and that
blob
and on the other so this so this over
here in blue would be f subr
and on the other hand this over here
would be f sub f sub one all of this
stuff uh is pretty high frequency
Okay. And notice that this f subar is
kind of roughly constant on any ball of
radius r. And so if I were to visualize
the set where f is big.
Um well there might be some bits in here
where f is big
but then there also might be some piece
in here where f is big.
Okay. Um so over here this is where f
sub1 is big and over here this is where
fub r is big.
All right. And and now the kind of
trade-off that happens is we might have
like a very strong bound for the L2 norm
of F1. And so that bound tells me that
this set where F1 is big is small.
And then we have a bound for the L2 norm
of FR. It might not be such a good
bound. It might be bigger. But on the
other hand, FR has this nice structure
that it is constant on balls. So the set
where FR is big is is group is clumped
into these big balls. And so that gives
us so the area might be larger than this
area. But the fact that it's clumped
gives us some other geometric
information about it. It's kind of
simpler.
Okay. So let's pause there. I was uh
recapping the main lema in the real case
and um I sort of tried to have a picture
of what it's telling us.
Okay.
Okay. So the next thing that we should
do is this is sort of nice but it is not
a actual precise math statement. So in
order to really make use of this idea,
we need to now replace this intuition by
by uh an actual precise thing. So let's
let's do that.
So here's a precise
version
of the intuition.
[Applause]
Okay. So um
okay. So how do we use
the fact that the support of g hat is
contained in something like v of 1 / r.
There's a a
nice trick for for doing this for using
this which goes like this. So suppose I
have a function
um ADA
so that ADA of C is one for all the C in
the ball of radius 1 / R.
There are many such functions ADA and
and you probably the mo the most useful
kind is to suppose that ADA is also
smooth and compactly supported.
Okay. So g hat is equal to g hat * a
ghat is supported on this ball and aa is
one on this ball.
And now I can take the inverse for a
transform of this and I get that g is g
convolved with a to check.
Okay. Um so this uh follows from and is
almost equivalent to this but it's often
a little bit easier to work with.
So next to work with this we should
figure out a little bit uh what this
function a check is like.
So properties of a check.
Okay. So for one thing a check of x is
less than
um r the minus2 in the plane
that just follows from the triangle
inequality to compute a check. We
integrate ada times a complex
exponential and ada has size one and
it's supported on this ball.
So we get this
um but in addition to that if if x is
large then we get cancellation so the
next thing is that
aa check of x um decays rapidly so I'll
I'll write something precise in a second
decays rapidly
if x is bigger than one and so the
reason for that is aa check of x is the
integral of c e 2 pi iix xc dx c and um
we can bound this integral by
integrating by parts um and uh this is a
nice and smooth thing and if x is bigger
than this we integrate by parts many
times we get a strong estimate from this
okay the estimate has the following
shape I start with an r to the minus2
just to compare to what I had there and
then I have um
uh x over r and I can put here
I can put here any exponent I like but
negative a th000 will be fine for us.
So if x is more than teeny bit bigger
than r this thing is very small.
Okay.
[Applause]
All
right.
So now let me set um C subR to be the
norm of A check.
And so C subR has bounds that we just
computed.
So C subar of X is bounded by R the
minus2 and it's rapidly decaying
if X is much bigger than R.
Um and now we can state a lema.
So if the support of g hat is contained
in the ball of radius 1 / r
um then
the norm of g of x is bounded by
the norm of g convolved with cr x.
And the proof is is
basically just what just what we what we
have. So we we started with G hat is
Ghat time ADA and so G is G convolved
with ADA check.
Now take the triangle inequality. The
norm of G is less than or equal to the
norm of G convolved with the norm of A
check. And that's the proof. The norm of
A check is called CR.
Okay. And um since we're going to
eventually be thinking about L2 norms,
it is helpful to have a tiny variant of
this lema where we have the norm of G
squar instead of the norm of G. And it's
sort of convenient to prove it ahead of
time instead of in the middle of what's
coming. So uh lambda 2
if the support of g hat is contained in
the ball of radius 1 / r then the norm
of g ^2 is bounded by the norm of g ^2
convolved with cr.
Okay. So be before we do the the
rigorous proof, let me say something
about how I think about this. Um, so
this here says that the norm of G is
bounded by this is sort of like taking
an average. It's like the norm of G is
bounded by the average value of the norm
of G on a ball of radius R.
Um
and then if you had that by Koshy
Schwarz you would also have that the
norm of G squ was bounded by the average
of uh the the norm of G squ on the ball.
Okay. So that so that's what we'll write
down now. So the norm of g
of x squared
is bounded by the first lema by the norm
uh by the norm of g convolved with cr at
x
squared.
If I write out what this convolution is,
it's the integral norm of g of x - y
cr of y d y all squared.
And now I can do a koshy schwarz. Um I
want to do a koshy schwarz to get this
guy squared with one of those. So when I
do my koshi schwarz
my first factor will be integral norm of
g ^2 x - y cr of y
and my second factor will just be the
integral cr of y dy.
So you could to see that this is a valid
Koshy Schwarz. The sort of total number
of exponents of G is two. Total number
of exponents of C is two. That matches
what's on the other side.
Okay. And now um this thing here is
bounded by one which follows by follows
from our bounds for how it behaves and
which goes along with the intuition that
um you know that this integral is one.
And so this convolution is like doing an
average.
Okay. And this thing here is just the
right hand side. This is G ^2 involved
with VC.
Okay. So this is the way we will
rigorously make use of the fact that FR
has frequency in there.
Um and it corresponds visually to this
picture that I think I'll erase now
that FR looks sort of like this. And the
places where it's big are consists of
some blobs with balls of radius r.
[Applause]
Okay.
Um
so now we can use our main lama to prove
some projection theory estimates.
All right. So our setup
is that we have X is a set of unit balls
in the two-dimensional ball of radius R.
D is a set of directions. So it's a
subset of S1, which is 1 / R separated.
and s measures the size of the biggest
projection of x in here. So it's the
maximum over all the thetas in my
direction set of the theta projection of
x.
So that's our setup and we're going to
try to bound these different quantities
in terms of how the directions and how
the spheres are clustered. So remember
nx of r is the maximum overall possible
center c of the amount of x in the ball
of radius c of center c and radius r.
And similarly n subd of row is the
maximum
over arcs in s1 of length row of the
number of directions in the ark.
So that's our setup
and the projection theory estimate that
comes from this method I'll call it
theorem 2 r theorem 2 in the real case
says that uh if we have the setup
then the number of directions is bounded
I
s big R / X times the maximum over
little R of um NX of little R and D of
little R over big R over little R 2.
Okay, so this is a little bit messy. Um,
and we'll eventually make some
hypotheses that allow to simplify it.
Um, but just notice for now that this
estimate takes account of how the set of
directions is clustered and it takes
account of how sorry it takes account of
how the set x of unit balls is clustered
and it takes account of how the set of
directions is clustered.
Okay, so the proof uh follows the uh
idea of the proof we did in finite
fields and and makes use of the main
lema. And here's our setup. So for every
direction in our direction set, let's
say t theta is a set of at most s we
could say exactly s one by r tubes t
that cover s.
So if this projection has size s then
looking at the fibers of the projections
I get s tubes that cover my set x.
Okay. Then um t my master set of tubes
will be the union over all the
directions t theta and f is going to be
the sum over all these tubes of the
smoothed approx uh smoothed um
characteristic function of the tube.
Okay. So we observe that for every x in
x um
f ofx is at least the number of
directions.
All right.
So now we now we use our main lama and
we break up f into these different frs.
use main lema.
Um, and I there are only logarithmically
many different choices of R. And so one
of them has to make a pretty big
contribution at each of these points.
And so I can I can choose R.
So that all right. So so I have X * D^2
that's smaller than the integral X of
F2.
And now there are only a few Rs. So that
should be somewhat smaller than a like a
log times the integral over X of R 2.
Okay.
[Applause]
Now the first thing I might try here is
if if you look at the statement of the
main lama it has an upper bound for the
L2 norm of FR and I could plug in that
that upper bound and I would bound this
I would get something out of it
but that's not the optimal thing to do
here. Um dep well depending on what we
know about X depending on what we know
about this. So to get some intuition,
let's look at this picture that I
haven't managed to erase yet.
[Applause]
So we're trying to understand this
thing, the integral overx of fr 2. So
let's add an x to our picture. Uh do I
have any more colors?
So x in this picture is going to be
yellow.
And x may look something like this
depends a little bit on nx of r. If nx
of r the biggest that nx of r could be
is r 2. If it's that big then x could
fill in this whole thing. But if nx of r
is smaller than r^ 2 then it's sort of
like the picture that I drew when x is
only a small fraction of this ball.
And in this picture it would be lossy to
estimate the integral over just x of fr
2 by the global integral of fr which
would include the whole orteal.
Okay. Um so we're going to try to do a
bit better than that by using our lemas.
uh about the about the locally constant
property of the function fr.
All right. So I'm going to erase this
but I'm going to leave this picture here
for our intuition.
All right. So we have the integral overx
of fr 2 that is I'll just rewrite it as
the integral of 1x
fr.
Okay. Now if I want to use the locally
constant property of fr 2 it means I
should I could use these lemas and in
particular I can use lema 2 which is
sort of well set up to deal with a
square. So this is bounded by the
integral of 1x *
fr 2 convolved with uh cr
and um if you write out what this is and
do fubini this is the same as the
integral of fr 2 times the
characteristic function of x involved
with E R
does that step something you see that
yeah okay let's do it so the algebra is
like this I have the integral 1x of x
and then I have this convolution which
is the integral fr of x - y cr of y d y
No, let me do it the other way.
Okay. So now what happens if I fubini
that
um that's the integral
fr of y integral of 1
x of x c of x - y dy
okay it doesn't look quite right yet and
it actually reminds me that there's a
little something else that's helpful to
say about cr Um
uh so you can also add here that CR is
radial. It implies that it's symmetric.
Yeah, I should probably have mentioned
that earlier in my plan. Uh so the
reason you can do that remember CR was
the 4A transform of some bump function
ADA. If your bump function ADA is
radial, it for a transform will be
radial. So so this guy is radial and
symmetric. Okay. And then because that's
symmetric,
I can switch those. So that's the
integral fr of y integral 1x of x c of y
- x uh sorry this one is this one is dx.
Uh so that's the integral of r of y 1x
involved with cr of y.
I feel like there also should be a nice
image of what's going on in this
integral.
um like we have this imagine for a
second that this was the characteristic
function of a set. It's not quite true,
but it's not far off either. So I have
one set and I have another set.
But before I multiply them together,
which would mean intersecting the sets,
I fatten out this set here by a distance
r. So I take this this call this set y.
I take y, I fatten it out by r, and I
intersect it with x.
And that's kind of the same thing as
taking X and fattening it out by R and
intersecting it with Y because I could
describe both of them like this. I'm
looking for pairs of points, one in X
and one in Y. The distance between them
is at most R. If I say it that way, it's
symmetric.
And and that's what's going on here.
I guess that's a fancy way of saying I
just took this integral and I wrote it
like this.
And now remember that the function CR is
symmetric. Now the whole thing is
symmetric symmetric in in exchanging
these two functions.
Okay, cool.
Okay, so now we've written it this way
and the intuitive meaning of this is
I've averaged the characteristic
function of X over balls of radius R.
Um and so uh this is bounded by
nx of r / r 2. So this is the integral
of that guy over a ball of radius r
and then I'm picking the average. So I
divide by the area of the ball of radius
r.
Okay.
Um so to check this a little bit more
carefully we have to use the bounds that
we have for this CR thing which are over
here.
So it's bounded by 1 / r^ 2 on the ball
of radius r that would give the average.
Then it also has this rapidly decaying
tail which to be careful we should take
account of. Um but what what it
contributes is is uh is smaller than the
first term the main term.
Okay. So that's how we bound this. This
is now a number. So we can take it out
of the integral and we just have left
the L2 norm of fr 2. So we plug in our
bound for that. So we have it's bounded
by nx of r / r 2. You can think of this
thing as the density of x at scale r
times the integral of f_sub_r 2. Okay.
And then I just plug in the the bound
for the integral of fr 2. And we'll
write that out. So um okay, we have
number of tubes. We have big r over
little r. We have nt of r. That's this
thing. Then we have n x of r
and then we have r square.
Okay, we are almost done. Um but what
what we have here is number of tubes in
a little r by big r guy and the
information we want to be using is the
number of directions.
So the last step is that the number of
tubes in a little r by big r tube is
bounded by the number of directions in a
little r over big r uh angle times
little r. So here's a picture.
Here's our um little r by big r tube.
Inside of it, I can fit in some tubes in
different directions. So if I pick one
direction, I can pick little r of them.
Um, that's this little r. But they don't
have to go that way. I could also have
them go may maybe the most extreme
direction is I could have them go that
way.
And this angle here is uh little r. The
angle there is little r big.
So all of the different tubes that
appear here um there are they have to
have an angle in a within a range of
little r over big r. So the number of
directions is like that. And then for
each direction then the number of
possible tubes is at most little r.
Okay. So if you substitute this for that
um then this expression becomes the
right hand side of the two.
Yeah.
>> Are you able to kind of use the fact
that the tubes that are at an angle like
you can fit less of them in? Does that
change the bound or do anything
different?
>> Yeah. Okay. So the question was um if we
knew that in a given direction these
tubes um were had to have some spacing.
So we could so we could also measure the
clustering of the tubes in a given
direction. So if we add some information
about that then maybe this would have to
be smaller than little r.
So in our setup
so our setup involves three things but
we only thought about the clustering of
two of them. Our setup involves set of
unit balls X and we looked at how it's
clustered NX of R set of directions D
and we looked at how it's clustered ND
of row and also a set of projections
which each have size at most S but we
didn't say anything about how they were
clustered.
So you could add to this setup something
about how each projection is clustered
and you could then use that to improve
this thing here.
Yeah. So, that could be a little
homework project if anyone is interested
in doing it.
Yeah.
Good. Any other questions or comments?
Okay.
Um Okay. So one uh so this the theorem
sort of naturally falls out from using
the fora method um but it's a little
messy looking and the the the thing
that's particularly messy looking is
this maximum over little rx and d and
there's a a fairly general situation
that we mentioned last time where that
that messy bit gets a lot cleaner. Um, I
don't know that that's so
philosophically important, but it's I
think it's worth mentioning and that
this is the way this the results usually
appear in the literature.
All right.
And and this will allow us to to you
know finally prove the result that we
stated last time.
All right. So um so definition we say x
is housedorf
or housedorf spacing
if nx of r to the beta is bounded by
around x to the beta for all beta
between zero and one.
So when beta is one this is trivial. Um
this is always true but this is saying
that at at smaller scales beta this x is
not too clumped compared to how it is at
the uh the top scale. Yeah.
>> How does the appear there?
>> Ah sorry thanks. There was one uh yeah
there was one other thing I forgot to
do. Um okay sorry thanks. So, okay. So,
the question is um how did we actually
do all this algebra and get the equation
that the inequality that's actually
stated in theorem 2 and thank you for
the question because I left out some of
the steps.
Okay. Um
so now that we have done the main ideas
we're just talking about the algebra I
will erase this
and um so what do we have so far? If you
put together the inequalities we have so
far, we have x times the number of
directions squared. That's where we
started over here. Then we did some
stuff and we ended up here. So that's
bounded by number of tubes time big r
over little r
um times
um
md little r over big r * r. That was
this thing for there.
n x of r over little r 2 and we can
cross those guys.
Now we still have this number of tubes.
What's that? Well, we have s tubes in
each direction. We have d directions.
So this is s * d.
Okay. So now I've gotten rid of all the
extra letters and we only have left the
letters that appear in the inequality we
want. And then the last thing you do is
you get D by itself.
So I take one factor of D and bring it
over there and cancel the two. And I'll
take the X and bring it over here. And
then what's what's left is what's there?
>> Yeah. Can that inequality be made shown
in any scenario
like
any choice of like s x?
Um yeah.
Yes. Okay. So, so the question is is
this inequality ever sharp? And uh it is
uh sometimes sharp although not super
often. And um and the cases that I have
worked out so far when it's sharp are
within this houseorf setting. So let's
maybe do that. It'll all get a lot
simpler and then I can say what the
cases I know are.
Okay. So the house spacing is uh bound
on nx of of little r in terms of the
size of x that looks like this. And I I
coined the term housedorf spacing
because it sort of comes up naturally
when you talk about housedorf measures
and things like that.
Okay. And it's useful in our setting
because
if X and D have housed dorf spacing,
then when you take the maximum
of actually many expressions, but the
one that comes up for us here is this.
Okay, what happens? So, so I assume that
both X and D have housed dorf spacing.
It's important to have both of them.
Then each one of these things get
replaced by some power of X or D.
And um once you have a power law, so the
whole the whole expression will be um
will be uh or another way to look at is
the whole expression will be some power
of little r. Power could be positive or
negative. the maximum will occur either
at one or at big r.
So this guy basically is equal to what
happens at one. Uh nx of one is always
one. Nd of 1 / r is always one. So we
just get one. And when little r is big
r, nx of big r is all the points. Nd of
one is all the directions. And we have
that.
So it's less nasty. And so we get the
following corlary.
So correlary says if we have our setup
and X and D have high direct spacing
then the number of directions is bounded
by
uh
S SR overX * 1 plus SRX * this thing. So
s d uh over r.
Okay. Now this one has an
interpretation. If this term dominates,
you can cancel the d's and it tells you
that s is almost r.
So we get either
s is almost as big as r. r is the
biggest it could possibly be. So s is
almost as big as it could possibly be
or d is bounded by srx.
So that's what we stated last time. The
formula is not as nasty as the general
formula.
>> Yeah.
>> There's also a factor of log in the two.
>> Yep. Thanks.
[Applause]
So the point from the audience was that
I I there was an extra factor of logar
that I forgot to write down. So I'll put
this to represent that. Yeah. Thanks.
Okay. So this relatively clean estimate,
it exactly matches our theorem to
infinite fields. Um I won't write it
down, but the the numerology is the
same. Um and it it's a little nicer to
look at. It still takes some digesting
and um this is sharp in some cases. Um
it's sharp in the case that s is pretty
close to r. So because I I need this the
smallest I could make s would be
something like r / log r and if you take
s around that r log r 1 - epsilon then
this is sharp in the example of a grid
of points grid of unit balls.
Yeah. So that's the main interesting
example when it that is the main example
that I know when it's when it's sharp
and there are plenty of examples where
it's not sharp but that great example is
is important.
Yeah. Um okay I guess it's also a
natural question if we go to the regime
that's not housedorf.
um this theorem added some
junk here to account for for this for
things being more clustered and it's a
natural question is there any scenario
where this junk is is exactly sharp um
and I wondered about that when I was
working on this lecture but I don't know
the answer yet so if anybody wants to
try that's also a nice little project.
Cool.
Okay. So, that was the meat of the class
and that was the the the the thing that
um you know
my my my discussion that I planned about
the 4A method in the real case. So, it's
another good moment to um see if see if
you have questions to digest
and we'll start something a little
different.
>> Yeah. Um for the the maximum term, could
you explain why only like it has to be a
maximum and it's like the part of the
proof that requires taking maximum over
R instead of any given R.
>> Um so I think the question is why do we
have a maximum over R instead of maybe
like a sum over R?
>> Yeah.
>> Where does maximum come from?
>> Yeah. Um so you you could put sum over
little r and the difference isn't very
important because the number of terms is
only log of r and the log of r is is got
absorbed here. But where did this come
from at all? Well, we had this um
function that's the sum of all these
tubes which describes our projection
situation. And then we are the key thing
is that we applied the main lema to this
function. And the main lema said you
could break up this function into a few.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And so one of those pieces is sort
of the important one and that's the one
that appears in the maximum.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Wondering. So in the proof we have to
keep track of all the Rs.
Um in the hos spacing case it seems like
we just there's only two cases. So I'm
wondering if if you do have positive
spacing is it really necessary? Is it
still important to do the static
division?
>> Okay. So the question is in the house
dorf spacing case it turned out at the
end of the day that only two values of
little r mattered in the final
inequality namely one and capital r and
the question was would it be possible to
write the proof so that only those two
appeared and we didn't have all this you
know rather complicated business of
keeping track of all the intermediate
little rs. Um I don't know any way to do
that. I I think the only way I
understand it is to keep track of all
the little Rs and then notice that under
these hypotheses, the intermediate Rs uh
are bounded by the extreme ones.
Okay.
Okay. So, I thought I would say a a
little bit about the history of these
ideas. I did haven't been putting names
next to the theorems and the reason is
that these theorems are small variations
of theorems from the literature and
there are many kind of related theorems
from the literature but so but but let
me tell you a little bit about the
history I think it's interesting I think
these are kind of fundamental ideas and
they were discovered uh independently or
somewhat independently by different
people working on different problems
Um
so the thing that we have been calling
the forier method.
So let's call this history.
The thing that we are calling the forier
method appears in a bunch places
including the following. Um the earliest
that I am aware of is Linux work in civ
theory
which I will introduce civ theory and
tell you what this work was uh in the
today. So that was in the 1940s.
uh a second place the second place I'm
aware of is Roth's work on the Hybrron
triangle problem
which at some point in the class
probably we'll talk about a little bit
in the 70s.
Um Roth was uh he he he knew civ theory
he knew Linux work well and he'd worked
on it but in in this problem he did
something similar that's in uklidian
space and the setup is kind of different
and any so I put it on the list then it
was something like this was done by
falconer in geometric measure theory
so falconer essentially proved um uh the
correlary that I just erosed and that
was around 1980.
Um, and then it was done by Van in the
setting of finite fields. So, lines in
FQ2
and I'm not positive about this, but I
think that many of these people were not
fully aware of others of these people.
Okay. Um, we also mentioned the double
counting method.
and the double counting method um that
that we did. So is it was done by
Calfman
in the context of geometric measure
theory
in the 1960s.
Um and it was done by Gallagher
in the context of civ theory
I think also in the 1960s.
I'm pretty sure that these two people
did not know what the other one was
doing.
Um, and I guess it was probably also
done in the setting of lines and finite
fields in the 60s or 70s, but I don't
know. I don't quite have I don't have a
reference.
And those people probably didn't know
about either of these.
Okay.
Um, so now let me tell you what civ
theory is and how it is analogous to
what we have been doing.
[Applause]
Okay.
So cif theory takes place over the
integers and the main character in civ
theory is taking the integers and
reducing it modulo q for different bases
q
um okay so z of course is the integers
I'm going to write zq for some people
write z mod qz this is the the integers
modulo q
and there's a basic map pi subq z 2 Z
cub which takes an integer and reduces
it modulo Q.
Okay, this map is going to play the role
of our projections. So let me mention
what is analogous.
So we've been talking about maps pi
theta that go from R2 to R or a
one-dimensional subspace or from FQ2 to
FQ.
Um, and now we're talking about the map
pi Q that goes from Z to Z mod Q. Um,
what do all these things have in common?
They are all group homorphisms between a
billion groups.
Okay. Um
so
so what we're going to do in civ theory
is take a take a set which is going to
be now a set of integers and think about
all the different projections of its
integer of the set and think about how
they're all related to each other and
how they're all related to the original
set.
Um so I have another little piece of
notation. So this thing is the numbers
from one up to n which is a subset of
the integers.
Um and let me illustrate projection
theory. Let me illustrate civ theory
with an interesting example of a set
whose projections behave in kind of a
funny way.
[Music]
Okay. So do an example.
Our example is going to be basically the
set of square numbers. It's going to be
the set of little n^ squ where little n
goes from one up to big n to the 1/2. So
it's a subset of the integers from 1 to
n and the cardality is about the square
root of n.
What happens when I reduce this set
modulo p?
Um so if p is prime
when I take pi p of x I get the
quadratic residues and the number of
quadratic residues is p + 1 over two. So
about half of that.
So that's kind of an interesting and
surprising fact. Um, of course if P is
bigger than square root of N, obviously
the size of this projection is smaller
than X. Um, so I might not even hit all
the quadratic residues if I take a big
P. Uh, that's not surprising. But I
could take P significantly less than the
square root of N.
And then um I when I do this projection
I only hit half of the elements in Z my
P and I hit each of those many times.
That's you know it's not something
that's likely to happen randomly. It's
kind of striking.
So one sample question from civ theory
is um uh
how big could a set X be and have all of
its projections be small like this?
And uh what examples are there? How many
sets like this can you find?
All right. Um so using the using his
ideas about civ theory, one of the
things that Linick did was to answer
this answer some of this question. So
theorem of lin
in the 1940s uh it says um if I have a
subset of the integers from 1 to n and
if pi p of x is at most p + 1 / 2 for
every p. Um so there's nothing so
special about this. We could put other
things here but I'm just using this to
compare with the squares.
Um then the conclusion is that the size
of x is at most around n^ the 1/2.
So it says that the square numbers are
just about the biggest set with this
property.
Cool. So we will give two proofs of
this. We'll give a proof using double
counting and we'll give a proof using
the 4A method.
Um
there are lots of hard open problems in
civ theory and one of them is to
understand uh what the examples are. So
the only known examples
only known examples
where where this theorem is roughly
tight
are the square numbers and close
cousins.
So sorry it's messy the square numbers
and close cousins of the square numbers
like you can you could replace this with
another degree 2 polinomial in little n
and it's not hard to see it's it's kind
of equivalent and those are all the
examples
okay but people know basically nothing
in about classifying the examples.
Cool.
Okay.
So, um, so we'll give two proofs of
this. One based on double counting and
one based on the 4A method. Double
counting I think we can do today and the
4A method we'll do next time, next week.
And first of all, I think that these
results are pretty cool. But I also hope
that you see that they're really
extremely parallel to the results in
geometric measure theory that we've just
been talking.
Okay.
[Applause]
Okay, let me make a little remark before
we start. Um, so, so I'm going to focus
on projections mod p where p is a prime.
You could also reduce mod q where q is
not a prime. And all of the ideas still
work. It's a little bit more complicated
because if you take two numbers Q1 and
Q2 that share a common factor, then
reducing mod Q1 and reducing mod Q2 are
kind of related to each other. And so if
you write everything down, you have to
keep track of that. That's just an extra
thing to keep track of. And not so
difficult, but it it uh it makes
everything a little longer and more
complicated. Sometimes you might want to
do that, but uh in applications, but
just to show the ideas, I'm going to
focus on my P.
Okay.
All right. So, here's the double
counting method.
U so I'll call it theorem 1 s.
Um so it says if x is a subset of the
numbers from 1 to n and d is a set of
primes
uh less than or equal to n.
Um
and for every p in our set of primes, pi
subp of x is less than equal to s. Um
then we get a conclusion. Um
either
x is bounded by 2s or the number of
directions is bounded roughly by us.
So I guess this is most interesting if
the number of directions is
significantly bigger than s.
So if we look at the squares
uh so suppose I know that pi p of x is
bounded by uh p + 1 / 2. So that's my s
um and I need to do this.
Yeah, that's
um
Oh, this may not quite work for this.
Actually, I'm not sure if this will
imply Linux theorem. Lin proved his
theorem with the forier method. Um,
let's come back to that next time. I
think we have just enough time to do the
nice double counting argument and uh and
then do the the for the next.
Okay. Um so proof we're going to count
uh coincidences.
That's the set of x1 and x2 and x and p
in our set of directions or set of
primes. So that pi p of x1 equals pi p
of x2.
Okay. So we'll count this two different
ways. One is a lower bound. So star is
at least for every direction.
When I do this projection, there are
only s images. So a typical image has x
over s pre-im images. square that for my
choice of x1 and x2 and then multiply by
s for the number of choices of the
projection. So that's um x^2 d s of
okay now what's our upper bound?
So now I going to fix imagine fixing x1
and x2 and think about how many ps can
satisfy this.
Oh um so
um
so if I have pi p of x1 is equal to pi p
of x2
that tells us that p divides x2 - x1
and there can't be that many different
primes that divide x2 - x1. x2 - x1 has
size uh n. So it could be at most log of
n that do this. Um so star is
upperbounded by
um okay so so there is a case where x1
equals x2. So that gives me x times the
number of directions.
And then if x1 is not equal to x2, I
have x squar choices for x1 and x2. But
I have only log of n choices for the
direction.
Okay. And now I'll compare these to each
other.
Okay. So I have uh x^2 * d * s inverse
is less than x * d plus uh x^2 * log.
So there are two cases. If this one
dominates um then I would have that x is
bounded by 2s
or if this one dominates then the x's
disappear and I get that d is bounded by
log of n * s and and that's the that's
the theorem.
Okay. So let me give you an example of
this and argue that this is uh well let
me give you an example flavor of what
this is telling us. So suppose that pi p
of x is bounded by n^ the 2/3
for um 10 log n
* n^ 2/3 different p
um so if that's true then the theorem
tells us that x is bounded by n^ X.
So these primes might have size around
this big or a bit bigger. So these
primes are much less than n. So each
projection the fact that each projection
one at a time is small, it's not that
convincing in terms of x being small.
But knowing that all of these
projections are this large number of
projections is small. It means that x is
really that small.