All right. Well, let's just talk about
games a little bit. Um, so your learning
journal assignment was, uh, what are
the, um, what are the learning games
that you all played in your in your
youth or your contemporary times? We
heard Omar has talked with us a couple
of times about his passion for typing
games um and the importance of them in
his middle school experience, but what
other kinds of games um are memorable to
folks in their growing up for learning
or otherwise? Yeah, Emily. I think like
there was this game like game 24 or
something. It was like you'll have math
24. Oh, math 24. Man. Yeah. You have
like four numbers on a card and then
you're supposed to add, subtract,
multiply, divide, however you want to
get to the number 24. Did you do it
online or in the cards? No, in the
cards. Yeah, I was in elementary school.
All right. Cool. This is it? No, we
don't know. I don't know. I used the
Yeah, those cards card game version. Oh,
all right. Spinning these things around.
Cool. Other And where did this show up
in elementary class? Yeah, it was like
they put it in like the indoor recess
spot.
That's great. That's great. Um, what
else? What other kinds of games did
people play?
Sabrina, what was your None of these
counts as like like really really
educational, but um I used to play a lot
of cool math games as a kid.
They kind of are. At first they were and
god is straight up just I teach you time
management with all my
they teach you alt tab on your computer
once a teacher walks behind your monitor
is is Fruit Ninja a math game. Oh my
god. They also teach you like teamwork.
[Laughter]
Um, yeah, there is a pretty funny just
naming convention of like, let's call it
cool math games and then like maybe
parents won't notice. I mean, there's
definitely a first glance of like, oh,
you're playing cool math games. That's
probably fine. They're like, no, those
are not math games. Categories at the
top.
Yeah, categories. Numbers. Yeah,
platformer.
Um, block removal. Yeah, it's a it's I
don't know. There definitely some
darts. Test your aim in an online
multiplier. Okay. Idle breakout. Maybe
there used to be like those
multiplication like penguin race games
and you have to like answer the
multiplication questions as fast as you
could. Yep. Um definitely
definitely a uh Oh, Math Playground.
Yeah, that is another one that I've
seen. Um no, this this I think is a
direct descendant of Math Blaster.
Um, uh, play now.
Play now.
Playing against Luke and Shamar. Are
Luke and Shamar real? We don't know.
Let's just see how close this is to
math. Yeah, this is this is exactly Math
Blaster.
Um, and we'll play a little Math Blaster
later. Good.
Yeah, good job everyone. nice strong
strong singledigit multiplication skills
in the MIT students. I'm very proud of
you. Other other things I was saying um
like in my other class, my learning
class, we're like really pushing the
boundary of what's considered like a
learning game. Um and like one I grew up
playing a lot of board games with my
family. Um and one that like I'm right
now doing a project on that like makes
me really realize all the skills that I
learned was a board game called The
Resistance. You never heard of it? Um
and like was just thinking about like
skills that I've learned from that of
like not like how to keep a poker face,
but like how to formulate an argument to
like back up the claims that I've made.
Um, and like how to just like have
constructive arguments about with
between people. So like a lot of
communication skills and just like life
skills that I use to this day that were
still just like developed in some of
those like almost like roleplaying
communication games. Have any of you
ever played Mafia or Werewolf? That's a
derivation of Mafia or Werewolf. Um, the
guy who invented rare where there is a
guy who invented mafia. Um, it's not
just like an like a sort of cultural
it's not it's not like a century old
game. It's a guy who now I think lives
in Newton or Welsley. He applied for a
job in my lab once. He's a Russian
immigrant. Um, he grew up in Russia and
then came here. But I'm like he was
like, "Yeah, I invented Mafia." And I
was like, "I played that at camp when I
was a kid." Like, nope. We, you know, it
came from a particular moment and things
like that. It's kind of cool.
Um uh that's definitely a topic I want
us to talk about uh today and is
featured in the book this idea of
transfer. Um what is it that you learned
playing the resistance that we might
plausibly think you would you would
actually be able to deploy in other
non-similar contexts and what does
research tell us about uh about that and
which which ends up being a sort of
crucial question that the utility and
value of learning games hinges around.
Um, if you can get better at lots of
things by playing Minecraft, if you can
get better at critical thinking, if you
can get better at teamwork, if you can
get better at socialization, then like,
oh, Minecraft sounds pretty cool. If
actually playing a lot of Minecraft just
makes you better at Minecraft, um, then
the then the social utility of Minecraft
playing in, you know, in schools or for
learning experience goes down quite a
bit. Um, what other games have people
played or other things? What was yours,
Khalil? Uh, so I generalize both. So
there's a lot of games that rely on
coordinate systems as an integral part
of the game and a lot of these like you
could easily draw the parallels of it
towards like massification with
regarding to that. The game that the
most closely resemble that I remember is
game over golfer to just like a car
zombie like uh plant versus zombie like
game. Uhhuh. Uh but it relies on you
placing like it tells you hey place this
at this coordinate and you have to
figure out that quickly. So it have to
like internalize the idea of the
coordinate system beyond just like a
search slow search because that would
just get you so far.
Uhhuh. How quickly will you will see the
basics of this?
No plot. No plot.
Oh, I see. All
right.
Cool. Um, the coordinate. Oh, and now I
turn the sound off on that. The Let's
see if this Let's see if we can find his
Apple trick. Um,
uh, Apple Trek. Yeah. Originally
released in 1971.
Um, also had, uh, I was just going to
let us get into it.
Um, this was the game that I played when
I was a kid that had a sort of
coordinate system in it. Um, where, uh,
you just had to shoot photon torpedoes
at uh, bad guys. You could press F. F
will
Thank you. Um, yeah. Good. Yeah. Yeah.
So, you have to sort of fly through,
you're sort of flying through the
universe and eventually if you want to
shoot the photon torpedo, you have to
um, you know, figure out what the angle
is and um, you know, you know, fire it
at 90 degrees or 70 degrees or um, other
kinds of things like that. Wasn't very
good gameplay video, but uh, but it's
but it's an example of a game with a
coordinate system from 1971. So, that
certainly seems like a feature that that
shows up repeatedly. Could you look up
Odell Fish? That was a I think a
descendant of that Odell fish game.
Yeah. Um but yeah, it was No, there was
an older version. There was one from the
198 1986 that it pretty much was just a
fish and you had to not get eaten by the
otter. So all you had to do was like
move up and down and it was riveting for
third graders in mid 90s. So
what's it?
Yes.
[Music]
I'm not quite getting down a little bit.
It's not Yeah, it's not letting me. Uh
there. This is the upto-date graphics,
too, guys. That
was good. All right.
Um, are you
all too old to How many of you had
Cahoot as sort of a central part of your
middle school or high school? All right.
Even we won't. How what what's your what
year did you graduate high school,
Jiren? 2019. 2019. It's still
It was used it a lot in high school
though. Like like 2015 like a lot pretty
pretty substantial. How how did it get
integrated into
um classroom experience?
I think like eventually my school had a
program of like we had like Chromebooks
and so then that like just sort of
naturally led to okay like we already
all have our Chromebooks like we're like
do some sort of quiz or whatever and it
you know it gets real intense in the
classroom obviously.
Do do people are nodding? You generally
like think of cahoot fondly like that
was a good sort of I mean I I built
similar things in my class when I was a
teacher in 2003. I don't know somehow I
had I had a I had a Jeopardy setup um
that was with like a PowerPoint thing
where I just deleted little like blocks
to show the questions and then people
guessed answers and stuff like that. So
the sort of quiz show format. I mean
it's not you know it's it really is not
that is a classic example of sort of
gamification or chocolate covered
broccoli like there's no uh there's
there's no intrinsic game mechanic
that's in there. This is like like
competition over you know review
questions or knowledge or things like
that. But it ends up being pretty I mean
it's not you know um widely enjoyed by
learners from lots of different
backgrounds and things like that. I feel
like it stems from like just being fed
broccoli your whole life.
chocolate broccoli. Like, man, this is
great. It's so Yeah. Yeah. No, I think
that's right. It's like, man, this is so
much better than just doing a review.
This is so much better than whatever the
like typical routine of class is. Um,
name Oh, great. It's like you get to
write your own custom name. Yeah. Yeah.
You know, there are a bunch there's
those identity components. There's a
sort of surprise components. It's also
like outside of Jeopardy being like a
group thing like everyone gets to give
an answer. Every everybody gets to give
an answer. Yeah. It does some good
mechanics. Um doesn't Cahoot have things
where on your own display it like
there's a classwide leaderboard, but
there's sort of your own personal
leaderboard. So like you're like even if
like even if you're getting demolished
in class, like it just shows you
competing against the people who are
nearest to you. So that there's far away
five points behind this other player.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So, it's giving
you relative uh some some I mean like uh
like Pelaton and other kinds of things
do that right like I don't know I don't
have a Pelaton but I you know I think as
these sort of leaderboard systems you
know across distributing computing
environments are developed they're like
oh you don't have to compete against you
know if you if you have people compete
against everyone and only one person can
win. If you have like everybody
competing against a small subset which
is not necessarily overlapping with
anybody else's subset then like you know
everybody but one can beat somebody in
some kind of way. Um you know and then
you make up some other people and they
can beat the rest of them. um good other
games have people played that were
um I guess like related to like
expanding what a learning game is like
um I most of my youth I guess I was uh
in Iran so like didn't really have like
the internet bandage for like the like
online learning games or anything and
learning games in general were like not
a thing that I was really aware of until
I got to the US but I guess Like some
stuff that I thought about was like
um uh one specific one is like my
parents got me a toy sewing machine that
was like functional. Um and I learned
how to sew with that and then generally
just like uh it was like gamification of
arts and crafts a lot of time. My mom
would give me a bunch of like stuff be
like go make something with this and and
like my sister and I are very much like
perfectionists. So like we would always
be like, "Oh, like I want it to be like
this." And then my mom would be like,
"Okay, well if you want that like here's
some like exploration of like how you
want to be able to do that." And I think
like a lot of that was like one like
obviously like the skill itself of like
I learned how to sew with a sewing
machine and stuff like that, but also
like a lot of practice of like um um uh
what do you call it like spatial
understanding and like how do you write
letters on a poster so that they're not
like all bunch stuff at one end and just
like how to like plan like a certain
space effectively. and things like that.
Yeah. What what makes that what makes
that a game to you as opposed to like a
playful apprenticehip or
um I guess some of it might be just like
the stakes. I was just like and then
like I guess it is um
um I mean maybe it was also just a
little bit influenced by like how it was
presented I guess of like it was just
like like if it has like some pretend
aspect or of like oh like if it's a
competition with my sister or things
like that I guess. Yeah. Famously you
know there are philosophers who've tried
to pin down the word game and some of
them have concluded it's not possible. I
think Whit Wickenstein was one of the
ones who uh who said that there that
there really is no um there's no way to
to accept to create a definition of game
that correctly includes all the things
that people think should be included and
excludes all the things that people
think should be excluded. It's quite
difficult to figure out um what what
gameness is, you know, and how it
relates to sports or play or other, you
know, the real life other kinds of
activities. Um, but that's great that
those things sort of felt uh felt
gameful to you. Um, they certain they
certainly have a bunch of what what you
describe immediately evokes sort of
situated learning kinds of things of
like, oh, you know, my like my mom does
this thing and so she gave me a little
version of this thing and then we did
some of that stuff and she gave us some
tasks and we played around with them.
Um, and it is funny
how, you know, across cultures, across
history, um, young people really like
playing at what adults do. Um, I have a
great photograph from Messiah, um, with
this little, uh, three-year-old Messiah
dude dude who's got a long stick, um,
and a set of rocks in the sand, and he's
sort of whacking the the rocks in the
sand because Messiah are all herders.
Um, and so he just watched his older
brothers grow up hurting goats. And he
knew that he was gonna end up hurting
goats. And it's, you know, like there's
like a lot of goat hurting going on. But
a thing that's fun for him is to grab a
couple rocks, pretend they're goats, and
start hurting them around in the sand.
And I think it's funny because it's
relatable, you know, um to to whatever
whatever culture you're in. Um, playing
at being older is a big part of
youth. Um, good. Other other games that
people played? Yeah, Omar. Um, this one
might unlock a couple memories, but
Starfall was a big part of my childhood.
No. What's that? It's uh I primarily
played it during uh kindergarten and
preschool and first grade. Um, yes, that
first link. Um, but I they added a whole
new section that I don't even remember
like I don't ever recall seeing that.
So, they significantly updated the
website, but that was where I really did
a lot of um sort of like uh reading,
intro to reading. Uhhuh. Um, and I mean
for me it got pretty old pretty fast,
but like it's very nostalgic nowadays.
So, um, that was one of them. And then
also like Leaf Frog Toys. So,
we had like a computer lab and we'd all
go there and we'd like watch these and
it was like really cool. Um, especially
cuz like we didn't have like a um a lot
of like computing technology when I like
grew up at that time. So, it was really
cool to see this kind of a kind of a a
special highlight for the day to be able
to do these kind of things, you know,
and and and I hope that as you think
about these kinds of things, think about
Cahoot and stuff like that that your
mind drifts back to what you read in
Larry Cuban and his description of kind
of the material concerns of teachers,
the schedule concerns of teachers of
things like, oh, it's pretty handy to be
able to have a bunch of like digital
books that people find extremely
compelling to shove six-year-olds in
front of for an hour during the day so
you can like finish your lunch or do
some grading or do a little PR planning
and prep for other times of the day. Um
I don't know if this is well studied but
I bet uh you know Larry Cuban's finding
that that uh television and film strips
were more likely to be used at the end
of the day in elementary schools
probably parallels findings that you
might have today about when cahoot games
or other things like this get used uh in
the in the rhythm of the day and so
forth. Um so uh yeah different different
technologies but we can apply some of
the similar sorts of uh analytic tools
and frameworks to them. Good. Um what
are some things that I wanted to let me
let me talk let me talk for you a little
bit and then I'll give you a little bit
of chance to play some games. Um and
then uh and then we can talk a little
bit about transfer. Um, one thing that I
just wanted to draw your attention to
that's in the syllabus is uh for failure
disrupt in the rabbit hole readings that
you're not required to do. One of those
links for every chapter is a podcast
episode. Um, and uh I was thinking about
them because some people who are missing
class this week because of Sloan SIP
week. I was going to recommend those to
them as sort of supplementary kind of
things. But for the um uh this chapter
in particular, Scott Auststerhile who
developed the logical journey of the
Zubinis is one of the guests and then
Constant Steiner who actually had a job
for a while in the US Department of
Education thinking about um the role of
games in education systems is there.
Probably one of the most fun things
about the podcast episodes um is that I
really encouraged the people who came to
disagree with me. Um and so
um you in in most episodes there there
are uh you know claims made about where
the book is wrong by very well-informed
people um on those topics. So so
Constant Steiner does not agree with me
in this episode about uh the
relationship between games and learning
and transfer and it's fun to to listen
to that. Um, I think uh Mitch and
Natalie had some disagreements with me
in in uh about uh what the what the
learning goals of Scratch are um in
practice. So, those can be kind of fun.
So, I don't know you're going for a run
or something like that. You need some
light podcast listening to these can be
fun episodes. If you're if you're not
getting enough education technology in
your three hours a week with me, um
there's more to be had.
Um so the way that this chapter is
structured is I call it sort of testing
this theory of the genres of learning at
scale. um which is um what you should be
you know the the reason part a big
reason for organizing um the the the
idea of three genres of learning at
scale is I want people to be able to
take new technologies and say oh that is
kind of like this and if we can say oh
that's kind of like this then we can say
all right so we probably know something
about its technology we probably know
something about the sort of pedagogical
underpinnings we can make some guess
about research like a big thing that I
would want someone who reads failure to
disrupt
to be able to do is to like look at new
AI tools and be like, okay, you know, we
did not have generative pre-trained
transformers that were pretty useful
until November of 2022, but like the
things that we're trying to do with them
are going to be similar to other kind of
stuff that we've done in the past, and
we should be able to slot the things
that we're going to do to them into
different kinds of categories. Um, games
struck me as a good testing place for
this because it's it's not the case that
I think games fit neatly into one of
these three categories of
instructorguided learning at scale or
algorithm guided learning at scale or
peer guided learning at scale. But I do
think that any given game probably fits
into one of those categories pretty
nicely or has some sort of like
recognizable hybridity across those
categories. Um, so something like Math
Blaster, um, you know, is is is kind of
an example of, you know, you could
decide whether or not it's sort of
instructorg guided learning at scale or
algorithm guided learning at scale or
something like that. Doesn't really have
a lot of item response theory to it. Um,
you know, but it's but it's basically
just an autograder. Um, you know, you go
you go in, you're given a type of
problem, you practice that problem over
and over again. Maybe the difficulty
goes up and you practice sort of another
type of problem. Um, had any of you ever
heard of Vanished before? Maybe some of
you in the other in the games for
learning classes you read about
Vanished. Um, so Vanished, which I write
about a little bit in the book, was this
really cool project that the MIT uh uh
education arcade did with the
Smithsonian Museum? It was any watch the
television show Lost? Um, okay. So, a
couple nods there. I don't Have any of
you ever participated? I I mean, it
actually d I don't know. Like are you
all aware what's going on with Kate
Middleton right now where people are
like trying to figure out like why she's
not showing up in public and sort of all
these conspiracies theories show up
about it and people do these detective
work. There's a bunch of things like
that or like I don't know um when the
Malaysian airline flight crashed and
nobody really knew. I don't know there
there's something that human beings have
that's like let's all kind of solve the
mystery together and it gets kind of
woven into conspiratorial thinking. It
overlaps nicely with fiction with things
like Lost or um sort of other television
shows that do that. But but Vanished was
basically like an alternate reality game
that was sort of played out on the web
um where there were codes to break.
There were secret messages spread across
websites. There were sort of scientific
claims that were happening. Other sorts
of thing. There are messages from the
future being beamed back into the past.
um and students signed up um to like
either as classes or individuals to sort
of like get the kind of messages that
went along. I think the game ran for a
couple months or something like that. Um
but very much a sort of peerguided
learning at scale kind of example like
you know just like a series of puzzles
put out there that you collaboratively
tried to solve. you had to interact with
other people um to kind of find
um a big you know the these two kinds of
games um illustrate uh some of the basic
principles that we were just talking a
about a little bit. Um Math Blaster. So
what you did in Math Blaster is you like
took that little character and you ran
it back and forth to get the get the
correct answer. Actually, what was the
what was the penguin game that we just
played? What was that called? Penguin
Race Off or something? Yes, I think so.
Yeah. So, so penguin penguin raceoff um
is uh is an example of what sometimes
gets called gamification, which is how
do we take a mathematic how do we take
an intellectual exercise that we think
is useful for people and put game
elements on it to inspire people to do
that activity? Um, uh, what what other
kinds of software have you played with
that takes like basically a worksheet
activity and add sort of game elements
on top of it?
It's kind of like thinking about the
what the slide you presented earlier
like Dolingo kind of Yep. Dolingo has a
ton of gamification built into it like
in you know I don't know how many of you
how many of you use Dolingo or have used
it. Oh just a couple. Okay. So maybe
more people play around with it. Um but
you know they have millions of people
who are doing little language activities
but a big part of why they're doing like
the little language activities are not
that inherently fun. Um but what are the
features in Dualingo that try to like
get people hooked to to do it and keep
doing it?
Streaks. Streaks are a big one. Yeah.
you know, which is just like a number
that you try to increment every day.
That's kind of a game.
Visual design. What kind of elements? Uh
colorful design, interactive design, all
of these like bubbly like feelings to
everything in it. Yep. Yep. So, yeah, it
like creating it and turning into a
playful space. Some of the most
important visual elements are when you
get something right. Um there's usually
like a little flash you for sound, a
little ding. Um, Edex had these big
green check marks for a while when you
got answers correct. I think another
thing that's been like a recent
development has been their PR. Um,
recently like at least on Tik Tok like
Duolingo's like gone unhinged. Um, and
like the birds like everywhere and it
like comments on weird things and like
every time it comments somewhere like
there's like a million like like replies
to it. Um, and I think like wanting to
be like a part of that community or like
say I've done that is also like a big
thing in society today. Yeah. Good.
Um, Mari who's not here wrote in like to
me um uh uh Dolingo when I think about
it is sort of a classic example of kind
of
gamification. Um, you know, sort of very
instructionist kind of inspired like
let's just put some game elements on
stuff. And Mario wrote an essay was
like, "No, actually this thing is like
super motivated by situated learning."
Um, the way that it makes you like
things like that are like, "Oh, like the
duo bird is out there and I can have a
parasocial relationship with the duo
bird and it will comment on my TikTok
feeds and I can respond to it and things
like that." Um, got me thinking a little
bit differently about it. Maybe we keep
talking about that. Um, yeah, the the
the the term of art for this uh kind of
approach is chocolatecovered broccoli.
um that basically like this is super
boring math to do, but we're just gonna
like pour chocolate on it to get you to
try to do more of it. And of course,
like the joke of chocolate covered
broccoli is that like chocolate covered
broccoli does actually not taste that
good. Um and Math Blaster is actually
not that fun. Like it's fun for a little
while and then you're like, "Oh, I'm
just doing division."
um whereas Vanished um and other kinds
of games like it there's not a there's
not an as well accepted name, but my my
colleagues at the education arcade um
refer to these games as resonant games.
Um and a key feature of resonant games
is that instead of trying to add game
elements on top of some kind of
intellectual exercise, you're trying to
find the playfulness in the intellectual
exercise. like what it's not it's not um
how do we how do we add game mechanics
to math. It's what is already fun and
playful and interesting in math and then
how do we have that fun and playfulness
kind of surface and emerge so that you
so that we get learners to engage with
that first. um in in vanished like how
do we teach scientific thinking,
scientific practices by having those
practices emerge kind of naturally in
this sort of conspiratorial mystery kind
of story um that happens. Um, oh, good.
These, this is a great example of what
Khalil was just talking about of, uh,
um, uh, yeah, the very the very sort of
playful environment that like we'll give
you some experience points. We'll tell
you about your time. We'll call you
amazing. We'll give you these funny
little sticker. I mean, like this is
this is I don't know if any of you do
did your elementary teachers like put
stickers on successful assignments and
stuff like that. Can you think of like
gold stars and stuff like that? Yeah,
this is just like a digital version of
that. is the same kind of thing. Let's
give you some kind of visual reward
reminder to get you to keep playing and
doing these things. Um,
uh, this is one that I talk about in the
book, uh, Lumosity, which maybe we'll
talk about a little bit later when we
talk about, uh, transfer and things like
that. Um, all right. So, I would like to
invite you to play two of these games,
and you can find these links in the
syllabus, but why don't we take 15
minutes or so and let you pull out some
computers. Um, I'm going to give you I'm
going to give you maybe before you pull
them out, let me just explain these four
things and then you can do whatever you
want with them. Um, the first one is
Math Blaster. Um, I could I don't think
I successfully found the 1983 version. I
think I found a 1996 one. Um, but you
should play a few rounds of Math Blaster
and see what all the hype is about. Um,
the second game is the logical journey
of the of the Zoominis. Um, which was a
key part of Erin's childhood. And so now
she'll get to go back to that. It has a
really long kind of intro story and
stuff like that. You if that's what
you're into, you can do that. But if you
want to play the game, you'll have to
like skip a bunch of introductory stuff
to get into some interesting sort of
combinatorics kinds of things. Um, one
thing which is not a game, but if any of
you are big Minecraft fans, um, I gave
you a link to what is essentially the
Minecraft website for teachers. Um, you
won't be able to unless you have got
Minecraft on your computer, you won't be
able to jump in there and play with
things. But a thing that you can do is
go to like their lesson plan finder.
Um, and uh, that's probably the most
useful probably the thing you'd find
most interesting is go to explore
lessons and pick a topic you're
interested in and you know see whether
or not you think the you know good going
back to the coordinate system like how
do you uh um, you know, how to how would
how would you use Minecraft to teach the
coordinate system and they've got all
kinds of guiding activities and student
activities and you won't be able to see
the world that's associated with them
but each one of these lessons has a kind
of Minecraft space that's been built,
you can at least get some screenshots
from it. And then if anybody hasn't
played Dualingo, it it it's not it you
could probably pretty quickly start
creating an account um and doing some
things like that. Um if you want to do
it with a person next to you, you should
feel free to do that. Um the easiest
place to find all of these links, you
could just Google them, but they are on
the syllabus, um bit.lym
LMT syllabus and then uh
um on the on the day for learning games
I've put uh four of these links there.
Um so it's 1:35. Why don't we take until
about 1:50 and just let you uh and feel
free to do it with a partner or
something like that. And if they've got
sound, you turn on the sound quietly and
stuff like that so you can hear it
without bothering people next to you.
But they're but they're pretty fun
things to mess around with. Sound good?
Ready? Go.
All right. So, having having who who
played around with Zooinis? Looked like
we had a lot of Zoominis player. What
are what are your reactions having spent
some time with Zooinis?
It's cute.
It takes so long. I I just I want like
go hurry up. Then you get to see them
walk up and bounce up. Yeah. Yeah. So
yeah. So the more you know the more I it
actually you know most of you were
playing with sound off which might be a
mistake because I think part of the part
of the stakes of Zoominis are set like
there's a narrator in the back who tells
you about how the Zoominis were
oppressed and you're saving them and
things like that and have like um you
know having you having you develop a
kind of affinity for them is is in a
sort of storytelling world is part of
the game having them be cute I think is
important that you develop some care for
them um and want to engage with them and
things like that sort of the more in
fact the more you peel away those
elements and ju the the kind of
narrative elements the social elements
the artistic elements and just get down
to the math the more like that that
could that could risk some of the fun of
the engagement I'd rather play Sudoku
rather play okay good yeah which is just
like a straight immersion into like yeah
and and those kinds of personal
preferences raise some real challenges
for teachers right like for like you
Imagine having, you know, if you were to
take time in a math class to have people
play the logical journey of the Zubinis,
there'd be some kids who are like, "This
is the best day of class ever." And
there'd be other kids who are like, "H,
can we just go back to doing whatever we
were doing before?" Um, and uh it's like
an expensive investment of time and
other kinds of things to to have a
third-year class be like, "Ah, this
game's not that fun."
Emily, did it did it sell you eventually
or?
Yeah,
I I would say I I kind of like it.
Good. I think it's just
um I don't know. It It could be like
that tendency like you said of like
create like having an affinity for that
or like, oh, it's like these like cute
little creatures like going across your
screen and like um how much you enjoy
that or how much you might care for
that. And I'm I'm very much down for a
fun little game with little cute
characters and identities and things
like that. But I feel like it might just
be because like now I'm so used to like
things having to happen like very
quickly cuz like even like lectures I
tend to watch them like in two times
speed instead of like the normal way
like the normal time. So then it's like
watching playing these games are so slow
that I'm just like you've lost my
attention. I don't want to play it
anymore. Good. Yeah. There's there's a
little kind of gap in there. Wait, I
have a question. Did you guys like skip
the like transitions or were you sitting
through them? I clicked out of skip
them. Yeah.
Okay. Cuz the the the transitions are
like I see what you mean, but like the
transitions are like Okay. Like you're
slowly highlighting the next place I'm
going in the map for like a minute and
it's like, okay, I I've seen enough. It
was fun to like figure out what the sort
of traits were that they were selecting
for, but then like you kind of inst I
felt like I instantly found the traits
and then I was just like, "Oh, okay.
I'll just like there I didn't really
have to like completely, you know, do
like a crazy search for the traits or
whatever." Like I was just like, "Oh,
okay. Well, maybe this hair is good."
And then all that hair turned out to be
fine. I'm like, "Oh, okay. Great."
I mean, it might have been harder if you
were 10, but Well, actually, to build
those two together, I'm like try I don't
remember like when I was going through
this game as a young person if I
recognized or was even looking for the
traits. Like I think maybe I I might
have been more pulled to like the
affinity to the characters and like, oh
no, they got bounced back. That's not
good. And just like doing I would do it
with my sisters and we just like drop
them all over the place and see if they
go in. that I cannot remember if I like
noticed that there were conditions and I
just we cared we were okay with the
slowness because we cared more about
just getting them through it didn't
matter like and I can't remember and
that's killing me a little bit. Yeah. Um
how many of you clicked the the question
mark hint button that has an explanation
and how many didn't discover the um it's
kind of an interesting design feature um
to be able to say that uh um you you can
you can play you can play the game
without any instructions about how to
play the game. you're just like put in
the world, start clicking things around,
start moving things around. If you had
to put the logical um journeys of the
Zoominis as instructor guided learning
at scale, algorithm guided learning at
scale, or um peer guided learning at
scale, what would you call it?
I feel like instructor guided learning.
Um, it's not like if I was able to solve
all of the like or get all of the Zenis
through on like one or two errors that
it would automatically jump to like
level five. Yep. Um, like there's very
much like a sequence that you're
supposed to follow. Um, and I when I
would place one and then it would try
and go up and felt like an autograder of
like it's like this is either pass or
fail. H yeah, the autograder is a lot
more fun because like a thing crosses a
bridge or gets kicked back or somebody
eats a pizza but doesn't eat a pizza,
but it's not really any different from a
green check or a red check or other
kinds of things like that. Um no, the
way the way that I argued that Zoominis
fit is that it's instructor learning at
scale with an autograder. However,
almost every MOO is inspired by more um
instructivist kinds of approaches. And
this is very much more inspired by kind
of a situated learning apprenticeship
kind of approach where it's almost
trying to trying to hide the autograder,
trying to hide the instructor. Um it's I
mean it's very much trying to hide the
instructions. You know, it says just
like go into this world, immerse
yourself into this world, play around,
see what happens. There's sort of
winning and losing, but like it's
actually, you know, it's actually fine
to fail a level. Well, it's fine to have
all your Zoominis kick back. You can try
again and rescue some other Zoominis,
other sorts of things. Um, you know,
there's there's no point in the game
where it stops and is like, "Okay, kids,
like actually, we're teaching you
combinotaurics." Um, or, you know, or
probability or whatever else you think
is the mathematics of the game. It just
lets that be a kind of, you know,
natural learning that that happens
throughout. um you know there are there
are other you know so this is this is an
exercise that I think is the kind of
thing that might be helpful if you were
um you know a department head a teacher
trying to figure out whether or not you
should adopt this technology in your
classroom um which is sort of for any
new technology three good questions to
ask or who drives and control the pace
and path of learning what are the
technologies here what are the
pedagogies and then sort of what can I
predict will happen in my educational
system given a consequence of this
design. So like Math Blaster is pretty
pretty instructor guided. It's got an
autograder. I mean they're just
worksheet problems. There's no
difference between um that and a
worksheet problem except like maybe I
will slightly motivate some of my
students to do more worksheet problems
because like there's aliens and it's
kind of fun and things like that. But
maybe not. Maybe there's some people who
are like ah I really don't want to have
to like I just give me the math problems
to answer.
Um I I had often thought of do How many
of you played around with Duolingo for
the first time as you're clicking around
here? Any sort of new Dolingo people? Um
you know it certainly is algorithm
guided as it's trying to you know
there's some there's a lot of good
writing um the the the developers of
Dualingo keep blogs and other kinds of
things where they talk about um you know
for instance they they have a um have
you ever heard of the concept of the
zone of proximal development? This is
sort of a classic educational concept
that basically you want to try to as
you're teaching people have there be a
difficulty level where you feel sort of
competent but also sort of stretched and
you know if you're if things are too
easy it's boring. If things are too hard
it's boring. There's a zone of proximal
sort of ideal development. Um for the
they measure that zone of proximal
development by saying like you you know
we're trying to aim for people to have a
certain kind of error rate. I don't know
exactly what it is but it might be like
we want you to get about 20% of the
things you're hitting wrong. Um, if
you're getting more than 20% wrong, then
we're probably making it too hard,
otherwise too easy. Um, but what are the
I don't know what we talked a little
bit, but what are some of the situated
learning elements that you saw? If you
were to say that there was not so
instructionist, but it was more um
inspired by kind of constructionism,
situated learning. What kinds of things
like that are in Dolingo?
I like I found out Dolinda has a music
thing now which is really cool because
I've always wanted to learn music. I
like play around with that but I don't
understand it. Like I can't read notes
or anything. I just like think and then
play piano. But it's more interesting to
see like they had this they had this
stupid simulation of playing hot cross
buns and I swear I could play that if I
tried. But doing it with their little
app, it was like you had to paste it and
you had to recognize the notes. And I
went back to that like 10 times and it's
like simulating playing the piano. It's
really simple for like a computer game,
but that was pretty engaging. So, so it
sort of immersed you in the feeling of
playing a piano even though you're kind
of on your phone. That seems like a good
quality of a situated apprenticeship
kind of thing. Um, now you you had
played Hot Cross Buns before. Um, I feel
like I could just play it like sitting
in a piano without like if I looked for
the notes soundwise. Like I can't read
piano notes, but like I can figure out
songs if you tell me what they like if I
hear them. Yeah. So, playing by ear.
Yeah. Yeah. Cool. So, yeah. Um, and and
so you feel like this could be a pathway
to doing I mean I I'm sort of
increasingly convinced now that Dolingo
um Dolingo came out of Carnegie Melon
University and they have some of the
best sort of learning scientists,
learning engineers in the world and one
of the things I like about them is that
they're they're sort of methodological
pluralists. They're like what are all
the good ideas and how do we shove them
all in there? Um so in some sense
Dolingo like is very much
instructionist. It's like taking big
complex things and breaking it down into
small pieces. It'll show you examples,
then give you part tax practice and all
those kinds of things. But it also has
this way of like, well, let's give you
an identity in this environment. Let's
have you build a parasocial relationship
with an owl. Let's feel like you're
sitting down with a piano. Let's reward
you. Let's help you go on a journey from
being a newcomer to an old-timer by
having badges and streaks and these
other sorts of things with it. Kind of a
nice blend um of uh of those things.
Um, you know, um, we've talked a bunch
in this class about how one of the
signature challenges of self-paced
online learning is that people are
typically bad at it. Like people
typically quit. Um, Duolingo has
probably been as successful, maybe more
successful than any other education
technology company in building a product
um, that's just super sticky for people.
Um they they really have put a lot of
effort into trying to break down the
challenges of self-paced learning. Um
and some you know through these
gamifications through streaks through
making it playful through having it feel
like it'd be fun through I don't have
have any of you quit tried to quit
Dualingo like they send you heranging
emails when you're not doing it enough
and things like that. They've got all
kinds of ways of trying to sort of
continuously pull them in there. They're
super scientific about all this stuff
too. So, all like I'm sure all of those
emails that you've ever gotten have been
AB tested a zillion times. Um, all
different kinds of timing and language
they use and other things like that to
sort of rope you back in. Um, good. How
many of you looked around on the
Minecraft um website? What did you find
there, Khalil? Uh, I played like a game
where like they're trying to like teach
kids good game like stuff and it's still
very like
uh like there's not much to do just like
go there do that should you feed the dog
you probably should feed the
dog. So it it feel it felt like a little
bit forced in terms of the path that you
could take. But after like oh doing
these chores it it tells you hey you
have to write this like good game guide
book book and like oh what's the you
should write like a certain instruction.
Do you want an example? Oh what you did
today was chores. You should do your
chores before playing games. And then
you get to write whatever you want,
which case they don't really check what
you write in there. But after that, you
get to play like a little game where you
shoot balloons, I guess. And then you're
back into a new day. So it felt a lot of
like
uh a lot of like let's simulate life in
Minecraft. You have like even you have
parents in the game because they named
them trusted adults.
Uh but yeah, it felt it felt like a
little bit too much like constrained in
terms of what activity you could be
doing and it felt uh like very like very
much like clearly instructivist. I mean,
I'm very much like an adult, so it's not
like you're not the target audience for
this, but I I hypothesize a kid would
like recognize. Yeah. They are telling
me to do my chores before playing games,
but they're just doing it in Minecraft.
Yeah. Yeah. I I think that's I mean to
me how many of you are Minecraft players
just like in your regular lives or were
at some point in your you know to me the
sort of joy of Minecraft the thing that
they discovered was was the you know the
the the joy of the boundlessness of just
people inventing their own um missions
and structure and things like that like
there's a little bit of the overworld of
the game but you know I mean for me it
was always like all right I'm in a new
world I will need a wizards tower like
you know I had like a sort of construct
in my mind of what I should live in um
and it was a wizard's tower um And uh um
you know that just cuts off it's very
difficult to conduct educational
activities which are like everyone go do
whatever you want. I mean usually when
you have some instructional activity
you're like let's all do X you know. Um
and so to some extent the kind of let's
all do go do X is like directly against
the fabric of one of the main things
that makes Minecraft so special um is
this open world where you can kind of do
anything you want. Um, so there's a sort
of um those those kinds of tensions show
up all the time in you know I think you
know could I think m Minecraft is
incredibly sticky to young people. It is
incredibly compelling and so you go oh
maybe we could take this really sticky
compelling world and have people do
learning in it. But as soon as you add
this dimension of okay you all have to
do X inside my Minecraft world. Um it's
uh it's often much much less compelling
for people. you're sort of pull you're
sort of taking away one of the key
features that made it sticky um in the
first place. Um but even if you want to
do that, I think one of the central
questions that games pose is
um if you spend a lot of time in
Minecraft, are there things that are
that you're learning that are useful for
other things or are you just learning
how to play Minecraft? Um and that is a
very old educational question. It is an
educational question that actually
somebody we've talked about a bunch. Um
Edward Thorndikeke was one of the very
earliest researchers in um and it
relates to a problem that's called
transfer. Um to what extent when you
learn something can you take that
learning and apply it into some other
different kind of context. That is one
of the most important questions we could
ask in education. Um the more you
believe that things learned in one
context will help you do other kinds of
things. Um, in some ways it sort of
simplifies the education system. Like
let's just get you to be really good
thinkers in one domain and then you'll
be good at all kinds of stuff. The more
that you believe that things don't
transfer very well, that people are
really only good at doing the things
that they're taught how to do, the more
difficult and complex education become.
In Thornikeke's time, um, the the the
sort of thorny challenge that he was
faced with, um, was that people were
still big fans of sort of classical
curriculum, um, teaching people Latin
and Greek. Um, and the argument that was
out there, um, was that if people got
really good at learning Latin and Greek,
they would learn sort of generically how
to think well. They would learn how to
think well, how to communicate well. I
don't You all are giggling at this. Why
are you giggling at
this? What seems silly about that
argument?
I mean, learning Latin Greek is first of
all, it seems like kind of elitist and
hilarious for that reason, but also it's
like any language or I guess any
singular task. It's a lot of like
pattern matching. I imagine I'm not a
great language learner, but I can't
imagine how you could apply the same
underlying like if I just learned a lot
of Polish, I would be really good at
lots of other kinds of things. It
doesn't doesn't stick quite well. Good.
Um what are what are things in our
current educational system that we tell
people if you will if you learn this
thing you'll be good at lots of other
kinds of things?
Math especially higher level stuff. Okay
good. So there's there can people think
of other kinds of things that have
claims that are similar to that?
Feel like just reading in general people
claim like oh like if you can read then
you can read anything and then you can
learn it. Ah good. Okay. So that that
there's domain independent reading
skills. That's a thing that comes out
there that that we can ask some more
about. I could argue that uh like many
academic stuff when not relating to
academic stuff gets that claim like if
you do this good academic like achieve
whatever like learning you will do good
at nonacademic certain task whether that
be like you know normal dayto-day
getting a job or something like that.
Yep. Yep. Yeah. schools help you with
other things. Um, chess gets this a lot.
You know, learn to play chess, you get
strategic thinking. Uh, if you take
classes, you will be good at the job
that they're teaching you. Yeah. You
know, my my wife works on the faculty
here um and uh in material science and
she had somebody from who did material
science in a in an engineering company
once come and came to a faculty meeting
and and basically was telling the
faculty like how little she thought of
the training that they got in in lab.
She was like, "Well, I guess it's okay
if you do a Europe. It's like better
than doing lifeguarding for a summer or
something like that, but it's really not
very helpful." Which was funny at the
time. But the point being that like yeah
the thing like the things that people do
in companies to like actually build
products are quite different than the
things that happen in academic research
labs to imagine these kinds of things.
Um all right here's here are a couple of
sort of striking examples. Oh um I and
I'll point out this later. I think
computer programming gets this. Have any
of you ever heard the phrase
computational thinking? Um, so
computational thinking is like roughly
the claim that if you teach people how
to program computers, they will have a
bunch of skills that are useful in other
kinds of domains. Like you'll learn how
to break problems down into smaller
problems. You'll learn how to think
through things with algorithms and stuff
like that. It is actually that line of
argument is very similar to the argument
a century plus ago or a couple centuries
ago um that if you learn Latin and Greek
you will have these domain independent
thinking skills that are good for
reasoning and other kinds of domains. Um
uh here's a remarkable study that a
colleague of mine did recently that sort
of illustrates this. He was trying to
figure out like how good are people at
um
differentiating at at sorting truth from
fiction online. Um so he shows them two
websites. One of them is the American
Academy of Pediatrics. The other is the
American College of Pediatricians. Those
sound pretty similar. The websites
actually look pretty similar. Um the
American Academy of Pediatrics is a
40,000 member organization that
represents pediatricians across the
United States. Um the American College
of Pediatricians is like a four, five,
600 person splinter group um that split
off from the American Academy of
Pediatricians um in opposition to
same-sex adoption. Um so like one is a
very mainstream group, one is sort of a
splinter group. Um professional fact
checkers who work in newspapers and
magazines and stuff like that um could
identify this the difference between
these websites and organizations 100% of
the time. Um how well do you think
historians did at this professional
trained historians did at this who spend
their entire lives studying how to
evaluate information and how well do you
think Stanford freshmen do at this task?
like saying this group is not the same
as this other group. Uh yeah, I mean it
was slightly more detailed than I was
like which which which which of these
would have like you know better better
substantiated claims but even sort of
recognizing the difference between them.
Um like even identifying that the
American College of Pediatricians is
like not the same thing as the American
Academy of
Pediatricians.
Um they do shockingly shockingly poorly.
Um so 50% of trained award-winning
tenured historians um either wasn't sure
I I think the question they ask is which
of these is sort of like a more reliable
source of information and the fact
checkers were like yeah the academy with
all the people in the mainstream group
and historians about half of them did
that and actually about 20% of Stanford
freshmen you know people who um got into
a university with a 3% acceptance rate
or something like that um are fact
checkers smarter than historians tenure
historians or Stanford
students like it like it doesn't stand
to reason that they would have better um
generic like domain independent thinking
skills or critical thinking skills or
problem solving something like that. Um
a better a better way to think about it
is like they must be doing something
different. Um and and it turned out that
when you observe them, they were um that
when historians and Stanford freshmen go
to a website to evaluate the website,
they scroll up and down and they look on
the website for markers of credibility.
Um uh you know, does this like is it
formatted correctly? Does it seem to be
from a reputable organization? Is it
aorg.com? Does it have citations? Stuff
like that. The American College of
Pediatricians has all of those markers
of credibility. Like the like all the
bad guys have lists of how to make a
credible looking website. Um the fact
checkers do something totally different.
As soon as they go to a website, they
leave it. Um so they would go to the
American College of Pediatricians and
they immediately just Google American
College of Pediatricians in which you
very quickly learn, you know, that the
600 person uh splinter group and and
those sorts of things. Um and so the
idea you know people would like even you
know the thing which is so striking here
actually the reason why this research
group picked this tenure group of
historians is they were hoping that they
would be examples of experts. It would
be like they would be like these people
have trained their entire lives to study
information and to sort truth from
fiction in historical documents. And it
turns out spending your entire life
learning how to sort truth from fiction
in the archives doesn't help you very
much. Learning how to sort truth from
fiction to the internet. Um so this is
one of the sort of key ideas of transfer
that if you learn how to do something in
one domain even changing the context of
that domain not that much going from
searching sorting truth for fiction in
the archives is sufficiently different
from sorting truth from fiction online
um that there's not like a generic set
of critical thinking skills that helps
you bridge that. Um if you want to get
if you want to get good at sorting truth
from fiction online you have to learn a
specific set of skills that are related
to learning to sort truth from fiction
online. Um here's another one of uh
those examples.
Um this is a classic experiment that
gets replicated in various kinds of
ways. In one experiment, third graders,
some identified by a reading test as
good readers, some as poor, were asked
to read a passage about soccer. The poor
readers who knew a lot about soccer were
three times as likely to make accurate
inferences about the passage as the good
readers who didn't know much about the
game. Current education practices show
that reading comprehension is
misunderstood. It's treated like a
general skill that can be applied with
equal success to all texts. Rather,
comprehension is intimately intertwined
with knowledge. So, we we think, you
know, there's ways of measuring like are
you a good reader or a bad reader. But
it actually sort of sets aside the fact
that like if you know a bunch of stuff
about soccer, you're a good soccer
reader. And if you don't know a lot of
stuff about soccer, you're a bad soccer
reader. Um, this is terrible for reading
instruction, right? It would be much
better for the world if we could just
make you a good reader. But actually the
way to be good at reading in a domain is
to teach you a bunch of facts and
knowledge and information in that
specific domain. Um that in fact like
the skill of reading doesn't transfer
that well from reading about soccer to
reading about softball. Um it's not that
it doesn't transfer at all. Um but you
know and also being able to read well
about soccer is sort of more like being
able to read well about soft well you
know softball and less likely you know
sort of less related to being able to
read well about restaurants or something
like that. Um
uh this this is my way of making fun of
the claim that computer science taught
me to break down problems into pieces.
This is sort of a classic kind of
computational thinking argument that if
you if you teach if you teach someone
computer science they'll be able to
break down problems into pieces. um you
know like so here's an AP literature
question like before using computer
science I answered this with one long
sentence but now I use paragraphs to
break up my arguments into pieces no of
course like from the very beginning of
you learning how to write you were
taught to break down problems into
pieces like that's what writing is you
break big ideas into paragraphs you
break paragraphs into sentences you make
sentences into phrases you've been
taught forever how to break ideas down
into pieces but turning you know written
words into breaking them down into
pieces doesn't really help you at all in
taking computer programming problems and
breaking them down into pieces. Um, you
know, before studying computer science,
I wrote one equation to solve all these
problems, but now I break problems down
into pieces. Um yeah, I could speak like
a little on that and from like firsthand
experience like I've done like computer
science like problem solving very much
since like middle school and in terms of
domain knowledge like I don't when I'm
encounter with a different domain I
don't know where to even cut the pieces
for the problem there are sure I want to
do that but where I don't know what
where to cut it into smaller pieces this
is something I have to acquire just like
anyone else. Yeah, that is the domain
specific knowledge that you need to
acquire in that particular domain to
know what break I mean it it is probably
slightly useful to have the intuition um
hey bigger problems can be broken down
into smaller problems like that's
probably a little bit helpful in a lot
of cases but I like the way that you
phrase that if you don't know anything
about the domain you don't know what the
sort of relevant division points for
breaking something into pieces are
um uh that one of the first people to
study this was uh Edward Thorndikeke I
was just rereading meeting today one of
the studies that he did which was um to
uh have people be really good at
estimating the size of rectangles. So he
would cut rectangles on pieces of paper
and have people look at rectangles,
estimate their area, give them some
feedback and you can actually get you
know there was a hundred different
rectangles of different sizes and you
found pretty quickly you can get people
better at estimating rectangles. Um then
he would give them piles of circles and
triangles and rhombuses and things like
that and they're no better at estimating
the size of circles and triangles having
studied how to estimate um rectangles.
Again, um there are all kinds of studies
that are done like this. A lot a sort of
wave recently being uh um you know,
studies that disprove that there's any
relationship between chess knowledge and
academic outcomes between or chess
proficiency and academic outcomes
between music knowledge and academic
outcomes. Um these things are sort of
much more separate than we might have
hoped. Uh about the reading
comprehension thing. Yeah. Do the
standardized tests like ACT or ACT take
that into an account or they don't? It's
a it's a hu it's a huge problem. Um so I
mean in a sense they here's how they try
to take it into account is
they try to indicate to educators what
are the domains of knowledge that will
be sampled by the SAT um and have people
read things that are related to those
domains of knowledge. Um, one of the one
of the knocks about particularly early
standardized tests. I think standardized
testing companies have done better about
these kinds of things. Um, is you know
there would be there would be all kinds
of questions that are about like or you
know where where the examples take place
in a country club or something like
that. Um, you know, and in 75 years or
whatever, maybe it would have been
pretty likely that just about everybody
who's applying to college knows what a
country club is. Um, but there are tons
of Americans who have no idea what a
country club is. Um, and so you know, if
you if you treat reading as a domain
independent entity where everybody
should be able to like recognize the
words country club and then process the
rest of the sentence, then that seems
fair. But it is the more you realize
like no, knowing something about a
country club gives you an advantage on
questions that are about country clubs.
Um, then you know, and I think we could
all agree that like knowing about
country clubs is not something that's
particularly important to going to
college or advancing higher education or
other things like that. then you're
like, "Oh, that is kind of unfair." Um,
so I think there's more recognition of
those things over time. Of course, you
have the opposite problem, which is that
the more you tell people exactly what
the domains are that might be tested,
um, the more you have people like just
studying and practicing those domains.
And that's not like exactly the point of
these testing systems either. Um,
ideally, ideally, they would sort of
give us some kind of indication of
people's proficiency like in a wide
range of things that might help them be
good at college, but it's a it's a real
problem.
I've heard that like SAT kind of changed
their argument a little bit or like the
way they phrase it into like it's not
that the test matters at all. They like
the argument now like is more leaning
towards like their performance on the
test indicates the students ability to
prepare for the test. Even though the
test is meaningless, the ability to
prepare for the test is what's being
tested. And that's correlated well with
other kind of things which is not like
completely outrageous to say like like I
give you like a completely stupid
subject no one heard of and tell you to
prepare for it. The people who better
prepare for it are probably better
studyers who will perform better at
college where you will also do kind of
that study but it's not perfect and it
will lead to like disproportionate
outcomes when like these people who do
not fit into the ne like nice like line
where the like standard fats go. I I
think that's right. I think the I think
an early early rhetoric of testing would
have been something along the lines of
like intelligence is uh is a is a
universal human quality. We can design
tests that's not culturally specific. We
can design tests that measure
intelligence and using these accurate
tests that me measure intelligence, we
can find the most intelligent people um
and then we can send them into college.
As soon as you recognize that some
degree of intelligence tests are
culturally biased because of all these
sort of transfer problems that we've
just been talking about um that uh you
know um if you if you have a bunch of
questions you know about ranching um
then you then you benefit uh you know
young people who are in rural states
where there's a lot of ranching going on
but like you know what does that have
you know that's sort of the equivalent
of the country club kind of thing. Um
and then the you know the other argument
for them is that uh they are pretty
good. You know there are correlations
between people's success on these tests
and their later success in college. It's
not a perfect correlation. Um but it is
one indicator that you you know if
someone is struggling to do well on
these tests. There's good there's
reasonable reasons to believe that they
might struggle to do well in college
settings and so forth. Um anyway, you
can imagine t you know um unraveling
this kind of question has huge
implications for how valuable it is for
kids to spend zillions of hours on
Minecraft. So when kids play when kids
play zillions of hours on Minecraft,
they learn a ton. Um you know, they
learn um uh how to collaborate with
other people. They learn how to find
information on the internet. You know,
the the Minecraft, a little bit like the
logical journey of the Zooinis, has no
instructions on the screen. Um, you have
to go to wikis, you have to watch
playthrough videos, you have to do other
kinds of exercises to like figure out
how to engage in Minecraft. And some of
those things seem like domain
independent sorts of skills, you know,
how to find information from other
places, how to set goals, how to pursue
those goals, um, other kinds of things
like that. Um but a but an enormous
question about the value of playing
games like that is something like well
um like if you know how to do all that
in Minecraft, does it help you do that
somewhere else? Um there's a lot of
educational psychology research that
suggests that transfer is really hard um
that when you learn things in one
domain, people are not that good um at
uh at passing it to another domain. Um
to me there are sort of two contrary
arguments to that. Um, this is sort of a
joking way of putting it, but like I
think one of the best arguments against
humans ability, one of the best
arguments in favor of humans ability to
transfer learning is civilization. Um,
like it's pretty hard to imagine how you
would develop civilization if pretty
people weren't pretty good at like
learning some things and then applying
them to new kinds of tasks. Um, uh, so
so a sort of a theme of counterargument
is that basically like educational
researchers are not good at detecting
and observing transfer. We're not good
at at conducting studies that measure
people's abilities to take things from
one domain um and put them to another
domain. If you listen to that podcast
episode with Constance Steiner, who's a
huge advocate of uh the benefits of
games for learning, you'll hear her make
an argument sort of along those lines,
which is like, come on, Justin, like if
you get really good at doing cool stuff
in Minecraft, like that will help you
with other things that you're doing in
life. Not that different from what Dana
said at the beginning of the class about
the things you learn playing in the
resistance, you know? Like I can learn
how, you know, I learned how to keep a
poker face there and now I can keep a
poker face in other kinds of places. Um,
so unanswered questions to be sure.
Good. Um, 2:25, you all should have a
wonderful spring break. Um, you should
come, there's a little bit of reading
that you have to do, but mostly you
should come with a draft. Um, the
strongest draft that you can put
together for paper two on Monday. Um, a
week from Monday, and we'll have a
chance to do some peer editing in that
class. Um, and we're going to sort of
shift from genres of learning at scale
to the as yet intractable dilemmas in
the second half of failure to disrupt.