thank you for joining uh for our joining
our St lighting talks my name is Arina
Gaza I'm a program coordinator with MIT
startup Exchange program over the next
hour you'll hear from nine MIT connected
startups each will have five minutes to
present followed by the exhibit on the
right side of the escalator so please
make sure to join and network with our
startups but first let me tell you about
our
program MIT startup exchange was created
over nine years ago to support MIT
connected startups in growing expanding
and solving the world's great challenges
we do this by fostering partnership with
LP members many of you on the audience
today as well as extensive MIT
Innovation ecosystem and
beyond our startups and our program have
a strong connection to MIT many of our
Founders have Founders and co-founders
are MIT Alam faculty or staff well some
of our startups have also licensed
technology as well as some of our other
startups are supported and vetted by our
MIT peers such as start. Nano the engine
cell startup connect
plus a bit about a network our program
has around 1,000 startup who typically
join at the pilot and Beyond stage and
our sector and geography
agnostic within our program we have a
group called st25
5 this is a a
curated uh group that receives
customized support for one year which
includes enhanced visibility to Industry
and um
corporates so when it comes to Value
startups in our program gain exposure to
a Global Network of decision industry
makers while at the same time LP members
benefit from a created selection of M
connected startups we host several
events both locally and
internationally these include
conferences with startup lightning talks
and Exhibits such as today's event as
well as virtual demo days where we
select a group of startups and you get
to interact with them in the breakout
rooms as well as
webinars speed networking events
workshops trainings and many more for
industry and corporate members a key
benefit is our ability to tailor events
to address your priorities for startups
this provides an opportunity to gain
visibility and enter new market and
ecosystems to grow and expand overall
it's a highly customized and curated
approach to
Innovation we know that some of you
already taking advantage of these
opportunities and if not please feel
free to see me and our team after this
presentation as I mentioned earlier St
exchange was established to create
collaboration between industry partners
and startups this slide highlights a
small sample of successful partnership
we've had to
date these uh partnership include
ranging from proof of Concepts large
scale Pilots customer engagements join
R&S and even
Acquisitions I hope that during exhibit
and networking breaks conversation with
startups would ins will inspire you your
own success story and add to our growing
Li list of impactful
Partnerships before turning over to our
startups here are some of our upcoming
events we have the MIT LP Symposium on
December 3rd uh if you're not able to
attend in person it will be live
streamed we have a virtual demo day on
December 11th and two events in Asia a
symposium in Bangkok and a conference in
Japan so please check out our websites
for these events and upcoming events in
the
future let's proceed and with that let's
proceed to our lightning talks today's
nine presenting startups represent a
range of Industries including space
Mobility AI healthc care and Quantum
Technologies