I always knew that I wanted to solve very
important problems that affect society.
And I'd read a book by Benjamin Carson
called "Gifted Ants."
And you know, that was a really big deal.
So at the point I thought I wanted to be
a neurosurgeon just because
Ben Carson was a real soldier.
But as I grew older, I realized that
there are other very important problems
in society that requires attention.
By the time I got into college, I knew
that I was attracted to solving problems
that are related to energy.
I'm originally from Nigeria, from a
little fishing town called Badagri.
One of those towns in Lagos that has its
own language, its own culture.
It's a little town that holds a lot of
history about Nigeria.
I was a very curious child.
I really liked to ask
the why questions.
Why do things exist?
Those are the things that
were more important to me.
And even as a 10-year-old, I
was more into reading books.
So my friends would call me "bookworm."
As a child, the US was like the place you
really want to go to.
The only way I get to go there was always
just reading the books.
It seems like that was like the frontiers
of civilization, right?
It was where the most important discovery
has been made and it was
really pushing the frontiers.
So it was like this
place that looks like heaven.
When I went to college, I knew I was more
interested in energy-related
types of problems to solve.
Because in Nigeria, we have
shortage when it comes to energy.
So it's very normal that you don't get 24
hours supply of electricity.
Those became problems that I care so much
about that I would like to solve.
As I went on, I realized that when it
comes to the density of
energy you can get from, say,
a solar cell versus nuclear energy.
Nuclear energy tops that.
I then pivoted to focusing on generating
energy from nuclear reactors
and making them technology that can be
adopted in the African societies.
I was finished in college.
I told my friends that I
really like to go to MIT.
But I couldn't do some more the courage
to submit an application, you know.
When I finished my PhD, I moved to New
York to Brookhaven National Lab.
I suppose then I
became a staff scientist.
And I really thought my career was just
going to be over there
because I really enjoyed it.
But it turns out that a place like MIT is
where you could also do
research that you care about.
You can do the
science that you care about.
When the opportunity came to
move to MIT, I asked myself,
"What else can I do that
I'm not doing at Brookhaven?"
And it turns out that I have questions,
science questions in my mind
that I've always cared about.
And I tell my students that what I do, I
don't see it as a job.
I see it as a calling.
And so when I get up every day, solving
this problem is what
is always in my mind.