Hello and welcome to Today I Learned
Climate, the climate change podcast from
the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology. I'm Lauri Fischer. Today's
drivers are buying a lot more electric
vehicles, or EVs, as they're also known.
In fact, from just 2022 to 2023, the
world's demand for the batteries that
power these EVs grew by 40%.
And that's prompted several listeners
and readers to ask us, what are we going
to do with all of these EV batteries
after they die? And as our guest today
will tell you, that's not a trivial
problem. My name is Linda Gaines and I
work at Argon National Laboratory and
I've been looking at life cycle analysis
which is basically an analysis of what
goes into the manufacturer of all sorts
of goods from raw materials in the
ground all the way through a finished
product. Where does the product get
manufactured? How does it get
manufactured? And then at the end of its
life, can you reuse it? Can you repair
it or do you have to just throw it out?
For our show, Dr. Gaines is going to
bring that lens to EV batteries. What's
in them? Can we recycle all of those
materials? And if not, what can we do
about that? And to get started, we
should be specific about what kind of
battery we're talking about. For nearly
all EVs sold today, that would be
lithium ion batteries. Lithium ion
batteries are much more energy dense
than other previous
chemistries. And so you can make a much
smaller, lighter battery. Lithium ion
batteries are the reason we have phones
that fit in our pockets and hold enough
charge to last all day. And this
technology is equally crucial for EVs. I
mean, there were electric vehicles
previously, but they were all powered by
lead acid batteries, which are very
heavy, and what those vehicles ended up
being was basically a battery on wheels.
And there wasn't really much room for
passengers or cargo or anything. With
lithium ion batteries, we now can have
roomy, zippy cars that run on
electricity. Now, this is a big deal
because cars and trucks that run on
gasoline produce literally billions of
tons of planet warming greenhouse gases
every year. And we would eliminate
almost all of that pollution if we drove
EVs instead and charge them on
electricity from cleaner energy like
wind, solar, or nuclear. And fun fact,
because of how energyefficient these EV
batteries are, even if you were to
charge your EV with electricity
generated from coal, you would still
produce less pollution than a
traditional gasoline car. But while EVs
don't burn gasoline, they do require new
kinds of materials that gasoline powered
cars don't. So, let's take a beat to
figure out what's inside an EV battery.
In any battery, there's an anode and a
cathode. And some charged particle,
either an electron or a lithium ion, is
going back and forth from one to the
other. And in one direction, it's
charging the battery. And then you can
connect a wire from one to the other and
electrons will go the other way and you
can get energy out.
It's kind of like that child's game. Red
Rover, like red rover, red rover, send
the electrons over. When you're driving,
the electrons come running along a
circuit from one side of the battery to
the other, providing the power to move
the car. And then when you charge it,
they run back to where they started. And
there are many materials used to coax
the electrons across the battery. We'll
start with the lithium that these
batteries are named for. So when we say
lithium ion batteries, we're referring
to the single atoms of lithium that dash
across the battery like part of the same
Red Rover team. Lithium is a metal. It
can be mined and we also find it
dissolved in water. The way that it has
been extracted most until very recently
is from salt lakes. In particular,
there's a set of lakes in the Andes
Mountains in Chile that are extremely
concentrated in lithium salts. And so
what happens is you pump these
concentrated lithium salt solutions into
big ponds and let the sun evaporate the
water, which can cause problems when
there are water shortages, as Chile is
wrestling with right now. But it's not
just lithium that we're concerned about.
There's a part of the battery called a
cathode that is made of several metals
bonded together. The cathode material in
a lithium ion battery is a chemical
compound that's made of lithium and
oxides of cobalt, nickel, and manganese.
Historically, they've basically been dug
out in either surface or underground
mines and then taken to a
smelter. This can cause local problems.
For example, cobalt, one of those
cathode materials that Dr. Gaines just
mentioned, mostly comes from the
Democratic Republic of the Congo, where
many miners live and work in terribly
exploitative conditions. So, it would be
ridiculous to just throw these materials
away when a battery dies. But recovering
them is not quite as simple yet as
plucking a lump of cobalt out of an old
battery pack. That cobalt is bound up
with all the other metals in the
cathode. And then the battery also
contains an anode, an electrolyte, and
aluminum and copper. And all of these
materials are arranged in super thin
sheets and then folded or rolled up
together into what is called a battery
cell. But an actual battery pack has
lots of cells in it. And if you think
about a Tesla, Tesla has cylindrical
cells. They're kind of stuck like beer
cans in a six-pack kind of thing. If
we're talking about a Tesla Model 3, our
six-pack is actually more like a 3 or
4,000 pack with all of these cells
cemented together. And that pack is the
big rectangular slab that actually goes
into the car. And as you drive around,
just like everything else, this big
complicated battery slowly slowly starts
to break down. When the battery is
charged and discharged, the lithium ions
can get stuck on the surface of the
anode or react with some of the
molecules in the electrolyte. Basically,
fewer and fewer lithium ions are free to
travel back and forth. And so, the
capacity of the battery decreases as it
gets older. And eventually, after maybe
300,000 miles or so, this battery, like
all batteries, will die. And when that
happens, we'd really like to get the
valuable materials back so that we can
reuse them. But it's not like we're just
separating our paper from our glass
here. The cathode material is a very
elegant and complex crystal structure.
And if you can actually retain that
during the recycling process, you are
getting a much higher value product out
and not having to redo all of the steps
that it took to make it. Right? Ideally,
what we want is not actually pure cobalt
and nickel. We want the elegant crystal
structure that's so good at giving us
our electric charge. But the closer we
come to that ideal, the harder the
recycling process is going to be. So,
let's say you want to do as little work
as possible to recycle your battery. The
method for you is called pyro
metallurgical recycling. And in that you
basically throw the battery into a big
furnace and some of the stuff burns and
some of the stuff
melts. And what you get out of the
bottom of the smelter is a mixed alloy
of cobalt and nickel and manganese which
can then be put back into batteries
after processing.
A jumble of melted down metals is not
very close to our beautiful cathode.
Well, at least we don't have to mine the
materials from scratch. But we could do
better. So, the next option would be to
put the battery cells through a big
shredder and get them ready for hydro
metallergical recycling. You basically
dissolve the chopped up battery in acid.
And the acid is a big soup that includes
all of the different ions that were in
the cathode material and also anything
that was in the electrolyte. And you can
do chemical reactions on that soup to
recover the different elements
separately. The cathode is still
destroyed, but this time we have pure
metals to make a new cathode. That's
better, but it's still kind of wasteful,
right?
Ideally, I would like to see some kind
of a system where you didn't need to
shred the whole thing. One small company
in Switzerland in particular has
designed their own cells for recycling
and they are building a machine that
grabs one electrode and another arm
grabs the other one and just pulls apart
this whole layered structure. So that
one arm is holding anode sheets and the
other is holding strips of cathode. So
there they're things you can imagine but
none of them has been developed
commercially at a large
scale. This is called direct recycling.
And if we can do it, it would give us
back our cathode practically intact.
With a little fixing up, it would be
ready to put in a brand new battery.
But as you can tell, direct recycling
really depends on the manufacturers
designing their cells to be taken apart.
And so far, most battery engineers have
had other innovations on their mind. As
battery technology evolves, which it's
doing very quickly, that makes a big
challenge for battery recyclers because
they really don't know what they're
going to be having to handle 10 years
down the pike. And so it's hoped that we
can develop some recycling technologies
that are more or less generic and would
work no matter what the battery design
was. It's a challenge. So there's
another issue here and I was actually
quite surprised. There aren't yet enough
batteries to recycle. Originally, people
thought that electric vehicle batteries
would only last a few years and probably
would have to be recycled and replaced
sometime during the lifetime of the car.
In actual experience, these batteries
are really lasting the lifetime of the
car. And in fact, they may be outlasting
the car. And when they do outlast the
car, even then today's EV batteries are
mostly not going to recyclers because
they're still good enough to find a
second life. If you've got solar panels
on your roof and you want to store
energy to use at night, you can use an
old battery as a backup. There's a big
stadium in Amsterdam that's powered by
old Nissan Leaf batteries. So there are
lots of ways you can use these
batteries if you don't demand the level
of performance that people are expecting
from their
vehicles. So to step back for a minute,
we should also be clear about what
battery recycling can and can't do. It
can leave us with less waste when
batteries eventually die, but it can't
replace the need to mine more lithium
and cobalt and nickel. at least not
while the EV market is still growing as
fast as it is. If you think about it
logically, because there's been such
rapid growth, even if we could get back
everything that we put into circulation
10 years ago, it would only be supplying
a very small percentage of our demand.
So, we need to be thinking about where
all this material is going to come from.
Can we improve mining so that it more
efficiently produces the metals that we
need? And how can we of course improve
the conditions of these mines for local
workers and communities? Or can we take
the most challenging materials like
cobalt completely out of the equation? A
big portion of the EV market now is
using a chemistry called lithium iron
phosphate, which has no cobalt at all.
And there are EV batteries that are
using sodium now instead of lithium. And
just while we were recording this
episode, Ford announced it's investing
in cathodess that use mostly
manganesees, which they expect will give
them a longer driving
range. So, if you're asking how we'll
deal with all of these batteries when
they die, to some extent, we just don't
know yet. Partly because we're still
figuring out what they'll look like when
they're
[Music]
alive. That's our show. Thank you to
everyone who reached out with questions
about EV batteries. And if you have
another question about climate change
and its solutions, we would love to hear
from you. Call us, leave us a voicemail
at
6172533566 or send your question in
through
climate.edu/ask. TI climate is the
climate change podcast of the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
Aaron Kroll is our writer and executive
producer. David Lashansky is our sound
editor and producer. Michelle Harris is
our fact checker. Madison Goldberg is
our associate producer. Grace Sawin is
our student production assistant. The
music is by Blue Dot Sessions. And I am
your host and senior editor, Laura
Hessie Fischer. Thank you, Dr. Linda
Gaines, for speaking with us. And thanks
to all of you for listening and for your
climate curiosity.