the research that's being done in the
clean energy sector is super important
in order to advance Solutions um using
the skills Technologies resources that
we do
[Music]
have my project was surrounding creating
a machine learning model that would
effectively predict how different
solutes and fluids flow through
fractured rocks underground we want to
monitor how solids and fluids flow so
that we can better manage carbon dioxide
storage nuclear waste repositories
groundwater contamination and all of
these things to ultimately be able to
develop better geothermal resources
having access to this kind of Technology
enables researchers scientists and
policy makers to be able to have access
to the data that allows them to make
decisions about how we're storing carbon
dioxide nuclear waste as well as
preventing groundwater contamination and
all of this ultimately brings us one
step closer to Bridging the energy
transition Gap