the MIT energy initiative presents three
questions Ana Danielson on energy
education and its role in climate action
written by Kelly
Travers the MIT energy initiative Mighty
leads energy education in MIT developing
and implementing a robust educational
toolkit for MIT graduate and
undergraduate students online Learners
around the world and high school
students who want to contribute to the
energy transition as mighty's Director
of Education anre Danielson manages a
team devoted to training the next
generation of energy innovators
entrepreneurs and policy makers here she
discusses new initiatives in mighty's
education program and how they're
preparing students to take an active
role in climate
action question what role are mighty's
education efforts playing in climate
action initiatives at MIT and what more
could we be doing answer
this is a big question the carbon
emissions from energy are such an
important factor in climate mitigation
therefore what we do in energy education
is practically synonymous with climate
education this is well Illustrated in a
2018 nature energy paper by fusu narini
which outlines that affordable clean
energy is related to many of the United
Nations sustainable development goals
SGS not just sg7 which specifically
calls for affordable reliable sustain
sustainable and modern energy for all by
2030 there are 17 SGS containing 169
targets of which 113 65% require actions
to be taken concerning Energy
Systems now can we equate education with
action the answer is yes but only if it
is done correctly from the behavioral
change literature we know that knowledge
alone is not enough to change Behavior
so one important part of education
program is practice and experience
through research internships stakeholder
engagement and other avenues at a
minimum education must give the learner
the knowledge skills and courage to be
ready to jump into action but ideally
practice is a part of the offering we
also want our Learners to go out into
the world and share what they know and
do if Done Right education is an energy
transition accelerator and mighty our
Learners are not just MIT students we
are creating online offerings based on
residential MIT courses to train Global
professionals policy makers and students
in research methods and tools to support
and accelerate the energy transition
these are free and open to Learners
worldwide we have five courses available
now with more to come our latest program
is a collaboration with mit's Center for
Energy and environmental policy research
Seer climate action through education or
Kate this is a teach the teacher program
for High School curriculum and is a part
of the MIT climate action plan the aim
is to develop interdisciplinary
Solutions focused climate change
curricula for us High School teachers
with components in history social
science English language arts math
science and computer science we are
rapidly expanding our programming in the
online space for our Global Learners we
are bundling courses for professional
development certificates for our
undergraduates we are redesigning the
energy studies minor to reflect what we
have learned over the past 12 years and
for our graduate students we are adding
a new program that allows them to Garner
industry experience related to the
energy transition meanwhile Kate is
creating a support network for the
teachers who adopt the curriculum we are
also working on creating an energy and
climate alliance with other universities
around the world on The Institute level
I am a member of the climate education
working group a subgroup of the climate
nucleus where we discuss and will soon
recommend further climate action The
Institute can take stay tuned for that
question you mentioned that you were
leading an effort to create a Consortium
of energy and climate education programs
at universities around the world how
does this effort fit into mighty's
educational Mission answer yes we are
currently calling it The energy and
climate education Alliance the
background to this is that the problem
we are facing transitioning the entire
Global Energy System from high carbon
emissions to low no and negative carbon
emissions is global huge and urgent
following the proverbial many hands make
light work we believe that the success
of this very complex task is
accomplished quicker with more
participants there is of course more to
this as well the complexity of the
problem is such that one MIT doesn't
have all the expertise needed to
accomplish the educational needs of the
climate and energy
crisis two there is a definite local and
Regional component to capacity building
and three collaborations with
universities around the world will make
our mission driven work more
efficient finally these collaborations
will be advantageous for our students as
they'll be able to learn from Real World
case studies that are not us-based and
maybe even visit other universities
abroad do internships and engage in
collaborative research projects also
students from those universities will be
able to come here and experience mit's
unique intellectual environment right
now we are very much in the beginning
stages of creating the alliance we have
signed a collaboration agreement with
the Technical University of Berlin
Germany and are engaged in talks with
other European and Southeast Asian
universities some of the collaborations
we're envisioning relate to course
development student exchange
collaborative research and course
promotion we are very excited about this
collaboration it fits well into mit's
ambition to take climate action outside
of the University while still staying
within our educational
Mission question it is clear to me from
this conversation that mighty's
education program is undertaking a
number of initiatives to prepare MIT
students and interested Learners outside
of the Institute to take an active role
in climate action but the reality is
that despite our rapidly changing
climate and the immediate need to
decarbonize our global economy climate
denialism and a lack of climate and
energy understanding persist in the
greater global population what do you
think must be done and what can Mighty
do to increase climate and energy
literacy
broadly answer I think the basic problem
is not necessarily a lack of
understanding but an abundance of
competing issues the people are dealing
with every day poverty personal health
unemployment inflation pandemics housing
Wars all are very immediate problems
people have and climate change perceive
to be in the future the United States is
a very bottom-up country where
corporations offer what people buy and
politicians advocate for what voters
want and what money buys of course this
is overly simplified but as long as we
don't don't come up with mechanisms to
achieve a Monumental shift in consumer
and voter Behavior we are up against
these immediate
pressures however we are seeing some
movement in this area due to Rising gas
and heating oil prices and the many
natural disasters we are encountering
now people are starting to understand
that climate change will hit their
pocketbook whether or not we have a
carbon tax the recent Florida hurricane
damage wildfires in the west extreme
summer temperatures frequent droughts
increasing numbers of poison pois and
disease carrying insects they all
illustrate the relationship between
climate change health and financial
damage fewer and fewer people will be
able to deny the existence of climate
change because they will either be
directly affected or know someone who is
the question is one of speed and scale
the more we can help to make the
connections even more visible and
understood the faster we get to the
general acceptance that this is real
research projects like seer's Roosevelt
project which develops action plans to
help communities deal with industrial up
people in the context of the energy
transition are contributing to this
effect as our studies related to climate
change and National Security this is a
fast-moving world and our research
findings need to be translated as we
speak a real problem in education is
that we have the tendency to teach the
tried and true our education programs
have to become much nimbler which means
curricula have to be updated frequently
and that is expensive and of course of
course the speed and magnitude of our
efforts are dependent on the funding we
can attract and fundraising for
education is more difficult than
fundraising for
research however let me pivot you
alluded to the fact this is a global
problem the immediate pressures of
poverty and hunger are a matter of
survival in many parts of the world and
when it comes to surviving another day
who cares if climate change will render
your Fields unproductive in 20 years or
if the weather turns your Homeland into
a lake will you think about lobbying
your government to reduce carbon
emissions or will you ask for help to
rebuild your existence on the flip side
politicians and government authorities
in those areas have to deal with
extremely complex situations balancing
local needs with global demands we
should learn from them what we need is
to listen what are those areas of the
world need most and how can climate
action be included in the calculations
the global commission to end energy
poverty a collaboration between Mighty
and the Rockefeller Foundation to bring
electricity to the billion people across
the globe Who currently live with
without it is a good example of what we
are already doing both our online
education program and the energy and
climate education Alliance aim to go in
this direction the struggle and
challenge to solve climate change can be
pretty depressing and there are many
days when I feel despondent about the
speed and progress we're making and
saving the future of humanity but the
prospect of contributing to such a large
Mission even if the Education team can
only nudge us a tiny bit away from the
business's usual scenario is exciting
in particular working on an issue like
this at MIT is amazing so much is
happening here and there don't seem to
be intellectual limits in fact thinking
big is encouraged it is very refreshing
when one has encountered the old you
can't do this too often in the past I
want our students to take this attitude
with them and go out there and think big