hello we welcome today Michael good who
is a vice president of Music XML
Technologies at make music Incorporated
creators of finale spart music and so
many other great things and um and a
dear friend of computational musicology
and music theory at MIT welcome Michael
hi thanks uh for the invitation great to
be here great virtually yeah I well
there's some great advantages to to the
way we're setting things up right now
and allows you to the students to get to
meet you in a way that we wouldn't be
able to perhaps in the
past I just want to jump in there and
and just ask you're the creator of Music
XML I mean this is incredible for me to
be able to talk to person who has done
so much why did you create music XML in
2000 and what what problems existed that
you H to solve with it yeah in 2000 I
was working at sap uh and I was the
representative actually to the MIT media
lab at that point which will come in
later and it was just the beginning of
digital sheet music happening sheet
music direct was out there which I
didn't know at the time but son Haw
released things where you could download
digital sheet I go W this is really cool
until I figured out oh you can only play
it in in the Su Hawk player well that's
really silly I want and finale and
sellus were there for notation programs
you couldn't move them back and forth
and get anything reasonable out of it
and it was like well the internet boom
is happening and people want to make
money on digital sheet this isn't going
to work without a standard
format to exchange sheet music between
applications people aren't going to want
to be stuck in just one thing you know
we need something like midi for musical
instruments or HTML for the web and a
lot of people tried to do an interchange
format and it had succeeded but I
figured I I could give it a good go and
I had some ideas for it and when I
visited the media lab uh I went to my
old uh thesis adviser Barry verco
Professor very verko who was at the
experimental music studio and then the
media lab and bounced this idea off him
you know you've worked in this area a
lot um am I missing something obvious
that makes it not going to work I said
sounds like it's going to work
go over to Stanford and talk to Walter
huet and elor srichfield with Muse data
and talk with David her on of humdrum
because they're doing the stuff closest
to what you're doing and David humdrum
was at Stanford that turn so that was
great I didn't have to go to Ohio to uh
to talk with him so I did that and
basically the first version of Music XML
was an XML version of muse data used XML
because at sap we were using XML to
communicate between our R3 system and
other systems so it's like old G it
seems like you have some standard
technology that the whole computer
industry is behind why not use that to
exchange for music notation back and
forth and so it's just we've got to be
able to exchange between applications so
the format is optimized very much for
exchange between applications not as a
native uh format for any particular
application so how did you get um the
initial application you users to to buy
into to this
format yeah that was always going to be
a tricky question I knew that it had to
work with either finale or seia so
nobody would care and so I gave myself
yeah if I can't get it within two years
or so to do two-way you know not just
writing not just reading but two-way
communication with either finale or
sellus I didn't care which one then
nobody was going to care and it turned
out that finale had a better plug-in
development git than Celia for that so I
was able to build a plugin that did the
two-way
communication and the way that things
really got rolling is that uh there was
a developer up in the north of Scotland
Graham Jones who had the sharpy music
Reader Program which was the best
scanning program out there
except the differences in the scanning I
mean you could only transfer via mid so
you all the great recognition that you
got in sharp ey you loss going into a
notation program because midi couldn't
handle it so I contacted Graham and said
hey we got this music XML format you
know if you do that we can and I got
this importer that goes into finale so
if you add this you know you could
really make things work better for
finale and increase your sales and he
said well because he supported nith at
the time nith was an older uh attempt at
a standard notation format that only
worked well for scanners so all the
scanning programs incremented it but
nobody else did so they said well you
could do a nift to music XML converter
and then I wouldn't have to do that I
yeah I'm not going to do that so you can
do a music XML and he did uh he wrote a
music XML uh exporter out of sharp eye
and then the make music people saw you
geez this scanning thing this is better
than what we have built in uh with
finale and it's better than what selus
has so that's when they got interested
in music XML and started to include the
plugin as part of finale 2003 for
Windows uh and and so once finale had it
in there you know you keep marketing it
you keep pushing it you know I I I spent
you know 11 years really pushing
developers to you know marketing to
developers to support the format and now
we have over 250 applications that
support it so it's great so you started
with a leader in one domain of music
notation and a leader in a different
domain that could communicate and that
ended up being part of the snowball
instead of right because because it's to
to useful
things and it it solves people go oh
this is useful so because I could
imagine that some of the industry
leaders might might have liked lock in
that they had before sure everybody was
very skeptical of of you know a standard
form which is one of the reasons why
it's not designed at all to be a native
format um because it had to be to a
reference you know it's modeling a
musical score it's not modeling how
somebody would represent a musical score
because then you would get oh your
favoring finale your favorite sellus and
and and you would get into all that that
conflict but once we had you know make
me we had the finale plug-in developer
kit and we had the two way communication
that was already working when I made my
first presentation to make music and
John Paulson the CEO said yep it's going
to happen nobody's gonna stop you so
make music figured they might as well
jump on board because there wasn't a way
to to stop it now that it was out so
let's use it for for the benefit of the
company which turned out to be for the
enormous benefit of the company over the
years so just to be clear for people who
see your current position and you were
not an employee at make music this was
not make music project yeah no I started
my in in 2000 at the beginning 2000 I
left sap and started my own company
called radari don't have me name your
company can't nobody can spell it or
pronounce it unless they're Coral
singers uh and I did a a program called
Dole for the uh uh which everybody calls
dlet to go with record a so yeah don't
have me music xml's okay but don't have
me do Crea of names for your products
I'm not very good at it but I can I can
write music notation software pretty
well so I had my own company called
recordar that was through 2011 and then
the assets of the company were purchased
by make music in November 2011 and I've
been a make music employee ever
since so you mentioned 250 applications
uh which from my look this might be an
undercount uh can read or write or do
something interesting with music XML I I
imagine you define that a success
why be beyond the initial startup what
aspects of Music XML have or your um
advocacy of it have led to this the
continued
success well the continued I mean it's
good
technology uh and we know been
continuing to Market in and improve it
we're now working on music XML
4.0 um and a nice thing now is that it's
part of the uh it's being maintained in
the worldwide Web Consortium is you know
as a community group we have a music
notation community group which is
independent of make music or recordar I
mean when I was at recordar we were kind
of independent you know it's just a you
know a one in one8 person company very I
had one one very part-time person
helping me so we were sort of like
Switzerland you know the neutral Place
everybody could go to but once I joined
make music forget about it and and
things did not improve with music XML so
Joe berkovitz was very persuasive and
worked on me for many years to uh to
transfer music XML from make music uh
ownership to know being maintained in
the worldwide Web Consortium as part of
a community group and my condition on
that was that uh Steinberg also transfer
the smole standard music front layout at
the same time so
which they agree to so we have both of
those standards in the w3c music
notation group as well as a Next
Generation project called them next
which tries to deal with the issue of a
native format and take the you know
we're trying to disrupt music XML from
inside rather than out because if you
don't keep improving formats and
improving Technologies if you think yeah
we're done it's succeeded we can kick
back and relax yeah in a few years your
your toast and so whether you know we've
there have been these awkward
transitions from midi one to MIDI 2 from
python 2 to Python 3 HTML 4 to HTML 5 so
you know we're trying to manage that as
best we can for what's the next step in
the evolution of of notation
Technologies and be ready for that while
still just keep on on working on
improving music XML for the use cases
that it does really really well so you
mentioned uh w3c's uh mnx format and
also that music XML was soon to release
version 4.0 and we see that there there
other notation formats that are not part
of w3c such as Mei and other um more
Niche formats that are continuing to be
developed um why why is music are music
representation formats still being
developed what what are the things that
are that are not totally solved here
well it's not so much that they're
whether they're totally solved it's
having the right tool for the right job
um music XML is optimized for the
exchange
between documents it's not optimized for
doing editing as in Finale or musicology
as in music21 or assessment as in smart
music it's designed for exchange and mnx
is designed more for a native format but
that's still going to be you know more
simple applications webbased
applications it's probably not something
where if you wanted to build the next
competitor to finale sellus or Doro you
would use mnx maybe you would but it's
not intended for that level as as you
get more and more sophisticated problems
and more specialized problems you want
your own you know your own abilities to
you know you want to optimize things for
those problems so Mei is optimized for
you know they think for the the the
issues of musicology I I have
issues with u how they have done that
and whether it really serves serves the
community or not but it's a it's a
specialized format for for a particular
type of application but nearly anybody
who's developing their own new
application it might be music XML
influenced and a lot of them are now you
know they oh okay I can take make if I
cover all these Concepts from music XML
I'm probably doing pretty good but it's
not going to look exactly like music XML
I mean smart music is that way the uh
the format is very much influenced by
music XML but it's not you know music
XML inside it's a lot closer to music
XML inside than finale is but it's still
not you know it's a different
format now you mentioned your advisor
Barry verco you're an MIT grad You're a
Rat bre rat is that yeah there we
go you're an MIT grad and you're a
supporter of the MIT Music Theater arts
section the leis music music library and
especially Jazz programs so I just want
to ask you um what advice would you give
to MIT students or I suppose students
anywhere who want to combine their love
for computer and their love for music
throughout their life like you yeah
that's that's an interesting question
because everybody has their own path
it's not just me I met my wife in the
MIT concert band so uh and we're both uh
lifelong performers so one one thing um
that we found out as an adult it's a lot
easier to have high quality performance
opportunities if you're a singer or a
string player than if you're a brass or
a wind player like we were uh because
there are a lot of really good Community
orchestras and choruses but not so many
good really good Community bands so we
switched to singing I switched when I
was 30 and my wife followed a few years
later and now we sing together in Opera
courses so you know being able to
maintain you know high quality
performance opportunities is one thing
uh if you want to do it for your day job
that's harder because it's a small
industry I mean I spent the first 20
years of my work working like well when
I graduated from MIT there was this was
before midi there was no computer music
industry there was okay there was New
England digital doing some clavas but
outside of that there were you know and
a few other synthesizer things but there
was no computer music industry at the
time so I did usability work for the
first 20 years of my career
and then moved
into uh music software but when I worked
I worked at deck and then I worked at
SAP with a virtual reality startup in
between there but deck and sap those
companies by themselves were way bigger
than the entire music technology
industry so it's hard but you know
you're from MIT you do hard things so um
you know connect with people uh do you
know do projects make your projects
visible contribute to open source
projects uh Network um you can't go to a
am show now n isn't going to happen next
year but yeah when nams come back you
could you know visit the N show and
visit all the different companies doing
things that you want to do show folks
what you're doing um most companies at I
mean you see the N thing it says it's
only open to members of the trade and go
I'm not I'm a student I'm not a member
of the trade well sometimes they have
student programs for access and most
companies have a very large guest list
that they can use to invite people so go
to one of the companies that you're that
you you are a customer of you know
something where you you've bought
something from them and see if they're
if they're exhibiting that they have see
if they can get you in or something to
to to exhibit the just it it's like
anything else and a when when you have a
nich market you know you got to do a lot
of networking and make your stuff you
know self-promotion make yourself
visible
you know look for the job openings that
are there if you're specifically
interested in music technology you know
i' I've got a list of you know the 25050
programs that support musicxml on the
music xml.com websites with links to all
of them so you can ah here are all the
folks who are doing at least music XML
related stuff so there's a handy uh list
of you know most of those are like one
or two person companies but some of them
are quite a bit bigger so uh everybody
has their own path I mean my path was
start my own company that's another way
to do it but I could do start my own
company because I married well and I
Married an analog integrated circuit
designer course 61 who did very well at
her company and so we were able to take
the financial hit of yeah let's start
this totally speculative thing which may
not have any income for a couple years
most people are not in such a lucky
position to be able to do
that well thank you Michael your path
has C been inspirational to so many
including myself so I really want to
thank you for taking the time to to uh
speak to me and to speak to the students
in 21m 383 computational music theory
and Analysis well thanks so much for the
invitation and everything that you've
done with music 21 which has been a big
contributor for music XML and for
musicology and just the whole general
area of computer uh music technology and
everything that you do at at Mi
thank you Michael