and thank you for giving me the
opportunity to speak today and show you
some of the work we have conducted in
the laboratory of Professor Roger k um
today I will talk about the humanizing
drug development brain Consortium and
the work that we have done into building
NE neurovascular models of neurological
diseases so it is well known that
neurodegenerative diseases affect
millions of people worldwide and pose a
significant concern in the elderly
population and despite the needs for
therapies we still lack effective
Therapeutics and this can be attributed
to the ineptness of animal models into
reproducing the pathophysiology of the
humans and which lead to high failure
rates of the clinical trials and in the
latest year um the initro research has
developed lot and in particular
microphysiological systems of MPS which
are complex multicellular system have
demonstrated superiority over
conventional inital cell culture um
because they can better recapit toate
complex cellular niches including the
neurovascular
unit in the last few years we have
collaborated with many pharmaceutical
companies and forming the humanizing
drug development brain Consortium which
main focus is the development of MPS
able to closely mimic neurological
diseases in vro in order to do so we
co-culture the blood brain barrier or
BBB with neuronal tisue which is able to
recapitulate Alzheimer's and Parkinson
disease phenotypes um the main um role
of the bloodb brain barrier in our body
is to work as a selective filter in
order to prevent armful substances into
enter of our brain is composed by three
uh cells types which are the endothelia
cells which are represented in the imun
staining of the BBB on the left in white
by parasites in red and the asoc sites
in green another big goal of the
Consortium is to shift from the use of
primary cells line into using ipss dve
because then they can better
recapitulate the neurovascular model and
with this we can investigate different
transport routs into the brain for drug
delivery and screening purposes so the
final main goal is then to develop of
invitro model which can be an
alternative to animal based
model the microfluidic neurovascular
co-culture platform that we are using in
our lab is the one represented by the
schematic on the left so there is a BBB
Central chamber where we can uh insert
the culture of the tree cells composed
in the BBB B the endoa says the Ayes and
the parasites in a mixture of fibrine
gel there is a central
compartment
uh okay no um which is used to insert
neuronal tissues which can be either
organoids spheroids or just neurons in
suspension into a Matel there are then
two media compartment on the side and
after one day after the seing in one of
the two media compartment we can add
some Sy syringes in order to apply a
trans a trans flow uh after a few days
the cells of the BBB self arrange self
arrange into forming some perfusable
microvascular networks which can kept uh
which can be kept perable up to four
weeks after the desire amount of time we
can then perform different analysis for
example we can perform or can calculate
the permeability of the Bas crature uh
we can um perform some immun staining of
the cells in the microfluidic device to
maybe visualize some specific proteins
uh we can collect super Nan either from
the media compartment or from the
central compartment and we can also open
the chip extract the gel we can digest
it with some enzymes and then we can
isolate the single cells to perform some
sequencing PCR or wer
blotting in order to check if the
vasculature is perfusable we can perfuse
some FES and dextron and the vasculature
then look like in the picture on the on
the right and by perfusing Flores and
exr we can also calculate the
permeability by looking at the intensity
in The Matrix or in the vasculature over
over time and with these methods we can
also perfuse or we can also introduce a
variety of molecules and Therapeutics
and we can see the effect that they have
on the vasculature in the context of
Alzheimer disease we can add some
exogenous Amoy beta 42 which plays a key
role in the pathogenesis of Alzheimer
disease and is also a key biomarker for
the diagnosis of Alzheimer disease uh
and by increasing the the concentration
of Amo beta 42 we can see that there is
an increase also in the permeability of
the vulture but this is not yet a
culture with the neurons um in order to
do so we use some neural progenitor
cells which they carry familiar
Alzheimer disease mutation and they have
the ability they engineer in order to
express Amo beta 42 pathogenic Amo beta
we can culture these cells into Wells in
order to form some spheroids which can
be predifferentiated for 1 days and
after we can take them and put them in
the centrer compartment for the
co-culture with the
BBB after 7 Days of Co culture of the
Alzheimer disease neurosphere and the
control one with the BBB we see that
there is a significant increase in the
permeability for the uh neurosphere
carrying the Alzheimer disease mutation
and this effect is much stronger than
just by adding the exogenous Amo beta42
meaning there is an additional effect
given by the culture with the neurons in
addition add to the change in the uh
permeability we also have some
morphological changes of the microvasc
we see that there is overall a decrease
in the vessel diameter vessel length and
the vessel area
fraction um this is a uh image that
gives an overview of the chip where the
endothelia cells are stay in in in green
forming the microvascular and you can
see the central compartment with the
neurosphere inside on the left there are
the um control neurosphere the L one in
green and on the right the the one
carrying the ad mutation in red and in
this image We Stand also for Amo beta
Aggregates which are more visible in the
case when we have the culture with have
the neurosphere carrying the mutation
and which lead then to vascular
dysfunction in the conf experimental
configuration when we have the neurons
suspended in the mitel um we can see
also some Pau deposition after four
weeks of co-culture with the BBB and I
think it's really important to underline
the fact that being able to recapitulate
these two phenotypes so Amo beta
deposition and P deposition in vro is
really challenging but it's possible by
using this uh model that we
developed as I mentioned in the
introduction aging is a risk factor for
neurodegenerative diseases however
current model still fail to um take into
account Aging in one while developing
the model um one main allk allmark of
Aging is cellular sence
which is a mechanism in which the cells
um basically is become PR is St
proliferating is resistant to apoptosis
and undergo morphological changes such
as flattening of the cells and also the
presence of multiple
nuclei um there is a strong interplay
between cellular syence and
neurodegenerative diseases and in
particular Parkinson disease shares some
of the mechanism that promote Cellular
sence in which in a viscious circle then
aggravates the uh progression of the
disease so for this reason it's really
important to develop a model that takes
into account the Aging factor and that
age match the condition of the brain
microvasculature at the onset of
neurodegenerative
diseases in order to induce in essence
there are different ways um the first
one is color replicative sence in which
the primary cells line are kept in
culture in order to be aged naturally
although this take quite some time
another wellknown method is to employ
the use of hydrogen peroxide which can
be add to the to the culture of cells
and this basically the addition of
hydrogen peroxide induce a inflammatory
state in the Cs which lead to premature
stenin um we test a different
concentration of hydrogen peroxide and
then we look at the amount of stenes
cell before and after the treatment
which was higher and then we also looked
at the main senin biomarkers or
phenotypes which are basically the
presence of nuclear damage DNA damage
the inflammatory state of the cells and
the cell cycle arrest which were all
confirmed after treatment with hydrogen
peroxide we then took a step further and
we treated the 3D
microvascular so once the microvasc
microvascular is formed we add hydrogen
perite for 5 days and then we look at
the permeability values which were
significantly higher compared to the
control case so the young BBB so with
this we were quite confident to have a
model of stence able to recapitulate the
um um the age uh brain micro environment
and that can be used then in culture
with the
neurons because of the um strong
interplay between Parkinson disease and
cellular sence we use some ipss deriv
human midbrain organoids which carry
familial PD mutations so these organoids
are able to secrete Alpha nucleus which
is a key protein in the pathogenesis of
Parkinson disease um these organoid are
differentiated up to 64 days and we
checked the effect that they have on the
uh microvasculature at different times
of
differentiation so at day seven day 21
and day 65 and we see that at day 65 the
permeability of the microvascular in
culture with these organoids was
significantly higher compared to the L1
so the next step in the project will be
to First Age the BBB with hydrogen
peroxide and then repeats the culture
with the organoids to see if there is an
additional effect or like um in the in
the um phenotype of of PD in the in the
reproducing the phenotypes of Parkinson
disease another really important goal of
the Consortium is the development of an
ipss derve sasone network of the human
BBB um
ipscs have revolutionized um in vure
research because of their capacity to be
almost unlimited expanded because they
can be um genetically engineered and
because they from them we can derive
almost the almost all somatic cell lines
and in the context of neurodegenerative
diseases is really attracting the fact
that we can derive patient specific IPS
CS with a real relevant genetic
background um in collaboration with the
whad Institute we were able to obtain
ipscs deriv parites asoc sites and the
NOA cells form in the BBB from the as1
ipsc cells and with this we were able
then to obtain an isogenic model of the
BBB similarly we can also derive some
ipc's midbrain and cber organoids and
then um have a co-culture of the
isogenic BBB with the organoids and see
if we can uh replicate or recapitulate
the uh phenotypes for specific
diseases we tested different
concentration of the Tre cells composing
the BBB the endoa the ASO and the
parites and we were able to obtain
perfusable networks with permeability
values comparable to the one of the BBB
culture with the primary cell lines and
interestingly by changing the ration of
the three cell types we were able to
tune and influence the vessel geometry
by reaching also some the vessel on the
right which are more capillary like and
More close to the invivo
situation at the same times uh we also
fully characterize the endothelia ipsc
endothelia says um making sure that they
work Express characteristic ipss marker
they were expressing OTAs and markers
and they were also really important that
they were not express any epar cell
markers and since we are also interested
in looking at the different transporter
routs in and out of the brain we also
look at the expression of the key
transporter which were confirmed so what
we are doing at the moment is to test
different transport of compounds in and
out of the microvascular networks and
also fully characterizing the ipss there
cerebral mid braing
organoids so with this I hope I convinc
you about the potential that our model
can offer into uh reproducing or into
modeling uh neur degenerative diseases
in betro uh I would like to thank all
the collaborators and colleagues that
work on the project and thank you all
for your
[Applause]
attention thank you anesca for that nice
introduction um to the project uh any
questions from the
audience thank you wonderful talk so can
we further add
micro like other immune cell part to the
MPS system so we can study the neuro
inflammation process yes so actually
that's what we are also doing at the
moment we can um at the white Institute
they can um culture the organoids with
microa in it and then the next step
would be also to look at the um at the
uh activation of microa in the case of
the neurod degenerative diseases so
that's what actually we are planning to
do yeah thank
[Music]
you excuse me sorry um I'd been handed a
microphone forgive me for a very naive
question um from some discussions with a
couple of farmer companies who've been
using AI for drug Discovery in these
areas they're producing compounds that
um have a higher percentage of which
have e efficacy uh
Effectiveness but also more of them turn
out to have uh to to be more
toxic particularly in animal models I
mean as as one of them put it to me
we're killing a lot of mice um and I was
wondering is this applicable to being
able to develop better models for
toxicity I think yes because we can
check the toxicity of the drug of the
compounds that we can add into the model
and the way the C responds in 3D
compared to 2D is quite different also
for the sesm model we see that the
effect of the hydrogen peroxide is
different in 2D or in 3D so that's
actually having this complex model would
help a lot in the looking at the
toxicity of drugs
to what extent are you able to do uh
sort of more mechanistic
characterization like at the end of this
co-culture period like how uh are you
able to isolate the different cell
populations that you've grown together
here and do um kind of deeper molecular
characterization um and uh have you been
able to uh yeah and how have you applied
that um to some of these disease models
yes um so as I mentioned in the
beginning we are able to obtain the say
from the from the gel and need with fax
or Max we can isolate the different cell
type composing the BBB so the Ayes ECS
and um parasites for the organoids we
have not yet tried to isolate the single
CS but I think there are antibodies that
we can use in order to sort them out um
we then when once we isolate the three
different cell type for the BBB we
submit them for sequencing and from that
we can obtain a variety of information
for the disease model and the control
the L one in order to compare compare
the two
so sorry if I missed it but are you do
you have the opportunity to test some of
the drugs that failed in your model soon
um it's a bit tricky um also
collaborating with uh I mean the
the the the one that are available yes
we could try them um it really depends
of the of also of the company
participate in the consultion because
some they cannot really share the
compounds that they are testing and use
so it's really also a bit
um we have to see into into that yes
because I'm sorry I'm not familiar with
the Consortium so I wasn't sure how many
industry Partners you have yes it really
depends of the rules inside the inside
the industry thank
you do you want to show briefly I think
you had a slide that said some of the
industry collaborators yes so we are
cating with taka isai
serono serono viser and