startup exchange uh discussion as I said
earlier at the beginning uh at MIT we uh
you know we we we don't just do research
uh we do produce companies uh companies
that will take the research F findings
to the uh prototype to the market and to
make an impact so that's why we have the
next session about uh startat exchange
and and my my colleague Karina will more
moderat the session and uh I'll just let
her take over
Karina thank you CJ for the kind
introduction hello everyone I'm
delighted to be here with you today to
present the startup lightning docks
we've invited two startups for you to
meet each one will present for 10
minutes followed by five minutes of Q&A
so please keep sending your question
through the Q&A feature but first I'd
like to take a couple of minutes to tell
you about our
program so startup exchange was created
within MIT corporate relations to
support MIT connected startups to grow
expand and solve The World's great
challenges and we do that by fostering
collaboration and Partnerships between
uh startups and Industry such as um
corporate members of the industry his
own program as many of you are and the
MIT Innovation
ecosystem so the startups we support all
of them must have a strong connection
with the Institute this connection might
come through the founding team the
technology and some um are also
Affiliated to uh our MIT peers who vet
and support the startups throughout the
year um today our program has a network
of close to a thousand startups
virtually work
in any sector they also may be located
in any country and we typically start
working with them when um they have a
technology or a product that is ready to
be tested or used in Real
Environment so everything we do at
startup exchange is to expose and
connect startups with the industry in a
highly Curative way and we also provide
learning opportunities to both parties
this includes launching calls for
startups based on carpet's own
challenges and strategic priorities
facilitating one-on-one meetings between
them and hosting different kinds of
events such as demo days um speed
networking events speach sessions and
the learning opportunities typically
come through via workshops that we uh
co-organize with our MIT peers so at the
end of the day the goal um of all these
activities is to fold um on the one hand
help startups uh scale pivot expand your
customer base and in case of corpet help
them learn as well about the most recent
Technologies um help them uh expand your
portfolio or even create new business
lines and um this slide features a very
small sample of the success cases we
have to date uh that usually uh include
proofs of concept Pilots um joint uh Rd
R&D and even
Acquisitions um this is startup Exchange
in a nutshell if you'd like to learn
more about our program please do reach
out I'd be happy to answer any of your
questions and uh now without further Ado
it is my pleasure to introduce you to uh
pru ra a president and CEO of ivis who
will tell us all about technological
solutions the company is working on and
now you can get involved and again
please do send us your questions through
the Q&A feature thank
you well thank you thank you Katherine
and thank you for giving us the
opportunity to present at this event um
our affiliation with MIT is through uh
Chris o Brian who's an alumni alumni of
MIT and a shareholder of one of the uh
IIs group companies um i' like to take
this opportunity to provide you an
interest C into a company IIs absorption
in um and the mission of this company is
to enable a sustainable and circular
economy um we engineer manufactur and
service most advanced gas condition and
purification products that enable a
sustainable and circular future for the
planet so think of the company as as a a
company that that produces products that
are like the genes and shovels of the
clean tech future uh our focus is in gas
conditioning and gas per ification and
these are based on our two core
Technologies temperature swing
absorption and pressure swing
absorption um the TSA technology is used
in um in in in our gas dryers um we and
and we use them to dehydrate very
various types of gases we started with
uh air dryers many years ago and then we
transition to um doing methane and
renewable natural gas dryers the methane
dryers are used in uh compressed natural
gas stations in North America uh and
more recently we've been deploying these
dryers in uh bio gas upgrading
facilities or renewable natural gas uh
generation sites um and and and more and
and now we are looking at hydrogen
whether it's green hydrogen or other
sources of hydrogen um those those uh
generation Pathways require hydrogen
drying for either fuel cell application
or industrial applications and we deploy
hydrogen dryers for for those sites um
our pressure swing absorption technology
is used to separate a mixture of gases
in many applications in the clean energy
industry um the core of our our
knowledge is in the absor absorption
materials themselves um so we we uh we
select and design absorbents that are
are used to separate um gases in a in a
pressure swing absorption system and and
our expertise in is in layering the
different types of absorbance and um and
making sure that the right Purity and
Recovery is achieved uh in the process
um so we've used this PSA technology
extensively in many many areas um PSS in
general have been around in the oil and
gas industry for a long time what is
unique about the ivis Technologies is
this combination of our knowledge and
absorbance and our um very unique what
we call a rotary Vala fast cycle
PSA and to explain that difference
between a conventional PSA and and a
rotary Val PSA there are two images on
the slide uh the image that you look at
on the left is a typical conventional
PSA um so it involves in in in in terms
of PSA purification what you typically
do depending on the gas mixtures and the
the Purity that you need you have
multi-stages of
purification and a conventional PSA
typically has um three or four stages of
purification and you see these tanks
they are very large tanks that are
filled with absorbance and these all
these tanks are connected through a lot
of plumbing and valving and these valves
are used to navigate the flow between
the various
tanks um what that what that does is it
obviously makes the the plant size quite
large it's complex um and and they have
no numerous switching valves and and
typically the failure modes for these
PSAs are the
valves what we been able to do is
replace all the plumbing and the valves
by what is called a rotary valve it's a
it's think imagine two metal discs that
are rotating um and there are lots of
channels that are machined within those
discs um and as these discs rotate we we
use the the channels to transport the
gases between the various cylinders so
what that's done in terms of uh uh in
terms of advancing the technology the
fast cycle PSA makes these vessels about
10 times small smaller and also
eliminates all the valving and the
plumbing so uh so you basically
miniaturize the industrial scale
Solutions into a much smaller system uh
which we manufacture at a factory and
ship to site and and as you're using
less amount of absorbance and less
amount of metal clearly uh it also
reduces the cost so we have used this
technology in many markets um but uh
over the last 10 years uh a lot in the
in the in in the clean energy space um
we've done a lot of work in renewable
natural gas U more recently in in in
many areas of hydrogen and now we are
introducing products in the carbon
capture space also um what I like to do
is the next few minutes talk a little
bit about our offering in the RNG space
and also the hydrogen
space so when it when it comes uh to
producing Ren renewable natural gas that
the the lingo that's used is called
biogas upgrading so the biog gas is
generated in uh many different
applications landfills Wastewater
treatments organic waste diversion da
Farms so a lot of these sites um the bio
the biom material is fermented and the
bio gas that comes out of there has a
combination of methane and CO2 and in
some cases with landfills you also have
some oxygen and nitrogen and other
contaminants so what we do is we take
that biogas and we use our PSA solution
to separate the methane from the CO2 and
that methane is called the renewable
natural gas is then either injected into
pipelines or it's used for
transportation fuel um so this is an
area that's uh we've been working in
this space for a while um we have about
uh I think it's close to 100 deployments
worldwide um just as an example of the
types of projects that we are involved
with uh these are four locations uh the
top two the top left is uh is in in
Toronto that's the organic waste
diversion facility for the city of
Toronto so all the organic waste comes
there it gets digested we take the
biogas from there we take out the sulfur
um or the H2S and then um and then we
upgrade the the bagas to to make RNG and
the RNG is injected into the pipelines U
the the side on the right is for the
city of Montreal uh again we have very
large uh plant there
um so both the locations in Toronto and
in Montreal we have uh we have managed
the construction of the site and also uh
do we provide services to those two
cities uh in terms of operating those
sites um we depl a lot of product in
Europe um much smaller scale um in uh
and we have done about 40 sites in
France and about five in Italy to date
um and we continue to expand in that
area typically we do about
five or 10 bio gas projects per year
these are these are obviously sizable uh
projects um more recently um there's
been a focus on uh farm digestors and
and the driver behind the biogas
industry that uh that uh the the the
economic driver is really that the
renewable natural gas that is formed it
is classified as a D3 Ren under the
Renewable Fuel standard so um and on top
of that you can add the lcf credits that
you get so the developers that are
developing this projects U take
advantage of the D3 r value and the lcfs
value and they're able to sell that to
the Renewable Fuel Market um so we've
been doing a lot of projects in the
Midwest and in California here you're
looking at basically um farm digestor
and menu digestor so our products are
called it's called the bio stream uh
what we have tried to do is try to
integrate the entire biogas upgrading
plant in a container so that uh the
installation cost the time to install
and the and the cost to install is
minimized and uh we are now deploying
these products um as I said as mostly in
the Midwest of the United States um so
we'll continue to work in the space um
the you know the first few years we saw
a lot of activity in landfills then it
followed then it was followed by farm
and manure digestors and now we are
seeing a transition to organic waste
diversion and a lot of companies like
the big retailers like the targets and
the
Walmarts uh and the Amazon are looking
at uh how to deal with organic waste um
and it's it's a pretty significant
number uh I think the number is 30 to
40% of all food product made in the US
is is wasted so there's a significant
amount of Bio source and the idea is to
take that and create uh Renewable Fuel
from that and so we're playing a I think
a significant role there so now let me
transition uh to the hydrogen space um
there was a lot of discussion today
about hydrogen um you know Green
hydrogen is there was presentations
about green hydrogen before and there's
there'll be a presentation after mine
about this um green hydrogen is a very
um good mechanism to make hydrogen uh
through electrolysis but a lot of the
economics Behind Green hydrogen depend
on the cost of the electron so in if the
cost of power is low green hydrogen
makes a lot of sense but if the cost of
power is high like in many regions of
the world um people are looking at other
sources of um low carbon hydrogen and
we've been working in a number of these
areas uh gasification is one taking bio
biosources and doing gasification or
pyrolysis uh people are looking at
pyrolysis of methane itself which which
they separate the hydrogen and the
carbon is collected as a as a as a
product and sold into the tire and the
paint industry uh um we have we have
done um again hydrogen production from
ammonia hydrogen production from
methanol these two are looked as
hydrogen carrier so when you either
crack the crack ammonia or the methanol
through reforming they requires
purification so uh all these various
mechanisms of making hydrogen require
some sort of gas purification whether
it's for industrial use or for you
purify to fuel C grate and we provide
our PSC technology for that uh we are
probably engaged with most of the
gasification companies around the world
in terms of producing uh compact small
scale uh PS
Solutions um one area which is
interesting is that there's a lot of
waste hydrogen produced from industrial
processes or from fuel cell systems that
are producing power and um there's a
desire to recover this waste hydrogen
because it is low cost and then reuse
that for different
applications one of the project that we
are involved with is in the Port of Long
Beach um this is a fuel cell energy fuel
cell system that's on site there that
produces power but also they have a
slipstream of uh gases that have a
significant amount of
hydrogen so what you're looking at here
is our PSA systems is a two-stage PSA we
take that gas stream we purify the
hydrogen and then that hydrogen is
actually sent to a fueling station on
site and the fuel cell cars and the fuel
cell trucks that come from Japan or
Korea or other locations when they come
to the Port of Long Beach that hydrogen
is used to fill those Vehicles so that
they can then go to the dealerships um
so there are there are many such
projects that we're involved with we
have deployed about 350 PSAs in the
hydrogen space over the last um last
decade or so um and and lastly you know
we do a lot of work um um in in the
renewable energy space but the same
technology is also used in u indust
industrial gases and and as an example
uh helium is a is a very um unique
commodity and the price of helium
fluctuates quite a bit but uhu um but we
are involved with u deploying between
four and five helium projects per year
uh in North America and what we do is we
work with an industrial gas company to
combine our PSA technology with a
membrane technology and produce high
high Purity helium for for the
semiconductor industry or other
industrial uses
um so that kind of gives you a quick
summary of the company I I mean we
obviously we've done uh work in many
different areas in terms of
possibilities of engaging uh engaging
with us I I I think um hydrogen and
biogas are core we do a lot of work
there um and we have commercial product
that we deploy so we look forward to any
uh inquiries surrounding that um in
terms of research and development and
and new products coming out um I would
say carbon capture is a space that U
we're looking at very carefully our
biogas product is actually is a carbon
capture product so we use the same
absorbant technology and the same
products uh to look at I would say not
very large scale carbon capture but
small scale from small factories
buildings uh we did a project with a
partner in New York City in Manhattan
there's a building in Manhattan which
has one of our systems at the b in the
boiler room and and they capture all the
carbon coming of the CO2 coming out of
the boiler system and then that's
liquefied and sent out to a a cement
manufacturing plant so um there are
opportunities like that where we can uh
we can do small scale CO2 capture from
point
sources uh but the more exciting thing I
think from a development point of view
is U we believe in circularity of
hydrogen CO2 and methane um there was a
discussion about CDR and I think we we
look at it as
cdrr is carbon dioxide removal and reuse
um so we looking at uh combining
hydrogen and CO2 to make methane that
can be injected back in the pipelines so
um methanization is not a new technology
it's been around for a while but it's
done at a very large scale in uh looks
like a plant uh what we are trying to do
is commercialize that as a product in a
containerized solution so uh there's a
lot of work related to heat heat
exchangers catalysis absorbance scoring
on metal
uh trying to make it almost like a fuel
cell stack or an electrolyzer stack but
looks and that does methanization so
that's an area we working with some
universities and U we look forward to
any engagement uh from the industry on
that space but um I'll stop here and
answer any questions that are
there thank you very much prau uh we do
have a few questions for you here um the
first one uh how do the economics
compare for the various sources of
hydrogen um I would say I mean you know
if you're following the hydrogen
industry over the last two or three
years there's been uh there's been
various way of classifying the hydrogen
and and uh and uh interestingly enough
there used a color scheme there's green
hydrogen there's blue hydrogen and
there's all types of shades of hydrogen
um when it comes to Green hydrogen as I
said the there's been a lot of work in
reducing the capital costs of the
electrolytes and I think uh there's good
progress there and we'll hear more about
it next um but I think the the driver
there is really the cost of power so if
you can get very low cost of power green
hydrogen becomes very attractive if not
then it's difficult to compete with with
blue hydrogen or other sources I think
people are looking a lot at gasification
today um I know we engage with probably
20 companies around the world that are
looking at various forms of gasification
I think there's some exciting things
happening there um I feel like uh um I
think over the next two or three years
we we'll see um out of the various
different Technologies some of them
succeeding and we can see gasification
based hydrogen being
competitive um I think the the other say
thing I would say is that people are
looking at ammonia and methanol is as a
as a hydrogen carrier so you make green
hydrogen or other forms of hydrogen and
use ammonia and meth ethanol um the
economics of that are not not clear yet
but I would I would think um right now I
would say green hydrogen with low cost
power or um hydrogen from gasifiers is
probably the two Pathways we look at and
then there's the obviously the
traditional making hydrogen from from
natural gas and capturing the carbon
that's probably also one of the
attractive batteries thank you um could
you tell us what's driving the bio gas
markets and the economics behind
them um I think the the driver is uh is
a renewable field standard right so it's
um um because of the requirements of the
uh the uh the refiners in they have to
buy a certain number of credits in terms
of renal fuel credits U that's so
there's the the RFS credits and then
there's the lcfs credits in California
and some other states in North America
so a combination of the two
is generating the demand for renewable
for RNG and there are some um you know
in some locations um the utilities
themselves are required to have a
certain percentage of uh renewable
natural gas in their pipelines um like
uh in some provinces in in Canada um and
that's driving a demand for RNG also so
those those utilities are then are able
to provide 10 15 20 or off oft
agreements to the Developers that I
think that's that's a strong driver okay
and um last question have you done any
projects in the carbon capture space and
how does your product fit uh in that
space um we've done a few um I think as
I said the most U interesting one that
we have done because you know our
product um is probably not suitable for
carbon capture from a utility from a
power plant or for a cement plant uh but
it's more uh small scale industry
and U and buildings so um one of the
most exciting projects that we did a
couple of years ago is as I said it's a
it's a residential building in Manhattan
and and there are some
legislative um requirements that are
driving some of these projects in
Manhattan or New York um and what we did
is we we um put in our um carbon capture
solution in a in a in a boiler room of a
building and we take all the exhaust gas
from their heating system and we
separate the CO2 from that and that then
CO2 is liquefied and taken out to a
cement manufacturer who uses CO2 uh to
create for for manufacturing of cement
um so that's one of the exciting things
I uh it's a very unique um project and
the reason why we are able to do it is
because how compact our PSA is and
that's the fast cycle PSA enables you to
do that I think if uh they economics of
that project are successful there's um
there's demand for that um and I think
um obviously from a regulations point of
view um the state of New York is pushing
that I think if you're successful there
I suspect that that will uh that the
same regulations will be looked at
probably in other parts of the
world okay thank you rabu thank you
again for being with us today well thank
you for giving us the opportunity