the MIT energy initiative presents
straight from the cow's mouth desire
Plata aims to capture methane before it
warms the climate written by Deborah
halber at one of the nation's largest
dairy farms environmental engineer
desire Plata and her students weighed
through the muck of a thousand cattle
inside the football fields siiz Barn
some animals sniff curiously at the
devices Plata and her team are using to
measure levels of methane in the air as
part of their digestive process cows and
other livestock belch methane releasing
large quantities of the colorless
odorless gas to the atmosphere
agriculture is the largest source of
methane emissions in the United States
with oil and gas operations a close
second according to the US Environmental
Protection Agency EPA methane is the
second most impactful human generated
greenhouse gas after carbon dioxide CO2
over the the past two centuries
concentrations of methane 120 times
stronger than CO2 at trapping heat in
the atmosphere have more than doubled
Plata an associate professor of civil
and environmental engineering at MIT has
developed tools aimed at reducing
methane emissions the good news she says
is that because methane is short-lived
compared to CO2 cutting methane could
have a fast beneficial effect on
atmospheric warming Plata is director of
the MIT methane Network a group of more
than two dozen researchers Around The
Institute and elsewhere dedicated to
reducing methane emissions through
Innovative Technologies business
strategies and policies the goal is to
cut emissions by 45% by 2030 which would
save up to 0.5° C of warming by 2100 by
removing methane plota says we could
potentially avoid critical climate
tipping
points sustainable from the
start when she was was 7 or 8 years old
plate was driving with her mom through
her rural Hometown a short distance from
the Atlantic coast it struck her that
many of the people they knew were sick
some with cancer some with what turned
out to be neurological diseases I said
it's got to be something everybody
shares Mom some residents didn't want to
believe they were being sickened by the
family-owned mckin company a 7 acre
liquid waste disposal site that stored
and buried toxic fuels solvents and
chemicals such as Tri chloroethylene
in 1977 the EPA confirmed that the
chemicals had leeched into private Wells
contaminating the groundwater the thing
that is really drawn me to environmental
science and engineering is that this is
a small town and the people who owned
that facility were family friends Plata
says it made me realize that we as
scientists need to do a better job
helping Industries identify more
environmentally sustainable routs to
profitability at Union College Plata
studied chemistry she earned her
doctoral degree in chemical oceanography
and environmental chemistry from the MIT
Woods hle oceanographic institution's
joint program in
oceanography in grad school I asked my
professors if I could poke around the
other engineering Labs at MIT and ask
people what they were making how they
were making it and how an environmental
engineer might help them make their
design and Innovation process
sustainable from the start she says
that's the underlying theme of all that
I do help people build better
Technologies in the hope of avoiding
another mckin company
in 2021 she received mit's Harold e
Edgerton faculty Achievement Award for
excellence in service mentorship and
research that impacts critical societal
challenges in environmental
sustainability and social justice she
mentors undergraduates pursuing Energy
Research through the MIT energy
initiative Mighty undergraduate research
opportunities program Europe up she also
serves on the faculty steering committee
for mighty's future energy systems
center which looks at how Tech
technology and policy demographic Trends
and economics are reshaping energy
supply and
demand catalyzing a
solution Plata's primary teaching focus
is aquatic sciences and water
engineering her knowledge of
oceanography got her thinking about how
to neutralize methane the way certain
ocean dwelling microbes do by processing
it before it escapes into the oceans in
the atmosphere when Plata and colleagues
measured methane leaks from natural gas
infrastructure the overall levels coming
from distribution pipelines were small
yet the problem was pervasive we were
thinking what engineered way could we
take this low-level methane and turn it
into something else Plata's lab found
that passing methane through a heated
zeolite a clay like material with a
consistency between baby powder and cat
litter can help convert methane into CO2
without a match or any other combustion
process converting methane to CO2 may
sound like a bad idea but because
methane is the more onerous contributor
to Global in it ends up being a net
benefit and because methane is much more
dilute than CO2 the relative CO2
contribution is minuscule she says
initially Plata's team envisioned
incorporating zeolite into household air
filters but they decided to focus on the
biggest methane offenders Dairy Barns
and coal mines the first time Plata
tored a large indoor livestock facility
she was struck by the enormity of the
air moving systems that keep the cow's
air fresh and germ free the sheer volume
is astronomical it's like 10 tractor
trailers moving past you in 5 seconds
that's our chief technical challenge
getting huge volumes of air through the
zeolite she says at the moment potential
Solutions are too energy intensive for
platus Taste when you're proposing a
climate technology you don't want to eat
up more fossil fuels than you're going
to offset she says but it's early days
and plenty of strategies are left to
explore the payoff could be significant
deploying the technology and ventilation
shafts at coal mines would have such a
big effect it could start to measurably
reduce atmospheric levels of methane
almost immediately and if you could
deploy the filters at Dairy barns you'd
solve the methane warming problem she
says it's equivalent to taking all the
combustion engine vehicles in the entire
world off the road times
three we want to fix this as an engineer
working on real world Solutions plot
strives to design innovations that
companies want to adopt because they're
better for the environment
they perform better and also because
they cost less than existing
technology however even with her
emphasis on cost co-optimization Plata
has noticed a shift in how corporations
and individuals view potential costs
associated with sustainability there's
been a huge swing in the desire to spend
a little extra money to prevent
environmental damage today people will
come to us and say we want to fix this
problem because of the environment and
even if it costs us a little bit more
we're willing to do it when Plata think
back on what happened in Maine she
doesn't believe the mckin company was
evil or even hiding the truth a lot of
the time she says polluters don't know
about the effect they're having on the
environment or if they know they don't
know how to fix it that's where our
expertise can come in pla says we can
say let's think about this problem a
little differently how do we get you the
function you want without the damage one
of the things my background and
upbringing have taught me is industry
and the people within industry these are
your neighbors and they probably want
the right outcome if you can innovate
with them or help guide them to that