very very happy. I actually transitions
beautifully to Don Lassard's
conversation on business models for
deploying and how to get that upfront
cost spread out. And uh Don, I I as I've
done all all day, um you are much better
off introducing yourself and all of your
history than I I'll be brief on my
history. I'm I'm Don Lassard. I'm an
extinguished professor at MIT.
51 years in the Sloan School. Uh my my
claim to fame, I guess, here I I was one
of the two faculty leaders on the energy
minor that we built across all five
schools, which was really really one of
the most fun experiences at MIT. Uh I
also once upon a time I taught finance
and I came to realize this is largely
about financial engineering. Not largely
but financial engineering is
overwhelmingly important here. Okay, I'm
going to take just a little tiny slice
of Nikki's presentation which is
fantastic. Determining appropriate
pricing that balances utility
investments with customer usage. So to
me that's the business model. All this
other stuff is everything you need to do
to get there. It's terribly even that
piece is complicated enough. So, let's
just focus on that one. Um, problem,
right? High capital cost, but your
all-in monthly cost has to come out
about the same as the current all-in
monthly cost of gas plus electricity.
Otherwise, it's dead in the water. If
you run current costs of geothermal,
like your p even your second stage of
your pilot through current utility
models, it costs 2x at least. So it's
two to three times as expensive as it
needs to be to meet the cost right now.
How do we get there? Well, this is my
whole presentation. I have 17 more
slides, but this is the whole
presentation.
Um, let's see. So, high capital costs.
That's our issue. We are replacing ice
boxes with refrigerators.
We don't have to buy the ice every day,
but the refrigerator costs a lot. And
when I hear discussions of pricing, it
seems to me we're still trying to price
it. is if we're pricing ice whereas in
fact we're renting a we're renting a
refrigerator right so if you think of it
as renting a refrigerator that's the
analogy we want as opposed to we're
buying ice uh so one-third bore holes
one-ird system one-third customer and
system and conversion I'd like I thought
I'd corrected that how do we solve the
problem is this is now 2x right we need
to get monthly cost of the homeowner
near current electrical and gas bill
that's what we have to
2x. How do we get there? Well, we got to
reduce the capital cost. So, you got to
work like crazy. The unions have to work
like crazy. We have to get down a
learning curve. We really have to do
this, right? The capital cost must come
down.
We have to allocate. At the moment,
we're overbuilding these systems. Loop
one, 425 tons against 70 275 tons
actually used, right? You overbuild the
system or whatever the numbers are.
Overbuild the system by a massive
amount. Somehow or another the excess
capacity has to get banked and the
customers only have to get charged for
the actual used capacity. Third,
right, this is a lot of the discussion.
How do we monetize some of these other
benefits? How do we get a heat pump tax?
How do we get an investment tax credit?
How do we get some payment for the
avoided utility investments? Those are
huge.
Monetize other benefits and apply. So
and then the financial engineering part
is how do we spread the recovery of the
capital over 30 years in constant terms
inflationadjusted terms real terms
if we run it through the current utility
model it looks like this in real terms
it's big in the first year gets smaller
over time it's twice as high as it ought
to be because we're using we're not even
using a nominal level payment mortgage
we're using rate of return plus
depreciation, right?
Well, 30 years ago, we invented a level
payment novel mortgage. How do we spread
the cost of capital equally in real
terms over time? If we could do all of
those things, we'd be there. So, you do
your job in getting the cost down,
really build it neat. Uh we find a way
to bring in some of the other grants and
tax incentives. Uh we grab back some of
the avoided costs out of the electrical
system. Ideally, we get some carbon
credits for the carbon saved and then we
spread the capital cost evenly and then
people say, "Gee, this is more
economical
than the existing system and it's better
for our kids, it's better for our
community, we avoid the heat islands, we
avoid all the other stuff." So, we get
all these other bennies for free in a
sense. Okay. Uh learning curve. So,
learning curve, right?
There are learning curves out there.
There's evidence out there. It looks
like you've got 50% from one to two, but
probably this is going to be an 11 or
12% learning curve over time. Like a lot
there's a lot of evidence on this. So to
the ratebased folk, we'd say you got to
be willing to eat some of it because
you're investing against the learning
curve and there's an investment in the
learning curve. And so you can't load
all of the current costs onto the
current customers because part of the
current cost is a public benefit of the
learning curve that everyone else will
gain. And so this has to be built into
the thinking. Um
excess capacity well let's allocate only
the capacity used right and the excess
capacity is banked.
um mechanisms to monetize benefit. So,
assignment of carbon tax or renewable
energy, linkage of various incentive
systems, assignment of voided cost
credits. I mean, complicated, really
complicated and hard to do, but we've
got to get our act together and make
this all in one place.
Capital recovery model. And I don't
expect everybody to follow this at uh
3:30 in the afternoon. But if you take
cost of capital times unavertised
capital plus depreciation and you look
at your annual charge, it starts on a
50, you know, it starts high and it
comes down over time. If you have a
level nominal charge, right? It's like
that. A level real charge would be
rising over time with inflation.
Short story.
If you if you had a payment that looked
like an index treasury
and you could tell people that looks
like social security because social
security is indexed to inflation.
If you have a payment that's indexed to
social security, it can start at 1/ half
the level of a fixed nominal payment and
it will grow at social security over
time and it will give the utility the
rate of return that they're allowed full
recovery of capital.
It's fairly straightforward. Just have
to do it. Okay. Uh so constant real
capital recovery. There are ways to do
this. Uh I wrote it up in 1975 for
totally different reasons. Uh it's all
in there. Okay. Now, alternative pricing
models. Uh we could consumer purchase
inhome uh and the utility supplies the
common stuff or the utility supplies
everything. Right? Those would be the
two choices. And you could charge for
thermal usage or you could charge for
capacity. I personally like charging for
capacity. I'm being told five minutes. I
think thermal usage is a little bit like
charging for ice in the ice box. I'd
like capacities. These are fixed cost
systems. You're largely talking about
recovering capital costs. But one, two,
or three or four. Okay. But now let's
get simple pass forward. Stage one,
pilot stage. Stage two, roll out stage.
Stage three, steady state. In pilot
stage, there are only very few systems.
They're incomplete. There's no market
for there's no thermal market and the
vintage for the technical types the
vintage of capital is too young. It's
all new and so if you have standard rate
recovery you're going to be recovering
way too high rates. What would I do if I
were in Jaime's position? I'd say in the
short run we fix the cost equal to the
current charge
per unit of capacity period
and we charge the customer with that
amount and the difference 80% of the
difference we stick on rate base
20% of the difference we give to Nikki
so she has an an incentive to bring the
difference down right we say basically
we're going to price it off current gas
plus electricity
and we're going to stick the rest of it
the rate base for learning curve for
learning for all of these other benefits
in the first and you might to protect
yourself you might say for up to 3% of
the ext installed base or up to 5% of
the installed base this is a learning
investment just matches the old one
roll out stage you're still going to
have relatively few systems but you can
you can do a cost of capital recovery on
those systems as long as it's level and
real as opposed to nominal and declining
steady state, it doesn't matter because
you're going to have investments of all
vintages and it's going to look like the
existing system and you could go back to
the existing system if you wanted to.
But by then, by then you would have
devised a new system. And remember this
is the problem for utilities in general.
We're going from operating cost to
capital costs. Renewables are capital
costs. We're getting rid of fossil fuels
which are operating costs. So this helps
us actually move from a volumetric to a
capacity charging system. Okay, I got
one more two more minutes. Uh
consideration for low-income lowwealth
households. I think this would be a
great area. Take the one-third that is
the retrofit in the internal system. Get
the Boston Foundation to work with you.
Get them to buy down the cost of the
household part for low-income
households.
Don't throw it at the utility.
say twothirds of it is a standard rate
and if you qualify low income we'll buy
down the other third and that will help
us get all of the 20 houses around the
culdesac to convert. Uh then their
appendices so that's it. Uh
so thank you Don. So so Don is a
neighbor and I went for a walk and I
said well here's here's where we are
with the cost. Can you figure out some
solutions? So uh
uh and I I just if you if you didn't
catch that in in the delusion of
information and ideas um he he's putting
out a whole bunch of series of solutions
to deal with the cost as it is today
with the first projects. And one of the
things I want to flag on that is that
that cost today with these first
projects includes the entire cost of the
building transition which incidentally
also includes all of the like challenges
of our aging. I think someone said
crappy buildings. Yeah, we we have
crappy buildings here. Just saying it.
and and all of those problems that are
ne from a hundred years of neglect, the
asbestos, the mold, the faulty wiring,
the code violations, they are a part of
the challenge of decarbonizing our
buildings because you cross the
threshold and you have to deal with
them. And so that cost is baked into
that total sum. Part of what Nikki was
referring to as going into new build is
you don't deal with that at all. And
even today, those pipes and bore holes
can actually balance out for the energy
supply in a kind of more classic gas
utility approach. So, the incredible
news is that we might have tools to
remove the cost of all of our building
upgrades, which has all these other
incredible benefits like health and
well-being and comfort. Um, so I just I
just wanted to clarify that distinction.