[Music]
is
in
[Music]
check one two one two
is
[Music]
check seven check
seven Sanjay was deeply interested in
the development of scientific
institutions in India and he visited
[Music]
is
on
[Music]
is
good morning everyone we're going to get
started uh it's a great pleasure to
welcome you all I just wanted to
introduce uh uh Dean huttenlocker who's
going to open the event thank you
[Applause]
good morning
everyone it's really an honor to be here
with you today to celebrate the life and
the work of sanjoy mitter with friends
and
colleagues I didn't have the privilege
of knowing sanjoy well like you
do but his warmth and his kindness could
be seen and felt even at a
distance and the inspiration and support
that he provided to students posts and
Junior faculty was known well beyond his
research group and Beyond Lids in fact
even way over there in Tech Square where
I was a graduate student in the 1980s
which felt like a different planet from
MIT that's for
sure
um my friend and colleague Petro perona
spent I think one year as a postto with
sanjy that's where I sort of really
first uh had a
close one one distance link and and you
know I think one year in uh San Joy's
group really changed I think Petro's
entire approach as a faculty member and
and not just in a scholarly way but also
uh in sort of you know bringing his own
Humanity to his group uh and you know
Pedro can reflect on that a lot more
eloquently than I can it's his direct
experience but that was something that I
watched happen in somebody I knew
well so Sandra was not only an
outstanding researcher mentor and
collaborator uh he also really excelled
at building the lids Community serving
as Lids director starting in
1981 and he really broadened the lab's
efforts in information Theory bringing
in uh Robert Gallagher starting a few
years later to serve as co-director
with him between
1986 and
1999 and that led to a period of um
really Dynamic advances in coding
information Theory large scale
statistical inference and estimation
where Lids played a really Central role
um and in some ways uh you know it was a
period of a lot of change much like what
we're trying to do with the College of
computing uh in broadening Computing not
just broadening uh what goes was on an
individual uh lab uh at
MIT and under the lead leadership of
sirach there he is I'm going to single
him out for a minute uh Liz is
undergoing another period of broadening
uh with you know new faculty bringing
computational informal methods to bear
on problems in both the physical and the
social worlds and I'm really proud to
have this lab and an exciting me to have
this lab with its long history of
innovation and of periodic reinvention
of the lab's focus and Mission as part
of the schwarzman College of computing
because it's that kind of repeated
invention and Innovation and change that
I certainly hope the college will stand
for 85 years from now uh when we think
about the 85 year history of
Lids
um with Sandro's nearly two decades at
the Helm of the lab I think it's hard to
argue that anyone else has had a more
positive impact on Lids in its 88 5 year
history so it's really wonderful today
uh that you're organizing this
reflection on sanjoy this celebration of
sanjoy and his broad and deep positive
impact on people on science and on
institutions and it's really humbling to
kick off this celebration and
recognition today thank you all
oh and awesome need
introduction hi everyone uh that's hard
to follow but uh uh well I'd like to
welcome everyone uh to join us today
looking over the room I'm so glad to see
so many familiar faces from Lids and ECS
both past and present some of whom have
traveled very long distances to join us
today for this special occasion uh I
want want to begin by thanking those who
have made this event possible uh through
their diligent planning and organization
first and foremost I'm going to also say
sarach caraman uh the lad's director who
was a key figure behind the scenes
pushing things forward uh as well as the
faculty planning committee including Ali
jbai who's here uh Pablo parillo Le Jong
Jang uh anant sahai hi
anant uh mardal as well as the staff
team including Shila pevu Bill tildon
Amanda Moore and many staff volunteers
thank you to San Joy's family especially
pronob uh for helping us bring a bit of
San Joy's character uh to the event and
thanks to all the members of our
community who are joining us today we're
very honored by your presence and uh
thankful for the chance to gather and
share memories of our colleague uh
mentor and friend sanjoy mid um I will
not be the last one to point this
straight out today but it Bears
repeating sanjoy was a true scholar um
someone whom I've learned so many things
from he was deeply and profoundly
curious about everyone as much as
everything everyone who was lucky enough
uh to know and interact with sanjoy
remembers how he opened conversations so
what are you up to and by that sanjoy
never meant how busy are you or what
important career Milestones have you
achieved he really really meant uh what
are you exploring what have you enjoyed
lately a conversation with sanjoy was
always about what sparked your interest
what questions you had what new
intellectual puzzles uh you were
intrigued by he always wanted to know uh
what the passionate and curious people
around him were excited about and it
shows in almost every picture um and
portrait of sanjo which we have he's
listening attention full generous and
always accompanied by excellent
open-ended questions and references was
his gift and he offered it freely for
all many of his students and those in
his orbit noted the change in atmosphere
that happened around sanjoy instead of a
high pressure fast-paced sense of frenzy
they were encouraged to take time to
reflect carefully on what they absorbed
allowing for time to Foster
understanding ask questions and make
imaginative connections I cannot
emphasize how wonderful and how
necessary these reminders to slow down
and think deeply were during my early
years at MIT and I'm not alone Ben
vanroy um a friend U colleague now a
professor at Stanford beautifully
described lid's calm atmosphere in a
testimonial uh about his time here
saying that the place encourages
students to take time in producing the
best ideas and problem for formulations
and to understand issues in deep
ways around the same time in early 2000s
Tom Richardson wrote I believe the
intellectual atmosphere at Lids was
largely set and maintained by the
director sanjoy met he was continually
reaching out to other areas of
engineering as well as mathematics and
physics in search of interesting and
potentially useful ideas problems and
techniques fellow graduate students
organized at one point a series of
internal lectures in which we would
present to each other interesting things
we learned the this eclectic choice of
topics usually had little to do with our
ongoing research uh or even engineering
per se this effort reflected the desire
many of us shared to grow in bread not
just in depth in retrospect I see that
such an effort was natural within the
atmosphere of Lids at the time so I
think we're sort of emphasizing the same
themes around ld's approach this is
natural but not coincidental sanjoy
fostered the culture of LD deliberately
choosing to create the kind of
environment that brought out the best in
people Petro perona um in a lovely
testimonial which we exerted from San
Joy's obituary wrote that the
intellectual and social atmosphere which
uh that I met in Professor M's group at
LDS was unique and precious wholly new
to me I liken it to the atmosphere of
the Renaissance court at its Center the
enlightened Prince sanjy M would provide
funding inspiration emotional support
and an aesthetic Cannon the courtiers
The Graduate students and post talks
would be given the intellectual Freedom
the encouragement and the resources to
follow their own curiosity and encourage
to work on a diverse array of problems
again and again we hear the same
refrains that characterize our
relationships with sanjoy quiet
encouragement to pursue interests
freely a thoughtful approach to
interdisciplinary educ Ed ation before
interdisciplinary education even was a
thing or a term but also done correctly
and deeply and the mentorship that felt
like a wonderful conversation with a
friend I remember that when I was a
graduate student very preoccupied with
my own research and trying to write
papers he always came to my office he
used to go around uh visiting offices of
all graduate students when he was a
direct when he was the director and told
me you should go to as many talks as you
possibly could
his reasoning was you never know where a
good idea will come from and he was
right sanjoy understood that scholarship
is not one lone genius laboring in
isolation producing publishing endlessly
it requires many curious people sharing
questions and ideas exploring areas of
study far outside their comfort zones
risking vulnerability as we admit
ignorance and um ask for um help that's
exactly the culture sanjo inst instilled
in LD and which makes me proud to be
part of this wonderful Community a
community consisting of friends pursuing
truly foundational and interesting
questions questions that change over
time but always with the same curiosity
and desire for a deep understanding
using a diverse set of
approaches friends fuel each other and
our work is better for it but that fuel
is never purely intellectual was not
that way with sanjo in particular we
fuel each other with kindness with
company and with shared meals I was very
uh Lucky had the privilege to attend
number of dinners with sanjoy who was
quite the gastronome and I remember him
saying life is too short for white wine
while raising his glass of
red sanjoy was as always quite correct
but looking around this room I'm struck
that life's brevity is made sweeter not
only by good red wine but equally by Joy
curiosity and good company I hope that
each and every one of you will take the
time to turn to each other great friends
both old and new and ask each other a
simple yet profoundly important question
so what are you up to thank
[Applause]
you so now we're going to have Professor
pron of meter this is sano's brother
who's going to tell us U
yeah was going to say a few words
go ahead PK
okay yes please
go go ahead PK okay I will
start so my talk is going to be on the
San early years
and the Genesis of his
interests first of all I want to say
that due to unforeseen circumstances I'm
unable to participate physically at this
conference I want to thank all of you
who have gathered here to honor my late
late brother djoy I thank the organizers
of this conference for giving me the
opportunity to say a few words about him
many of you are his
colleagues and friends as well as his
former
students you have known him in his
mature years and can attest as to his
wide range of
interests his office and home was filled
with
books on his professional interests on
mathematics and at home also books on
economics sociology
history art and so on as well as novels
in many
languages the coffee table of his Mount
oen Street home was always piled with
books which were on his reading list he
was obviously a very cultivated person
speaking fluently besides English
Italian French and German and of course
his native language
pingori he and his late Italian wife
Adriana maintained a home in Florence
and it has been said that he spoke
Italian with a fartin
accent what I want to address here today
is a question of the Genesis of his
diverse
interests and for that we have to go
back to his early years in postc
colonial
India the story of his family background
is well told in the obit MIT obit his
father who died young was electrical
engineer and Sano was to follow later in
his footsteps he left so Sano father
left a library of books which Sano
inherited mostly on mathematics as well
as notebooks filled with calculations
which her mother had
preserved amongst the books I want to
two which sanoy must have read there was
a book of calculus written by an
electrical engineer at the turn of the
20th centur at the beginning of the 20th
century where you were taught to
calculate as Newton must have done with
power series for good function but no
but with no proofs
whatsoever learn to calculate and proofs
will
follow the other book also by an
engineer was in F series but dealt with
in a very sophisticated way and this
time with proofs including the fact that
the F series doesn't always converge for
all continuous functions and examples
due to
V this must have
left a profound impression on my
brother between the ages of 16 and 18
and 20 sanj was a Unity of Kolkata where
he took his first degree in
mathematics the early postcolonial years
of Kolkata were those of intellectual
ferment San had his classmates many of
whom would become well known as
economists and
historians amongst them was his very
close friend the E colist Economist
sukar chakravarti who was later close to
Samuelson and solo at M
sanjo and his friend who had anic
knowledge engaged in discussion in pure
mathematics logic economics history
novels Etc all this was in his Kolkata
years before he went to
England to become an electrical engineer
in his
turn I inherited my brother's library
and also found books on poetry and I
here I speak of the French symbolists
and German Romantic Poets of the 19th
century novels by Thomas V and so
on all this was a translation of course
but later when he he had mastered many
of these languages he was to read some
of these books in the
original so you see here the roots of
sano's intellectual
interests after these formative kak
years he went to England where he was in
engineering school of the Imperial
College after his first degree in
electrical engineering he went to
Switzerland where he worked as actually
as an engineer at Brown B near
cich it was there that he mastered
German after his SN as an engineer in
cich he went to work in Geneva as an
engineer where he mastered French he had
a private French tutor and he once
showed me proudly The Notebook he kept
where he did the grammar exercises quite
methodically as you know from his obit
he then went back to Imperial College
for his PhD then to the US first at Case
Western Reserve and Hereafter for the
rest of his career and life at
MIT the speakers who follow will talk
about many aspects of San's work at LS
and at the center for the study of
intelligent control systems of which he
was a co-founder
on my part I would like to close by
saying a few words about San's deep
mathematical interest he was not a
calculation
man although he could calculations when
necessary his 4y was in his
comprehension of deep mathematical
Concepts which permeates his work I will
site as a mathematical physicist a
sample of some papers of Sano and
collaborators which show this there are
for example his papers with Nal Newton
on a variational approach to nonlinear
estimation their papers on the calan buy
filter and entropy flow this work I'm
reminded is close to the variational
formulation of non-equilibrium
statistical mechanics due to jonan and
collaborators which deal with
macroscopic fluctuation of
non-equilibrium stationary States and
produces a hydrodynamic like equation
for the
fluctuation another people which I like
to which I would like to site as an
example is that with the Princeton
mathematician Charles feferman and oppos
do Har Nar on testing the manifold
hypothesis which states that big data
tend to concentrate around low
dimensional sub manifolds as some
sufficient at of some sufficiently high
ukan space in this paper they produce
algorith
to test the hypothesis there are no
doubt many other examples which you
would know better than me with them with
these remarks I end my reflection and
thank all of you for listening to
[Applause]
me thank you panov and I guess now we'll
start with the speaker with the panel
I think I'll do the same
I
think I was going to start this off is
this mic
on yeah okay Shila if you could put up
the slides of mine
yeah I was asked to moderate this uh
session my name is George verges uh and
we'll get a slide up now to show you who
else is on this oh there we go
um so I'm with MIT and I'll tell you a
little bit more about um my story here
as I talk about sanjoy um and we have
Alan wilsky Peter FAL Jose mura Maxim
rinsky and I'll leave them to introduce
themselves as uh their turns come up uh
so maybe we can do I have a clicker for
the is it
yeah I tried the green button there we
go okay uh so I first
um went back
um I first heard about sanjoy when I was
um doing my doctoral work at Stanford
and the work I heard about was what he
did with his first PhD student at Case
Western and the Simon mitter work is
very well known uh
1968 this was his uh he joined case
Weston around 1965 and this was his
first uh PhD student um and I ended up
writing a paper that that had some of
the same themes it was about modal
control of uh State Space Systems as I
look back on that paper I see that
sanj's work was so well embedded that
all my references are to uh secondary
sources after sanjoy after the mitter um
uh Simon work uh so but it's a beautiful
paper and I've reread it uh recently so
this was where I first heard about
Sunjoy um and then he had a very direct
impact on my coming to MIT because he's
the one who told my thesis adviser Tom
kyot that there was a position being
advertised in the electric power systems
engineering lab and they wanted someone
who could do systems and control things
in the context of Power Systems uh so I
gave it a shot came and interviewed and
it was actually sanjoy Telling Tom kyot
that I'd actually got the uh position
that's how I first heard from it started
with sanjy
um I came to a different lab than Lids
so I always had one foot in Lids uh but
sanjoy was kind of a guiding spirit and
guardian angel as you'll hear from many
people uh throughout my uh career at
MIT I remember him at the time I was
coming up for tenure um collaborating
with Fred schwee to advance my case and
I think he he never told me that I
shouldn't be doing something I'm doing
or that I should focus on something else
but he was concerned that I had one foot
in each of two labs and he didn't want
me to fall through the crack so he spent
some time trying to find a handle for me
as he put it uh that he could something
he could use to describe me to other
people anyway um whatever he did worked
and I uh stayed um and so we went
through many years uh these are pictures
from a party um after I'd been here 31.4
years so that's why ppai um my students
on a post at that time Thomas held
decided to throw me a party you see
Sunjoy there and also another dear
colleague whom we lost uh very recently
Arvin
um and for the rest I'm going to hand
over to my colleagues here to fill in
the picture and then I'll come back to
what else I had on my slides so Alan
sure oh you have your own
okay uh first it's uh really nice to be
on this panel with uh people to pick up
on things that uh uh gone up for many
years I renewed my technical discussions
with Peter phal on wine um and uh great
to see George and somebody who says that
he's Jose mura um when we were graduate
student students to together and then
when I was in a thesis committee Jose
had Rastafarian hair if you remember
Rose Ro remember uh Rowan Martin's uh
laugh in he looked like Father Guido
Sarducci who are you U so so uh my
memory of sanjoy goes back to my senior
year as an undergrad here in course 16
uh when i' taken a course on function
optimization from Wally vandery which
included discussion a variety of methods
and I voraciously read things including
a paper on the conjugate gradian method
uh co-author by sanjoy so I think I'm
the only one here who attended his job
talk when he applied uh for the position
um at
MIT uh after uh that the summer that
followed U I had a great job at Bell
labs and my my the people I worked with
there urged me to go talk to Roger
rocket who just moved up to to Harvard
um and I did that and Roger said I
needed to talk to two people at MIT one
of them Yan Williams was on sabatical
the other was Sandro uh and Sandro
became the only member of what was then
the E Department uh on my thesis
committee and I split my time between
hanging out with John Baris and others
in Rogers Group uh and building 35 with
the students of Mike Athens Yan Williams
Lenny Gould and Sandro uh a second thing
about about Sandro being on my committee
uh I wrote a really long thesis
something that I I prayed that none of
my students would inflict on me and this
was at a time where I hand wrote it um
and then would hand it off to to a word
processor that is a technical typist uh
who would uh use things called rubons
now now if you're not familiar with rub
on what rubons are you can ask my wife
who uh was before she launched her um
her career as a children's book uh
illustrator worked as a technical typist
and for some reason loved to do rubons
um uh I should say that um uh uh I can't
say that i' look at this badly but I
know there's at least one person here
and I'm thinking of you love vne who has
more books with my wife's name on The
Spine and
mine sanre scholarship which everybody's
talked about his it was just
extraordinary and as muner talked about
last night I would go in and the
conversations would go everywhere uh I
remember particular uh him pointing out
a couple of papers by Lowden slogger and
helson I was working on estimation on
groups both Lee and finite and uh I
looked at that work up and you think of
X of t for me the group was where X
lived for Lon Slugger and helson T was
the thing where the group lived and that
came back to roost for me when I started
moving into random fields and graphical
models there were two times when I met
with sandj where I have to admit I was
distracted the first time we're sitting
there and sandj was sitting back and
gesticulating about things and all of a
sudden he knows there's a hole in his
shirt why was there a hole in his
shirt I found out a few weeks later when
I was in there and he was smoking a
cigarette just gesticulating with it and
this particular occasion the ashes did
not fall on his shirt they fell on the
ground but sanjoy on occasion would burn
holes into his shirt uh I will say that
Sandro gave me one of the quotes that
I've used most in actually the most
important uh lectures I've given uh it's
by 1960 Nobel laas Peter medir which
really speaks profoundly to the
importance of creativity and really
important research and that was defining
science as the art of the
solvable uh and sanjoy had read meir's
papers which are an astounding thing to
read not as technical papers but as ones
on uh philosophy of
science uh has also been mentioned
sanjoy had Mastery of of a number of
languages is what some of you may not
know is he also translated books uh and
the most famous one that he translated
was JL Leon's book on infinite
dimensional systems uh a real
Masterpiece Leon at this time was the
president of what was then called Ira
they hadn't added yet the N for National
on that uh and uh I remember picking up
an issue of the Siam news which was
distributed and it had an advertisement
for this book by J Leon uh translated by
San Joy mitter talking about the
generalizations of various things
including the generalization of the
celebrated Capital bu
U lowercase k a l m an filter now Sandro
had a pretty good relationship with Rudy
but he received incredible amount of
grief from from Rudy uh on this that's
only one of two occasions in which I
know he came out rather flustered from
dealing with cman the other was uh
Rudyard at some point calman decided the
only way he was going to win the Nobel
Prize was to switch into
economics um um and he came to give a
lecture as it turned out the lecture was
one of of U Reinventing total Le squares
uh but Rudy wanted to the to to attract
economists and the one he wanted to
attract was John Von man's daughter uh
Marina van noyman Witman uh who wasn't
up in the Cambridge area but I believe
she was on sabatical at Harvard and Rudy
insisted sanjoy call her and sanjoy
walked into my office after this with
the looks the only time I've seen a look
on his face that looks somewhat
flustered and dazed cuz Rudy said I want
you to call her up and once you get her
on the phone I'm going to take the phone
away from you and I'm going to sweep her
off her feet verbally and she'll be
dazzled and come to my talk and agree
that I've reinvented economics for for
fortunately fortunately um San only got
an assistant who said that Dr Whitman
was
unavailable food and wine uh in 1975 I
had good taste for California wines but
I frankly I didn't know a whole lot
about French Wines in 75 um my first
doctoral student Steve Marcus and I uh
went to Paris and then we're going to
meet up again with sanjoy at UD for a
really interesting Symposium on
algebraic System Theory and uh sanjoy
told Steve he was going to complete his
education as it was he completed my
education as well he took us to allar a
one-star restaurant in the Latin quarter
and the food was excellent but what blew
me away is my first gron crew burgundy
cloar um and i' I've actually discussed
this with porob several times um uh it
was wonderful wine five years later in
1980 when I had a sabatical in Paris
Susanna and I took my host Michelle
fleece out for dinner at alar and it was
a one-page m mograph menu which just had
a couple
of good but not gr Crew wines listed and
so uh when the waiter come over I said
AVU clar
and he stepped back and he said
FL we and for the rest of the meal he
insisted on calling you miss
presid and he cracked jokes only some of
which I got in my limited French one of
which was telling us that the mineral
water he was serving was us was from an
excellent
vintage thanks sanjoy all right
Athletics something that's not been
talked about with sanjy u in several
stories about this first is in 1978 the
Red Sox uh uh had a crushing loss in the
onegame playoff with the Yankees which
eliminated them and vaulted the Yankees
into the World
Series uh it came in the next day an ran
to sand joy and he said how could they
let Bucky Dent hit a home run to beat
them sanjoy followed the Red
Sox uh but the other the other
uh athletic stories I have to tell I
have to talk about um lid's answer to
Felix uner and Oscar Madison of The Odd
Couple that was sanjy mitter and Yan
Willams uh the first is one where
there's only one other person here who
who participated in this and that was
John uh Roger asked me to organize a
soccer game between the Harvard group
and uh the MIT group I I played on The
Winning Side John didn't
um uh and and the the The Odd Couple was
there and there was sanjoy in his
dazzling white shirt and shorts looking
like he was ready to play for the India
field hockey team and he'd make these
wonderful rushes down the right sideline
with beautiful centering passes at least
one or two of which led to goals and his
form was
perfect secondly Steve Marcus and I when
we were both graduate students played
doubles tennis with sanjy and Yan and
sanre was there in his dazzlingly white
shirt and shorts contrasting
dramatically with his skin tone and his
form on his ground strokes was perfect
in contrast in both of these things for
the for the soccer game Yan spent the
game running around telling people what
to do and directing them and complaining
in the in the tennis match it appeared
that yam was engaged in a form of
performance art best described as
executing a space filling curve while
holding a tennis racket it was quite an
experience with them uh one more Yan and
Sandro story um uh there was one year in
which uh uh Sandro and yam were team
teaching a course on algebraic System
Theory of course I inherited and took on
after that using a very
peculiar book written by Rudy calman
Michael ARB and Peter FAL uh and uh one
day sanjo is giving the lecture and Yan
see Marcus is the one who relay the
story to me he's sitting next to Jan and
as M sort of described you know Sano is
is an extraordinary in some ways as a
teacher he go to the board and he wrote
the word theorem and underl it and put
it a colon typically then he would give
the incredible history intellectual and
conceptual history of how what he was
going to do related to things broadly in
the field really remarkable then he'd
write the theorem
statement uh and then uh he might add
some more comments at that point then
he'd very carefully write the word proof
and underline it then put a colon in
after it and all of this his board
Technic and his
handwriting were perfect it was not
however wearing blindingly white
athletic shirt and shorts um and then
Sano we'd walk over to the far corner of
the board on the bottom put a little
square in and fill it in where the proof
would end and quite frequently after
that all hell would break
loose and he end it with the w the
Whimsical smile sanj could could always
put on saying well this is a research
seminar isn't it now on this occasion in
this course Sandra was lecturing and and
Steve all as SRE is going through all of
this Steve realizes that Yan is writing
furiously with his hand raised and sanoy
finally recognized him Yan said would
you like the counter example to the
theorem before or after you prove
it sanoy chose
after now four um uh professional things
uh not humorous but ones that actually
mean a considerable amount to me uh the
first is the center for intelligent
Control Systems we were talking about
this last night I mean uh sanjoy was the
the the the originator of this idea
brought in people from Harvard and
people from brown people wonderful
Scholars from all ranging from ol Gander
at Brown to Roger Brock at Harvard just
an extraordinary group and it was one
where the vision was lofty what we were
going to do and we were fortunate enough
to have a sponsor who allowed us to
pursue that for a number of years and it
became a magnet for work around the
world uh it provided support for many
many students for many faculty
especially Junior faculty uh and for
wonderful post STS and Sandro deserves
all the credit for
that second was um I was um off at an
Air Force scientific Advisory Board um
Retreat uh at the Beckman Center in UC
Irvine and I received an email for
sanjoy saying there's a mury topic
coming out on sensor networks we should
bid it um and so I joined San sanoy on
this who again in his typical fashion
brought in in this case uh guys from
Princeton uh sanie Carney and Sergio
overdue uh and we won the won the
proposal uh but at the
opening the opening seminar we gave to
our sponsors it was clear that the Army
audience wasn't really interested in San
Joy's lofty
view so sanjoy asked me to take this
over and we never sacrificed that view
but I will tell you every single uh
review meeting we had my presentation at
the start was like a game of Twister
where you have to put your arms and feet
in various places trying to to to
maintain this lofty Vision by showing
but also showing things that the Army
was interested in by the end of the
project our our monitor uh used this as
the Exemplar of what good good M muy
should
be uh the third what occurred in began
in 2007 when um the future existence was
of Lids was under serious threat um and
um I'd always said that I never wanted
to be in charge of a group of people
people like myself or like any of you U
uh and or but the their job fell to me
to be director um at a very troubling
time uh but all of the faculty uh
pitched in incredibly and there were
three individuals who were
extraordinarily important to this muner
dala and John CES for um their
leadership and sanjoy who was mostly
behind the scenes but pushing what Lids
had been and should be going well into
the future um and was an incredible
source of uh of
uh of gratitude for me to have sanjoy
doing that and we did did
okay and look at Lids now it's quite
something finally uh fourth one as some
of you know a number of years ago I was
uh elected to National Academy of
engineering and you're not supposed to
know who it was who nominated you or any
of that process okay but I'm pretty sure
that sanjoy was involved in that and
that's not surp surprising sanjoy
championed all of us again and again and
these are not trivial jobs to do if
you're going to write a nomination or
even if you're just going to write a
letter for promotion if you're going to
do it right fair amount of work and the
fact that he did this time and again for
all of us uh speaks volumes about this
wonderful man a valued colleague and a
very dear friend thank
[Applause]
you could you put up uh Peter's
presentation
Peter can you see your slides there this
is the arrow for advancing the upper
okay well
I'm you need did you not want to
go well okay should I turn the chair
around for you or is that helpful
that's uh well from the Where's your
microphone okay well I I I I'm not used
to uh these kind of electronic
devices and so forth the slides were
actually uh taken from old pictures and
they were done by one of Mo's Stu Mowin
students or Mo so I have to thank them
and hopefully I'll be able to advance
them and so forth
uh I'm going to go sort of from the
sublime to the mundane
uh sandre was a friend of mine a little
closer to your mouth just okay thank you
George uh sandre was a very dear friend
of mine and
actually almost a family
member so I have what in the old days
would be home movies excepted
slides all right this picture all right
now there's one of the things we used to
do do with him there were many
thanksgivings Christmas birthdays is go
to the head of the Charles which is a
regata for some of you who don't know
that's in October very close to his
birthday uh and there's a friend of
ours uh with sand Joy enjoying a liation
some of you may recognize Carl
Asam uh one of the things sanjy did when
uh
he took over the
directorship was have what I'd call a
board of directors it
included uh Carl Asam George
zames uh
Irwin
Jacobs and uh Gunter Stein and Jean
Wong and contrary to some he would
actually listen to their advice
uh okay now there's Uncle
sanjoy uh in a pose I don't know that
many of you would see him with one of my
daughters he's undoubtedly explaining
some abstruse
Theory wanting to get her started uh
early uh that is his 50th birthday and
you can see somebody's stealing the
cake uh but we had many such
parties uh
and I
will on there he is again with my
daughters uh and his wife uh
Adriana uh and they referred to him
always as Uncle s joy and herzan Adriana
and they were really a part of our
family and I think it's
important uh you know in the pains and
praise uh of his
Brilliance and so forth uh to see him as
a very uh committed human
being uh and he was a wonderful
friend
uh uh that is a Thanksgiving
uh which I will come back to they
spent oh
probably 30 thanksgivings with
us uh there is the
same uh the older man is actually my
wife's father and
mother
he got along with
everyone uh in
fact in all the years I've known him I
never knew him to lose his temper now
I'm sure he did at some point but but
never uh in my
presence there's another head of the
Charles uh which if you are around at
the time is something very worthwhile to
go to uh Adriana would bring down some
things Sandra would bring a wine and we
would bring various stuff
now all right this is a
Christmas and this is a Chinese
gentleman Yang Yang we acted my wife and
I as host family to students at
Harvard he was a George Mason fellow he
was about 40 at the time at the Kennedy
School he was a deputy Minister for
development uh he had been a translator
for dong shiao
ping his English was far better than
mine no and
well if you're a translator for the
head uh of the Chinese government you
better not make a
mistake now the reason I have this slide
aside from uh CH Sandro and US keeping
uh Pace with
him uh is
that towards the end of his Fellowship
his wife had come over she was a surgeon
and the daughter of a real General
somebody who had been in the Long March
but was a general not a political
General and at about the time he was to
return to China tenanan Square took
place and he decided that it would be
better to stay here for a while
uh and I had offered him a job uh in a
company I was connected
with which he graciously
refused uh his wife worked as a waitress
in a Chinese restaurant till the coast
was clear but the point I want to make
is that Sandra and I lived Our Lives as
many of you have in a period of freedom
and prosperity
and these are pretty fragile
things and uh sanjy knew
it uh this is a another
Christmas uh showing that that he really
participated as a family member
now on the
right uh this was on the
cape is
uh a great friend of sandice and mine a
member of the so-called Club of 34 this
was a group of people born in 1934 who
were active in the
field uh that's George
zames uh who died
prematurely uh when George was in his
final illness sanjy suggested
that we fly up to
Montreal to see George in the hospital
we
did
and
George he could understand us but he he
couldn't communicate he had brain tumor
I mean sort of out of nowhere he said a
prime
number and it was very sad
and I was flying back on the plane and I
was very sad depressed and
suddenly an image of George because he
and his family would spend the week on
the cape at a uh motel by the Sea an
image of George leaping out of the
surf with a big smile on his face and I
see the picture still in my mind's eye
and that's the way I choose to remember
George and I will at the end tell you
how I choose to remember sand
Joy uh this is another
Christmas uh he and Adriana brought many
presents to our
children uh they would often bring uh
Indian and Italian
dolls so the girls have quite a
collection of them uh here uh Allan
mentioned his athletic prowess by the
way uh he was a superb pingpong player I
don't think he had the dazzling white
shirt at that time but there he is at a
Harvard football game uh with us at one
time my wife and I had uh seasoned
tickets now now har he is with her
daughter uh encouraging her to some
reading I I assume it was
probably uh a novel by his friend van
rori who was a Romanian novelist who
lived in
Italy uh in fact he he has a a picture
which is of an
rori uh and uh he encouraged me to read
him there we are at another Christmas
dinner now the point of this you will
see a salad bowl in there and I've
called this uh maybe it's in the next
slide no that's Halloween I I don't know
how to go back so anyway
but uh some reading okay the thank you
that we call Adriana's salad now sanjy
of course would bring some fine wine
either a Brunello once in a while a
Baro and
occasionally a special
graa sasaya graa but Adriana would
always bring this salad
now it contained Italian greens real
pruto provolone peino but especially
fresh figs
it was known for the special fresh
figs that's
Halloween Sandro again as you can see
really a true Uncle this is at a
conference uh and of course you all know
that there was hardly an important
conference that he didn't attend frankly
I don't know who the fellow in the
middle is if somebody does tell them
now here again is my daughter a bit
older with Carl
Asam and sand
joy and
finally this is a family
picture at my younger daughter's wedding
on Martha's
Vineyard and you can see
prominently is uncle sand
Joy now the way I remember
him is not as a brilliant scholar not as
somebody that on these dinners we would
discuss oh a vast array of topics
economics uh
history Italian politics Indian
politics a whole range of subjects we
did not discuss technical matters
because there were ladies
present
so but
anyway at the end of an excellent dinner
fine wine we'd have a little after
dinner drink and a small glass a cognac
an
armanac once in a while a special graer
and you know the glass would be empty
we' said would you like a little more
sandre and he was just a
drop with that
gesture and he would finish it and then
oh after about 15 20 minutes say time to
make a
move
and you know after a wonderful dinner
great
conversation there's a kind of
contentment and sand I had an expression
of
contentment and that's the way I'll
choose to remember him just a
drop time to make a
[Applause]
move well
thank you Ali and Pablo for organizing
this tribute to S Joy thank you George
for having me in your
panel of course uh I've known s Joy I
think for all my life and if it's not
all my life is close to it and um s Joy
was of course my
professor was a mentor was a
colleague and was a friend friend of me
a friend of my family a friend of
Manuela my
wife and of my kids Barbara Andre and
Pedro we all had lots of times with sjy
and Adriana and uh lately with
Rea so my first class with uh s Joy was
Advanced topics in linear
system and
um it was not
like Ellen explained that he would write
the theorum and the proof he wouldn't
even D to do that it was all reading
papers and uh not even reading papers
because he would invite the authors to
come and present the work and the poor
authors would come and these were the
people that now maybe Peter also showed
up once that like 50 years later we know
oh these are the gods of systems and
linear systems but these poor people
would come to present their paper they
couldn't go beyond the title because
once they start talking sjy would
interrupt and start with the big
questions and uh and that was it uh
there was no more talk there was nothing
else and it was just a discussion of why
didn't they do this rather than doing
what they had done so so that was my
first uh uh course with sjy and I had to
write the paper and uh I picked or and
joy picked for me papers on what's
called then geometric control by Steve
Morris and uh one them they had written
some beautiful papers and uh I had to
learn all that then and joy maybe a few
few months or a year later was on my
area exam I don't know if MIT still has
an area exam but at the time you'd need
to pick papers and then write and I
picked papers on the stochastic
realization which was a topic emerging
at the time and one of the papers was by
winner and mazani um on linear
prediction and uh I was trying to read
it again coming here and I must tell you
I couldn't understand anything and I
don't know how I wrote and had s jooy
then uh quiz me for one hour or so and
the last course was um a course that
Professor Timothy Johnson was giving on
distributed control for systems uh
described by partial differential
equations and again this was typical s
Joy so Tim was the professor in charge
but because the topic was so relevant
alen and all the faculty at leads were
were like with the student sitting in
the audience now guess what Timothy
would start and
immediately one of them maybe alen or S
Joy or or Yan Williams would
start uh saying whatever else and again
Timothy would kind of sit down relax and
let them give the lecture which of
course was no lecture and we students
would stand there and and try to pick up
the balls as they flew from one side to
the other but even before I met s joy in
the classroom I had already heard a lot
about sanjoy I had a um an office mate a
Brazilian uh he spoke uh Portuguese with
me I spoke Brazilian with him at least
by the time he finished so J paer paer
kept talking about this guy this new
faculty member that came and was giving
these courses on
optimization now optimization today is
our bread and butter okay but this is
the early' 70s and Sunjoy somehow
brought to uh m a course that you can
see his foresight that became really the
tools of um bread and butter that we use
today but this is back back then and uh
of course convex optimization and all
such
things
so this kind of illustrate s joy as a
professor to me and at the time so after
I completed my thesis in 1975 I became a
professor at the University in Portugal
and experiencing exciting times because
the dictatorship of 48 dictatorship had
fallen in 197 24 in December 1980 at the
systems analysis and optimization
conference at inria in Ro and C France
so inria was Ira I Chang the name by Lou
Leon that uh Ellen mentioned so I met s
Joy again so this is 1980 We Set Side by
Side during a sightseeing tour from
Versa to parie and my life was about to
change we were were both interested in
nonlinear filtering sojoy from a
continuous time fundamental perspective
and I from a discrete time design
problem solving
angle during that bus ride sanj invited
me to a meeting on nonlinear filtering
in tulus this is now March
1981 I actually know the dates 12 and 13
March 19 81 he was organizing this
conference at the laborat
the system called L and that last s Joy
asked me to give a talk at leads which I
did in
1983 but when I wrote this I forgot but
now I remember that in between um I
organized the meeting um um one of those
NATO Advanced study institutes that
there were at the time two we meeting in
algarin Portugal with dick buy sanjy was
a a speaker there and of course s joy
and Adriana showed up and they showed up
with a Cy of Italian friends and those
Italian friends in those two weeks we
all became friends for life although we
never met again but it was very
intensive very uh Sunjoy like at at the
end of the day we all would go to the
beach and S Joy would entertain with
lots of stories andriana and
Italians and by talking about Italians
Bruno is here and so he must know what
I'm talking
about okay so I did give that talk in
leads in
1983 and then sjy invited me to come on
sabatico um which we did Manuel and I
came and this is 1984 to
1986 and during those two years we had
countless discussions on the theoretical
underpinnings of nonlinear stochastic
filtering System Theory identification
inference and learning and the way it
was was like this I would spend the
whole day immersed on two or three books
highly theoretical books that I was
trying to study okay and then sjy would
come early in the morning and then would
come at the end of the day and during
lunch and during lunch we would always
grab a sandwich and if Peter was around
we would go with Peter to some joint
nearby Building 35 on MF there were few
there and would bring and it it there
and of course I spent the whole day
trying to do the proofs and trying to
understand and so forth and that the end
s Joy would come and put everything back
in place and I would understand what I
spent eight hours trying to understand
after my sabatical I joined CMU in
1986 but now things change completely
because our relation with sjy now uh
enlarged to
Manuel and um and Manuela was of course
doing her PhD and finished and became a
professor in Ai and Robotics and S Joy
had this fascination with AI okay and I
think that in over
those H 30 or 40 years that followed we
uh we kept coming to Cambridge just to
to be with sanjo and Adriana and Adrian
and I would sit back because Manuel and
sanjy would spend the evening or the
dinner or the lunch just talking about a
and Adrian and I would try to
participate a little bit here and there
but of course it was not for
us I even um one story uh I suggested
once uh uh to my department or college
that they invite s sjy to be part of a
visiting Committee of the department so
sjy came and uh of course uh he had the
big ideas about education and all that
and uh and then at the end they reported
to the president Cherry Cohen who
unfortunately passed away sadly very
recently so Jerry Jerry Cohen the
president and S Joy immediately
connected because the moment Jerry saw
sjy coming in he recognized his
Professor from optimization when Jerry
was a student here at at MIT so he was
he kept telling me over and over oh it
was so great meeting the professor and
the optimization that made my life and
so forth in my numerous
interactions um I think I referred to
this
already but but by then as I mentioned
uh the group had enlarged so Adriana
manueles and joy myself we became from
Professor and Mentor we became family
friends and uh we kept coming as I
mentioned uh to um to to Cambridge just
to be with sjy so in preparing for this
event um when sanjy passed away I spent
a couple of days just going on the web
and looking at the YouTube videos of of
sanjy um but uh I did the same again
this time and um I looked at a lecture
two 20124 lecture at the Tata Institute
and that's an a quintessential s joy and
this is goes along what Alan uh said but
with a few twists in just 50 minutes
with 10 minutes to spare so it's 60 but
he only covered 50 minutes he
masterfully presented his variational
approach to filtering on a green wall
to--all chalkboard so you have to see
the the this this lecture so it's a a
huge green CH green board and he picks
up the chalk piece walks to and and he's
going to give a lecture about this
variational approach to filtering okay
which combines stochastic process
nonlinear Fields random Fields uh
quantum physics mechanic quantum
mechanics thetis all these topics to
this 20 or 30 students sitting in front
of him okay and
uh any one of us trying to do that would
feel am going to be able to do this it's
going to be a fiasco because no student
will understand anything of what I'm
going to say he walks into the the board
and as as Ellen says oh divides the
board into with vertical lines into
pieces okay and uh I don't know I
sometimes I try to do that and I can't
constrain myself between those vertical
I start going to the next one so I erase
the line and then I go to the next next
one but he
did kept it and then he start writing
with a
beautiful meticulous and beautiful
calligraphy he fills the board not too
densely with a comprehensive Panorama of
filtering starting with Bas law and the
search for the conditional distribution
he then transitioned to Gibbs
distributions the harmlessly Clifford
theorum and connected this Con Concepts
to Marco renom Fields sjy reformulated
Gibbs with the hamiltonian introduced
free energy and L linked it to
differential entropy in a magical moment
he reveals that the conditional
distribution which is the solution to
the nonl to the nonlinear filtering
problem is the minimizer of the free
energy so I gave you these words and I'm
sure that not everybody followed them
but this is what he did to these 20 or
30 students at the Tata Institute
and throughout he never hearded welcomed
interruptions and encouraged student
engagement with time to spare he
provided a broad view of the significant
questions worth pursuing even suggesting
in the middle of his talk suggests oh
and by the way you should revisit the
book Gibbs measure and face transitions
by some author some distinguished author
and you should reformulate the book in
terms of conditional probabilities okay
this is a program he proposed to these
students and it's a very deep very deep
actually I also revisit his brief
comments at leads at
80 and uh many of you I'm sure were
there I unfortunately I couldn't be
there he masterfully reminded us of what
he called The System Theory revolution
of the 50s and 60s
that he attributes to several people
including Colman of course who brought
the new language of algebra differential
equations and stochastic process to
engineering problems so he point his
point was okay there was a revolution
but the
revolution scientific revolution in the
50s and 60s but the revolution had to do
also with the language the new tools
that you brought and he then challenges
the audience and the leads people there
and uh all of us to look at
problems in a fundamental way to develop
a revolutionary new paradigm with an
appropriate language so he says we are
missing the language of the next
Revolution sanjy couldn't resist
challenging us to think big and think
fundamentally we visited sjy and Adrian
in cambrid several times a year and
returned for another sabatical in 2006
our tradition of having dinner on the
Friday after Thanksgiving because you
heard that Thanksgiving he was taken by
Peter so we were left with the day after
okay we were and uh that lasted for
several years we frequently continue
through the years to meet now often with
Rea at the alers cafe for a burger or at
legal seafood at the Charles hotel and
after they both Clos to have lunch at
the Harvest also in Harvard Square
continuing our conversations until
almost the very end in June
2023 our last visit with s Joy was on
March 2023 Manuel had do some work in in
London and uh I accompanied so that we
could go and visit S
Joy the record in
London so we all deeply miss uh the many
conversations with enjoy that profoundly
uh shaped our thinking I cherish how he
always pushed me in particular to ask
the fundamental questions to view
problems view problems from an abstract
Global Perspective and to use the most
appropriate mathematics and insights to
find the simplest yet most profound and
comprehensive Solutions s Joy was uh of
course a professor was uh a a mentor was
a league was a friend was a thinker was
a gentleman
and that's uh how I uh I choose to
remember him thank
you I think we're cutting well into
other people's time but we'll we'll
continue and we'll make it uh shorter uh
these memories are too precious to cut
off or cut short so
Maxim I'll get
you you have that
right okay so um right I think the first
paper uh by
sanjoy um that I that really profoundly
affected profoundly affected me before I
I I got to meet sanjoy was uh the paper
his brother mentioned on variational
approach to nonlinear estimation I think
that was about 2008 that's when I was
kind of you know soul searching I uh did
my PhD in mathematical physics and I was
switching to uh information Theory
control and machine learning and this
was a paper that really kind of put a
few things uh together for me and my
Fred Todd Coleman um who was at
University of Illinois I I was a post do
at the time he was faculty he said oh
yeah you know I took courses with sanjoy
mitter he's an amazing scholar and the
uh overall aidite and just just really
knowledgeable about everything and my
adviser Horus Yuan who did his PhD uh at
MIT with Bob Kennedy said he had
countless conversations with sanjoy
during his days um so that that paper
really uh kind of said the standard for
me intellectually and uh and even
philosophically and it turned out that
um after I uh first met sany in 2013 I
think when I came to give a talk at Lids
on some work I had done at the
intersection of uh ideas in economics
and rate Distortion Theory and then we
had a conversation with San joy and it
turned out that our common interest
really really was philosophy and uh so
so this uh this is just a few samples of
I think the kind of deep philosophical
ideas sanoy put together uh he
articulated what it means to be an
engineer that it's not uh just a
utilitarian you know always thinking in
terms of costs and benefits it's it's a
world viiew that uh is really aimed at
creating and maintaining systems that
that serve uh that serve purposes for uh
for improvement of of lives and uh uh
infrastructure systems that that's
surround us so I'm I'm just going to
give you a few examples so this is
1979 um he had this paper called the the
analogies uh between certain models and
quantum mechanics nonlinear filtering
and so I you know I I kind of chose a
few quotes from pH philosophy of science
here's a a book by uh Mary Hessa who was
a philosopher of Science in the UK in
1966 on the role of analogy in metaphor
and science the idea is that not science
does not just proceed deductively there
there's a role for for metaphors that
help you link one thing to another and
and thus lead to better explanations and
and result in growth of ideas and that's
exactly what you see in the opening
paragraphs of of of sanj's paper on on
quantum mechanics nonlinear
filtering and by the way this paper also
has a um precursor to some ideas that
are now becoming fashionable have become
fashionable and context of probabilistic
generative models based on diffusions a
lot of the roots of this are really in
sano's work and here he also makes a
distinction between uh problems in
physics where there's a language that
that's uh uh important in physics but
but also problems in engineering where
one distinguishing factor is this idea
that you you're trying to make
inferences based on noisy observations
which he correctly says is absent in
physics and the reason why that's absent
in physics is that physics
is concerned with discovery of laws that
are stable and will continue to be
stable um throughout time whereas
engineering is really about synthesis of
new systems and this is uh this is a
memo he wrote 1985 uh some thoughts on
engineering education that really puts
this puts this forward very very
forcefully and the idea is that um
Engineers should embrace the role of
creators of of new AR facts new laws
that are based on interaction between
systems in their environments and that
would include not only devices but also
uh the human element and he reiterated
this uh so these you know these are all
just just the kind of things that Sano
would and I would discuss over email um
and in fact just I think just a few
weeks before he passed away we're
exchanging some emails about uh
philosophy of biology that was kind of
uh an interesting U thing as well you
know because that's also connected to AI
so here are some ideas on conceptual
foundations of computer and system
Sciences again really emphasizing the
fact that um creation of new systems
understanding of of the role of function
and purpose which sort of was was was
gone from uh 18th century um Newtonian
physics uh is really it really
profoundly present in in the context of
Engineering Systems and sanjoy really
took the time
to uh provide expository notes about
this that that I think deserves further
um further study and reflection uh and
going through the years this is
1994 this is an amazing monograph 150
pages that he co-wrote with Bernard Gau
and Charles Rockland that really
outlines more or less uh the way that we
think
about large scale neural networks but
viewed from the point of
um seeing seeing where the limitations
of limitations of formal modeling come
up against the complexity of these
systems so I really Rec I I recommend
this to anyone um who will listen
because because it was really extremely
forward-looking
um document so the main thing that
really really struck me here is that uh
the you know this humility in the role
of mathematics that we think that
mathematizing the world is the way to is
the way to uh uh to understand it but
here sanjo and his co-authors are really
really emphasizing the point that uh
certain systems for example those that
have Arisen through biological evolution
not necessar are not necessarily
formalizable mathematically and the role
of the role of Engineers is not to write
down more equations it is to suggest
principes Les uh that underly certain
complex architectures and see how these
principles are common in a variety of
settings again this if if if uh uh I
hope that this uh I'm pretty sure that
at this point in Google Scholar this
paper has one citation it's by
me would always email this oh nice
um this is 1997 I think this is the talk
he gave at the Norbert weiner Symposium
here he you know really uh has a unique
take on the problems of uh learning uh
that I think he was becoming interested
in this in the context of U Ai and in
multi-layered complex architectures and
when he says that he wants to take an
internalist perspective where various
internal templates that that that kind
of characterize different different
invariants and different features in the
system system uh are the main ingredient
and and data are just used as uh as the
link to the empirical reality I I I
think that he actually borrowed this
idea from no chsky who had this
internalist perspective on language what
what is inside speakers heads their
internal States um and then this is the
last uh document that that I'll mention
this is a this is a um a paper he
presented on a at a symposium on on uh
economics and and social systems on
system Effectiveness and this one is
remarkable because after the paper
itself there's a transcript of a
discussion San Joy had with economists
and sociologists where you know he
really held his own he he knew his
literature you know where else could you
see references to Yan williams'
behavioral approach to control uh but
also uh um books by um shenberg on you
know composition in in in modernist
music and Alfred North Whitehead who was
you know co-author with Russell of pipan
Mathematica but whad actually had uh his
own philosophy which was in many in many
ways kind of connected to Buddhism it's
to see the world as a network of
interlocking processes as opposed to as
opposed to as opposed to things and this
is the way of thinking about complex
systems that Sanu really brought to the
four so here the idea is that we build
all these systems such as the internet
that are so complex that we will never
be able to really make uh detailed
statements about what each packet and
the internet is doing what each link is
doing and yet as a whole this system is
called coherent and effective and the
reason why that happens is because it's
connected to an environment that
includes users includes the you know
shifting shifting demands shifting
realities and these systems we as
Engineers are responsible for
maintaining designing and and really uh
exercising responsibility as not just
Engineers but also as humanists and this
like I said this this is this is the
part of Sanu that I'll I'll miss the
most is
conversations that go beyond just just
technical papers so thank you sanjoy
very much for for the
inspiration we've gone well over the
time we had in the program I'm just
going to wrap up if you could put uh
George's slides back up um with a few
pictures and I'll go through them
quickly
okay so I'm just picking up where I left
off but there's a big gap because I
really started to interact with sanjoy
more closely in his later years this is
a a picture with Tom kyot this is from
some time ago uh it's a picture I'm very
fond of uh and Tom Kyo actually sent in
a message for this conference but I'm
not going to read it now although I have
it all here we'll have it read at the
afternoon session he does point to the
same paper on testing the manifold
hypothesis um that was mentioned by
pronob San joo's rather um I I
highlighted uh the something that has
come through in everything people have
said that he never seemed to be in a
hurry about anything and um that's
really the the picture we have okay
we'll we'll get through this uh later
but I I wanted to show you some pictures
this is uh in London you see Tom kyot
there you also see Martin Clark uh
sanjoy you see um David Maine and some
of you may know um ARA M as well who I
think was is related to sanjoy and then
Reika his wife uh who's based in London
and so they had to have this back and
forth visiting each other either in
London or Cambridge over the
years
um this is a picture this may be from
wedding of the FES perhaps because I've
never seen sanjo in a tux till I saw the
picture that um Peter put up but anyway
I wish it was in sharper Focus but I
thought he looked very elegant and I
pulled that out this is sanjoy
expounding at a dinner in his room uh
that hand gesture is something that was
kind of unique to sanjoy I haven't seen
anyone else hold his hand quite like
that uh and he's talking about something
always the glass of wine nearby
um this is sanjo with raika on one of
her um visits extended visits to um
Cambridge this is an dear friend Tuli
Banner's
home um and uh this is on one of PR's
visits he pronob talked about uh the
coffee table with all the books and it
was it's fascinating if you zo zoom in
there to see all the different titles
and indeed it's the bhat Gita but
there's poetry there's Dylan
Thomas uh and uh
a whole range of things and of course
pouring wine to
entertain August 2022 and then in h
September I had the uh pleasure of a a
lunch at tuscanos in Harvard Square One
of sanj's favorite restaurants uh with
pronob and then this is the two elegant
gentlemen walking we walked all the way
back to uh his apartment so you can see
where the prince of Florence uh
description comes from very elegant
there this is sanjo back in uh England
um I think before his last trip uh out
to
Cambridge uh this is him enjoying a
drink uh in his garden just a couple of
weeks uh before his passing and um you
know right to the end uh enjoying the
conversation enjoying being
outside and couple of weeks later he
passed away I think apart from his
caregivers
I may have been the last one to see him
of of this crowd he had a big support
system here in Cambridge that included
his dear nie aneli duva mitter uh friend
Tuli banagi whom I mentioned uh there
were folks from MIT menen and snow and
uh Rachel and um uh the fs and I'm sure
I'm not listing everybody there but
um people
looked on him looked in on him and he
actually apart from the health issues I
think had a very um happy time here
thank you so I should
break so as you know we're running a bit
late we'll take a 20 minute break and
then we'll come back 11:55 or sorry
1055 it's always good to see you
you thank you thank you for all those
great stories that was wonderful
thank you thank you very much no no no
no wonderful ially agree we cannot just
like good next time you have to
[Music]
is
in
[Music]
oh
[Applause]
[Music]
is
[Applause]
[Music]
is for
is
[Music]
in
[Applause]
[Music]
for
is
[Music]
ch
check what
[Music]
yes am I
here and
I've seen you on
many did you come from India nice thank
you okay um good morning everyone uh
we're going to start the next session
we're running a little bit behind
schedule but we had a wonderful uh uh
set of uh remembrances and memories in
the morning so we're going to continue
uh with our next panel uh uh about sanjo
as a gentleman and lifelong scholar
we're going to hear testimonials from uh
colleagues um and I'm going to get uh uh
moner to have us uh start the session
hopefully monzer can also moderate
session as well thank you so
much thank you ali uh good morning
everyone um I had my day in court
yesterday and I gave you my uh my briefs
about sanjoy so I'm not going to bore
you today in fact I'm to try to make up
some of the time because of that uh um
so I think it's recorded so you can you
can hear it there's one thing that I
wanted to mention that I didn't talk a
lot you know quite a bit about it
yesterday in the banquet and that is
sort of the the vision that sanjoy had
and how he helped in realizing and
building institutions at MIT I do want
to just say a few words about sort of
the creation of idss and the role that
sanjo played in that um you know so in
2013 when we started deliberating around
the idea of how do we uh be prepared to
address the the the growing world of
artificial intelligence data science and
so forth sanjo sort of brought in the
his perspective about how you know the
system Theory thinking and statistical
thinking can actually help in the in the
growing sort of data that is coming
essentially from people coming from not
just from machine not things that we
know the physics of or the biology and
the fact um statistics has actually gone
uh through a a revolution you know in
terms of high dimensional statistics and
thinking about networks and interactions
and so forth that in fact that has to be
at the core of what we're doing if we
are going to bring solutions to societal
challenges so the first piece and is
that whatever idss did it had to bring
statistics right at the core of what
what it's doing and bring a a sort of a
home for statistics at MIT and for those
of you who didn't know you know MIT has
attempted to build a department of
statistics for almost 50 years before
that and has never happened and so San
Joo was actually adant about the fact
that in fact this is the opportunity to
build something doesn't have to be a
department but a place to convene and
think about statistics the second piece
as we started thinking about sort of
societal challenges the big problems and
we sort of
um you know arrived and I'll tell you
you know not in the same sequence of
things but we arrived to this idea that
I often call the triangle sort of the
the the a triangle that guided the idss
and that is every almost every societal
problem you can think of it as the
interaction of three important
components uh the
physical um aspect of a system the
social interaction with that particular
system and then the institutional part
that regulate that that particular
interaction almost every complex problem
has those components and data is often
available about all of these components
but the data that is available at these
components isn't always sort of
connected and timestamped it's very
different from each other and so forth
so the vision that always Sano has
talked about is that you don't just slap
these things together and think that you
have a model to solve a problem you have
to think about abstraction and sanjo
used the word abstraction very often
you know you take this complex
description and you abstract or you
distill from it a piece a problem that
you are able to to tackle that you can
solve the formulation of the problem
matters and then the data can help you
sort of address and solve these problems
I would say that you know I talked
yesterday about sort of the kind of the
impact that sanj talked about human
interaction and human connections and
having the right people in place but
also the importance of the topics and
the Notions of abstractions were also a
big piece of the advice that he
continuously gave in the in the creation
of idss so I'm not going to bore you
anymore I want to say and I want to give
the the floor to our panel we have and I
don't know the order I think we have
John CIS who is on Zoom that's going to
appear shortly um we have V borar uh
John Baris Maria illich and U mimo
Francis so uh I don't know the order um
is John coming
next okay they just fixed it okay so
John you're
on all right well I'm really sorry that
I was not able to attend in person I had
planned a long time ago to be in a
different continent but I definitely
wanted to take the opportunity to share
Impressions and feelings about sanjoy he
was a truly remarkable person a dear
Mentor colleague and
friend so I first met San Joy when I was
beginning as a graduate student in LS
that was in the early 80s so around that
time sanjoy was very interested in
nonlinear filtering I guess that stayed
for a long time and he had written uh
just a little before and import paper on
the famous Innovations conjecture and so
I remember our first real scientific
interaction we were both taking a flight
to a CDC across the country we were on
the same flight so while we were
boarding sanjoy goes oh by the way there
is this open problem in nonlinear
filtering okay so I was hoping that I
would be sleeping on the flight but San
Joy had this great way of nudging you
and pointing to something interesting
and to get you thinking so actually I
was not a student of sanjoy he was not
even in my thesis committee I didn't
work with him in my student or Junior
years I did not attend any of his
classes so we at those Early times we
didn't have any formal
intersection however he was everywhere
his presence
was
ubiquitous so he was a constant presence
in my life somehow despite the fact that
we didn't have the formal interactions
that's because he was passionate about
all kinds of intellectual matters a
source of inspiration all the time he
had a very distinct and unique
intellectual style he would always try
to make connections between viewpoints
and Fields people have already commented
that but uh his favorite was clearly to
make links between mathematical physics
and control theory uh so I think that
was a recurring recurring theme and so
he would nudge people to look at those
connections and look for deep and
fundamental
connections uh even if he wouldn't get
into the technicalities himself he had
this vision of research programs that
people uh should follow and how to look
into the deep aspects and the essence
and also as an informal advice
he was most famous for whenever you
would talk to him about something he
would dig out from his folders some
obscure paper that could actually be
relevant but which no one might have
seen and all that so you would always go
okay do you know about this paper and
find some photocopy some her deep in his
folders okay but the interaction with
sanjoy was not just in the direction
from Professor to the students in the
disciples it was not one way he was at
the same time getting input or feedback
he was a very keen Observer of
everything that would be going on so let
me share this picture of
his uh so you can see San Joy here he's
observing he thinking there's a glimpse
of a friendly smile but also a sense
that he's inspecting something and you
also get a hint that there are many
parallel processes going on in his brain
so in his mode as Inspector now back to
leads and MIT I think many many of us
have experienced what ASU also mentioned
in the morning San jooy roaming the
corridors finding an open door or
catching you
uh uh let's see
okay I'm getting a message that the
picture is not properly
shared uh my zoom says that it
is supposedly shared okay
um is it
visible
no let me do stop share and share again
you are screen sharing participants can
see it
okay is it there
no
h okay let me try once more or I can
send it to send the file to someone
and H
it's
on okay good let me continue then so
sanjo with this observant look he would
either grab you in the corridor or find
an open door and come in and ask so
what's going on what's new what's
important so I think a good way of
keeping his legacy alive is whenever
we're working on something and want to
crystallize it to something basic and uh
find a way to describe it in a short
succinct way just think how would you
answer s Joy if he were to suddenly show
up and and ask you so what's up how do
you summarize it in few words so of
course as people keep mentioning San Joy
was about the big picture he was a true
scholar I try to look at said in the big
picture and that did really pay off for
lots of us and the community and for
lads I mean he would always encourage to
explore new directions and provide
leadership and famously he launched the
center for intelligent control it
involved leads it involved also Harvard
Brown and people from seale and was
trying to develop a coherent but broader
vision of the field of systems and
control so the center was ahead of the
of the times in many ways uh it was
formative for many people it did play a
huge role in my career here uh the
presence of that Center and I think for
many others as well and for the
community overall but now going Beyond
math and science uh sanjoy was basically
a citizen across multiple scales so a
citizen of the University a citizen of
our intellectual community and the
citizen of the world so the university
scale he had strong uh with a healthy
classical dose of academic values clear
sense of what's worth doing and a clear
distaste for noisy diversion and he was
not afraid to tell things like they were
uh sometimes with a dry British style
humor or with a sharp philosophical
quotation uh somebody already mentioned
a quotation from San Joy I do remember
another one that he made uh while there
were some sort of political type
discussions around the department and
some people feeling that they were on
the upswing and San Joy said well there
is a tide in the Affairs of men meaning
that one should remain humble and
grounded and not to feel too a bullant
if things seem to go one way or
another so if we think of San Joy a
little more holistically basically was a
wonderful person a well-rounded human
being or people already mentioned about
his bread I still remember him that he
would always recommend a new book to
read on sociology politics history
philosophy he was a true
humanist uh yes I would I I guess I
share in common Peter fal's uh
experience that I've also SJ recommended
for rori and read his novel and actually
this week
maybe because of the feelings around
this event I took another history book
that sanjoy had recommended a few years
back so having those conversations wond
starting little lightly on the academics
but then going into World politics and
philosophy and all that that was an
amazing experience so time with San jooy
was always a very rich
experience and sanjoy was a citizen of
the world
Cosmopolitan as Cosmopolitan as anyone
could be what does that mean okay uh
since sanjoy liked physic physical
analogies so sanjoy had plenty of very
definite intellectual momentum and so
the uncertainly principle means that his
position would be impossible to pinned
down with Precision so he was everywhere
his life crisscrossed the world
uh having life in India in Italy in
England
everywhere and on the Cosmopolitan side
also way before recommendation systems
were
invented uh sanjoy was there for any
major city in the world he would be the
one to recommend special hotels and
restaurants not the fancy ones but the
hidden gems with style and class so he
had class in a sort of oldw world
fashion in a fashion that's maybe
disappearing these days he had this
sharp observant eye but also enigmatic
sometimes as is captured in this picture
that I
posted so uh my wife and I spent a lot
of time with s joy and with Adriana back
then uh they
really enjoyed our kids as well when
they were present we had a wonderful
time with San jooy in many parts of the
world with lots and lots of fond
memories he was a very gracious horse
showing us around Florence and of course
knowing anything everything about that
City that we should know about we did
stroll with him through London he
visited Us in Greece and speaking about
the visit of Greece people talked about
lots of activities of San Joy from
Sports to intellectuals and all that
nobody mentions dancing so while in
Greece we even got if I can get the next
page uh okay we managed to get some joy
into a Greek line
dance uh would be person who would
immerse in everything maybe sometimes
keeping in the depth of his mind some
distance and still observing but he was
open to any kind of experience in any
kind of culture and situation he was
full of life his advice his values were
Priceless had a huge impact to me so I
feel that it was a big honor big
pleasure that we crossed paths I'm I'm
honored that I can think that uh we
became
friends I always I will always remember
him as he trolls Beyond this world uh
will
remember uh fondly with lots of love as
he's moving on thank
[Applause]
you okay next speaker we have um ve
I just made a few jottings mainly from
my personal experience which are kind of
instantiations of a lot that has already
been said so we know that he took a lot
of interest in his students
collaborators and so on and not only
academically but also helped them with
their careers and sometimes in personal
problems as well but he sometimes helped
people whom he did not really know well
also that includes me
the first time I met him was in Holland
and I my plan when I finished my PhD I
was decided to go back to India I wanted
to spend a year in Europe and then head
back and there was a position in tent
which had been advertised I applied for
that got it and ended up in Holland and
in the meantime lot of my friends and
seniors and including my
adviser they kept sort of
trying to convince me that it was not a
wise move to just pack up and go back to
India like that so I was a bit jittery
and I sent a few feelers to couple of
places in India and the responses were
also not encouraging and then I met
sanjoy so I introduced myself and he say
yes PR has told me about you I heard you
are going back to India so he said yes
very good so he says this first time
somebody is actually encouraging me to
do that and then he said do you know
that Tata in of fundamental resarch is
starting a new center in Applied
Mathematics why don't you apply there so
I didn't know about that so I said okay
I'll
apply please do and I'll write write a
letter for you and that was it I just
after so much stress I just walked into
a job without having to do much just one
letter from him did it that was one
experience other thing that has been
mentioned how he a very curious person
used to just keep trying to em from
wherever he went some new facts factoids
Etc and was very good at connecting them
that's another thing I benefited from
one one several times actually but one
incident with incident which sticks to
my mind is some prity conference where I
had some looking for some some result I
don't remember the details and Professor
Wan was there I asked him is such and
such a result available he thought for a
while and he said I don't think so after
some while he walked away Sanjay was
standing next to us seeing nothing and
then he says have you looked at so and
so paper and that was it correct
hint then at one point he had me and Tom
Richardson and ofer Juni all of us
invited to Pisa together and there was
one incident which you know his wife
offer he left by then he was not there
full time so Tom and I and S and Adriana
he took us for dinner to some fancy
place I think it was in Florence and it
was kind of uphill on top of a hill and
you couldn't drive all the way up so you
had to park somewhere and then we sort
of climbed our way up and suddenly
Adriana started feeling that he had not
locked the car door she got very
agitated SJ locked the car door and kept
getting more and more worked up then s
says take it easy what's the worst that
can happen somebody will take the car
away that was
it this another
sort of odd incident which also shows
his character there was one conference
where this was in mombay in fact and
there's one very senior Professor from
one of the institutes there probably I
think probably was sin I'm not sure but
he gave a talk which was just bizarre
and there was very lot of distinguished
audience it was a major International
Conference and they
stunned just a really strange talk and
then at the end of it gentleman was
expectantly looking at audience for
something sanj raises his hand asked
some some generic question and the guy
said something and some small
conversation and S thanked him and the
guy went away feeling good it just the a
gesture gentlemanly gesture which really
stuck in my
mind really sort of awful talk absurd in
a way but he did not make the person
feel
uncomfortable at
all okay then finally used to visit
India a lot so I kept changing my jobs
and everywhere I was there San has
visited that's T of fundamental research
IND of Science and I and he s on many
advisory roles review committees and so
on he always took these very seriously
his reports were detailed
and sort of accurate I mean exactly you
would recommend what is needed and so on
and also you used to talk to he would
insist on meeting students so we would
give him an office he would sit all day
there and students would sort of sign up
for slots to talk to him
and you would sort of give them advice
and that's one point when I I was
sometimes witnessed to some of this
sometimes I felt that it was too nice
and should sometimes become blunt for
one thing this often you find that our
students it's partly because of sort of
being geographically cut off and not
enough of travel and so on
they often get stuck in some kind of
time War let's say some problem which
was hot long time back and there are
maybe some technicalities left which may
be even very difficult they take them up
and solve them but nobody is interested
but they don't know that in full
sincerity sort of devoting a lot of time
and effort and talent to solve this
things so I was in one such meeting when
he he was trying to persuade the student
that okay this is interesting thing but
you should be doing something more
relevant or more current Etc I think the
message did not go through and I did
feel that it should have been blunt
anyway
so nicity has its limitations in the
sense that cannot achieve everything I
think that's all I had to say thank
you joh bar
thank you very much for organizing this
tribute to
shanjo I think there are about two
people in the room that they know Shan
jooy as much as I
do because Alan and Peter right I don't
think there's anybody that new sanjoy
before 1970 in the room so let me tell
you a little bit about the story because
we sanjo and I go a long way first I'll
talk about technical things and some
jokes about technical things so I came
to the US in
1970 after a lot of advice to come here
because of the wonderful environment at
MIT and Harvard and I'll give you some
parts that Alan mentioned also they were
not technical from that environment and
I didn't know what I wanted to study I I
knew I had to do something about
mathematics physics and Engineering then
I linked with Roger at Harvard first and
those days uh Roger sanjoy and Yan were
here and you will get a lot of
interesting courses and ideas and
questions I met sanjoy in
19771 that year he became What I Call my
second
advisor and through shanjo I I I met and
linked with my third adviser which was
PR Vara I'm telling you all that because
I lost all three of them in one year and
it was to me devastating when that
happened s became very good friends and
yes I'll will tell you some interesting
stories about about how I answer some of
his questions what's new although some
of these questions were given to me
while we were riding the bus from
Harvard Square to MIT took some courses
and uh it's interesting so technically
what always impressed me with Ando even
today it was he's passionate about
trying to understand systems control
information Theory all unified in one
way going all the way back to Gar
Kramer's you know directed information
which later surfaced in the thesis with
m and Nuna Martins and so on so forth
The Duality of information and control
he was struggling with that later with
Nigel Newton and many others and the
continues puru of connections with
mathematical physics and biology and the
fact that the biggest mistake you can
make in life is to think about humans as
ad as causal
systems okay and and what this affects
statistics and other stuff and then
economics philosophy and sociology and
politics no matter what the differ
difficult subject was what impressed me
with Ando and already was mentioned was
that he was calm and almost stoic okay
so he will make a statement as as as M
said and then he will stop then you you
say what do I do now okay and I'll give
you some examples so imagine this this
picture okay two people sitting on the
back row of the bus from Harvard Square
to it talking about things like Hardy
functions the corona theorem
in PE you know Nas for Theory the
generalization of of shift and shift
register
synthesis not paying any attention to
what the environment was who was around
and whatever okay can you imagine what
the other people thought about us and
that was going on every almost two or
three times a week okay now in uh after
I left from here although the The Roots
can go back to sanoi I got involved with
uh because of my colleagues at Maryland
and this connects me to Max razinski
on Quantum estimation information
because we had to solve problems with
communication with
lasers and uh that problem is different
than what we do in signals and systems
because uh in addition to the algorithm
you have to find the
measurements and even those days with
shanjo who connected this things to
multiagent systems and so on so forth
and I remember in my sabatical I came to
my about three times and then for a full
year in 98 we're in the room with sanjoy
and anansa at taond and a few others
talking about things right and this
connection say what they mean s turn to
the group and says what is
measurement he
stopped and now we know that this
question goes very deep even to certain
discussions that happen in mathematical
physics today all right so he then uh
what came about in in terms of history
and some people mentioned it already in
their interaction with sanoi came n
linear filtering
right so there was all kind of
excitement because a fellow by the name
of benis from Babs came up with a
so-called first nonlinear dynamical
filter so uh in many groups in the
country including MIT and Harvard a
super conductivity like competition came
to figure out who is going to find new
finite Dimension filters okay
unfortunately and then we went to dunan
Mor s zai equations for those of you who
were around at the time this is totally
inspired by the way physicists turn
nonlinear problems into linear Problems
by treating unnormalized
equations unfortunately all the results
we came up with were were negative
whether you look at them from Le
algebras or inv Varian Theory or
whatever the result was you have the
gasan linear case and everything else
okay and and S was in the middle of this
trying to to guide the abstractions of
the problem and what was the right
statistics and the right
formulation all right and then around
the same time of course Sanji who had a
very deep interest in in these problems
came about with Deborah alinger with a
solution to the Innovations problem and
I still remember the arguments between
him and kalampur on whether it was
actually solved or not this was the the
problem of whether I get the innovation
in the general diffusion you get all the
sigma Fields constructed and so on so
forth and the other thing was in the
variational theory of filtering and the
path integral representations of
filtering with f cat formula which today
has reincarnated itself in what's called
path integral control and mppi for path
finding and all that okay just just look
at the time right we're talking about
7080s and now okay and then he
introduced me to Nelson stochastic
mechanics which basically says yeah
there's this a for qu mechanics but you
can also think about it as an AS it's a
different very strange version where you
actually connect with stochastic
mechanics to make it simple for you you
take the parabolic equations of of
control change time imaginary they
become scar equation go back and forth
and this has come back again to try to
see if one can develop sort of a theory
of analog quum Computing away from qits
okay so it
uh the negative part was okay we didn't
prove anything that existed time F the
positive thing is that this pushed us to
to understand the generalization of the
H Infinity Theory to linear and set
value and all systems by sanjo asking me
every time we meet what is the system
theoretic interpretation of the two
equations what's the analog in no linear
case how much you can do it okay and we
developed this the later on and I think
at the end he was satisfied
okay uh even in the work I did with uh
internet overs it where we were the
first to to do internet over satellite
when everybody was calling us idiots and
stupid and all that stuff when I came
here in '98 I remember I see in the
corridor and I was trying to explain to
Bob Gallagher and to sanjoy what we did
and sanjoy pops up and says what exactly
did you do I don't understand and then
he kept on through the year until I was
able to explain the problem as a control
problem and the fact that we cheated to
solve it by changing the physics and the
control okay and then he was satisfied
I'm telling you that because what I
admired in San jooy is the
calmness and the ability to persuade you
to go away from the immediacy of the
problem and think a little bit outside
the box and try to see if you can see
more generality and if you can see
connections and I and I think he
influenced me a lot another example
which I learned from him sto was in
Florence but I think he was really in
Florence because he admired the colal
Superior in Pisa and the mathematicians
there I mean maybe that's not true but I
learned from him the mark conjecture
about Imaging which says that you can
reconstruct an image by the
multi-resolution
edges and then he of course worked with
um the Georg theory of variational image
segmentation and so on so forth and he
had somebody here by the name of Tom
Richardson who did the physic on the
subject okay again think about it okay
you take a problem like IM computer
vision and you try to think of it from a
variational perspective and you connect
to some of the deeper theories and um
you know get some new fundamental uh
results in this area and he did it by
minimizing the so-call man foram
functional okay by by these theories and
I
always was very impressed with Tom
Richardson's thesis that was before he
turned to wireless although I still
think he did some very great things in
Wireless and I close with some examples
of things outside science SOI was a
great friend Mentor colleague and
reviewer and and he was always as you
mentioned before calm couldn't get
excited I couldn't get Sano to be very
passionate I'm Greek right so I I get
very I had short fusion and all that
stuff you know all my sins right so it
was always it was always what we call in
Greece stoic okay so he will ask
something and he will ask you to
philosophize let me give you an example
I won't mention names because you may
guess so we were in a review of a
department so somebody who I believe was
the chair stands up and says you know
I'll do XYZ and so on so forth and I'll
get the Department to be top 10 and so
Jo thinks about it says yeah there are
some other people now that they are top
10 okay so can you tell me who you're
going to replace and how you're going to
do it and then he stopped
[Laughter]
again soccer in Cambridge Alan mentioned
it I want to add some things all right
so of course sanjy was coming all
perfectly uh addressed and playing all
the games with the rules and so and so
forth
yeah now you know had somebody named Yan
Williams who will come and grab my elbow
in corner kicks and try to pull me down
okay because he was shorter than me and
he will not let me to go ahead there and
sanj will come and say foul okay from
the other side of the field and then
also he will comment about Tamir Bazar
who just came from turkey and he was
always coming he was playing soccer in
Turkey he will come in with professional
attire where the rest of us were very
informal with not a proper shoes and and
he will he was calling it the Turkish
Terror okay when you would come down the
field okay nobody could stop him and
then we had somebody from Australia darl
Williamson who is a fellow student of
mine who will give you open field rugby
type tackles in soccer and then we'll
say Dar you don't that's not how you
play soccer oh I'm sorry I forgot about
it okay nobody mentioned about I think
it was mentioned but I want to say
something specific about San Joy's
passion with cooking I cook too but he
is Way Beyond me okay and he went
actually to a special school in France
in font Blau to take cooking lessons
unfortunately I didn't have any chance
to observe whether this unhan is cooking
talents or whatever all right and then I
want to mention Adriana of course okay
Adriana was the um what we call the
human intervention in human in in San
Joy
driving sometimes Sano will drive and
we'll get you a conversation and then
you can see that random walk was Tak
over and Adriana will come and say Sano
what what you're doing okay we're in a
car in in a kind nice way all right I
will close by remembering sanjoy as
somebody who deeply cared about
students and Advising them and not just
for a few years almost for life and I
really always remember fondly these
encounters the exchanges and the
influence he had on Me Through The Years
even until now thank you very much
[Applause]
Mar thank you uh I just have very few
remarks I did not know sanj for
extremely long time but I sort of feel
obliged to say something that hasn't
been mentioned this morning he everybody
talked about theorems and I think I have
some slides everybody talks about
theorems and proofs and so forth and
abstractions but actually I come from
Power assistance Community where people
know of sanj's early PhD student Tom
diako who actually introduced the
framework for Power Systems which
industry has adapted so that is a huge
impact so I just want to share that very
little with you so I want to talk about
professor mitter impact on on
applications on Power Systems so he
trained this very person who became very
famous uh person in um software for
control centers in Power Systems Tom
dako came from Philippines and uh this
happened at Cas Western that's one of
his first earlier jobs it was at the
time when actually systems at kage
Western were Golden Era they were left
fovi mesarovic and many other people and
uh I just want to put a couple of slides
to show these industry knows that they
go by these rules that's how they
operate now and that was sanjy and sanj
student Tom diako so basically what Tom
diako did for his PhD thesis he
introduced this framework of adaptive
reliability control system for control
centers of very complex Power Systems
and so what was adaptive about this it
was that when you have normal operation
large complex system and everything
works you still prepare things in a
preventive way just in case something
happen and that became this uh famous
concept of n minus one security if one
large component fails the system still
operates and customers are not
interrupted then emergency state is when
you have a lot of equipment lost and uh
then you have to apply different methods
different models and so forth
restorative is when After the Blackout
when things have fallen apart how do you
bring it back this was Tom liakos first
P one of the first PhD students came
from the industry and many people
mention about uh sanjo being in the
background he really was in the
background you know nurturing Tom who
came from industry from Cleveland
illuminate Illuminating Company c c I at
the time and uh they actually magically
changed the industry this is if you go
to the control centers this is what's
happening this is the rules these are
the Frameworks that that follow
restorative emergency think measurements
that you need this is how the control
centers in the US and everywhere else
work so these were not theorems and
proofs that's what works in real world
and so it's a today's industry practice
and wide adoption on worldwide system in
in 1974 there is a very nice it Spectrum
paper that summarizes that so this is
what how I knew um of sanjoy and Tom
before I came to MIT in
87 first time and
then uh after I came I wanted to just
give a few personal Reflections about me
and Professor m
I think he looking in the H side he was
a catalyst of my own research and there
were just very few things that happened
along the way over long period of time
that actually determin you know where I
went so I for people who don't know I
spent more than I want to admit how long
how many decades in working on
preventing blackouts but I was sent from
Yugoslavia to do PhD on that how do use
systems theory to prevent the the
blackouts and so I did PhD um in at wasu
on U basically beginning to work on the
intersection of systems theoretical
systems because that was my PhD I took
all the control courses but then by I
don't know by some fate I always ended
up applying them to Power Systems and
that was the the what happened and uh I
have to say after so many years this was
not an easy path
because you have you you are right away
on the intersection of theoretical stuff
and applications and this is I think
where sanjo helped big way you know he
got to know me early on and I basically
still do that these days so very
thankful to sanjo for
that uh particular help and
encouragement happened and George is
here and some other people remember when
Fred Fey was the one who invited me to
work in Power Systems at MIT and uh then
he prematurely passed and I was left by
myself so there was SJ who once in a
while would come by my office and say
what are you doing you should be doing
that oh do you remember Tom diako and
you know you can have an impact and so
forth so this is how he kept me go going
several you know several times only but
then I went to um to CMU and
um basically he kept in touch we kept in
touch a little bit but when I returned
in 2015 it was very interesting he came
and says oh you have to just continue
what we started why don't you put all
the MIT people across different
departments and do the brainstorming he
was always Community Builder so what we
have here is the first Workshop that
leads organized uh there and I think I
don't remember exactly we have all those
doc but must have been 30 people
proactive really working actively in the
area of systems across different
departments we we are still spread
through different departments but San's
idea was let's work together and it was
a really wonderful um wonderful uh
Workshop we plan to sear ja is
encouraging us now to continue to build
such momentum at
leads here he and that
Workshop sitting in the first row with
participants for two days I was
absolutely
amazed
um and just one more thing which
happened a few years recently and
actually changed my uh my direction
confirmed the direction I was going on
people were talking about these
behavioral models that Yan Williams had
he he said what's up of course and I
told him I'm working on trying to unify
models for power system to simplify so
that people can actually understand
without knowing all the Technologies and
he said why don't you go and read this
paper I trip control magazine by Yan and
that's where shared variables you know
confirm our idea of interaction
variables in complex systems and I still
do that that's why I'm not retired
so just to
close I'm really grateful for continuing
encouragement that he has done for me
and I will miss him very much and I
thank for teaching me how to persevere
when things are hard there are lot of
young people here roads are not going to
be easy but sanj found a way to actually
keep people going and I definitely had
that I don't know how other people feel
I'm sure that students at least who have
graduated te talk seminars everything
looks emptier now he always was sitting
on Wednesdays I forget when the seminar
was and I also want to say in the H side
as we get get older we really don't know
what we have before we lose it and
that's how I
remember uh sanjoy with my warmest
memories thank you
the thing he was most proud of was his
patents he had I believe two patents yes
he had got a
brown yes yes and he was extremely proud
of those much prouder than of uh uh the
variational approach and all CL St thank
you Peter I this is why I mentioned this
early work because it's unbelievable I
mean you go to control Community I've
been on the sides uh sidelines of
theoretical control Community but
actually people don't know about this to
go to Industry and I work a lot with
industry I have a startup everybody
thinks according to this that diagram
that uh they he and Tom uh um
conceptualized at uh at Case Western
this is the rule you develop software
for preventive control for uh
restoration and so forth and uh you know
I just wanted to say thank sanjo for a
lot of things that he has helped in the
industry one thing just maybe a little
technical thing if you don't have these
uh these different operating modes then
you end up that's what industry does
worst case approach so they put all
these reserves you cannot utilize clean
energy you cannot utilize um the least
expensive power so one thing that I wish
I can do before I retire is put a
student to compute to estimate what is
potent saving that has come dollar
saving that's actually come from this uh
invention and I think what it teaches us
is that uh you know a lot of far out
things that we do actually ultimately
have big impact on on uh real world
that's what I wanted to sh with you
thank you thank you
[Applause]
Maria hi so when I was uh preparing for
this um I was thinking about what to say
um about sanjoy and his human side and I
find it quite difficult to you know
Express in words uh and I was looking
for for for things to say and um and I
felt a little bit lost also because he
was you know to me and to many of us he
was the professor that was who was up
there and we were the disciples that
were down here here so he kept his
distance so in order I I became curious
and in order you know to jump start the
thing I became curious and to see what
was the collective knowledge about San
joy and so I did this experiment and
asked Chad GPT to help me and uh in the
spirit of San Joy's investigative um you
know inclination I want to um check if
uh know starting from AI there is
something person personal that I can add
on the collective knowledge that is
there so I will just uh start by reading
the beginning of chat GTP answer to a
gentleman and lifelong scholar sanj
mitter so chat GPT says We Gather to
today to honor The Life and Legacy of a
remarkable man Professor sanj mitter a
gentleman a brilliant scholar and an
inspiring Mentor whose influence
extended far beyond the bounds of the
academic word in C crating his life we
also remember the profound impact that
he had on each of us both personally and
professionally so it looks to me like
rather standard perhaps not too
impressive opening from chat
GPT uh but then he continues he say
anter was more than a professor he was a
true intellectual giant of the fields
and control theory systems theory
information theory he was work bridged
multiple disciplines and his research
transformed our understanding of complex
systems and here chat GPT
is clear that has done its own homework
and and hit the
target um yet despite his immense
contribution to Science and Technology
it was his warmed quite humility
graciousness and deep kindness that left
and the indelible mark on all of who had
the privilege of knowing him so here in
delible Mark so then I start I started
thinking what is the indelible Mark that
he left on me and um I can tell you my
little story here
so when I uh first met him it was 2002
and I was at Berkeley as a postto and um
I met him together with Bruno
Copo he's here he was a pitch the
student and Shankar SRI told us there is
this professor who's visiting from MIT
you should uh go for coffee entertain
him okay let's uh do that so Bruno we
have to uh entertain this Professor from
MIT we should definitely try to make an
impression and uh let's go and so we go
for coffee and jooy camps uh uh see we
sit down and it was like almost a comic
meeting uh you know the two of us and
sanjoy the center we started you know
trying to say uh sanjoy we we worked on
this cman filtering problem that I think
is very interesting and we try to
impress him and you know sanjo is not
going to be impressed not going to be
impressive stops right away and says oh
you should look at uh uh you know the
the work that I did with Nigel Newton uh
and and then we say oh that's very
interesting and and then we continue
yeah but but our result here say
something interesting and it stops oh
there is this other reference that you
should look at and and so on and so on
just you know throwing references at us
one more obscure than the than the other
of course so so it was not impressed and
then late later I I realized you know
why this was very impactful is because
you know the the role of the
advisor I think that uh uh he showed me
that the role of the advisor is not to
first of all not to be impressed not to
tell you how great you are doing not to
tell you exactly what to do like give
you task and you should do this and that
but just to help so so the his role was
to help he was helping
helping by providing information and uh
and stimulate your own curiosity and you
know think out out of the box and U and
this is really and not to be concerned
about impressing people but uh satisfy
your curiosity and and put your own
goals and this is is very much related
to what John was saying about you know
stoic philosophy it ties very well to to
the principles of
that um nevertheless uh you know somehow
you know these two strange Italian
fellows were were interesting enough
that we kept in touch um um through the
years and um and uh and he really became
um a a a light for
us um so let let me um say something
else here from from um uh from CHP he
says um uh sanj's life reminds us its
core scholarship is not about just facts
theories or discoveries is about people
and uh uh this is I think is very true
in the sense that what he was doing and
it was also mentioned before you know
the statement that Petro perona made
that he created this environment right
where where where where people will
congregate and he was in the center just
facilitating discussions and U and
creating an environment where people
could uh Exchange ideas and I think
that's that's very important part of
what he did um even I remember at
workshops you know sometimes happens
often at conference and workshop
somebody gives a talk and then you know
there is no interaction just you know no
no questions and so on so if he was in
the audience he would rather than ask
questions sometimes know identify
somebody and say Ali you have something
to to comment about this or something
like that so so so that was uh uh quite
unique
um
um okay then the LA the last thing is um
well I just skip some of CHA answer here
but it says uh but beyond academic
accolades and jooy was a man of profound
character he had a quite Elegance about
him a Grace that defined not only his
interaction but his entire Outlook of
life and U uh at the end I think that
that's what um it's pecular about this
is that U it's the character of the
person that really inspired us so he
created this image in this way of sort
of uh being somehow distant but
accessible at the same time and uh we as
disciples really wor worshiped the him
so and I I talked to you know yesterday
over dinner about this you know he would
say these things that uh are very
obscure and then be quiet and then we
spent like days afterwards you know
sanjo said this what what what what what
did he mean you know I start you know
just trusting him completely 100% and
try to sort of decode what what he meant
and and and and possibly uh go beyond
what he said and discover things uh new
so that that was uh was really part of
of his uh of his character and the
figure that that he
created um and he really inspired us
through uh I mean he advised us through
inspiration that's what um Maxim rinsky
also
mentioned okay one um one last thing is
U how I like to remember San jooy and I
tell you another little story um 12
years
ago he came to uh to my webing he flew
to San Diego and I was very honored that
he did that and he he participated in
the wedding and then he brought uh a
present to us uh it it was um a pair of
wine glasses champagne glasses that were
beautiful engraved very nice uh present
and so nowadays uh every time uh we have
some celebration or something at home we
are drinking a glass of champagne glass
of prco my wife would say uh masimo take
the S met out of the closet so because
this is really special occasion so that
that's how uh we like like to remember
him okay this is the end of the session
I just want to end it on a light note in
echoing uh Maria's and Peter's uh
comments about uh sanj's
practicality um we often found sanjoy uh
talking practical stuff in a classroom
so one time he said to be practical
let's consider a measure that is
continuous with respect to leag
I don't know if that was in his patent
anyway I would like to thank the
speakers this was a wonderful um
collection of information and memory
from sanjoy and um you know thank you so
[Applause]
much okay uh thank you so much for a
wonderful session uh the next session is
sano's legacy and impact uh I'm asking
uh Tom LA and anant to come to the stage
uh we're going to hear from three of uh
sanj's former
students uh and uh so an an if you
may you know introduce everyone thank
you so
much
so it's a
real pleasure to to be able to talk
about San Joy
uh from the students perspective I think
so Tom will go first then love and then
then
me okay uh so first I like to thank the
organizers for inviting me I'm very
happy to be here at first um I wasn't
sure if I wanted to speak because I you
know at the lid's 80th anniversary I'd
introduced sanjoy and I was quite happy
with how that went and I thought maybe I
would leave it at that but this is a
memorial conference and I do have quite
a lot of memories and uh at least some
of them I wanted I thought would be good
to share so Vivic already mentioned um
the trip into Pisa and I remember um
Adriana mentioning that the car had been
left unlocked and and thinking uh that
she wanted San to go back and and I
remember thinking at the time you know
um yeah maybe maybe he should I
suggested maybe you should move the car
but then I kind of regretted it because
I was thinking uh the less driving the
better and John Paris was right the
drive there was nerve-wracking I
remember it very well but uh you the
trip in that time in Pisa was really
great for me and also ended up having
important um contributions to my work at
MIT because of the connecting to the
Georgie who was there and sanj brought a
student of his uh Luigi Ambrosio to MIT
and who taught us all about sbv spaces
and free discontinuity problems and and
the math uh was very important to the to
the work that I did
and um as Alan had mentioned uh Sano did
look after the career of the students
long after so uh yeah just same with
Allan I it came as a total shock to me
somewhere around 2011 I got this letter
that I I was elected to the National
Academy of engineering and I I had I
knew right away that sand was behind it
it was a little odd because the word
work had no connection really well very
little direct connection at least to uh
what I had done with sanjoy but maybe a
year before he had asked me to send him
some information on some patents at
first I thought he was trying to get me
into a faculty job but uh that didn't
happen so then I realized that's what it
was and I so I next time I saw him I
said you know how did how did you know
like he said Ana chbby helped me a
little and so they uh so somehow behind
the scenes you know watching over me uh
kind of like a a fairy Godfather or
something I I I I was really kind of
shocked by that experience but what I
really wanted to share was my Mo most
poignant memory of s joy and maybe it's
a little difficult in a sense to to
explain because it may sound a little
self- serving because uh I have to
discuss my relationship with sanjoy and
how I experienced him and it was it was
a real experience but it was a little
unusual so I came to MIT in 1986 the
center for intelligent Control Systems
had just been started and uh in brown
there was this group looking at Mark our
random Fields as supplied to computer
vision sto I just graduated a student
Jose amican Amin who was um also in the
Cs lab had worked on inverse problems
and using essentially Marco random
Fields as a prior so San was interested
in uh Pur showing these kinds of ideas
and Mark a random Fields I remember um
going to meetings with him and I the
means were very exciting and very
inspiring and often I would leave the
office like said some great thing is
coming I can't believe you know the
vision that I just experienced and then
I would go back to my office and sit and
think about it and work on then think we
just kind of
dissolve I it was very hard to find an
actual
um it's
actionable um step to take from this
inspiration but it was it was generally
real and and very enjoyable and and it
lasted for years I and I still had them
um years later but uh just give you an
example um so actually there's a quote
from Einstein something along the lines
students are not a container to fill but
a torch to be set a light and sanjo is
very good at setting a light but he's
also filling the container um so I
remember like very early on uh he told
me you know Kenneth Wilson's giving you
a talk so he had just won the Nobel
Prize two years earlier for
renormalization group so renormalization
group clearly should be connected to
computer vision right so I went to the
talk and I didn't understand anything
thing and came back to talk to sanjoy
and uh said well I should read this read
this read this so I read all these
papers I finally started to learn get
some idea what it was all about it was a
very delicate object mathematically
quite difficult there were a lot of um
problems with doing the renormalization
and so on and it was basically something
that could be applied to a very special
case in statistical mechanics so yeah
very interesting great great stuff but
what do I do with it and then there was
another experience like that uh shortly
after I was learning you have to go read
Bran's papers or Mark of random Fields
what are the conditions for Unique gives
measures
difficult stuff and uh I worked quite
hard and but the thing was I wasn't
getting anywhere I wasn't producing any
of these great synthesis results that I
think the let's say the um Global
viewpoints that SRE was after and so I
was starting to feel frustrated and a
little defeated this went on for maybe
two
years and I was starting to think that I
just didn't have what it takes I mean he
was sharing these Visions but I somehow
was not able to fulfill them I think the
connections are are there and many of
them I think will play out if not
already but um eventually
but okay but but I wasn't I I was
starting to think that I just didn't
have what it takes I couldn't I couldn't
realize the vision and I was starting to
think that maybe
um I wasn't going to make it now
sanjoy
um like I said
he I was under the impression that he
would have these make these connections
between things and he could see what was
coming from them and it was my job
basically to realize that vision and it
was in some sense that's right but
wasn't exactly right and uh so my most
poignant memory is when I realize what
was actually going on there and it
happened like I said after about two
years and I was actually thinking that I
I maybe I should give this up because I
just wasn't producing any results I
didn't have anything to show for the
efforts which had been kind of
extreme so I had a meeting with sanjoy
and
he and he and I was in the state of
almost delirium because I thought um I
should just this is gonna this has got
to end and and San was talking about
random fields on the board and he was
saying something about you know maybe we
can treat this as a signal noise ratio
and I looked at it and I thought and in
my delirium I was
thinking there's something wrong with
that there's something wrong with the
units and up to this point you know my
discussions with Shan Joy were mostly he
would say something explain something
and I would try to understand now um I
had nothing left to lose and he and I
looked at you know thought about what he
said um and realized that okay there was
something wrong with the units maybe
there's a way to fix it came up with
something and then said to him well you
know maybe maybe we should defin it this
way and he turned to me me and said
maybe you're right and that completely
changed everything so in that moment I I
had a there was a huge shock to my
system that all along sanoy had been
putting these ideas out there it was
meant to as a guide here's interesting
Territory go explore but as far as
deciding what to do or finding the path
to actual work and results that was up
to me to do and and
so that completely sort of inverted my
world that point and but from there on I
was able to I was able to take sanj's
advice in a different way now after that
point I was able to take suggestions and
his pointers think about them you know
and as far as actually getting things
done reject them if necessary and the
amazing thing was that you know that
never seemed to bother sanjy that
whatever I decide to do and whatever I
could think of doing which was always up
to me U was okay and so I managed to
muddle through and finish the thesis
this and carry on and so this um idea of
the global Viewpoint to me what I think
remains with San sanoy with me the most
is this idea which I think I experienced
in those first two years of his trying
to point out you know what were the
possibilities for some Global synthesis
some great perspective uh some something
really achieving uh in terms of bringing
the best ideas together and seeing
something new and deep and to me that's
what's going to stick from San Joy it
sounds it's kind of something worth
living for I think it's a good worthwh
life mission and that's what San left me
with I'm I feel much better for it thank
you
[Applause]
uh I also want to thank the organizers
for putting this together um just a a
great way to to remember sanjoy um it's
been emotional already for me and um uh
just just really really great um I just
wanted to first uh comment on sojo's
sorial splendoress like no one has
really commented on this right whenever
I used to go to his office he had his
three-piece suit on he was um you know
on his game um it's really awesome and
um uh in fact yesterday morning when I
was packing to come here uh I was
looking in my closet and I decided let
me go ahead and go with the white linen
jacket right um so one of the things sjo
really gave me was kind of a an
emotional education kind of confidence
to to do and to be um and that's
something I think is um perhaps unusual
um I think a lot of advisers you know
they focus on on technical train
training they focus on um um you know I
mean a variety of things but uh kind of
that emotional confidence and and that
kind of education I think is something
that um uh really um kind of made made
me uh kind of um pursue things that
might seem a little unusual or out of
the
mainstream um so um yeah that's kind of
um like one of the the core core
attributes I think of of Sunjoy advising
that many people have have kind of
brought up
is um this confidence to explore um and
and to kind of try to bring these pieces
together um just like maso um sanjo came
to our wedding uh in in Florida in 201
end of
2013 uh just before Christmas and uh he
actually he gave us glasses as well uh
maybe that's his thing for wedding gifts
I'm not quite sure um um but uh yeah he
was on the dance floor as well which
which was kind of fun and um uh the the
I wanted to mention was um the dessert
that we served at our wedding reception
was something that was designed by by a
technology that I had developed at IBM
this Chef Watson technology um it was a
caymanian plantain dessert it had uh
Cayman um pepper uh kind of a banana
cream L and so on and um I mean it was
it was a solid dessert but he was
actually very effusive like like more
than he should have been it was again
kind of a nice way to to give me
confidence and I was going to be
starting as a professor the following
week after the wedding so we went on our
honeymoon then I moved to Illinois and
then then started so um again it was
kind of this kind of bringing um
bringing kind of some confidence um that
uh you know um you can you can be who
you are um and um when I was a student
perhaps I wasn't the the strongest
mathematically um but um again he often
would say that um you know you can be
who you are um you're an engineer um
kind of solve the problem that's in
front of you and uh and it's okay if you
don't use the uh the fanciest
mathematical techniques but if you can
make an impact um conceptually or or
kind of in a um uh kind of in a in a
societal impact manner I mean that's
that's appropriate as well so um so that
was kind of um some of my experiences as
a as a student and and later on um I
came um to Cambridge once uh with my
2-year-old daughter and you know we we
stopped by Sun Joy's office um she Drew
on his board uh with his chalk which
which I don't know like he had very
thick chalk I'm not sure why he had such
thick chalk so she had very kind of
difficulty holding it so then um he gave
her a a piece of paper and a pen so she
Drew on that and we had kind of a nice
chitchat and um like as when when I was
a student of course um but also um at
that time he had you know a lot of books
on his on his table his Round Table in
his office and one of the books that he
had on his uh office desk at the time
was uh grenander General pattern Theory
Book which many of you have may be
familiar with um and we kind of had this
conversation that um you know no one's
really pursued that direction uh to its
fullest this pattern Theory idea and it
kind of struck me and um in the last
several years I've been pursuing this
direction that we call information Lotus
learning which kind of takes group
theoretic ideas and information
theoretic ideas to learn and discover
knowledge and um in many ways I think
that grenander influence I mean VI
sanjoy was uh has been kind of driving
that and um and really kind of also sjo
kind of humanism in in a sense so music
theory has been our first application
area I'm trying to learn the laws of
Music Theory from just a small amount of
data um data just 300 CS from by Johan
Sebastian Bach um so um so again kind of
just uh just you know that visit uh to
MIT with my daughter U I mean it was
more just kind of a social visit but he
said you know read read revisit
grenander and then it kind of inspired
this uh this line of work um another
kind of interesting visit was uh
actually I mean an kind of encouraged me
to also talk a little bit about his
modern influences so or impacts so let
me just actually do a brief aside on
that um so um I think early on today
someone was mentioning his 1968 paper on
modal control um and it uh it's
something that I've been working on
myself actually recently um so I've been
collaborating with the with a
neuroscientist eron barbet and he does a
lot of um fmri studies on human
intelligence so he does studies on a
large number of people and there's
behavioral measurements on how they
score on intelligence tests and so on um
but then fmri studies on looking at
nature of their brain and and the basic
question is are there neural correlates
of intelligence um and uh and it turns
out that um in fact yes uh so modal
control ability um provides a mechanism
to measure uh individual differences in
in human intelligence uh in particular
um kind of the flexibility in driving
kind of Global Network architectures to
to disperate States um seems to be U
very strongly correlated with uh with
human intelligence so um uh yeah when we
were doing this work in fact I didn't
realize it was sanjo who developed modal
control uh when I was first working on
this but uh and we looked back and saw
you know it was that 1968 paper where it
came from um and more recently we've
been looking at some kind of
Neuroscience questions um with mitovski
at the flat iron Institute in New York
um and and the kind of emerging view is
that at an anatomical level um seems
like there's maybe data driven control
all the way down to individual neurons
um um there's uh kind of been a
long-standing view that at a cognitive
level there's uh kind of control
theoretic things happening but even at
the individual neuron level it seems
that maybe there's uh some control and
uh so we've been drawing a little bit on
on on seare and and and uh and Sunjoy
work on communication restricted control
so um so kind of all these ideas that uh
kind of that I was exposed to kind of in
the in the millu of of sj's work and and
of Lids more broadly seem to be seem to
be coming back and these questions
around Neuroscience likewise the the
Charles Rockland seans report uh again
we've been thinking about that more and
more uh to think about how um
segregation and integration are kind of
key to uh to human
intelligence um or or also even at the
level of nematodes like seans and and
other small
organisms um so I think I fulfilled my
my duty to talk about modern impacts
um uh and then I wanted to briefly speak
about the last time I met sanjoy this
was Memorial Day Weekend uh in 23 uh
just a month before his before his
passing um so I um at the time I was on
leave uh to serve at the white house uh
so I was a bureaucrat for a year um and
sanjo I was actually um not displeased
about it uh so he was actually quite
like he was supportive of you know these
deviations in in in my life's journey um
and uh a couple of the things that we
talked about were were quite interesting
so um uh there's this uh there's this
religious text the uh the um
Chand um and there's a a section in
there which talks about um kind of the
knowledge that's available to Kings
versus the knowledge that's available to
to Scholars um essentially um and uh I
mean the central point is that uh you
know the practice of doing things like
govern um leads to different sources of
knowledge than than just kind of
theorizing about it um and so he was
kind of bringing that up a little bit
that you know you should take your year
uh in the National Security Council and
you know um gain that practical
experience so then you can think about
it uh in in some more deeper ways um
when you go back to being a scholar um
and um he also brought up uh his his
childhood friend Amaria son's uh kind of
multi-dimensional view of uh of social
welfare um that uh um I mean the the
prevailing view in uh in in the
Eisenhower executive office building is
of Cl Switz um kind of these distinct
levers of power um as as kind of how you
think about uh National um
competitiveness and National Power um
but uh you know sanjoy was was kind of
helping me think through a little bit
that um this kind of older view like
cilia the the prime minister of jandra
gup Moria he had put forth more of a
networked View of of National Power um
so yeah kind of we we discussed that as
well and um you know just kind of just
to give you an example everyone has
talked about this um you know kind of
Sunjoy wide ranging interests but uh it
kind of brought it home for me um uh
that day uh just uh just last year um
and I've been kind of reflecting on this
a little bit more um uh with respect to
public policy and um engineering Theory
seems fairly absent from most public
policymaking um so you know there aren't
so many information theorists uh serving
in government let's say um but uh in in
kind of some of my Reflections uh
especially coming back to Illinois after
after serving um is that in fact
engineering Theory and some of the ideas
that come from it can be really powerful
for public policym um sjo used to always
emphasize to me that Shannon's greatest
contribution was the separation theorem
and the architectural
aspect of separating Source coding from
Channel coding um not just I mean he
also liked the universal interface of
bits which he I mean he also likes to
talk about but um the architectural
principle that you can have these
different blocks um and as we're
thinking about for example technology
policy um or other branches of of public
policy and these architectural
principles that might come out of
optimality theories um can actually be
informative for for public policym is
something that I don't think many people
think about um but yet um seems to be um
uh a compelling approach so um yeah just
kind of um random thoughts uh apologies
for rambling I didn't prepare a very
cohesive uh thing but um very much
sojo's kind of emotional education has
been you know very important to me um as
well as his kind of um push to expose
myself to different ways of thought to
walking around in in some ways both
physically and and metaphysically I
suppose um and uh yeah I mean I think
like many of his students feel the same
way so um let me just stop there and and
really um say you know uh it's it was
it's been a great journey and um you
know he'll always be in in my head uh as
we go forward thank you
okay
so a lot has been said about San joy and
from the perspective of his students um
I realized there's one thing that has
been brought up but I wanted to sort of
give my personal take on on this and how
it helped me develop you
know in the outside world it seems
people think of Engineers and people who
are science oriented as being very
narrow and I I come to realize that for
myself my education especially having
Sandra as an adviser is I think of the
exact
opposite right because San was like the
model of what it what a what a scholar
an engineer should should be like to me
and this
really I remember as a first year grad
student you know sitting in the office
and building building 35
and you sitting there thinking about
something you know research oriented
sanjo would walk by and he'd
say have you seen what happened what
this thing in the New York Review of
Books and I'm like what no am I supposed
to know what's in the New York Review of
Books when I came I honestly when I I
started as a gradu student I didn't even
know there was such a thing as the New
York Review of Books forget you know
what's in it you know and at first I I
talked it up as oh this is you know some
must be something particularly odd or
interesting you know and so I'll just
like listen and follow on and then soon
I realized that okay and every day I
would actually go to the engineering
library and like go and see what's in
the New York Times what's in the Wall
Street Journal and what was in the New
York review of book so that when sanjoy
walks by I'll be able to comment
something you know um it's part of this
education that love was mentioning about
you know looking at a person and sort of
trying to understand okay not you know
maybe you should know this a little bit
better and be a little bit more engaged
with all this other stuff and it really
had an influence on me you know during
grad school one of the things
that you know at the time I didn't put
it together but now I can see clearly
with sanj's influence was that maybe I
should go and actually read some of this
classic literature you know not I wasn't
going to read it in the German as San
would have probably preferred but you
know like let me read it uh you know in
English or translation at least
and experience of being a student um and
being exposed to this was in part seeing
how it really felt that sandre didn't
have like one way of thinking about art
politics and a completely different way
of thinking about you know uh
differential equations and stochastic
calculus it was one way of thinking it
just ranged broadly over
everything and
ideas and connections were coming from
everywhere and this encouragement was
already mentioned of you know hey you
should I think ASU mentioned it you you
should attend talks I remember this and
I remember complaining at the beginning
I said San I attend the Lizz colloquium
and after five minutes I have no idea
what is going on um you know why why are
you telling me I should be attending
these talks and he goes just
wait you know you'll see and indeed that
was very very true just sort of seeing
the different kinds of things and talked
about and being able to watch how ideas
get developed over the course of a PhD
you know just seeing other not even
stuff not stuff you're working on just
it it just did inform what it meant to
be uh a scholar and I think that focus
of sanjy on kind of developing us as
Scholars with
an with intellectual taste that was
trying to be cultivated as well as
breath of ideas is something that I know
many people here are our faculty and I
you know I often find myself reflecting
on the experience that um the students I
have and the students in the milu today
have
and sometimes feeling
like I haven't been as good of a mentor
as sanjoy was in terms of providing them
with the same kind of encouragement to
be
uh
patient and it's one could argue it's
harder today than it was then um but
still just what he modeled was very very
profoundly
influential so this is on the sort of
side of you know you know kind of
General Recollections and and things
more specifically I want to comment on
sano's I think Tom has mentioned uh this
already I'm surprised others have not um
I think Mike branik is the one who
described it uh in the language I'm
about to use he said that walking into
San Jo's office is like walking into a
special reality Distortion field where
you walk in and you know there's a
conversation about something and it's
like completely clear and makes total
sense sort of you kind of reaching but
it's kind of you're following it but
then as you walk away you know the the
further you get from his office the more
it fades you know almost like a dream
you know
but in there were ideas and I could see
sometimes ideas that I mean there ideas
that sanjoy had mentioned in his office
that a decade later you know while I'm a
faculty member or even longer you know
come back wait that was a really good
connection and now I can understand it
and appreciate it but I think as Tom was
saying it wasn't that Sandy already had
thought out what was going to happen you
know 15 years later but that he could
see the possibilities and he wanted to
encourage us to be open to these
possibilities and so a part of this um
for me was actually the area exam uh so
uh with the uh with Sano I'm very sad
for any current MIT graduate student
you're missing out by not having any
area exam anymore it was a wonderful
thing
um but uh you know we were given San
picked out uh part of the committee you
know a few papers uh and picked these
Classics for me I think it was the uh
Colman's original paper on common
filtering um witsen Housen a pair of
papers on the witsen Housen counter
example and his paper on separation of
estimation and control and uh the the
classic paper on Dual control and it was
go off go think about these things and
you know it was a very very intense uh
month of uh thinking about these things
um
sanjy later told me he wasn't just
saying here are some cool papers he was
exposing to certain ideas putting them
together and think and suggest saying
you know what I there's more
here and that was something that sanjoy
uh brought out
was it was as though in his
mind there were these intellectual
questions ranging across many many
different fields and these little points
of this doesn't we don't understand this
yet this is important to understand we
don't understand it yet that he would
keep circling back and connecting you
two it wasn't just random what he was
connecting it wasn't just technique
although he would definitely bring up
technique it was also
anomalies we don't understand this we
don't understand this and we don't
understand this and they feel like these
are all anomalous in a similar maybe way
or maybe not
and so you know that area exam was fun
you know we was very influential for
pushing my direction of what I was going
to think about and and work on but for
example on the witsen Housen counter
example stuff I found myself revisiting
it uh you know a decade later you know
uh as new and making and the spirit of
making connections and seeing what
techniques can be brought in connections
from one thing to another which
eventually let us you know do something
uh and push move the ball forward um you
know significantly not fully solve but
you know push the ball
forward and in that way for me as a
faculty member and as a researcher San
Joy's experience being a student has
continued to influence me uh and well I
think continue to influence me and
influence my students indirectly and I
think that's really a very important
part of sanj's Legacy Beyond any
specific
results um that that he had um final
comment I wanted to make was a little
bit about uh sanjoy as a a professor a
teacher and other people have commented
on this um I had the pleasure of being
his ta also so which was a really fun
experience um because sanjo is brilliant
you know and he would give these
lectures I think dynamic programming was
the course um and I'd be like wow that's
very cool but then soon I got to
thinking I'm not sure the students are
following what is happening here and I
would then find out later in you know in
office hours as I would try to you know
help and that also shaped uh uh my uh
myself and influenced my my teaching and
so on um both in positive and in
negative ways but uh so I think when we
think about San's intellectual Legacy
you know it's it's broad deep and
embodied in people and uh
so also had experiences of of having uh
coming back to visit MIT and I think I
mentioned to some people when I came for
um John's uh retirement party um that
was held here that was my first first
visit back to MIT uh after sanjy passing
and it was actually quite hard because
every time I'd come uh to visit uh
Boston MIT I would always go and visit
him and talk to him and that time it
really hit that I'm now visiting this
place and I can't see him and uh even
this time it it's still hard so um yeah
thanks
[Applause]
thank you so much for a great session
we're on time and uh lunch is served
next uh next door I believe thank you
we'll start at two
[Music]
in
he
[Music]
is
for
[Music]
for for
for
[Music]
is
[Laughter]
[Music]
is
for
[Music]
m
is
[Music]
for
e
e e
[Music]
is
for
[Music]
good afternoon everyone uh we're almost
ready to get started I'd like to ask uh
the panelist for the next session to
come to the stage
[Music]
you want us to sit ontically
in the order
of said
justed you sles okay I it is not in yet
so I'm just waiting by it's
not okay good afternoon everyone in this
session we're going to hear from uh some
of uh
sanj's litz colleagues um and Le Jang
will moderate the session uh so thank
you so much again for being
here yeah I actually get uh uh Greg uh
agreed to also speak in the session and
uh so this becomes the current uh uh
faculty who didn't speak so far right uh
that's uh that's where it is uh my name
is Le J I'm going to start this and um
you know uh I have a confession to make
that when we were organizing this I
didn't plan to talk uh but when we put
this together I started to realize uh
that uh um there we are actually on a
smaller fraction of uh current uh
resident at
MIT um that uh we still know where was
building
35 and more and more people are hired
after we moved away from that and uh I I
you know many of you mentioned that SRO
likes to wander around talk to people
and uh personally if I close my eyes
think of where Sandro was walking around
the background was building 35 it was it
was a it was that big uh big Corridor
and um yeah I I actually um
met sorry I I I first met I I'm really
not good at doing this I I I I first met
sandre uh in that building uh when I was
a graduate student visiting and uh this
random day sand showed up get invited a
couple of SC for for coffee and at the
at the time the only place you can get
coffee from building 35 is across the
street to the to the student center and
Sandro would in that you know would ask
me um you know what what what I was
doing and he would suggest you know what
what I should be doing and um and how do
I like MIT so far because I was a
visitor uh little little did I know at
the time that this same meeting probably
happened 100 times after that when I was
a new faculty sandre just keep coming
like randomly like uh like every other
day you can see him and uh uh Sandry
talked to all of my early graduate
student you know he would ask you know
how's Shashi right and uh and and he
speak with my student IMU in Italian
which I do not even understand and they
they pretty much every one of them had a
very extensive meeting uh with with with
C like hours and hours of of real
technical discussion you know that
started from how are you doing that kind
of a uh random encounter and uh um you
know when when we were organizing this
meeting I I talked to uh Bob Gallagher
who's the co- director with with SRE for
long time and uh uh by the way he sent
in a video message together with a lot
of other video messages and written
messages we're going to do them at 4M
last session and uh and Bob mentioned
that besides all the really exciting
technical contribution that sandre has
made sandre was also a exceptional
leader that his contribution to MIT was
to make LD a very pleasant place that
people like to work together um you know
you know come to this place to work and
I I I sometimes when I look back to that
uh uh kind of memory I I feel uh maybe
maybe um maybe I was really really young
and naive at the time but uh but the
feeling was life was simpler when sway
people were around and we we we we
didn't have to worry about that many
things we don't worry about where money
come from where do we publish this stuff
and uh those graduate student they they
just do not worry about a thing at all
right and uh we we're just a whole bunch
of young people coming together figure
things out right and uh uh we we figure
out one thing we talk about it then we
figure out the next thing and uh and
there was a pure joy of uh uh
intellectual um you know exchange and uh
I think I think I'm speaking at the
receiving end of this of having s as a a
senior you know Mentor colleague then we
we are we enjoying that and I think what
um the environment at the time um I
think as who call that a calm
environment uh love call that a sense of
confidence I think that these are all
right on uh what we got the feeling at
the time was uh was just uh you know if
we just keep on doing what we're doing
then every other problem in life would
just solve themselves right see that was
um you know you could call that a
correct or wrong uh view but uh but it
was really enjoyable and I I I will
remember sway because of
[Applause]
that all right uh
I thought I will use some slides with
some pictures not necessarily pictures
of sanjoy
himself but pictures that reminds me of
him um all right so let's see as they
come up uh so I met sanj first time on
April 5th 20 2004 literally four plus 20
plus years
ago uh there was a that was the day I
was interviewing here at MIT um and he
was of the earliest members I met among
LS faculty members I had 4-day visit and
I think I met him four different times
uh he didn't take me to mandarine but he
took me to Royale East and that was a
definitely an enjoyable meal uh more for
the conversation than just uh food but
then I kept going to a royist by the way
after that uh uh as all of us have
spoken about sanj I was always curious
about what's going on in your life in
your group students Etc and as I was
sorting through my pictures I trying to
find the latest picture where he was
fully involved in all sorts of thesis
and all that and so maybe if I can do
this these are just of two pictures that
came out um and as you can tell he was
on those thesis committees with uh uh
some of colleagues here uh and that was
always great you know he's always
interested like uh one of my student
finished his thesis in
2022 and he immediately sent a note
saying that hey I'm really interested in
doing this send me let's get on Zoom
call and we had a long conversation so
that was
him uh for me personally he played u a
huge role I'm just eternally grateful to
him uh one thing is when I joined MIT uh
many of you might remember uh the
precursor of idss was Engineering
Systems Division and my position was
half Engineering Systems Division and uh
eecs and at that time in Engineering
Systems division there was no faculty
member from Leeds or eecs at large and
he' made a huge gesture of joining it
halime which now in hindsight I see how
big it is I don't know if I will do it
but it was amazing in a sense that was
his view I believe and this is something
I would attribute to Ramesh as in Ramesh
ji one of my same AG uh former graduate
from Lids his view was that I think or
view was that Sunjoy prior about people
was very simple these are amazing people
okay no matter who the person is and he
would fully believe in that prior and
typically he would not go to
posterior uh and that was him uh when I
started uh in my first year at uh I
wanted to develop a course on
Engineering Systems Division and then he
helped me developed the course and the
interesting thing was is just do what
you think is the
best when uh help was needed he was the
one of the invisible hands and so thank
you about
that coming
to pictures now so as many of us have
heard multiple times that he would come
and ask you stop by our office whatever
it means what's new like the few minutes
ago Pablo stopped me and asked me what's
new reminded me of that and the
typically uh initially my response was I
would sort of prepare for that right soj
is going to come this week maybe
tomorrow what am I going to tell him new
that's different from last week because
he didn't forget so after a while I
realized that the best response to that
was hey let's go get
coffee uh why don't we go get coffee
because that's what I will explain you
what's new and of course then was never
what's new came up and then you would go
with him where you go to not so great uh
Starbucks minus minus uh in in the in
the building 32 or somewhere else he
would sort of carefully tell them give
me macchiato and macchiato is made this
way literally like that recipe uh so
that was always uh amusing and uh
great
um I'm sure you remember uh the pen that
sanjoy always carried around with him
very quintessential scholar in my mind
um so I'll tell one story around that I
think this was 2006 2007 just around the
time when we had started I think Greg
teaching graphical models so thinking
about uh I was telling him this is what
you're thinking part of that is
variational characterization and all
that he says oh that's uh Gibbs
variational or Gibbs maximal and Georgie
and all that came up and I said hm
because I knew certain way of thinking
about it and then he caught the H in my
face without me saying so next day late
morning I roll in and then I see on my
desk this
beautiful uh A4 likely Rachel you might
have come and dropped it uh in his
beautiful handwriting one and a half or
even one and less than that page note of
just a simple proof Jensen's inequality
uh that stuck with me uh and it was
correct and it was precise um was always
excited about talk about everything so
this was 2012 when I just got back from
my sabatical at Stanford and um I was
thinking about doing uh um engaging into
the uh commercial world uh think about
sort of starting a company and then I I
was telling him this is what happened I
really enjoyed my time at Netflix but
this is what I think it's oh great why
don't you prepare a pitch for me and
give it to me as if I'm a VC I said are
you sure he said yes so then a week
later to that me
now but so he listens to it carefully at
the end he says I think you need to work
harder so there was that and what was
very useful uh uh goes without saying
any seminar is interesting happening
whether it's by chomsky's yet another on
uh you know he had a sequence of those
things or whether it's yet another young
kid coming and giving talk about some
interesting math problem he would always
show up and take you
around uh one thing that always remind
Ed me in addition to his watch is that
he was interested in things which were
always Timeless right he always asked a
question that uh so what's the abstract
meaning of this what is the essence of
it uh he lowed as some of you pointed
out that the principle of
uh the separation it's the right way of
thinking about it's very important to
know abstractly what's happening and
behind that I always found that his view
was that look we academics we educators
are guardians of uh important knowledge
that needs to be passed on to next
Generation rather than we owning it and
sometimes you know we do get personal
and I thought his non-personal take on
that was just beautiful and clean and uh
just uh something to Aspire
to and finally
um um you know he uh when Adriana passed
away uh just around that time I don't
remember exactly when but few days
later uh I was driving him from either
funeral home or something and then he he
he made this comment which I thought was
uh pretty remarkable simple but
remarkable is that you know people do
wonderful things you value them when
they are around there's a hole that they
leave and you don't know how big a hole
that is till they're gone so on that
[Applause]
uh hello everyone my name is Yuri pansy
I'm a faculty at Le I work on
information Theory I do I'll try to be
brief so we have more time for you know
mo and Greg to say more things I have
never been to building 35 I did not
benefit from that magnificent grant that
Lids you know was getting in the time of
sanjy right so I I never can share my
sort of stories from that but I wanted
to take you back to uh an important day
in my life which was May 4th 2006 so
this was the end of my first year uh in
grad school and uh I I I was an
undergrad uh majoring in physics and I
did uh a master's project in system
identification so I decided to switch to
electrical engineering but I was
completely clueless like I did not know
who Shannon is I did not understand
anything about digital communication and
all our seminars were constantly you
know myo block fading you know error
exponents
you know network capacity power control
I didn't understand a single word of it
so I thought okay this is probably a
mistake I should just go back home you
know back to Russia and just have an
industry job but then you know this was
the end of the first year when you in
Princeton you have to do all the uh
classes and so on and then it's time for
you to you know choose adviser and
choose a topic you know so I was in this
turbulent moment where you know I wasn't
sure what I want to work on and so um
this was I I should tell you that this
was a couple of years after you know um
sahai taond and sorry sahai meter and
Tonda meter happened so everybody was
thinking about control and communication
so uh my advisor Sergio Verdu and Vince
poor were also very interested in this
so they kind of encouraged me to go to
this talk um so the talk was uh titled
information and entropy flow in
filtering and path estimation this was
uh sanjoy talk of course and um I should
say I sat in the talk just like the
usual I understood 0% of it it was it
was even harder than you know iCal talk
because here there was not even
beautiful pictures right of radios you
know and and radio waves so there was
absolutely pure math you know and but
the last two sentences of the abstract
stood with me and so let me just read
them We examined the structure of
interaction between sensing
communication communicating and
controlling in the context of
statistical filtering for signals
described as hidden Mark of processes
and in the context of stabilization of
an unstable control system where the
sensor and controller are linked where
via a noisy Communication channel we we
argue amongst other things that a
fundamental reexamination of information
theory is needed to address these
questions these ideas appear to have
nontrivial connections to recent work in
non-e equilibrium statistical mechanics
okay so I should tell you that again I
do not know what information theory is
but here's the you know a sage of MIT
right coming and telling me that
information theory is something that
needs to be Revisited A and B he's
telling me this has connection to
non-equilibrium statistical mechanics
I'm a physicist right I understand that
stuff so I say okay finally that's a
field where I can be helpful right so um
so that's you know sort of the rest is
history I went to do PhD in in
information Theory I also should say I
quickly learned that you know knowing
what entropy is in the physics uh World
actually is detrimental for being an
information theorist and detrimental for
your sanity as well so I quickly decided
to forget about that uh so then 5 years
later I came here for uh Muriel Mard
invited me for um a small talk for her
group and this was like the time when I
was supposed to be you know on a job
market so there was nobody no faculty
showed up except her and um and at the
very end there was you know sanra meer
who uh I think walked in halfway through
the talk and you know so I gave my talk
and students were very interested you
know we chatted with Muriel and so on
sanre never said a single word but you
know the next day I received his 11w
email which I want to quote to you um
because I also emailed him and I said I
saw you in my talk you know maybe we
should should meet and said he responded
with 11 words we will have to meet
another time I enjoyed your talk period
right so this actually you know again
this made a big impact on my life
because at that time I think I I applied
to grad to to faculty positions but I
also got a job offer from Bell laabs and
I was actually thinking about taking it
because I thought okay there's no point
you know the job market is so tough so
but this kind of encouraged me to um to
to stay so when I became a faculty in
leads uh I think in the first couple of
months I asked Sano if I can meet him
and I received another 11l email um from
him after our conversation he said by
the way you can talk you can walk into
my office anytime period again he was a
very friendly guy right we could always
um you could always come and talk to him
um what I think is something maybe not
everybody especially younger students
maybe don't realize that he was also
very quick to you know quip some kind of
fun joke uh so I remember this was again
maybe
2012 or 13 I was very interested in
combinatorics and with my friend Marco
Dalai we noticed that you know the
famous loas uh tetaun so l l loas is of
course the pillar of combinatorics right
he made his name uh uh by when he was
very young he proved the conjecture of
capacity of the Pentagon and there he
introduced Teta function and with Marco
we noticed that actually that was
already contained in Bob Gallagher's
work so if if you put together a paper
of Bob Gallagher and Fred gelin paper
they together already proved capacity of
the Pentagon so we were super excited
that that moment I told this to sanjoy
in the hallway and I said sanjo can you
believe it like all of this stuff that
you know this was actually in Bob
Gallagher's you know this is our
information theorist and at this time
Bob Gallagher was passing by and Bob
Gallagher said so what are you talking
about and sanre looked at me and said he
will make you
famous I I still remember that joke know
but um in any case
so yeah I wanted to finish by saying
that you know I still read that uh so I
I read that that that paper and that you
know my notes from sanjoy talk many
times I think I made it to about 50%
understanding but I hope to catch up in
the in the remaining sort of time in my
career thank you
[Music]
my name is Mo win uh I don't know sanjoy
as long as uh many of you is in this
room uh but the years that I know him it
was the quality they were the quality
years so you know a little bit like his
thinking you he push us to focus on the
quality and not the quantity so I'm
going to try to show you some uh
pictures with uh less words uh just to
show you the last uh several years that
we are
together oh here I found so we I call
these bonus days uh
sanjoy uh get together with us with
Peter Karen and my wife snow a few times
a year uh this is probably about 10
years
old and uh but these are what I call
bonus Day always in
fashion um you know a lot of people talk
about sanjoy being so subtle and he
doesn't tell you what you have to go and
figure out I felt a little different cuz
he was pretty direct to me he says you
know you need to shop at better place I
will tell
you he said I'll tell you a place in
Florence where you can buy a suit okay I
said professori you know you're a
professor with Deep Pockets and you know
I'm just starting out here so anyway so
I remember sanjoy commenting uh about my
uh suits and uh he told me a few places
to to shop in fact this morning uh I
asked my wife you know just to think of
sanjo I'm going to wear a linen suit
today because this is typically how I
see sanjo but you you know you tell me
which color I should pick and she said
you know wear this color and somehow it
sort of coordinated with him it was just
by by
chance um so we had uh some parties
together to sanjoy organized together
with my colleagues a lot of Italians
sanjy knows my colleagues and he
organize a party and it was interesting
party where you're required not to bring
any present but there's a raffle and
then you know everyone who come to the
party have a raffle so I'll say a few
names so over there uh here anjoy this
is Andrea jetti from University of
bolognia Andrea Conti from University of
Ferrara Alberto Rakin who is a European
Commission Now Greg Mitchell work in
Washington DC George Chrissy goes at
Qualcomm so sanjoy and Greg connected uh
quite well and it's interesting because
you know it takes you go and talk to
sanjo everybody mentioned already how
you go away with sort of feel like you
understand but you don't understand uh
but that was I think sanjoy DNA but Greg
was different he works in Washington and
I think he's trained to tell you a story
at the end of the story it has zero
entropy and but the two of them talk and
you know they can Converse uh and that
was something I remember from that party
and here's a party where sanro is
drawing a raffle and he's supposed to
get something so you know everybody uh
wear a uh everybody pick
a a ticket and they find out what's in
there and this is a picture of West
Harris Sandra and this is Marco
keani uh snow my wife Andrea conti and
this is my my
sister-in-law um and and uh at the party
I'll show you a couple more so that that
was just you
know need a little luck and a lot of
love and then you know you get the
winner so the party was planned in a way
that the
winners get little present and and
sanjoy had uh uh a tie here and West
also have a different color of ties and
so on and that was just a quite uh
memorable uh time for me and then
finally I wanted to talk about sanro
he's a center of gravity he attracted
many many colleagues who became my
collaborator and you know he would go on
the board and he explained to me so this
is the time where France laat from
University of uh uh wean Austria was
visiting a signal processing person and
that sanjo and he had a a talk and I was
there so I clicked the picture just so
that I can
remember uh so many people that come
around me end up uh close uh friends
with sanjoy and talk to them partly
because I think uh sanjoy is a very good
speaking Italian and my Italian
collaborator said he speak better
Italian than us
uh so this is another bonus day where we
had a party for Peter uh with a lot of
family and you can see everybody and the
center of attention was here and he is
sanjoy you know singing happy birthday
for Peter but I think attention was
really there and uh so I'm going to move
on so you know people talk about Royal
East and uh Mandarin uh restaurant but
with me was like some reason it's a
legal seafood we always get upgraded I
think from you know Mandarin to Legal
Seafood and sometimes we go to happy
hour oysters and uh I couldn't find the
pictures you know these days it's very
hard to search so I couldn't find as I
was trying to find sanjoy with a dozen
oysters that Peter would remember uh so
this is at legals sanjoy Marco keani
West Harris Peter f Andrea Cony and
myself this is probably about uh 78
years old photo so we have days like
that throughout the year and of course a
lot of technical interaction too which
I'm not going to mention uh there was
another time that I sort of St away I
thought that was interesting picture and
I wanted to save it and this was one of
the LDS event I forgot what event was
and some
reason Peter and Jose kind of get down
to business get a piece of paper and
they arriving in the middle of the party
sanjoy said you know I want to be a part
of
it that was it and I thought it was just
kind of a moment that I want to capture
so I I clicked that and I found this
uh so now you know I want to talk a
little bit about Cambridge tea party so
we had covid and after the co you know
we were all locked down and so on
everybody so re tired and then he wanted
to be a little rebellious so like a
Boston Tea Party there's a Cambridge tea
party and the Tea Party uh at uh Peter's
place and sanjoy came and we were very
happy to be out of it but notice that we
were sitting not so close to each other
it's just right after Co and and I
wanted to show you a few pictures uh um
of sanjoy uh before and after covid uh
so this is one night that I remember I
call him napolita KN because we have
someone from Naples um Stefano Morana
was visiting me and uh Rea was there and
uh you know we were having a meal at
home it's it's I think it was February
it's still cold outside so we couldn't
sit
outside
um uh there uh there's this beautiful
picture I thought uh this was sort of
like you know in the second half of the
dinner um we talk a lot about you know
southern Italy mainly sanjoy and uh
recers talking about they both have been
there many many times they talk about
you know you can go to I think it's a
place called santagar and you can go to
the rich and you can see the two coast
of saleno and Naples and you know you
should really go there and you know you
should go find this little village
called narano and the you know pasta
there is really nothing like it you know
that kind of discussion that we have and
then you know the night goes on is is is
not a time yet for the last drop and uh
not a time yet to move on so it started
to talk about songs and turned out that
uh stano plays a little bit of guitar
and he was trying to teach me so I
wanted to show you uh a picture and
there's a little video you can start
like 20 second or so Stefano was playing
a napolitan song songs many but I just
only have a clip because I don't want to
take the whole
[Music]
afternoon so I kind of think of it as
night you will see sanjy and rea
[Music]
this is something I think about
often I'm like
[Music]
this
oh um so this is like Peter is saying
you know this is just
time to move
move um and I'll show you a few other uh
summer time we have a lot of good times
outside uh you know mostly around meal
and mostly around Rich conversation I'm
just not going to do to spend a lot just
just clicking through so give time for
Greg to talk uh um and um so I want to
talk a little bit about this picture
sanjoy was uh looking to move he was
dragging his feet uh he didn't wanted to
really move away from MIT I think he MIT
is so so much a part of him talking to
students and so
on and uh there was two option that that
uh of where he would stay and you know
and so I said you know I'm going to be
in uh London and I'll go check it out so
we went to EBY Road this is where Rea
lives and go check out sanj's place that
he was going to go anyway to fast
forward he moved there but he always
said let's have a zoom call where's your
student is he making progress let's have
some Zoom so we would have several Zoom
call over there and I asked him sanjo
how's the food did you like it well it's
adequate it's Ed they play piano for me
whenever the dinner time but the food is
just adequate but it's giv me nutrition
so I'm surviving so I said okay so do
you like it there he said like well you
know I like it there but they all are
old
people I said okay let's have a zoom
call so we have a zoom call and you know
we have a uh we had uh written a few
papers with sanjoy in his uh Golden
Years um which basically following again
the connection between Communications
control imperfect feedback limited
capacity that type of stuff uh and this
was
the last photo that I took with
him and uh San was again subtle but you
know he sort
of somehow get me a message that he
needed some
selos during Co
so I usually go to Costco every other uh
month whenever they have a sale I'll get
him a box and so on so this time he came
back and his house was empty and he
needed some so I went over
there and drop him a
box and that's a photo
I want to close with the slide sanjoy
sent me an email sometimes ago I I have
a date here I didn't remember now with
this
line but he said you know you got to be
careful reading this you got to be
careful reading this he said they forgot
to tell you
that the following
proposition so I wanted to stop here
basically he's saying that you know you
got to live forward but you got to look
back and make the best out of your past
experience so here it is and one last
thing before I get off the stage is that
sanro would ask you questions when you
go to his his his uh office uh and you
know he expect some answer and if you
don't answer he don't ask you again he
look at you but he look through as if
he's looking to the infinity through you
right and it's very
uncomfortable and so you have to come up
with the question very quick otherwise
he look at you through you to the
infinity and this is a little bit that
remind me a little bit of that uh
looking to the Infinity of
sanjy uh so we will miss him
[Applause]
all right uh hello everyone I'm Greg
warell um delighted to be here and to
help celebrate San joo's life um uh it
was just a an hour or so ago that uh
Leong suggested that maybe I could make
a few words so I haven't prepared a lot
but uh I've just collected a little bit
of my thoughts and I'll try to keep this
pretty
short um there's a there's a quote um
attributed to Frank Lloyd Wright when
someone observed that he had five grand
pianos um that said if you take care of
the luxuries the Necessities take care
of themselves and I struggled to
understand that um based on the way I
grew up but in some ways sanjo helped me
understand
that um there's a later quote by uh
Louie KH that goes great art is not the
fulfilling of a desire but the making of
a new desire so the world never needed
Beethoven's Fifth Symphony until he
created it um now we couldn't live
without
it and uh I feel
like that was the spirit that that
sanjoy had in him he understood the
connection between Art and Science and
engineering and about creating something
beautiful um you know he carried that
into the way he interacted with people
and the research uh
agenda and the way he ran Lids you know
when I arrived in uh 1985 uh he was the
head of Lids along with Bob and they
created an extraordinary culture there
as as people have commented on he he
brought some remarkable funding to
campus that it it's it wasn't the size
of it that was important important it
was the quality of it it's I've been
unmatched in its quality and it enabled
a whole generation of students to pursue
really beautiful basic research and it
created a whole community of colleagues
for me at that time that exists to this
day and I'm grateful for that um and
like many of you he he made many trips
just stopping by the office and asking
me the same questions he asked you and I
I appreciate that now even more than I
did at the time um you know and and he
he would always kind of make these very
insightful comments you know he he would
often talk about computer vision as a
field and the way they sort of set up
the foundations of the field you know
that there are these problems and they
had this notion that there are a set of
broad problems not narrow problems broad
problems that the field should solve and
he felt like every Community should have
this notion of a these are our problems
you know um and and more generally I'd
say what I appreciate about sanjy is he
had this kind of quiet confidence I
always felt like he had nothing to prove
to anybody never sought the Limelight he
just wanted to build community and he
was an exceptionally kind
individual um at the end of the day I
think he understood that research was
really about people and uh you know when
when he passed away Mitch trod andos
lapido and I we were all colleagues at
the same Junior colleagues at the same
time we swapped a bunch of email and
what what Mitch wrote was that's very
sad news not only did he help me a great
deal early in my career but he was a
really really nice guy um so in
conclusion I'll always remember sanjoy
as um sure he was stoic subtle if I I
think what it is is he he never his
highs were never super high and his lows
were never super low he was just he he
was he was a man of subtlety and what I
always remember of think of him as
always pointing towards the light and
encouraging us to go there and I hope
his spirit continues to guide us thank
[Applause]
you thank you so much for the beautiful
remembrances uh we'll start the next
session in four minutes after um a very
short break and uh the next session
we'll have uh Nicola Elia Jeff shama
leier and BJ chandre to talk about
sanj's influence on them as a mentor so
and then after that we'll have a coffee
break
close down good that be
checked all right let me just check the
check the
settings audio settings just to make
sure it should still remain
should I
sorry
[Music]
m
I'm not
[Music]
whichever you
want okay okay then
[Music]
okay let's get
started okay welcome back everyone uh
for this final panel of the day uh the
theme being uh sanjoy as a mentor um
Jeff shamama with the University of
Illinois at Urbana champagne uh today we
have uh or for this panel we have VJ
shandrew Indian Institute of science
nicoa Elia at the University of
Minnesota and lei at Harvard University
and so please we'll start with uh
VJ thank you uh could you just load up
uh my slides please thank
you
so um so I uh
actually uh came to MIT in
1977 uh to be a PhD student at the O
Center and um uh my first exposure to
sanjoy was actually a a bit scary
because um you know we were I think 11
PhD students who had come in and uh I
think uh we considered Deb sarar to be
one of the bright brightest and uh and
Deb had actually gone to see
sanjoy and you know Deb had come from
Case Western so so you know he knew
sano's reputation from there and and he
went in to see sanjoy and uh so sanjo
asked him probably in Bengali you know
do you want to work on Theory or or
applications and Deb said applications
and he was sh on the door right so so
you know that was uh that was my uh the
first exposure but you know I was
definitely oriented towards
combinatorial optimization so so I
didn't have to go through that but I um
so went on to learn from Tom and uh
who's here and of course from sanjoy as
well uh and uh but Lakers and uh you
know there were lots of great uh of
course Jerry Shapiro was my PhD advisor
so lots of people in discreet comori
optimization so um so and then of course
I there was a long break and I started
interacting with sanjo Moore in the '90s
uh mostly in India I taught at Purdue
for 10 years from 82 to 92 and then went
back and uh started meeting sanjoy more
when I was in India and uh and then uh
spent a little time visiting Lids uh you
know in from 2003 onwards but uh
um part of what I was working on in the
late 80s and then in the '90s was on
embeding uh uh theorem proving in
optimization and uh this was a program
of research that had been initiated by
Bob
juslo uh and uh a few of us sort of
followed him on that uh unfortunately
Bob passed away very
prematurely and so John hooker at Kani
melon and I sort of picked up the thread
and we continued the work uh and it
resulted in a in a
monograph and uh right towards the end
of that project which took about 10
years um I was at lids with uh with
Vivic borker and uh we were chatting
with uh with sanjoy and uh and uh there
was a a problem that was still remaining
and a chapter of the book that needed to
be written which was uh could you
actually embed first out a logic a full
predicate logic in uh in an
optimization problem and then what would
be the insights you could draw from that
and uh so that led to uh collaboration
and uh and the paper that you see there
uh which eventually also became a
chapter of the book so so that was uh a
very exciting uh sort of technical
collaboration that I had
uh with sanjoy and and VI um and um soon
after that I think uh there was a
conference in kin in India that uh that
sanjo had come for and that a bunch of
us uh were also at uh I think there was
uh if I recall Ravi mazunda I think uh
Balaji praka lots of uh lots of people
uh whom of course sanjo knew well and um
and we had a long conversation about
biology and uh and uh whether physics
would really solve the problems of
biology or did you really need computer
science uh because of the complexity
involved in biological systems and uh
and and I think I was convinced that we
needed computer computer science and uh
sort of data science uh in a in a strong
way and uh and actually uh took a pivot
in my career and I just uh started
working on this and eventually built a
company uh which was uh India's first
sort of uh life science informatics
companies uh it was called Strand
genomics and uh and sanjoy uh George and
several other uh faculty friends
actually supported us uh as we got the
company going and um you know and it's
been a a phenomenal journey and um and I
think uh um it's um uh so for the
question to me from sanjoy was not
what's new but what's new with strand
right so so I'd keep coming back and
every time the question would be what's
new with Strand and um you know I think
he would be happy to see where the
company has gone today it's uh it's a
600 employee company it's uh it's
actually India's leading uh Precision
medicine company so um uh just to uh uh
tell you a little bit uh about uh you
know his association with the Indian
Institute of science he was there almost
almost every year uh you know the month
of January we could expect uh sanjo to
to come around and uh there are a whole
bunch of uh faculty who were associated
with the Indian Institute of science who
in One Way or Another worked closely
with
Sano and um um and I think uh in
particular uh Professor narahari who um
uh ran the game tary lab and was a
colleague of mine in computer science
and
automation actually uh learned a lot
from sanjoy and uh and you know the this
other aspect of sanjoy about uh
institution building leadership I think
uh you know narahari really sort of
imbued that and went on to be the dean
of WCS at uh at the Indian Institute of
Science and actually uh did remarkably
well I think he's really sort of built
that into India's leading sort of WCS
group um and um so I have two more
slides which are like messages from
narahari and another institution Builder
called spenta vardia whom uh you know
sanj worked with um I'll leave it to you
on whether those should be played now or
later it's okay if you don't mind I'll
take a couple of minutes and just play
those this is n
and um there you
go hello uh I am narahari from the
Department of computer science and
automation uh Indian Institute of
science um Professor
mitter was an
unforgettable Mentor for me since
1991 in
1991 as a young assistant professor at
Ias
I approached him to host me at Lids MIT
for a year as a part of the Indo us
Science and Technology Fellowship he
readily agreed and uh in 1992 I spent
almost a year at LS MIT and it was such
an enriching
experience among several courses that uh
uh I was able to do during that Sprint
uh uh there was this Visionary course
that was offered by Professor Sanji
mitter um in collaboration with
Professor Shankar shastri uh this course
was called intelligent uh control and it
opened the doors uh for so many future
research
areas I think ever since
1992 Mentor for me and uh I have had the
pleasure and privilege of Hosting him uh
at CSA
IC uh on the occasion of many multiple
visits by him and during those visits he
also gave uh lovely talks I think in his
passing we have really lost a Doan and a
legend of uh systems signal processing
and uh control theory for me personally
uh I would consider this uh as a very
deep loss and uh
uh it is very difficult to forget the
kind of mentorship that Professor sanjja
M has provided to me during the past uh
three three and a half
decades so those beautiful flame of the
forest uh you know flowers and and the
Indian Institute of science Tower are
sort of iconic um for those of you who
have haven't visited the campus please
do it's a 400 Acres of you know wooded
and wonderful Gardens so
um now spenta varia um is a string
theorist uh and he was building this
brand new
institution uh called The International
Center for theoretical Sciences in
Bangalore and again I think sanjoy was
uh an advisor and a mentor uh and here's
Penta Sanjay was deeply interested in
the development of scientific
institutions in India and he visited the
International Center for theoretical
Sciences of tifr in Bangalore regularly
for almost a decade as a faculty
associate during each visit he would
focus on a specific area like
Neuroscience nonlinear filtering and
data assimilation Network science
Etc I still remember a small conference
he had organized in
2012 in which he lectured on John Fon
Norman's ideas on the architecture of
the
brain his vision of the unity of Applied
Mathematics probability stochastic
analysis and computer science influenced
the areas to grow at icts and its
initial faculty hiring that included
people like Amita
Vishal Vasan and saram ambas Saran these
teams continue to grow strongly at
icts Sanjay was a deep researcher a
gentle and kind individual who
contributed greatly to icds and his
faculty he will be greatly
missed yes um he will be greatly missed
I think he was almost a family member I
think uh uh so for both my wife
and me and um and also our daughter Maya
who was in mi undergrad and so he's uh
you know we will miss him but uh I think
we'll also have very fond memories of uh
of his great contributions thank
[Applause]
you it's uh the last session and a lot
of things good things have been said
about s Joy it's difficult not to repeat
several of the good adjectives for S Joy
but I'll try to put this uh this little
talk in a in a very personal
context um contrary to many of you which
met s Joy after being get got into
graduate school or doing PhD or postdoc
and so on I was an engineer at Fiat in
Italy and I wanted to just take one year
to learn about control and I didn't know
I was going to meet and Joy or I didn't
know anything about
him and uh
sorry and
uh and so I didn't know who he was to
such a giant of the field right and uh
and uh I was very naive and and this is
the the story that took me about meting
him the first time and I apologize for
certain parts that could be uh a little
bit naive or or or Politically Incorrect
at this
time so I needed some money to go at M
and I needed a signature from Professor
mitter about the fellowship in Italy and
so I call leads and they they say oh
Professor mitter is not here Professor
but I'm calling from Italy keep in mind
this is
89 there is no there is no cell phone
there is no credit card there is no uh
email and uh and so I said
okay but but you're lucky I keep calling
leads and they say hey you're lucky
Professor MIT is in Italy I said oh I'm
Italian so I I'm going to I'm going to
get him give me the phone so so give me
Adriana's phone in Florence personal
phone well house phone
and
uh so I start calling from every place
because the deadline for presenting the
the the fellowship you know the the form
for the fellowship was coming up and I
call Adriana I call Adriana they never
answer and so I said oh what's up what's
up we are in crisis and so I called the
school the school of normal
pizza and they say well what about
Professor met is there well he he really
here said so what is it he not in us he
not in in
Italy
uh so I said but at some point I call is
the day before the deadline is due at
this point I cannot send the stuff by
mail there is no FedEx or anything I
have to drop it by hand and I live in
Turin and I need to go to Rome to give
this thing and so they say oh Professor
m is coming here for a
defense
uh tomorrow at 9: so I take best friend
of mine we take a car leave at 3:00 in
the morning and travel
until 7 7:30 in the morning 8 to be
early to schola normal and sit there on
the steps waiting for this professor
Metter who the hell is
it and uh and
so so as around nine he shows up with a
group of students around him and and and
I have never met him I never met and a
person from India anyway um and so he
says so I say oh Professor Metter a
little bit kind of you know Italian ways
he speak this this discussion is in
Italian but I translated in English so
Professor M where have you been I've
been looking for you all over the
place
po I was at the
beach then I didn't know what to say I
felt like
I came out this thing came out from out
of my mind and again I apologize and I
said oh that's why you're are so
tan imagine this
discussion
so okay that's not a very good
introduction of
course but that's not all I get the
signature finally meet the professor
very you know I get him very very very
good going I get the signature and I
leave immediately almost immediately to
Rome because I need to deliver this the
the form to the to the Rome
University and
uh so I called my girlfriend which used
to you know be my wife and I say in the
boot phone boot get the cards and so on
uh call her everything all I got I got
the signature I'm going to Rome I'll see
you
soon after after half away from from
from from Pizza to
Rome I discover I find out I don't have
my wallet on me my driver license with
$1,000 worth of money that I took in
case of any inconvenience or so and so I
had a a very Pro I say what is possible
the only possibility is that I left the
wallet in the in the phone
Boot and so I had a very big question
now I said do I continue without driving
license and go to Rome or I go back back
I call I go back we decided to go back
and and the SEC and then the secretary
the students found this wallet with
$1,000 in it at the time equivalent
money they gave it to the secretaries
the secretary gave it to San Joy M say
listen this guy lost
$1,000 and and and uh and and uh and
then when I went back the secretaries
were all happy they came back and S Jo
was there he didn't say
anything but but uh uh but he had this
mark on his face right and then I
learned to recognize in the future right
and and and a sparkle in his eyes and
and I say I'm sorry I'm sorry thank you
I left to go went to Rome and gave this
thing 10 minutes before the
deadline
uh
yes
no I didn't get the fellowship and and
and and I thought I destroy my
relationship with this guy I mean
that's but but uh but in reality he
became my my guardian angel from there
own he felt I think he felt this guy
needs a lot serious
supervision and and and he gave me into
the hands when I got to MIT to the to
the capable ends of muner I was a
student eventually I became a PhD
student student and I
graduated and that's then officially
sanjoy was always behind the scene as
everybody has said in this in this
conference but after my PhD I I I
started a postdoc and this time I was
postdoc with s Joy
M and during the years we staying with
the other students I would I would
experience some of the lectures that
andjoy M would give on on quantum theory
quantum physics or or or or or what's or
um statistical mechanics and of course
we were having these lectures in a very
small room on building 35 and of and of
course everybody was lost but then then
there is a there is a question that
comes right I need to ask a good
question I need to ask a good question
it's kind of sort of panic that you have
when you are now in the presence of of S
Joy right when whenever is is is asking
you question you have to have a good
answer somebody was repeating saying
before and so and so when when Ali asked
me to to to to to say something about
influence as a mentor I said I need to
say something deep for some
joy and and
uh then I remember these stories right
that you have to say something it felt
like you have to impress him you have to
at least I did impress him say something
smart say something good
and to my surprise when I start working
with him the reaction that I got is that
almost not almost everything I said
discussion but he will conclude his his
his his his story this meeting saying
that's interesting let's talk some more
about this and that gave me a tremendous
confidence because I said is Joy likes
it I don't care about anything else I
think it's good and gave me a lot of
confidence in trying to think like he
does or mimicking little mimicking of
what he did in trying to be more open
more more embracing of different way of
approaching a problem and most of it uh
learn to ask the good questions and
those has driven me for all these years
and of course andjoy has been always
part of of my life since then my kids
are here because is because of s joy and
and and and was been always being in
contact and asking how the family and
how the theory and what's going on so
I'll thank you s jooy I don't know if I
if I made a deep point but the fact that
you
were encouraging me with this let's talk
more this is
interesting I find that there has been
very empowering for me the fact that you
like the stuff I was thinking and so I
conclude here thank you
[Applause]
this feels like a gathering of a very
important
tribe who all of us are fortunate to
call San Joy our intellectual and
spiritual leader
um a lot have been said throughout the
day about all facets of of San Joy being
a great scholar a mentor a
teacher um I I could hardly do anything
better than that um perhaps I
thought um I could just talk a little
bit about a particular problem that has
been largely inspired by S joy and
perhaps to a small degree uh
contextualize a lot of things that
everybody has talked about so my
association with s Joy U started during
his Golden Years uh from
2018 uh onwards um starting out as a
lead um visiting scholar and later on
carried on through many long walks
across the Charles River and late night
phone
calls um and many thing that we talked
about have already been talked about
here Jose mentioned about his
fascination with
AI um Aria mentioned about her his
earlier association with the field of of
Power Systems and almost everybody
talked about his deep commitment of
abstraction and seeing through the
things the connection between seemingly
diverse
Fields um this is sort of a largely
inspired by by by this by these
qualities that San Joy uh passed on to
us so I'm going to talk about um
something started out by really you know
from Rachel's email so Rachel has been
always the reliable messenger every time
you know s Joy had something to deliver
he would say Rachel send this to to and
and this is one of the lecture notes I
got from Rachel it's about architectural
thing I think architecture is something
s Joo is deeply deeply U interested in
and this is his quote is the
organization of distributed algorithms
in hardware and software for performing
complex heterogeneous functions um I
think throughout the years has been
always been um having a this deep quest
of of what is the underlying
architecture of complex systems and
architecture is is enabling uh
conceptual underpinning of a lot of
success on the technological sense like
the success of the internet or perhaps
more recently the proliferation of
decentralized trust and cryptocurrencies
right um we did a little bit of attempt
I was fortunate to be co-authoring a
couple papers during those golden years
of St Joyce times um one of them was
sort of attempt to think about what
exactly should be the architecture
moving forward for the sort of a new
Energy Power Systems um I don't declare
success but this is sort of just an
attempt but at the he at High of it it
it's the the top layer the top layer
that many of you mentioned about Sano
being a humanist I think the top layer
was largely instilled by him saying that
a lot of these complex systems evolves
not only on technological reasons but
also on societal choices we as a humans
we decided to choose to combat the
climate change it was not a
technological reason but it was a
societal choice so how does that affect
then the evolution of complex
Engineering
Systems um
so we kind of wrote A Few papers
together in the 2021 time we were
thinking about this whole vehicle being
electrified is going to give a lot of
trouble to the power grid um then later
on more recent years the proliferation
of computing and Ai and cryptocurrency
has ADD on a lot more energy to the grid
and that becomes even more challenged
though we wrote some articles about why
the Grid or perhaps more broadly
speaking why infrastru structure matter
in these whole climate change
discussions and this is sort of a very
new paper about that and
uh but the it really was started from
from San Joy just keep asking me what is
the architecture of power system what is
the architecture of Power
Systems and uh um I think this is sort
of a an area where this particular tribe
actually will have a lot to do and a lot
to contribute to I just give you one
data point um you know everybody here
knows a lot more electricity will be
consumed in the US in particular in in
the context of electrifying the cars and
trucks and also all the Computing
demands but I really was took kind of a
bit of a surprise to see that um if you
think about electrifying Americans cars
and trucks that's a lot of electricity
but there even more electricity on on
thinking about the Computing um energy
demand and it's not even a one:1 ratio
it's more like a 1: five ratio so being
being a humanist being San joy as a
humanist he cares a lot about the the
human society's biggest challenges if
you ask around what are the biggest
societal challenges of human society I
think many of you would probably agree
with me that two of the biggest societal
challenges out there number one is how
do we combat climate change and number
two is how do we harness the potential
of AI little did we realize little did I
realize there's a common
bottleneck that common bottleneck is in
the manifestation of the electric grid
in the US is just not ready for
both there's a full stack research ahead
of us this tribe can make a lot of
impact on this particular uh full stack
research agenda all the way from new
materials to energy efficient Computing
to networks and Power Systems to you
know including climate models and and
and optimization and the past 15 years I
was living in Texas and just on my
backyard something was just happening
which was this uh cryptocurrency mining
So 20% of the worldwide Bitcoin mining
was was in the state of Texas so we were
sort of a ground zero on seeing some of
these challenges so we saw firsthand
about this tremendous amount of
electricity consumption happening in in
the in the crypto area and you know
largely you know San Joy thinking has
inspired us to think about what what can
we harness this Computing demand for the
for the use of of grid purposes um and
and this sort of something we have been
doing over the past few years about
thinking about what is the role of a
university in thinking about these
issues of blockchain and Computing and
the implication on energy and
environment I think a huge role for the
University Pro in in play to in
education research public perception and
policymaking um and uh you know I'll
just show you this just the scale of the
problem a little bit if if the video
comes
um this is a 700 megawatt uh Bitcoin
mining facility 50 minutes away from
where my house was and is the world's
largest Bitcoin mining facility and it's
um it's it's consuming as much of
electricity in this Cham seven Chambers
as as as the entire city of Cambridge
right so um and uh This was done just in
18 months it's just set up during the co
time and uh so so so I mean we're
talking about big scale changes on on
the electric grid big
scale and uh you know we then sort of
think about what can you actually do for
the grid and so there is something
interesting about you can harness them
for for flexibility purposes and so on
um but the the mindboggling part is that
you look at their financial reports they
ended up making more money in the energy
Market than they make money out of the
selling the Bitcoins
so uh again um just my modeling and uh
and then on the other hand there's also
a lot of watershed moments for for how
can we harness the latest and the
greatest AI for the energy system in
itself so it's energy for AI but also AI
for energy and that again is largely
inspired by by San Joy's um um remarks
to me about thinking about these
architectural issues and trying to
figure out the can do and cannot do of
the state of the AI for a particular
area that dear to my heart and uh um so
I think on both ends power to Ai and AI
to power there's a large role that
fundamental deep thinking architectural
thinking is going to make a very
important impact and and sanjoy keeps
inspiring us to to think about that
along those ways and and leading that
way of transition today is also a very
special day today is the mid- autumn day
so for all the Oriental culture this is
the day where we celebrate a lot this is
the day when the moon is the brightest
and the roundest and the
biggest so tonight when we watch the
moon maybe some of you were enjoying
some moon cakes I know that San Joy will
be looking down to us with a lot of
smile and love thank you
[Applause]
so for some closing thoughts on on the
panel I uh you know this was supposed to
be a non-technical symposium and it
largely has been but there's been an
underlying mathematical theme uh
throughout the day in that uh we've
talked about sanjoy uh as the uh the
mentor the the the adviser The Scholar
the humanist the specialist in coding
controls uh biology computation and and
so and everyone in the room and in
particular the panelists have been
talking about how these attributes were
projected onto their own experiences and
so sanjoy has us doing projection
theorem uh for the the whole Symposium
uh I have two projections to my own uh
experiences with sanoy that are more so
sanoy is a role model than the then
Mentor uh the first was uh when I was a
PhD student at Lids I was here in the
80s and I was working with Mike Athens
and sanjoy uh he was on my committee
this is unrelated to his being on my
committee he was very proud of Lids as a
leader and as a leading lab and always
felt that lid students if there's an
interesting emerging direction should be
on top of that at least be aware of
what's what's happening and on a couple
of occasions he organized a reading
group uh you know to get us uh up to
speed on this uh on this area whether or
not it was related to or could be of use
for our dissertation just for the sake
of of being on on top of the field and
for these reading groups rather than
just assign papers to students and have
them present it he would also take the
time to prepare lectures uh himself and
I Ed the term prepare with some
reservation but he would do that and one
of these topics was for example
algebraic methods in in control and
controller factorization and
parameterization and the like and in one
lecture he wanted to illustrate just how
this perspective could
simplify uh a lot of uh kind of in or
and and also in give new insights and
simplify uh various types of
calculations and manipulations and in
control systems and uh so the point was
that it was just simple algebraic
manipulation so he's giving the lecture
and he got tripped up in some of the
manipulations on the board and he said I
I I seem to have made an algebraic error
but but the point is it's just algebra
okay and then and that was the end uh
the second experience I had when I was
now a new graduate and uh postto and I
happened to be uh invited to give a talk
at eth and he happened to be I Now
understand that wasn't really a
coincidence he happened to be in Italy
uh but then he invited me uh you know to
uh to swing by and uh he was very
welcoming and still I was feeling
somewhat
uncomfortable just from the perspective
that that such a prominent individual
would be spent such hours with me as a
gracious host and having extensive
conversations and treating me to these
uh uh lunches and and and dinner at the
time and how he would someone who's not
my PhD adviser uh and someone with whom
I've never written a paper uh would uh
kind of just spend this time and give
that time to me as a as a new uh a new
PhD graduate from Lids and it was only
later in my career that I came to really
appreciate those two experiences of of
the time that he spent with us as uh
leading the reading group or the time he
spent with me uh as my as the host and
then giving me that that gracious
invitation and especially now that I and
probably everyone in this room kind of
just feels perpetually busy we're just
busy all the time and uh and at that
time in my innocence I had no idea of
just how much demands there must have
been on sanjoy time and just it was
invisible to me uh the way he was uh uh
interacting with us and and and hosting
us and and hosting me and uh so sanjoy
as his generosity especially for
students especially for junior people
set a very high standard and and even to
use the Expression finding time for us
is is wrong is just he made time uh for
us to make sure that we had those
interactions with him just for what for
the sake of intellectual curiosity and
for the sake of a a scholarly
environment and and culture and for this
I'll always be grateful so thank you all
for this uh day I think there's still
some things coming in in uh in the next
session but uh thank you all for it
[Applause]
today so we have a coffee break and
we're going to resume at 4: at 400 p.m.
it's the placeo be
thank
you e
un
what
e e
the e
think
than e
you e
un
than
for e
keep
see
[Music]
sh
this
I e
[Music]
you
it's
[Music]
is
for for
[Music]
is
I
[Music]
[Applause]
oh hi
Larry you're on mute
[Music]
than me oh okay you hear me
now do you hear me
now I guess I still music
hello I'm still muted I guess I don't
know how hi professor
ho yes we will we will have you zoom in
uh speak in a little
bit uh how about this can you hear me we
can hear you we can hear you we can hear
me okay
fine I was just talking to Dr
MMA hi Mar okay now we hear each other
yeah we can
he my volume down um so this is this the
segment where
[Music]
h
[Applause]
[Music]
in
is
[Music]
for
okay we're almost ready to start if
there's anybody in the other room if we
can have them come
in is everybody
in okay um so
this is the last session of uh of the
day uh we're going to have uh some
tribute videos uh uh from uh San joo's
uh admirers colleagues and friends and
then some written tributes that uh some
of us from the organizing committee will
read out loud after that we will have a
reception um at at uh at uh 5:00 p.m. so
um without further Ado I'd like to
welcome Professor Larry ho who should be
on
Zoom uh before we share some of the
video tributes Larry are you there yes
I'm here can you okay great thank you so
much we can see
you well
I'm in just celebr event to remember the
life of San M I'd like to add a little
tiet The History of contral Science and
Engineering in which say and I
participated and some of you may know
this some of you probably don't know but
may have heard about it everything
started in 1984 on beach
Yugoslavia and I was ATT Tedy C another
name activist in control some of you may
have met or at least know about Peter
kovic which his home country so after
the conference he invited me to enjoy
the beach to braic and with see other
Beach Chad and we thought that we were
both that born in the year
1934 little bit further exploring we
found another good friend Kon and also
said your
B well technically B was born in the end
of
1973 but that's we not going to be
bother about a few days differ anyway we
all point
the 12 mons period mostly in 1934 so we
decided to form a club 19 Club
34 they we should try to beat again in
1994 when we were all 70 years old and
uh he is a picture oh well actually I
didn't want to show this I want to show
the other picture I have uploaded too
yeah here
so we met in 1994 as some conference
that don't remember now but 2004 the
20th
anniversary it was the all child Affair
there was a meeting in Shanghai
Beijing and in the ancient capit of CN
all four of them were there I think it
was the robotic automation society and
cence so we took
it a joy picture uh next to the Statue
of uh scholar confusious so that was
2004 but then at that time with we are
all 70 years old and we don't know how
long we we can go out and uh I forgot
who suggested that we maybe too
optimistic to look forward to
2014 we all be 80 years old beyond the
last expectancy of so we better switch
to a 5year cycle to have a reunion
so after 2004 in
2009 at the retirement party of uh Peter
Co to and I think it's where Sor
retiring his from his L job we met and
he
the next photo you see with all four of
us yes right here I think it's at
the the retirement party of pet Peter
kovic but s also was retired that year
so we we all met
there
together and
then as we said yest we go to beat on
five years ago so after 2009
which was the 25th anniversary of the
club
34 we met in 2014 I think it's a Cy Zur
on the border of Switzerland Italy we
had a good
time then in 5e cycle we said next work
with
to9 and we hope everyone will be still
be around turns out we were all still
alive beond our life expectancy
and we had a private Affair T conference
so just four fam wife together uh in
Italy very beautiful region in the tuska
area uh we have sweet days they had
beautiful e and lot lots of good
time which finally that was a private
Affair in
2019 and uh s be the oldest M of CL C4
he was born in and of
C3 uh so naturally as the leader of all
of Club
34 as you said this the name Club 33 has
already been taken so we never called it
Club
3334 uh it was belong to a sub Club in
New York City
anyway s not being bing living in Great
Boston area we had more that two of us
we have jointly lunch every couple of Bs
together reminiscing about all times
really have a good time and
so uh at the risk of being
self-promotion
I if you're drink wine drinkers I would
say 1934 was a great year was a v year
uh we had four of us both started couple
of AG 196 61 and uh but stayed active
for all these years uh I also should
mention there a couple of honorary
members of Club 34 George James and uh
Eugene W and uh
marij who occasionally joined
us so I have actually more written
information on these events I'm talking
about but uh
and you can write to me if you want to
do the war so thank you very much for
this occasion
[Applause]
bye-bye oh I'm done okay thank you so
much and next we have uh sidartha M uh
who is going to say a few words I
believe on behalf of the family sidara
please go ahead thank you for joining us
thank you
thank you so much can you hear me yes
okay wonderful uh
I send you greetings from the family uh
you you heard from my father pronom
earlier this morning um I also want to
give you greetings on my behalf and on
that of my sister anelie anelie mitchard
Dua who lives in the Boston area but
wasn't able to be there this afternoon I
am in New New York City um and I
apologize for being a few minutes late I
am on Deadline I'm a journalist working
in the Arts um a mid-career shift that I
made uh 10 or 15 years ago and in which
my uncle sanjoy was extremely
supportive um bearing witness
to uh the way that my intellectual
curiosity
evolved away from an ear early Direction
in the social sciences and into
something uh that could have seemed
entirely new he
was Adept
at observing and understanding making
the connections and seeing how all these
things work together and how you can
think
about Society economy Civic practice
Civic possibility imagination life of
the mind uh through politics and
economics through science and philosophy
and indeed through the Arts in the end
of the day uh this pursuit of knowledge
and insight and Collective possibility
is like a uh kind of an Agora right a
public square into which we have all
these different roots to arrive and I
think that uh uh I heard I heard some of
the early part of the of the conference
this morning and and I can imagine the
the tonality of the rest of it I think
that you all know and have heard from
different perspectives how his mind um
welcomed and thrived on uh thinking
intellectually through all of these
directions and not in one and not in one
narrow field um
so uh he was very supportive in this
regard
um
his life at MIT and scientific life I I
have to say was a little bit of a black
box for some us some of us in the family
he kept it
um he kept he kept his compartments he
kept his
separations um but over the years uh we
became closer and closer uh and his
loyalty and support
and true intellectual curiosity were
absolutely never in question um I think
that uh I think somebody maybe earlier
this morning said something about a
Renaissance Prince or Renaissance Court
uh he he definitely was that
uh it comes from Kolkata it comes
from a a lot of deep roots that maybe
have been evoked today or that maybe
some of you will recognize in people in
your families and backgrounds of that
generation I hope that um we can
renew that impulse and continue
to uh and continue to uh to seed it in
younger Generations now especially given
the uh polarization and the fra ization
of discourse right now and what is
happening uh administratively and in the
in the conditions of fields and
universities um I I I I can tell you
with absolute certainty that he would
have been aast at what's happening in
universities in America in general right
now his politics were very clear he paid
very close attention he was absolutely
an anti-racist an anti-fascist and and
an internationalist
and I think that we should bear that in
mind as well uh and take uh
encouragement and uh fortitude uh from
that as we continue to fight these
fights forward in all of our respective
spheres so I'll leave you at that and I
want to thank you again uh for this very
generous occasion and for celebrating
his life in this
[Applause]
manner thank you so much uh we have uh
Dr Raman mea uh on uh on Zoom from
scientific
systems uh Ramen if you're there uh yes
I'm here okay thank you please go
ahead uh hello uh my name is Rahman Mara
um I'm the founder and CEO of scientific
systems and sanjoy M played a very
important role uh in in in our company
actually I met sanjoy in
1969 at one of the conferences The Joint
automatic control conference and became
familiar with his work on the conjugate
gradient method with the lden and Warren
and that inspired me
for part of my PhD thesis so in fact I
ended up taking the work and using it
and extending it for for part of my my
PhD thesis and then when I joined
Harvard in
1972 uh I interacted with sanjo quite
often uh and in 76 uh I started
scientific systems and sanjoy was a a
consultant to us as well as an investor
in our company uh and with sano's help
we did a lot of work in what is now the
was at that time was called the
automated analysis of electrocardiograms
and sanjoy and uh his student
adant and Don Guston were doing that
work very pioneering work now of course
it's EGS are are well automated but that
was a pioneering work which we did in in
scientific systems at that time uh
withon and
Adan and then also we heard earlier
about uh Tom dako who was a student of
sanjoy at Cas and worked in the electric
power area so sanjoy introduced me to
him also and in the 80s we did a lot of
projects together with the Electric
Power Research Institute and Tom was
definitely a a great person and and
sanjoy U kept introducing me to uh
really great people uh
throughout our interaction and which
lasted uh I would say till till covid
times uh my last interaction uh was with
um Alan Canon bomb who was introduced to
me by sanjoy I think about 10 years ago
and sanjoy told me that uh alen's work
on this area new area of optimal mass
transport was going to be real
revolutionary and he was absolutely
right uh so we all sort of collaborated
on some work wrote some proposals on it
and we continued working with Al tenant
bom who unfortunately also died last
year so I have wonderful memories of
sanjoy and Adriana we used to get
together for dinners at their house at
their department and they came to our
house in
Lexington uh he was a real intellectual
real warm person we really miss him very
badly
thanks thank you so much uh now we're
going to go to uh video tributes uh
starting from the video from UHA sano's
wife uh who is in London she sent a
video and then there are a few other
videos after that then we're going to
read some of the written tributes before
concluding so
I thank a mighty for asking me to say a
few words to this gathering in honor of
my late husband
shanj shanj and I remained friends since
our first meeting on the shows of the
Indian Ocean on August 6th
1945 a date that many will remember as
it was the day the bam bomb hit
Hiroshima 12 years ago we took our
marriage vows and continued our strong
friendship shanai was a person of utmost
integrity and above all caring for his
students
worldwide wherever he is I hope that he
has found students to teach
on behalf of all his family in London I
wish him
peace Om
Shanti Shanty
Shanty sanjy mitter he was a true
Renaissance person he started in the
control field but he had much much
broader interests he was knowledgeable
and understanding and it stretched
through mathematics Science and
Technology he had the rare Talent of
seeing the broad
picture and he had great generality in
seeing the picture and great Focus he
could switch from abstraction to Broad
connections a detailed understanding
with ease it was always a pleasure to
talk talked to sanjy about research
education and almost everything he
usually had very interesting and
different viewpoints from most other
people he had many friends and admirers
at
MIT he had friends and admirers
nationally and
internationally he had a distinguished
research career but I'm not going to
talk about that here other people can
talk about it uh I will talk about his
long-term leadership at Lids which I
think is what I know the most about uh
he joined the MIT faculty and he joined
the control lab which was then called
the electronic systems lab
ESL as an associate professor in
1970 he worked at Brown Bou Switzerland
and then Case Western before coming to
MIT so he was already recognized as a
CER in the field it was uh DSL in that
period was getting much more conceptual
and math oriented much less application
oriented this was necessary because of
both the complexity of
implementations and the implementation
of the technology that was used for the
implementations that was stroken like a
through true theoretician
superb Theory people Brocket Yan
Williams George zames alone with sanjy
met they were added to the ESL faculty
at that time this was called the Golden
Era of control and MIT was certainly a
leader at that time the connection of
control and
communication was clear by
1970 especially to sanjoy there was a
dependence on information also at that
time the communication at area era area
at miit was broadening at that time
there was less emphasis on
point-to-point
communication more on networks and more
on congestion system issues the
communication era area combined with
electronic systems lab the form Lids in
this was Far More Than Just a new
administrative unit all of us the
faculty and the grad students at Lids
recognized the commonalities in our work
this was primarily a payoff for San jooy
missionary work for many years before
1978 when the mercher occurred sanjoy
was not appointed director of the lab
until
1981 but he'd been the intellectual ual
leader of the combined effort in
communication and control for years
before
1978 working in ldz under sanj's direct
directorship was a memorable and
wonderful experience for most faculty
and
students the new faculty coming in at
that point uh especially uh theit bacus
and John cus took to the combined
orientation
naturally uh from sanjoy leadership
everyone understood how much they could
gain by working together uh they could
work together both from similar areas
and from very different
backgrounds it was easier to write a
paper on old stuff at that time than to
really get interested in a in an
in in a totally new area so it was much
harder for people to start working
together than one might think at first
there was a sense of competition also
between different people at the lab but
for the most part there was a real sense
that everybody wanted to help each other
and they wanted to be helped by others
they would listen uh which is sometimes
difficult today my sense is that sanjoy
was primarily responsible for this
Cooperative effort uh the whole time
that he was director from 1981 to
1999 I was a co-director from 86 to
99 but sanjoy was the intellectual
leader he was the master of working
together I just tried to help in small
ways I wish I could tell you the secret
of how to keep a lab of faculty and
students working together and helping
each other my only clue is it in the
long run helping is more satisfying than
competing a good set of
collaborators especially having a
director as a collaborator is truly
important thank you st joy for making
all of this
happen to my friend s
Joy I have known San joy since 1969
just after my
PhD it was before he joined MIT he was
still at
Cleveland K Western Reserve
University he was instrumental at the
origin of a cooperation between inia and
his research center in the
US the scientific fit was
immediate and the friendship followed
he invited me several times to MIT in
the early'
70s and he was a regular visitor of
inria his wife Adriana was Italian and
the friendship extended to the
family one of his main student at the
time was Michelle
deur a French scholar settled in
Montreal all of us became extremely
close
the research of sanjy and
Michael in those
days was devoted mainly to the control
of dynamic systems with
delays with Jack L Leons my supervisor
we were working on the control of
distributed parameter Dynamic
systems our techniques were very
close since they both represent case of
infinite dimensional dynamic system I
have always been very impressed by San
not just because of his competence in
control
theur but also because of his
culture he could speak many languages
including French he even learned
Sanskrit in
India for me look like a
gentleman with all the tradition related
to this world in Great
Britain he was educated in Great Britain
and work in Geneva where he learned
French he got a position of a school
normal in Pisa
Italy and became very related to the
famous mathematician JP
DPR have been very impressed by this
connection since after all he was
supposed to do research in
engineering clearly it was a sign of his
ability to work in various
domains and be respected by all the
experts in all of them
in my opinion it also reflects his
vision that mathematics was essential in
control of dynamic system as well as for
information
systems this for us very clear from the
very beginning in
1969 when the cooperation with Jack lons
and I was
initiated I've been very fortunate to be
involved in the initiative to write a
book in two volumes with Jose Jose D
Michelle delu and S
Jo his book is representation of control
of infinity dimensional system which was
published in 1992 in 1993 by be CER the
second edition in
2006 both sjo and J pass away in 2023 in
June and October
I want to thank both so much for this
fantastic common work which represent a
lot for
me sonjoy was will remain unique by many
standards a great scientist a gentleman
a wonderful
friend as an example and a reference and
forgettable forever
I just want to take this opportunity to
highlight Professor mither's one uh
trait which was his awareness of
research results from across
disciplines I remember a meeting with
Professor Shapiro and Professor mither
where Professor MIT had accompanied me
to Professor Shapiro's office and um
during a discussion with Professor
Shapiro very nonchalant Professor MIT
says and you know there a theorem by
korovich which does so and so and so I
was just flabbergasted like how could he
even know that result I mean of course
he works in optimal transport and so on
but um his um Rao with the results and
research across the board was quite
amazing thank
you I met sanjoy at Kate Western
University in in Cleveland almost 60
years ago 60 years
ago and in our frequent contacts and
then join
travel I have always been
impressed by
sanjy vast knowledge truly vast
knowledge not just
technical but also in very broad areas
of History literac culture
Humanities just blood humanities
I will talk just about sanjoy the
humanist I assume other colleagues will
discuss the scientific and his
scientific and Technical
contributions which are very
significant yeah it is natural that
sanjy who might consider the renaissance
man be married to Adriana from
Florence Florence is Center of
Renaissance
and they
spent a lot of their vacations in
beautiful Florence and my wife and I
were lucky to visit them a couple of
times we sanjoy and the group of us we
had many join travels and listening to
sanjy during our
travels was really an enjoyable learning
experience
perhaps the most significant travel we
had was when a group of
Us San Joy included with
us all of the age of
16 when we were taken to a long tour of
China organized by our generous Chinese
colleagues I was amazed that sanjo seem
to know more about cultural and
historical monuments than our excellent
professional
guide at at one point Sano asked that we
be taken to an ancient
pagod and he explained to the guide how
to get to it in the
Pagoda sanj spent time browsing through
ancient manuscripts and explaining to us
their
significance now imagine in a Chinese
pagod he is there and knows something
about this Ancient M
manuscripts well I would ask him
sometimes to talk about ancient
philosophers and he did it brilliantly
with
equal say I would say he would Express
criticism about some contemporary
philosophical Trends his interest was in
Classics contemporary philosophy was a
bit of a less interest for him but he
was a broad
broad he had a broad knowledge he was a
renaissance man and also a humanist of
our time he truly lived a full life
intellectual scientific full
life okay we thank uh the individuals
sent us the videos we saw videos of Dr
Alan Ben Susan Aman chaa and of course
the voice of Professor Peter
kotovich uh now we have uh a few written
tributes that some of us will go through
and read uh in order um so I'm going to
start the first one uh is by our uh
friend and colleague hendrik Sandberg uh
who was a professor at kth in
Sweden uh hendrik would have liked to be
here but he had some professional
obligation so he couldn't make it he
sent us a paragraph to read uh he writes
as a postto at Caltech in 2006 I
encountered the article information and
entropy flow in the calman buy filter by
sanjo mitter and Nigel Newton few papers
have I read so many times few papers
have puzzled me so deeply and few papers
have fascinated me as much as this one
beyond the calman buy filter it delves
into the second law of Thermodynamics
heat pumps information Supply and
dissipation hamiltonians and Maxwell's
demon the breadth of sano's interest and
insight is vividly Illustrated in this
work who else in our field could write a
paper with such an extensive scope this
paper is a gold mine that kept me
engaged for a long time and profoundly
inspired our research on measurement
back action many years later during my
sabatical at LDS my office was
fortuitously located next to sanjy to my
great joy he was in his office almost
daily and always took the time to meet
with me to discuss the intricate
relationship between statistical physics
and control theory initially my goal was
to create simple physical models to
illustrate the results of sanjoy and
Nigel's work however our discussions
quickly evolved leading to the
development of new performance bounds
for linear quadratic control which even
C the interest of physicists in my
conversations with sanjoy I often felt
like a humble engineer in the presence
of a great wise scholar always ready to
reveal new connections and relationships
to older work his knowledge of control
and information theory was nothing short
of
encyclopedic so the next one next one is
by sand colleague Richard winter sandre
stood out for his Grand Vision of
control the and his insight into it's
link with other field his extensive
contacts and wide reading mean that that
he was exceptionally well informed about
important research issues of the day and
ideas in circulation including those not
generally
known uh he had a repetition in
consequence of being the go-to person to
ask what research has been done in this
field regarding supervision and
collaboration he was at his best with
bright independent minded student and
doctoral
fellows uh these uh he would steer
toward serious topical research areas
then allow them the freedom to develop
their own ideas and in many cases
Advance them towards flourishing
academic careers to say he was cultured
would be an understatement multiculture
would be a more appropriate description
of someone at home in many language
languages and so immersed in the
cultural words of India European
countries and United States sandre was a
truly exceptional person and he will be
generally uh he will be greatly
missed so the next one is from Nigel
Newton I first me I I first met sanj
when I spent the semester on study leave
atlet in the fall of 1999 I remember his
infectious enthusiasm for
interdisciplinary scientific research
and for getting to grips of the
fundamentals of a problem this was at
the time where there was an increasing
pressure to follow topical discipline
specific Trends in research over the
years sanjo encouraged me to Cross
disciplinary boundaries and pursue lines
of research that I could not otherwise
considered I am most gra I am most
grateful for the moral and practical
support he provided during this period
along with his first wife Adriana who
passed away in 2008 Sanji was always a
gracious host he was he was very much a
citizen of the world my thoughts are
with with his widow rea
this is from Antonio Vino I'm very sad
for not being able to attend this
important event in honor of sanjoy I had
several occasions to meet sanjoy he
spent several weeks in Sienna he gave
several seminars and taught graduate
courses in my University his lectures
were always Illuminating and intriguing
I remember neatly one Sunday of 20 years
years ago when I met him by chance in a
restaurant in the Kean area he was
having lunch with his wife Adriana and I
was with my wife and son we spent some
time together at my place and after that
occasion we met several other times I
believe the systems and control
researchers are lucky to be able to cons
consider such a polyhedral researcher as
a member of their community
well this one is from sandre student
colleague Peter doruk it's a short one
uh Professor meter and I first met in
the mid
1970s he has had a great influence on my
activities ever since especially the
range of applications that interested
him and the diversity of disciples from
which he drew ideas he was a wonderful
person and an inspir inspiration to me
for half a century
okay uh the next comment is by Dr Janan
abunar director of The Sandbox
Innovation fund and a former student at
LDS and
ECS uh she writes sanjoy was the
director of Lids when I was a student
and he served on my thesis committee I
remember him fondly as a mentor and
dedicated faculty he was kind and
thoughtful I am honored to have known
him and to have benefited from his
guidance
and uh last on my end uh U Miss uh
Bernice Bry who's a friend and colleague
uh she was here earlier today writes um
I've known sanjoy since 1974 when my
late husband Jeremy Shapiro Sloan
professor of operations research and our
children traveled with sanjoy and
Adriana to
Venice um so with that I'm going to
leave it to colleagues
so this is me a message from Rachel
Rachel Cohen she was a she is or was I
guess sanj's longtime admin and friend
Professor Meer hired me parttime in 2001
my major qualification was typing in
latek he was a true gentleman and a joy
to work with and for in our more than 20
years together encompassing birth deaths
marriages and aging we maintain the
respect and caring that was a border of
work and life but never that of too much
he was such an easy person to want to
help but there was also there in my
times of need too supportive flexible
and in my corner I miss him every
day and this is from at gami who is one
of his sanjo post dos uh Professor sanj
mitter was a great mentor and friend his
kindness and support was beyond what I
can express with words he traded his
students and colleagues his family
during my time at MIT as Professor
mitter's postto it became clear to me
that he was widely liked and respected
with connections from all different
fields this reflected his great interest
and intellect so his great intellect and
interest in continuously learning new
things there's one conversation with him
that got printed in my brain and I will
never forget I remember we discussed how
to choose a path of research how to pick
a problem I said said that taste is very
important he replied taste is
everything these three words I will
never forget Professor mitter had great
taste in everything not only research he
was a true identifier of quality and you
can see his Spirit still alive at Lids
when he was director for 18 years he
will be missed
dearly uh this is a message from Tom
kyth I first met sanjoy at Imperial
College in the summer of 1972 and we
were both spending a few weeks there I
was immediately impressed by his Poise
and his diction he never seemed to be in
a hurry about anything and this remained
true all the years that I knew him
sanjoy had a wide range of professional
and social interests so our
conversations were quite wide ranging
from control theory to quantum physics
and statistical mechanics I profited
from his eagerness to expound on these
topics our main technical discussion in
the late '70s was on something I had
introduced called The White Noise
Innovations process associated with a
given stochastic process without going
into details there was a technical issue
associated with what is called the
Innovations conjecture on the resol on
the resolution of which several papers
have been written by mathematicians
mostly in Japan and the former Soviet
Union to my mind the most progress on
this issue was made in a paper by sanjoy
and his MIT
collaborator uh Deborah allinger uh the
ma mathematics of which was beyond me I
find myself in that position with
several of his papers including a recent
one written with the distinguished
Princeton mathematician Charles
feferman I would be remissed not to
mention my warm interactions with sano's
late wife Adriana at their homes in
Cambridge and in Florence and later with
his wife raika in Cambridge and in
London um my son-in-law George I suppose
he's ref in to me but um has been
diligent in keeping me posted on the ups
and downs of sanj's Health in recent
months and of sanjoy typical optimism
that he would return to his office at
MIT it is a thought that may temper our
grief that we shall not be seeing our
dear friend again in the words of the
ancient Hebrew saying may his memory be
a blessing
[Applause]
okay um this concludes our uh
remembrances uh before we go to the
reception I just wanted to thank uh
everyone who made this event possible my
co-organizers uh Pablo leang anant and
moner uh LDS and ECS staff especially
Shila who did uh a lot of the work uh
Jane Bill Amanda and other staff
volunteers
I would like to especially thank uh
sanjoy family uh uh his brother Dr prab
mitter for helping to bring sano's
character to the event and thank you to
all of sanj's friends colleagues
mentees um um and I'd also like to thank
uh uh lid's uh um director s who's here
uh ECS department head also was darkar
and uh and uh the generous support of uh
LDS and ECS for making this event
possible with that I'd like to invite
you to join us for uh a reception next
door thank you