So we're now at...
Just over 1,000 RPM
2,400...
...3,000. Yeah.
Could the amount of cavitation be affected
by our particular blade geometry?
Yeah!
I remember Zack
organizing this workshop out in California.
It was about reusable rocket engines.
And there was this huge outcry
from industry
about students not having enough
hands on experience.
Not just hands on, but not knowing
how to make things.
So when they designed, keep that in mind.
“The impellers are supposed to go...”
Yeah, I think it's making things
but using modern manufacturing tools.
So things like 3D printing,
metal, 3D printing, plastic, 3D printing,
rapid prototyping for engineered devices.
“We can use Bernoulli's principle...”
We're spending this semester designing
and then building this pump system.
The overall idea of turbo pumps
is that they're used a lot of similar machines.
So on a bigger scale you could think about
using them in a jet engine or a rocket.
It works!
And if you operate at maximum speed,
it doesn't leak!
It's nice to have a system
that you can take
responsibility of the whole thing,
and then figure out
all the little details that end up to what
puts, you know, people on the moon.
We started off
by designing basically some impellers.
Impellers that are 3D printed metal.
It’s starting to get too narrow...
We didn't specify the specific pumpdesigns,
the impeller shapes really anything.
We gave them tools.
They developed their own designs
and each team arrived at their own
unique specialized design.
And many discovered
interesting design features
which are actually used in
real applications.
The real high performance engines.
[LAUGHING]
That works?
Yeah!
And your’re moving stuff!
So far it has gone
remarkably smooth, in large part
because we have exceptional students
and then also exceptional TA’s.
Yeah, the TA’s play a huge role.
“That should be dry.”
Because it's a new course.
We're running it for the first time.
We spent most of the summer
developing the lab activities
and the problem sets
that would go with it,
and then most of the fall course correcting
as fast as we could
and just reacting
to how the students were learning.
Yeah, we start every module
with familiarizing the students
with the same concepts.
But after that they all branch off
into their own designs basically.
This class is probably the most
multifaceted class I've ever taken.
I think it really captures the entire
process of an engineering cycle.
Some of the parts that they're using were
farmed out to manufacturing companies.
I mean, especially with 3D printing,
like essentially we have like 12 teams.
And so if we tried to print
12 of these would have taken like months.
Different teams
use different manufacturing techniques
and different materials, different color,
different surface
finish, different mechanical properties
and maybe different performance.
And they're going to see.
I think initially we chose polycarbonate
because it was the cheapest option, but
it would have absorbed a lot of the water
that we were going to be using.
So we decided on nylon 12
because it was the second cheapest option.
You know, they're using actually the auto
pricing tools to assess cost curves,
and they're actually seeing
how that directly relates
to fundamental things
that they learned in lecture and.
How to deal with vendors. Right?
If you don't communicate well,
you won't get what you asked for, right?
Yes!
Oh, the seal is leaking!
Oh, this is the problem.
No!
Drainage system?
You guys have a drainage system?
[LAUGHING]
It works really well.
OK!
All right, all right!
Well, anyway,
we got our data.
How much oil was that?
[LAUGHING]
Being able to use all of the design
principles and things we've learned
for the past four years
to be able to incorporate all of these
into one system that's integrated
has been really nice.
When you're doing a problem set,
you're just working through numbers
and then you look back
and there's plenty of time to revise it.
But once you're doing these more
hands on and practical applications,
the decisions carry a lot more weight.
And so at some point,
we just had to decide that, you know,
this impeller design is,
what we want to go with.
And we're going to actually
go get it printed.
Same thing for rotordynamics setup
as well as the casing.
So I think that process of learning
with your team when to kind of commit
to a decision and what variables you need
to know to feel confident in that.
I think that was pretty unique
from past classes.
You really stepped up becoming engineers.
It's also a communications
intensive class.
So the main deliverables aren't exams
or anything like that,
but it's it's a presentation
and a report.
And so that kind of communication stuff,
we like having input
from the communications department.
To be able to use that process
of communicating to somebody else
to really enrich and deepen
your own understanding.
These students, they might develop
more efficient aero engines.
They might develop better,
more reliable rocket engines.
They may develop the next consumer
electronic device.
The skills that they're learning here
are transferable
to like any kind of physical system.
“...or the water pressure rise...”
These students are now going to go off
and they're going to have huge impact.
And I'm excited to see how they apply
what we teach them in the real world,
and what implications
this has for our partners and industry
for the next generation of technologies.
These are the future leaders, and
it's our privilege to get to educate them.
[CHEERING AND CLAPPING]
Thank you so much!