First up, I'm pleased to introduce
Professor Joseph Doyle, the Irwin H.
Shell Professor of Management and
Applied Economics at the MIT Sloan
School of Management. Joe is also the
faculty lead for MIT's Health Systems
Initiative or HSI. Today, Joe will
discuss efforts to apply behavioral
economics to increase engagement with
wellness programs with the goal of
better understanding their effectiveness
in improving employee health and
productivity. Over to you, Joe.
>> All right, good morning everyone. This
topic of trying to improve employee
wellness just a fascinating topic to me
because we could think about lowering
health care costs but also improving
productivity, employee satisfaction and
I really feel like it fits with the
mission of most most uh large employers
that you want to do well by your
employees. So there's this a lot of lot
of uh arrows pointing in the in the
positive direction here. Um there's a
lot of interest in what works and what
doesn't in this area and unfortunately
from the research side we just don't
know what works so well. So what I want
to do is uh as part of our presentation
today is show you what we've been
working on and ultimately I want to be
recruiting you know potential
collaborators for other curious
like-minded folks that want to know how
can we actually go about improving the
employ the well-being of of our
employees.
All right. So first I very brief
introduction to our health systems
initiative here at MIT. We have three
focus areas in healthcare analytics
operations and incentives and there are
many shops that do analytics quite well.
What we bring is both the frontier
knowledge of how to build analytic tools
with the management lens coming from
anthropology, sociology, economics,
psychology of how people actually use
these tools, how they buy into them and
how they can be successful.
On the operations side, we do help
health care systems. So think payers and
providers uh um work to be more seamless
in how they run their operations. A big
piece of that which is related to what
we'll talk about today is how do you
improve the workforce both at health
care systems but also with large
employers to try to think systematically
of how to improve employee wellness and
in terms of healthcare incentives I'm an
economist so this is my bucket of of
greatest interest how do you use
behavioral science to encourage healthy
behaviors as well as on the provider
side of health care systems how do you
get them to um provide best practices
What I want to talk about today in the
brief time I have with you is our
employee population health lab where
we're working with large employers.
We've had some funding from American
Express and Quest Diagnostics to think
about how do you go about improving
employee well-being. So just a bit of
background on this corporate wellness
industry. You know I find it to be a
really exciting area. Um just to give
some numbers um in 2022 we spent about
$42 billion worldwide on corporate
wellness programs half of that in the US
40%. But this is an industry that's
going to be growing. There's more
expectation on the part of employees to
have the access to these types of
programs. employers are receptive to uh
introducing these programs both for
selection of employees that they feel
are productive as well as uh to try to
lower health care costs. So we expect
this industry to grow to about 100
billion by 2033.
There are three types of things that I
have in mind when I talk about wellness.
One is what you might think of as well
per se, which is how do you screen
employees for how healthy they are? How
do you provide fitness programs for them
to get healthier? Another category would
be disease management. So for people who
already have a disease or on the edge of
getting that disease, how do you prevent
that? And then there's a third bucket
which is mental health programs. So
think about your employee assistance
programs which are now um you being
revolutionized by tellaalth. And about
half of the employers, large employers
that we see will offer some kind of
wellness program. um and about a quarter
of them are offering disease management
and mental health uh programs.
Sorry there's a lot on these slides but
I just I'll hit the highlights given the
the limited time we have today. So to
give a sense of who are some of the
major players uh think about firms like
WellHub, ShareCare, Levongo and
personally as of if I'm speaking with
the payers of these programs, large
employers like yourself, I'd be really
interested to know whether these
programs actually improve wellness um
and improve productivity of employees.
And to do that, we need to have some
rigorous research. And I'll show you why
in a minute. At the bottom there we have
well and you'll hear a presentation by
well today of how they use gamification
and software to try to encourage healthy
behaviors among employees.
So the average participation rate among
employers if they're going to offer a
program how do their employees actually
take them up? Well if it's a health risk
assessment this HA you know half of the
employees who are offered it will take
it up. Um if it's a fitness program you
know we're going to get people walking
at lunch 20% are going to participate in
that. As soon as you get to disease
management or some harder things like
smoking sessation, you start to get down
toward those uh single digits. This is
uh not uncommon to have 5 to 15% of
people participating in programs among
those who are eligible for those
programs.
And in terms of as an economist, I'm
interested could we use finances to
encourage people to do so. About
twothirds of large employers will be
offering some financial incentive to
participate in a program. And that's
often with this health risk assessment
or disease management programs. They're
not usually large amounts of money
that's capped by law. In many cases,
think like $200, $300 being lowering
your your healthare premium. And as a
behavioral economist, I do like to think
about how do you structure those
messages about how those funds are
available to people. If you tell people
you'll see this at the end of the year
and a paycheck that you don't really
look at that closely, you're not going
to have near the effect as if it was
sort of front and center. Hey, you have
this money, you're going to lose it if
you don't use it.
Now, there have been two large clinical
trials, randomized control trials of
wellness programs, and these are the
type that you know screening employees
for are they healthy or not? And then
maybe giving some suggestions on a
pamphlet u maybe encouraging exercise.
There's one at with the large retailer
BJs and another at the University of
Illinois among their 50,000 employees.
And both showed that if you look at the
treatment and control groups ran like a
drug trial that these programs have very
little effect on clinical outcomes or
healthcare spending. And the reason why
I'm bringing this up is because if you
look in these data at people who
actually engage with the program or
those who don't, you would get the
misleading impression that the programs
were very effective. Because those who
engage look like they improve their
health over time and that's because they
have those attitudes and encouragement
of their own behavior to get healthier
with or without the wellness program. We
know that because of the of the clinical
trial. We if we look at the randomly
assigned treatment group who has access
to the program and those who don't then
we find a very precise zero that these
programs are not effective at least in
these two contexts. So why am I bringing
this up in a and something I'm trying to
encourage you to think about these
issues. Well one is at MIT we're going
to do rigorous research like this to see
actually what works and what doesn't. We
don't go we're not an advocacy
organization. We want to know what works
so that you're putting your money where
it is most effective. Um but also we
need that rigorous type of research to
uncover that you need a control group.
You need someone who is randomly
assigned not to have the program in
order to see what would have happened if
the person who was randomly assigned to
get the program what what would happen
if you took it away from them. You won't
know that in an observational study but
you would with a randomized trial. So we
do have other methods besides randomized
clinical trials to estimate these with
quasi experimental methods. But getting
a valid and credible control group turns
out to be key to actually understanding
what works and what doesn't. So just as
a summary of this literature, I think
there's huge potential here. We have a
well- definfined group of employees who
are uh you you know who you're trying to
intervene on and and companies do want
to improve the well-being of their
employees. That's one of the missions of
the of organizations. So I feel like
there should be some collaborators out
there who want to go out and and figure
this out. It's a big and fast growing
industry with lots of changes of how
things are being delivered both through
apps and using artificial intelligence.
And so with all that churn, it gives us
the opportunity to start testing things.
We do need to test it rigorously.
However, the sort of pre-post
comparisons of the past are just not
going to cut it when we think about are
these programs actually effective. So we
have a lot of room for improvement both
in terms of designing these programs but
also how do you get people to engage
with them once they are eligible.
I want to delve into that last piece a
bit more in the remaining minutes I have
with you. So I'm working with David
Moler of University of Illinois who ran
that workplace wellness study there and
Nicholas Torsiello from Quest
Diagnostics to think about how do you
encourage um engagement with programs
once people are eligible. So we have
data from a large employer and we think
about their annual risk assessment.
Everyone we're looking at here are
eligible to engage with that and we
found you know precoid about twothirds
of people were engaging with that
program. That's been similar across the
years maybe a little higher recently.
And then among those who are um screened
about a quarter will be eligible for
some kind of wellness uh program.
And among those who are eligible for the
wellness program, only 6% are actually
engaging with the program. Um, that's
right. So, it's might be hard for you to
read if you're looking on a phone and
that's intentional. U, basically, people
are not engaging with these programs.
Um, if you do look at who actually does
participate, they tend to be female. So,
63% of people at the firm are eligible
for the program. basically all the
employ 63% of the employees are are
female but and 66% participate in the
annual risk assessment. So that's pretty
much on par with the representation that
you would expect. Among those 66% who
are eligible or who are um participating
or 66% are of the are participating in
the annual risk assessment um 58%
are of the eligible population are
female. So they're sort of
underrepresented. they're they're
healthier. Women are healthier. But then
if you look at among the 58% of
eligibles are female, um 74% of those
who actually engage are female. So
they're disproportionately engaging. And
this is something we see across a number
of contexts that women tend to engage
with these programs more than men. If
you look at the income level of the
employees, um by construction, we
created a data set where half are low
income and half are high income. They're
basically the lowest cortile of spending
of income versus the highest cortile.
But then if you look at the
participation, it's largely the high
income folks who are participating in
the annual risk assessment. And then we
know that 14% are low income. About 14%
15% are eligible. So actually they're
actually it's pretty similar in terms of
whether they'd be eligible for a
program. And then if you look at whether
they actually engage, it's about 15% of
of those high and low-inccome folks that
engage in the program. So that's a
slightly different year. It's a subopul
of what I showed you before, but it
looks like if we looked at income
disparities, it would be coming through
the front door here of do they start off
with any engagement, but once they're
eligible and engaging, they do it at a
similar rate whether you're in the top
or bottom of the income distribution. In
terms of age, as you age, you are going
to be spending more on health care,
which is very typical. Um, but you're
less likely to engage in these types of
wellness programs. This is a disease
management program. So maybe folks at
the upper end of the age distribution
are um are already getting a lot of
access to health care whereas the
younger folks are taking advantage of it
through their employer more.
A couple other things we found that I
think is pretty interesting. The people
that are engaging in this program that
we're looking at which was a a weight
loss program. we see that they have the
people who engage are more likely to
have had a shock increase in their
weight in the year prior um to engaging.
So maybe they they put on a few pounds
and they're the ones who are motivated
to try to take them off. In terms of
mental health, we find that those who
engage actually have higher rates of
depression and anxiety. Um and they had
a little bit of a shock increase in
their mental health problems. And it may
might be times when you people want to
engage with these programs to start to
get healthier.
This graph is one of many that we have
in our research, but I wanted to show
you one. If we look at the the annual
survey that people take as part of the
annual risk assessment, we can learn
things like have they had a flu shot in
the past? Have they avoided health care
due to the cost of healthcare in the
past? We find for those two categories,
they are engaging more with the program.
So, you know, people who are interested
in preventive health are the ones who
take up preventive health care and those
who don't have as much access to health
care because they can't afford it are
more likely to take these programs up.
The bottom panel here, um, when we think
about risk aversion, we have these
measures of do you speed on the highway
or do you use sunblock? And we find that
the people who speed on the highway are
less likely to engage in these wellness
programs. They're like more of the risk
takers and they decide not to engage.
And those who people who wear sunblock
can and we could do this controlling for
demographics um they are more likely to
engage. So again riskaverse folks are
more likely to engage in the um in the
wellness programs.
So a big question is is there a return
on investment for firms to offer these
types of wellness programs and one way
you could have a return would be through
healthcare spending. And so we find that
those who engage with the program
actually in the year before and after
they actually stay steady only a $12
reduction in their healthcare spending
per member per month that the
non-engagers actually saw an increase of
134. So this would suggest that the the
program cost $600
um and the claims over the course of the
year you would have this savings of
1,700 and this is a type of number that
you do see in the literature quite a bit
that you could save 3 to one if you look
at program people who engage and those
who don't engage but if you remember
back to the slide I showed you a few
slides ago about a randomized control
trial showing no effect we could
replicate this type of result in the
those RCTs randomized control trials
If you compared those who actually
engage who don't engage, you would find
this seeming improvement. But when you
go back and you compare the treatment
and control groups who are randomly
assigned, you don't find an effect,
suggesting that some of this is likely
due to selection. The people who engage
are the ones who are going to be on a
better trajectory regardless of whether
they engaged or not. So the returns are
so large 300% or so that you know that's
probably going to come down if you do a
more rigorous study. But there's still a
large potential here to see. The other
part is that it's not only healthcare
claims that firms might might care
about. Maybe they you could care about
job retention. So we find that after a
year of engaging, the engagers are more
likely to stay at the firm. 94% are
still there versus 90% of those who
didn't engage. So the reason why firms
could have these wellness programs would
be to attract and retain employees. And
that shouldn't be lost in this
discussion of whether firms should be
offering wellness programs. and
something that we'd love to uh to push
on.
So just as a summary of what we found in
the background investigation of
historical data, we found that disease
management engagement is very low. Women
are more likely to engage, those with
low income are less likely to
participate at the front door of the
annual risk assessment, and members with
low health care costs are more likely to
engage. So that's kind of interesting
that the relatively healthier folks are
more likely to engage and mental health
shocks may precipitate um engagement.
There is a large potential for return on
investment here both through medical
spending and through higher productivity
measures. So a big question we have is
how can you get people to engage more in
these programs? And so we've designed a
randomized trial of uh with our
collaborating partner of looking at the
power of defaults. So we know from
behavioral economics that defaults are
very um powerful. So here's a classic
study of if you have people default into
their 401k versus having to join on
their own that you have much higher
participation for those who are
defaulted to do so even though um it's
people are leaving money on the table by
by not. So what we did is we designed a
trial and outreach campaign that there
the firmo already had an outreach
campaign that basically said something
like you see on the left of your screen
there. if you you get a a drip of emails
saying, "Hey, you're invited to join
this program. You're eligible. Please
enroll today." And we said, "Well, what
if you reframed this in terms of, hey,
you're already in this program. Why
don't you start engaging?"
And we thought that this might not have
that large of an effect. Like, it's not
that big of a difference between saying,
"Hey, you're invited," versus, "Hey,
you're in." Um but it turns out that we
find that with a large scale like 5,000
people in this trial that the simple
framing change led to a two to three
times higher engagement rate. So those
people who are typically we we see at
that 5% engagement level for men you're
going to triple the uh the engagement
and for women about double the
engagement rate. If you just said hey
you're already in this program why don't
you start engaging? So in the next phase
of that we didn't get from five to 100%.
So, we're we're encouraging and we're
investigating is whether we can use on
the job time to engage with that program
where supervisors would tell eligible
employees, hey, you're you're welcome to
use a half an hour a week for 12 weeks
to meet with your health coach. We feel
like that could really boost engagement
and we'd love to find collaborators who
would be willing to test that type of an
idea. So going forward, what we'd love
to have are finding additional
collaborators who would like us to look
over their data and see what their prior
wellness activities have generated, but
then also think about outreach campaigns
or other methods to try to improve
engagement. Maybe experiment with
financial incentives or how they are
announced. And then annual risk
assessments. A lot of firms offer those,
but when you get your results back, they
could be kind of confusing. So, how do
you we could test different ways of
messaging
how healthy you are based on those
annual risk assessments. So, thinking
about how do we get an interpretable
health score, maybe have some
competitions with how you are ranking
versus your co-workers and kind of
gamify that approach. So, my name again
is Joe Doyle. You could reach me at jj
doymit.edu if you're interested in
collaborating. And um I left a few
minutes here where Anna and I can talk
and hopefully get a few questions from
from the audience. So Anna,
>> uh thank thank you Joe for an insightful
and timely discussion. Uh to take us a
bit deeper, I'm now happy to hand things
over to Anna Quadrass, senior lecturer
at Sloan and director of HSI. Anna will
be moderating the questions and answer
sessions with Joe and our other speakers
today. Welcome, Anna.
>> Well, thank you so much, Jim, and thank
you for giving us the opportunity to
share the research that we're doing and
to uh I'm thrilled to see so much um
attendance and engagement uh by the
audience in terms of uh coming to our
webinar. Um, and you are of course more
than welcome to uh put questions in the
Q&A um as we go along and we'll be keep
coming back and um and asking some
questions. So Joe, I'd like to start
with uh one question which is um what do
you hope to achieve with the employee
population health lab going forward?
>> Well, what I want to do is bring
together leaders in the industry of the
wellness industry. Whether that's
disease management or these wellness
type screening programs with large
employers who are interested in
improving the well-being and
productivity of their employees. And you
know if we could get five to 10
companies coming together. We have an
annual workshop that we is an invite
only workshop among our collaborators to
see what we what are we seeing in in
your data and how can we design
prospective trials to see if we can
improve wellness. And that's in
collaboration with about 30 faculty
members here at HSI as and hundred or
100 plus PhD students across the
institute across MIT um who are eager to
uh to grapple with these questions.
>> All right. And we'll actually see some
of that later today in this webinar in
terms of our collaborators and uh one of
our PhD students who is actually uh
working working on this. Um well another
question that I had is um in your in the
first part of your uh presentation you
show that you know the Illinois study
and the BJ study didn't really show um
you know a difference between the
treatment group and the control group
after one year. Do you know if you know
if this study had gone on longer or if
there are if there are additional
results that that just takes a long time
for um for uh results to show. What what
do you think? Yeah, there was follow-up
to the Illinois workplace wellness study
that I know that went out two years and
they just continue to find um that these
the people who were randomly assigned to
have access to the program
um they did engage with the program but
they did not see improvements in their
um in their clinical outcomes or with
their healthcare spending. And so yeah,
if if something might take 10 10 years
to see effects, they're going to be weak
incentives among employers to offer
those types of programs.
And we're thinking about a literature
here saying within a year you're going
to see 300% returns. I think people
really don't believe those 300% returns.
They might be closer to 40% returns,
which would be fantastic, but we need to
figure out which programs work for what
type of employee. And for that, we need
this type of rigorous research to get
that done.
>> Absolutely. So, I just had a question in
the Q&A, which is I love the idea of opt
out and optin model. Um, do you know if
there's legal compliance or privacy
concerns with the wellness partners or
the employers um autoenrolling, you
know, using these messages and
essentially autoenrolling them in a
program,
>> right? So, we've certainly had the
lawyers at both MIT and at our
collaborator look at what we were doing.
And so I feel like from a legal
standpoint, we were on solid ground. But
importantly, the the collaborator was
already reaching out to eligible
employees with emails saying, "Hey, you
should join." And um
it the way that you frame that is a
choice. You could say, "Hey, you're
eligible." Or, "Hey, you're already in
this program." It's it's quite a subtle
change. And we're not forcing people to
go to meetings. We're not um there's
really it really is a nudge and not a
push. Um, and so I wasn't so surprised
to see an improvement, but I was a
little surprised to see that tripling
among men that they would take that,
hey, you're in this program versus, hey,
you're eligible for this program and uh,
and see that big big jump in engagement.
I think the next phase there is to see
if we can improve it much higher than
15%, get up to 50% with something like
uh, support from your supervisors.
>> All right. Well, thank you so much.
Those those are all the questions I have
right now.
>> All right. Thanks everyone. I appreciate
it and I hope to hear from uh anybody
who would like to collaborate with us.
We'd love to talk with you. So enjoy the
rest of the show.