Okay,
recall. So, of course, I'm going to go
over a few things from last time.
Suppose
we have
a subi things
of size.
So these could be um well I mean they
could be Dick Walts
in which case a subi is the Catalan
number and um the generating function
is summation
a subi x.
Okay the notes generally use n
[clears throat] for this. So I'm going
to try to do that but
I'm probably going to um
not be consistent. The general question
is a of x
a subn x to the n
and equals well let's say 0 to infinity
but I
we you know maybe we want to start
counting at one in certain cases.
Okay.
And suppose
we have two classes of things,
a sub i and b sub i
like that. A subn and B subn and C subn
equals
A subn plus B subn where C is the union
of A and B
or the disjoint union. Then
C of X is equal to A of X plus B of X.
And suppose
C equals the direct product of A and B
where the size of C.
So C = A comma B
something from A and something from B.
So the size of C is equal to size
of A plus size of B.
N C subn= summation
i= 0 to n a sub i
b
sub n minus i
because you know if you want two things
to sum to n one should be i and the
other should be n minus i and c of x is
equal to
a of x times vx.
And there's one last
way of manipulating generating functions
that we should that I did not discuss
last time.
Actually, there's more than that. I
mean, you can differentiate them and
integrate them, but I gave you an
example of that last time. But
um
let's let
sequence of a
b be
a set of finite SEQUENCES
OF THINGS IN
SO let's
do an example that will illustrate this.
Suppose
a is equal to
0 and one.
sequence of A is equal to
binary springs.
Oops.
is an Aub
for example.
So what is the generating function for
sequence of a
Uh, I want to claim
s of x
is equal to sum from i zero.
Um
n = 0 to infinity
a
okay let's write it out first
is = 1 + a of x
plus a of x^2
+ a of x cubed.
So this is the empty sequence.
This is
0 and 1.
This would be 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 1 for binary
sequences
etc.
And a of x= 2x
for binary SEQUENCES
because you know here there are two
binary sequences of length one and
x means length one here and two means
there are two of them.
So
s of x is =
1 + 2x + 4 x^2 + 8 x cub + dot dot dot
which you probably all recognize as 1 /
1 - 2x.
We can go up here and say this = 1 / 1 -
ax.
So this is
I guess this calculation is not very
impressive for binary strings because
everybody knows how to come up with this
in much easier ways. But we will next
what we're going to do is we're going to
do Fibonacci numbers and Fibonacci
numbers are
a little bit harder and we will see that
the generating function actually gives
you interesting things for Fibonacci
numbers.
Okay.
So
let's start with another question.
Suppose
we want to send information over a
send
information
over
a telegraph type channel
where
we can send
dot and a dash.
And the question is how much information
or how many messages can we send?
Can we send
time
n? And I forgot to tell you, a dot has
length one
and a dash has length two.
Okay,
let's start
um
calculating it with one
with time one.
All we can do is send a dot. So that's
not really a message. That's just I mean
if you can only send one message, it
contains no information.
and time two, we could either send the
dash or two dots.
Um, and time three. So that's two
possibilities. Here's one possibility.
In time three, we can either send a dash
and a dot or a dot and a dash or three
dots. That's three.
And time for
send dot dot
dot or dash dash dash dot dot dot
dot dot dash and dot dot dot dot. So
that's five messages. Does anybody
recognize this sequence?
Okay, let's do the next one.
Well, there are two dashes and a dot or
a dot and two dashes or dash dot dash.
And we can
dash and three dots
dot dash dot dot dot dot dash dot dot
dot dot dash and dot dot dot dot
um dot. So there's eight of these
things.
Okay, do people recognize the sequence
now?
Um, what is it?
>> Fibonacci numbers. Yeah. So, we get the
Fibonacci numbers. And actually, there's
a very easy way to prove that we get the
Fibonacci numbers. We
[clears throat]
I'm going to claim F sub N= F -1 + F sub
N - 2
So this is
if something ends with a dot. So uh
sequence of length n is either going to
lend with a dot or a dash. If it ends
with a dot then there are fn minus one
ways of putting filling the first n
minus one time units. and ends with a
dash there are fn minus2 ways of filling
the first n minus two times.
So you get this recurrence for the
Fibonacci numbers which I'm sure
everybody already knows about.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to ask how can we use generating
functions to find a formula for the eth
Fibonacci network.
[clears throat]
And
I want to say something
back when our lecture notes were first
written,
I used,
you know, f_sub_1 = 1, f0 zero.
There's one way of sending message of
length zero
which is the empty message. So f_sub_0 =
1, f_sub_1 = 1, f_sub_2 = 2, f_sub_3= 3,
f_sub_4= 5 etc. So,
um
since then,
um Wikipedia has
um
you know,
Wikipedia has installed itself as the
default um you know,
the default um arbiter of definitions
etc. And today
Wikipedia says f0 equals 0, f_sub_1= 1,
f_sub_2= 1, f_sub_3= 2, and everything
is shifted by one.
And I have not had time to rewrite the
notes. So the notes
disagree with Wikipedia's definition of
Fibonacci numbers. And you know today
Wikipedia basically is the default
definition for everything even if um
some even if some references disagree.
Okay.
So
um
and it's much easier to do this
calculation.
I think it's much easier to do this.
It's a little bit easier to do this
calculation if we use the alternate
definition rather than Wikipedia's
definition. But let's write down the
generic function for f of x.
f ofx
equals summation f ofx
summation
the i Fibonacci number * x to the nth
Fibonacci number * x to the n which is
equal to 1 + x + x^2
+ 3 x cubed + 5 x 4th + 8 x 5th + 13 x
dot dot dot.
Okay. So, how do we compute
the value? How do we find a closed form
for f ofx?
Let's um
take x fx
= x + x^2 + 2 x cubed + 3 x 4 + 5 x 3r
and x2 fx
=
x2 + x cubed + 2 x 4 + 3 x plus dot dot.
Okay,
so now we have these three formulas. Can
anybody tell me what I should do with
them?
>> Subtract them. Very good. f ofx
- x f(x)
- x2 f(x)
equals
Can anybody tell me what this is?
One exactly. So it's one because
anything after the first term we have f
sub i f sub i minus one and f sub ius 2
and we take this and subtract that and
subtract that we get zero. The first
term doesn't quite work like that. We
take 1 - 0 - 0 and we get one.
And of course, this gives you the
equation f(x)
1 - x - x^2 = 1 or f(x)
= 1 / 1 - x - x^2.
Okay.
So how do we find a formula for f ofx
from this?
How many of you remember from calculus
um the method of partial fractions?
So some of you do. How many have never
seen the method of partial fractions?
Okay, so most of you remember it.
I mean
I guess there's some question as you
know
when we have Mathematica does anybody
need to remember how to integrate um
expressions but
I guess they haven't taken away all the
integration methods from calculus. this
yet.
Okay. So, what do we do?
We use the method of partial fractions.
We say 1 - x^ 2 = 1 - 5 +
1 - 5 -
and 5 +
5 minus
are the roots
of
Well, what we're going to do is we're
going to reverse the order of these
coefficients and say y^ 2 - y - 1
And um
ah I forgot I forgot to put the x's in
this equation. So we
um yeah maybe I should explain why 5 + 5
- roots of y^ 2 - 1 - 1. So, y^ 2 - y -
1 = y -
y +
y - y -
And let's let x = 1 / y
1 /x^2 - 1x
- 1.
Wait,
this should be y^2 + y - 1 y^2 + y - 1.
And now 1x^2
- + 1x - 1
=
1 /x - 5 +
1 /x - y -
I think I've done something wrong.
Let me think about this. So we want 1 -
x - x^2 =
Okay. And now we want y^2 + y.
This should be
if y is 1 /x
then this
corresponds to the one. This corresponds
to y. This corresponds to y^2. But this
really should be - y - y^2 + 1 equals
that. And now we have
That doesn't work.
Okay.
Oh yeah.
Yeah, this is right.
Okay, good.
And multiplying both sides of this by
x^2,
we get
um 1 - 5 + x, 1 - 5 - x on the right
side. And we should get 1
- x -
x^2. So this should be a minus and this
should be a minus
and this should be a minus.
Yeah. Okay. Good.
So the roots of y^2
roots
are
-1.
No, 1 plus or minus the of 5 / 2 by
the um quadratic formula.
And
these are 5 + and 5 minus and 5 plus
will have the plus sign and 5 minus have
the minus sign.
Wait, no. I wanted I'm sorry. I wanted
to keep
um I want to keep this equation.
Okay.
How did you get there? y^2 y.
>> Oh, so what I did was I replaced um y by
1 /x
and then multiply by y^2
um
and I clearly did this too fast because
I confused myself. So let's do it. And I
confused you too by going too fast. So
let's go over it more slowly.
Let's let y equ= 1 /x.
So this is 1 - 1 / y - 1 / y^ 2 is equal
to 1 -
+ y
1 -
y.
Okay.
And now multiply both sides by y^ 2. So
this is y^2 - y - y = y - 5 +
y - y -.
So 5 + is the largest root
of y^ 2 - y - 1. and y - is the smaller
root of y^2 - y - 1. So we have
y + is equal to 1 + 5 / 2 and 5 - =
1 - 5 / 2.
Okay.
So
okay. So what do we have? We have f ofx
= 1 / 1 - x - x^2
= 1 / 1 - 5 + x
1 - 5 - x. And by partial fractions, we
know this is equal to
a / 1 -
y + x.
+ b over 1 - 5 - x.
Okay. So, um
what do we do with this?
Well, let's
try to
solve this equation.
So this is equal to a * 1 - 5 - x
+ b * 1 - 5 + x over
1 - x - x^2 because this * this is 1 - x
- x^2.
So now we have this is equal to this. So
this gives us two equations. We have a +
b = 1
and
a 5 - x + b 5 a.
get a 55 - x + b 5 +
x = 0x.
Okay, so we have two equations.
We have two unknowns a and b and you
know how to solve them. And I am not
going to do it because it's a lot of
algebra and I quite possibly would screw
up somewhere along the way. and you know
how to do it anyway. So the answer comes
out to a = 1 5 *
1 + 5 / 2
and b = 1 / 5
* 1 - 5.
So this is pi plus and this is pi minus.
So the formula for
f
well
f of x
=
a / y - 5 + x
+ b 1 - 5 - x
= a * 1 + 5 + x
+ 5 + 2 x 2 + 5 +
cub x cub
and and
b * 1 + 5 - x +
5 - x^ 2 x^2 + 5 - cub x +
And of course f ofx
was equal to
summation x sub i s subn x to the n.
So to find the nth Fibonacci number, we
need to find the nth term in the
sequence.
So we get f subn is equal to
a
y + to the n
+ b
5 minus to the n.
And let's go back and see what a and b
were. a was 1 over 5 * 5 + and b
was 1 over 5 * 5 minus. So this is
equal to 1 /
5 + n + 1
+ 5 -
n +
where
um
5 plus is 1 over plus 1 + 5
and 5 - 1 - 5 / 2.
So here we have a term for the nth
Fibonacci number, a formula for the nth
Fibonacci number.
Oh,
okay.
So how fast does the Fibonacci number
grow?
How many me? How many
messages
can we send
n time
n with dots and dashes?
Well, it's just this formula.
It's 1 / 5
+ n + 1
5 - n + 1.
Okay.
Now
I want to say that 5 plus
is bigger than one and 5 minus is less
than one. So this is just very
approximate very close to 1 / 5
5 + 1.
So the information transmission rate
Right.
Is
log base 2
+ n + 1 5
which is approximately.
Well, we want to divide this by the time
per time limit.
Let's say information rate per time unit
is log 2 + 2 n + 1 5 / n which is
approximately so this n + one comes
close to canceling this n root five is
just a constant factor a constant
addition factor which is negligible. So
it's log 2 of 5x.
So if you have a channel that uses dots
and dashes to transmit information, this
is how much you can transmit in time.
And we're actually going to be going
back to this later in the course and
talking about information theory and how
much information you can transmit in
general. Okay.
So, um,
let's see. Trying to think if I have
time to do this next um
next bit. I think I do.
So, let's answer another question.
Oh, wait. Before we answer another
question, I'm going to go back and say
we actually could have gotten this
formula.
Um,
where is it?
f ofx
equals 1 / 1 - x - x^2
much more easily.
So, how could we have gotten a
generating function for
this dots and dashes problem much more
easily? Anybody?
Okay. So yeah, it's not not completely
obvious.
So f ofx
is
number of sequences
of dot and action.
So the generating function
A of x = 1
I'm sorry x + x2
for
dot dash because dots have time one
which is x dashes have time two which
corresponds to x^2 and we just add them
because you know it's generating
function when you have two disjoint
things you take this sum.
Does the sequence
of
dots and dashes is equal to? Well, we
use this formula up here 1 / 1 - a x is
1 / 1 - x - x^2.
And we just saved oursel a lot of effort
by using that formula rather than
deriving it through,
you know, writing out the recurrence and
adding the equations up and um
and seeing what the result was.
So maybe we should try applying this to
a different question
which
is a tiling question which you're not
getting on your homework.
I think there's a tingling question on
your homework.
The generating function for
number of tilings
of
2 by N strip
with
two kinds of tiles.
Uh triangular tile and a
zigzag tile.
>> Say something.
>> Huh?
>> Yeah, you're allowed to rotate a flip.
Otherwise, this would otherwise you
couldn't tile the strip without flipping
this one. So, for
three, you get
and
it's
um for
six.
you get,
you know, let's let's do five first.
For five, you get um
yeah, that's five. 1 + 2 + 2 and it's
flipped.
And for six, what you can get is you can
get
um I'm doing this wrong.
six you can get and now you can
join another unit of six.
Okay.
So how would you find the generating
function for this?
Well, let's use this sequence formula.
Um
is equal to well there's two ways of
tiling a
3x two strip. So that's
x cub * 2 +
well there are two ways of tiling a five
length five strip. So that's two x to
the 5th. There are two ways of tiling a
length seven strip. Um
I mean you just stick two Z tiles in
instead of one Z tile. So that's + 2 x7
+ x and that is equal to 2 x cubed over
1 - x^2.
So
g of x is = 1 / 1 - 2x cub over 1 - x^2
is equal to
um
1 over
I would say 1 - x^2
- 2 x cub and I'm going to the one
that's squared on top.
Okay.
Okay. And you can figure out what the
recurrence
for this is,
which is really weird,
but um
maybe I shouldn't say weird, which is
really quite non-intuitive,
but
you know, if we had the recurrence
um
f(n) = fn -1 + fn - 2 that came out to 1
- x - x^2.
So this is going to be fn is equal to
f n
- 2 - 2 fn - 3.
And the top says what the initial
conditions are. Um
f0
wait should be a plus. F0
= 1 and f_sub_2 = -1.
And
um I'm not going to have time to explain
why
going from here to here makes this, but
let's see what sequence we get.
And I should not say this is f_sub_2 =
-3. This is
because I
- x
What was that? 1 - x^2
- 2x cub.
The initial condition
condition is
f_sub_2 = 1 f f0
= 1 and f sub i = f i - 2 + 2 f - 3
and
x^2 over 1 - x^2
- 2x cubed is the same thing except
The initial condition
is f_sub_2 minus one and
the same recurrence.
So we can look at the recurrence and see
if we actually get what we
wanted.
So,
so one,
so this is zero. One, um, two, we get
one here. Three, we get one.
We get two here.
Four, we look back.
Two, and we get
another one.
Um,
is that right? Yeah, that's right. And
now we subtract minus one
0 1
for five. We look back two and we get
two and we add two *s this. So this
should be four. And now we subtract 1 0
0 because subtracting
shifting over two and subtracting is the
same as multiplying by - x^2
and we get
[sighs]
well this should be
two
1 0 1 2
and we get 1 0 0 2 0
um two
and indeed there were two for five there
were two for there was
two for three and there's one for length
zero which is just the empty tiling
and the next one should give us next
element should really give us four if
I've calculated it right and it probably
does I'm not going to
I'm not going to check it.
So that is how you could do another
tailing. Okay. So now let's switch to
a different question.
Let's look at Pascal's triangle.
Okay.
Okay. Pascal's triangle is 0 0 1 choose
0 1 choose one two choose zero 2 choose
one two choose two
etc.
And let's look it in numbers 1 one 1 2 1
1 3 3 1 1 4 6 4 1 1 5 10 10 5 1 etc.
So let's
let's do this now. Suppose you're
just looking at this and you start to
sum and you ask what happens if I sum
I guess diagonals of it. I mean, let's
take 1 + 1, that's 2.
1 + 3 + 1,
that's 5.
Um,
1 + 6 + 5 + 1,
that's 13.
And you happen to notice that these are
um Fibonacci numbers. I mean two is the
third Fibonacci number, five is the
fifth Fibonacci number, 13 is the
seventh Fibonacci number, etc. Okay, so
once you've noticed this, you can ask
how can I prove it? And actually there
are a whole bunch of ways to prove it.
You can prove it by counting something
two different ways. You can prove it by
straightforward induction and you can
prove it using generating functions. And
I'm going to prove it using generating
functions.
And I have to say I think this this
proof is written up fairly badly in the
notes. It's in the notes.
Okay. So
using
generating functions.
Okay.
Well, first let's
compute
the generic function
for Pascal's triangle.
Now, this is a twodimensional array of
numbers. So, we're going to need two
variables to do this. And we'll call
this x to the 0 y 0 x to the 1 y 0
um x 0 y 1
etc. So what we get is we get x + y
choose x
x = 1 0 to infinity from y = 0 to
infinity x + y choose x * x to the
okay
I am
not looking at my notes because in my
notes I'm sure I did not use x for
two different things.
So let's see.
Oh
yeah. Sum a= 0 to infinity. B= 0 to
infinity.
A + B choose A
X to the A Y to the B.
So this is the generating function for
Pascal's triangle two dimensional
generating functions. So you get two
different variables.
So what is it?
A + B to Z to the A
to B.
Okay.
So what I want to do is I want to break
this up into
a = 0 to n
and
b = n - a
and then
n =
So I'm going to break this up and just
sum it along the rows first and then sum
all the rows after that. So single row
is sum n choose a a 0 to n
X to the A Y
to the Mus.
Can someone tell me what this is?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. This is X Y.
Good.
So from n= 0 to infinity
um x + y to the n is = 1 / 1 - x - y
Okay.
Well, what do we do with that?
Well, what we're going to have to do is
we're going to have to go back and look
at the sum a little more carefully.
Okay. So
here one one one two one 1 3 3 1 1 4 6 4
Um,
let's take
1 5 10
5 1 and there's a one over here. So,
let's look at this diagonal.
6 5
that's 13.
Okay.
So this turns out to be 3 choose 0 plus
3 + 0 choose 0
times
x cubed
y 0
plus
2 +
2 choose 2
x^2 y^ 2 +
1 + 4 choose 4.
That's 5 choose 4. That's this
x
y cubed +
0 + 6 choose 6
x to the 0
y to the
um
this is white fourth this is y6
So what we're doing is we're going along
and we're
you know subtracting one from
m and adding two to n each time.
So
I want to say this is
summation
i = 0 to
um
Okay.
Um,
let's call this F.
n - i +
2 i
choose
x to the
um
2 i y
X to the N - I Y 2.
Okay.
So what we want is we want
to somehow
group all these terms together in the
generating function. Can anybody tell me
how to do that?
Okay.
X = Z^2.
and let's let y = z.
Okay. So now what we're going to do is
this becomes
summation i = 0 to n
+ i choose 2 i
x to the or z 2 n - 2 i * z 2 i and this
is
z to the 2n
So if we plug the generating function,
if we plug x= z ^2 and y = z into the
generating function for Pascal's
triangle,
the generating function we get will give
us these
I guess diagonal sums.
Is this clear?
Okay, great. So, what was the generating
function for Pascal? For Pascal's
triangle,
um, it was 1 - x - y
Okay.
SO SUBSTITUTE
x = what was that? x= z ^2 z^ 2 y + z
and 1 / 1 - x - y.
You get
1 /
1 - zus
1 over z ^2 minus z. And this is a
generating function for the Fibonacci
numbers.
And you can go back and you can look at
this and you can realize that
our proof not only gives you the
Fibonacci numbers for these diagonals,
it also
if you look at the other diagonals
2 + 1 is three.
And
I want to say
3 + 4 + 1 is 8.
These are I mean these diagonals
starting on the left side of the
triangle give you the oddnumbered
Fibonacci numbers are the every other
Fibonacci numbers and these diagonals
starting on the right side
give you
the Fibonacci numbers between them.
Okay.
And that's actually all I wanted to say
about generating functions today. We're
going to be doing generating functions
for Catalan numbers on Tuesday, but I
want to hold that off because
I want to do everything on the same day.
So I thought maybe I should show you the
proof of the same recurrence with
counting something in two different
ways.
So
Natur numbers
number of length and
sequences
of dots and dashes where the dashes are
like two and the dots are like one.
Okay.
Okay. Um,
and
if n equals
5,
a number of sequences
is eight.
So we will be doing that right now. So
let's
group
sequences
by number of dots.
Okay. So, we can have eight dots. Well,
we can have zero. We can have one dot,
two dashes.
We could have two dots.
Um, well, we can't have two dots. We can
have three dots and one dash or we could
have five dots
and zero dashes.
So, if you have one dot and two dashes,
how many ways are there of ranking these
things?
Yeah, it's 1 + 2 choose
two.
If you have three dots and one dash, you
get
3 + 1 choose 1. And if you have five
dots and zero dashes, you get 5 + 0
choose zero.
And I want to claim that this is
essentially this sum. So summation
um
let's say a
n + i i= 0 2
something
choose
This is three. This is
3 + 1 + 1 is 4. And this is 1. And that
corresponds to this diagonal 3 + 4 + 1.
So this is a way of proving
this
formula by counting things in two
different ways. You count the number of
sequences of dots and dashes of length
n. And first you do it by just saying
that's a Fibonacci number. And the
second way you do it
is by grouping them by the number of
dots and dashes in each one. And
twice the number of dots plus the number
of dashes is equal to the length of the
sequence. And summing them up gives you
these diagonals.
Okay. Any questions about this?
Can you explain what's the last step?
The last thing you said? [snorts]
>> Yeah, I'm connecting it with Pascal's
triangle. Um,
actually, I probably should have
Okay, I have a formula in here, I
believe.
Okay.
So
summation
m + j choose 2 j j
claim.
This
is the number of ways
of
arranging
dots and dashes
to have
um
let's see.
So
I want to call this as Mus J
plus 2 J 2 J
and we have length F.
If we have
M minus J dashes
2 J dots
you get like them.
Yeah. I mean the dots are length one,
the dashes are length two. So this is
length
and um
number of ways
to arrange
uh
minus J box options
2 J dots
is
m - j + 2 j choose 2 j
which is
m + j choose 2 j.
uh sum
There's a number of ways of breaking 2 m
length 2 m
of arranging dots and dashes to have
length 2 m total. So this is equal to FI
number of like 2m
maybe plus or minus I mean or maybe this
is 2 m + 1 or minus one or something but
anyway this gives you the formula
Okay. So next time we're going to derive
the formula for the Cadillac number
which
I can't remember if I told you what it
was already or not. I think I did
using in fact we derived it using Dick
Walts. I'm next time we will derive it
using generating functions and a
recurrence for the cataly.
And that will I think finish our um
section on generating functions and I
think