[Music]
so hi everyone my name is Ora ashenberg
and I'm a computational biologist at the
Bro Institute in Cambridge Massachusetts
in the Eric and Wendy Schmid Center and
the claran cell Observatory and today
I'm going to lead you through the
introductory uh lectures that are going
to uh give you an overview of all the
materials you'll need to engage in this
data science Challenge and so the
introductory lectures are broken into
three biology technology and data uh in
the Biology lecture we're going to
discuss uh can and how it grows the
immune response to cancer in particular
te- cells and cancer immunotherapies
then in the second lecture on technology
we'll discuss uh how we can profile the
immune system and perturb it to get
outcomes that we'd like and then finally
uh in the third lecture we're going to
talk about the data that was generated
for this Challenge and how we can uh
load up that data play around with it
analyze it and this will get you going
for the actual
challenge okay so the first lecture of
biology is going to cover cancer te-
cells and cancer
immunotherapy so uh it's broken down
into four sections um the first will be
how cancer forms followed by our immune
system's response to cancer and then
we'll talk about tea cells in particular
and how they become exhausted and
finally uh we'll talk about cancer
immunotherapies so let's start by
talking about how cancer forms so cancer
is a disease that arises in our own
healthy cells and here as an example
we're looking at the cells in our skin
and these cells can transform and start
to grow uncontrollably and then spread
throughout the body in the process of
metastasis and you know if left
untreated this will lead to the death of
the individual so cancer is a disease
that arises within the genes within our
own cells and there are mutations that
happen uh that lead to the cancer and
these mutations commonly happen in
certain classes of genes DNA repair
genes tumor suppressor genes and Proto
Ana gen and as an example tumor
suppressor genes are genes that are
controlling uh how your cells are going
through the cell cycle and growing in a
regulated Manner and if you get a
mutation in one of these genes now the
cell is no longer really controlled and
how it's growing and it can start to
outgrow the tissue and that's one of the
sort of Hallmarks of cancer so uh these
mutations that happen in these genes uh
what they do is they actually change
gene expression programs in the cells so
gene expression programs are uh groups
of genes that are uh turned on or
expressed together and they function in
a shared biological process and so as an
example we can consider a melanite which
lives in your skin is a cell living in
your skin and normally it's going to
this gene expression program of
melanogenesis whereby the cells produce
melanin which is important in the
pigmentation of your skin uh hairs hair
and eyes and so uh when there's a
mutation in the melany uh this leads to
a transforming from a b benign melanoma
into a sort of an advanced melanoma and
as you get these sort of Transformations
you get these changes in the gene
expression programs of the malignant
cells and they start to acquire these
programs such as a program for cell
division so the cancer can keep growing
and growing and growing and also a
program uh in epithelium as enal
transition which is important for
metastasis and again these programs are
just groups of genes that the cancer
cell turns on to accomplish uh its
function so uh in the United States uh
we get about uh 2 million cancers that
were diagnosed in the past year and
cancer is overall globally the second
leading cause of death and so in the
United States the most common cancer
types are breast prostate and lung but
there's cancers that are kind of
occurring throughout different sites in
the body and then even within a cancer
type there are subtypes so you're
probably familiar with uh triple
negative breast cancer that's one
subtype of breast cancer and so uh
there's all these really diverse Cancers
and they're appearing throughout the
body and fortunately we have this
amazing protective mechanism in our
bodies which is the immune system and
this is really what's going to be
leading the fight against cancer
[Music]