Don't start small. Start with what you
have. At the start, nothing is new.
Often not even the idea. The origins of
the Greenpeace Foundation illustrates
this point really well. Greenpeace
changed how we think about the
environment. That was their innovation.
The founders of Greenpeace got started
by trying to stop the United States from
testing a nuclear bomb or with a fishing
boat. They got everyone's attention.
This was certainly a bold idea. It was
also not new. The Golden Rule Expedition
had tried the exact same thing 10 years
earlier and the founders of Greenpeace
knew about it. The Golden Rule was the
name of the boat another group of people
had tried to use to stop the United
States from testing nuclear bombs. There
are many more examples of innovations
born out of repurposing old ideas.
Blockchain, the laser, Tesla, Ford's
affordable car, biotechnology, all
started out as a combination of things
that were not new. You can find more
about these and others in the first two
chapters of my book, Innovating Adors
Manifesto, and in the other materials I
have shared online. This gives you a new
way to think about innovating as
reshaping and repurposing old ideas and
technologies. In fact, because one
technology can lead to many ventures,
and there are multiple ways to chip at a
problem, you do not even need to come up
with that great an idea. You can go
looking for things that someone else
left half finished. Technologies on the
shelf or ideas that did not pan out the
first time around and start big. This is
a bit of a mental shift from how we
imagine innovation. We tend to believe
that innovations have to start small.
That's because the emphasis is on the
word new, which everyone associates with
unproven. But if all you're going to use
is old, this frees you to think about
how you start in a different way. You
can start big as big as your current
resources allow you to. The reason why I
put the emphasis on starting with what
you have is to make you realize that you
do not need to start small. Of course,
I'm not asking you to put your entire
fortune into one single project, but I'm
inviting you to consider what's the
right amount of resources to demonstrate
what you want to do. Whether you start
from a hunch about a problem like the
founders of Greenpeace did with a
well-ressearched technology coming from
a lab or any in between, repurposing
ideas and technologies and starting with
what you have is how you chip at the
problem. You might still wonder about
how to start, when to seek more
resources, and how much. More on that in
the next video.
[Music]