I'm going to discuss today if we start
the slides uh nuclear reactors place
replacing gas turbines and of course the
reason why is the largest source of
electricity in the United States is the
natural gas turbine uh it's relatively
cheap furthermore it can go up and down
like a yo-yo which happens to match
power demand I'm going to give a very
broad view first a broad view of what
the option space is and then I'm going
to drill down on some technologies that
we've been working on at o at at uh MIT.
Next slide.
Whoops. I'm the guy who controls this.
Now, there are four technologies that
can produce dispatchable electricity
from a nuclear power plant and replace
the gas turbine. The first, you can run
the reactor power at variable levels.
The second, you can you can have a base
load reactor with heat storage in a
power cycle. The third, you can have a
base load reactor with a thermodynamic
topping cycle. I'll explain what that is
a little bit later. And the fourth, you
can have what they call cogen, of which
the cogen that's probably most important
is a base load reactor with a hybrid
system that produces electricity and
hydrogen. But th those are the four
options you've got. If there's a fifth
option, I would love to hear about it.
Uh starting point, the electricity grid
is changing. historical grid, high
capital cost, low operating cost, space
load power plants, uh, low capital cost,
high operating cost, dispatchable power
plants, gas turbines, the new grid, lots
of non-dispatchable electricity. Solar
wind is wind is when the sun is out when
uh when it when it blows. And right now,
of course, the rest of the grid is gas
turbines and nuclear power.
Now it's important to understand exactly
what's happening to the the electricity
market. Uh and the thesis I have here is
that variable price of electricity
creates incentive for energy storage.
This happens to be the 2023 California
wholesale electric prices. The vertical
axis is 24 hours in a day. The
horizontal axis is 365 days in a year.
And all those different colors are the
different colors represent different
prices of electricity at different
hours. And what is noteworthy in
California is there's a whole bunch of
hours with negative price electricity.
And then there are other hours of the
time time of the year where you have
really expensive electricity. And what
that says is there's a need for a
dispatchable electricity that sells when
the price is high and maybe buys
electricity when the price is low.
Now let's take a look at the options for
nuclear power plants. Let's start with
the oldest option. Operating reactors
at part load to meet variable
electricity demand has been fun done for
decades.
Old technology
standard offtheshelf uh France has been
doing for 40 over 40 years but a number
of other countries have also done it.
you just reduce the power level of the
reactor when the power demand goes down.
Uh the problem with this is it it costs
a lot of money to build a nuclear power
plant and you'd rather not operate it at
part load uh if you can make beneficial
use of full load capacity. So yes, it's
doable. It's off the shelf, decades and
decades of experience.
The second option is a base load reactor
with heat storage in the power cycle. Uh
this is what I call a first generation
commercial for nuclear. Uh store hot and
cold nitrate salts or other other
liquids. Uh there are of course a
variety of advanced options that are
currently under development.
Uh today hot and cold nitrate salt
thermal energy storage is used in
concentrated solar plants. concentrated
solar plant. You have a big tank of cold
salt. You send it to the concentrated
solar plant, heats it up, and you dump
the hot salt into a hot storage tank.
Separately, you have a power cycle.
Steam power cycle takes hot nitrate
salt, runs it through the power cycle,
generates steam electricity, dumps it in
the cold tank. Uh this was developed for
CSP to reduce capital costs. Uh the
solar power solar input peaks in the
middle of the day. You don't want to
size your power plant for peak output.
So what you do is you size the power
block for average uh power output and
you let the salt tanks go up and down uh
daily. So the hot salt tank fills up in
the middle of the day and it goes all
the way down as you approach evening and
into into the night. It also allows of
course electricity after dark. And the
picture on the right shows one of the
commercial plants. And you can very
easily see the two salt tanks because
they're they're big and the most obvious
things on site after the mirrors.
Now, the same technology enables base
load reactors to provide dispatchable
electricity to the grid to replace gas
turbines. Base load reactor on the right
takes cold salt, heats it up, dumps it
into the hot salt tank. uh the power say
power plant takes the hot salt makes
steam makes electricity and dumps the
salt into the cold tank. Now if it turns
out you have negative priced electricity
or very lowriced electricity the same
system would take electricity off the
grid if it's negative priced why pass up
a bargain and heat up more nitrate salt
to make hot salt whenever the price gets
too low.
Now, Terrap Power is constructing the
Natrium reactor in Wyoming. This will be
the first reactor with nitrate salt heat
storage about 5 and a half hours.
Variable output if you ran this plant at
pace though to be 345 megawatts. The
actual power output is between 100
megawws and 500 megawws. And of course,
the name of the game is to deliver
electricity to the greater time at high
prices. It's in Wyoming at a coal plant
site for one very good reason. They have
a power line to California, the land of
highriced electricity, which makes this
an extremely valuable site. But you have
a minimum assured output of 345
megawatts all the time.
That's current state-of-the-art.
Now, what's new? We've been looking at
adding a steam accumulator that may
enable going from 100 megawatts to 500
megawatts
in less than 15 seconds. In other words,
instead of a slow ramp capability on
your steam plant, we're going to have a
fast ramp capability. So, if the grid uh
needs power in a hurry, we can deliver.
The grid pays for these services, for
these auxiliary services. And what a
steam accumulator is is a big tank of
steam and you get the push button push
the button and what happens is that
steam accelerates up the turbine
generator in the power plant while
you're very rapidly in 15 seconds to
full power. At the meantime the hot
nitrate salt is going through the boiler
and the boiler is making steam but that
takes 5 to 10 minutes to start up. So
this is a fast start mechanism if there
is a demand by the grid for a fast
start.
Uh, we're not exactly talking about a
brand new technology. Here we see a
picture of the 1929,
yes, 1929 Charlottburg power station in
Berlin state-of-the-art accumulators
uh, heat water and pressurized in
pressurized vessel with steam, release
pressure, flashing steam to turbine, uh,
produce electricity. This steam
accumulator was about 1 hour output. It
was fired up or loaded up, I think is
the right term I would use, with a coal
power plant that was sitting right next
door. So, we're sort of deciding to
marry 1929 technology with something a
little newer application. And by the
way, the common use of steam
accumulators that you're most familiar
with is the Navy uses them to launch
airplanes off of carrier decks. you
know, you need a lot of power for about
five seconds.
And so the steam flows into the piston
and the piston goes roaring down the
track and your airplane hopefully is
airborne uh a few seconds thereafter.
Uh as mentioned, fast ramp capability
provides anxillary services opens up new
markets, data centers, defense
applications about 15 second response
time. In comparison, high-speed hydro
start is 90 seconds, five minutes for
gas turbines, and 15 seconds for diesel
generators. So, it's an alternative for
fast start diesel generator.
Now, I should mention there are actually
three generations of heat storage
technologies. Uh we're on generation
one.
Generation two's pilot plants are being
built. And then there's generation
three. And the whole goal here is to
knock down the capital cost further and
further. Uh generation one of course is
commercial. We're working on generation
three and I'm going to give you some
picture of what these advanced
technologies look like. Third generation
crush rock ultra-large heat storage
systems enable long duration storage.
Now when you think about storage, what's
important is it be cheap.
That's the criteria. And so if you want
cheap materials, so far we found the
cheapest material is crushed rock. If
you find a cheaper material, please let
me know.
And we're working on developing a
crushed rock storage system. Initial
work at MIT. It's at a technological
readiness level of a little over four.
So it's early in the game. And we have a
self stupporting
stack of crushed rock
20 30 40 meters high,
20, 30, 40 meters wide. and very long.
And we want want to heat it up. We have
a bunch of hot nitrate salt that we put
drains down on top on sprinklers and
trickles on through the crushed rock to
the pad below.
To get our heat out, we throw cold
nitrate salt on top. Trickles on down,
gets heated up, goes to the power plant.
Now, that sounds very simple. There's a
few minor complications which is why
it's a technological readiness level
four, but it eliminates where the big
cost is on the existing systems. It
eliminates the salt, replace it with
crush rock. The salt's only used for
heat transfer agent. And it replaces a
tank with something that looks like an
aircraft hanger.
And here's again a second summary. Uh
hot salt trickling through crushed rock
recover heat by cold salt trickling on
top. a little more complicated than
that. And the other thing is it's a
freestanding rock pile.
It's got some other internals to make
sure the edges don't the rocks don't
roll down the edge. That's important
because tanks are expensive and we want
to put this into what amounts to an
insulated aircraft hanger. They're
cheap, but this is the nature of
storage. Cheap is better. And if you get
cheap enough, you can do seasonal
storage. Uh this is a case for Texas
where we assume the nuclear plants you
have you have 30 gigawatts online and
200 gawatts electric equivalent in
storage for every gigawatt nuclear you
have. And the chart here on on the right
shows the amount of heat in storage as
you go over the year. In the winter time
you have a winter peak suddenly the
amount of heat storage goes down. When
summer comes the amount of heat in
storage slowly goes down over the summer
months and then it rebuilds in the fall.
It's an option for potentially seasonal
storage and to eliminate all fossil
fuels, but recognize the technological
readiness level is four.
Our second option
is base load nuclear reactors with
thermodynamic power peaking cycles that
is convert lowriced electricity to heat
and use it for a power cycle.
Well, what is a thermodynamic topping
cycle? I'm going to give you an
explanation. I'm not sure if it'll fly
if you don't have an engineering degree.
I apologize for that. Um, the starting
point is that the heat to electricity
efficiency increases with the
temperature of the working fluid in the
power cycle. The steam temperature is
higher, the gas temperature is higher.
As the temperature goes up, the
efficiency of the system goes up.
And a power topping cycle is you add
high temperature heat to boost the
temperature of the of the power fluid
above that of the reactor coolant.
Lightwater reactors with steam cycles,
you double the output if you turn it
into a peaking cycle. Higher temperature
reactors, you use something called a
nuclear air braen cycle. The requirement
is is that the added heat for peak power
has to be at a much higher temperature
than the reactor fluid is.
Now, let's take a look. As you can see,
I'm a good historian here. Back to the
future again. Nuclear thermodynamic
topping cycles are a 1960s
technology.
It's better than 1929.
Indian.1 PWR.
The steam exited this plant at 270
degrees C. It then went into the hot
air. It then went into a superheater, an
oil fired superheater. a boiler
effectively that raised the steam
temperature to a higher temperature of
540 degrees C before it went to the
steam cycle. Much more efficient way of
doing business and very low capital
cost. Now what killed this plant is the
price of oil went up. I don't know if
you remember it but you had the 1960s.
this plant was built in the 1970s. You
had the oil embargo and the price of oil
went through the stratosphere and this
plant was uh half oil and half half
nuclear and that got killed by the the
price of oil. It was when it was built
however the most efficient oilto
electricity plant in the world. The
incremental oil generated more
electricity at a higher efficiency than
any of the competition.
Uh this shows uh the basic cycle. You
got feed water, nuclear reactor, normal
conditions, steam to super heater, stere
heater, you add additional heat, run the
temperature way up and that goes to the
steam turbine and I show the power
cycles below for those who have an
interest. If you take a modern
lightwater reactor, GE or Westinghouse,
uh you can essenti peak power will be
about equal to the base load electricity
that you're producing. So if you're
producing a thousand megawatts you put
on the peaking unit, you get another
thousand megawatts for peak power.
There's an equivalent air nuclear air
braiden cycle. I'm not going to go
through it. This is for higher
temperature reactors. The slides will be
available so you can read the fine print
and it also has my email so you can send
me an email if you have questions about
it.
Now how do you provide that high
temperature heat? Option A, burn fuel,
natural gas, oil, bofuels, hydrogen.
Option B, convert lowpriced electricity
to on the right to very high temperature
heat. That's the option we've been
working at and then use that heat for
peak power.
We can convert lowric electricity into
high temperature heat stored in fire
brick.
A nice technology invented by the
Hittites about 500 BC.
Needs a little modification. We blow air
through channels in the fire brick to
deliver heat as hot air to the customer.
And we show the cycle here where they
have fire brick in a silo, cold air in
the bottom, hot air out the top. We heat
the fire brick by electricity. So it
could be wind, solar, nuclear, whatever
your low price electricity is. Uh the
system has a characteristic that it
delivers hot air to the customer which
means if we run out of heat storage we
can add an auxiliary combustible fuel
oil, gas, bofuels, hydrogen to make uh
to keep on running at whatever
temperature we want.
Now why are we choosing fire brick?
Well, firebrick is the only cheap high
temperature material and we currently
have gigawatt hour heat storage
technologies used in glass plants. When
you're making glass, plate glass, and
plate glass, you have this glass furnace
at the top and the cold air, there's hot
hot air goes over it, heats the glass,
and then the cold exit air at a
temperature up to,500 Celsius, about the
melting point of iron, goes through a
sixstory fire brick structure, deposits
his heat in the fire brick, and then
comes out cold at the bottom of that six
story thing on the left and goes up the
stack. Every hour they switch the fan
direction. Cold air goes up through the
fire brick.
Then you pour on the natural gas and it
goes into the glass furnace. So we have
the technology to store heat cheaply at
a 1000 C if we have a way to heat the
fire brick. The rest of the technology
is commercial.
Uh what we did is we invented
electrically conductive fire brick to
enable lowc cost high temperature
heating. Uh fire bricks is a mixture of
oxides, cheap oxides. We add a dopant
about 1 or 2% of something like nickel
to make it an electrical resistance
heater. The brick is an electrically
conductive and electric conductive
surface between the bricks so we can use
it as a resistance heater. And we have a
startup company called electrified
thermal solutions run by my former
graduate student who's in the process of
commercializing the technology.
Here we show traditional uh electrical
heaters on the left. uh 1100C if you
really push it on the right the fire
example of a fire brick heater
essentially it's a brick wall you look
you want to make a fire brick heater
it's you could lay it like a brick wall
that's you know foot or two feet high
you put current through it away you go
as you can see you get up at the
temperatures we're at it's actually
white hot
and a demo is going to start next month
in uh in the Southwest Research
Institute and you can see some of the
crew in front of want a small demo
that'll do 5 megawatt hours up to up to
uh 1,700 C. If we can pull it off,
that's of course the big question
because it's still in development. Uh it
means we may have a cheap way to eat up
all the world's cheap electricity.
Uh you ain't going to you're going to
sell electricity less than the delivered
price of natural gas or oil. If there's
electricity at less than that, we want
to eat it all up every last kilowatt
hour
and turn it into hot air for commercial
and industrial products.
Well, let's now take a look at the third
option. Hybrid energy systems that is
the co-production
of electricity and hydrogen. This is a
type of co-generation.
Uh the reason I'm talking about this
specific one is the potential scale of
the industry. One of the issues of
co-generation reproducing industrial
heat and electricity to the grid is
who's your customer and what constraints
do they have? It may be that they can't
go up and down and power demand very
much and so they're essentially a base
load electricity generator. So this is
the the last of the technologies that
can convert a nuclear reactor into the
equivalent of a gas turbine.
lowcarbon world uh the hydrogen demand
for the chemical industry may exceed 750
million tons a year. Now when I'm
referring to the chemical industry is
I'm referring to people who need
hydrogen to run some chemical reaction.
We do not assume a single kilogram
is used to heat anything.
So this bunch of customers doesn't care
about the heating value of hydrogen. It
cares about the chemical properties.
Obviously ammonia production that feeds
half the world. Uh you know three
hydrogen atoms and one nitrogen atom. So
you need a lot of hydrogen. The second
is if you decide to decarbonize the
steel industry, you replace uh coke and
coal w with hydrogen as a chemical
reducing agent that pulls the oxygen out
of the iron oxide as water to get iron
to for your steel process. The third
option is liquid hydrocarbons from
solistic biomass which on paper can
replace every single barrel of crude oil
on the planet oil on the planet earth.
By the way, silosic biomass is the part
of the plant you don't eat. Leaves,
trees, grass, kelp,
it's not corn,
you know, it's it's not a protein
vegetable oil. This is a stuff you can't
eat. The rest of the plant that is
non-eable uh with a single exception of
celery, that's the only kind of uh
cellulose that people actually eat. But
of course it has zero nutritional value
because as a human being turns out your
body doesn't know how to take out the
energy value from cellulose.
What we can do is build nuclear reactors
to switch from electricity to hydrogen
and back and export the electricity to
the grid. Uh the important part about
this is it turns out hydrogen on a large
scale not a small scale large scale is
very cheap to store. And what that means
is if we have variable hydrogen
production, we can guarantee steadystate
hydrogen production to the chemical
plant. And that's really important for
the chemical plant operators.
Okay. Okay. Now, the most efficient
nuclear hydrogen production method is
high temperature electrolysis. The
nuclear reactor provides steam and
electricity.
uh this creates the option of diverting
electricity to the grid at times of very
high electric prices. So our nuclear
reactor is most of the time producing
hydrogen and when the price of
electricity gets high we switch the
electricity to the grid.
This system works for chemical plants
because hydrogen on a large scale not a
small scale on a large scale is cheap to
store. Very important distinction.
Hydrogen on a small scale is really
expensive to store. Really, really,
really expensive. That's a separate
discussion.
Here's the system. Hydrogen storage
enables peak electricity to the grid
with steady state delivery of hydrogen
of a base load reactor.
We want to make life boring for the
reactor operators.
Boring is good if you're running a
nuclear power plant. Preferred mode of
operation.
We can send variable electricity to
produce hydrogen and heat. We can also
produce heat that goes to the goes to
the industrial sector. And if the price
of electricity is high, we stop
producing hydrogen or reduce hydrogen
production and shove a few gigawatts
into the dispatchable electricity
market.
But it works because hydrogen is
storeable on a larger scale. So we can
keep the chemical plant guys happy.
Chemical companies do not like shutting
down chemical plants. And the reason why
having worked done startup on chemical
plants is that sometimes it takes two or
three days to get restarted.
And uh this is not fun. You do not want
to be on a startup crew of a chemical
plant. 12-hour days not fun.
And of course it's means you're not
generating any product which means the
chemical company's equally unhappy when
this happens.
Now, the hydrogen requirements if you
want to actually do this, 750 million
tons a year. Now, remember, we're
talking about fertilizer, steel, and
replacing every single last barrel of
crude oil.
So, we're talking about decarbonizing
about 40% of the global demand, global
of the global economy. Not a trivial
task. If we use nuclear reactors, we
were going to need 3200 gawatts,
3200 large plants, which means we can
also deliver 3200 gawatts of peak power
to the grid on demand, which far exceeds
the world's demand for peak electricity.
Alternatively, if we have wind, all we
need is two million square miles
of high quality,
lowcost great plains wind.
Now, we don't have that much in the US.
Globally, I'm not sure. These are global
numbers, but that's the scale. Or if we
want to take natural gas, we only want
to convert half the world's natural gas
production into hydrogen
and sequester the carbon dioxide. But we
decarbonize 40% of the world. Uh the
largest industrial user of course would
be the bofuels operation in this
specific case.
Now some conclusions.
There there are four ways for a nuclear
reactor to replace gas turbines.
Four technologies, four different ways
of thinking about the problem.
The technologies are rapidly changing.
They're advancing very quickly and as a
consequence, I'm afraid I can't give you
a prediction of what which are going to
be the winners and which ones are going
to be the losers. My suspicion is that
different technologies will prove
superior in different parts of the world
with different electrical grids and
different constraints. So that's the
overview. I will stop now and open up
for any questions you might have.
Remember you can get the slides. I think
you can get the slides and uh it's got
my email on it. So you can send me a
note if you want and I'll be happy to
send you more reports than you ever
wanted to read
that go into the gory details of the
major options we've discussed here in
>> well thank you Charles
this was quite enlightening I always
thought that energy storage is based on
batteries but you just gave me
completely different ideas
>> batteries the expensive option
>> the expensive option if it costs more
than crushed rock I have something
against it
>> are here. Any questions? So, we have a
microphone. If you want to ask a
question, I'll I'll pass it on to you.
>> Okay, good.
>> Just in terms
in terms of cheapest version. You mean
sand in terms of because I I've heard of
that solar heating battery with sand
>> sand is one of the competing
technologies and uh that's probably
requires hot air rather than liquid
liquids in it. The reason has to do with
something called capillary action where
when you put some liquid through sand it
tends to hold hold up in the sand and
not flow through. So it's a that's a
technical detail but it's if you're in
sand you probably in a gas heat transfer
because of something called surface
tension. You have a question you catch
me later and I can explain why that
probably is going to sink that option
for liquid heat transfer.
Graham,
>> thank you. Thank you very
>> Thank you very much. This is a wonderful
presentation. I really like it. You
mentioned about pneumonia. Ammonia, I'm
sorry.
>> Yes.
>> U in ammonia production, people can
leverage nuclear instead of other energy
sources. Could you comment like people
call it pink ammonia?
>> Can you comment? There there's a lot of
work on using ammonia for peak
electricity. And if you have to ship uh
an energy source over the ocean, uh
ammonia may be the cheap way to ship it
versus uh something like liquid
hydrogen. So if you're shipping a fuel
for marine applications in particular,
but also for peak power to places like
Japan, uh ammonia will be cheaper to
ship, much cheaper to ship than
hydrogen. And for that reason, the
Japanese have a program developing gas
turbines to burn 100% ammonia. That
ammonia will probably come out of the
Middle East where they take natural gas,
make hydrogen, make ammonia, and
sequester the carbon dioxide
underground. That's one of the
replacement options for exporting
natural gas from the Persian Gulf. My
guess is it might be the winning option,
which is a guess on my part.
>> Hi, very interesting. Sorry. Um, how
sensitive is the time? So, if you've got
sort of this uninsulated pile of rock,
what are the losses? You know, is it
hours or or days?
>> The the problem with with rock with
rock, we're still looking for for
somebody who's what what it's going to
take is going to take somebody who's got
a serious budget because I won't go into
the details, but because of the nature
of the process,
uh, your pilot plant has to be at least
six stories high of crushed rock in an
insulated building. And then you're
going to have the hot nitrate s salt and
the cold nitrate s salt. So this is not
a technology that you're going to get to
a commercial level if you have a $10
million budget. This is a hund00 million
development budget. Uh that's that's the
issue. And I think going in that you
just can't avoid that. Uh my guess is
what's going to happen on crushed rock
is the Chinese will do it first.
A, they have more need than anybody
else, and B, their bottom line is it
might work. We'll try it. I I don't know
if you're familiar with the Chinese
development strategy. They'll give you
the nuclear strategy. There were six
They bought five or six different kinds
of reactors from different vendors. Went
down to one. Try it out full scale.
Throw a thousand engineers at it. What's
the problem? We don't quite do it that
way.
A potential source of crush rock is a
mine mining operation. Would it make
sense to have a plant close to a mine?
>> Um
the problem is you have to be very
careful which rocks you choose. Many
rocks will not tolerate higher
temperatures and they certainly won't
tolerate nitrate salts. So you choose
the cheap rock that is in shippable
distance of where the facility will be
built. cheap rock that's chem chemically
compatible within uh so that that's
what's going to control this. It's
mostly going to be unless you're really
lucky and you happen to have the site of
the right rock, it's going to be the
logistics cost, the train cost to move
the rock. You're talking you're talking
about a big chunk of rock, you know,
okay, so it's only 200 meters long and
20 30 mters wide and 40 meters in
diameter. It's not. This is a big This
is a big construction project, but you
got to pick the right rock.
Super. Any other questions?
So, I have another question. So, when do
you think we're going to see some of
these technologies actually coming into
the market? And what's the adaptation
rate? What's
>> the electrically conductive fire brick?
That's a that's about two years out
because the pilot plant's starting in
December. So that technology for
electrically conductive fire brick
that's going to be commercial within a
year or two assuming we don't run into
problems on the pilot plant. The crush
rock is going to take a little bit
longer. um that probably the Chinese the
fast acceleration with the steam
accumulators depends upon somebody
having a problem where they where
there's a market that says I really want
to accelerate my steam plant quickly and
as soon as the market appears I have no
doubt that GE missishi
or seammens will be more than happy to
uh demonstrate the technology on your
plant it's you know this is going to be
oh you bought our steam turbine, how
would you like to buy option A as an
add-on because
it, you know, it's very tightly tied to
the control systems and the steam
turbines. So that I think the steam
turbine manufacturers are going to be
the the actual vendors in this case, but
they just got to wait until you see a a
big enough market to be worth the
prototype.
>> I have one final question before we
switch over to the next speaker on it.
So you as a research scientist here at
MIT, what do you need from industry
because you've been working all your
lifetime on these technologies?
>> What I need is good entrepreneurs who
have very deep pocketbooks.
That's that's the actual answer. By the
way, I'm not an entrepreneur. I'm a very
good inventor, but I'm not an
entrepreneur and I've always known that.
So that's not my skill set. So you're
I'm the wrong person to ask.
>> Yeah, that's great. All right. Thank you
very much, Charles. Uh really appreciate
it.