the MIT energy initiative presents using
combustion to make lithium ion batteries
electricity storage for the energy
transition written by Nancy W
stoffer for more than a century much of
the world has run on the combustion of
fossil fuels now to avert the threat of
climate change the energy system is
changing notably solar and wind systems
are replacing fossil fuel combustion for
generating electricity and heat and
batteries are replacing the internal
combustion engine for powering Vehicles
as the energy transition progresses
researchers worldwide are tackling the
many challenges that arise silly D has
spent her career thinking about
combustion now an assistant professor in
the department of mechanical engineering
and the class of 1954 Career Development
Professor Den Le's an MIT group that
among other things develops theoretical
models to help understand and control
combustion systems to make them more
efficient and to control the of
emissions including particles of soot so
we thought given our background in
combustion what's the best way we can
contribute to the energy transition says
Deng in considering the possibilities
she notes that combustion refers only to
the process not to what burning while we
generally think of fossil fuels when we
think of combustion the term combustion
encompasses many high temperature
chemical reactions that involve oxygen
and typically emit light and large
amounts of heat she says given that
definition she saw another role for the
expertise she and her team have
developed they could explore the use of
combustion to make materials for the
energy transition under carefully
controlled conditions combusting Flames
can be used to produce not polluting
soot but rather valuable materials
including some that are critical in the
manufacturer of lithium ion
batteries improving the lithium ion
battery by lowering costs the demand for
lithium ion batteries is projected to
Skyrocket in the coming decades
batteries will be needed to power the
growing Fleet of electric cars and to
store the electricity produced by solar
and wind systems so it can be delivered
later when those sources aren't
generating some experts project that the
global demand for lithium ion batteries
may increase tfold or more in the next
decade given such projections many
researchers are looking for ways to
improve the lithium ion battery
technology Deng and her group aren't
material scientists so they don't focus
on making new and better battery
chemistries instead their goal is to
find a way to lower the high cost of
making all those batteries and much of
the cost of making a lithium ion battery
can be traced to the manufacturer of
materials used to make one of its two
electrodes the cathode the MIT
researchers began their search for cost
savings by considering the methods now
used to produce cathode materials the
raw materials are typically salts of
several Metals including lithium which
provides ions the electrically charged
particles that move when the battery is
charged and discharged the processing
technology aims to produce prod tiny
particles each one made up of a mixture
of those ingredients with the atoms
arranged in the specific crystalline
structure that will deliver the best
performance in the finished battery for
the past several decades companies have
manufactured those cathode materials
using a two-stage process called
coprecipitation in the first stage the
metal salts excluding the lithium are
dissolved in water and thoroughly mixed
inside a chemical reactor chemicals are
added to change the acidity the pH of
the mixture and particles made up of the
combined salts precipitate out of the
solution the particles are then removed
dried ground up and put through a SI a
change in PH won't cause lithium to
precipitate so it is added in the second
stage solid lithium is ground together
with the particles from the first stage
until lithium atoms permeate the
particles the resulting material is then
heated or analed to ensure complete
mixing and to achieve the targeted
crystalline structure finally the
particles go through a deag
that have joined together and the
cathode material emerges
co-precipitation produces the needed
materials but the process is timec
consuming the first stage takes about 10
hours and the second stage requires
about 133 hours of a knealing at a
relatively low temperature 750° C in
addition to prevent cracking during a
kneeling the temperature is gradually
ramped up and down which takes another
11 hours the process is thus not only
time consuming but also energy intensive
and costly for the past 2 years D and
her group have been exploring better
ways to make the cathode material
combustion is very effective at
oxidizing things and the materials for
lithium ion batteries are generally
mixtures of metal oxid says Den that
being the case they thought this could
be an opportunity to use a
combustion-based process called Flame
synthesis a new way of making a high
performance cathode
material the first task for Deng and her
team mechanical engineer ing postto Gian
and Zang Valerie elund dun sb20 sm22 and
current graduate students manasa bot and
Shu Zang was to choose a Target material
for their study they decided to focus on
a mixture of metal oxides consisting of
nickel Cobalt and manganese plus lithium
known as ncm811 this material is widely
used and has been shown to produce
cathodes for batteries that deliver high
performance in an electric vehicle that
means a long drive driving range rapid
discharge and recharge and a long
lifetime to better Define their target
the researchers examin the literature to
determine the composition and
crystalline structure of NCM 811 that
has been shown to deliver the best
performance as a cathode material they
then considered three possible
approaches to improving on the
co-precipitation process for
synthesizing NCM 811 they could simplify
the system to cut Capital costs speed up
the process or cut the energy required
our first thought was what if we could
mix together all the substances
including the lithium at the beginning
suang then we would not need to have the
two stages a clear simplification over
co-precipitation introducing fasp one
process widely used in the chemical and
other Industries to fabricate Nano
particles is a type of flame synthesis
called Flame assisted spray paralysis or
fasp Den's concept for using fasp to
make their targeted cathode powders
proceeds as follows the precursor
materials the metal salts including the
lithium are mixed with water and the
resulting solution is sprayed as fine
droplets by an atomizer into a
combustion chamber there a flame of
burning methane heats up the mixture the
water evaporates leaving the precursor
materials to decompose oxidize and
solidify to form the powder product the
Cyclone separates particles of different
sizes and the bag housee filters out
those that aren't useful the collected
particles would then be analed and
deagglomerated to investigate and
optimize this concept the researchers
developed a Labs scale fasp setup
consisting of a homemade ultrasonic
nebulizer a preheating section a burner
a filter and a vacuum pump that
withdraws the powders at form using that
system they can control the details of
the heating process the preheating
section replicates conditions as the
material first enters the combustion
chamber and the burner replicates
conditions as it passes the flame that
setup allowed the team to explore
operating conditions that would give the
best results their experiments showed
marked benefits over co-precipitation
the nebulizer breaks up the liquid
solution and Define droplets ensuring
Atomic level mixing the water simply
evaporates so there's no need to change
the pH or to separate the solids from a
liquid as dang notes you just let the
gas go and you're left with the
particles which is what you want with
lithium included at the outset there's
no need for mixing solids with solids
which is neither efficient nor effective
they could even control the structure or
morphology of the particles that formed
in one series of experiments they tried
exposing the incoming spray to different
rates of temperature change over time
they found that the temperature history
has a direct impact on morphology with
no preheating the particles burst apart
and with rapid preheating the particles
were Hollow the best outcomes came when
they used temperatures ranging from 175°
C to 225° C experiments with coin cell
batteries Laboratory devices used for
testing battery materials confirmed that
by adjusting the preheating temperature
they could achieve a particle morphology
that would optimize the performance of
their
materials best of all the particles
formed in seconds assuming the time
needed for conventional annealing and
deag glomera the new setup could
synthesize the finished cathode material
in half the total time needed for
co-precipitation moreover the first
stage of the co-precipitation system is
replaced by a far simpler setup a saving
in capital costs we were very happy says
D but then we thought if we've changed
the precursor side so the lithium is
mixed well with the salts do we need to
have the same process for the second
stage maybe
not improving the second
stage the key time and energy consuming
step in the second stage is the anink in
today's co-precipitation process the
strategy is to anneal at a low
temperature for a long time giving the
operator time to manipulate and control
the process but running a furnace for
some 20 hours even at a low temperature
consumes a lot of energy based on their
studies thus far Den thought what if we
slightly increase the temperature but
reduce the analing time by orders of
magnitude then we could cut energy
consumption and we might still achieve
the desired crystal structure however
experiments at slightly elevated
temperatures and short treatment times
didn't bring the results they had hoped
for in transmission electron microscope
tem images the particles that formed had
clouds of lightl looking nanoscale
particles attached to their surfaces
when the researchers performed the same
experiments without adding the lithium
those Nano particles didn't appear based
on that and other tests they concluded
that the Nano particles were pure
lithium so it seemed like long duration
of kneeling would be needed to ensure
that the lithium made its way inside the
particles but then they came up with a
different solution to the lithium
distribution problem they added a small
amount just one % by weight of an
inexpensive compound called Ura to their
mixture in tem images of the particles
formed the undesirable nanoparticles
were largely gone toang experiments in
the laboratory coin cells showed that
the addition of Ura significantly
altered the response to changes in the
analing temperature when the Ura was
absent raising the analing temperature
led to a dramatic decline in performance
of the cath of material that formed but
with the Ura present the performance of
the material that formed was uneffective
Ed by any temperature change that result
meant that as long as the Ura was added
with the other precursors they could
push up the temperature shrink the
analing time and omit the gradual ramp
up and cool down process further Imaging
studies confirm that their approach
yields the desired crystal structure and
the homogeneous Elemental distribution
of the Cobalt nickel manganese and
lithium within the particles moreover in
tests of various performance measures
their materials did as well as materials
produced by copre itation or by other
methods using longtime heat treatment
indeed the performance was comparable to
that of commercial batteries with
cathodes made of NCM 811 so now the long
and expensive second stage required in
standard co-precipitation could be
replaced by just 20 minutes of a
kneeling at about 870 de C plus 20
minutes of cooling down at room
temperature Theory continuing work and
planning for scale
up while experimental evidence supports
their approach Deng and and her group
are now working to understand why it
works getting the underlying physics
right will help us design the process to
control the morphology and to scale up
the process to stting and they have a
hypothesis for why the lithium nanop
particles in their flame synthesis
process end up on the surfaces of the
larger particles and why the presence of
Ura solves that problem according to
their Theory without the added Ura the
metal and lithium atoms are initially
well mixed within the droplet but as
heating progresses the Li diffuses to
the surface and ends up as nanop
particles attach to the solidified
particle as a result a long a kneeling
process is needed to move the lithium in
among the other atoms when the Ura is
present it starts out mix with the
lithium and other atoms inside the
droplet as temperatures rise the Ura
decomposes forming Bubbles as heating
progresses the bubbles burst increasing
circulation which keeps the lithium from
diffusing to the surface the lithium
ends up uniformly distributed so the
final treatment can be very short the
researchers are now designing a system
to suspend a droplet of their mixture so
they can observe the circulation inside
it with and without the Ura present
they're also developing experiments to
examine how droplets vaporize employing
tools and methods they have used in the
past to study how hydrocarbons vaporize
inside internal combustion engines they
also have ideas about how to streamline
and scale up their process in
co-precipitation the first stage takes
10 to 20 hours so what one batch at a
time moves on to the second stage to be
annealed in contrast the novel fast
process generates particles in 20
minutes or less a rate that's consistent
with continuous processing in their
design for an integrated synthesis
system the particles coming out of the
back house are deposited on a belt that
carries them for 10 or 20 minutes
through a furnace a deag
glomeratus apart and the cathode powder
emerges ready to be fabricated into a
high performance cathode for lithium ion
battery the cathode powders for high
performance lithium ion batteries would
thus be manufactured at unprecedented
speed low cost and low energy use Den
notes that every component in their
integrated system is already used in
industry generally at a large scale and
high flowthrough rate that's why we see
great potential for our technology to be
commercialized and scaled up she says
where our expertise comes into play is
in designing the combustion chamber to
control the temperature and heating rate
so as to produce particles with the
desired morphology and while a detailed
economic analysis has yet to be
performed it seems clear that their
technique will be faster the equipment
simpler and the energy use lower than
other methods of manufacturing cathode
materials for lithium ion batteries
potentially a major contribution to the
ongoing energy
transition This research was supported
by the MIT Department of mechanical
engineering