Hi, I'm Dr. Praep Narajin and I'm the
director of preventive cardiology and
genetics researcher at Massachusetts
General Hospital and the Broad Institute
of MIT and Harvard.
South Asians have a substantially higher
risk of atheroscllerotic cardiovascular
disease compared with most other
ethnicities. Atherosclerosis is the
underlying plaque buildup that leads to
heart attacks. US practice guidelines
now recognize South Asian ancestry as a
risk-enhancing factor. That's because
available clinical risk estimators that
doctors use underpredict cardiovascular
disease risk in South Asian populations.
The risk tools currently used were
developed using cohorts with a minimal
number of individuals of South Asian
ancestry. And because risk is higher in
South Asian individuals, having a
populationspecific tool to identify risk
is important for disease prevention.
Given this and the increased
cardiovascular disease in South Asians,
we developed the our health polygenic
risk in South Asian study, also known as
our health PRS.
Hi, I'm Dr. Aner Patel and I'm a
cardiologist and researcher at
Massachusetts General Hospital focusing
on multimodal cardiovascular risk
prediction.
Your DNA contains instructions that
guide how your body works and grows.
While most of our DNA is the same, we
each have small differences that make us
unique. Some of these differences can
slightly raise or lower your chance of
developing certain health conditions
like heart disease. Apologetic score is
a single number that adds up the effects
of thousands of these small DNA
differences. It gives us a way to
estimate your genetic risk for a
condition like coronary artery disease.
For South Asians, the risk of heart
disease is higher, even in people who
are young or otherwise healthy. Knowing
your genetic risk can help you take
action early before problems start. To
calculate a polygenic score, scientists
look at many genetic variants. Each one
may increase or decrease your risk just
a little, but together they create a
bigger picture of your inherited risk.
Your polygenic score tells you how your
genetic risk compares to others, but it
doesn't predict the future. It can't say
for sure whether you will or you won't
get heart disease. Many other things
like your diet, exercise, smoking
habits, and blood pressure also play a
big role. If your genetic risk is high,
there are proven steps you can take to
lower your overall risk, and your doctor
can help you decide what's right for
you. The RH Health PRS looks at your
genetic risk for coronary artery
disease. In the future, it may also
include risk scores for other related
conditions.
Hi, I'm Dr. Kavia Parachuri and I'm the
clinical operations director for
cardiovascular medicine at the
Massachusetts General Hospital where I'm
also a preventive cardiologist and
researcher. When a patient walks into
clinic, we want to offer them care
that's both predictive and personalized.
That's where polygenic risk scores come
into play. Polygenic risk scores can be
a powerful addition in the clinic. They
help us identify patients who may still
be at increased risk for heart disease,
even if their traditional risk markers
like cholesterol or blood pressure look
fine. With this insight, we can guide
prevention more effectively. From
starting medications sooner to boosting
lifestyle interventions or scheduling
screenings more often. The beauty of PRS
is that it bridges research and clinical
care. It empowers our patients
information and it gives us as
clinicians a sharper lens to catch heart
disease before it happens, especially in
communities that have historically been
under represented in routine guidelines.
It is important to clarify though that
polygenic risk report returned in the
RHL participants is a research finding,
not a clinically validated result or
diagnosis. Participants are advised to
consult with their healthcare providers
to discuss questions and implications
before making any clinical care
decisions.
>> In order to be eligible to receive your
polygenic risk score report, be sure to
sign up for the Our Health main study
and send back a completed saliva kit.
For more information, visit
ourhealthstudy.org
and navigate to the other research
projects PRS tab. Thank you for your
interest.