okay uh thanks for that great
introduction uh actually Yugi's talk was
a great uh uh introduction also for what
I want to talk about uh so traditionally
uh CO2 uh is first uh captured into a
pallet reactor into calcium carbonate
and then uh into high Purity CO2 when
when we c on it and then it's passed to
this gashes electrolyzer into Co or
other products C2 products so what I'm
going to tell you today is a way to
convert uh liquid to liquid so is
captured as a bicarbonate uh hc3 1 minus
and then uh is turned into this uh
highly concentrated alkaline metal uh
for example potassium um formate uh
liquid and uh as Yuki mentioned uh there
is this problem of carbon efficiency of
the current room temperature
electrolyzers and and and one big
problem is with the crossover from the
castled uh so a lot of the an exchange
membranes uh couldn't stop the carbonate
from car uh from cross over because
carbonate 2 minus is an anine and uh the
other issue is is actually
thermodynamics how do you maintain
steady state pH as you're operating this
electrolyzer so uh what we try to show
is that is indeed possible by uh
engineering the uh partial pressure of
CO2 uh and by selecting the membrane to
achieve a stat State operation and get a
very high carbon deficiency uh from this
CO2 capture uh potassium bicarbonate
liquid to uh potassium formate liquid
and uh uh as you see here uh when you
have uh this uh carbon capture uh Fe
stock uh some of it uh after the
electrolyzer most of it is actually
unreacted and some of it even cross over
to the anod side and so you re really
waste a lot of the carbon uh just
captured because of the inefficiency and
because of the design of the
electrolyzer uh what we have done is to
use a near neutral uh pH instead of
alkaline uh pH and use a Katon exchange
membrane instead of a bipolar membrane
or a uh Anon exchange membrane and it's
very important uh to maintain uh this pH
balance uh in steady state operation as
Yuki mentioned if you're actually uh
consuming the uh hydroxy in the in the
solution then that's actually not a uh a
steady state operation so by uh uh
engineering the uh overhead space so one
thing is you have to make sure uh the
partial pressure of CO2 uh is not uh the
air condition but it's a 1 atm then uh
you have a lot more of this pink stuff
which is the monovalent hc31 minus
instead of co32 minus and that's
actually key for uh maintaining this pH
balance so uh we demonstrate uh in uh
dilute uh potassium uh bicarbonate Fe
stock uh initially we show that uh when
we uh operate the castle light in an an
open air uh in free circulation then the
uh formate yield is very low 6% meaning
that uh you know for all the uh
potassium uh bicarbonate we only have 6%
conversion into form M that's not good
but uh when we have a sealed bottle uh
to maintain a a a high uh partial
pressure of CO2 overhead then uh we can
enhance that to 94% and the proof of the
uh uh formate product is both in the uh
MMR as well as uh in the uh xrd after
crystallization and then we increase it
to 1 M of potassium bicarb bate uh and
we get an yield of 96 97% for potassium
bicarbonate and for sodium bicarbonate
is
93% uh the fire efficiency uh is uh
still uh not very high uh is only uh 30%
but that's uh greatly improved by uh
putting in a 3M uh feast stock so this
is very concentrated uh potassium
bicarbonate and we get uh very very high
conversion version so we get eventually
the formate weight percent is uh 16
weight per of the liquid so uh it's
nearly 100% conversion uh and we get so
much uh uh potassium formate uh that
that we can uh just uh uh evaporate the
the water and we can get a solid uh
potassium formate Fuel and we can repeat
uh this for 100 hours over you know we
can exhaust the Fe stock through this
complete version for four Cycles in this
kind of uh lab scale
electrolyzer now once you have uh the
potassium uh formate uh you can put it
in uh this uh uh direct formate Fu cell
so this is not our uh pattern this was
uh uh 13 years ago that people show just
by throwing this pum formate into the uh
this alkaline solution you can uh get a
a decent uh power out put so if we
compare with uh the standard which is
hydrogen Fu cell uh now uh there is uh
methano economy ammonia economy but both
methano and economy uh uh both meth and
ammonia are kind of toxic uh methano
also have a poisoning problem so in
direct meal Fu cell you really uh get a
very low power uh output uh in contrast
in the direct formate F cell uh you are
not as good as the hydrogen but uh it's
quite a bit better than a mthal direct
methal Fu
cell and uh good thing about uh this uh
uh formate uh uh Alkali metal formate uh
salt is uh it's really uh uh safe so I
want to draw analogy to water
electrolyzer and hydrogen fuel cell so
we know that uh in the uh water
electrolyzer you supply electricity you
get
uh hydrogen gas on one electrode and
oxygen gas on the other electrode in the
fu cell we recombine them and we get
electricity out now on a per molecule
basis uh you get uh about uh 5.9
electron volt per reaction uh now if you
look at this uh uh between the uh carbon
capture product potassium uh uh
bicarbonate uh so this is like the water
uh with the uh reduced fuel which is the
potassium formate then all is left I
mean all that's different is O2 so it's
complete analogous uh this is like water
and this is like hydrogen on a per moo
basis this is actually more energetic is
6.9 electron volt per per reaction now
of course uh there's a lot of baggage
right so there is a potassium cation and
there is also a uh CO2 in there so it's
on a per weight basis is much less
energy efficient than
hydrogen uh but the benefit is uh it's
really uh safe and stable so there are
actually people who have look at molten
uh uh formate salt uh and they find that
it does not corrode carbon steel uh uh
you know even in molten form for 2,000
hours and in fact you have these uh
formate salts for example this sodium
copper formate in organic salt in a lot
of the Heritage objects and you can
pretty much kind of uh digest this uh uh
Sal and you wouldn't have a problem this
is sort of the uh MSDS uh safety uh
sheet uh it's actually used as a uh
deicing salt uh potassium uh or sodium
formate is it's uh very safe
nonflammable
non-toxic uh and so uh uh again uh on a
per molecule basis it's uh it's is quite
uh quite good now what about uh you know
uh in an engineering setting uh so we
are comparing uh always with the
hydrogen now uh hydrogen gravimetrically
is of course very good but it has to
have a big uh auxiliary component so
this is a Toyota Mirai uh hydrogen uh uh
tank and to store five kilogram of
hydrogen uh you need uh uh this uh uh uh
90 kilogram of carbon fiber polymer
composite to store it at 700 atmosphere
so compared to this tank uh this uh salt
you know you can just dig a tank in your
backyard dump it inside uh it's uh about
onethird gravimetric energy density as
this tank uh and about 70% volumetric
energy density as this tank so uh uh we
think this is uh pretty pretty
advantageous and uh the other question
we have is you know uh where do you get
so much uh uh sodium hydroxide or
potassium hydroxide uh now traditionally
you get this from the Chlor alkal
electrolyzer process but in that process
you also get chlorine gas so if you
imagining you know uh kiloton sorry
gigaton scale to replace all the fossil
fuel uh economy we need a lot of
potassium or or sodium uh hydroxide and
so one idea is to uh mine the alkaline
Bal rocks so there are a lot of these
kind of volcanic rocks with excess
potassium oxide or pottassium hydroxide
so you don't take it from uh let's say
sodium carbonate because to do that you
have to release CO2 back to the
atmosphere so we look for rock which
have this excess of alkalinity uh inside
and you also have this kind of advanced
weathering schemes where you have also
this
insoluble alkaline uh oxy side so the
idea is to pump CO2 inside and the uh
soluble part you pump out to drive this
uh formate economy but then the uh
insoluble part you just leave it as a
permanent uh
sequestration uh now we also now
developing Catalyst uh for this both the
fuel cell and as well as for the
electrolyzer because right now uh the
round the trip Energy Efficiency is
still pretty poor is around only uh less
than 30% so uh what we're trying to do
here is to use AI to look for
multicomponent catalyst so here we have
this precursor where and we do the high
temperature treatment to get this High
entropy Catalyst and then we do this
automated uh three electrode kind of uh
catalysis
search uh we are also using this method
for uh battery electrolytes as well and
what you see here is actually a
semi-automatic where there's still a
human after we have this uh
multicomponent liquid electroly still
drop it on a Co cell for electrochemical
testing we're also doing quite a bit of
generative Avi looking at literature to
come up with uh better uh formulations
uh so combining experimental data with
computational
data and uh in this space uh we have
actually encountered quite a bit of
challenges uh so juren who was the
student who put together this workflow
found that there's still a lot of
irreproducibility even though we use
automation uh in the in the system
because there's still uh actually I'm
going to show I mean if I have time I'm
going to show you why there's still a
lot of uh uncontrollable factors uh even
though it's fully automated so there is
also issues with reconfigurability so
the current robotic workflows are pretty
rigid and pretty subcritical in size so
different automated Labs need to connect
with each other and you need to
interoperate and exchange data and
samples and so forth uh but after after
about two years I eventually we're able
to sort of look at catalysts which have
multiple elements and if you look at you
know human uh cataly search usually
people stop at four to five metallic
elements uh because human mind kind of
get confused uh Beyond uh you know four
or five Dimensions but the computers
with active learning have have none of
those so we're able to do uh this eight
dimensional search and this actually uh
received a uh best student award in this
Europe's
conference and uh the last slide is also
in terms of modeling uh recently we're
able to come up with so-call universal
potential that allows us to study tens
of thousand atoms so much more
computation efficient than traditional
quantum mechanical calculations but yet
at uh density functional Theory kind of
accuracy and able to simulate the whole
periodic table so uh on computational
front we also have uh this uh deep
learning driven uh fundamental modeling
approach that can combine with the high
throughput uh Catal search and then
hopefully that is integrated with Device
level and and sort of drive this kind of
format economy so the final sort of uh
uh slide is just to show that this is
analogous so we try to achieve a steady
state pH electrolyzer that does this
inorganic uh kind of you can think of
this as as water and this is the
hydrogen gas but there is an
electrolyzer and F cell so I think we're
able to show this can be a closer cycle
so with that I'd like to thank you and
welcome any
[Applause]
questions have questions on on pigeon
hole questions from the
audience please raise your
hands any questions any comments
oh if there are no questions then okay
we have a
question thank you and it's a very
similar question to the one I had before
this is an absolutely fascinating you've
proposed potentially there's this
alternative and you have some
some data to to support that what will
it take to bring that to an industrial
kind of scale and is it really a
technical barrier or is it more of a
politics and Regulatory barrier at that
point so right now it's still uh
relatively low TRL so what we have is we
have a few centimeter by few centimeter
electrolyzer and uh we need to increase
the temperature and also the overhead
pressure to uh uh increase the current
density right now is 0.1 ampere per
centimet squared to be really uh
competitive against hydrogen for example
we need to be uh one or two amp per cm
squar and we think to do that we need to
engineer the Catalyst we also need to go
to higher temperature and pressure and
so uh sort of situating in a university
lab we do have issues with you know we
need funding and and also you know uh um
I would say a multidisciplinary approach
uh to increase the you know intensify
this process right now it is uh still at
a university lab level
question any more
questions where oh I have a question uh
can you read the question the screen uh
Professor
Julie how much energy needed uh gig per
Tong uh so uh we are uh as I said uh
about uh 30% efficient so this is much
less than hydrogen cycle so whatever
hydrogen number you get uh you sort of
need to multiply that by maybe a factor
two so uh so right now the round trip
Energy Efficiency is is quite low still