Chemical engineering at
MIT and former Director
of the MIT Energy Initiative.
It's my pleasure to welcome you
to this webinar in which we're
going to present results of
a study on the role of fusion
in a decarbonized
electricity system.
The full report for the study
is being released today.
This study was done
by the MIT Energy
Initiative in collaboration with
MIT's Plasma Science and Fusion
Center, and involved the
research and analysis
of an interdisciplinary team
of more than 30 researchers,
with expertise ranging from
nuclear science and engineering,
to economics and policy.
Fusion has long
captured the imagination
of those interested in
emissions-free, abundant energy.
With more than 40 fusion startup
companies and more than 100
government-supported
fusion projects,
there has never been more
momentum and enthusiasm
for the role of fusion
in the energy transition.
Two characteristics
make fusion particularly
important to the
energy transition.
First, that it can provide
zero carbon firm power.
This is not only essential to
the future electricity system,
there simply are not many
options for providing it.
Second, fusion can
also meet needs
for scalable energy-dense
generation capacity.
So the time is
right to understand
how fusion power could
transform electricity generation
in the decades ahead.
Among the questions we
addressed in this study
are how fusion will
complement and coexist
with other low-carbon energy
technologies, deployment
scale and global distribution,
sensitivity to costs,
sensitivity to
emissions constraints,
renewable resources,
and critical materials
and supply chains.
Not only can this understanding
be helpful to strategic planners
and policy-makers,
but it can also
be helpful to those involved
in fusion commercialization,
because it provides economic
targets for the use of fusion
in electricity markets.
This better quantifies the
technical design challenges
for fusion developers
with respect
to pricing, availability,
and load following.
To dive into the study, I'd
like to turn the program over
to Randy Field, who is Director
of Research at the MIT Energy
Initiative and was executive
director of the study.
Randy?
Thank you very much,
Professor Armstrong.
And thank you all for
attending the webinar today.
Before discussing
the fusion study,
I'm going to take a very
brief moment to give you
an overview of fusion.
When two nuclei
fuse together, they
release a tremendous
amount of energy,
more than a million times the
energy released per unit mass
from combusting of fossil fuels.
And this energy source does
not release greenhouse gases.
Thus, fusion has great
potential as a energy
source going forward.
However, to enable fusion
to occur at a useful scale,
we need very high
temperatures, and we
must bring the
fusion fuels together
via confinement to
enable them to fuse.
There are various categories
of confinement methods.
One method is
magnetic confinement,
where a very strong
magnetic field
is used to ensure the fuel ions
are kept close together and away
from the walls of the reactor.
Another method is
inertial confinement,
where lasers or
projectiles are used
to rapidly compress and
heat up the fuel capsule.
A third method is magneto
inertial confinement,
which uses a combination of the
prior two confinement methods.
These confinement methods have
been successfully demonstrated
in experiments, and
fusion has been achieved.
However, the challenge is in
the engineering and economics.
Commercial success
for fusion energy
requires that we build
economically-viable systems
to handle the high temperatures
and the high-energy particles
that are released,
and also, the ability
to convert the released
energy into electricity.
Each fuel type and
confinement method
has its own set of
engineering challenges
and its own
innovative solutions.
As Professor Armstrong stated,
given the great potential
for fusion, it deserves
a close examination
to understand how fusion
power plants could
transform the energy generation
in the decades ahead.
We started this project
in fall of 2022,
and we organized the analysis
along four major work streams.
These were examine the global
deployment of fusion power
plants in all
regions of the world
out to the end of the century.
We also analyzed the
subregional grid at grid scale
to understand how fusion will
fit in with the generation mix
when you have different
resources available.
We also assessed
critical materials
and manufactured components
that are needed for fusion
to understand
potential bottlenecks
and to build out the fleet
of fusion power plants.
We also examined
key cost-drivers
for fusion power plants.
I also want to take
a moment to point out
that this study intentionally
does not make predictions
about when fusion will
be deployed commercially,
or which fusion technology will
come first, or which fusion--
or what will be the cost
of fusion in the future.
Instead, we have conducted
a scenario analysis
and sensitivity
analysis in order
to focus on the conditions
required for fusion
to be deployed at scale.
Now we will move on
to the main findings
from the study with a
series of presentations
by several members
of the project team.
And I will be starting
with Sergey Paltsev, who
led the global analysis
workstream for the study.
Sergey is an economist, and
he is the deputy director
for the MIT Center for
Sustainability, Science,
and Strategy, and he is also
a senior research scientist
for the MIT Energy Initiative.
Sergey?
Thank you, Randy.
Stressed in the
earlier remarks, there
are substantial uncertainties
about several aspects
on the technological
side of energy.
On the economic side, one
of the goals of this study
is to provide to
technology developers
the indicators of the goals
for the potential economic case
for fusion energy.
To better understand
these indicators,
we assess several scenarios.
Details of the scenarios
are provided in the report,
but let me very
briefly orient you
about the major settings
of these scenarios.
First, we assessed the
world, which is on its path
to decarbonization goals.
And in all scenarios, the
world reaches the goal
of stabilizing the global
temperature at 1.5 degrees
Celcius.
In these scenarios, we do not
force any particular technology,
but rather, they compete based
on their relative economic
competitiveness.
Second, we evaluated
several cases
for the cost of zero carbon
dispatchable technology,
like fusion, and we
evaluate the full dynamics
of the costs over time.
And for simplicity,
we label the cases
for fusion in terms of their
overnight capital costs in 2050.
So it means that before
2050, the costs are higher,
and after 2050, the
costs are decreasing.
And the full curves are
provided in the report,
but for simplicity, you will
see these labels, $8,000,
$5,600 per kilowatt, and
these are the costs for 2050.
To assess the potential
societal value,
we compared the scenarios
where the fusion does not
exist with the
scenarios where fusion
exists at different costs.
So, for example, where fusion
exists at $8,000 per kilowatt,
you can see, represented
in the blue line,
the societal value
of the fusion.
And, of course, if fusion
developers are able to reduce
their costs, in this example,
to $5,600 per kilowatt,
the economic value
for society is higher.
And that example is given by
the yellow line on this graph.
We can also aggregate
those benefits
over time and over the century.
Compared to a scenario
without fusion,
the global cumulative GDP would
be 0.4% higher in our base case
of $8,000, and if the costs
are lower, to $5,600, well,
then the benefits are higher.
In that particular case,
it's about 1% increase
in the global GDP if fusion
energy enters the mix.
So these results
indicate that investment
in developing and
deployment of fusion energy
can create a large societal
value for the global economy
and support the efforts to
achieve decarbonization goals
over the course of the century.
Next slide, please.
We also ask the
question, how large
is the contribution of fusion
energy to the global power
generation mix?
And in this graph,
in these diagrams,
in these four diagrams, you see
different cases for different
costs of the fusion, where the
value of the cost from less than
$3,000 per kilowatt, to more
than $11,000 per kilowatt.
And you can see the results
in this magenta color
for fusion, that the share in
the global power generation mix
varies from less than
10% to about half.
And this show that the
contribution of fusion
can be quite large, but this
sizeable deployment of fusion
is going to be mostly in the
second half of the century.
Next slide, please.
To realize these sizable
contributions of fusion,
the technological, economic,
and regulatory challenges
of fusion energy
needs to be addressed,
and we need to start
addressing them now
to have the meaningful
deployment by mid-century.
As you can see from
these illustrations,
we found that initial deployment
is strongest in the United
States and Europe.
The largest increase in
fusion takes place in India
during the last three
decades of the century.
And Africa is a late
adopter of fusion,
but seeing very strong growth
in the late of the century.
We also stress that these
results depend on many factors,
and some of them are
listed on this slide.
Of course, many aspects
of fusion operations
are beyond the scope
of our global modeling,
and therefore, the
exact numerical values
should be treated with a
great degree of caution.
We provide some more granular
results in this next session
and in the report.
I want to finish my
part by emphasizing
that with all
inherent uncertainty
about the potential
cost reductions
in technological options,
one message is very clear,
the successful resolution
of technological challenges
and appropriate
regulatory incentives.
Fusion can provide a
substantial contribution
to the world that requires
the expanding electrification.
And it helps the global
society to reach and sustain
its decarbonization goals.
Thank you.
Randy, back to you.
Thank you very much, Sergey.
Next up is Amanda
Farnsworth, who
recently graduated from MIT with
a PhD in chemical engineering.
Amanda worked on the subregional
grid analysis workstream
for the study.
Over to you, Amanda.
Thanks, Randy.
So in this particular
section of the report,
we used a different model, ideal
grid, to zoom in a little bit,
looking specifically
at the United States
and comparing and contrasting
the adoption of fusion
within the different
regions that are highlighted
in the map on the right.
We looked at generator buildout
at a variety of different carbon
ceilings, ranging from 50
to 1 gram of CO2 equivalent
per kilowatt hour.
And just as a reference, grams
of CO2 equivalent per kilowatt
hour marks about an 85% decrease
from our 2023 national average,
and a 90% decrease
from our 2015 levels.
So with all this data on
optimized generator fleets,
we were able to
see which regions
saw different roles of fusion
given the same constraints.
We adopted two main metrics
to quantify fusion's role.
First, penetration, which just
measures what level of adoption
we're seeing in
general in comparison
to the national
average, and the second
is sensitivity,
which measures how
much fusion penetration changes
as we adjust our carbon ceiling.
We've grouped together the
regions with similar fusion
trends to better understand the
characteristics of those regions
which affect fusion.
I'll walk you through
this chart on the slide
here which summarizes our
findings really well, starting
on the left, with the
regions which saw the highest
need for fusion, and then
moving to the ones which
saw less need for fusion.
So first, the
Atlantic and Southeast
saw high penetration
and low sensitivity,
meaning that they saw a large
amount of fusion present
at all carbon caps
that we tested.
This is because these regions
have very limited and weak
onshore wind resources,
and also don't
have any alternative
dispatchable low-carbon
technologies, such as
hydro or geothermal.
Next, we have California,
the Northeast,
and the Southwest, which saw
moderate fusion adoption.
We didn't see any fusion at 50
grams of CO2 per kilowatt hour,
but installations were
reaching up to 50% of demand
at the deepest
decarbonization levels.
These regions have moderate
onshore wind resources
and decent low-carbon-supporting
technologies.
The Northwest saw the
lowest penetration
and a low sensitivity
level, meaning
we didn't see a lot
of fusion until we
reached lower emissions caps.
And even at those low
caps, the penetration
did stay relatively low.
This is because the Northwest
has decent wind resources
and a large amount of
geothermal and hydro, which
fusion is competing with.
Lastly, we have the
Central, North Central,
and Texas regions, which saw
low penetration, but high
sensitivity.
There was no fusion adoption
until deep decarbonization
levels, but when fusion is
adopted, it reaches almost 50%
of demand in some regions.
These regions have the
strongest wind resources,
but don't have any alternative
low-carbon-supporting
technologies.
This analysis summarizes
the driving factors
behind fusion adoption.
First and foremost, you need
decarbonization targets.
Without carbon constraints, the
role of fusion is very limited.
But fusion plays
an important role
for all regions at deep
decarbonization targets,
with installations reaching
at least 25% of demand
in all regions at our deepest
decarbonization level,
1 gram of CO2 per kilowatt hour.
Secondly, fusion adoption
is dependent on your more
conventional renewable
energy resources, wind,
what are your capacity factors?
What are your buildout limits?
And then, also,
we know that it's
competing with alternative
firm low-carbon technologies,
your hydro and your geothermal.
Thank you very much, Amanda.
I will now introduce
Ruaridh MacDonald, who
received his PhD in nuclear
science and engineering at MIT,
and he is a research scientist
at the MIT Energy Initiative.
Ruaridh worked on the
subregional grid workstream
for this project.
He actually zoomed in to
look at the New England area
and the potential role for
fusion in that context.
Over to you, Ruaridh.
Great.
Thanks very much, Randy.
So we studied fusion control
in the New England grid
in greater detail using a GenX
model of the ISO New England
grid and reservoir hydro
resources in Quebec for 2050.
This grid has
relatively limited sites
to construct onshore
wind and solar,
so other low-emission resources
have an important role to play,
including fusion power.
These three plots show the
installed capacity, generation,
and capacity factors
of the fusion fleet
as a function of the fusion
power plant capital cost
and for three different
emission intensity limits.
The left plot shows how the
installed capacity of the fleet
increases as the
capital costs fall.
The changing gradients
in Patos correspond
to fusion plants substituting
for the different competing
resources.
The peak load of the ISO New
England grid is approximately 60
gigawatts in this scenario, so
this 50% value is a 30-gigawatt
fleet.
The rightmost
point of each curve
is the fusion power plant cost
at which the first reactor
is added to the grid.
This is essentially a cost
target for fusion designers.
The cost targets
are 6 and 1/2, 8,
and $14,000 per
kilowatt at the 50, 12,
and 5 grams CO2 per kilowatt
hour emission intensity rates,
respectively.
These cost targets are slightly
lower than they might be today
because we're using 2050
costs for alternatives,
such as renewables, storage,
and natural gas for CCS units,
but on the other
hand, we're also
assuming 2050 emission
limits, which, as we can see,
significantly determine the
cost targets for fusion power.
The other two subplots
show how the fusion fleets
share of generation
and capacity factors
changed with the
fusion plant costs.
At 12 and 50 grams
CO2 per kilowatt hour,
we see the trends most
of us would expect.
A small, moderately
expensive fusion fleet
operates mostly as baseload.
If the fusion
plants cost more, it
begins to substitute for
more technologies as a larger
fraction of generation
and therefore also
has a slightly lower
capacity factor.
However, we were
surprised to see
that with the strictest
emission intensity limits,
very expensive fusion plants
are operated at low capacity
factors.
When we investigated
this, we found
that it's because it's difficult
to meet this emission intensity
target with natural gas
and CCS units alone.
Natural gas units
can only operate
for a small fraction
of the year,
so you must construct additional
storage and renewable generation
in order to meet the demand.
And this is a very expensive
way of going about things.
And that creates an
opportunity for fusion
as a clean,
dispatchable resource
to operate in a variable manner.
And so even though
it's expensive,
it has an important role to play
in replacing those underutilized
alternative resources.
Operating with this low
of a capacity factor
also reduces the maintenance
costs of the fusion plant
by reducing the rate at which
radiation-facing components can
be replaced.
Next slide, please.
So these results clearly
hinge on the alternatives
that were in the market
against fusion power plants,
but in particular, natural
gas, their combined cycle
units with CCS.
So these plots show
the installed capacity
of the fusion fleet with and
without natural gas CCS units
being available.
Without CCS units, fusion
becomes the primary alternative
to excess renewables
and storage,
and it's able to cost roughly
$4,000 per kilowatt more than
in the base case.
While it's unlikely that New
England won't have any CCS
units, we wanted to understand
the impact of this change,
as there are plenty of
regions in the world where
natural gas is more expensive,
or CO2 sequestration
at large scale may be
expensive or impossible.
And lastly, we've assumed a 95%
capture rate for the CCS unit,
regardless of how the
natural gas unit operates,
whether as a base
load or as a peaker,
and that might not be
feasible in the future.
And so these are
the bookend cases
of how fusion costs can be
impacted by the presence
or absence of natural gas.
Thanks very much.
Thank you very much, Ruaridh.
At this point, we'll go
on to another work stream.
Professor Dennis Whyte and
postdoc Theodore Mouratidis
led the work stream
on supply chain
for materials and
manufactured parts.
Our assessment found that
different technologies
are at very different
stages of maturity.
In the report, we
identify issues
and potential bottlenecks.
A key point is
that additional R&D
is required to develop some
materials and manufacturing
technologies as
needed for fusion.
This is more often the
case for technologies
that have little or no
markets outside of fusion.
An example is tungsten heavy,
which is a very dense alloy that
can handle the harsh
conditions in a fusion reactor,
whereas other technologies,
such as high-temperature
superconductors, have strong
commercial opportunities
in non-fusion applications.
Thus, those supply chains
are more developed.
Next, we also looked at
the techno economics.
Professor Koroush Shirvan
and graduate student Layla
Araiinejad led our
techno economic analysis.
In this cost analysis,
we examined prior studies
that assessed the costs or--
the costs for alternative
fusion configurations.
We also conducted a
bottoms-up analysis.
One key observation is that
the fusion reactor equipment
is the leading cost
contributor across a wide range
of different fusion
plant configurations.
We also concluded that fusion--
that how fusion is regulated,
can have a large impact
on overall costs.
The logical upshot of that is
that fusion power plant designs
need to minimize
their risk footprint,
and governments need to adopt
appropriate and efficient
policies that ensure
safe use of fusion energy
while enabling
fusion to contribute
to our decarbonization goals.
We also observed that the
operating and maintenance
costs for fusion power
plants can be significant.
So from what you've
heard here today,
I just wanted to summarize
some of the key takeaways.
First of all, fusion has a very
large potential societal value
in the trillions
of dollars range,
as was presented
by Sergey Paltsev.
We also saw from
several of the analysis
here today that the
deployment, as well as
the operation of
fusion power plants,
is highly dependent
upon, of course,
the cost of the fusion
technology itself,
as well as the
availability and the cost
of alternative
low-carbon technologies.
Furthermore, as Ruaridh
MacDonald showed,
the carbon emissions
constraint has a large impact
on what this
penetration will be.
And also, when we looked at the
global deployment of fusion,
there are many things that
shape the deployment of fusion,
and part of that is economic
and electricity demand growth.
And we saw growth in
different parts of the world,
including India, in the
later part of the century.
Furthermore, the study looked
at market design issues.
And this really affects all
types of power generation
investments, but certainly,
that includes fusion.
As discussed in the
supply chain topic,
the ability for fusion to
scale requires development
of materials and
manufacturing capacity,
particularly in the
niche component sector.
And lastly, the raw
materials were investigated,
quite a few different
raw materials considered
in the report.
And we do not see and do
not anticipate showstoppers,
but, in fact, the need
for these raw materials
will grow over time.
And so the capacity will
need to be built up,
and it will be an
area that will require
attention and encouragement.
I'd like to also acknowledge
the large team of people
who contributed in various
ways to this important study.
I thank you all for that.
So at this point, we will
commence with the panel
discussion here today.
And for that, I will turn to
Professor Dennis Whyte, who will
moderate our panel discussion.
Dennis is the co-principal
investigator for this study.
And he is a professor of Nuclear
Science and Engineering at MIT.
Over to you, Dennis.
Thanks, Randy.
And you've met through
presentations or introductions
already the other panel members.
I'd also like to introduce
Dr. Sara Ferry, who
is a research scientist at the
Plasma Science and Fusion Center
who works on fusion
technologies,
and Professor John
Parsons, who's
the deputy director for
the Center for Energy
and Environmental
Policy Research at MIT.
So welcome, panelists.
I've got a few prepared
questions to start off,
and then we'll take-- and then
we'll tackle some questions
from the audience.
Thank you for the good
questions from the audience.
Keep them coming.
So I'm going to start
with what I actually
considered a bit of a surprise,
actually, from the study, which
was typically, when we consider
fusion power plants, people
think of them as base
load units, namely,
to provide continuous
power as backing.
But what we found--
particularly, this is
to you, Ruaridh-- was,
can you explain your analysis?
Which was interesting is
that you could actually
find places where the economics
optimized for lower capacity
factors, namely, running
them not all the time,
and sort of run it more like
a peaker that was doing that.
So could you just please comment
to some more of the details
of that surprise that we found.
Sure.
So I think, first off,
it's important to note
that these are really just for
the very low-emission scenarios.
We didn't see this
at the 50 grams
CO2 per kilowatt, which is
at 12 and 4 grams per CO2.
And it had to do with the
relatively small handful
of hours where you
have very high net load
in the system, net
load meaning demand
minus your renewables
generation.
And we ran these optimizations,
GenX optimizations,
over 20 years.
So we got to see a pretty wide
variety of weather and demand
patterns.
And so I think we got to
see some of the edge cases.
Those edge cases do
go quite a long way
to determining the
optimal investment
decisions in the system.
But during those hours
of high net load,
the cheapest option
would be just
to use flexible natural gas,
with or without CCS units
to cover the net demand, as well
as having some high utilization
storage resources.
But we have a strict
emission limit.
And so there's natural
gas CCS units are capped
at a certain number
of hours or generation
they can produce per year.
At the lowest emission rate, it
was something like 1,000 hours
or less per year.
And so there's still many
more hours you have to cover.
So the primary option you
have is to build more storage,
but then, you also
need more renewables
in order to energize
or charge that storage.
So that's a very expensive
option over the long term.
And fusion plants, as a
zero-emission dispatchable
resource, are a
strong alternative.
And the prices are very
high during those hours
because the alternative is all
these additional renewables
and storage.
And so the fusion plants
are paid very high revenues,
as long as the market is
designed properly, in order
to operate with these
relatively low-capacity factors,
but during the hours
that matter most
from the systems point of view.
There are two things to note.
One, there are plenty
of technologies,
advanced or upcoming
technologies, or clean fuels
that we didn't consider.
So there is a chance
that one of them
may have a significant drop
in price in the next 30 years
and be a competitor,
and that would
reduce some of this
impact, particularly
on the clean fuel side.
And the other thing
to note is we're not
saying that cheap fusion plants
will have low-capacity factors.
If you look at the
plots in the report,
whenever the cost
of fusion falls,
the capacity factor
initially rises
and it becomes a base load.
And then, once it starts
directly outcompeting renewables
at very low costs, then
the capacity factor
starts falling again.
So it's really just
about those small number
of very expensive
hours and having
something that
has zero emissions
to cover the net demand.
Thanks Ruaridh.
Nonetheless, an
interesting insight,
I would say, for
fusion designers who
are considering aspects of what
kind of variability in the power
output they could have.
Amanda, I'm going to turn
to you next, which is really
very interesting to see
the high variability just
among the regions in
the United States.
And if you then think
of the United States
relative to the
rest of the world,
we have relatively low
population density.
We have access to a variety
of renewable resources,
as you pointed out.
And it tends to
be more than just
for geographic reasons
or population density.
Could you just
share your thoughts
about how you think if we
took this and your analysis,
what this would tell
us about the importance
of firm low-carbon
electricity generation that
comes from fusion in regions
of the world that have,
in some sense, poor access to
renewable resources, or to,
clearly, less diversity
in renewable resources.
Yeah.
Thanks, Dennis.
That's a great question.
So we can take the trends and
the conclusions from my analysis
and extrapolate those to
international locations.
So the first thing
we learned is that we
know the country
in question needs
to have decarbonization targets
to incentivize a transition away
from fossil fuel technologies.
Next, we need to look
at their availability
and strength of traditional
renewable resources, solar
and wind.
And we also need to look
at their alternative firm
low-carbon technologies, their
geothermal and their hydro.
And this is going
to look different
in different countries.
So I'll give two
bookend examples
to wrap our heads around
these conclusions.
The first country
I'll bring up is
Iceland, which has very
strong geothermal resources.
Based on our
analysis, we learned
that fusion is going to struggle
competing with geothermal.
So we're going to
see a limited--
fusion is going to have a
more difficult time being
adopted in a place like that.
On the other hand, we can look
at a location such as Singapore,
which has very large
demand, not a lot of land,
and essentially, very, very
limited wind and solar buildout
options.
No geothermal, no hydro.
To get to decarbonization levels
below fossil fuels with carbon
capture, you're going to need
energy-dense, low-carbon firm
technologies like fusion.
So it really just
depends on the resources
available to the country
that you're looking at.
Yeah.
Thanks, Amanda.
Very insightful.
So of course, I love the
next set, this next question,
because it's almost always
the first question that's
always asked, when.
What is the timing for fusion?
When is it going to happen?
It's OK.
It's a good question.
So I'll just point
out, in the study,
we essentially
made an assumption
about when commercial
fusion would start.
We aligned it--
and this actually
goes to some questions
that have already
come in from the audience.
We aligned it with the
comments and the average
of where the commercial fusion
developers now are seeing that.
We started at 2035.
We took historic data
from other new energy
sources about the doubling
time in terms of capacity.
So we put that in because we
needed to make some assumption.
This goes to the question,
if you take that timeline
as a given one, is it too late?
Does fusion still
have an impact?
And so here, I'll turn
to Sergey and Randy
about your thoughts on this.
And in some sense,
people think of this
often from the impact on the
environmental consequences,
but I'd also like you to comment
on the economic consequences
of the deployment timing.
Yeah, I'll start.
And Randy, you may add
your comments as well.
Well, that was also one of the
questions which we were getting.
Well, by mid-century, the
decarbonization will be done,
and why do we need a
fusion if everything
is going to be decarbonized?
And this is very oversimplistic
view of the world,
simply because the
needs for electricity,
the needs for
electrification, the needs
to provide energy to the society
is growing quite substantially
over time.
And you see those projections
and increases in demand.
And also, as
previously mentioned,
and Ruaridh has illustrated
that very well, is
these last reductions,
those very tough targets
require quite substantial
solution, engineering solution,
how to deal with these
zero-emission provision
of the power generation.
And indeed, depending on
how different technology
may evolve over time, the answer
might be slightly different.
And that's exactly the point of
this study, we exploring that.
But what we're finding out,
that the increasing demand
for electricity in
the global area,
and especially in
the emerging markets,
and also, with the limited
resources for wind and solar,
and especially for increasing
cost of integrating them
and making the system running
fully on wind and solar,
we actually see very good
economic case for fusion
in the second half
of the century.
And we see that under reasonable
assumptions about the costs.
We see very
substantial deployment
of the fusion technology
in the decarbonized world.
Randy, I don't know if you
want to add anything or expand.
No, Sergey, your
comments were perfect,
so I will not ruin
it with my comments.
Thank you.
Very good.
And next topic is about
fusion's cousin, fission.
And as you heard,
many of us are members
of Nuclear Science and
Engineering Departments
as well, too.
John, could you make
a comment to this
about how we treated fission
in the study and the overall--
your overall comments
are regarding that?
Sure.
So in the executive
summary, we took this point
on pretty clearly.
The economic analysis
in this report
is focused on what we think is
a key feature of modern power
markets, which is the
increasing penetration
of low-cost renewable energy.
And the accessible capacity
of these renewable resources
are variable across
hours and seasons, which
means there's a complementary
need for technologies that
provide firm, dispatchable,
low-carbon electricity
to guarantee you've got
electricity in all hours
when renewable
generation is low.
Both nuclear fusion
and nuclear fission
are firm, low-carbon electricity
generating technologies.
And they're also both
energy-dense technologies.
And so they're really
competing together
for the same sort of
competitive space in a country
or region's portfolio
of generating capacity.
However, they each differ from
one another in key respects.
The safety profiles
for each are unique,
and the two technologies may
face different regulations.
They rely on different
sets of materials
and evolving areas of
technological development.
Fission has encountered highly
variable social acceptance
across countries.
Fusion's social acceptance
is entirely untested.
And so how those things develop
is going to be very complicated.
So the research is focused
on the economic opportunity
for fusion as a firm,
low-carbon-generating
technology, and how that
varies regionally and globally.
The competition
between them is going
to be very complicated
depending upon the evolution
of scientific, economic,
political, and social events,
which we don't put at
the heart of this report.
I do want to just mention, in
addition to fusion and fission,
there are other firm,
low-carbon technologies,
as Amanda mentioned, for
example, enhanced geothermal,
bioenergy with carbon
capture and storage.
And so they'll all be
competing for this same space.
But I think
identifying that space
and how it varies across
countries was the focus here.
Yes, it seems optionality
is always key in this.
And almost in some sense of
what Amanda was commenting
to, that you're seeing this
distribution of uses of hydro,
wind, electric, we
already consider
that we're going to have to have
a set of choices on the table.
So it seems natural
to extend that
to it shouldn't be
fusion versus fission.
They're going to be
adapted in different ways.
Yeah.
Thanks for that, John.
Actually, turning to a little
bit more technical one,
it was seen and it was
commented several times
that R&D is still
required for providing--
and you could see
this in the data,
actually, high-capacity factors
are a very wanted thing.
This means, from a
technical point of view,
we need components and systems
which have a high availability.
Sara, you work
directly in this field.
Could you comment
as to what are some
of the challenges about
making that happen,
where we are relatively now, and
what are some of the efforts,
including some of the things
that are going on at MIT
right now about
addressing those issues?
Sure.
Thanks, Dennis.
So we work on a lot of different
aspects of fusion technology
here at the PSFC, and in the
US community more broadly.
One that you might
hear a lot about
is the technology associated
with fusion fueling.
So the fusion technologies
that we're primarily
focused on focus on burning
deuterium and tritium fuel.
We have very scarce
reserves of tritium,
so a fusion power plant
needs to breed its own.
And how you do this is
when the neutron comes off
of the fusing D and
T in the plasma,
you can capture that neutron in
a lithium-containing material
and breed tritium.
So it's straightforward
in principle,
but in practice, it's
quite challenging
to breed enough tritium.
That depends very much on
the operating parameters
and the design of your plant,
how much tritium you need
at any given point in
the plant's lifetime,
how to extract that
tritium efficiently
and get it ready and
prepared for fueling.
So this involves a lot of
different components in the fuel
cycle.
And a challenge of
fusion is that we
need to do this at a
very high throughput.
We have some experience with
this from the fission sector
at much lower throughputs.
So there's a lot
of work that needs
to be done with regards
to scaling that up,
with understanding how to
breed the tritium using fusion
neutrons in the
lithium-containing materials.
We have a major
experimental campaign here
at the MIT Plasma
Science and Fusion
Center called LIBRA
that is focused
on testing tritium breeders
that are of direct interest
to advanced commercial entities,
like Commonwealth Fusion
Systems.
And so that's really exciting.
Another big challenge is,
of course, fusion materials.
Fusion power plants operate
at much higher temperatures
and neutron fluxes
than anything else
that we really have experience
with in human technical history.
So it's a much higher
rate of radiation damage
that you're experiencing
than what we would be used
to from the fission sector.
So we have to do a lot of work
to develop advanced materials
and maintenance
strategies that are going
to be able to account for that.
And these challenges
are quite enormous.
But a reason to be
optimistic is that we've
seen from other systems, such as
high-temperature superconducting
magnets, that even if something
is starting at a very, very
low technology readiness
level, when you
apply the right levers
and the right pressures
and get the right
teams on board,
we can actually accelerate
that very, very quickly.
And that happened
with the magnets,
as demonstrated by PSFC in the
CFS over the last five years
or so.
We can take something from a
pretty low technical concept
up to a full commercial scale in
a pretty rapid time as long as--
when you just get the
right plan on board
and get everybody committed.
So there's a lot to do, but
we feel pretty optimistic.
And it's very exciting to
work on challenges like that.
Yeah, well stated, Sara.
I mean, my own comment to
this is a study such as this
actually really
does help provide us
a quantification and
a better way of what
is the economic consequence
of such innovations,
or what the targets might be.
And so those things become
a little bit clearer for us.
So I'm going to move to
a few questions coming
from the audience.
Thank you for the
excellent questions.
I'm going to start
with one which
is about what the
study didn't cover,
because this was concentrating
on electricity, using fusion
for electricity.
And one of the questions
was asking, well,
what about hydrogen production?
Or, for example, water
purification or desalination?
And so fusion being
applied to that,
if you could adapt fusion
to be able to bring it and--
technologies which would
adapt it into those
uses, would that be a
significant business opportunity
for the expansion of
fusion as well, too?
Randy, you want to
give that one a swing?
Yes, absolutely.
So that's a great question.
And, yes, our current study
focused on electricity,
and, in many
respects, electricity
may be the first
application for fusion,
but there's
tremendous opportunity
to apply it for things such as
generation of low-carbon fuels.
The characteristics of
a production facility
for low-carbon fuels is that
you're investing in a facility,
whether it be electrolyzers for
making hydrogen by electrolysis,
or other techniques, you want
to operate that plant 24/7.
And so it actually creates
a beautiful marriage
between a fusion
power plant that
can be run with high
availability in combination
with a fuel production facility,
which also, you want to operate
at a high availability.
And so that's a
beautiful marriage.
And the other
aspect is that many
of these facilities, whether
it be making hydrogen,
or low-carbon fuels,
or any other things
like that, you usually want
a combination of electricity
and process heat.
And so fusion can deliver
both of those to you.
Likewise, there are many
industrial processes
that we're trying to
decarbonize by removing
the use of fossil fuels in them.
Again, fusion can
play a role there.
The question asked
about desalinization.
It also works for
that application.
Potentially, carbon
removal technologies.
Again, you can be running those
facilities 24/7 with the use
of fusion and not
having to worry about,
when is the sun shining?
When is the wind blowing?
So it's a beautiful marriage.
Yeah.
And in fact, there was
a follow-up question
in this, which was, what
would be the impact,
given fusion's
expected capital costs?
And this is one of the
outputs of the study,
that it showed the varying
penetration and impact
with pricing.
So our study did not do that.
And my own personal
hope is at some point,
we would expand, as we've done
in previous future of studies
run by the Energy
Initiative, where
we could take an even larger
look at something like fusion
for its impact in these areas.
So anybody in the
audience who wants
to fund such a study,
please, come talk to us.
That would be fantastic.
There was several
questions, burning question
which was about the study.
And this probably
goes to Sergey.
What was the assumption
about carbon pricing?
What did we apply for the study.
Well, again, we
have different tools
which we applied at the
different levels, global,
regional, US.
So for the global
tool, the carbon price
is the result of the model.
So in other words, we impose
the emission mitigation profiles
region by region globally,
and the carbon-- and the model
was providing carbon prices.
And the carbon prices obviously
depend on many assumptions
about different technologies.
But just to give you the
order of the magnitude, if we
are talking about the
advanced economies,
typically, by the
mid-century, we
are at the level of the
carbon pricing of about $700
per ton of CO2.
So that's what it
takes to decarbonize.
For emerging economies,
while the profiles
are slightly different, and
also, the options are different.
So for the emerging economies,
we are at about $500
per ton of CO2.
Just to get you oriented,
currently in the world,
we are not at those
level of the prices.
And so there is the EU
emission trading scheme,
where the prices at some point
were reaching almost 100,
but now, they are
back to the levels
of '60s, '70s or so, depending
on the time of the year.
And the only two other
meaningful systems
which gives meaningful
carbon prices,
I would say, in Canada,
and maybe in New Zealand.
While there are other
emission systems,
emission trading system
and carbon pricing schemes,
but those have provided
much lower levels.
So in comparison
to where we are,
those are very substantial
increase in carbon prices.
And not surprisingly so.
If you want to
decarbonize the system,
well, it means
that we would need
to do a very accelerated
action in order to incentivize
that decarbonization.
But to summarize this, in
some sense, there wasn't--
fusion itself wasn't gaining
a particular advantage
from carbon pricing.
It was actually a
level playing field
about how you would achieve
those things as well, too.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Any other comments to
the carbon pricing?
OK.
Let's see which one
we're going to go.
So here was a very
good question.
How do we expect
these findings to have
an impact on private and
public decision-making
regarding R&D, supply
chain, and policy infusion?
Anybody want to take that?
Go ahead.
OK.
Yeah.
We've seen this large growth in
the private sector for fusion.
Before, let's say, eight years
ago, most fusion activities
was all government-driven.
In the past eight years, the
growth of the private fusion
sector has grown tremendously.
And there's been a lot of
investor funding coming
into that.
Basically, in each
of those cases,
those companies are working
to do risk mitigation.
They're trying to address the
technical engineering aspects,
making sure they have the
different technologies they
need to build out their system.
So I think what this study
does is it helps people
to continue to prioritize.
And I guess one lesson, it
goes back to this question
that Sergey answered
about timing.
Basically, regardless of
when fusion comes to market,
we will need it.
And so I guess my
guidance to the industry
is, take all the right steps,
solve all the technical problems
so that when you deploy
those first power plants,
you have a pathway to scale
it up and make it successful,
as opposed to rushing through
and having to backtrack.
Dennis, I'm sure you have
some other thoughts to that.
I do, actually, I
think, in particular,
to the private sector.
What I have been very
intrigued to see here is,
what is the economic return that
you make on what is essentially
an early stage investment
about addressing
particular technological
challenges in fusion?
And because the technical
challenges vary a lot
across the different concepts,
what this brings into play,
in my opinion--
and particularly, if I take
a look at Ruaridh's beautiful
plots of a particular-- if
you're considering deploying
a fusion power plant
in the New England ISO,
what it shows you is
that, for example,
for the cost point per watt--
which is not just economic,
it's a technical set
of decisions-- it
literally shows
you the economic return about
the change in the market
penetration for an investment
in making the technology reach
a particular point.
That is extremely
necessary and worthwhile,
not just to fusion technologies,
but to the entire system
that is investing in fusion
R&D around on those ones.
And that was just one
particular example.
But I found that
particularly important.
In some sense, it sets
the goalposts for fusion.
Let's see.
Just, Dennis, maybe
just to extend on that.
Please, go.
Please, Ruaridh.
We've seen, in the
fusion world, there's
this push to reduce costs at any
price, or any cost, so to speak,
so sacrificing
technical capabilities
in order to reduce
costs of your reactors.
And I think fusion
plant designers now
have the same trade-offs.
And I think, as you said, these
models help set these goalposts,
but also how those kind of
technical economic trade-offs
play out and whether
you can still--
whether it's worth to perhaps
use a slightly worse turbine
because it's cheaper,
and do you care
about the loss of efficiency.
But I think elsewhere
in the report,
it shows we looked at these
20-year time series and there
was this big emphasis on being
available in the high-priced
hours.
And so I think, as
an industry, it maybe
helps highlight that
fusion plants have
to make sure these markets are
designed properly so that people
are compensated in a way that,
similar to storage today,
you might not see those very
challenging high-priced hours
for several years, and
then, on the fourth or fifth
or sixth year, you're going
to earn an outsized share
of your revenue.
So making sure that it's
possible for businesses
to operate like that,
where they're only useful--
they're somewhat
useful all the time,
but they're really essential
once a decade or twice a decade.
Yep.
Another question that came
from the audience, which
is a good one.
So flexible operation as
opposed to a base load
operation of fission
plants has been difficult.
Will fusion plants have the
same level of difficulty?
Anybody?
Sara?
Randy?
I can also comment.
What is the question?
Basically, what will
be the challenges
around fusion of delivering
variable power rather than just
constant power levels?
I can speak to that if it--
I think it's not just--
in fission, it
hasn't always really
been a technical challenge.
There have been fission
reactors that operate flexibly.
It is as much an
economic challenge
because you're investing a
significant amount of capital
in this physical
plant, and you want
to earn money in as
many hours as you
can to pay down that capital.
And so it's really an
economic challenge.
But the markets are changing
with the penetration
of low-carbon electricity
renewable power.
There is now a much
greater variability
in the value of power
across different hours.
And the systems are going
to have to learn to adapt.
The electricity
markets are going
to have to learn to adapt in
the way Ruaridh was describing
to give incentives for
the owners of plants
to operate them flexibly,
and also, to reward them
enough money for the investment
of a plant that will be operated
flexibly.
Yeah, great.
Sara, did you want
to comment quickly
to the technical
challenges there?
Nothing specific.
Just I would say that, in
general, at this stage,
we tend to assume that we
are designing to steady state
operation.
So if we had to be
flexible, or you
wanted to ramp the plant up
and down, it would just--
it would require an
appropriately-directed research
initiative to
understand how that
would affect the loading on
already sensitive materials
and components.
So it's certainly not to
say that it's impossible,
but there are
challenges, I think,
associated with the
magnets and such
that you wouldn't necessarily
want to shut the plant off
and on in the same way.
So it would just
take directed effort
to understand how
to best be flexible.
And I can just say, from
a physics point of view,
fusion's physics actually
inherently allows
it to be quite
variable in its power,
but that's probably
not the limit here.
I agree.
It's probably the technical,
economic, and market limit,
actually, which comes from that.
So, Kelly, I believe
we are approaching
the end of the timing of this.
There's a great
question, which is,
where is the report available?
Randy?
Yeah.
So the report should be
available on your screen now.
It'll be posted
there in a moment,
so you can grab a link to that.
Excellent.
I also want to turn the
floor over to Bob Armstrong
to close out our session.
But as I mentioned a moment
ago, on our website, MIT Energy
Initiative, you will be able
to find the report there.
You should see the link to that.
And with that, I'll turn
it over to Bob Armstrong.
Great.
Thank you very much, Randy.
So I have three points to make
as we're wrapping up here.
First of all, want to
thank you for attending,
all you in the audience online.
And I want to thank Dennis,
and Randy, and the entire team
on this project for the really
interesting work they did
and for a great set
of presentations.
Thank you.
Second, wanted to
remind you very quickly
of the key takeaways that
Randy discussed earlier.
And those are here
on the screen.
Keep in mind the huge
potential there is for fusion
to benefit society at large.
In the trillions of dollars, as
Sergey pointed out in his talk.
Deployment operation
of fusion plants
depends on a number
of key factors.
Those are listed here.
Cost is foremost, but that
depends on other things as well,
including market design,
as we were just talking.
Third, the ability
of fusion to scale
is going to require development
of the right materials
and manufacturing capabilities
for those materials,
for niche components.
And then, lastly,
I want to point out
that for raw
materials, we don't see
any showstoppers at this point.
So the potential for
fusion is enormous,
and the future looks really,
really good for it, I think.
And then, finally,
I wanted to invite
you to visit the MIT Energy
Initiative website so that you
can download the full report.
The MIT Initiative
website is energy.mit.edu.
Easy way to remember
and get there.
And you'll be able to
find the full report.
So thank you all for attending.
And thank the presenters.
And thank you, Bob, for your
leadership at the Energy
Initiative as well, too,
and for our sponsors
as well, too, on this.
It's been wonderful.