the MIT energy initiative presents
cutting Urban carbon emissions by
retrofitting buildings MIT study shows
that Ci's plans often won't achieve
their goals decarbonizing the local grid
could make the difference written by
Nancy W
stoffer to support the worldwide
struggle to reduce carbon emissions many
cities have made public pledges to cut
their carbon emissions in by 2030 and
some have promised to be carbon neutral
by 2050 buildings can be responsible for
more than half of municipalities carbon
emissions today new buildings are
typically designed in ways that minimize
energy use in carbon emissions so
attention focuses on cleaning up
existing buildings a decade ago leaders
in some cities took the first step in
that process they Quantified their
problem Based on data from their
utilities on natural gas and electricity
consumption in standard pollutant
emission rates they calculated how much
carbon came from their buildings they
then adopted policies to encourage
retrofits such as adding instulation
switching to double glaze windows or
installing rooftop solar panels but will
those steps be enough to meet their
pledges in nearly all cases cities have
no clear plan for how they're going to
reach their goal says Kristoff Reinhardt
a professor in the department of
architecture and director of the
building technology program that's where
our work comes in
we aim to help them perform analyses so
they can say if we as a community do a b
and c to buildings of a certain type
within our jurisdiction then we are
going to get there to support those
analyses Reinhardt and a team in the MIT
sustainable design laboratory sdl PhD
candidate Zachary M Bola sm21 former
doctoral student yian Ang PhD 22 now a
research collaborator at the sdl and
former postto Samuel latelier desen now
a senior building performance Analyst at
the international building engineering
and consulting firm in troba launched a
publicly accessible website providing a
series of simulation tools and a process
for using them to determine the impacts
of plan steps on a specific building
stock says Reinhardt the takeaway can be
a clear technology pathway a combination
of building upgrades renewable energy
deployments and other measures that will
enable a community to reach its carbon
reduction goals for their built
environment analyses performed in
collaboration with policy makers from
selected cities around the world yielded
insights demonstrating that reaching
current goals will require more effort
than City representatives and in a few
cases even the research team had
anticipated exploring carbon reduction
Pathways the researchers approach Builds
on a physics-based building energy model
or bem akin to those that Architects use
to design high performance Green
Building buildings in 2013 Reinhardt and
his team developed a method of extending
that concept to analyze a cluster of
buildings based on publicly available
geographic information system GIS data
including each building's type footprint
and a year of construction the method
defines the neighborhood including trees
parks and so on and then using
meteorological data how the buildings
will interact the air flows among them
and their energy use the result is an
urban building energy model or ubm for a
neighborhood or a whole city the website
developed by the MIT team enables
neighborhoods and cities to develop
their own ubm and to use it to calculate
their current building energy use and
resulting carbon emissions and then how
those outcomes would change assuming
different retrofit programs or other
measures being implemented or considered
the website
.io provides step-by-step instructions
and all the simulation tools that a team
will need to perform an analysis says
Reinhardt the website starts by
describing three roles required to
perform an analysis a local
sustainability champion who is familiar
with the municipality's carbon reduction
efforts a GIS manager who has access to
the municipality's urban data sets and
maintains a digital model of the built
environment and an energy modeler
typically a hired consultant who has a
background in Green Building Consulting
an individual building energy modeling
the team Begins by defining shallow and
deep building retrofit scenario scarios
to explain Reinhardt offers some
examples shallow refers to things that
just happen like when you replace your
old failing appliances with new energy
efficient ones or you install LED light
bulbs and weather stripping everywhere
he says deep adds to that list things
you might do only every 20 years such as
ripping out walls and putting an
insulation or replacing your gas furnace
with an electric heat pump once those
scenarios are defined the gis manager
uploads to u.io a data set of
information about the city's buildings
including their locations and attributes
such as geometry height age and use for
example commercial retail residential
the energy modeler then builds a new bem
to calculate the energy use and carbon
emissions of the existing building stock
once that Baseline is established the
energy modeler can calculate how
specific retrofit measures will change
the
outcomes Workshop to test drive the
method 2 years ago the MIT team set up a
a 3-day Workshop to test the website
with sample users participants included
policy makers from eight cities and
municipalities around the world namely
brag Portugal Cairo Egypt Dublin Ireland
Florianopolis Brazil Keel Germany
middleberry Vermont United States
Montreal Canada and Singapore taken
together the cities represent a wide
range of climates socioeconomic
demographics cultures governing
structures and sizes working with the
MIT team the participants presented
their goals defin shallow and deep
retrofit scenarios for their city and
selected a limited but representative
area for analysis an approach that would
speed up analyses of different options
while also generating results valid for
the city as a whole they then performed
analyses to quantify the impacts of
their retrofit scenarios finally they
learned how best to present their
findings a critical part of the exercise
when you do this analysis and bring it
back to the people you can say this is
our homework over the next 30 years if
we do this we're going to get there says
Reinhardt that makes you part of the
community so it's a joint
goal sample
results after the close of the workshop
Reinhardt and his team confirmed their
findings for each City and then added
one more factor to the analyses the
state of the city's electric grid
several cities in the study had pledged
to make their grid carbon neutral by
2050 including the Grid in the analysis
was therefore critical if a building
becomes all electric and purchases its
electricity from a carbon- free grid
then that building will be carbon
neutral even with no on-site energy
saving retrofits the final analysis for
each City therefore calculated the total
kilogram of carbon dioxide equivalent
emitted per square meter of floor space
assuming the following
scenarios the Baseline shallow retrofit
only shallow retrofit plus a clean
electricity grid deep retrofit only deep
retrofit plus rooftop photovoltaic solar
panels and deep retrofit plus a clean
electricity grid note that clean
electricity grid is based on the area's
most ambitious decarbonization Target
for their power grid the following
paragraphs provide highlights of the
analyses for three of the eight cities
included are the city's setting emission
reduction goals current and proposed
measures and calculations of how
implementation of those measures would
affect their energy use and carbon
emissions
Singapore Singapore is generally hot and
humid and its building energy use is
largely in the form of electricity for
cooling the city is dominated by
high-rise buildings so there's not much
space for rooftop solar installations to
generate the needed electricity
therefore plans for decarbonizing the
current building stock must involve
retrofits the shallow retrofit scenario
focuses on installing energy efficient
Lighting in appliances to those steps
the Deep retrofit scenario adds is
adopting a district cooling system
Singapore's stated goals are to cut the
Baseline carbon emissions by about a
third by 2030 and to cut it in half by
2050 the analysis shows that with just
the shallow retrofits Singapore won't
achieve its 2030 goal but with the deep
retrofits it should come close notably
decarbonizing the electric grid would
enable Singapore to meet and
substantially exceed as 2050 Target
assuming either retrofit
scenario Dublin Dublin has a mild
climate with relatively comfortable
Summers but cold humid Winters as a
result the city's energy use is
dominated by fossil fuels in particular
natural gas for space Heating and
domestic hot water the city presented
just one target a 40% reduction by 2030
Dublin has many neighborhoods made up of
georgean row houses and at the time of
the workshop the city already had a
program in place encouraging groups of
owners to insulate their walls the
shallow fit scenario therefore focuses
on weatherization upgrades adding
weather stripping to Windows and Doors
insulating crawl spaces and so on to
that list the Deep retrofit scenario
adds insulating walls and installing
upgraded Windows the participants didn't
include electric heat pumps as the city
was then assessing the feasibility of
expanding the existing District heating
system results of the analyses show that
implementing the shallow retrofit
scenario won't enable Dublin to meet its
2030 Target but the Deep retrofit
scenario will however like Singapore
Dublin could make major gains by
decarbonizing its electric grid the
analysis shows that a decarbonized grid
with or without the addition of rooftop
solar panels were possible could more
than have the carbon emissions that
remain in the Deep retrofit scenario
indeed a decarbonized grid plus
electrification of the heating system by
incorporating heat pumps could enable
Dublin to meet a future Net Zero
Target middleberry middleberry Vermont
has warm wet Summers and frigid winters
like Dublin its energy demand is
dominated by natural gas for heating but
unlike Dublin it already has a largely
decarbonized electric grid with a high
penetration of Renewables for the
analysis the Middlebury team chose to
focus on an aging residential
neighborhood similar to many that
surround the city core the shallow
retrofit scenario calls for installing
heat pumps for space Heating and the
Deep retrofit scenario adds improvements
in building envelopes the facade roof
and windows the town's targets are 40%
reduction from the Baseline by 2030 and
Net Zero carbon by 2050 results of the
analyses showed that implementing the
shallow retrofit scenario won't achieve
the 2030 Target the Deep retrofit
scenario would get the city to the 2030
Target but not to the 2050 Target indeed
even with the Deep retrofits fossil fuel
use remains High the explanation while
both retrofit scenarios call for
installing heat pumps for space heating
the city would continue to use natural
gas to heat its hot
water Lessons Learned for several policy
makers seeing the results of their
analyses was a wake-up call they learned
that the strategies they had planned
might not be sufficient to meet their
stated goals an outcome that could prove
publicly embarrassing for them in the
future like the policy makers the
researchers learned from The Experience
Reinhardt notes three main takeaways
first he and his team were surprised to
find how much of a building's energy use
in carbon emissions can be traced to
domestic hot water water with
middleberry for example even switching
from natural gas to heat pumps for space
heating didn't yield the expected effect
on the bar graphs generated by their
analyses the gray bars indicated carbon
from fossil fuel use remained as
Reinhardt recalls I kept saying what's
all this gray while the policy makers
talked about using heat pumps they were
still going to use natural gas to heat
their hot water it's just stunning that
hot water is such a big ticket item it's
huge says Reinhardt second the results
demonstrate the importance of including
the state of the local electric grid in
this type of analysis looking at the
results it's clear that if we want to
have a successful energy transition the
building sector and the electric grid
sector both have to do their homework
notes Reinhardt moreover in many cases
reaching carbon neutrality by 2050 will
require not only a carbon free grid but
also all electric buildings third
Reinhardt was struck by how different
the bar graphs presenting results for
the eight cities look this really
celebrates uniqueness of different parts
of the world he says the physics used in
the analysis is the same everywhere but
differences in the climate the building
stock construction practices electric
grids and other factors make the
consequences of making the same change
vary widely in addition says Reinhardt
there are sometimes deeply ingrained
conflicts of interest in cultural norms
which is why you cannot just say
everybody should do this and do this for
instance in one case the city owned both
the utility and the natural gas at Bur
burned as a result the policy makers
didn't consider putting in heat pumps
because the natural gas was a
significant source of Municipal income
and they didn't want to give that up
explains Reinhardt finally the analyses
Quantified two other important measures
energy use and Peak load which is the
maximum electricity demanded from the
grid over a specific time period
Reinhardt says that energy use is
probably mostly a possibility check does
this make sense and Peak load is
important because the utilities need to
keep a stable grid middleburry analysis
provides an interesting look at how
certain measures could influence Peak
electricity demand there the
introduction of electric heat pumps for
space heating more than doubles the peak
demand from buildings suggesting that
substantial additional capacity would
have to be added to the Grid in that
region but when heat pumps are combined
with other retrofitting measures the
peak demand drops to levels lower than
the starting
Baseline the aftermath an update
Reinhardt stresses that the specific
results from the workshop provide justce
shot in time that is where the cities
were at the time of the workshop this is
not the fate of the city he says if we
were to do the same exercise today we no
doubt see a change in thinking and the
outcomes would be different for example
heat bumps are now familiar technology
and have demonstrated their ability to
handle even bitterly cold climates and
in some regions they've become
economically attractive as the war in
Ukraine has made natural gas both scarce
and expensive also there's now awareness
of the need to deal with hot water
production Reinhardt notes that
performing the analyses of the workshop
did have the intended impact it brought
about change 2 years after the project
had ended most of the Cities reported
that they had implemented new policy
measures or had expanded their analysis
across the entire building stock that's
exactly what we want comments Reinhardt
this is not an academic exercise it's
meant to change what people focus on and
what they do designing policies with
socioeconomics in mind Reinhardt notes a
key limitation of the uban .io approach
it looks only at technical feasibility
but will the building owners be willing
and able to make the energy saving
retrofits data show that even with
today's incentive programs and subsidies
current adoption rates are only about 1%
that's way too low to enable a city to
achieve its emission reduction goals in
30 years says Reinhardt we need to take
into account the socioeconomic realities
of the residents to design policies that
are both effective and Equitable to that
end the MIT team extended their u.io
approach to create a socio
technoeconomic analysis framework that
can predict the rate of retrofit
adoption throughout a city based on
Census Data the framework creates an
ubam that includes demographics for the
specific types of buildings in a city
accounting for the cost of making a
specific retrofit PLUS Financial
benefits from policy incentives and
Future Energy savings the model
determines the economic viability of the
retrofit package for representative
households sample analyses for two
Boston Neighborhood neighb hoods suggest
that high income households are largely
ineligible for need-based incentives or
the incentives are insufficient to
prompt action lower inome households are
eligible and could benefit financially
over time but they don't act perhaps due
to limited access to information a lack
of time or capital or a variety of other
reasons Reinhardt notes that their work
thus far is mainly looking at technical
feasibility next steps are to better
understand occupants willingness to pay
and then to determine what set of
federal and local incentive programs
will trigger households across the
demographic Spectrum to retrofit their
apartments and houses helping the
worldwide effort to reduce carbon
emissions this work was supported by
Shell through the MIT energy initiative
Zachary Bola was supported by the US
National Science Foundation graduate
research
Fellowship Samuel atalia desen was
supported by the post-doctoral
Fellowship of the Natural Sciences and
Engineering research Council of Canada