Kicking off the lightning talks today,
I'd like to introduce our first
presenter, Tim Carr of Ver. Vier
develops highcapacity superconducting
power transmission which is designed to
meet the massive energy demands of the
next generation data center
infrastructure. Welcoming to the stage
Tim Carr.
>> Thank you so much Trisha. Uh very happy
to be here today. Um my name is Tim
Carr. I'm with Ver and I'm here to tell
you about the superconducting technology
that we're bringing to the data center
uh AI data center market. And so our
technology
is built around a core reality of AI's
growth, which is that power is at the
center of it. Power is the backbone. As
we continue to see the proliferation of
AI models across inference, uh,
reasoning, and training, we're seeing an
explosion of power demand globally with
gigawatt scale campuses now the norm.
And frankly, this trend not expected to
stop anytime soon. And what's becoming
clear as this growth unfolds is that our
conventional power distribution
technology that we've used for decades
is being brought to the brink, being
outpaced and outrun by the power
requirements of these AI workloads. And
so the capability for our current power
delivery equipment to move massive
amounts of power to these campuses and
ultimately into the data center
buildings themselves is now becoming a
bottleneck due to the size, the weight,
electrical resistance, and the cost of
conventional options such as copper bus
bars and cables. And so data centers
really need to start thinking about and
finding new solutions to unlock the
scale and performance that this growth
requires. And this growth is tether
tethered as we all know to the high
performance chips that support these
workloads GPUs and similar processors.
And so I have on the screen a snapshot
of GPUs of excuse me Nvidia's GPU road
map. And you can see that in today's
Blackwell family we're at 150 to 250
kilowatts for a server rack. But within
48 months we're going to be at a server
rack of a,000 kilowatts a megawatt rack
in a very short time. And so how do we
solve this power delivery problem to
unlock AI's promise? And so at VR, our
solution is superconductors.
Superconductors move 10 times the power
of conventional options with nearly no
resistance in a dramatically smaller and
lighter conductor. These options can go
much further than conventional uh
conventional equipment and do so without
the creation of of thermal resistance or
heat ultimately enabling highly power
dense efficient and high performance
data centers that can support the most
advanced AI chipsets without breaking a
sweat. And so to do that today we have
three products. Uh we have our SL series
which is designed for low voltage indoor
application to support the highest AI
pod densities. We have our ST series
which is designed for power distribution
at medium voltage level in a form factor
that's up to 140th the size of
conventional options. Our ST series can
move over 200 megawatts of power in a
single cable. And finally our SE series
which is V's uh flagship and early
product innovation which moves
transmission level power over long
distance in an overhead superconductor.
And so to help kind of put you know show
where these products go in the campus
and what their applications are I have
on the screen you can you can see you
moving high power connections uh to the
campus at the grid and substation level
moving that power throughout the campus
between substation transformers and
buildings and then finally delivering
that power in low voltage form directly
into the whites space of these data
centers. And the unifying thing of all
these applications is that they deliver
10 times the power density with nearly
no losses over dramatically longer
distances. And what that results in is
the ability for us to support multiple
gigawatt scale campuses easily.
This slide really hones in on our low
voltage product and compares some of the
physical attributes of us to a
conventional 4,000 amp copper bus bar
which is used frequently today. And as
you can see, we can now move an
equivalent amount of of current in a
conductor that's 10 times smaller, 10
times lighter, and can go 10 times
further. And this benefit of re of of
congestion reduction is a big deal for
data centers as they continue to wrestle
with larger and more complex server
equipment, the services to support them,
the introduction of liquid cooling, and
balancing that with the need to get the
most amount of compute in a given in in
a given space. And lastly, on our low
voltage product, because we're removing
a large amount of thermal resistance out
of the inside of these buildings, we
encourage the compression of servers,
which can help with latency performance
and help to speed up uh model training.
This next slide shows a similar
comparison for our medium voltage
underground product. And I I really
think the visual speaks for itself. The
takeaway is here we can move the same
amount of power uh from a conventional
option in a much smaller cross-section.
And the reason for that is largely due
to the fact that we can remove the need
for concrete duct banks. And so you see
on the lefth hand side this is a picture
of a very common concrete duct bank
installation. These are typically done
to manage thermal dissipation and to
house many conductors underground. So we
can now take all of that power that you
see on the left hand side and use it in
what's represented on the right in a
single superconductor. The big
efficiency to note here is time. By
doing this we're able to remove
thousands of hours from uh labor hours
from a construction project which
ultimately allows our clients to get
their facilities online faster. And
speed to market is something that our
clients care a lot about in uh in
today's environment. And so we're
looking to partner with data center
operators, developers, engineers,
designers um to solve these tough power
delivery challenges with superconductors
uh with early commercial scale
deployments. And so reach out today to
get started. Thank you very much.