Yes, there's a
one-part solution that uses a quantum buffer. I'm going to have to do a quantum computing experiment
and then I
'm going to have a
new kind of computer that harnesses the
power of quantum computing to perform tasks much faster than
normal classical digital
computers. In 2019, in an experiment, we used
mathematical prowess. The world took the best
supercomputer in the world 10,000 years to solve the
problem on the quantum computer in under
minutes. This is how some improvements in
classical algorithms have factored down,
but essentially, that sort of experimental
improvement still exists, and it increases.
The factor increases with the size of the problem. Another
important problem, if
you all have heard of quantum computing, is
a factoring algorithm which underpins all of
the encryption. We know  Today, so at least given a large
amount of large enough quantum
computers, you could break encryption in under
a day. That would take normal classical compute
millions, if not billions of years. Let's say
you get sold on quantum computers and you can
try them out. So this is what the experience
looks like. You have to deal with lots of messy
classical computing tasks. You have to
set up the environment and manage all the access to
cloud-hosted quantum computers. Deal
with different architectures of quantum computers and
their couplers and simulators. It's a
messy thing that you have to learn about
quantum computers. You have to deal with
problems as well. And we're saying that we are a
cloud-hosted one-stop platform
that provides you with the easiest access. I'd love to
pitch it. We'll take you from not knowing much about
quantum computers to writing your
first quantum program to running it on
a real quantum computer in under 5
minutes and it's done.  This is many times and this
is the entire region where so many different companies
are starting to partner with us we
partner very close with IBM nvia and many
times their hardware is available as well we cant help but
expand our partnerships with many more
companies so in order to serve our end user
customers better and we also support gpu and
cpu so all your compute needs in one
place you can just buy some credits
and decide to spend them on gpu and cpu ultimately we
believe the architecture for
compute will be a hybrid one it will solve part
of your problem on some compute
part on gpu and cpu and we are the
best places to serve that model and let's say you have a
place to get started with all kinds
of applications you might be looking for  There are a
whole bunch of applications that people are
starting to explore with applications in
pharmaceutical materials science, aerospace, and so on.
With pharmaceutical materials science, the
real improvement is expected with
higher confidence in other industries.
People are still exploring how to use
quantum computers. One of the areas that we're really
focusing on is protein-
drug interactions. How do you go from protein
and drug molecules to solving this problem
on a quantum computer? And this is where we have a
protein coming from an Alzheimer's drug, something called
beta-lide, and understanding its
interaction with a metal ion that leads to the
disease and plaques in the brain that can solve
signs of the disease. And so this is a
project with the University of Chicago's Envia, Argonne
National Lab, and we're building this really cool
pipeline that takes advantage of state-of-
the-art algorithms being  I'm glad to see you at the moment
bringing them together and allowing you to
run on a quantum computer. This is in active
development and we have things being tested
on APC and quantum computers.
We work with various scale holders with
enterprises for your use cases. We are one
of the largest. We have one of the
largest user bases in the community and
by the fact that they are super easy to use. We are
incredibly popular with users. We have one of
the largest user bases. We are incredibly popular at the same time. We
support more than every year and with
quantum computing companies, we allow them to
launch their software and hardware on
Qube. We are looking for other
test companies for using our Qube
pipeline for protein and drug simulation. We are also
happy to work with you to
provide access to the Qube platform.
Thank you very much
[appreciation]