so this is the article I want to say
just a few little things about it that
um it's it's an article that was written
for um for other academics at the time
so just just so we know that it wasn't
at the time it was published in 200 for
really designed that we're going to read
it in class and we're going to have
various academic articles in here so
some people are old hats reading
academic articles in the humanities or
in or in science or in this case at the
intersection of humanities and Science
and other people had less um less
introduction to that so I just want to
take a minute and say how I approach
reading a new article because we'll have
some of them um first all always take a
second and think about the the title for
a second figure out okay is you know
sometimes I even just write it down and
put it somewhere because uh when I'm not
assigning articles there are things that
you can put down at any point and so
when I get to the point where I'm
somewhere through it and I see they're
not answering they're not talking about
the title they're not answer then I can
throw it away uh you're not allowed to
do that in this class but that's you
know sign to do then I always start
paying attention to the Bold points and
try to see about that because uh I don't
read very fast and things so I'll want
to jump ahead a bit but always read the
introduction really carefully I would in
some ways if you have you know let's say
this would never happen to you but
you're behind on a reading or something
it's 10 minutes before class and you're
trying to figure out what to do um don't
read the whole thing fast read the
introduction really carefully twice and
that's um because that's what almost
everything should be there if it's a
good article we may read U because
you'll get to very specific things in as
you get to your projects we may get to
the point where you're kind of assigning
yourself articles or it's like hey look
at this these five articles that I may
have seen um if at the end introduction
again you don't know anything what it's
going to be about throw it out move to
the next article but um a well-written
article should give every
there I go to the pictures yet next I
don't want to ever see that cliche of
pictures with thousand words in any of
your things but it's kind of true so you
can figure out okay what are we going to
be talking about um from reading the
introduction I knew we're going to be
talking about music representation so I
start asking are these music
representations that are been talked
about and then when I look at the text I
can do it I can see okay the next topic
is issues representation I've skimmed
ahead so I know there's only uh two real
topics in this so this should be the
first half of it oh my gosh like that's
why we remember
like um okay um and read the first
sentence the first paragraph of that and
go ahead and see if
um if the if the ending tells you what
it's going to be about it's this is not
like watching your favorite movie don't
an academic article you shouldn't feel
like you're spoiling the the great
reveal um there there's maybe five
articles in my life where I think if I
did if I read this way the first time I
saw it I would have ruined the article
all the rest I just improved my so I can
see that um okay so we have a problem of
multiple requirements and we have some
sort of a solution that doesn't work so
that I can go back and read and try to
figure out what it is we're going to be
talking about and we can see the final
um thing is an introduction to the next
section you see that the second part is
a case study of one particular example
of computational and comparative
comparative and computational
musicology and um I can see okay I
probably should have some fun looking at
that later and then jump to the
conclusion and this article's great in
that it does label its conclusion with
where is it the word conclusion um not
every article does that but again
um go ahead and read the last couple
paragraphs of the article so you find
where it ends go back and go ahead and
figure out what the article is going to
be
about when you're assigning articles to
yourself and and the Articles just keep
getting longer um it's this weird thing
that people used to write things in
typewriters double spaced in Courier 14
point now we write single spaced in
Times New Roman 11 or 12 or something
and but people keep thinking that my
article needs to be 30 pages long and
that's actually double the length of
Articles so uh they're starting to get
too long I do encourage you to read like
this and then only only after you figure
out what the
main s conclusions of the article are
um this one is pretty obvious to those
of us in this class that you can use
computational methods without giving up
to gistic values only once we've done
that um we go back uh hopefully you can
skip notes the first time you read
Because if they've written well these
should be additional parts or places
that you can look at later um if it's a
poorly written article then you have to
read the notes to get to it
and if it's a new subject go ahead and
look at the references and see who
appears a lot so you can see okay these
are probably important people okay this
guy paulon hipple hipple hereon here on
here on here on on here and I should
probably if I want to go further read
something by here this what I'm think
yeah was just more more and more of them
and um and then also if there's anybody
that we recognize from the class and
will you'll be looking at El Sil Fields
writings today she's
awesome I'm going so with this in mind
these are some of the strategies that I
go through in in looking at it and then
the other great strategy is talk to
people and hopefully um they can give
you the their tape on the article and
again we can you know be richer for it