Without further ado, I will invite Jose
Pacco, co-director of the Advanced
Manufacturing and Design Program of MIT,
Jose, the floor is yours. Good morning.
In antoasta, they told me that in
Santiago, people were more energetic.
Good morning. Okay,
my name is Jose Pateco, co-director of
the advanced manufacturing and design
program of MIT. It is a pleasure to be
here. Let me warn you firstly and also
apologize. I am a Mexican, but I have
been in the USA for 45 years and I don't
have the chance to practice my Spanish
often. So once in a while I will use a
word in English or spang English
or I will invent a word. If I invent a
word and offend somebody, my apologies
for that.
You came here to hear
my colleague Brian Anthony.
Unfortunately, he could not come. But I
have had the chance and honor to work
with Brian in the last 13 years also as
a co-director
of the advanced manufacturing and design
program.
He's not here. I am here. Maybe he's a
more fit, taller.
However, I think we are handsome, the
two of us. Okay, let's talk about
technologies.
That's why you're here. So I will start
immediately talking about
technologies
and how they connect to enable
innovation.
My first topic is the concept of
tomography.
Tomography
is
a difficult word. Somehow
it is about creating an image in 3D, a
3D image for anything.
I'm sure you've seen this in movies
where you are looking at something that
is uh internal then it is opened and
that is the concept how to build 3D
images using different technologies that
is tomography.
I will show you the beginning the
inception of a technology
>> that we are developing in the in Brian's
laboratory.
Let me show you this because sometimes
we think that advanced technologies are
originated already advanced and very
pretty but the truth is that they are
started as ideas. Let's imagine imagine
this. Let's imagine that we can use the
concept of ultrasound
through X-rays. Well, that's interesting
or laser. How can we test that idea?
The first test
was done here in a
cast of gel
with
iron pieces.
It looks like a
jelly, but you cannot eat it because it
has iron inside. Okay, but this is the
model. We would like to see the
differences between the jelly and the
bone and the ironon pieces to simulate
the differences
in the tissue of humans.
The purpose of this concept of real time
tomography needs to consider different
characteristics
of what we are looking at including
roughness of the surface.
Acoustic attenuation
imagine
that's my favorite word imagine. so much
that sometimes I am introducing myself
to somebody and I say Jose
and somebody says no he's not Jose he's
imagine okay let's imagine that you have
a laser
into the tissue
this laser penetrates
the skin
heating the skin by doing that it
creates creates
a sound, an acoustic wave that we cannot
hear with our ears, but we can anyhow
we do that
and we have here a sample. This is part
of how you develop things. We started
with the jelly. Now we are moving to
this sample. We have a detector laser
here that will give us some ideas about
how we can see this image inside the
sample.
Here you can see the ultrasound image
without much detail.
However, here you can see the ultrasound
image with light.
You can see how different they are.
You can see the different parts of the
tissue
where we
can see the graph or we can see this
image. How does it work?
The sample moves
based on the laser on this platform
because we are heating the surface with
that laser with a pulse of 10 hertz.
The optical exposure during measurement
will use an intererometer to measure the
vibration on the different rough
surfaces.
How do we do that?
This is only possible. Oh, before going
there, imagine that we can use the same
concept
to see if a rock has copper inside.
This was part of a conversation that we
had some days ago. And I said, hm,
that's interesting. Maybe there is a
possibility to do that. We'll see. Okay,
how can we do that? Maybe in the future
even more.
Applying this concept of photonic
integrated circuits. What's this?
Photonic integrated circuits
are a combination of an integrated
circuit as the one you can see to the
left.
This is what you
regularly have seen inside your
computers, your iPhones with a power
supply source, transistors, resistors,
capacitors among others.
What is equivalent in a photonic
integrated circuit is that instead of
using electricity,
the system will use light.
These are wave guides, lasers, source,
detectors, etc. These elements are
combined to create the photonic
integrated circuit. They are really
really small
because today we have the chance to
build
the circuits
at nano scales.
So when you do that at that scale,
you lower the cost of the sensors and
this is very important because these
technologies have been
around for many years
but the manufacturing
of these elements
in small sizes reduces the cost so they
become more affordable.
So we have this concept. This is an
idea. We're testing it. We have access
to this tool. That's how we can measure
this.
What can we do with this technology?
I started thinking.
I don't have a mining background but at
the same time I have learned a lot here.
And
with AMSA we have talked about
structural monitoring of tunnels
and shafts. Imagine
how we can reduce
the risks of collapse.
Secondly, we can characterize the ore
as we saw in that uh slide. And thirdly,
the inspection of critical equipment in
operation. This is something that we
already do in manufacturing.
In this case, we can do that to look at
heavy equipment to detect internal
cracks, corrosion before failure occurs.
>> Yes, there is a possibility to do this.
We are just imagining
things so far. Let me give you an
example of innovation in real time
echoing the words that were said before.
Innovation is a joint community work. I
arrived
on Monday.
We had our first presentation. And I had
the honor to visit a mine site sentella
and by learning
so many things I was asked can we use
this technology to characterize the or
in a non-destructive manner. I said, "I
don't know. Maybe. Let's see." Last
night, I Whatsopped my students and
said, "Imagine
that we want to characterize an or
nondestructively.
What should we do?" Well, firstly, we
have to analyze whether it is possible
to do it in the lab or not. Secondly, we
should imagine and see
if the model makes business sense. Here
we have sorting. This is a process that
already exists in the mind.
Automatic sorting. And I learned that
these belts go really fast. So, how can
we
use this technology
at such a fast rate.
So yesterday when I was on the site, one
of the workers said, you know, we can
have different belts
running at a lower rate,
then we can merge them to gain speed. So
that's interesting. We are innovating.
We are figuring things out.
An innovation
it is important to do that. So as I said
I sent a WhatsApp message to the
students and I said can we do this? What
do you think? They replied and uh we had
a quick FaceTime and we said you know
what I don't know if it is possible but
there is already a technology called PG
NAA and PFTNAS
prompt gamma neutral activation analysis
and what I said is what you are thinking
of of course there is a technology why
didn't I think of that
and I said okay give me a second because
I have to look at something then chat
GPT
now I really understand what chat GPT is
this is
immediate gamma rays uh neutronic
activation analysis and the neut thermal
neutron ronic activation
of PFT
NA. Interesting. We started with a jelly
with iron and we are ending up here. How
can we use new technology
to detect and create 3D images
faster?
And I said, "Wow, this is interesting.
What what should we do to get there?
It is interesting to see that there is a
company that is using this technology
already. They are testing it. Therefore,
here you can see
how
this technology may be used. So
our work as researchers is changing.
the starting point changes.
Okay, this already exists. There are
people looking at the possibilities. We
had to pilot the solution and see how
the solution connects to other
possibilities or areas. But
you are detecting things through
sorting.
Then you can see how to process the
volume differently. This is part of
innovation.
I couldn't be talking about this if I
hadn't visited the mine and if I hadn't
proposed what we proposed in the
beginning. So the end will be a
combination of what we have seen maybe
something new maybe other students in
the future will say you know what we can
do this and this is how the concept of
innovation moves on that's the first
technology the second technology is
about digital twins
they are used already here what I saw in
Santella
is that this is the technological
foundation of the future of mining.
>> Not only for mining but also
for tangible jobs of the future.
Digital twins
have been
here
for a long time. They have been
implemented in several industries. A
digital twin is a virtual replication of
an object, process or physical system in
maybe an engine,
a factory or a city. This is very
important.
I have um colleagues in media lab. They
have a digital twin for
Andor a country. Do you know where Andor
is?
Well, these are my optical sensors as
you can see
and they are working.
>> Okay. And Pandora
is a very small country between France
and Spain.
In the lab, there is a digital twin of
the country.
Authorities can make decisions
based on the infrastructure
and they
can also receive real time data
to update the model
permanently.
Therefore, this is what
turns a model into a digital twin.
If you have uh children or maybe you
have played this game where you are
driving in a race, a car race, but it's
the model, right? Let's imagine imagine
again
that this video game receives updated
data of a car race connected to the car
of your favorite driver. You can see the
temperature of the tires
of the road, the engine, the level of
fuel, etc.
That combination, the model plus the
update
will become a digital twin
and there are different tastes of
digital twins.
Normally these are models created first
as the one for this car race game
it derives from physics.
So
when we do this we know why the car goes
that way because of the way in which we
have programmed the model derived from
physics. On the other end, we have
something very popular
which is the use of data
to program AI,
machine language
to create the model, but we don't know
why
this is not derived from physics. And
then we have the hybrid combination in
the middle.
This concept of digital twins is not a
new thing because
we have been doing this for years. This
is the science of measurement and
applied simulation.
However,
data update
is only possible here. We because we
have new sensors. That is part of our
job. That is part of what is changing
the world and the way in which we work.
Today we can create new sensors
in such a way of high scalability with a
very high low cost.
Another colleague is looking at the
possibility of creating sensors that are
like powder, like dust
that can be spread on
an area to measure temperature,
humidity,
to see how much water can be irrigated
to a park. For instance,
with the combination of new sensors, we
can see a change in the trends.
This is what we have done for 100 years.
We had we used to have statistical
process control. We have a more digital
way of doing things. Now, in the last 15
years, we have developed the concept of
models and now digital twins. But what's
next?
The concept of the digital twin
could be merged with more intelligence.
We are connecting digital twins with
artificial intelligence
and that is what we're doing now. But in
the future, we will be able to do
something more interesting. And in fact,
this is already taking place. Some
colleagues are using this here in the
live stream. Probably they know what I'm
going to explain now. This is the
cognitive digital twin model. This is
the moment and the future.
A cognitive digital twin.
If we think of the overall general twin
digital twin, this is a mirror without a
brain. Now we connect it to AI
and we infuse capabilities that are very
interesting and key. For instance,
perception and attention.
Perception is about sensors. attention
is about machine learning
also memory and learning.
One of the main challenges that we face
is that we have too much data.
These systems at present
don't have the capability to filter
irrelevant data by themselves.
As human beings, we do that immediately,
easily. However,
we should infuse
AI with the capability to filter
irrelevant data.
And then
we could use memory and learning in
these models learning continuously from
history data in real time. I think this
is fascinating.
The models are being improved because
they learn from history data. This is
what we have seen and we continue to see
in our daily lives with Chad GBT and
Gemini. This is improving
day by day.
What we see in the LLMs
is totally different from what we see
today if we compare that to 18 months
ago. Of course, there are things that
still need to be changed. But here we've
come to something really interesting.
Reasoning and problem solving.
If we ask chat GPT
what should I do based on this data
chat GPT will provide a solution.
However the next question should be why
imagine we can do that with the digital
twins
that are updated with this data
and AI. So digital twins could give us a
suggestion
on how we can improve operations
and they can do that in a collaborative
manner. Then again maybe you have tested
this with J Gemini particularly or Siri.
We can have a conversation
not only through AI but also
a conversation with the system in
operation. This is something totally
different. This is not with a model. It
is a conversation with a system of
operation with the context that has been
trained on that context. It is a
different way of working and we have
come to the future with this
capabilities of perception, attention,
memory, reasoning, problem solving and
collaboration in the digital twins. We
have cognitive digital twins.
Essentially, if a traditional digital
twin tells you what is going on when you
add cognition,
you can see
why this is happening, what will happen
in the future and what you should do
about it.
Something changes
when that happens and that is what we
see today.
AI models, LLMs
are learning from us. What we have
written in the past, what we continue to
write, with the videos that we upload to
YouTube, with the books we write, the
models are learning from us. But today
with this concept with this
collaboration that is more natural we
are starting to learn more and better
with them. So this becomes co-learning
a very interesting co-learning with a
context
that is real in front of us. It is
immediate. We know that learning
is easier and better when we don't have
to imagine things. How will I use this?
Now we have things in front of our eyes
and we can ask ourselves what would
happen if or imagine if
I change this if I change that.
So that is the future digital trend.
Thirdly, this concept of process
improvement,
something that already exists that we
have uh managed very well in the last 50
years with the lean system, the Toyota
production system that has applied to
has been applied to different
industries.
With new sensors, we have the cognitive
digital twins
and they are trained
on data of our processes.
So
by asking ourselves what would happen if
we can come
to the application of the digital twin
to an NG. Nissan
for a long time has uh
wanted to create a variable compression
system
engine.
very difficult to do but very
interesting. They were able to do that
because Nissan has a digital model.
They started to iterate by doing that.
Why is this so important?
If you have a variable compression
engine,
you can determine if you want more power
or more efficiency in real time.
So
this is only possible
because we have these new ways of
co-learning
with the new models. And what can we do
with that? Imagine
that we can use the same technologies
to improve
what we already have on the field.
Electric generators with fuel
flexibility.
When designing a generator, that
generator is designed for a particular
fuel like diesel. But in the future we
have nitrogen or ox or hydrogen.
That depends on the compression system.
So maybe we can extend the life cycle of
that uh generator with a lower cost with
a new fuel or we can reduce the energy
consumption of whole tracks. Autonomous
whole tracks. When they are loaded they
need more power. when they are unloaded
they are more efficient.
We can also apply that
to
the change of engines or motors in uh
shovels and drills
to provide performance or better
performance to a fleet that is operating
at a higher elevation. So we can start
looking at possibilities.
This is
connected progressively
in a way that is not just
technological.
I believe this is the key of innovation.
I gave you some ideas about
technologies.
Brian, Anthony, my colleague and others
are working on uh ideas that have
inspired others
with a context. In addition to the
context,
we are iterating things to reach a place
where we can say okay we should test
this. But
reaching that point
When you say okay we can conduct a test
is a process that is human
organizational
and also business related.
Not all companies, not all
social and technical
systems
have the same culture of experiencing
things,
testing things. This comes from the
culture
created within a company considering the
values.
In addition,
The processes are important. What will
your KPIs be? What are the measurement
systems to understand or know if the
system has improved, if uh humans have
improved
so that we can create digital twins for
organizations.
In addition to that, we have to change
the way in which we learn. When we put
all those factors together,
adding also some other concepts that we
are studying in terms of finance risks
and we combine that with technology,
engineering,
we can scale ideas that may start from a
jelly
with metal inside to what we are we have
in front of our eyes. We have to connect
all of that. This is not easy.
So part of my research is based on this
on escalation.
Thank you very much again. It's been a
pleasure to be here with you on behalf
of Brian Anthony as well. Thank you very
much.
on behalf of Brian Anthony
u who couldn't be here. Okay, now we
have a Q&A I guess. Thanks for your
interesting presentation. You have five
minutes
in your favor.
You were very efficient in your
presentation. But we have questions
because as I said we have a QR code and
you can post questions
for our speakers from the technical
desk. We have Rodrigo
asking the questions from the audience.
So let's start with the Q&A.
How are you integrating
digital twins
to these technological projects?
Well, that is exactly what we're trying
to do
>> in different industries and and in
different manners.
Now that we have this possibility to
create systems with which we can
interact in a more natural manner,
we can create a digital twin
but also subdigital twins
with the unit
in an organization.
You can build your models, your
concepts. You can do scenario planning.
When you do that modeling, you can also
put together all the outcomes. And this
is what we have been studying also. It
is a process of communication between
different units, different
uh organizations and that is what
innovation brings about. Instead of
focusing on the differences of our
functions
with advanced manufacturing,
we have differences in design and
production.
When we have this artifact as we call
it, we can focus on the concept itself,
not on the differences between a
designer and somebody in protection.
There is something that I would like to
add also. And we define advanced
manufacturing
in MIT.
We also you can see that this also
includes mining. For us manufacturing is
transformation and flow of material.
When considering that we can include
everything
from
the rock to the point of delivery of the
product to the consumer to the end
consumer and of course when it returns
to the system for recirculation or
recycling.
Yes, we have one more question.
Jose,
how can we efficiently manage the
portfolio of innovation when faced with
so many challenges and ensuring that the
project contributes to medium and
long-term goals?
That's a very good question and this is
where we come to the final part of my
presentation.
How can we simulate different systems
of measurement but not also measurement.
>> In recent years we have focused on key
on KPIs
the key performance indicators. We talk
about indicators.
So what we see today is that these are
not just indicators with a target but
there is a range. What can we do if we
change this indicator with another
indicator and how the outcome would
change? This is not
about
key performance indicators but key
performance indicator ranges.
Secondly,
we need to open to the possibility
an opportunity
to our colleagues who are
building simulations and brainstorming
to communicate
that to the rest of the organization.
So key performance indicator instead of
key performance indicators, we should
have key performance simulators
so that they report new and better ways
to manage operations. Yes, KPIs I just
invented that uh uh concept.
So
you saw what I showed.
We should give uh the opportunity to our
colleagues to create simulations. You
saw that in real time with that. You saw
the images that didn't exist 24 hours
ago,
especially with the three
pictures of the stone
inside the mine and then in different
belts
with the use of AI.
I said, "Imagine
what could happen to help me imagine and
help communicate. This is a new
capability. How can we help our
colleagues use that capability
that changes and accelerates the way in
which we communicate and innovation of
course Jose it's been a pleasure to have
you here with us sharing your knowledge
and expertise and applause to Jose.
He said that people in their north were
more enthusiastic.
I will report to Antoagasta that they
were right.
Thank you very much.