All righty. So, thank y'all for being
here. Uh we can just have a very as a
casual presentation. Uh questions can
come in basically um almost anytime. Uh
so just feel free to raise your hand and
um I'll get to you. So yeah, very happy
to be here again and uh we can get
started. So we see AI development um and
efforts towards regulating these systems
um increasingly becoming centralized in
western countries um despite the impacts
of AI um and other systems transcending
borders. We see western corporations
that are at the frontier uh quote
unquote of AI development be largely
reliant on the African continent um
alongside others um for natural
resources like tantelum, cobalt um and
tungsten uh which form the GPUs that
power these large language models or
large AI models excuse me um also known
as foundation models as coined by
Stanford. And we also see these human
resources uh particularly from data
annotation and also content moderation
um which are used to train um and refine
AI systems. Given that we see Africa um
or Africa is seen um as the next
frontier um for AI development um also
something that Sam Alman recently
mentioned uh we see that digital
resources like data that advance the
capabilities of AI um will likely become
the next commodity that's exploited um
by foreign entities. And so this could
potentially fuel, if not already, this
new era of techno neo colonialism. We
see that these current concerns, excuse
me, um along with issues of bias,
disinformation, uh climate impacts, um
and economic inequality, uh elevate a
need for comprehensive and a robust
alongside harmonized AI and data
regulation efforts across Africa. Um
this will this talk will talk about many
of these aspects particularly focusing
on AI and data governance the bridging
the AI ecosystem in the continent um and
then also thinking about some priorities
um to democratize African participation
um in AI development and
governance. Um so we see that when it
comes to AI progress across the world,
we AI development is primarily
centralized in countries like China, uh
the US, uh Canada, the UK, and also
those throughout the um the EU EU,
excuse me. Uh this includes countries
like France um and Germany. However,
we've begun to also see a lot of
progress um from African grassroots AI
and machine learning communities that
have really helped to fill in some of
these capacity gaps um of accessing
traditional AI and machine learning
education uh particularly from these
universities and also tertiary uh
institutions that offer these masters
and PhD level courses and programs. So
across the continent uh we see
organizations like Masakane um and Ghana
NLP developing data sets and machine
translation tools to help expand access
to low resource African languages. We
also see efforts like deep learning and
daba AI Saturdays Legos and also data
science Africa um and data science
Nigeria um among many others helping to
grow um and enhance these communities of
AI researchers. And so they offer things
like study groups um and even up to uh
workshops and large conferences like
deep learning in Nadaba which will be
held later this year in Kaggali. And so
outside of natural language processing
we also see these specialized AI
communities um also beginning to form.
And so they focus on healthcare um like
Cisson Botique in South Africa um and
then also African AI focusing on
sustainability. And then we also
fortunately I began to see a bit more
let's say diversity in terms of where
these communities are focused. And so
within Francois Africa we have
organizations like AI hub synagal and
also Kami in Cameroon. Um and then also
in northern Africa uh we have Morocco AI
the Tunisian AI society and also Zer AI
um in
Algeria. when it comes to academic AI
research, I'm particularly fond of this,
you know, as a computer scientist and,
you know, someone who has gone through
extensive academic training. And so, um,
it's great to also see that we've, uh,
begun to see more progress, um, in AI
research labs across the continent. And
many of this have been, uh, traced to
the 2020, uh, 4-year 20 million Canadian
dollars, um, AI for development in
Africa initiative, um, also known as AI
for D. And so this is funded by um the
IDRC which is Canad Canada's like
international aid agency and also CEDA
uh which is Sweden's um international
development agency. We also see these
notable academic labs um AI labs
particularly begun to rise on the
continent um in countries uh like Uganda
uh with uh the AI and data science
research lab um at Mccur University. I'm
also the data science for social impact
lab um at the University of Ptoria in
South Africa and also the AI and
robotics lab at the University of Lagos
in Nigeria. There are also more formal
degree programs um arising in AI machine
learning. Um I know some of you are
familiar with the African master of
machine intelligence um that's offered
by the African African Institute for
Mathematical Sciences and then also
masters um in AI from the University of
Maitius um and a bachelor um in AI uh
which is offered by Kumasi Technical
University in Ghana. And so it's really
great to see AI degrees um being offered
at these very uh relatively early
stages. When it comes to the um market
map for AI in Africa, we've also seen a
lot of growth uh particularly in uh
countries that have already been known
as tech hubs on the continent. So this
includes countries like Nigeria, uh
South Africa, uh Kenya, Tunisia, and
Egypt. Um I'll talk about Tunisia um in
a bit because they have a very
interesting use case in terms of um a
startup that arised um out of the
country as well. And so these startups
they focus on um a range of fields that
include healthcare, language generation,
robotics and also just generally show a
lot of promise to help uh address some
of these fundamental development
problems but not you know obviously
solve them completely.
So um according to startup list Africa
there are 85 ASRBs on the continent um
that have received cumulative funding of
about $262 million. Um the top 10 have
commanded about 300 238 million um and
the top three have commanded $27 million
or 28 million um or so. And so this is
again not a comprehensive list. Uh it's
honestly sometimes a bit hard to
determine uh what if a startup is purely
an AI startup or leveraging AI in their
operations, but this is one of the best
analysis that I could find um as of late
last year or so.
Oh, go ahead. Yeah. Do you know if
there's any theme
to
those particular task in general?
Uh, I would say for me like I also did
analysis for a book chapter I wrote, but
this is like really early. It was it was
published in January of 2023, but we did
the analysis basically like way before
Chad GBT came out. And so I feel like I
saw a lot of fintech startups like
adding AI for like identity
verification. Um, you know, fraud
detection. Um, we didn't really see like
a lot of growth in terms of um, say like
language generation or NLP stuff. Uh,
which we do see a lot of like grassroots
efforts focused on now. So I think a lot
of it is focused on finance. We do see
like healthcare and medicine. So not
healthare uh healthcare and also
agriculture. I think agriculture is
probably um one of the main areas that
we see too. So cool. Thank you.
All right. So now um we get to insidep
which is actually one of the most
successful or not the most successful um
AI startups to come out of Africa. And
so in 2023 um it was acquired for $680
million um by biiointech which is a
German far pharmaceutical company um and
it was founded in Tunisia in 2014
um and it has more than 400 uh employees
across the world at different offices
like in London, Paris, Berlin, Tunis,
Lagos, Cape Town, Boston and San
Francisco. And so incident focuses on um
decision-making AI systems for biology,
logistics, electrical design um and
energy. And one of the co-founders,
Karim Buger, he's a really um I would
say a prominent voice within the African
AI ecosystem space um and also supports
AI startups and educational efforts
across Africa too. Uh which is great to
see um that as well. He also returns
back to Tunisia to found Insta Deepep.
And so this is something I think that's
also um really inspiring as well. And so
this research uh comes from Afrey Labs
which is a network organization um that
you know supports innovation hubs and
centers across Africa. Um and this work
is analyzed by Techabal which is
basically like a tech publication within
Africa. And they showed that basically
50% of AI um African AI startups um are
just in seven countries. And so again um
as um mentioned or showed um in one of
the maps earlier we do see a lot of
correlation between basically this these
existing tech hubs like South Africa,
Nigeria um Egypt and the correlation
with where AI startups are as well. And
this is a book chapter I mentioned um on
responsible AI in Africa published in
January 2023. Um and so the analysis
honestly is a bit outdated because you
know um of you know the ChachiBC's
launch um in November of 2022. Um but we
analyzed 102 AI startups um just to
really understand the problems they
addressed um and the implications that
this has for the wider um African
startup ecosystem. And very similar to
the prior slide uh we did see that um
there was not that much diversity in
terms of where these startups were
located. And I think this is also just a
big issue because um investors are
particularly are are more likely to
invest in English-sp speakaking African
countries because a lot of investors in
African startups are from the US um UK
and similar regions like that. And so we
see a lot of exclusion you know from
franophhone and also lucophone Africa.
So, you know, as we continue to grow the
AI ecosystem across Africa, it'll be
really essential um that AI services
built on the continent um also serve
these diverse um linguistic communities
and um cultural communities as well.
And so there's so many challenges um
across AI AI ecosystem and not just you
know dedicated to AI particularly um but
we have things like infrastructure
education a digital literacy and just
unequal access to ICT um resources and
services that have impacted the African
continent for decades. And so this um
you know impacts things like
infrastructure obviously particularly
when we consider the large amounts of
data um that are needed to train AI
systems um and the high number of
computing resources that are consumed in
this process and so again infrastructure
really challenges um the abilities of
African uh researchers and developers to
innovate in this space um we've seen
that um particularly uh many challenges
with internet access um and the
international telecommunications union
um as estimated that about from um in
2011 um internet penetration across the
continent was about 8% um and it grew to
36% um in 2021 and the numbers honestly
um haven't really changed that much. I
think we had some issues with um with
issues exacerbated by the COVID pandemic
as well. Um so I I think it's around 45%
now but we'll have to to look at that.
Uh fortunately we also see um a lot of
efforts that have begun to focus on
improving connectivity across the
continent. Um this u map on the screen
details the two Africa cable and so this
is the longest uh subc internet cable
that's ever been designed. Um it's
currently under deployment and has 46
connections uh to landbased networks
across 33 countries in Africa uh Asia
and Europe. And so again, we only know
that internet is uh access uh is only
just one aspect of a successful AI
ecosystem. And so we also see other
challenges across Africa that include
things like digital literacy um talent
AI talent concentration and also having
access to these uh relevant data sets to
build and train these um AI
models. So building upon these
infrastructure challenges um this
research is really interesting. and it
comes from the Oxford Internet Institute
and shows that AI compute is also um
unequally distributed globally. So their
work classifies countries um basically
excuse me into three categories. Uh so
we have the compute north uh where
predominantly rich countries um host
data centers uh with the latest GPUs for
training uh these frontier AI models.
And then we also have the compute south
uh which essentially are um these
predominantly middle inome countries
that host older GPUs um that are
relevant for deploying but not necess
but not necessarily excuse me training
this frontier AI models. And then we
have compute desert which you can
basically see like right in the middle
um of the map and also around Russia and
similar areas where countries have no
cloud AI compute at all and they may
have necessarily like data centers but
that this um doesn't necessarily count
um data centers that are uh specifically
used for non AI purposes. Again we see
these disparities um with you know
regions like Africa, Latin America um
the Caribbean and also Oceanana
specifically around the smaller um
islands not having a lot of access you
know to these specific compute uh
clusters as
well. And then also very interesting
work um a lot of the uh researchers from
this project are actually here at MIT.
Um and so this is uh from the data
provenence initiative and so this work
was um I think mainly published starting
from 2024 and I know they also had
papers at Iclear and some other
conferences as well. Um and so they
conducted a widescale audit of data sets
that were used to train AI systems and
they found extreme disparities um in the
global representation um of data sets
and found that less than 0.2 um of a
percent uh comes from Africa um or South
America. Again um we see that these
issues of underrepresentation um impact
the development of AI systems. And this
is something I wrote recently um for the
international AI safety report uh that
was chaired by professor Yosua Benjio.
Um and this leads to bias and also
unequal performance um of these tools on
global languages, cultures and also
value systems as
well. And so now uh we get to the topic
of digital literacy which is honestly
something I think it's a bit hard to
really address uh because people have to
act have access to these digital
technologies in the first place. um to
really become literate in a sense and
the World Bank shows that um out of all
world regions uh subsaharan Africa has
the lowest percentage of citizens that
are equipped with digital skills and so
this equals to about half of the average
level um of digital literacy or digital
skills adoption that we see globally.
Thus, we also have to ensure that um AI
is accessible to these broader
nontechnical populations um across
Africa, particularly when it comes to
women uh youth and older adults um who
tend to be excluded um from digital
technologies as well. And so efforts,
you know, that are focused on um
literacy and and and other things and
media training as well um have to ensure
that these populations are included.
Go ahead. Oh, sorry. Just one question.
What's usually counted in digital
woodshake? Is it like navigate the web
email or is it like something more
specific? Yeah, I think it's yes uh some
of those. I don't have the specific uh I
would say measures or metrics from what
the World Bank measures, but I think
it's a lot of that. I don't think social
media is included. I think it's really
just like sending text messages,
accessing email. They probably do being
able to do like a basic search on some
search platform. So, yeah.
Is that a good?
Yeah, it's hard to say because I think
like for search many people would not
necessarily do that well. I think like
for communication like uh texting um and
also like calling I think like people
would score a bit higher on that. Um but
when it comes like information seeking
and access I think that's also a big
challenge too. And then you know it's
definitely changed with all you know the
disinformation and misinformation too.
So yeah, thank you. Um and so this is um
this slide talks about the respective
concentration um and production of AI
talent something that I've also written
about um and what we consider basically
where AI talent um is concentrated. We
have mainly two countries. So this is
the US um and also China. And so India
is also really an interesting uh place
but they have I would say a lot of
attrition which is also known as like
brain drain um because developers you
know from India you know often go to the
Canada, US, the UK to basically seek um
these like tech jobs and also AI jobs as
well.
However, we've seen some interesting
research um this was published in the
Harvard Business Review um that shows
that there are many hot spots
particularly a lot within India and also
within other global south global
majority countries um in cities like
Johannesburg, Nairobi and Lagos um also
be quickly becoming AI hotspots within a
continent and again um these cities
basically kind of correspond uh to I
would say like the countries that are
already hotspots for tech Thailand as
well. Um so it would be really great to
see how this evolves um over the next
couple years to include some of the
smaller markets across
Africa. And something which is really
interesting is that um I mentioned
branding pre previously. This is also an
issue that affects African countries uh
particularly more so in the service
domain. So we see a lot of um like
medical workers um and also domestic
workers leaving the continent um you
know for the Middle East and also other
countries as well. Um and so this uh
report is basically um this uh image uh
is analysis or uh report of the 2021
Africa developer ecosystem um initiative
that was uh detailed by Google. And so
they estimate that about 38% of African
developers um they work in Africa for a
company that has its headquarters
outside of the continent. And so they
haven't necessarily updated this report
recently. Um, I've also seen
organizations like OECD report on these
stats. Um, so I'm not sure what the
trend is for AI jobs. Um, but I know
that uh, for example, Microsoft, IBM,
and Google have big AI hubs on the
continent. And so um, I assume they they
also have a higher concentration um, of
AI talent um, compared to other like
local companies as well. And so again um
you know for AI talent within Africa or
just for the African AI ecosystem to
grow um more broadly there has to be
efforts um that encourage people to stay
um and be well compensated you know for
the labor that they contribute um to
developing researching and also building
um AI
systems. And so I'll talk uh about AI
and data governance in Africa. It'll be
very broad. Uh there's so many different
developments that are happening.
actually recently found out that Kot
Divvois um announced or developed or
sorry released um their respective AI
strategy and data strategy around March
20th or so. So it's good to see a lot of
progress and uh good to see that my
slides are becoming um outdated about
every month or so.
So uh the Carnegie Council for Ethics
and International Affairs defines AI
governance um as a set of rules,
regulations, ethical and technical
frameworks and similar mechanisms that
guide the development and deployment of
AI technologies. Um I also find that you
know if you talk to me that data
governance is also a very essential
aspect of AI governance particularly as
it provides protections um over how
personal information is collected,
stored uh transferred um and also
provides data subjects with the ability
um to have control um over their
information and also rights to be
informed uh regarding personal data
breaches which have become uh a bigger
or more higher in occurrence, excuse me.
um you know due to many issues around
the pandemic but also limited capacity
um you know of companies across the
continent to have effective safeguards
for data and so again um given that we
see that uh data has a fundamental role
in training machine learning models um
evaluating AI systems uh refining
predictive models and also improving AI
enabled services um enacting effective
data governance can also form the
foundation of robust and comprehensive
AI governance measures.
Um over the past 5 years a global
interest in regulating AI has also grown
dramatically. Um we see this effort uh
this graphic from authority hacker um
shows basically the world stage or state
um of global AI regulation and they
break it down into four tiers. And so um
they detail countries that have enacted
regulation um initiated regulatory
efforts um those who are actively
working towards regulation and also
those who have no regulation. And so
again similar to some of the other maps
I've shown um throughout the
presentation we honestly see like Africa
sticks out a little bit. Um and I would
say like again there's a lot of
progress. There are about 17 countries
or so um that have made formal AI
strategies. There's technically only one
country um on the continent that has an
AI policy, which is Wanda. Um but it's
still in draft stage and hasn't been
fully enacted. And so uh I don't even
know if they're highlighted on the
screen, but it's a very small country.
So yeah. Uh and so again, while we see
that the EU has um led global regulatory
AI efforts, um we also see countries
across the global majority or global
south uh making progress. And so Brazil
actually had um a recent AI law uh that
was approved in December 2024. Um again,
but I um also mentioned uh or talked to
some people that there's also been a
interesting influence of tech companies
um on these regulations. Um there were
some provisions in the uh draft um AI
law from Brazil that were actually
weakened because of lobbying. And so
unfortunately I I do expect this to
continue um in some
manner. And then again um or just more
more broadly uh we see that the
increasing development and adoption of
AI have really drastically or
dramatically shifted practices around
data. Um this has spurred the uh
development of new industries
particularly like data um labeling and
content moderation. Um and then also
revealed new forms of exploitation
particularly um from these respective
fields that I mentioned. um these new
complexities um around data production
uh refinement and also use have really
impacted African countries and also
again um elevates the need for
comprehensive governance and um
enforcement measures. So about 38 out of
55 African Union member states. Um so
this is 54 African countries and also uh
the disputed territory of uh Western
Sahara. Um also known as the Sari Arab
Republic and they have enacted formal
data uh protection regulations and 15
out of 38 were enacted in the past 5
years and 26 out of these 38 were
enacted in the past decade. And so we
saw the first data protection law come
into play um in 2001 by Cabo Verde. And
then also we see that there's been a lot
of progress recently over the past year.
Uh we see countries like Malawi um
enacting a data protection law in June
2024 um and Ethiopia in July 2024. And
then as of yet we see that there are
draft laws that are still in progress um
from countries that include Namibia,
South Sudan um and the Gabia. So we hope
to see a bit more progress um towards
data protection um in these countries
soon. And then also um aside from these
country specific efforts uh we also see
um efforts from regional economic
communities uh basically which serve as
like economic blocks across Africa um
and also entities like the African Union
uh which I've been fortunate to work
with um on different initiatives
particularly the AUAI strategy um which
I'll detail in a following slide and so
they've introduced these data protection
acts and also like cyber security um and
personal um data protection. This is
actually ratified um in 2023
uh 9 years after it was formally
adopted. Uh it was drafted in 2011 um in
Malabo which is in Equatorial Guinea uh
which is where the name comes from and
was uh came into force on June 8th 2023
um after being ratified by Moritania uh
which was the 15th country that was
needed for full ratification um to take
effect. Um unfortunately this is I would
say protection or this framework is not
necessarily enforceable. And so this is
something I think that the the AU um
will also have to work towards um as we
expand efforts for data governance and
AI governance um across
Africa. And so regional efforts um have
also something I would say I'm a bit
more bullish on in terms of um them
being able to provide more sufficient
protections uh for different African
countries. And so we see efforts um on
data protection um that have been
implemented by the economic community of
West African states um most probably one
of the most prominent economic blocks
within Africa um known as EcoAs and we
also have the southern African
development community um known as SEDC
and also the East African African
Community excuse me um and then fortunat
unfortunately uh we haven't seen any
regional governance measures um proposed
or enacted by the Arab McGregor Union
which consists of a lot of um Sahel and
um northern African states. Um and then
also we have another community for uh
Sahel Saharin states um and the economic
community of central African states and
honestly particularly when it comes to
central Africa there um unfortunately
happens to be I would say a lot of
conflict um that you know definitely
delays uh the um development and
enactment you know of data regulation
and you know probably will you know
follow on to AI regulation and also
within ECOAS as well we have three
countries that actually left the block
um due to you know different uh regional
and cultural differences and so um I
think we stand to see a little a lack of
cohesion unfortunately um across these
respective
efforts and so uh this work um this
graphic is from lawyers of Africa and
basically that does a lot of work around
AI and data governance across the
continent um and more generally um
there's research from the African
Observatory on AI um that shows that
only 75 out of 55 African Union member
states um have a policy strategy plan or
guideline on AI. And so this includes
like a ministerial or presidential
statement or a fully blown um or
developed strategy document like that of
Maitius, Nigeria, Rwanda and other
countries as well. And so again as I
mentioned uh Rwanda is the only African
country that has introduced a formal AI
policy. Um again it's yet to be enacted.
So we hope to see a lot of progress. Um
I was actually in Kaggali um earlier
this month for the um a global AI summit
on Africa and so there was a lot of
progress like a new declaration for
African AI and so I hope to see um
movements towards um enactment of AI
regulations or policies um in the near
future. Go ahead. Um so can I ask what
are some of the like similarities or the
difference between like what the like
the EU's polic
Yeah, I would say like um when we think
about AU um AU member states, countries
um the thing is because like there isn't
advanced AI development, a lot of the
plans are really focused on like how can
we leverage AI like in the across these
different sectors. So a lot of them and
I when I worked on the AUA strategy it's
like focused on like healthcare,
education, agriculture and many of the
like state level or national level uh
policy excuse me strategy documents also
mimic this as well. Um we don't
necessarily see like you know the EU
talking about oh we want to leverage
again a agriculture because you know
they already have to an to an extent. Um
and there they I would say there's like
more of um I guess people call this like
a human rights approach or framework to
governing AI. um even though the EUA act
does fall short um particularly when it
comes to covering migrants and and other
um issues around border control and
immigration um and they have separate
provisions you know for that um I
unfortunately I don't see and I wanted
to say like you know African countries
are thinking about developing and
implementing AI in responsible ways but
they don't necessarily take the
forefront um of like these respective
approaches compared to uh like how the
EU has I would say positioned themselves
to be. So those would probably be the
main differences I see. Yeah. Cool.
Question is like how much heterogeneity
is there in sort of policies sort of at
the highest levels of
densities policies. Yeah. I would say
for me I just you know see a lot of
similarities or homogeneity um across
these strategy documents and sometimes
like you know you you start to see that
they become very repetitive but um I
know that countries are also trying to
understand how AI aligns best with their
respective national priorities. Um I
don't think there honestly there's
enough emphasis on doing that. Uh for
example um I I'll talk about Angola
later but um the country is actually
very focused on oil and I don't think
they have a they yeah they don't have an
AI strategy um I know they do have a
data protection strategy and so um I
assume like any document they develop uh
will probably more so align with
basically you know trying to understand
how AI can augment their respective like
oil petroleum gas sector um as well and
so I think that other African countries
should take similar approaches but you
know obviously there are other concerns
concerns we um around climate um ethical
uh issues and and bias as well. So yeah,
China is comparable to the
US China
Yeah. So I would say it's still I would
say hard to understand like China's
influence on the African AI ecosystem. I
think you know they've had uh really or
made like really great progress and
influence basically on infrastructure.
So, you know, like ports, um, you know,
um, airports, uh, roads, uh, shipping
rails, railways, all that stuff. Um,
it's interesting because I felt like
there were a lot of the development
agencies from Europe actually were
playing a big role. So like GIZ from um
from Germany um IDRC CEDA um USA a
little bit now you know it's obviously
like not really you know doing anything
now but um and so a lot of my
understanding or just like belief in a
way was that these development agencies
were essentially trying to counter
China's influence in a way particularly
especially the US um because they had um
like this effort that was announced in
the Biden administration um I think like
global AI sharing something like that um
I'm not sure if it will continue or not.
Um and so I think again like China is
actually very well positioned um to
really start supporting like fundamental
African research. Um again not sure how
much that is happening. Um, but I think
again they I don't like to see you know
Africa be a I don't know like a ground
or like a what am I I'm trying to say
just like uh a place for people to kind
of like pick and choose you know how
they did with you know with the um
Berlin convention and all that stuff as
well. Um but you know honest
unfortunately that's happening. Um I
think the the long-term game or goal
would be to move towards like
sovereignty, data sovereignty, AA
sovereignty, but we're still very much
far away from there. But I think in the
meantime, like African countries also
have to understand um how they can best
um like leverage AI um in ways that meet
their national goals. And unfortunately
um I would say like to the US's I say
like dislike um many African countries
ideologically align more so with China
and Russia you know than with you know
US and other democratic countries and so
I think this is also something that um
many governments are considering in
terms of how they set up their alliances
um with international development
agencies or the countries themselves.
Thank you so much.
Mhm. Yeah.
Mhm.
Yeah. Mhm.
Yeah. Yeah. This is a very tough
question. It seems like you know you're
well verssed in it um a bit yourself but
I would say for
me I don't even know if it's possible to
do that now just because like the way of
like I guess like AI diffusion or how
like AI models um and tools and systems
are spread across African countries and
also just generally the world like we
would really have to like start from the
ground up but we don't have the
resources you know to build these
systems um or tools like natively um in
ways you know again that align with
African value systems
um and also you know comprehensively
integrate African data sets as well and
so yeah I think again we're a bit far
past that and it would really again take
like kind of a revolution or just like a
reframing or rethinking in terms of how
um African researchers lead in AI
development and also like um approach
and also like what kind of models that
they take um or methodology excuse me to
build these systems in the first place.
So thank you. Go ahead. So, how much of
the strategy is sort of
thinking about like starting from the
ground up and building something
natively versus like what's the right
strategy to Vietnam?
Like the vision.
Yeah. Yeah, unfortunately I don't see
like you know the building from the
ground up um happening or being
mentioned in these documents because um
unfortunately I would say like African
countries or researchers have become
reliant um on these you know open source
or models which you know happen to be
more so open weight um like for example
llama and like fine-tuning them and I
think honestly it it's a bit of an
easier way to approach AI development
but again I don't think it's the right
approach because I don't think these
models are particularly built
um you know for African linguistic
context um which is something that I
think that's why we need to really
invest in this fundamental AI research
across the continent um and then also
even just like when we consider cultural
needs and nuances and even like you know
the size of these models are is really
not feasible in general um so I would
love to see more of that being
integrated but it's really not
unfortunately yeah awesome great yeah
thanks for the great questions everyone
Yeah. So now um I'll talk about um the
AUA AI strategy. Not honestly won't go
too deep into it, but um it basically
aims to provide guidance um to African
countries um to harness AI um to meet
Africa's development aspirations. And
this basically is a quote from um uh the
the AI strategy itself. and they
mentioned that the goal um is also to
improve the well-being of African people
um while promoting ethical use,
minimizing potential risk and also
leveraging different opportunities that
AI could potentially bring. And so the
African Union Executive Council endorsed
the continental AI strategy during the
45th ordinary session in Acra, Ghana. Um
this happened last year from July 18th
to 19th. Um and it was formally formally
released on August 9th and it's expected
to be fully endorsed by the AU head of
state. Um I think it was supposed to
happen earlier this year at the AU
summit but it is still um in the process
of you know going into full
implementation and so again still
waiting to understand how this framework
will be binding and also whether or not
the AU will um improve enforcement
capacity um to ensure that African all
African countries or AU member states um
can be on uh the path to developing AI
strategies and eventually AI policies
which is the end goal.
So now let's talk about some
implications of AI in Africa. I think uh
this is what a lot of people will be
interested in. Um and I'm sure you are
aware of the different challenges
particularly you know from AI being
purported or like posed um as a way to
help African countries fasttrack
development. Um and so again we know
that these technologies are you know
filled with different risk um and
implica and implications. Um
particularly we see that a lot of
literature um on bias and limitations of
AI uh really focused on domains like
healthcare, employment and policing. Um
unfortunately we do see a lot of this
work focused um on western context and
this is something I've you know written
about you know mentioning how you know
things social constructs like race may
not necessarily be applicable across
contexts like Africa you know suffering
countries like South Africa for example
um where we do see these racial
stratifications um but again I think
it's really important to emphasize or
promote um you know contextual AI
research that really understands things
like cast and tribe and religion and
also the intersections of these
identities um to really promote this
contextual understanding um of bias and
the implications of AI across Africa and
also across the rest of the the global
south or uh the global majority. And so,
um, this is a stat I mention a lot. Um,
and we see that, um, African countries
are spending about a billion dollars a
year, um, on surveillance, uh, contracts
with companies that are based, um, in
the US, the UK, uh, China, across the
EU, and also Israel. In these countries,
uh, we see that these technologies um,
have been used to unjustly hold citizens
in detention um, and also um, because
they've made critical posts to the
governments and also track activities of
journalists. Um there's a really
prominent jour journalist in Eastern
Africa uh eastern southern Africa uh
Gregory Gone um who has actually been
jailed and um talked about his
experiences um you know dealing with a
AI enabled surveillance because um of
his outspokenenness against
governments. We've also seen and this is
a very prominent topic at the moment
which is great um about the harms that
you know data annotators and content
moderators have faced um particularly
within Africa Kenya is seen as the hot
spot or the hub um for AI development
and particularly like AI labeling and
content moderation uh within the
continent and again I think because you
see that many African countries have
issues um around you know unemployment
and even undermployment um that you know
this say data exploitation
And also uh you know this form of labor
may become more widespread because you
know there's a lot of young people in
Africa they're looking for opportunities
um and you know data labeling is
relatively easy to do um you know
despite the strenuous task and and other
issues associated with it as well. Um
again we do see a lack um you know of
robust data protections um and AI
policies throughout the continent's our
strategies at the moment uh which we're
you know are mainly focused on um and I
could think this will have a greater
impact um because you or lead to greater
levels of misuse um as AI continues to
grow um in reach again you know I don't
want to highlight Africa as being slow
in the AI regulation race because
technically you know the EU AI act is
the most uh prominent legislation. Um,
and I think mainly the most like only
the only enacted regulation, excuse me.
But again, there's still a lot of
efforts um that African countries need
to focus on as well. Go ahead.
Mhm.
Yeah.
you saying that the potential of AI for
that? Yes. Okay.
Uh yeah, I know Google's doing this. Um
they have a really interesting like
flood forecasting tool um that they've
been leveraging and actually has been
helpful in predicting floods across
Africa also mainly across the world too
and um they have been able to like
integrate this or allow governments to
leverage this information to like help
with like uh warning systems and
everything. Um there's also a really
interesting project um from the
distributed air research institute led
by Tim Gabru um and one of the fellows
there um I always I don't want to
pronounce her name wrong but uh Resa J
Safala uh she is in South Africa and
she's actually leveraged um AI based
geospatial mapping to actually map like
apartheid um and understanding like the
differences in housing and also just
like geographic or geographical like um
you know structures and everything like
that too. So um that work is super
interesting and I think there's many
more implications for um a lot of work
you know actually from like MIT
researchers and um I my colleagues like
Lily Zoo uh for example she's starting a
professorship at Colombia and I think
next year later this year um she's done
a lot of work on like conservation and
like mapping using AI too. So, um I
think there's a lot of um Oh, sorry.
They Lily was at Harvard, excuse me. Um
uh but uh Meen Tombbe was like the
professor that was uh like leading or
steering that work too. Um so there's a
lot of I think like promise in that
domain and I I actually think it's one
of the use cases of AI that I'm a bit
more I would say like fond of. So yeah.
Cool. All right.
So yeah, so this is some work um that
I've done over the past uh like year and
a half or so um that really under tries
to like unpack um the growing discourse
on the negative impacts um of
technologies like generative AI for
example. Um this work was really focused
on myths and disinformation um
particularly in the context of African
elections and other democratic
processes. um because you know not just
in the US but within Africa we've seen a
lot um of interesting usage um in terms
of how you know these tools have had an
impact um again on elections. Go ahead.
One of the things that at least has been
true to my
friends a lot of missing disinformation.
Yeah. How is that true here? How hard is
it to
study Twitter?
Yeah. Yes. I would say like very similar
for Africa too. And we also see like how
disinformation and misinformation also
moves offline particularly through like
radio um and also like print media too.
So, this actually makes it even harder
um because we know like there's some
social media companies, I'm not sure if
Twitter's still doing this. Um but
basically like if you know the community
notes and if you saw something they
would actually notify you after you saw
it as well. Um it's very hard to do that
you know through you know these
encrypted platforms like WhatsApp uh
signal etc. And again even more so
harder for um you know print and and
radio media as well. Uh so I don't think
we have any good statistics um on this
in Africa and I think just because it's
a a measurement problem um that's really
hard to to focus on. So yeah.
Cool. All right. And so when it comes to
this information just to give a very
brief um definition it's the intentional
creation and spread of deliberative
sorry deliberately deceptive information
um to mislead or influence people
communities and also institutions. Um
again we see that African countries
particularly struggle with
disinformation and research um from
Wasammen and Madrid morales shows that
media consumers in countries like Kenya,
Nigeria and South Africa are regularly
exposed to disinformation.
Uh we've also see that these issues
around dis and misinformation have been
exacerbated by the growth um um or
access of information you know through
platforms like social media and then
again even you know further exacerbated
by the introduction of generative AI um
in content
production and so when it comes to
African elections uh we've seen a lot of
different uh interesting use cases of
generative AI um and I think something
that I would love to see in future work
it's not a focus of mine at the moment,
but really understanding like the usage
and impact um of AI across African
elections. Um there's been reports and
surveys that show you know that African
governments are actively already um
leveraging AI to assist uh with um
processes like authentication um voter
registration management and also
engagement and also you know some things
like detecting cyber threats um and
aiding in oversight um and decision-m
and so we've seen a lot of um AI uh
generated propaganda that have
influenced um elections or even
precipitated coups um in countries like
Nigeria, Burkina Faso and Sineagal. And
this really underscores the need for
more comprehensive um detection and
mitigation efforts as
well. And so this report was from
December 20 uh November 2024. Um but
Ghana held their elections in December
of last year and show that the incumbent
political party within Ghana was using
AI to spread misinformation about
opposing candidates. Um but actually I
don't it's also hard to understand the
impact of dis this and misinformation um
on voter um I would say I would say
intentions or choices because the
opposing candidate party actually won um
and so we saw that they saw that there
were tweets um that were using AI
generated profile images and also they
would post between certain times of the
day um and Ghana time or Ghanaian time
um as well. And so the again as I
mentioned the opposing party actually
won. So uh would love to see if there
have been like further analysis trying
to unpack um the actual influence of
this content. And so this is a really
interesting case and I like to bring it
up because it happened um in 2018 and so
this is when I would say like GANs were
really coming into play and you know
obviously way before tools like chatbt
and you know other image generators like
Dolly and and and Mjourney and others
and so we've seen that um political
propaganda has shown to impact coups um
before during and after they happen and
so this happened um in 2018 December
2018 and this is a video that claimed to
depict Ali Bango uh who was the
president of Gabon at the time and it
stirred concern on social media because
people noticed that um there were
unnatural expressions you know his eyes
weren't moving um his lips were not
necessarily super consistent with the
words um and also the posture was
unnatural you know for him because he
was suspected to be very ill um and
undergoing treatment and so reports
claimed that uh you know this video
raised concerns about his ability to
rule and actually sparked a coup uh in
January of 2019, but it later failed. Um
and so again um you know this has been
happening you know for you know about
seven years if not longer now. And so I
think there still needs to be a bit more
awareness in terms of how generative AI
and even you know more recent
technologies continue to impact
different processes across
Africa. And so in Bkina Foso's most
recent coup um in September 2022 um
there's actually a really interesting
series of AI generated images or videos
um from Americanbased pan-Africanist and
so they appear to express support for
the new regime um and these videos were
initially detected on Twitter and
Facebook and were also shared um by
videos uh by people who actually
received these videos through WhatsApp.
Um the videos were created um from the
AI generated application Synthesia um
and the company actually confirmed the
user banned them um but they never ideal
uh reveal the identity of the person
also. Are we good on time? I'm not sure.
Okay, cool. Okay, cool. No worries.
Cool. Yeah. So again, we see that
generative AA has a really strong
potential to impact democratic processes
across Africa uh primarily in elections.
Um again I'm asked you know there have
been a lot of coups particularly within
the sahilian region um within west
western Africa and so I think there's a
lot more potential or possibilities to
understand um you know the role of
generative AI um in any of any of these
respective events and so kind of just to
wrap up um I'll talk about some AI
policy opportunities uh for Africa and
really again thinking about we have so
many pressing challenges um this
includes refining social services uh
tackling insec security, uh, planning
for climate change, building
infrastructure, um, and also fighting
corruption. Um, and so sometimes, in my
opinion, they really take greater
precedence over regulating AI. And so,
however, I think there, you know, are
efforts needed by African countries to
concurrently work towards addressing
these issues and also developing robust
data and AI regulation. And so, this is
a paper um, I wrote with some colleagues
last year um, that focused on uh, case
studies of policy development in Africa.
Um and so we show that you know African
countries face a range of challenges um
in meeting their technological potential
and you know this includes weak or
insufficient data protection regimes um
and then also um a lack or complications
in achieving robust oversight frameworks
and then honestly like limited uh
resources to devote specifically to um
AI governance and development and I
mentioned Angola and because of their
respective priorities in terms of um
scaling um the oil petroleum ecosystem
AI honestly isn't as a priority is not a
priority for the country and so just to
wrap up um these are some of the I would
say areas I think you know are most
essential it's not super comprehensive I
don't think it's meant to be but really
thinking about how um African
governments can focus on strengthening
data and computing infrastructure uh
which is you know obviously helpful for
things outside of AI um also really
thinking about increasing this regional
and and continental cooperation
um particularly you know as I mentioned
the role of these regional economic
communities um in order to bolster um
countries that don't necessarily have
the individual capacity um to enact and
draft regulations and then also really
thinking about um enhancing AI and data
governance also including things like
reform uh which is uh something I've
read written about recently as well um
and then you know obviously to help
support AI ecosystems there needs to be
efforts to expand AI education um and
also employment opportunities um many of
which will come through entrepreneurship
um as we've seen in the case of the US
for example um and then again something
I'm very fun um I would say passionate
about is accelerating fundamental AI
research um because you know African uh
AI that's used in Africa uh needs to be
developed you know to fit the contextual
needs um and the daily realities of
Africans um and then finally um
something something I don't think that
is addressed enough is really just
improving this um public engagement uh
within AI and really having just like
the average person understand you know
about data governance, data privacy, you
know AI regulation as well um and
soliciting input from these um
stakeholders before you know uh
strategies or policies come into action
um and then also ensuring that um they
are included in processes to refine um
and improve um you know policies and
strategies as well. Um so I'll end here
and take any questions but thank you all
for attending. I know it's a very busy
point in the semester. Um, so I
appreciate the the participation. So,