I'm delighted to introduce Isabelle
Varela um to discuss some of the um
research and learning we're trying to do
at
>> I have
Thank you.
So I'm Isabelle with heat and I will be
sharing with you today uh how heat is
trying to learn from these geothermal
energy networks. Um so learning from
geothermal energy networks and thank
you.
Keat has a research project um that is
called learning from the ground up and
it is funded by Massachusetts clean
energy center and the goal of this
project is to evaluate the potential of
these geothermal networks in
Massachusetts
um and mainly to really increase
understanding of this technology and uh
to optimize it as much as we can. We
want to share all the learnings with the
stakeholders and make that knowledge um
public open source.
Here is a brief organizational chart um
in bubbles. I'm not going to go into
detail but I just want to share you know
what are the different organizations
that are collaborating with us. So we
have this great uh consortium where we
have uh ENL that Juliet will be speaking
today. We have LBNL. We have uh Boston
University uh Nathan Phillips, he was a
speaker yesterday, Jonathan Bunor as
well. They're part of that legup
research group. We're also collaborating
with Burough Habold. And of course, we
partner with our utilities that are
doing these systems and these
installations uh here in Massachusetts.
So, how is this project organized? at
the core of this project. The project is
anchored on the data demonstration uh
projects that are here in Massachusetts.
And then we're looking at core modeling,
the impacts of these installations and a
scaling of these systems. So we'll go a
little bit into uh these in more detail.
So in Massachusetts there are different
pilot projects or demonstration
projects. uh as we heard from uh Eric
Bosworth, there's the Frammingham
project. So that's the one that is
installed already uh already in the
commissioning stage. Then there's
Franklin Field uh national grid uh just
is right now in the design phase of that
and they will be drilling their test
bore hole this month. uh and we also
have the extension the second loop in
Frammingham and heat has collaborated
with Eversource and got grant from the
department of energy uh to do the design
phase and now we were selected for the
construction phase of that project. So
we're very excited to have that moving
forward.
So what are the things that heat is
doing as part of this? So the data
acquisition here is focused on
temperature data acquiring temperature
data down the bore holes. So this is
fiber optic cables that are being u
installed in a subset of bore holes. So
there are 90 bore holes in the
Frammingham project and 15 of those have
fiber optic cable to measure temperature
at every location down the bore hole.
And this is temperature that is measured
constantly and the idea is that we can
um analyze this data with the variations
that we see in the days with the seasons
and with the years. So really when we
have one year of data when that system
has been performed for one year and we
get that sinosoidal curve that uh Connor
uh showed earlier today that's when we
want to you know uh really leverage this
data and how do we think it's going to
keep on performing throughout the years.
So with this we can monitor the systems
and see if there's any change that needs
to be made so that it functions
optimally within the temperature range
that the heat pumps work best.
the modeling part. So we have two groups
LBNL and ENL that are focusing on
developing these core modeling uh tools.
So LBNL has focused on developing a full
physics model um that is more
complicated runs in Modelica softwares
that are less accessible if you will and
then ENL has been working on um reduced
order models tools and I won't steal
your thunder uh Juliet will be talking
more about that um that will uh run
quicker and you can still get uh the
behavior of the system with these models
and the idea is that they're going to be
open source as well
And this is another slide uh from that
model and I'll just briefly mention that
for example one of the outcomes that you
can get is that um you have this in the
horizontal line you have the buildings
going along that uh loop and then in the
summer for example as you go from
building to building in that ambient
temperature loop you're getting hotter
and hotter until you reach the bore hole
and then you cool down and then you go
around the loop hotter hotter and then
you reach the bore hole and you go down.
So this is one of the advantages of
having different bore fields as Brian
Erlab was mentioning earlier today. Um
so we have that in this uh
in this Frammingham um project and then
we have a similar example uh when we are
uh in the winter.
This project is looking at what are the
impacts of these geothermal networks in
a more holistical way. We're looking
also at ecology um at the impacts on
health, the impacts on equity. So this
is a work that is being done right now
uh and Angie here is the lead for that
in heat impacts on emissions impacts on
the electric grid. One of the things
that we want to do is to have
measurements at these demonstration
projects uh to measure what um to
quantify the impact on the electric
grid. So Zay mentioned you know what is
the impact of ground source heat pumps
with this ORNL study if you had them at
a national scale and here we want to
quantify it for a particular project uh
these demonstration projects that we
have in Massachusetts and we also want
to know what is the impact of costs one
of the things that we're working with
Boro Hapold and ENL is to make this um
survey about costs um cost of drilling
cost of the construction of the main
loop and costs also of the retrofit. So
the three different phases that were
discussed earlier today
and all of this the idea is to uh feed a
study on this regional assessment uh how
would it look like if we had these
systems installed uh for an entire city
uh here in Massachusetts uh say for
example the city of Cambridge. How would
it look like if we had it for the entire
state of Massachusetts? So, what are the
impacts uh of that
and
this ties very well into the previous uh
session we were talking about data. Data
is one of the things that is needed and
here this is a database that heat is
making. Um the idea is to enable
quantitative comparison between the
systems to identify what are the design
parameters that work best. Things like
the diameter of the main pipe. Uh what
is you know the temperature range that
the uh main pipe is allowed to fluctuate
in. Um so all these kind of engineering
technical aspects but also uh practical
things. So we want to capture the
knowledge of the demonstration project
in Frammingham. We want to capture the
knowledge of the demon of the project in
Colorado Mesa University that will be
presented later on that has been running
since 2008. So all of this uh knowledge
we want to be able to capture it in a
database that will be open source and
this uh interface uh heat has created it
is up and running right now our beta
version and we're in the process of
collecting data from all these existing
projects. Um
we also want to capture information
about costs.
We want to really eventually identify
how to reduce those costs. Right? But we
want to first have that database and we
want to support the development of
datadriven u legislation and regulation
which connects to uh our session
yesterday with chair von nostrren.
So what is it? We're creating a public
datab bank of these geothermal network
installations and why we want to do this
to inform and to facilitate future
developments of these systems
and how this interface is linked to the
heat data uh website and it is stored in
the Harvard data versse which is has the
infrastructure to store data in
perpetuity.
So as we right now have few of these um
demonstration projects for example the
one in Frammingham and Colorado Mesa
University the idea is that when we have
more of these systems we want to be
populating this database so that it is
really useful and that knowledge can be
u the knowledge from the database can be
useful for those installing uh these
systems for communities that are
thinking of doing these installations.
Uh for example, we have the kickstart
program here in Massachusetts that is
also part of this uh legup project where
uh 12 communities in Massachusetts are
doing either feasibility studies or uh
community engagement projects as to how
can they move to have one of these
geothermal networks in their community.
And we often get the question is this
database only for the US or if we have a
system in Canada can we uh can can it be
there and the answer is yes. So uh while
the legup research project is funded by
Massachusetts clean energy center and
it's focused on the uh demonstration
projects in Massachusetts. This database
is really open nationally and to um
projects in other countries as well.
So what are the c different categories
that we are uh acquiring in this
database? Um information about the
buildings we talked about the building
retrofits in the previous session. Uh
about the system performance that was
the coefficient of performance that was
referred to. um about the emissions
reductions about the subsurface that's
where the borehole uh test um
information gets input about costs about
the energy usage of the buildings before
and after these geothermal networks have
been installed and about uh demographics
how many people are being uh benefited
by these systems
and uh these different categories can be
also um put into these three buckets of
the thermal resources what's happening
um in the bore holes, the distribution,
the main loop, and what's happening in
the buildings.
And now I'd like to close with um one of
the projects that heat is working on. As
as I mentioned, this is the extension to
the Frammingham project that um Eric
mentioned earlier. This would be the
extension to that project. Um
and this is the original loop. Right now
we are planning a borefield right here.
And uh the the idea is that this is the
very first extension loop of one of
these systems that is connecting to an
already installed and operating system.
So this extension loop can be the model
for how these systems can connect in
modularity and grow throughout the city.
So learnings about how to uh do those
connections and grow these systems will
come from uh this expansion project.
And with that I'll hand it over to our
next speaker. Yeah.
[Applause]