the MIT energy initiative presents
reversing the charge battery power from
electric vehicles to the grid could open
a fast lane to a net zero future written
by Lita
Zimmerman owners of electric vehicles
EVS are accustomed to plugging into
charging stations at home and at work
and filling up their batteries with
electricity from the power grid but
someday soon when these drivers plug in
their cars will also have the capacity
to reverse the flow and send electrons
back to the grid as the number of EVS
climbs the fleet's batteries could serve
as a coste effective large scale energy
source with potentially dramatic impacts
on the energy transition according to a
new paper published by an MIT team in
the journal energy advances at scale
vehicle to grid v2g can boost renewable
energy growth displacing the need for
stationary energy storage and decreasing
Reliance on firm always on generators
such as natural gas that are
traditionally used to balance wind and
solar intermittency says Jim Owens lead
author and a doctoral student in the MIT
Department of chemical engineering
additional authors include am genser a
principal research scientist at the MIT
energy initiative Mighty and Ian Miller
a research specialist for Mighty at the
time of the study the group's work is
the first comprehensive systems-based
analysis of future Power Systems drawing
on a novel mix of computational models
integrating such factors as carbon
emission goals variable renewable energy
VRE generation and cost of building
energy storage production and
transmission infrastructure we explored
not just how EVS could provide service
back to the grid thinking of these
vehicles almost like energy storage on
Wheels but also the value of v2g
applications to the entire Energy System
and if EVS could reduce the cost of
decarbonizing the power system says
genser the results were surprising I
personally didn't believe we'd have so
much potential
here displacing new
infrastructure as the United States and
other nations pursue stringent goals to
limit carbon emissions electrification
of transportation is taken off with a
rate of EV adoption rapidly accelerating
some projections show EV supplanting
internal combustion Vehicles over the
next 30 Years with the rise of
emission-free driving though there will
be increased demand for energy the
challenge is is ensuring both that
there's enough electricity to charge the
vehicles and that this electricity is
coming from renewable sources says
genser but solar and wind energy is
intermittent without adequate backup for
these sources such as stationary energy
storage facilities using lithium ion
batteries for instance or large scale
natural gas or hydrogen fueled power
plants achieving clean energy goals will
prove elusive more vexing cost for
building the necessary new energy
infrastructure runs to the hundreds of B
ions this is precisely where v2g can
play a critical and welcome role the
researchers reported in their case study
of a theoretical New England power
system meeting stract carbon constraints
for instance the team found that
participation from just 13.9% of the
Region's 8 million light duty passenger
EVS displaced 14.7 GW of stationary
energy storage this added up to $700
million in savings the anticipated cost
of building new storage capacity
their paper also described the role EV
batteries could play at times of peak
demand such as hot summer days v2g
technology has the ability to inject
electricity back into the system to
cover these episodes so we don't need to
install or invest in additional natural
gas turbin s Owens the way that EVs and
v2g can influence the future of our
Power Systems is one of the most
exciting and novel aspects of our
study modeling power
to investigate the impacts of v2g on
their hypothetical New England power
system the researchers integrated their
EV travel and v2g service models with
two of mighty's existing modeling tools
the sustainable energy system analysis
modeling environment Sesame to project
vehicle Fleet and electricity demand
growth and Gen X Which models the
investment and operation costs of
electricity generation storage and
transmission
systems they Incorporated such inputs as
different EV particip ation rates costs
of generation for conventional and
Renewable Power suppliers charging
infrastructure upgrades travel demand
for vehicles changes in electricity
demand and EV battery costs their
analysis found benefits from v2g
applications and Power Systems in terms
of displacing energy storage and firm
generation at all levels of carbon
emission restrictions including one with
no emissions caps at all however their
model suggests that v2g delivers the
greatest value to the power system when
carbon constraints are most aggressive
at 10 G of carbon dioxide per kilowatt
hour load total system savings from v2g
range from $183 million to
$1,326 million reflecting EV
participation rates between 5% and
80% our study has begun to uncover the
inherent value v2g has for a future
power system demonstrating that there is
a lot of money we can save that would
otherwise be spent on storage and firm
generation say Owens
harnessing
v2g for scientists seeking ways to
decarbonize the economy the vision of
millions of EVS parked in garages or in
office spaces and plugged into the grid
for 90% of their operating lives proves
an irresistible
provocation there is all this storage
sitting right there a huge available
capacity that will only grow and it is
wasted unless we take full advantage of
it says genser this is not a distant
Prospect startup companies are current
currently testing software that would
allow two-way communication between EVs
and grid operators or other entities
with the right algorithms EVS would
charge from and dispatch energy to the
grid according to profiles tailored to
each car owner's needs never depleting
the battery and endangering a commute we
don't assume all vehicles will be
available to send energy back to the
Grid at the same time at 600 p.m. for
instance when most commuters return home
in the early evening since genser he
believes that the vastly varied
schedules of EV drivers will make enough
battery power available to cover spikes
and electricity use over an average
24-hour period And there are other
potential sources of battery power down
the road such as electric school buses
that are employed only for a short stin
during the day and then sit idle the MIT
team acknowledges the challenges of v2g
consumer buyin while EV owners relish a
clean Green Drive they may not be as
enthusiastic handing over access to
their car's battery to a utility or an
aggregator working with power system
operators policies and incentives would
help since you're providing a service to
the grid much as solar panel users do
you could be paid for your participation
and paid at a premium when electricity
prices are very high says genser people
may not be willing to participate around
the clock but if we have blackout
scenarios like in Texas last year or hot
day congestion on transmission lines
maybe we can turn on these vehicles for
24 to 48 hours sending energy back to
the system adds Owens if if there's a
power outage and people wave a bunch of
money at you you might be willing to
talk basically I think this comes back
to all of us being in this together
right says genser as you contribute to
society by giving this service to the
grid you will get the full benefit of
reducing system costs and also help to
decarbonize the system faster and to a
greater
extent actionable
insights Owens who is building his
dissertation on v2g Research is now
investigating the potential impact of
heavyduty electric vehicles and
decarbonizing the power system the less
mile delivery trucks of companies like
Amazon and FedEx are likely to be the
earliest adopters of EVS Owen says they
are appealing because they have
regularly scheduled routes during the
day and go back to the depot at night
which makes them very useful for
providing electricity and balancing
services in the power system Owens is
committed to providing insights that are
actionable by System planners operators
and to a certain extent investors he
says his work might come into play in
determining what kind of charging
infrastructure should be built and where
our analysis is really timely because
the EV Market has not yet been developed
says genser this means we can share our
insights with vehicle manufacturers and
system operators potentially influencing
them to invest in v2g Technologies
avoiding the costs of building utility
scale storage and enabling the
transition to a cleaner future it's a
huge win within our
grasp the research search for the study
was funded by mighty's Future Energy
Systems Center