[Music]
morning everyone my name is ABI yadav uh
I'm the co-founder CEO of a company
called I customer uh I customer is a
decision intelligence company missone
grad
2013 um so I'm going to talk about a
problem I mean we all have heard about
generative Ai and lot of contents
getting creative but I look at this or
we some of us look at this very
differently we seeing in go to market
GTM is go to market so go to market and
marketing what is really the evolution
happening is that there was a big
machine on the creative side which is
generating content video images and a
whole bunch but now what you're actually
seeing is actually where compan is
really struggling is how to deliver that
message to the right person right place
the right time in a very individualized
way not a spray and prey way which is
kind of working um and this kind of
misalignment of thinking is actually
costing
companies um a two trillion like fit you
know which is basically primarily led by
like data fragmentation wrong identity
wrong matching wrong message wrong
timing one size fitall segments whole
bunch a thing while marketing keeps
thinking that the more campaign they
could churn they could engage more
people which is kind of creating the
false positive uh signal Loop effect so
um this is also the challenge because
you know nowadays the goto Market is not
just marketing it's kind of the whole
customer experience between sales
marketing customer success you know
personalization um so how we trying to
tackle this is really about taking
agentic AI approach which is basically
to manage your data chaos the whole
fragmentation and sort of you know
having these three pillar of our
platform called match decide and
activate which is basically creates this
what we call a decision optimization
Loop more under the hood the way it
works is we are a composable platform
for multi- agentic system uh pre-train
it sits where your data is so could be
an on-prem data it could be on any of
your data warehouse we see ourself as a
brain between your data warehouse and
all things about which send out you know
campaigns or act DEC Mark de like
activation you know basically with of
course like human in the loop but a lot
of like repeatable task more in an
augmented way and uh so so think of this
as a like a GTM assistant working for
the marketing business team which is
continuously monitoring the signal the
data and things like that basically like
helping um you know with the business
team we we see this as a you know uh
intersection of like human expertise
with agent Ai and customer data specific
use case uh because of this AI decision
engine um you could do customer life
cycle orchestration at scale I mean
we've all seen this you know people have
been doing segment LED thing I mean us
election is a classic example where how
segments do not work today and
everything we all are individual
everyone has his own perspective own
time so that moment is finally here like
oneon-one personalization which we're
enabling in production today same with
that targeting inside planning and
things very quick case study for a large
cpg retail brand we've been working with
um so it not just tells you looking at
your data what is really missing or why
it missed but also do the root cause
analysis and suggest you very
prescriptively which are the new
segments which are the new campaign or
what what you should be doing classic
result we already have are in large
corporate e-commerce company cpg Finance
you know uh including some asan clients
we've just started working with I'm here
today um to also like seek out for
Partnerships customers introduction you
know specifically to Thailand in my
previous like previous company I had
work with like Tha Thailand based
companies client so I'm really excited
about here this is my information and
I'm happy to you know talk to you more
you know post this talk as well so thank
you for having me guys appreciate it
[Music]