hello everyone and thank you so much for
your time today uh I'm a recent graduate
of my team mechanical engineering and
together with horor and Donald were the
three founders of eor and early stage
startup out of MIT Delta V and let me
share my
slides so um our goal our goal behind
ecor is to innovate energy storage to
tackle the biggest challenges faced by
the electrical grid Peak demand
management congestion upgrades to the
Aging infrastructure all of these issues
use can be helped by adding more storage
to the grid without it one of the
immediate consequences is rising
electricity costs now how bad do those
get here's an example of an industrial
utility rate in California which in just
the last few years has tripled that for
some of the Facility Owners we know to
move their business or even shut it down
while some storage is getting added to
the grid it needs to happen faster and
cheaper and that's exactly what eor does
we offer an endtoend energy storage
solution that generates scalable savings
for businesses it is installed on the
side of a facility behind its
electricity meter and serves as an
optimizing filter between the facility
and the grid it changes the shape of the
electricity usage from the point of view
of the utility which makes it cheaper
now from the point of view of the
customer nothing changes they continue
operating as they normally would while
our system runs in the background
generating savings and those are
scalable because distributed storage can
help the GD in a variet ways uh that can
be monetized so accordingly we're
stacking different revenue streams
within our software to maximize the
value of every battery deployed now
tying this back to integrating storage
faster and cheaper most battery
providers Focus either on front of the
meter utility scale deployments or in
tiny residential batteries we on the
other hand are enabling private
commercial industrial customers to
afford their own storage these customers
have a burning demand for battery
enabled savings yet they've been vastly
overlooked so much so that existing cni
BTM offerings only feature manual highly
limited controls meaning the customer
has to somehow plan battery behavior on
their own uh then try to implement the
simplest version of it and keep updating
updating it at on their own as well so
our software allows us to operate the
battery autonomously and intelligently
achieving much higher optimal value
extraction now thanks to that efficiency
we're able to offer rois as high as 35%
before any incentives which finally
allows us to provide Affordable Storage
to businesses and close the gap in the
market we're also working to tackle one
of the biggest bottlenecks in the
industry deployment by focusing on
simpler BTM installations and optimizing
every step of the way we're streamlining
storage integration currently we have
six Fain customers and three of them are
already moving through our installation
pipeline um and to showcase our value
proposition for this customer in
California our system with a footprint
of of just 30 square ft and the total
space requirement of 160 Square ft is
projected to produce over 62,000 in
effortless pure savings every year the
resulting payback is just three years
without any incentives which is only the
fifth of the cist of lifespan so we're
quite excited to launch it in the coming
months and last but not least our ask uh
another customer of ours is part of an
international manufacturer called
Alberts our project with them opened up
a on to many approach where a successful
outcome in one company location can lead
to deployments in the others too so we
would love to connect to more similar
Enterprises with multiple energy
intensive facilities uh please feel free
to submit a contact form by scanning the
QR code on the slide and thank you so
much for your attention happy to answer
any
questions great Valeria thank you so
much so again please um POS your
questions to the Q&A Tab and indicate
which start of it's for but um I'll get
started first um so your targeting and
mentioning energy intensive
manufacturing facilities but do you see
opportunities for other sectors as well
yes absolutely uh We've started with
energy intensive manufacturing because
um that's where the cost savings and Roi
are most immediate but our approach is
designed to scale as we develop our
software further and improve our unit
economics our customer base can be can
really expand and for example in the
near term Beyond industrial we see
opportunities in Comm commercial real
estate and large scale retail and longer
term we could install in multif family
residential and even individual
homeowners fantastic um and you
mentioned uh the software enables the
stacking of multiple revenue streams um
could you speak to that a little more
definitely so um as I mentioned
distributed storage typically can be
useful for a range of applications
across uh transmission distribution and
behind the meter parts of the grid so on
the transmission side that includes
variety of services like energy
Arbitrage and frequency regulation in
distribution it can be all of the
transmission plus deferral meaning
helping substations uh level out the
load and behind the meter is most
interesting to us because it can provide
both transmission and distribution level
services but also individual meter
Services where we actually unlock the
most value so say Peak shaving time of
use shifting automated demand response
backup or solar self-conception uh happy
to explain those further as needed
fantastic thank you again area thank you