why is so difficult to build a computer
vision system well an image is made of
pixels when we look at a picture what we
see are shapes and objects that we
immediately recognize however what a
machine gets is a collection of numbers
where each pixel is represented just by
a single number and we want to build a
system that will tell us whether there
is a car or not in that image so the
first thing that we need to do is to
collect the training data and we will
need some images that contains examples
of cars so that the machine can learn
all the different ways in which a car
car might look like and then we also
need examples of images without cars
once we have built this data set the
final thing that we need is the learning
model neural networks are the way in
which we build those systems they are
composed of very simple units that are
interconnected with adjustable weights
and we will use all those images to set
up the strength of the connections
between the units so that the neural
network learns to solve the test that we
care about for more MIT moments from MIT
open learning like subscribe or follow