all right welcome back to 61200 today we
are talking about number Theory uh and
number is I guess an old word here for
integers in modern terminology um you
know this Set uh Blackboard bold Z which
is all positive and negative integers
although mostly we think about natural
numbers the non- negative integers uh
number theory is a a big topic we're
going to spend three lectures on it
today and to next week um and it's a
really important branch of sub Branch I
guess or related branch of discrete
mathematics uh in particular because
it's found a lot of applications in
modern days in cryptography and error
correction every when you use your cell
phone probably several different things
uh in your in that software is using
number Theory at some level to do crypto
to access your bank to do uh error
correction to talk over radio waves all
sorts of fun things uh number three is
also extremely old it's probably the
oldest branch of mathematics though you
know past 4,000 years it's a little hard
to tell exactly what people were doing
uh but in particular the Babylonians uh
3,800 years ago were uh doing number
Theory uh Pythagoras uh 25 200 years ago
was doing number Theory um in the it had
a a lot of exciting activity in the
middle of last century uh Hardy is one
of the famous uh number theories number
theorists of sort of near our time um he
wrote uh number theory is great because
it's one science whose very remoteness
very remoteness from human activities
should keep it gentle and clean he was a
pacifist and he wanted to do math that
was completely useless from the
perspective of warfare sadly uh that's
not the case for number Theory anymore
but it used to be um
so uh but the things we'll be doing here
are pretty fundamental uh today we're
going to talk about divisibility and
something called gcd which you may have
heard of before it's a pretty basic
notion both of these are but we're going
to Define everything carefully and prove
uh all sorts of cool properties about
divisibility and use it to solve at
least one fun
problem so uh the notation for
divisibility is a divides
B uh we use a vertical bar we use a
vertical Bar for a few other things like
absolute value and set notation so try
not to be too confused uh this will only
be for uh a couple weeks um divisibility
means uh a evenly divides b or B is
evenly divisible by a okay so for
example
uh let's say uh two divides 4 as an
uh but in general what we would like is
a a def a formal definition of
this um so we'll say a divides B if
there exists some integer
multiple
K such that uh B is that multiple of a
so b equal K * a very important that
this is an integer otherwise over reals
this is always the case pretty
much um and we Define divisibility in
terms of multiplication instead of
division I mean you could divide both
sides by uh a here and so for example
this is saying B divided by a is an
integer but that's not such a great
definition because it doesn't work well
when you try to divide by zero this
definition works even when B is when a
is zero and uh otherwi if you do
division it doesn't so that's why we
Define divisibility this way so more
interesting examples are 2 ID n uh means
what we have been saying n is
even whenever we say n is even what we
really mean is two divides n there's
some integer multiple of two that equals
n okay uh some other weirder
cases every natural
number uh n divides n
it's maybe not so intuitive what
divisibility means for negative numbers
but here are some examples we allow this
integer multiple K to be negative so in
particular K can be minus1 and minus1 *
negative n is n okay also n divides n
but that's a little less exciting uh
another fun fact is that every number
divides
zero this is also maybe not the most
intuitive but it comes from the
definition K in particular can be zero
and if you take 0 * n you get zero so
everything divides zero uh number also
divides its negative things like that um
a consequence of these two things
together is that zero is even if you
were ever worried about whether zero was
an exception to evenness in the
alternation of of these numbers yes uh
this is even this is even this is even
because uh in particular 2 divides 0
everything divides Z but in particular
two divid Z that's the meaning of
even okay great uh
let's State some theorems about
divisibility I'm going to call these
divisibility facts we're going to use
them several times
today uh let's say we have
two numbers divisible by the same thing
uh we call this uh D is a
common
divisor of A and B so D divides A and D
divides B we call it a common
divisor uh
then I claim uh for example D divides a
plus b their
sum why this is very easy to prove if
you just work through the definition so
let's say um a = j * D and Bal K * D for
some integers J and K they might be the
same they might be different uh then a
plus b well it's it's just the sum of
these two things right it's j + K *
D not very hard uh more generally uh D
divides
uh sa a + TB for any integers s and
t uh this is just a a simple extension
of this property um I guess you can
write uh this thing equals uh SJ + TK *
D um and it turns out this
structure is interesting it's what we
call an integer linear
combination this is a concept we will
also be using throughout
today so much so that uh I'm going to
give an acronym I don't usually like
acronyms but this is so long that it's
going to save me a ton of work to write
ilc for integer linear combination uh if
you know linear algebra this is just
linear combination but where the
coefficients need to be integers so it's
exactly this notion so an integer linear
combination of A and B uh is some number
s * a plus T * B uh for
any uh s and t that are integers okay so
if I give you two numbers A and B we'll
only be doing integer linear
combinations today of two
numbers uh then this is what they always
look like and given two numbers there's
some numbers you can construct VI
integer linear combinations and some you
can't uh actually fun fact divis
is like integer linear combinations of
one number this is saying B is an
integer linear combination of just a uh
but we that's so special we call it
divisibility U two numbers is where
integer linear combinations really get
interesting all right so to motivate
these Concepts more turns out these are
key Concepts to solving a famous puzzle
uh it's at least 80 90 years old called
the water uh water pouring puzzle but it
became particularly famous uh through
Die Hard three Die Hard with a Vengeance
so we're going to watch a little clip uh
and if you uh if this clip is not
included in this video you can go uh
stream or uh purchase Die Hard with a
Vengeance and start at the one hour mark
and you will see an exchange like the
following so we have uh of course John
mlan here uh who's uh trying to save
Manhattan uh along with his friend Zeus
who's like an electrician who just
happens to get uh brought into this
whole chaos basically the bad guys are
trying to distract the good guys by
solving forcing them to solve puzzles so
here we go all right so we're going to
focus on the problem at hand uh which uh
we can formalize as
follows uh so we have two
jugs uh we'll say of
capacity A and B and we'll assume
they're integers and in the
example uh that saves Manhattan we have
a equals 5 and b equals 3 and we'd like
to represent some number uh in this case
four by a sequence of pouring
operations uh so um how could we
represent this water porn in problem
using techniques that we have from
previous
lectures any
ideas I heard
something yeah State machines good so
we'll use a state machine um and so
we'll have a
state x and y means that there's
currently X gallons in the first jug and
Y gallons in the second jck
uh or let's say the uh
amounts in uh
each
joke okay so uh we
start at the state z z let's say the
drug started empty uh we're given an
infinite water supply because they're at
a fountain
conveniently um
and let's see we want to finish at a
state that has four in one of the two
values and as John mlan said uh it has
to be in the bigger one in this case
because four is bigger than
three so we'd like
to uh goal is to get to uh four comma
something and the tricky part is to
write down the transitions here so let's
write down some of the
transitions
transitions so given X and
Y uh what are the some of the things I
could
do any
suggestions I have some partially filled
jars these are two jars of uh five and
three pumpkins capacity respectively uh
maybe I'm at some position here what
could I do to these trugs yeah the back
fill one to the top I I go to the
Fountain I pour it up until it's
completely fill or or this one I could
go to the fill Point other suggestions
yeah empty I could empty one of the jars
hopefully I won't need that so in the
transitions this is this corresponds to
going to uh I guess a comma y if I fill
the first one um or I could go to x
comma B if I fill the second one um I
could empty by going to uh 0 comma y if
I empty the first one or I could go to x
comma 0 so these are all sorry this is
all transitions from
XY uh anything else
yeah I can pour the contents of one jug
into the other cool yeah so here for
example I filled up a three I poured in
three uh I could fill this one up again
and pour it in again and at some point
uh I'll run out of capacity in this jug
and that's an event that I can detect
when I reach level Che okay so to write
that down more carefully given
XY we can transition to one of two cases
either we get to completely empty the
left jug into the right jug so this
would be uh x + y but that's only
possible
if it fits in the second jug If X Plus Y
is less than or equal to B otherwise to
do arithmetic this too hard uh we move
over B minus y or something um so we
have x minus B minus y comma B
otherwise okay if we end up filling up
the second one then this is how much uh
of the original X that I started with
remains
okay uh and you can do the there's one
more rule which is if I pour from right
to left those are the available uh State
transitions in this puzzle uh and now
maybe I've talked about it long enough
you have some intuition on how to solve
this start
empty any suggestions on how to
construct the number
four yeah
let fill up the five gallon
jug
okay okay we're going to transfer the
three gallon jug until the three gallon
jug is exactly empty which if you're
using water it would be
level okay empty the three gallon
jug okay move the two over this now
feels like towers of anoi
okay fill the five
and then transfer like
this from five to did I get the right
number there we go water's water's
particularly unsettled today all right
so we've got uh five on the right if I
can count and we fill over here until
this one is filled and now we've got the
number four
yay uh that's how we solve that's how we
save Manhattan with uh with this water
pouring problem but uh while the bad
guys are off uh stealing
money from the bank um but sometimes
this puzzle isn't solvable so let's take
another
[Applause]
example uh let's say we want uh AAL 6
bals 4 and we want the number
three is this possible I already gave
away that this is impossible why is it
impossible any
feelings hint it has something to do
with this
stuff
yeah okay you said there are no integer
linear combinations where of six and
four that make three that is true but uh
this problem isn't directly about
integer linear combinations is it I
don't
know
yeah there's no way to get an odd number
from these two
gallons that's the simp both of you are
correct uh the simpler reason in this
case
uh is it's impossible to get an odd
amount um I guess the proof of both of
these things is you look at all the
possible Transitions and uh You observe
that if you start with A and B being
even you can never construct an odd
number by adding and subtracting all
we're doing here taking numbers that
we've constructed adding them and or
subtracting them with a and b or each
other and so if you start with even
numbers you add and subtract them you
always stay within the even numbers but
also as you're saying if you start with
an integer linear combination of A and B
all you can get are integer linear
combinations of A and B so here is uh a
key Lemma about this puzzle and why that
is impossible more
generally is uh all reachable
amounts in this puzzle are integer
linear
combinations of A and
B let's prove
this any suggestions on how to prove a
property like
this you remember all the way back to
State machines hopefully you've been
studying for the test State machines are
on the test this lecture is not it will
be on quiz
two invariance yeah in particular
uh this this is a statement about
invariance this is saying uh for all
reachable uh X comma
y um X and Y are integer linear
combinations of A and B so this is an
invariant property this is a state
predicate we want to prove that it's
invariant that is true for all reachable
states starting from 0 0 um and we
usually do that using the invariant
principle which has requires two steps
one is base case we need to check that
this predicate holds
initially uh and the initial state for
us is 0 comma 0 and we observe that zero
is indeed a linear combination of A and
B namely 0 * a uh plus 0 * B great base
case is true and so now we just need the
inductive step or the I guess the
preserved the fact that this predicate
is
preserved uh so suppose that we're at
some State X and Y where the predicate
is true uh so xal sa a + TB and y = s
prime a + T Prime B
um and then we just look at all of the
available
Transitions and we show that every
number that you can make uh is indeed an
integer linear combination of uh A and B
so let's do one example we can construct
X + Y X + Y uh we can rewrite as um s +
S Prime * a and t + T Prime * B so
that's uh if this transition happens to
be possible it may not be possible
because there's this if condition but if
we show that every thing every number we
could possibly build has this property
then of course all the ones that we can
actually reach also have this property
uh so X+ Y is indeed an integer linear
combination of a uh A and
B um Etc and of proof okay I don't want
to prove it for for every single
transition here uh just because there's
a bunch of them but for example a is
indeed an integer linear combination of
A and B it's 1 * a plus 0 * B this one
looks mess here it's actually just X+ y
minus B so it's almost the same you just
add a minus one here but the general
property we're using here is that all of
the constructible numbers here are
integer linear combinations of X Y A and
B Okay I lied we're using integer linear
combinations of four things but all of
the X and y's are also integer linear
combinations of a and B so what we're
really taking is integer linear
combinations of integer linear
combinations of A and B and it turns out
that if you take two integer linear
combinations of A and B like X and Y and
you add them together or in general take
an integer linear combination of them
you still get an integer linear
combination of A and B as you can see
from this proof it's actually pretty
much the same proof we were doing over
here uh this was integer linear
combinations of one number D and
divisibility was preserved even when you
took inte linear combinations so same
idea and for any puzzle where you have
that property you can only construct
numbers that are integer linear
combinations of A and B now for this
puzzle you can actually construct all of
them that fit in the
jars uh
so I'll just mention this as a claim and
if we have time at the end we'll come
back to
it uh we
can we can
obtain uh a value
X um if and only
if
uh let's say x is an integer linear
combination of A and
B
and
uh Z is less than equal to X is less
than equal to Max
of okay so we might try to um prove that
later
uh so now the central question is how do
we know whether one number is an integer
linear combination of two other numbers
and when it is can we actually construct
the values s and t so that sa a plus TB
equals x because that's what we needed
to solve this puzzle was some way to uh
we were only given the capacities of the
jars and the target value and now we
want to represent oh let's check that
this is actually possible for this
example
uh so if we um sorry not this example
the one that's actually solvable so for
this solvable puzzle uh 4 equals 2 * 5
that's 10 minus 2 * 3 that's
six right 10 - 6 is four so that's
intuitively why this puzzle is solvable
although that's not a proof I mean we
just saw that it wasn't limited by this
same issue uh so for example if we
started with six and
four We Know by this Lemma because two
divides four and two divides six two
will divide any integer linear
combination and therefore any
reachable uh value in this puzzle and
two does not divide three three is odd
not even and so we will never be able to
reach three because all the reachable
states are even that's a corollary now
of this
Lemma okay um
okay but how when in the good case in
the bad case it's easy to see I guess uh
how how do we know whether we're in a
good case or a bad case how do we know
whether X is a integer linear
combination of A and B given X and A and
B that is kind of the purpose of the
well some motivation for the rest of
this lecture we can use it for all sorts
of
things all right and I claim that this
is going to be true um if and only
if uh
this property is
true so now I'm going to restate this in
terms of divisibility this is this
equivalence is not obvious we'll prove
it by the end of today um so I claim
what what we really want to shows that
every common divisor of A and B remember
this is our definition of d is a common
divisor
uh common divisor of A and B divides a
and it divides B um then it should also
divide X so in the example uh we saw
that two was a common divisor of four
and six and so two better divide
anything that we make uh what are the
common divisors of five and
three three doesn't work five doesn't
work two doesn't work four doesn't work
I guess one is a common divisor one
divides
everything uh
so yeah that's also this is true in our
in our good case
uh and this we can rewrite in yet
another way which motivates our next
topic uh the gcd of A and B divides X
okay so I claim in particular this is
going to be a way to tell whether X is
an integer linear combination of A and B
you compute something called the gcd of
A and B and you see whether it divides X
so let's talk about gcd
gcd is another acronym it stands for uh
greatest common
divisor I assume it comes
from uh Britain in particular where they
use great to to indicate large uh so we
might call call this the largest common
divisor uh or the biggest common divisor
all synonyms for the same thing
um so this is the I'm going to give two
equivalent definitions of
gcd to me the more intuitive one is this
but it's a little bit uglier because it
has a special case so what I'd like to
say is the gcd of A and B is the largest
integer D such that D divides A and D
divides B again this is common common
divisor D is a common divisor of A and B
I want it to be the largest common
diviser that would be gcd uh but there's
one annoying special case which really
won't matter for the rest of lecture but
to be technically correct we should say
what happens when you compute the gcd of
Z and zero because remember every
integer D divides zero everything
divides zero so what's the largest
diviser of zero and zero I mean Infinity
I don't know it's like there is no such
integer that's the largest so there is
no largest integer uh so in this case it
turns out the right thing is to Define
gcd of 0 comma 0 to be zero that will be
a little counterintuitive maybe uh until
you see the next
definition Okay so
here's another
definition gcd is uh the only non-
negative common
divisor of A and
B uh divisible by all common divisors of
A and B
okay so uh another way to think about
the large the greatest common divisor is
it's greatest in terms of the
divisibility relation um the one that is
uh the most divisible by by other common
divisors so it turns out there's going
to be one common divisor that's both
non- negative and is divisible by all
common divisor of A and B uh so in these
examples uh for four and six gcd
of of 6 and four is going to be
two uh because the only let's see the
the common divisors if we think what are
all the common
divisors between four and
six uh maybe obvious there there's two
there's minus two uh there's one and
minus one zero divides nothing except
itself and all you can check all the
numbers between like6 and six uh those
are the possible divisors um and uh
these are the only ones that divide both
A and B and the
largest uh non- negative one here is two
and also it has the property that all of
these other common divisors divide
two okay so uh whichever way you want to
think about it you can use either
definition I'm not going to prove that
these definitions are equivalent we're
just going to take it as an axiom but
you can prove it uh this maybe an
exercise
uh so we but when we're proving things
about gcd we can use either of these
definitions whichever is more
convenient so let's um do one more
interesting
example which
is
gcd of I think I want to do zero first Z
comma a so suppose I want to compute gcd
of two numbers maybe I should put a b
there uh and one of them is
zero any
guesses what the gcd of zero and B
should be remember everything divides
zero B is a good guess almost right what
if B was -7
should be absolute value of B so uh if
we want to handle positive and negative
things this turns out to be the right
answer uh here is a mini
proof uh there are two things we want to
check one is that absolute value of B is
a common divisor of zero and B uh so
well the absolute value of B this gets
notationally pretty gross divides zero
that's true because everything divides
zero uh and absolute value of B divides
B namely when we let K be uh1 or one
depending on whether B was positive or
negative or
zero um cool so uh good it is a common
divisor and now I want to claim that
it's the greatest common divisor
according to the second definition so
let's suppose that we had some number D
which divides zero and which divides
uh
B so d divid z and d divides B then uh I
claim in particular D also
divides uh the absolute value of
B Because if you divide a number you
also divide its negation just by
negating the value K that you're
multiplying by right if I take K * D and
I get b i then I take negative K * D and
I get absolute value of B if B happened
to be negative okay so that means if
you're a common diviser of zero and B
then you're also a common diviser of
this thing and that was our defin second
definition of gcd uh so great uh this
means we're
greatest okay uh now the the question
arises how do we compute gcd of A and B
because I claimed uh
over here that what we need to check is
whether gcd of ab divides X so given a
and b we need to be able to compute this
thing
how do we find the greatest common
divisor turns out there's a great
algorithm to do it and the base case of
that algorithm is this if we can get one
of the numbers down to zero then that we
found the
gcd okay so our goal now is given some
big numbers to make them smaller
somehow and the big idea here to make a
gcd algorithm is
subtraction how do we make numbers
smaller with arithmetic subtraction or
division seem like good ideas we're
going to use both starting with
subtraction
so I
claim gcd of ab equals gcd of a minus B
comma B comma
B uh for all integers
a so if a and b are big numbers this is
pretty cool this is saying we can
subtract one of the numbers from the
other and we get the same gcd somehow
okay we'll prove this in a
second now actually going leave a little
bit of space let's do
proof okay so um then we're going to
turn this into an algorithm but let's
first see why this is the case so
um we this is a statement about GC CD
gcd is this complicated definition uh
it's a little easier to think about all
common divisors you think about the
common divisors of A and B those are all
the numbers D where D divides A and D
divides B and you think of the common
divisors of a minus B and B I claim
these sets are the same so the set of
common
divisors of a and
b equals the set of common
divisors of a minus B and
B okay this is a kind of proof we
actually haven't seen in this class yet
uh this is the brace not a minus sign uh
when you want to prove two sets are
equal a very common template for such a
proof is to show that every element of
this set is also an element of this set
that if you recall back to our set
definitions in lecture one is that this
set is contained in this set and also to
prove that every element of the second
set is an element of the first set
that's saying the second set is a subset
of the first set so uh we're going to do
a proof in two parts one part one is to
show containment that the first set is
contained in the second set uh part two
over
here is to show containment in the other
direction this set is a suet of this set
okay if I can prove that these sets are
equal then in particular the maximum
element of these sets if it exists is
also going to be equal right if you have
two identical sets you take the max
you're going to get the same thing now
there's this one I'm using the first
definition here of course there's this
one case when the two numbers are zero
then there is no maximum because all
integers actually will be common
divisors of zero and zero but in that
case again if the sets are equal that
means that A and B or these numbers must
be zero and then of course these numbers
are also all zero and this this
statement is trivially true when
everything's zero okay it's just saying
gcd of 0 comma 0 equals gcd of 0 comma 0
that one I'm fine with but as long as
we're not in the z z case these sets
will be finite and if they're equal then
their maximums will be the same so this
is all I need to show let's do it in two
parts so first we suppose that we have a
common diviser of A and B so that means
D divides A and D divides B for some
number number
B um well I claim that also D divides a
minus B because a minus B is an integer
linear combination of A and B and we had
over here in our divisibility fact if D
divides A and D divides B then D divides
every integer linear combination of A
and B so we're plugging in s equal 1
tals minus one here and we get the D
divides a minus
B great so uh we have d divides A and D
divid A minus B so in other words uh we
have D divid A and D divides a minus B
and that sorry wrong one I want to D
divides
B and this is the meaning of a common
divisor of a minus B and B so we we
assumed that D was a common divisor of
this we proved that D was a common
divisor of these two numbers therefore
we have containment every element in
this set is contained in this set now
let's prove the reverse and that will
imply that these sets are equal so now
suppose that D divides a minus B and D
divides
B then I want to show that D divides
a
why any
suggestions can I use integer linear
combinations yeah
T equals z I agree if if I put T equals
0 and S equals 1 then integer this is an
integer linear combination of A and B
but in this case I don't know that D
divides a that's actually what I want to
prove so I can't use integer linear
combinations of A and B but you do Aus I
can take an integer linear combination
of a minus B and B if I do 1 * this uh
Plus 1 * this a - b * 1 + 1 * B is
a uh so in other words because this
equals the sum a minus B plus
b and because I know that D is a common
divisor of a minus B and B I know that D
also divides any interger linear
combination of those two numbers and in
particular
a cool so so both of these are using the
uh divisibility facts that if you have a
common divisor you also divide all
integer linear combinations of those two
numbers uh so in particular this means
we have D divides A and D divides B I'm
just taking this thing that we proved
and this thing that we
assumed and this says we have a common
if we had saying if we had a common
divisor of a minus B and B we also have
a common divisor of A and B so that says
every element in this second set is an
element of the first set and because we
have containment in both directions in
fact these two sets must be exactly the
same set so if you ever have to prove
the two sets are equal I recommend a
common template is to do it in two
halves like
this
okay great uh so I claim we can get an
algorithm out of
this out of this subtraction idea and
gcd of 0 comma B
so let's just do an example of that I
won't write a careful algorithm because
we're going to do
better let's say we want to do uh gcd of
9 comma
6 okay uh oh and maybe I want to write
another fact
here um does it
matter yeah I do uh so gcd of a comma B
is also equal to uh gcd of B comma a by
symmetry of this definition A and B
could be swapped and you get exactly the
same things we're talking about and if I
apply this subtraction Lemma uh with the
elements swapped what I get is uh gcd of
the first argument which is B minus the
second argument which is a comma the
second argument which is a
so um all these things are equal just
from the same subtraction LMA and using
the Symmetry uh but what this is saying
is either I can subtract the second
argument from the first and get a minus
b or uh I I can also rewrite this as gcd
of a comma B minus a alternatively I
could leave the first argument alone and
subtract it from the second argument so
I'm free to subtract whichever way I
want and I find it much easier to think
about non- negative numbers so I'm
always going to subtract the smaller
number from the bigger number I can do
it either way so let's do it
for uh 9 comma
6 so I'm going to subtract six from 9
and I get this is equal to so this would
be uh a minus B this one minus this one
uh is three 9 - 6 is three second
argument stays the same okay I still
don't know the answer so I'm going to
keep subtracting in this case I'll take
the smaller number subtract it from the
larger number so this is uh B minus a I
guess replacing B with B minus a I get
gcd
of sorry uh I wanted yeah 3 comma
3 subtract three from six I get three
okay this that looks pretty easy I'm
guessing gcd of three and three is three
uh but if we go all the way uh we can
subtract one of them from the other I
guess I want to do B minus a again and
we get 3 comma 0 and this we actually
analyzed over here uh we said gcd oh I
got it backwards but of zero comma
something is the absolute value of
something so absolute value of three is
three and so gcd of three comma 0 is
three okay great uh another
example gcd of 1 comma
100 okay well I take the smaller one
subtract it from the larger one I get
gcd of 1 comma
99 H okay now I subtract one from the
larger number I get gcd of 1 comma
98 and so on I won't bore you with the
details in the end the answer is one but
uh this is a very slow way to arrive at
the answer of one um I have to do a 100
steps to figure out the gcd of 1 comma
100 so the number of steps you get in
this algorithm which I haven't precis
defined is going to be uh roughly at
least in the worst case um the sum of a
and b or the maximum of A and B it
doesn't matter up to constant factors uh
and this is what we would call a slow
algorithm for in number
Theory because generally we want to
think about numbers that are huge you
know uh 100 bits long if you have a 100
bit long number that is as large as two
to the 100
and that's a very large number uh
it's big roughly the number of particles
in the known universe I think that's
about to the 128 or something so we
don't want to spend that much time uh to
compute this in fact we can do a lot
better using
a better technique which is division so
we've seen here uh the idea that we can
subtract one number from the other but
if we subtract and then subtract and
then we subtract and we subtract that
sounds a lot like division right this is
like the bad way to do division is to
repeatedly subtract one number from the
other and that's exactly what happens in
the 100 comma one case we have to
subtract one from 100 subtract it from
99 keep subtracting one until the left
hand side uh becomes larger than the
right hand side and then we can stop in
fact they become equal because one
divides 100 uh but in general we want to
keep subtracting on until we go beyond
or we would go beyond what we can afford
and that's exactly division so let me
give
you a very precise version of
division with something called the
division theorem this is one of the core
theorems
in number Theory we won't prove it here
it's kind of TS um for every integer n
and for every positive integer D so I'm
going to write z+ to mean uh D is
greater than
zero
uh there is a
unique
um and usually we would write this as
exists exclamation mark there is a
unique so you know this means there is
exclamation mark it's really exists but
there's only one of them uh there exists
a unique uh pair of
integers uh q and
R uh I don't want the parentheses
actually uh I want to say those are both
integers um such
that and n = q * D +
R and R is between zero and strictly
less than
D okay you actually have seen this in
other terms probably before uh this Q is
what we would call the
quotient and this R is what we call the
remainder I'm sure you've heard those
terms before this is like a very precise
way to say what division gives us in all
cases
given uh a numerator and a
denominator that's why they're called n
and D here um and as long as D is uh not
zero we're going to furthermore assume
that it's positive so it's easier to
think about um then there's a unique
quotient and remainder you get from
dividing A over
B right Q is how many whole copies of D
you can fit inside n and R is whatever
is left over so that's roughly a proof
that this is true um and it if you think
about what the remainder should be it
could be zero in the zero case that's
when we have divisibility right if D
divides n if n equals Q * D that's
exactly divisibility if there's no R
that's when R equals z that's what we
get uh but in general we know R should
also be less than D because if if there
was D left over we would just increase Q
one that would be a whole copy of D so
the remainder is always going to be
between zero and strictly less than
D okay uh I guess the the interesting
part here is that there's only one sorry
I should have put an i in unique uh
there's only one way to do this um that
with these conditions there's only one
uh quotient and
remainder okay uh I also want to give
you some definitions some notation
which is uh for the quotient we write
the numerator div D div for division uh
and for the remainder we write n remd
REM for
remainder uh this is also sometimes
called n mod D so if you ever see that
we probably won't use it in this form
we're going to use mod to mean a
slightly related slightly different
notion um also the textbook uh they
write REM as a as a two argument
function but same
idea okay so uh we're going to use
division theorem a lot from now on and
as a way to uh reduce our numbers again
in a more powerful way than subtraction
so we would like to do subtraction
repeatedly and what will we be left with
we'll be left with the remainder if you
keep subtracting until you can't
subtract anymore that's remainder
okay so let's do
[Applause]
that probably still need this
divisibility facts I'll leave it
there
okay so this is gcd
division
theorem
um if let's suppose a is less than or
equal to B is less than or equal to
one that what I want no way around that
seems weird be weird to be at most one I
want things to be non- negative so I'm
going to assume a is the bigger one of A
and B and I want to compute gcd of a
comma
B and I'm going to assume we haven't
gotten down to zero in particular
because I can't divide by zero uh but
also because when we get to zero we're
done if one of the numbers is zero we're
happy so let's assume they're both at
least one and let's assume by symmetry
that a the one on the left is bigger or
equal uh then I claim gcd of a is gcd of
a remainder B comma
B okay uh so before we had a minus B and
now we have a remainder B seems like a
small difference and indeed the proof is
basically the same
um I'm going to do a proof sketch which
is to say well gcd of a comma B is equal
to gcd of a minus B comma B uh and if we
apply by the subtraction theorem uh
which we just did over over there um and
if we apply the subtraction theorem
again we can subtract the right argument
from the left one again A minus 2 B
comma B and so on eventually we get to
to gcd of a minus um a div B *
B right a div B is how many whole copies
of B I can fit into a and so if I take
that number multiply it by B that's how
much uh I can subtract away before a
would go negative if I subtracted one
more time and what I'll be left with is
exactly the remainder a minus uh a remb
times uh oh no times comma B If I
subtract off that many copies of B I
will be left with uh a remainder B sorry
no a
minus okay that's
uh that's what we're writing here in
fact so we wrote uh let me rewrite this
um we have n or maybe I'll write it as
uh Want A or
B I'll stick with that what this over
here is saying is uh n div D * D plus n
RM D equals to n okay I'm just rewriting
this formula using the notations for Q
and R and if I rearrange this I get that
n minus n divd
* D equals
ND okay and that's exactly what I'm
using here the remainder is what you get
what's left over if you take uh the
numerator and subtract off uh the div
many copies of the denominator so I use
dot dot dot here you can't really use
dot dot dot in a proof technically this
is a proof by induction but I think
hopefully you're familiar enough with
induction that you could turn this into
a formal proof it's not hard
okay so we can
divide and uh this will make this gcd
algorithm much faster because now if I
want to uh say to compute gcd of 1 comma
100 this is the same thing as gcd of 100
comma
1 and what that says is I can divide 100
by
one and see what the remainder is well
one divides 100 so the remainder is zero
so I instantly get that this is gcd of 0
comma 1
boom uh I'm done this gcd of Zer comma
anything is the
anything so in like one step now one
division instead of having to do a bunch
of subtractions I compute the
gcd great let's write this down as an
algorithm
this is called ukis algorithm or the
ukian
algorithm it's called UK's algorithm
because uclid was not the first to
discover it of course uh but he was
still pretty early uh around 300C C uh
but I'll mention an earlier version in
in a moment uh so what this does is it
computes gcd of
ab uh
for a greater than or equal to B greater
than or equal to zero okay I'm going to
assume everything's not negative if it's
negative just negate it I'm going to
assume the left argument is is bigger
than the right one or equal uh if it's
the other way around swap A and B okay
so this is enough for computing gcd of
any two
integers um and I'm going to write this
of course as a state
machine so in general I'm going to have
a pair of integers A and B where a is
greater than equal to B uh greater equal
to
zero uh so I guess I should say the
states are X comma y uh
where X is greater equal to Y is greater
than equal to zero and then the
transitions go from X comma y to X REM
y Oh wrong
order y comma X Ram
y okay almost the same as this theorem
except I'm going to rewrite this as gcd
of B comma a rem B just flip the
arguments because I would like the left
argument to always be greater than or
equal to I would like the left argument
to be always greater than or equal to
the right argument um and if I do them
in this order if x was greater than
equal to Y I do this division this
division will of course be less than y
and so the left one will be bigger than
the right one actually
strictly in that case
okay uh so that's basically just
following this rule
repeatedly and those are my
transitions uh now this only
works uh when Y is bigger than
zero if Y is
zero uh at um X comma 0 we
return
X as the
gcd that's the final state or there
these these are various final States any
X comma 0 is going to be a final State
there's no transition out of there
because we're not allowed to divide by
zero because I wrote this for all y
greater than zero rule but at that in
that situation we know the gcd of 0
comma b or B comma 0 is the absolute
value of B because everything here is
non- negative uh the answer is X at that
point so why does this
work well because we just proved an
invariant that uh as this machine
runs um I want to say p of
XY is the state predicate which is uh
the
gcd of X comma y equals the gcd of a
comma
B right whatever we designed the change
in arguments here we started with a
comma B so this is true initially in our
initial State a comma B of course gcd of
a comma b equals gcd of a comma B and
then every time we do a transition and
we do this Division and take the
remainder we still have we know that the
gcds are equal by this
theorem right that's exactly what this
tells us and so this is saying this
theorem tells us that this state
predicate is preserved and because it
holds initially that means it's
invariant okay uh true initially
uh and it's
preserved by this theorem and so by the
invariant principle we know that this
will remain true for any reachable state
XY we'll have gcd of XY equal gcd of ab
and
furthermore uh when we get to a final
state so this is a final
State uh we know that this answer is
correct because gcd of X comma 0 equals
X for non- Negative X so this was this
is partial
correctness if we get to a final
State uh
gcd of X comma 0 equals
X for X greater than equal to Z by this
theorem that we
proved Okay so if this machine
terminates we're
done and I claim this machine does
terminate so let's prove
termination in a couple of
ways so how do we prove termination of
State machines we
Define uh some value some function of
States that's an integer a non- negative
integer and we show that it strictly
decreases that's our main tool for
proving termination of algorithms uh so
for example we could uh take the
function X+
y this strictly
decreases why uh just think about a
transition we start with X comma y y
doesn't change and then the other term
in the sum used to be X and then it
becomes X remainder y so we're dividing
X by y so X gets smaller in that process
and so the sum of these two values is
going to be smaller than the sum of X
and Y so that's cool we now know that
this algorithm terminates um but stating
it using this
uh function is not so great because it
tells us that the number of
steps uh is uh at most a plus b
but that's not great that's that's what
we had before uh from our slow algorithm
we got a running time of a plus b like
so that's still true it's an upper bound
on the running time but I claim that in
fact our running time is much
smaller by a more clever proof let me
erase subtraction
okay so I
claim uh in
fact if we look at the bit count of X
and the bit count of Y in summation this
also strictly decreases
what is a bit count this is if you write
X in binary how many bits are there
what's the length of the binary
representation of X um this is
essentially 1 + log base 2 of X
ceiling a little gross but uh ASM
totically this is log base 2 of
x or when you use ASM totic notation you
don't even need the base because it only
makes uh constant Factor difference so
this is roughly log of x it's Theta log
of x this is Theta log of Y so uh the
number of
steps is order log X Plus log
Y and that's really good that's
exponentially faster sorry I should have
written uh log a plus log B because
that's where we start is a a comma B so
if I give you two numbers A and B I can
compute the gcd in roughly
logarithmically many divisions whereas
before we did a plus b now we have log a
plus log B so that's what we call an
exponential Improvement and this is a
what we would call a fast algorithm
because now if I have a 100 bit integer
it only takes me like or or two 100 bit
integers it only takes me around 100
steps whereas before is taking me two to
the 100 steps big difference
okay uh why is this true why is bit
count of X Plus bit count of Y strictly
decreasing um
because I
claim so I should say
because XR Y is less than x over2 this
is another fact about division um I
think
the intuition here is uh Y is smaller
than x when we're doing this Division
and so we can remove at least one whole
copy of Y from X and maybe we remove
more but um yeah you can think about
when y if Y is more than half X then
just in the first step we've removed
half of X and so we've gotten down to
less than x over two um if x is smaller
if Y is really small like one then we're
going to be able to eat all of x uh in
both cases you'll end up uh eating at
least half of X and so in general the
remainder will be less than half of X
over2 and so if we start with X and we
in the next step we get to X over2 or
smaller that means we removed one bit
from the binary representation or if you
think about it in log base 2 we've if we
have the number log base two goes down
by one so even with the ceiling it goes
down by
one okay so that's why this uclid
algorithm is fast and good that's why we
love it um I have for you a little of
the algorithm and then we'll talk about
extensions so here uh on the screen
we're Computing gcd of 189 and
66 if we think of that as a rectangle
189 by
606 uh then doing a division is like
Square
packing um so
here if we have an A by B rectangle and
a and b is the smaller one uh then a b
by B squ like subtracting off B and so
uh if you think of the whole rectangle
it's how many squares can I subtract off
and what we'll be left with is the
remainder because one dimension stays
the same the other dimension gets
reduced to the remainder so hopefully
that's clear why the geometric view of
squares is the same as what we've been
doing with UK's algorithm makes for a
much nicer picture and then you take
that rectangle and you flip it so that
the horizontal Dimensions bigger you
take off as many squares as you can and
you flip and you take off as many
squares as you can here's just just one
that's just a subtraction you flip uh
you take off as many squares as you can
you left with a remainder of three by
six uh and now here we get even Division
and so one of the dimensions becomes
zero and then the gcd of three and zero
is uh
three
cool so if that helps great if not don't
worry uh hopefully you can now compute
gcd uh we will do another example in a
second I would like to first uh
strengthen this algorithm and make it uh
do more
because remember we wanted to compute
gcd uh why we wanted to see whether gcd
of ab divided X because if the gcd of ab
divides X then all common divisors of A
and B will divide x uh and what the
reason we cared about that is I claimed
it was the same thing as X being an
integer linear combination of A and B
but where did the integer linear
combinations go all we've done so far is
compute gcd of ab well it turns out
there's a connection
and the connection is called bezus
theorem or
LMA it's called bazus Lemma because B is
like the last person to discover it
after uh in
1779 after another French mathematician
mesak uh in 1624 and after uh two Indian
mathematicians around 500 uh AC so uh
but we call it Biz LMA
this is the
connection uh gcd of ab is an integer
linear combination of A and B and we can
prove this using UK's
algorithm is pretty
cool we're going
to uh buy ukids algorithm
okay uh let me do this
quickly let's assume a is greater equal
to B again if not we can just swap A and
B and I guess we'll assume greater equal
to zero so we can apply ul's
algorithm uh UK's algorithm tells us or
the theorem we proved before UK's
algorithm tells us gcd of ab equals gcd
of B comma a rem B
uh
and we can use induction
Now by strong
induction on a plus b so this is very
similar to what we were saying here uh X
Plus y strictly decreases it's all we
need for induction to work here so we're
assuming by induction
that if a plus b is smaller than the
current value then gcd of AA B is an
integ linear combination of A and B and
so here we have gcd of A and B and we've
reduced it to gcd of some smaller values
or whose sum is smaller and so we can
apply strong induction to the this
pair uh and so we'll get that this gcd
is an integer linear combination of its
arguments so
let's continue here
so by strong induction we get that uh
gcd of B comma a ram
B uh is an integer linear
combination of b and a rem
B okay and this value of course is equal
to gcd of
ab by this equality and so uh we get
that the gcd we care about is integer
linear combination not of A and B but of
this reduced version b and a rem B okay
that's kind of annoying but it turns out
uh a r
b is an integer linear combination of A
and
B Why by the division
theorem actually wrote it out over here
we wrote that NR D is n minus something
time D that is this thing is an integer
linear combination of N and
d and so if I'm if I'm doing a rem B I
get that it's a
minus uh something the div times uh B so
that's an integer linear combination of
A and
B okay so what we're left with is we
have that this gcd that we care about is
an integer linear combination of B and
something else that is an integer linear
combination of A and B so in other words
we have an integer linear combination of
two integer linear combinations of A and
B Because B is definitely an integer
linear combination of A and B it's 0 * a
plus 1 time b a rem B is an integer
linear combination as written over there
and so now we're just taking an integer
linear combination of those two things
and that's also an integer linear
combination
of A and B as we showed
before okay so that's maybe a little
abstract but it does prove the theorem
now I'm going to turn that into an
algorithm cool
algorithm uh maybe over
[Applause]
here which is called the pulverizer
I mentioned ucl's algorithm was
discovered before uid in fact a stronger
version of ID's algorithm called the
pulverizer was Des uh described by Arab
Bata an Indian mathematician around 500
AC so uh long time ago and he called it
kutaka which is sanskrit for
pulverization so we're going to call
this the pulverizer most people call
this the extended ukian algorithm
uh and it's basically run ID's algorithm
but also keep in mind what's going on in
beus LMA and always keep track of X and
Y as an integer linear combination of A
and B okay so that's the
intuition uh as a state machine it's
quite simple kind of simple
A10 B 01 is where we start because a
equal 1 * a + 0 * B and B = 0 * a + 1 *
B so that's how we represent a and b as
integer linear combinations of A and B
pretty trivial and then our transitions
if we have X
St so this means u x = s * a + T *
B and we have uh y u v so in other words
we've represented y as U * s plus v *
sorry uh V time U * a plus v *
B then we transition
to
uh that's a mistake this should be y UV
uh we we as usual we just copy y to the
left argument we don't change it and
then X changes to um x r
y and then it turns out you can
write uh you can figure out how XR Y is
relative to the as a linear combination
of A and B like
this it's kind of a little
gross okay so we started with
representing X as uh s * a plus T * B
and we take s and we subtract off a
corrective term which is XD y time
either U or V where U or V is what
represented y okay if you work it out
that's exactly what we were doing here
we started with one number and we uh
subtracted off the div times what we had
before so if you stare at it at this
equation long enough uh this is exactly
what we're doing but in uh integer
linear combination space of A and B
um so I'm not going to justify this
anymore and I won't even show an example
but it gives you this is a particular
way to compute it um and I I'll say at
the beginning of an example if you have
0301 and you run this a few times you
get
to
um 2 1us
1 1 -1 2 and this part tells us that 1
equals -1 * 5 + 2 * 3 I hope that is
correct uh - 5 + 6 is 1 yep okay so this
is how you represent one as an integer
linear combination of five and three one
is interesting because it's the gcd of
five and three I'm this is connecting to
the water pouring right with water
pouring we had a container of size five
container of size three their gcd is one
they have basically no common divisors
except one and minus one uh and we can
represent the gcd as an integer linear
combination of five and three namely
this one therefore we can represent four
as an integer linear combination of 5
and three we just multiply both sides by
four and we get minus 4 * 5 plus 8 * 3
is one way to do it and uh that gives
you at least a way to solve this problem
problem it turns out you can take uh
eight copies of three and subtract out
four copies of five how do I do that um
well I just fill this up eight times in
total and each time I pour in uh all
that I can into the thing of size five
and each time it overflows I empty out
the five and so that's exactly how I can
build any integer linear combination of
five and three by start as long as one
side is positive and the other is
negative which turns out to be necessary
um then you can just take that many
copies of filling up one bucket pouring
it into the other removing whenever it
overflows and you will get uh exactly
the number you wanted for these numbers
one two pores of three uh into five will
give you one uh if you multiply this by
four I get the number four and I save
Manhattan
great good luck on your quiz on Thursday