Hello everyone. I'm Chidian, a postto
fellow at Eric and Wendy Schmidt Center
and I'm excited to introduce our speaker
Eric Shin. Uh Eric is the president of
Muhammad bin Zed University of
Artificial Intelligence and co-founder
and chief scientific officer of Jim
Bioai. Prior to this position, he was a
professor of computer science at CMU and
the founder of patent. His research
focused on the development of machine
learning and statistical method
methodology and large scale computation
systems and architectures for solving
problems involving automatic learning,
reasoning and decision making in high
dimension multimodel and dynamic
possible worlds in artificial biological
and social systems. He is a board member
of the international machine learning
society and fellows of the triple triple
E and ASA. Eric, I'm excited for your
talk and the floor is all yours.
[Applause]
Well, thank you very much. Uh I want to
thank Caroline and the colleagues for
inviting me here. I had uh really a
feast of uh you know of uh learning you
know for the past two days you know
learning all these uh very wonderful
exciting uh projects and ideas which
actually uh pushed me to uh like a many
you know edit my slides almost
constantly because I feel like the stuff
I prepare to talk about can be easily
outdated by the new presentations in
here. So I try to make it more fun. In
fact, just a minute ago, I added a few
more slices just to give a maybe a fun
context of this. So, we are here to
solve very complex problems. In a sense,
it's a you know a form of complex
reasoning. And I heard the word LLM, you
know, has been mentioned all the time
and LM has now been also a backbone for
many other applications that is
mentioned in here. you know uh you know
in fact the the architecture was
directly borrowed to train DNA models
and RNA models but I think there is a
need to really take a maybe a step back
and look at what is this whole business
is about what is LM and uh and what the
potential that we might have ignored so
LM is basically a system that does uh
reasoning you know inside you know the
space of
language it is actually not meant to be
built to make chat bots or to make uh
linguistic functions. Okay, it is
actually originally built to be a next
word generator that is meant to simulate
linguistic behaviors. Basically, it is a
success when you feel what you get out
of a LM interface does not look
different from a human. So, it is
simulating a human in the special
language. And LM doesn't work when you
add a space to make it bigger to have
images and uh when you have you know uh
you know adversaries and other agents
you know you add another degree of
dimensions and uh we are here you know
in fact we are now in a space of study
nature laws right so the problem become
really really complex how we might
approach it what is the kind of a
fundamental spirit inside large language
models and foundation models that we
could even borrow but not necessarily
just directly use to attract and to
attack bigger problem. So I heard I I
hope some of you who are like myself a
sci-fi fan have heard about the story of
Doom. Have you heard about that? Right.
Don is a super intelligent agent which
solves larger problems like all of us
larger problems. They saw problems like
uh winning a galactic war uh
transforming the climate and turn desert
into greenlands and so forth. So these
are problems really difficult right and
uh one thing very interesting in the
book is that uh he solves the problem in
a way that is very different from uh uh
way physicist and mathematicians who are
doing linear thinking. We have the
inductive reasoning machine to drive
through very very logical inference.
He's doing simulation. Basically, he
would have a mental word that allow him
to simulate all possible plans and ideas
and approaches before he even take a
single step and then he would be able to
choose the best scenario and then you
know action on it. And the reason he has
that capability is because he inherited
the all experiences and knowledges and
meaning data from his ancestor. And the
more he inherit the more simulation he
has and then the more power he can use
to solve problems. Right? So in the
world of psychology and philosophy there
is actually a term you know for such way
of thinking called the hypothetical
thinking. We actually do it all the
time. We say we do thought experiment.
That's exactly hypothetical thinking
right? I'm not sure that in our daily
research in fact talks that we heard
about we do thought experiments that
much. uh but uh uh what I'm going to
talk about today is to basically uh
build you know uh a system that
hopefully allow us to do simulational
thinking and thought experiment in the
world of biology. So in a sense the
project is about building such a
function which could be called a word
model you know if you are in a different
study domain but in here I call it a
virtual organism. It is a distribution
of the next state given the previous
state conditioning also action you take
which could be perturbation for example
knockouts and other things and um that's
here I want to uh conclude the primer
you know uh the models released like
this they are basically the same thing
trying to simulate phenomenons and the
possibilities in different uh space of
the word LM you know uh lives in the
space of language word models mod lives
in the space of a space and time and
agent models lives in the space of a
multi- agency and the ADO model that I'm
going to talk about lives in that space
of a physical biological word. So I'm
not trying to solve a model which make a
good prediction of herbivation outcome
or make a good prediction of a structure
given the sequence. These are
byproducts. The real goal is to be able
to simulate biology, you know, the way
that you would expect, you know, from a
natural creature. Uh but uh the goal of
uh explaining why you simulate that way,
what's the mechanism behind biology is
actually not in the goal. Okay, it is
not the purpose of such a project. So
with that I want to get started toward a
AIdriven digital organism using a
multi-skll foundational model approach.
So we've heard enough about this in the
past few days. The living creature is a
very very complex system. You know uh
highlighting multiscalability and the
multimodality and is a holistic system.
So I'm not going to say anything more
than that. You know you need to be able
to understand and process information
across the scale.
And that's actually not uh traditionally
even until now how biological science
and medical science are actually
positioned. You know for example you
know how do we study biology? If you are
given a piece of tissue which has a cell
you know uh we in our school we have the
department of cell biology and uh the
scientist would focus on that take data
in that domain and study that and there
is also a department of molecular
biology who goes down which I used to
get my PhD from and there is also
biochemistry which go even one level
down right if you want to go up you have
uh you know medicine if you go to a
hospital uh you see divisions organized
by organs
Okay, if you have a liver problem,
you're going to that division and
therefore they're not looking at your
other organs and other tissues and other
things. And uh you know um we also have
public health and other things. Um but
uh we use the knowledge uh in those
research to solve say this kind of
problems drug design and target
discovery uh coming up with uh treatment
and so forth. So maybe you can already
ask yourself does the solution to each
of these problem exist in one of the
slides or not right maybe not right you
probably are expecting something like
this each of the problem cross basically
that sector or that silo that defines
our research discipline where we get
degree from which kind of force us to
look beyond where we are but our ability
to look beyond is limited by tools and
also by our brain power we may not be
able to source many knowledies And
that's where LLM all of a sudden kick in
because they seems to be a good tool at
least to begin with digesting and
consuming all knowledges right and uh it
is maybe also echoing that very you know
uh reality that every human health care
problem is essentially biological
problem. If you really talk about
someone being sick, you want to come up
with a design of the drug and antibbody,
it's not just you know uh a medical
problem anymore. You need to know the
biology you know at all scale anywhere
from molecular behavior to cellular
behavior to tissue to organ to organism.
Right? So if you really want to see your
answer in that holistic
context, I do see you know the need to
rethink about the tool we use which is
like this our classical mathematical
tools you know uh which uh you know uh
have been with us you know for decades
and uh and uh we spent career and life
you know uh developing higher and higher
version of that is actually of that
nature. It's uh under the principle of
one model for one problem with one data
set. That kind of specific design. In
fact, we are very proud of advocating
that spirit that you need to be very
specific. Okay? And you shouldn't be
trying to be a generalist because that's
going to uh cause you losing performance
and so forth. But in terms of
correctness and that that's second
issue. In the recent years you know uh
we see a new generation of technology
you know you know um you know maybe
featured with deep learning approaches
in the form of uh convolution neuronet
networks uh you know uh transformers and
uh now bigger foundation models. you
know um how are they going to be you
know uh maybe uh used you know uh maybe
in a different way to address the
problems that uh biologists and medical
practitioners might be interested. Well,
we see some very good success already,
right? So Arfold is one of the highlight
of uh uh using these new tools to uh
solve a uh you know um you know a very
very uh classic and difficult problem in
a very very impressive fashion and as a
result of that these days we see a boom
of foundation models you know you in
fact it's even more active than the
space of uh large language models and
the word models almost every week we see
announcement from certain labs you know,
of a new model, you know, in a
particular modality and so forth, right?
In fact, you may wonder why so quick
why, you know, you only see a foundation
model in the in uh in language and in
visual only from big companies and only
after a couple weeks or maybe a year and
why, you know, we can see uh biological
foundation models coming up every week.
Um in a sense, my humble opinion is that
these are not really foundation models.
Okay, these are transformer models uh
which are smallish specialized. It's
just a bigger uh classical tool happen
to be adopting the same architecture. Uh
you don't call a bicycle you know a real
kind of a same beast as a you know uh
you know a 18-wheeler even though they
all have the wheels. It's a small thing
and also the design philosophy probably
is also very different. For example, uh
imagine that uh uh we use a tool that we
are doing now to solve a simple, you
know, u say structure prediction
problem, right? You probably can see
that the structure prediction problem
right now is
happening out of the biological context.
You take a DNA uh amino acid sequence,
you put them into you know uh a may say
AF3 you know or other you know uh you
know u fundamental foundational model
tools and you get a stretch out of it.
Here I give a result for you. This is a
comparison of the ground truth of a
slightly complex structure prediction
problem which you need to consider
context. You are predicting the
structure of a antibbody in the presence
of a antigen. Therefore, you know, it's
not just about your amino acid sequence
determining the threedimensional
structure of uh a protein, but also it
needs to work, you know, on the antigen,
which actually will induce additional
structure, you know, consequence and so
forth. It turns out that the alpha 43
didn't do very well for this task. Okay,
this is the kind of complex prediction
problem. In fact, the problem can be
even trickier because uh not only your
uh uh structure needs to interact uh
properly with the antigen, it also
shouldn't interact with something
they're not supposed to interact with.
Therefore the offtarget problems the uh
non-specific uh prediction uh
interaction problems should also be in
context so that you don't trigger
toxicities and other side effects when
you deploy you know a molecular design.
So in a sense what I'm trying to say is
that uh even for a biological problem
which look as specific as a from
sequence to structure you need to
consider a much bigger context.
Therefore, that so-called one model per
one data set, you know, per one problem
kind of mindset isn't going to work very
well. Okay, for complex problem like
this, right? So, that's why when you say
you look at large language models, it
was never trained in this way. It is not
like a I train a large language model to
answer your Olympic math problem. I
train another model to answer your
reason problem. It begins the reverse
way. I train a generic general purpose
model which is humongous very very big
and they don't perform very well but
they actually does work for everything
and then only when you want to do your
math problem you want to do a financial
problem I specialize it and fine-tune it
that's the workflow in LM but uh in
biology we are not doing that we
actually are treating the foundation
model as a N2 already for a specific
problem and I feel a need to remind
everyone that this may be a problematic
we are missing opportunities. So in that
sense I would say uh not every
foundation model or state space models
or combinations is really truly
foundational. Okay. And the LM is never
meant to be you know uh doing that kind
of a task specific fashion. So then what
should we do? So that leads to uh you
know uh my uh very humble proposal where
I want to uh welcome some debates and
inputs. So we've got all this data right
you know uh this data include you know
uh multimodal data from a sequence to
structure to tabular record of
expression and to image to time series
and everything right and we've got all
these questions out there you know all
the way from designing a protein
structure reverse folding you know a
protein sequence and all the way up to I
don't know you know deploy a antigen or
a vaccine you know at the proper time at
a proper dosage to a proper population
and so forth. All these problems look
very different but they have a common
foundation of following some biological
principles and also they may be you know
uh reaching out to solutions that is at
this level connected right so in that
sense um what should be in the middle
should we see a jungle of spikes which
connects one thing here to one something
over there or do we maybe uh imagine
maybe a future solution that is more
modern down the road is taking a more
holistic approach. Right? So I believe
that there may be a opportunity to uh
think about a more unified and
integrative system for foundation models
biology where they can do one thing
right to simulate biological systems and
through that simulation hopefully you
can make predictions you can make
programmings and designs right so that's
a system where I call a digital organism
it is basically a computing system which
would empirically you know uh simulate
uh the phenomenon and outcome of uh a
living system upon any of your you know
legitimate and implementable you know uh
perturbations interferences as if you
are interacting with a real world
organisms. So I have some very very
strict definition here. It's not a
hypothetical thing. Say you do
everything for me. First of all, you
need to be able to ask and execute your
ask on that system. Don't basically try
something that is spiritual and say tell
me how do you work because uh this is
something that you cannot really you
know uh execute and implement. Right? So
typically you'll have a prompt which
could be a sequence, could be a
structure, could be a knockout, could be
some kind of perturbation and then the
system hopefully simulates your back you
know uh whatever consequences. So that's
a digital organism in my definition
which is not a digital twin. They don't
ne necessarily look like a cell but uh
the numbers that they give you may be
what you would expect from measuring a
real cell. And uh in the essence this uh
uh system is essentially mathematically
equivalent to such a conditional
distribution of the next state given the
previous state and also the action which
represents your perturbation. Right? So
uh the the uh the the the host just
introduced uh one of my function to be
uh the chief scientist of Jamba. Jamba
is a company that we actually recently
created exactly to execute that vision
because it requires not only you know uh
very very uh intense engineering work
but also resources and machines and so
forth. So Jamba's vision of a AIdriven
drogism is illustrated in here. It is a
holistic family of uh foundation models
each built on you know a different
biological data modality but they will
work together at some point you know to
deliver you know a holistic
multi-dimensional and multifaceted
functions and we are hoping that such a
system can be you know used to augment
not just a single slice but a uh
spectrum of um you know of uh um every
stage of uh processes in development
medicine. For example, nowadays you know
uh I remember uh very recently FDA just
announced that uh there is time maybe it
is time to start now uh stepping away
from using animals and the real systems
to do all the trials. How to make that
happen? Well, that means you need to do
something in a digital environment with
simulations. So that means you know uh
the AIdriven you know uh innovation in
medicine is not just about uh simulating
or designing a drug structure. You need
to also simulate an environment where
drug will be act on and uh hopefully
predict their consequences and you may
also be able to you know help designing
the trial you know given such context
make it more efficient and more
informative and maybe even help in
personalizing the outcomes. So we see
such a system called ADO you know
potentially uh uh usable for you know uh
needs of across the spectrum and our
dream is to really uh reach to this
point to close the loop of biological
study. In the past I was actually
trained as a biologist. I remember that
in my whole five years of pitch study I
studied the three genes you know uh and
uh um I was taking pride of being able
to pour a beautiful gel you know and and
get a sequence out of it and then we use
that method to basically do biological
exploration of hypothesis we basically
make hypothesis and we make some
constructs and uh and then we're going
to see in real life you know how uh that
uh you know uh perturbed system will
look like. This is a very expensive and
dangerous kind of uh experiment because
it's in the physical world. What if you
have a leak, you have a spill, right? So
I imagine with a AI system, the whole
workflow will be turned upside down.
We're going to probably you know spend
uh uh instead of uh now uh you know
using uh data and computer as an
afterthought but using them as the
primary filter you know uh to search the
hypothesis until you you know reach to a
few very highly plausible spa uh
hypothesis you know using computational
simulation and then you do a much more
guided and a small scale wab experiment
and then hopefully use that to include
data. So that's basically what a ADO
vision at very high level look like. Now
for the rest of the talk I'm going to
dive into the technical details and tell
you how such a system might be built.
It's a very complex system and for every
complex system you know uh if you take a
industrial view you have to basically
come up with a engineering road map and
our engineering road map is no different
from building a aircraft. just take into
parts and do distributed manufacturing
and then assemble and fine-tune.
So stage one very obviously it is where
we are now. Uh we divide and conquer.
Basically all these uh uh existing
efforts that we see in the literature in
a sense belongs to at this stage. You
are building modality specific
foundation models you know for DNA RNA
protein um you know uh RNA seek image
and so forth. Yeah. But uh why we need
to build that rather than just collect
them from literature because you know uh
we want to seize all these different
components first of all to be performant
but also to be ready to integrate
because to talk to each other so that uh
a problem can be addressed in a bigger
context and also information flow.
Therefore, our next step is to really
connect dots. And this is the
technically more interesting part
because uh you know uh different models
use different data and they have a
different representations you know of
different uh modality and maybe even of
the same modality. That creates you know
the need to seek alignments across
different modality to also evolve the
model continuously when you get more
information and also to maybe uh allow
you know arbitrary conditioning to be
incremented so that you can you know do
forward generation, reverse generation
or you know uh coming up with uh you
know uh correct responses to your
creative prompts you know say you know a
particular drug situation stretch
requirements
temperatures and so forth and then
cascade. Um maybe I should replace this
word with a little bit technical
description so that the people who are
here working on the models uh can maybe
uh appreciate the the the the substance
what is evolving. For example, you know,
uh you have a you know a language model
uh that's trained on uh unaligned
collection of sequences. Now what if I
give you additional information that uh
your sequence you know uh can be aligned
into multiple sequence alignment. Do you
retrain a model from scratch or do you
continue and how do you continue right?
So that's another interesting problem
and also maybe you get more data you
know of a completely different uh you
know distribution uh that you need to u
maybe uh take on a non-trivial way of
waiting them so that they don't uh spoil
the previous train models. So this is
evolving. You need to basically allow
the model to continuously receive new
information that is uh cleverly you know
engineered and formatted to you know
allow the model you know keep learning
without disrupting in the overall
architecture. I will give you a few
examples when I come to that point.
Second is about the alignment. Yeah, you
know, uh you your protein sequences come
from you know uh amino acid sequences
but also could come from the structure
tokenizations of structure you know
discrete motifs and uh uh can you
actually you know cross predict each
other so that your representation become
uh you know aligned and consistent. So
this is a art of alignment. It's like
you put two languages next to each
other. Therefore, your representation of
the language in the language model
become suddenly
connected. Uh conditioning you know I
don't need to say too much if you do
inverse folding your input a structure
then your production of the sequence
need to be conditioned as structure so
that they become consistent. So our goal
of course is to allow arbitrary you know
information to be encoded properly so
that they can be conditioned on. This is
particularly important when you do self
perturbation. How do you you know embed
and represent a perturbation or maybe a
knockout or genetic perturbation versus
drug perturbation? Right? All these uh
could leads to a new need of
architectural innovations. Cascading is
another interesting information that
actually maybe uh the one of the best
justification of having all these
different models in the same place. Why?
For example, when you build a cell
model, how these days people build a
cell model? Well, you use a table of uh
RNA seek data and therefore you train
you know uh a model uh using uh such uh
tabular information as the input and how
do you represent your gene? Well, a gene
in those models is ID. The ID could be
ABC could be 1 2 3. It's a code number
that is not carrying biological
meanings. But a gene has DNA sequence. A
gene encodes a protein which has
structures. How do you put all those
information you know uh into the
learning so that they carry you know
both you know uh just a uh a information
that tell them apart but in addition
their actual functionality. Well, you
can imagine once you have a DNA
foundation model, once you have a
protein foundation model, you can
extract representations of every gene
and every protein from those models and
use them to represent the genes, the
protein uh the gene the genes in the in
the cell model and that cell model
itself actually could return you a
representation of a whole cell which can
be used in the next level of modeling
say a tissue in our organism. Right?
That's how you see the cascading can
happen continuously you know top down
and bottom up.
Once you have that we can write at the
age uh where uh you need to do optimal
alignment and uh across the scale. It's
just like when you assemble all the
parts into a aircraft you still need to
do a lot of fine tuning to make them
harmonic and working together. So in
here that pose another technique
challenge because that means you need to
be able to co-rain now multiple models
at the same time so that the gradient
can flow across modality and across
model modules and also there are
additional consistencies to be honored
you know in this finetuning. So that's
roughly the three stages that we are
using right now to train the ADO model.
There are again you know a good number
of technical you know uh challenges that
we are working on both front end and the
back end. I just want to name a few. On
the back end these models are bigger
models. I'm going to have a graph with
you showing you that why you know we are
not at the optimum spot yet even in
terms of model size. Therefore that
involves you know uh handling long
context you know million or maybe longer
and running on tens of uh hundreds if
not thousands of uh GPUs and uh doing
proper paralizations doing proper uh
discretization quantization and uh and
and uh and uh other type of projection.
So these are you know uh the level of uh
you know engineering work on the back
end. Then on the model part the need to
invent new representations you know for
biological information which is the
business called tokenization is not end
yet. Right now in fact we don't have a
lot of uh new ideas coming straight out
of biology in treating biological data.
We basically borrow all the ideas from
NLP which was meant for you know
cognitive languages not for biological
languages. Therefore you can imagine
there is a big room there to improve our
current way of representing even
biological information in the form of
tokens and then positional encoding.
What does it mean you know uh by
position you know uh in a biological
token you know in the language is very
obvious is the position of your word
inside a sequence but in biology that
kind of assumption is not there.
Therefore, right now we see many trivial
treatment of positional encoding which
actually lose huge opportunities in
capturing additional informations and uh
also you know uh you know uh training
strategies do you still want to do the
missing token partition training or you
use contrastive training and so forth
again that gives you additional
dimension to make the model perform
better inference how do you use the
model after it's trained and uh I I
think especially in those generation
task where you need to you know have a
particular structure uh serving
particular goal in the space of doing
agentic and the word models now one of
the trendy term is called the purposeful
reasoning and the purposeful planning so
that's another idea that is not very
often practiced right now in here in
biology what's the purpose you know of a
design in biological world how to encode
our purposes so I meant to say that it's
a very very exciting field that is
almost empty at this point in terms of
technical new ideas. So uh both for
machine learning people and also for
comb biologist you know it's a gold mine
you know for us to uh discover you know
new technologies and new advancement and
now of course there is a huge need there
for soft engineering you know in the
space of we talk about the megatron
database we talk about the deep speed
all these other things in here the
tooling of uh you know LM of biological
modeling is really really chaotic right
now I saw a few presentations today and
yesterday mentioning about certain
companies is already making that effort.
It's nice to see more of that coming out
of of our work. So, just to report some
preliminary results before I end, we
were able to publish, you know, a good
uh collection of u train pre-trained
models already in the past few months.
And if you go back to this graph, all
these little components uh with a check
mark uh already has a model released and
some released more than once already.
And uh uh of course you know uh they are
evaluated very exhaustively over uh
hundreds of different downstream tasks
to make sure that they you know are
performant and also
consistent what we do with all these
models what have been happening you know
in developing this. So here are some
technical insights. First of all, I want
to report that we did scaling law for
many of these models and we found that
even with the current data, okay, the
model size isn't saturating yet. You
still have the room to push up the
performance of the model just by making
the model bigger. That's like know very
very low hanging fruit uh that we can
try. Of course, it requires capital and
engineering capabilities. There are some
more interesting technical advancements
which I'm going to quickly list out. uh
for example you know uh in this ADO
protein model we start to see you know
uh the opportunity of uh uh very very uh
deploying you know diverse pre-training
strategies you know to constantly
continuously boost the model performance
so in this particular production of the
protein language models we started from
single sequences and then you add MSA
the MSA actually can be actually treated
as a single sequence if you inject a
positional encoding which indicates the
evolution position of every sequence and
then put them back. They remember not
only who you are but also where you are
from the evolution history and that
essentially turn a previously single
sequence based RLM into you know a model
which based on MSA. You can then inject
stratization to further improve. You can
then play with uh uh data reweing
temperature analing and many other
tricks to constantly push up. So you can
see this curve you know is still not
stopping yet which actually gets us to a
point where we can outperform models
like AF3 ESM quite significantly you
know over protein function
predictions in another model which we
called uh 80 fold uh again a combination
of different ideas you know really can
leads to a quite strong results I
mentioned about the prediction problem
out of context and here's how we did it
first of all we rely on a much much more
powerful for protein language model that
features ideas like multiple sequence
alignment slate training a mixture of
experts to allow you addressing
different model modality rack you know
to uh really allow you to focus on you
know connected data and then you know
some diffusion process you know to allow
you you know simulating structures and
uh we found that with this combination
we were able to actually predict you
know a complex antigen antibbody
structure you know in a much much uh
higher quality than existing models. In
particular, if you look at these three
graphs, this is the prediction quality
comparison between us and alpha fold and
another model um you know over uh only
antibbody which is basically a one
complex stretch pretty problem and then
in here the the the the task is
performed on antigen and antibbody
complex and you can see the improvement
is now over 20%. And also nanogen and
nanobbody and antibbody stretch
prediction also is a hard one. We can do
much better than ex models. Basically
the the harder the problem the better
improvement you can get from such a
slightly more complex
systems. Uh yet another uh innovation uh
related to the the diffusion based uh
generative models. Um here um again you
know you can see that uh we implemented
a pipeline which allow you to uh do uh
reverse folding you know of uh uh the
protein structure you know given you
know a a target say generate something
that binds this particular structure. We
found that uh uh our system was able to
generate a much more realistic
distribution you know of the protein
structure. So here's a comparison. This
red curve is the distribution of native
proteins in terms of the proportion of
alpha helix and beta sheets. This red
curve is the distribution of the
generated products from David Baker's
group. And here you have another
function. You can see that they are very
far away from this red thing. Right? And
this blue curve is the generative
distribution from uh the ado diff gem
which appear to be a lot more uh
faithful to the biological
reality. One more is uh on the ado
tissue model uh we built a cell and
tissue model which can be tested on
problems like niche prediction. But the
way do that is uh more than just
building a cell model you know uh with
single cell uh RNC data. We actually use
uh another new technique called the two
dimensional positional encoding. So that
whenever you know you want to build a
representation into the prediction you
take not only the cell itself you also
take the cell information embedding from
a neighboring thing. your basically your
neighborhoods you know which are
connected you know to you will all be
incorporated into a much larger
representation so that you have the
context you know into that. Therefore in
training this model every count is not
just from one cell but also the cell in
the neighborhood properly positionally
encoded. Last but not least we actually
could use this entire idea of foundation
models to redefine some classical
practice such as gwas. Right? So in JAS
you know it's a very very important
field in medicine but it's also really
you know you know hampered by technical
difficulties. You cannot for example
work with a very fancy phenotypes such
as a time series. You also rely on very
very statistically weak data in the form
of snips right but now with a foundation
model that works across modality. First
of all, you can turn your complex
phenotype such as a image, such as a
time series into a vector representation
using the foundational model embedding.
You can also turn the genomic
information into a continuous vector
which can find separate all the
polymorphisms and the behaviors and
patterns in your genetics in the form of
a vector and then at the end of day what
you do is vector to vector association
analysis which is a multi-dimensional
regression problem using classical
approaches. So that kind of opens up the
way of you know arbitrary flexibility of
working with different type of uh
phenotype modality and also genotypic
and molecular polymorphisms.
And all the uh results I just talked
about are actually uh packaged you know
uh in you know a uh nicely structured uh
software stack uh where we uh regularly
release in hugging face and in GitHub
and you are welcome to uh to try out and
to uh give us feedbacks. I think
recently you know we we've been uh keep
an eye on the the downloads. It seems to
be picking up quite nicely with
thousands of uh you know downloads uh in
certain models. So I definitely
encourage you to take a look. So to wrap
up, I think I'm maybe uh you know uh uh
sending uh some uh slightly
controversial messages in here in terms
of my methodology belief, right? Because
we were trained as scientists and uh we
believe in ration and the math and the
first principle was supposed to be like
Newton, you know, writing the laws and
predicting the objects and so forth.
That's actually where you know
scientists you know really hold uh very
secret about but I want to say that this
may not be the only way to do science
because uh even in science there are
many phenomenons which is defining
causality in a traditional way here I
just give you a few examples you know
you know if you you are a believer of a
general theory of relativity then there
is a phenomenon called time travel
therefore what is causing what is
unclear there okay quantum superposition
is Another problem only when you observe
you know uh the final consequences
otherwise there are parallel universe
out therefore there's no causality right
and the evolution also is not causal by
the way we are not the perfect design of
the god okay we are the the the outcome
of you know a random mutation plus
directional selection therefore even in
nature you know uh it's a hypothetical
thinking type of you know process rather
than a direct design I want to design a
creature which lives in the mountain of
ops That's not the way we evolve, right?
So I just want to you know uh you know
uh maybe uh uh stress that there is a
room for us to be a little bit r less
rational and more empirical and that
basically comes to the conclusion
between the two kinds of school right
now you know countism you know is you
know maybe uh you know the kind of a
guiding principle you know uh for much
of the scientists they ask always ask
why and uh can you explain to me this
and I need to have a pure total clarity
and causality
before I can believe you know and move
on. But uh in humanism you know uh you
you can take your face on data and
empirical results before you even
understand what's going on there. That's
actually what's uh inside LLM and large
language models and FMs. We actually
honestly don't know exactly you know the
reasoning path and everything inside
that but it doesn't m hurt us from using
that. At least in biology I find one
example similar. the invention of the
vaccine is like that when it is invented
we don't actually know DNA RNA we don't
know at all why it is working but it
worked and then people used it right so
I hope that uh uh we can take the same
kind of uh approach in here with the
availability of foundation models which
does job like this instead of this I
would like to have in a position where
we have a periodic table and predict the
compound you know when we mix
But uh I guess uh even if uh uh the FM
based approach, the deep learning based
approach, the AI approach you know are
not quite there, it doesn't you know
prevent us from uh using it to do you
know uh you know uh to make progress. So
with that I want to return to uh the
initial vision. Ado is one of these uh
simulator you know of the biological
world allowing all these phenomenons to
be simulated and some of them to be
programmed and predicted and uh there is
a potential that uh such a system could
be you know a paradigm for holistic and
incitical science where you carry out
your virtual web lab you carry out your
virtual trial and then you do you know
maybe pandemic simulation using a
simulation system like that like what we
actually see in many other domain in
physics in semiconductor in agriculture
in many other places it is happening or
it happened for a long time biology is
one of the last place where we are very
very heavily still you know relying on
wab and uh uh I imagine a change uh
toward a modern approach is needed with
that I want to conclude my presentation
thank you for the attention
[Applause]
Thanks for your inspiring talk, Eric.
And we'll have time for one question.
Hi, thank you for the talk. Uh, I have a
question. Have you faced any challenges
in terms of evaluation benchmarks? I
would assume this is like an over idea
you are exploring and I would assume you
have faced some challenges that are you
working on to creating new benchmarks
for this task. Thank you. Great
question. So uh uh fortunately you know
uh just like uh you know in uh uh
imageet in a biological world we have so
protein gene from debra you know which
gives you already hundreds of downstream
benchmark tests. So we use that. Okay.
And uh I think there is always a need
for the community to share and publish
more standardized benchmark test. But uh
there is a twist going forward. These
benchmarks were designed with the old
mindset of having new tools delivering
old functionality. They may be not
strong enough to test the future
systems. Therefore, I think with the
evolution of new systems like this
coming out, uh there may be a space to
think even harder to come up with
additional uh stronger test and more
difficult problems. So, that's uh uh of
course, you know, uh our company, my
team is uh very committed, you know, to
uh publish and to share uh not just the
benchmark uh data and test actually the
benchmark tool. You need to have the
right tool to plug in your data and run
the experiment and even that right now
is not very standardized. This is not
like you have a chatbot arena you know
in LM which actually was built by my
group. Everybody go there using the same
platform you know to fairly compare. I
think this is a emerging need that we
need to address in our biological
community.
Thanks a model. There's a you know very
nice presentation and you have wonderful
you know very platform but you know um
not all health issues are
biological
bios in three dimensions where like
addictions you know can only account the
genetic only account for to
60% and you know guided
environment all the
patient would like to
entertain a model.
Thank you for the question. If you look
at this graph, uh this is not meant to
be, you know, setting already the
limitation of the data we're going to
use. These are examples of the data we
have and if more data is going to be
available such as epigenetic, such as
environmental, of course, we're going to
use it. The key question is that do you
already design a architecture that is uh
you know uh you know uh you know maybe
uh ready in advance for taking those big
data new data or do you just plug one
after another right so this is a
technical question we don't have an
answer yet but uh if you look at the uh
the practice in large language models
and in large visual models these days um
the attitude over there on data is very
different from biologist I keep hearing
in biological domain People say we need
to have a high quality data. We need to
curate the data and we need to do
something something. I have a
drastically opposite opinion. Maybe just
to be psychotadic. All data is data.
Wrong data is data. Dirty data is data.
They carry informations and they if they
reflect a flaw in the experiments in the
collection that is something you want to
learn as well. Therefore in language for
example they just take everything okay
and let the machine the system to try
come up with their own internal
connectivity and coherence and then give
you the simulation. I think in biology
if you take a open view like this to try
make the model larger and make the model
inclusive of all data that might be you
know you know a opportunity to uh see uh
certain emergent properties.
We'll unfortunately have to move it on
to the discussion. Thank you very much.
Sorry for taking your time. Thank you.
Thank you.