first just to give you uh a quick
overview of the work that we're doing in
the MIT climate and sustainability
Consortium um we're a group of 14 member
companies that are from different
sectors who are working with each other
and the MIT Community to try to rapidly
scale climate and sustainability
Solutions uh and so our members are from
a variety of different sectors ex
centure uh Amazon Apple Cargill Dow
PepsiCo IBM Verizon
and we intentionally do that because we
listen to them about what are their
challenges when it comes to achieving
their climate and sustainability goals
um and then we help work with them on
ways that they can work with each other
and then also with the MIT Community to
co-create Solutions uh and just like you
heard from some of our former speakers
here we love to have industry working
with uh MIT researchers to help make
their work uh kind of more relevant
um and more likely to have impact and
then to be be able to be scaled so um
and the way in which we do our work we
identify a variety of different topics
uh on which um our members have set our
priorities and these range from things
like transportation to circularity
climate Finance nature-based Solutions
Computing uh social dimensions and um
and then when when uh the work happens
through uh a variety of different means
one is that we invest in um seed Awards
to the MIT Community these are are
faculty and graduate students and
postdocs who we invest to work on
projects with our member companies and
the other way is that we fund uh
postdoctoral impact fellows um and they
are experts in one of those areas and
their their job is to understand the
landscape at our member companies on
these topics and then also um within the
MIT Community to try to help make those
uh connection so um so today we're going
to hear from three uh posts here at MIT
two of who are mcsc impact fellows and
another who's working on a topic uh
that's still very relevant to climate
and Computing in particular um and we're
going to hear about the work uh that
they're they're doing uh and then I'll
come to close at the end so um our first
presenter is Dr Nan Basher and he is a
mcsc impact fellow working uh on
Computing and he'll talk about how
that's both the
impacts of computing how we decarbonize
that while also um trying to determine
solutions that Computing can help to
create so thanks very much no
[Applause]
one just one second
hi everyone um I am Nan Basher I am the
Computing and climate impact fellow at M
CSC uh I also work with the sale group
with Christina deletro in mitc sale I'm
a computer systems researcher by
training and today I'm going to talk
about the climate and sustainability
implications of generative
AI so there has been a lot of talk about
how AI Data Center need a lot of power
and that is true here we have a graph
where power demand is on y- AIS and
different quarters are of like recent
years are on x-axis we see that uh
before pandemic the demand was growing
but slowly during pandemic it kind of
slowed down but since um the
introduction of generative AI tools it
has
skyrocketed and if these numbers are
like for North American data centers and
this is the capacity for data centers
that is already under construction and
not the one that are being requested or
the even the ones that are um um being
basically operated right now so let's
take a look at the numbers from a
different perspective if you look at a
more uh global scale and particular to
um hyperscaler companies like Google
Microsoft uh they have massive projects
going on uh throughout the world and you
have these like uh 2,000 megawatt of
capacity just in Sweden and Norway for
Google alone and while these are more
region specific and Company specific
numbers here is uh a high level trend of
ICT industry at the global scale if you
see and if you look at these numbers
from 2005 to 2018
the demand kind of remained constant
like from 2010 to 18 it only increased
by 6% and the reason was that there were
these massive efficiency gains in
computer systems Hardware became
efficient people moved from uh on premus
data centers that are typically
inefficient to these cloud data centers
which are much more efficient so that
curbed that demand but all of those
efficiency gains have physical limits
and we are approaching those limits and
at the same time we have this
exponential increase in demand and it is
projected that by 2026 our demand will
go
from
2,200 terawatt in 2018 to almost 1,000
terawatt and beyond that any prediction
is uh mute because like you cannot
really um predict what is going to
happen Beyond like one or two years
so to understand this problem what is
going on we um I worked with um this
amazing set of researchers uh across MIT
on understanding what is driving this
growth and what are the implication and
how can we uh support a more responsible
development in generative
AI so for that basically uh we set out
to understand what are the key drivers
uh behind this growth so there is is
like in paper we outline like more uh
detailed drivers such as gains in Energy
Efficiency computer became cheaper
training bigger models became easier
there is this consolidation of AI
capabilities there is this perceived
benefit and so on but I think the major
uh driver has been this incomplete
consideration of value where people just
look at what AI is going to do for their
business and uh themselves and how
transform ative it is going to be even
though it is just an expected value not
the realized value but they don't really
uh look at the not so bright side where
you don't consider the impact on climate
or on people that don't have a vice on
this table uh that is discussing the
growth in
AI so what should we do about it so we
proposed in that paper that we we should
have a framework for assessing the
benefits and costs of generative AI
Technologies to inform or enable
stakeholders and decision makers to
decide okay is this a valuable
application of generative AI or not
rather than applying it to anywhere and
everywhere and it requires estimating
costs and benefits and requires
multi-stakeholder engagement and an an
ex example I show this like tradeoff
metrix for example that you have
societal benefits to be gained from um
generative Ai and then there are climate
impacts and total emission impacts so if
you for example make um some Energy
Efficiency improvements and the energy
per task goes down but the total
emissions Jon Paradox and all would
probably go up having um big Tech
control the generative AI makes it
probably more accessible just like
Google search was to a lot more people
but it may also restrict or resist to
regulation and uh other form of um
measures that enable a more sustainable
development so with this we call for
like people who are stakeholders
including policy makers Civil Society
uh computer scientists like myself and
uh other uh any other stakeholders to
come and decide okay how are the
decisions currently being made what do
they need um to make better
decisions and how can
we populate this framework that we are
talking about of benefits and cost to
enable those decision makings and for
that I set out to do my part which is I
am a computer systems person so my what
I do is that sense what is the impact of
computing figure out how to reduce it
and then develop systems that deploy
those optimization at scale and for this
talk I wanted to list out or map out
basically all the costs that are
important but things got very
complicated very quickly and I stopped
so this is not a complete picture this
is probably not even an accurate picture
but this just shows you that the when it
comes to just quantifying the cost of
like materials carbon water energy and
any other kind of like uh metrics that
may use to quantify environmental or
social or any other kind of costs there
are so many angles and variables and the
major problem in most of these uh
efforts is the lack of data for example
if I want to quantify how much um and
for gpt3 training took or like the most
advanced GPT 4 or something what it took
I may have an estimate of onetime
training for that cost but I don't know
the development effort that went into
training that model or how they are
regularly fine-tuning that model how
much is the Environmental cost on that
so a lot of things are hidden behind
these uh proprietary
um like controls and even if some of the
data about environmental impacts is
available it's uh in the basically
behind pay walls that may not be
accessible to researchers so given that
um I am just like saying uh in in terms
of this that before we go on uh
developing uh framework we need to
estimate these costs well and for that
uh broader
engagement from industry stakeholders
would be helpful in terms of informing
us where the costs are coming from and
how we are going to um um better
quantify them and what do they need in
terms of U decision making from our side
and with that I will conclude my talk
and at the end of the session I will be
happy to take us
[Applause]
all right thank you noan um our next
speaker is Dr Bjorn lutan and he is a
post-doctoral associate in Earth
atmosphere and planetary Sciences
department and he's working on a project
that's actually um one of mit's climate
Grand Challenge Flagship projects called
bringing uh Computing to The Climate
challenge I know it's bc3 I always I
remember which order the CES are um but
which is a really neat way that he'll
talk about to make a digital PL twin of
our um of the climate and one of the
neat things is that this is not an mcsc
project per se but we have set up
discussions between researchers on his
team and some of our member companies
from insurance and Computing sectors to
figure out how is it that we can apply
what they're doing to support decision
making so we'll be curious for your
feedback on that too so beorn please
[Applause]
okay hello everybody so I will be
sharing with you sort of a research
exert from our bc3 team which we label a
cautionary Tale on deep learning climate
emulators and climate
emulators um in a nutshell are we have a
very computation expensive um climate
model that has created a large data set
and now we want to find fast
approximations to that why would we want
to do this right now um some of you
might have heard of the CIP assemble or
SSP scenarios um these are assumptions
on co2 methane emissions black carbon
sufur dioxide um basically assumptions
on how they could um behave in the
future so there's a business as usual
scenario um there's a negative carbon
emission scenario the green one the SSP
126 basically internationally we have
agreed on four to five of those
scenarios that are the most important
scenarios to explore with the climate
models that um International climate
modeling centers have developed
so researchers around the world ran
their climate model there's about around
about a 100 climate models uh in the
world for these scenarios and that gives
us the body of um global temperature
predictions or
precipitation um projections uh for 2030
2050 ahead the issue with that approach
is that every time you run a climate
model it takes about two weeks on 20,000
CPUs that's the equivalent of hundreds
of thousands of dollars just in the
compute cost to run a single climate
model for a single scenario so that's
why we only have five scenarios and that
what makes it really hard for example to
find out um let's think about
uh what would be the impacts of uh
nature-based Solutions increasing
Wetlands we would have to ask our friend
at the climate Computing Center to run
their model uh spend $400,000 on compute
to really find that out so what if we
can take all the data we have created
and find fast approximations to that and
that is sort of the goal of this bc3
team and today we'll explore one
particular research paper out of that so
um these climate emulators some of them
exist already I want to point out mit's
model called nroads where um you can
explore sort of the impact of what if we
dramatically curb deforestation reduce
it and how would that impact Global
temperature change this model is really
great it can run on your your your
laptop after the session you can Google
nroads but what it cannot really give
you yet is local impacts they're working
on that um but that is one of the big
challenges of these climate emulators so
how do we emulate the effect of climate
policies onto local climate impacts for
that we need to understand that earth's
climate is a chaotic system so let's
take for example one of these scenarios
the SSP um 245 and we run one climate
model and then we take the average of
the temperature that the climate model
predicts we average that over every year
and
a we average that over every year and um
over over the full globe and that gives
us the global temperature change so here
you can see the global temperature
change uh might be might be 2.5
degrees um and um now what you can see
though are these Wiggles in here and
these Wiggles are interannual
oscillation things like elino mjo um
these are unpredictable they're chaotic
um so if in fact if we run the model
again here we run it five times more in
black and you can see every time these
are at completely different locations so
climate emulation climate modeling
becomes a a a statistical problem where
it's more important to think about the
means and the standard deviations rather
than the exact trajectory so if we run
this 50 times then we can really see
very nicely this mean temperature uh
Trend increasing and we can even see
things like uh this this this like here
that was a volcano eruption that put out
a lot of sulfur dioxide so 50
realization uh the more realizations the
better we can understand the climate
mean so now we want to think about how
can we approximate this data with a
machine learning model so that we can
for example train the model on three of
these scenarios and then validate it on
the fourth one in the middle and then
test it on sort of all scenarios in
between that one could
imagine so for that in machine learning
often the first way is to create a what
we call a benchmark which gives us a
standardized data set and metrics where
scientists agree on uh so that if one
method is better on the metrics that are
in this Benchmark then that means it is
a better method so one of those
benchmarks exists it's called the
climate bench version um 1.0 and in this
case uh they have again these five
emission Pathways they ran one climate
model called the nor esm model three
times per emission pathway and then the
they were only able to run it three
times and we will find out later why
that was an issue um and then the the
target of the machine learning model is
to predict the assemble mean
particularly the Machine model is tasked
given maps of black carbon and maps of
uh surfur dioxide and Global cumulative
CO2 emissions and methane emissions um
of let's say the year
2050 the target then becomes given these
four input uh data points to predict the
temperature change annually averaged
over the year
2050 and currently deep learning methods
are being cited as the best models on
the stand Benchmark so I think there's a
lot of excitement uh we need bigger
machine learning models um to be better
but in in in our work we took maybe one
two three steps back and said what if we
do this with linear regression so we fit
one linear regression model that is the
easiest possible it just takes
cumulative CO2 emission as input
ignoring methane uh black carbon and
sulfur dioxide and predicting what is
the global temperature that's that's two
parameters that we're fitting there and
then from the global temperature we fit
one um one linear regression model per
grid cell to focus the local temperature
given the global temperature and in fact
now if we have um the full table sort of
across climate variables and then across
models we can see that the best model so
far which is we call it a foundation
model that has 100 million parameters
and has similar technology what's behind
an llm that you can use so their model
had some score some error and then the
linear regression model had actually
lower score had a better score on
surface temperature precipitation and on
precipitation so we were quite shocked
by that why would this linear regression
model be better than the 100 million
parameter model for for these variables
you want to find that out why would it
be so good and actually and there we
realized well we realized that it is
already for a long time known that um
cumulative CO2 has a linear relationship
with the global temperature increase
which is kind of ironic you ran these
like incredibly complex Earth system
models uh into the future but what comes
out is a linear relationship with global
cumulative CO2 and Global temperature
but even more more than that actually
the local temperature change also is a
linear function of the global
temperature change so that is cool and
the linear regression model was able to
exploit that um to do these relatively
pretty good predictions but in
precipitation it was more complex the
precip the linear agression model also
was pretty good for precipitation but
the relationship of global surface
temperature with respect to local
precipitation had much more much more
complex much more noise in it so why
would this also be better and here the
story is because it was only three
realizations in the Benchmark so for
example here we plot the blue line is
the is the precipitation change in
southern Central America as modeled if
you just average over three realizations
and we realize that's too much noise no
model can sort of see the trend there
except for the linear regression model
uh that just says okay the trend sort of
goes slightly down um but the Deep
learning model would overfit on these
very strong Wiggles and try to forecast
the exact trajectory even though that
was not possible due to the chaotic
system but if we then sort of repeat
this Benchmark practice with 50 emble
members H then we can see that local
Trends are more um more visible in the
data can be better
learned um so you can see this also here
but I'm not going to go into that for
that um I'll point you to a discussion
with me or reading the paper uh the
takeaway is linear regression could
outperform this large scale deep
learning model uh on the standard
Benchmark in the
community which pointed out that linear
regression works really well for
temperature but for precipitation uh we
had to update the Benchmark because
there was too much noise in the
Benchmark
targets and addressing this noise was
really necessary so that now we have a
more robust assessment on how can we
make progress in climate emulation
techniques and we are on the on on the
path of taking this linear method for
surface temperature integrating it into
on roads so that people can play with it
explore the local temperature change um
but also in the context of this
presentation we are on the look now for
more complex climate variables if you
have a climate variable that you in
particular are very interested in uh
then I'd be happy to talk about how to
emulate that thank you very much
[Applause]
thank you so much beorn um as I said you
know what I love about that project is
they're taking some really complicated
things and uh thinking about how to make
them more accessible and now you know
the question is for many people like you
what would you do with that information
that typically was only accessible to
you know government policy makers or
academics uh you know kind of turns over
a whole new Leaf so um last but not
least in this session we have Dr Danica
McDonald who's a um mcsc impact fellow
in our transportation area and she's
going to talk about some work that she's
doing uh related to trucking
decarbonization that was very much
motivated by uh the challenges of mcsc
members and she connected their needs
with a lot of expertise that's going on
here at MIT and of course a lot of her
own skills and capabilities as well so
Danica please come on up
everyone now that you've seen the whole
presentation um so I'm I'm going to be
talking about a geospatial tool that
we've been developing here at the mcsc
to support uh Trucking Fleet
decarbonization
sorry um okay so I'm going to start by
just quickly uh motivating why we're
focusing this tool on uh the TR Trucking
sector so even though um this uh this
even though trucks only make up about 5%
of on-road vehicles they produce just
under a quarter of all greenhouse gas
emissions in the
US um so the trucking industry itself is
under um very um increasing regulatory
pressure to um decarbonize its
operations and it's um very difficult
for Fleet owners to actually make this
transition for a few reasons first the
industry operates under very tight
profit margins and this can make it
really difficult um for Fleet owners to
make these high-risk Investments that
are needed um to decarbonize their
fleets um another thing is that these
fleets tend to operate on very strict
delivery schedules and that makes it
very difficult um to make any um
significant changes that would
um that would drastically modify how the
fleet operates and then lastly a lot of
these fleets are very reliant on um
energy dense fuels like diesel to carry
these superheavy payloads over very long
distances um so there's a lot of
different um energy carriers that are
emerging that have potential to help the
trucking industry reduce its emissions
and um different carriers seem to be um
better Suited for different sort of
segments of the industry there's also a
lot of different public data sets out
there that um can support fleets in
navigating this transition to
alternative energy carriers so the goal
of this tool is to compile all of this
data into one um interactive tool that
can um support fleets in navigating
this so I'm just going to start by
actually demoing the tool so you can get
a sense of what it looks like um so it
lives on the mcc's data Hub website and
from there you can go into the tool and
um bring up different data layers so
this one is a total cost of truck
ownership and you can change details
like uh looking at the cost premium or
changing like um aspects of how the
truck actually
operates um and then you can also
overlay different infrastructure layers
like Highway flows or um hydrogen
electrolyzers to customize um the
transition
assessment so the development of this
tool actually ended up following a
pretty regular cycle between stakeholder
engagement and um and focus development
so a lot as as jerem mentioned a lot of
the early motivation for this tool
actually came from a study group that
the mcsc hosted last June where
um a lot of the feedback emphasized a
need for um dedicated tools to be able
to support fleets in um understanding
how like when where and how to um to
make these early Investments for Fleet
transition so over the next few months I
started prototyping this tool initially
in qgis and then shifting over to a
custom open source framework based on
open layers
and then uh late last year
oops sorry and then late last year um I
uh engaged different stakeholders across
the trucking industry both mcsc partner
companies and um and non non-mcc members
to uh demo the tool and ask their for
their feedback on how we could um
improve this tool and make it more uh
relevant to their actual decision-making
process and um what this feedback
actually highlighted was that we needed
to go back and and develop some clear
case studies to demonstrate to users how
they could actually work with this tool
and um use it to support um their
decision- making so um over the next few
months I worked with an undergraduate
researcher to develop these case studies
and shared them as blog posts and videos
um and then uh this past June we shared
these case studies with uh six mcsc
partner companies at an outcome workshop
and what the um feedback from this
outcome Workshop highlighted was
actually a lot of um alignment around
two major points the first is that users
need to be able to explore the data
that's actually underlying these these
features that they're looking at on the
tool and the second is that um users
need to be able to um overlay their own
own private data on top of all these
public layers so that they can do a more
customized assessment that's relevant to
their Fleet and their
operations so over the summer we've
implemented a click feature that allows
users to do this exploration into the
underlying data and I'm also working
with a wonderful programmer to um allow
users to securely upload their private
data to the mcc's data Hub website so
that they can then do this overlay and
um and see their own data on on the
tool um so moving ahead uh in starting
early next year my goal is to then go
back to um demonstrating this tool to
stakeholders and hopefully identifying
some Partners who are interested in
piloting the tool for their own
transition
assessment um so I also want to
highlight some of the ways that we've
been able to engage other MIT
researchers in the process of developing
this tool um so the total cost of
ownership layer that I showed in the
demo was actually adopted from a um an
electrified Trucking model that was
developed by Karana and cheyen deep two
grad students in Prof Bill greens uh
chemical engineering group so earlier
this year I worked with uh these grad
students to adapt their model over um to
the to Pilot data from the Tesla semi
and then um modify it so that it could
um work within within the
tool we've also been super fortunate to
have some really um incredible
contributions to the tool from
undergraduate researchers through mit's
year op program um so Micah our first um
student working on this project
developed a novel algorithm to be able
to um compare transition potential
between different uh Trucking
corridors and then Helena uh worked with
us to develop these case studies to
demonstrate to different stakeholders
how they could engage with the tool and
um and use it for their transition
planning and then Brooke worked with us
over the summer to implement this uh
click feature that allows users to dig
into um data underlying these geospatial
layers um so the last thing I want to
just talk a bit about is um the emphasis
that we placed on transparency and
adaptability throughout the tools
development so the goal um here is
basically just to make the tool as
widely usable as possible so all of the
source code that underlies the tool is
um hosted on public GitHub repositories
the data that the tool pulls from is uh
is published on zenodo so anyone can
download it and adapt it for their own
uh research and we've also made it so
that that's super duper easy for anyone
to download the tool onto their own
computer and bring it up and um develop
with it and make changes so I guess like
looking ahead My ultimate goal for this
tool is really that as user start to
Pilot it and um use it for their own
decision- making that we can start to
develop a sustaining community of users
who are um proposing changes and
implementing new features to support
their own transition assessment so
that's that's all for me
[Applause]
thanks thank you so much Danica so I
think the theme um that we saw across
all three of these is that there's a lot
of great work that's happening here at
uh MIT but really you know our goal here
is to try to have impact right whether
that's moving the needle on climate or
anything else that we do and that's
where we really benefit from
interactions with industry to help us
figure fure out how do we pilot these
things to learn from your experiences
using them uh and then also something
that industry is very good at scaling
things uh and so how do you take many of
things that we're doing help to scale
them and so we'll be glad to do that
with you um uh you can get in touch with
me and or directly with any of our post
talks who shared work here um and we'll
be glad to work with you on that so
thank you so much
[Applause]