Someone's
here. Yeah.
Experienc
Yes.
We started at 5. I know you have famous,
right? I quarter costume. So, I've got
my tea time.
Van's a legend.
every
classroom time and it's all always best.
different technology.
I wonder who that is.
Wonder if there's any connection.
[Music]
One more minute.
Just for a second,
[Music]
I'm
not sharing.
Yeah. Yeah.
I know.
Stop.
We should probably get started. So,
thanks to all of you for being here.
Those of you who are on Zoom, thank you
also for being here. It's very exciting
for me to get to hear what you, the grad
students here, are working on. I'm
hoping I will understand some words of
it. And our first speaker is Angus,
who's going to talk about materials for
fusion energy and the Kevlab. Thank you.
Um, so I'm the first speaker, so I get
uh to introduce all of the fusion stuff
to you uh this fusion energy week. Um,
first things first, I'm just going to go
over what fusion is, what are our
requirements, and then a little bit
about what we do in the lab. Um so first
of all uh this is a slice of the EA TOK
uh which is like the next big nuclear
fusion device in south of France. Uh
it's about 6 m in major radius which is
the uh
distance from the center of the plasma
over to the to the center of the um of
the device. So it's kind of like this
doughut shaped device and you're
squishing your plasma inside the donut.
So this is a cross-section of that
doughut. slicing into it and seeing um
our plasma which is our main way of
creating fusion damage.
Um the plasma itself is made up of
hydrogen. So dutaterium and tritium
which are heavy heavy hydrogen we smash
them together uh and hope that they
stick together and get our energy out.
You want to do this you got to have all
this stuff around it to make it not just
fly out. Right? you've got lots of
positively charged stuff in there and
you're trying to squish it and make them
go together but they really don't want
to go together uh because light charges
recover. So around that we've got a lot
uh a lot of plasma facing components
which experience a lot of heat. Uh the
core itself is like ultra high
temperatures 100 million Celsius. Um and
the plasma facing components themselves
don't get that hot because nothing
nothing can get that hot. Uh but they
are at thousands of Celsius. And then
around those plasma facing components,
you got to have something to hold it up
and keep the vacuum uh that's required
for this at vacuum level. So, we've got
a vacuum vessel and then also we've got
some magnets around the outside uh that
sort of squish everything together and
make our plasma behave the way we want
it to. And that's a very sort of rushed
overview, but the point I'm trying to
make here is that everything in there is
made up of a lot of materials. Uh so
we've got uh superconductors and the
magnets which themselves are like these
complex layered uh structures. Uh these
superconducting tapes. uh the vacuum
vessel itself is made up of many things
that are all welded together. Uh the
plum facing components has a lot of uh
cooling and a lot of candidate materials
that could be there. All of which have
to be evaluated and then that's not even
talking about uh cooling or breeding of
fuel uh which in itself is a is a huge
challenge we're working on here. Um
there's a lot of stuff and they all have
to survive what is created by by the
plasma itself. When we do fusion, we get
a lot of energy. Hooray. And we also get
a lot of radiation, which is both our
best friend and worst enemy. Radiation
is how we get out energy out. But it
also does a lot of damage to our
materials as well. So that's kind of me
singing for my supper. Why do we
actually care about radiation material
science and what we do in our lab? We
need to know how how our device is going
to behave. So what do they do? What do
these what do these things do uh in the
material? Uh, for example, a neutron can
come in, hit our nice, in this case, uh,
crystalline material.
All of our hard work forging, melting,
heat treating. We spent so much effort,
uh, making this nice omelette. And then
the neutron comes in and turns it into
scrambled egg. Um, so it's just it comes
in, it can knock atoms around, it can
transmute atoms. Where the neutron is
absorbed, it turns into something else.
Uh, which has a lot of knock-on effects.
But there's a lot of extra stuff that
can happen inside a material uh that can
degrade it.
Secondly, in the plasma facing
components, we've also got this idea of
uh erosion. So something extremely hot
and extremely uh we use plasma elsewhere
in industry to erode materials and
redeposit them elsewhere. You know, like
that's how we do all of our
semiconductor manufacturing. You just
fire plasma or something and let it
sputter away. So we don't want that to
happen but it wants to happen very much.
Um so what we do is what can happen is
the plasma itself which is typically
hydrogen or helium. Helium is the the
waste uh from the fing process. Uh
helium can go into the material and at
high temperatures it can form these
bubbles uh in this case in tungsten
which is one of the candida materials
for the plasm facing components and it
can form these like bubbles which can
then grow and then rupture and they make
this fuzzy
stuff on the surface. Um which is not
great because you don't want little bits
to break off and start whizzing around
inside your plasma. That will waste a
lot of energy.
Um so what does this actually do?
radiation damage stuff. This is just
some examples of kind of like how bad
how bad could it be. Um
you can get why do we like metals in in
structural materials? Because they can
flex a little bit and not break. Um but
in radio radioactive environments your
metals can go from being very ductile in
this case. So here they can this is a
plot of energy to energy to breakage and
temperature. So for a normal material it
can absorb a lot of energy at room
temperature.
uh and not break. Whereas if you irdiate
this, this has just been taken into a
vision reactor for some amount of time.
If you radiate these, you can start to
have this what's called a hell fracture,
brittle fracture rather than ductile
fracture. So when you when something
starts to break, you want it to like
bend a little bit. You don't want it to
just snap. So big degradation there. You
can also get swelling, which is a bit
more intuitive. Uh your materials can
grow as little gaps inside them uh
coalesce. you and if you've made things
to a certain tolerance which they
definitely will be in these in these
fusion devices then this can just
completely ruin that you get a loss of
thermal properties as uh like I was
showing in the previous slide your
crystine structure gets all messed up
and your electrons which generally carry
all of your heat and electricity in some
cases uh it can't flow as well so you
can get a loss of thermal properties in
this case you've got neutron dose on the
x axis here and thermal conductivity on
the y axis so you can it drops by a
factor of 4 plus over over some
exposure. So you want to know what's
going to happen here. Um
how do we actually figure that out? So
in our lab uh we have a look at various
uh various material properties. I'll
just go kind of through the various beam
lines uh in the lab which is an
accelerator lab. So at the back here
we've got the accelerator itself. Uh
this is the thing that makes our ions
and we can hit our materials with our
ions and just see see what happens. Uh
on the left we have a corrosion beam
line. I was mentioning coolant and fuel
breathing earlier. Um those things if
you have something that's effectively if
you imagine what corrosion is, it's your
material comes in it interacts with the
surface and then it goes away and
carries some material away with it.
Perhaps if you have lots of radiation
kind of like moving things around, it's
just it's effectively like stirring your
uh stirring your cup of tea with a with
a spoonful of sugar in it. It just helps
that process along or you know you can
you can grasp that it helps things
along. So we need to assess how that's
happening.
One of the backbones of the modern
design is the superconductor. We don't
really know how radiation affects that
very well and if that's like your most
expensive critical showstopper, you kind
of want to know how that's going to go.
Um, so we have a beam line that looks at
how radiation affects those uh those
materials. Uh, and we also have this uh
we also have this plasma device that can
do simultaneous radiation and plasma
exposure at the same time for pl for
plasma facing components to evaluate
them. And on the right, we also have
some a laser technique that we can use
to evaluate things as they're being
damaged at the same time. Go over that.
Um,
okay. So, the corrosion stuff, we have
this little cell. You've got uh liquid
metal on one side of this foil, which is
this target uh device. So, there's a
little foil of metal. We've got liquid
metal in this case on one side of the
foil and high vacuum on the other. We're
shooting the radiation through seeing
what happens in a certain irradiated
region versus unradiated. And I was uh
I completely lost my train of thought.
Sorry.
Oh yes. Yes. I was saying earlier that
uh you can effectively speed up this
this process of uh of corrosion with
radiation but in this case it's
counterintuitive because what we saw was
in fact the corrosion was slowed down by
radiation. So this is a paper that was
published off of that um and in the
center you can see where we have
radiation there's actually uh less
corrosion that happens. Uh so we're
still finding these like
counterintuitive effects that you can
that you can observe when you try and
interact with this radiation stuff and
the corrosion stuff at the same time. Um
I have a few more slides that go over
kind of like the other beam lines, but I
think in interest of time I will simply
skip to the end and ask for questions
before uh before I head off. So we've
got some laser stuff. Uh if you have
questions on any of those other beam
lines, I'll be happy to take them now.
Thank you very much.
[Applause]
Any questions in here or in the Zoom
room? We've got about a minute at most.
Is the reduction in corrosion with the
radiation? Is there a mechanism that's
understood at this point or is it still
mystery? Uh they proposed that in the
paper they proposed that uh a lot of the
corrosion happens along grain
boundaries. So your corrosive material
um your material is made up of many
grains and between those grains it's
kind of like the material is not so well
held because it's kind of just like this
chaotic structure of atoms and so
corrosion tends to happen more
efficiently there and so a region around
that grain boundary is depleted in for
in this case chromium it was taking it
was leeching chromium out of the
material um and the idea was that what
what's happening with and uh process of
diffusion in grains is slow to the grain
boundary compared to the process of
diffusion within the grain boundary into
the liquid method. The idea was that
they proposed was um with this kind of
like churning effect from radiation that
enhanced the diffusion within the grains
to the grain boundaries. So it kind of
pumped this uh it pumped it full of the
things that it lacked in this case the
chromium and kind of allowed it to
survive a lot longer. Uh whereas before
that was just getting depleted and then
eroded.
Any more questions?
Mostly concerned about getting you out
of here in time. If not, let's thank
Angus again. I was about to call you
Sean and
Sean is next up. I'm not going crazy.
All right.
I can plug in. Yes.
On that screen.
Have a little bit of extra time because
one person cancelled. So, we should be
fine. Have to leave. He just had to
leave. Hey, so now we have Sean Mackey
who's going to be talking about studying
burning plasmas with fancy science.
Hi, I'm Sean. Uh, so I'll be telling you
a little bit about studying burning
plasmas with neutron emission
spectrometry. So, first of all, just a
little bit about, uh,
let me just get rid of some of the stuff
on my screen so you can see it.
Uh, so fusion reactions produce
energetic nuclear particles. Um, dutium
and tridium are isotopes of hydrogen
with extra neutrons and it's the most
reactive mix of fusion fuel we have. Um
when dutaterium and tridium react
together it emits an alpha particle and
a neutron. Uh the energy of that's
stored in the nuclear bonds within the
dutium and tridium is released in the
form of kinetic energy in these
products. And um you know since it's a
two-body kinematic reaction the amount
of energy that goes to the neutron and
the alpha particle is um a discrete
quantity. every time you get 14 me of
energy to the neutron and three and a
half me of energy to the alpha particle.
Now in a magnetic fusion situation you
have a strong magnetic field which
confine the alpha particle because it
has a net positive charge. Uh but the
neutron is uncharged and so it escapes
carrying with it about 80% of the um
energy liberated from the nuclear
reaction.
Right.
So the goal of any sort of fusion
reactor and research into fusion is to
get more power out than we put into the
plasma. Um and so the key metric that we
use to quantify this is called the gain
factor. Uh we call it Q. It's defined to
be equal to the ratio of the power out
minus the power in. So the net power
produced divided by the power that you
put into it. Um and so if you assume
that you're in a steady state thermal
equilibrium, um this reduces to the
fusion power divided by the heating
power. Um if Q is greater than one, that
means more energy was produced than you
consumed to actually heat up and produce
the plasma. And the point of this plot
on the right is just to show that, you
know, through the years, we've made a
lot of progress towards actually
achieving this goal. Um on this plot in
the top right hand corner, that's Q
greater than one. And you can see uh all
these dots and shapes represent previous
fusion experiments and the sort of trend
towards high gain uh regimes. And so now
after you know six decades of research
on the topic, we're basically right on
the brink of energy break even. And the
National Ignition Facility, if you saw
Maria's talk on Monday, um they've
actually already achieved this. And so
we know that it's possible to get more
energy out than in um from these types
of uh reactors. So we just need to make
it sort of commercially relevant or
economically relevant.
And so okay, if our goal is to make Q
greater than one, how do we actually
know if we've achieved that goal? We
need to somehow measure the energy or
the power gain of the reactor. And so
the denominator of that expression, the
input power, that's pretty easy to
measure. You could just call up the
electrical company and say, "Hey, how
much uh power did I use to heat up my
plasma?" And they'll say, "Oh, you know,
you used a megawatt or whatever." The
output power is a little more tricky. Um
and so the most reliable method that we
have to actually measure how much fusion
is going on, the power liberated from
fusion is to count neutrons. Since each
dutium tridium fusion reaction makes one
neutron, uh the fusion power will be
proportional to the neutron emission
rate. And so if you can count your
neutrons, you can infer what the fusion
power was. My research is all about
developing advanced neutron detection
methods for the spark tok. You may be
asking, well, what the heck is spark? If
you missed Alex's lovely talk on Monday,
um Spark is a demonstration device um
designed to generate net magnetic fusion
energy. Um it's being built by a PSFC
spinout company called Commonwolf Fusion
Systems. They're building this reactor
out in Devons. Um on the right I have a
picture of the Spark facility and then
in the pink box is the interior of the
Tokome Hall. Um you can see a picture of
what Spark will look like printed on the
back wall of that room. And then on the
left wall uh you can see the neutron
camera slit which is that all vertical
slit and a number of other diagnostic
access holes through the primary shield
wall. Um so spark is designed using high
temperature superconductors uh which
like Angus mentioned is like sort of the
key break technological breakthrough
that's enabling um fusion to really sort
of take the next step. Uh these magnets
are more powerful than previous
generations of magnets and they confine
the plasma a lot more strongly. So
you're able to achieve higher temp
temperatures and densities um without
you know sort of having to put in a lot
more power to maintain those uh
densities and temperatures. And one of
the key parts of Spark's mission of
proving that, you know, net energy is
possible with magnetic fusion is having
a really robust set of neutron
diagnostics and neutron measurement
techniques.
In addition to just telling you about
how much fusion is going on, neutrons
also carry a lot of information about
the plasma. Um so if you can make a
nicely resolved measurement of the
neutron energy spectrum you can also
diagnose plasma par parameters such as
the fuel ion temperature the bulk plasma
density the ratio of fuel ions so
dutaterium to tridium uh if it's not
50/50
um and also sort of more subtle effects
like the heating power coupling or you
know more sort of uh subtle things
beyond that as well and on the right
here I just have a plot showing how the
thermonucle Lear neutron spectrum
changes as a function of fuel
temperature. So in blue you can see
relatively low temperature plasma four
kevs the units that we use. Um it's sort
of low amplitude and skinny and as you
increase the temperature the amplitude
goes up there's more fusion going on but
also the distribution gets wider because
um the thermal broadening of the neutron
emissions uh gets increases with
temperature and that broadening actually
increases as the square root of
temperature. So if you can measure your
neutron spectrum and measure how broad
it is, you have a measure of the ion
temperature, which is really useful uh
for assessing how well your plasma is
actually heating up and things like
that.
Um so okay, this thing goes to 11. Spark
is designed to reach Q of 11. So while Q
greater than one is a big milestone to
be economically viable, you really need
Q to be much larger than one because you
need to take into account all the
inefficiency of efficiencies of the
plant. And so if we really are reaching
Q of 11, that would be really great
because it would demonstrate that okay,
this reactor concept, it's actually
scalable to economically viable levels.
Um, but from a scientific perspective,
once we hit Q of five, the majority of
the plasma's heating is actually coming
from the fusion reactions itself. And so
this state where most of the heating is
coming from the fusion itself is called
the burning plasma state. Um, and it's a
new regime of plasma physics that hasn't
been studied experimentally. And so
that's what I'm really excited to work
on. And so you can probe a lot of the
interesting novel physics of the burning
plasma regime using neutron
spectrometry. Um, and so there's a
couple of ways to see this. Like first
of all, the neutron spectrum is in a
sense the twin of the alpha birth uh
alpha particle birth spectrum because
they're both being born from the same
reactions. The spectrum of neutrons is
intimately related to the spectrum of
alphas before they have a chance to slow
down in the plasma. So that's an
important input to modeling what's going
on in the plasma. Also, nuclear
scattering becomes really important at
these high uh gain regimes and that
manifests itself in the neutron spectrum
as a high energy tail. And so if you can
measure that high energy neutron
spectrum, you know something about how
the fusion products are actually slowing
down and heating the plasma. And so
that's a useful input as well. And so
I've spent a lot of my uh time here at
MIT developing what's called the a
magnetic proton recoil spectrometer. And
so that's what I'm showing on the bottom
right here is a schematic of that
diagnostic. Um it's basically a giant
proton beam line. And you generate the
protons by having neutrons scatter them
out of a plastic foil. They go through a
big magnet system and get sorted and
focused based on their energy and you
detect them in a detector array. And so
you have this position resolved
measurement of the protons which is uh
in turn related to the energy spectrum
of the neutrons.
Um
yeah so in summary um neutron
measurements are critical to validating
fusion reactor performance. The neutron
energy spectrum encodes a lot of useful
diagnostic information about the plasma
including the ion temperature, the fuel
composition and uh information about the
heating and the burning plasma regime is
an unexplored scientific territory and
neutron spectrometry gives us a way to
empirically map the terrain of this new
regime. And then you know this is just a
picture of me and the rest of the
neutron diagnostics team for Spark
standing in front of the neutron camera
slit which is where we're going to put a
lot of our diagnostics.
Happy to take any questions.
We have time for a question or two if we
have any.
So I was wondering about the so you
mentioned about the the efficiency as uh
comparing the amount of power you put in
with the power which is stored inside
and I'm wondering about the physics of
how this power is going to be converted
in a useful way into let's say
electricity and so on. Few words. So, in
a real fusion reactor, um, you're not
just looking at these neutrons as a
diagnostic tool, but they're since
they're carrying out 80% of the energy
from the nuclear reactions. If you could
thermalize those neutrons, you could
drive a thermal cycle. And so, the
leading idea is that you would have some
sort of neutron moderator to catch all
these energetic neutrons, slow them
down, and heat up that moderator, and
then you can boil water with it and turn
a turbine. Thank you.
Any other questions that we're squeezing
in?
If not, let's give Sean a hand again and
Abby.
When Abby gets up here, I will tell you
what she's talking about.
I should have asked for titles before.
You're a USB.
Just get rid of this.
All right. So, Aby's going to be talking
to us about exploring runaway electron
impacts in Spark, which we just learned
about. All right. Hi. My name is Abby.
I'm a grad student here, and I'm going
to be talking just like Lauren just
said, I'm going to be talking about
exploring runaway electron impacts in
Spark. And I'll define what those are in
just a minute. So,
um, like everyone else has been talking
about, I'm also still talking about
tokamax. And one way that I like to
think about tokamax is that tokamax are
kind of like trying to contain jello-
with rubber bands. So, what we're doing
here is we're containing a plasma with
magnetic fields. And so, you've got
magnetic fields that wind around the
tokamac in both the tooidal direction
and the poloidal direction. And these
contain your plasma. And these tokam the
reason that we're all talking about
tokamax is because tokamax have been the
best at confining plasmas so far. They
very have very better confinement than
any other fusion device that we've been
able to build so far. However, they are
quite unstable just like if you had
jello- in the middle of a bunch of
rubber bands. And so if something
happens, if it goes slightly off, you
can have sudden losses of your plasma.
So you can have your plasma suddenly be
lost from the device, hit the wall, and
it can lose a lot of its energy very
fast. So this is known as disruption,
and these are bad for business. If
you're trying to make uh fusion energy
and make money off of that, it's very
bad if you lose your plasma because you
lose your fusion and you're no longer
producing energy.
Um, and one other thing that can happen
during disruptions is you can get beams
of relativistic electrons. So in a
tokamac when it's operating in its nice
steady state it contains mega amps of
plasma current which is a lot of current
and so when your plasma gets unstable
you can transfer this current into uh
these relativistic electrons um and
these are known as runaway electrons
because they're in essence running away
and so you've got this beam of electrons
spinning around and around and around in
your tokamac and then it has to go
somewhere and if you're hearing this and
you're thinking oh a beam of very high
energy electrons. That sounds like sort
of familiar to me. Um, you would be
correct because this is the same thing
as lightning. So, you can think of a
beam of runaway electrons as sort of a
beam of lightning in your tokamac that's
going around and around and around until
it has to go somewhere. So, when this
beam of relativistic electrons goes
somewhere, you can get damage. So, what
I've got here is I've got a video from
the Alcatore CMO tokamac, which was a
tokamac that was here on campus at MIT.
And you can see in this video, it's
pretty boring. The plasma is
transparent. So nothing is really
happening and then it starts to get a
little crazy and then boom, you've got a
beam of runaway electrons which hits the
wall and causes sparks. So it's melting
the wall because it went unstable and it
hit the wall and then you got some
melting, some sparks. Very exciting but
also very bad.
And this is not unique to Alcatore Sean.
We've seen this across several
experiments across the world. So we've
seen wall melting, metal vaporization,
and even a magnet quench. And if you
punch your magnets, your tomax stops
working. Um, so we've seen this across
several experiments. And here I've got
just sort of a fun collage of damage
that's been caused by runaway electrons.
So the CMOD damage up in the top right
corner. And then also Jet, which is a
tokamac um over in the UK. Texor and
West are two other examples of tokamax
that have had runaway electron beams hit
something and cause some melting. So
this can be bad for tokamax that we've
seen in the past. But the question is
what does this look like for power
plant-l like devices? So when we go to
the future and we're try to actually
make power and then make money from our
tokamax, how does this scale to that? Um
and the answer uh and before I talk
about what the answer to that is, I want
to just talk about Spark really quick.
Um Sean already did a great job of
introducing it. So spark will be the
first tokamac to achieve Q greater than
one. So more fusion power power power
than the power you're putting into your
tokamac. But what this means for spark
in comparison to other tokamacs that
have previously been run is that spark
will have a higher magnetic field, a
higher plasma current, higher
temperatures, which means lots of stored
energy in your plasma. And so for the
disruptions, this means lots of energy
that then has to leave or lots of energy
that can be transferred to runaway
electrons. So if we look at this more
quantitatively
um we can see that this damage could be
worse in spark because spark has so much
stored energy. So the damage that a
runaway electron beam can cause is
largely related to both the energy of
the beam. If you have a very high energy
beam, you can melt a lot of material. Um
but it also depends on how large of an
area that that beam strikes. So if you
hit a very small area, you deposit a lot
of energy into that area and you're
going to really melt a good section of
that. However, you you spread out that
energy over a wider area, maybe you
won't hit a melt threshold, and maybe
you'll just cause the area to heat up,
but it won't quite hit melting. So, this
uh
there is a threshold for which melting
occurs, and that threshold is around 3
to 5 mega per meter squared um for
tungsten, which is going to be the first
wall material in spark. And the energy
that a runaway electron beam has is
proportional to the current squared. And
so this is why when we look forward to
spark which will have a plasma current
of 8.7 megga this starts to get quite
concerning because spark will have the
highest plasma current of any device so
far. Um that means that we could see
really high energy u runaway electron
beams up to tens of megajles which is
very very powerful. And so what I've
done here is I've scoped um what
potential runaway electron impacts could
look like. So I've got um I've scoped
from zero to 8.7 mega of runaway
electron current. And I've also scoped
what the average energy could look like.
And then on the graph, I've put the
wetted area for which the beam exceeds
that melt threshold. So if you look at
this simulated spark case um which was
simulated with a code called dream that
runs um that has about five megaamps of
current and an average energy of about
eight uh me. And you can see that this
lies on the 10 meters squared contour.
So that means that this simulated case
could melt 10 m squared of wall area
which is a very large section of wall.
So we got to hope that that does not
happen because that would be quite bad
for Spark operations.
So what are we going to do about this is
the question.
Spark will have some mitigation
techniques to mitigate runaway electron
beams and mitigate damage. So one thing
is massive gas injection. So if you um
inject some massive gas into your
plasma, your plasma radiates away its
energy. And this means that the energy
of your plasma gets more uniformly um
radiated into the walls rather than a
runaway electron beam which can hit a
very small area and deposit a lot of
energy onto a smaller area. So the goal
is to spread out where the energy goes
onto your walls. The other thing that
will happen uh that Spark will have is a
runaway electron mitigation coil, which
is this image that I put here. Um, and
so what this does is it sort of has a
funky shape. And when you have a
disruption with a runaway electron beam,
what the runaway electron mitigation
coil does is it introduces perturbations
to your magnetic field. It messes with
your nice ordered magnetic field, making
it a bit chaotic. And so this means that
your runaway electrons are just
deconfined. So they just exit before
they have the chance to uh cause a very
large coherent beam of runaway electrons
that can then cause damage. Um and so we
have some mitigation techniques but what
what else we are doing is modeling. So
that's where I come in. Um so the goal
is of my modeling is to determine how
bad different runaway electron scenarios
will be and then to determine how we can
avoid those scenarios with our
mitigation techniques. If we know how
bad certain things we can be uh we can
avoid that and we can make sure that our
machine is okay and operates in a safe
um in a safe sense.
So to conclude, tokamax can get
lightning like beams of electrons in
during disruptions and these electrons
can damage the walls which you can see
over here in this collage again and this
damage might get worse in future
devices. So we need to understand this
damage so we can mitigate it better. So
hopefully Sprite will not look like
this. So thank you.
[Applause]
Uh questions from the audience and if
not we'll take the one from the chat.
First, do any of you have a question?
You mentioned gas injection as a way to
mitigate runaway electrons, but that
seems to run counterintuitive to uh the
whole standard of fusion where you want
to try to have as much fusion power as
you can in the core. Um, is there like a
trade-off here? And how big is the
trade-off? So the massive gas injection
is a thing that you do when you're
already operating when basically when
you're already operating in a space that
is going towards a disruption, you do
the massive gas induction to mitigate
the effects of the disruption. So you
wouldn't want to have a nicely
performing plasma that then you then uh
put a lot of massive gas into because
then you just radiate away your power.
Um, so it's when your plasma is
performing badly, that's when you throw
in the massive gas to get it to get rid
of its energy in the safest way it can.
Any other questions from in the room?
We have a question here which is asking
the re beams are expressed using energy
terms versus using power terms. Is this
is this because the damage is better
thought of as an impact like an
instantaneous projectile versus energy
deposited over time? Yeah, this is a
this is a really good question. So the
time scale of runaway electron impacts
tends to be quite small. I think on the
order of milliseconds to sometimes even
can be even shorter than that. And so
that's why we think of it in terms of
energy rather than power because it's
basically you can kind of think of it
like an instantaneous thing when the
beam hits the wall.
All right. Well, maybe for the sake of
time we'll move on to the next speaker,
but let's thank Abby again.
[Applause]
We'll take about 30 seconds to
transition as we do
here.
Try
it. Take it. Link is also
Can you I didn't see it. No, you're
fine. Super cool.
Like just like Did you join the Zoom
room? Uh, I should be in the zoom room.
Make sure for later.
Joseph is going to be talking to us in a
second about superconducting diodes for
quantum computing. And we are just
getting this. You got that working.
So,
hello. So, uh, I'm Joseph. I'm going to
be talking about a slightly different
topic actually from plasmas and so on.
Very high energy physics. I just saw an
axis with mega. I'm going to be talking
about milliamps. So, uh the idea is that
we work with superconductors that are
very useful materials as you're going to
see especially at very low temperatures.
So, let me just uh get started and
motivate why we are doing what we are
doing. So you know that there is
recently this uh this very large
evolution in in quantum computers which
are working at at low temperatures and
you look at the at some of the latest
nowadays I think they already by 100 or
200 but you look at those quantum
computers which have like 50 cubits and
then they have a lot of cables around
and so on. You compare this with uh with
our usual uh desktop computers and you
see that uh there are almost no cables
laying around. everything is actually
integrated into circuits and so on. And
that happens because uh these quantum
computers they need to operate at very
small temperatures and it's actually
hard to have uh the logic that we are
used to operate at room temperature at
such low temperatures because it's very
difficult to cool down at down to those
very low temperatures. You can have
mills of cooling power at at those
temperatures. So you have to be very
economical with how you spend energy
there. Now, there are some computing
approaches which are actually able to do
these operations at 4.2 Kelvin, but
those actually need some DC power
delivery, which in practice implies that
you need to have tons of cables going
down and that's why you see all this uh
stuff. Our goal is to find a way to to
do this uh uh AC to DC conversion at at
these low temperatures so that all these
cables can be removed or just very
heavily reduced so that scaling can go
farther. That is how we want to do it.
And of course what we want to do there
is to to do that with what we call
superconducting diodes which are a
variant of semiconducting diode just as
a reminder. So semiconducting diode is a
is a system which is semiconductor
actually as the name says which uh has a
very asymmetric response to an applied
voltage. So when you apply a voltage
between its terminals if it's in the
forward direction you can get very high
current in the reverse direction you get
a very small current. That means that
the resistance in this direction is very
high and this res direction is very low.
Now this is very useful because it
allows for conversion of AC currents
into DC. But do you see also that there
this is a resistive system that means
yeah the slides are not changing on
Zoom. Oh really? Thank you for letting
me know.
Now it's Is it now working? Let's try.
Is it changing or something? Yeah, we're
seeing the speaker view. Um ah
Okay.
Sorry.
[Music]
Speaker view. Where was that?
Amazing. Now it should work.
Is it now working? Thank you so much for
letting me know. Sorry for that. So,
so coming from the uh from the
semiconduity
of the response. So you have this very
large asymmetry between positive and
negative voltage which allows for
converting AC currents into DC. But the
prime is a resistive so it dissipates
heat. So we need to look for an
alternative that can work at low
temperatures and that is what we call a
superconducting diode. As some of you
know superconductors are materials that
can can carry current without the
resistance. That means that you do not
have heat dissipations in that regime.
But you know everything has a limit and
superconductors have a limit which is
called critical current and that is how
much current they can carry without heat
dissipation. Now if we make that
critical current to be direction
dependent meaning that for positive uh
critical current when you apply a
positive current you need a lot of
current to to drive the system resistive
and when you apply a negative current
you need much less current. What is
going to happen is that you also have
this kind of non-reciprocal response
which is very asymmetric between
positive and negative voltage and now
that uh that may allow also for the AC
to DC power conversion at at low
temperatures but then you'd have a lot
of less power dissipation because in
this whole regime you're not dissipating
heat
and our goal is to actually make use of
these systems. However, first let me
just briefly explain you how we make
these superconducting diodes. What we do
is we actually make use of what is
called the masoner effect which is this
property of superconductors that they
repel magnetic fields. The idea is that
you apply a magnetic field to a
superconductor and it's going to repel
it by uh creating what is called a
masoner current inside. So here you have
a circulating current that is going to
oppose the flow of this magnetic field
inside. Now if we make a device which is
just an ultra thin stripe of a
superconductor, we apply a magnetic
field perpendicular to the plane. That
means that at the opposite edges we're
going to have opposite mason currents as
you can see here. Now since our s this
just the top view of the sample when you
apply a positive current meaning that
it's going up as this purple arrow shows
we have that at this edge we're having a
very high current but at this other edge
we're having much smaller current. If we
reverse the current direction then what
happens is that this edge is the one
that has more current. Now we are using
a type of superconductors which are
called type two where the edges are
actually the ones which limit the
critical current. And that actually
means that because we have made these
notches here. We have reduced the
critical current of this edge. And now
by controlling the direction of the
current, we can have a low critical
current in this direction and a high
critical current in this other
direction. However, this technique
requires a magnetic field to be applied
on the sample and we want to get rid of
that. So what we do is the following. We
just place a ferroagnet
uh on top of the superconductor and now
we have the stray field from the
ferroagnet which have opposite sign in
both edges but they actually result in
having a minor current that has the same
sign of both edges because the very edge
is what limits the critical current.
This allows you to have a diode even at
zero magnetic field that is useful
because it will not disturb other
superconducting components working next
to it. Now comes the part of converting
AC currents into DC. I mean we have all
gone to high school and we have all seen
what a diode bridge is. So the question
is how would that work when instead of
having semiconducting in diodes we
actually have superconducting diodes.
Now the rules of the game with
superconducting diode as I told you is
that the resistance is zero when the
applied current is very small. But then
if the applied current is either higher
positive than the than the critical
current in forward direction or lower in
negative than the applied current in
than the critical current in the reverse
direction then it's going to turn
resistive. Now what uh we can see just
simply what is going to happen to this
circuit. uh here the moment we apply a
positive current you can see here that
half of the half of the diodes will
become resistive and it's going to be
the ones where the current is opposing
the the arrow as defined here and what
you see now is that you apply a positive
voltage here and you eventually you get
a positive voltage here now the moment
that we reverse the the applied current
again this is uh this is uh reversing
the diodes which become resistive
because it's the ones which are opposing
and so you end up having again a
positive voltage on this side and this
This is how the full wave
superconducting uh diode rectifier
works. Now let me just show you a little
bit on how we our results look like. So
we made the superconducting diodes
following these techniques that I told
you and then we just applied some AC
currents as an input and then you see
how the output shows this full wave
rectifier operation and then of course
we apply a magnetic field which is
reversing our diodes and we can just
have a programmable rectifier in a
sense. you don't you're not fixed by the
device design but you can use magnetic
fields to tune it so you can reverse the
diodes you can get opposite uh signals
and then finally we just replace the the
resistor with a smoothing capacitor and
now you have AC2DC conversion as uh
people do conventionally at room
temperature but now we have done this
one at 1.8 8 Kelvin and that that is the
goal that we had here. So sorry it's 1.7
Kelvin to be precise. And with that I
hope I have convinced you that by by
exploiting masonary currents you can
create what is called superconducting
diodes which are these non-reciprocal
superconductors that are useful to for
instance make full wave rectifiers
working at low temperatures that are
capable of converting AC currents into
DC and that this is actually useful for
superconducting quantum computing and
with that I thank the the collaborators
and you all for your attention.
[Applause]
We're a little behind but we can take
one question if there is a question.
Um so you mentioned that this uses type
2 superconductors. Do you think that you
know with all the excitement around high
temperature superconductors that does
that also have uh applications for you
know power electronics for quantum
computers? It it could but so it's um so
I mean it needs to be type two to work
with this with this method but any type
two will work. Yes. Okay. But in high
TTC usually they they tend to be type
two right.
Yeah. It's usually a matter of of the
condition at which you need it to
operate. The the main thing here maybe
is that you don't want to operate at 77
Kelvin because typically wirings and
everything that connects down these are
resistive wirings but usually below 4.2
2 Kelvin people use nobium and so on. So
you can have superc conducting
interconnects between the different
levels. So if you may use a high TC
superconductor
but um but you you eventually want to
use it either at 4.2 Kelvin or below. So
the benefit will not be so much unless
you want very high critical current for
specific high power application. I see.
Let's thank Joseph again. Um,
[Applause]
oh yeah, I think
right here.
Perfect.
I've got it.
people on the Zoom this
up. Xander is going to be talking to us
about disruption prediction with
scientific machine learning.
All right.
So,
so for the last 60 years, Tokamax have
dominated magnetic confinement fusion
research. So, this is because tokamax
have excellent particle confinement and
there we go. excellent particle
confinement and have demonstrated a 100
times better performance than other
magnetic confinement fusion designs.
Further, their simple donut-shaped
geometry make them relatively easy to
build. As such, there have been dozens
of Tokamax constructed around the world,
and the research community has decades
of experience operating them. Given the
successful experimental history, many
think tokamax are the natural choice for
building a fusion pilot plant. However,
tokamax have a little bit of a problem
uh in that they are prone to
instabilities and these instabilities
can lead to disruption as Abby was
mentioning earlier. Uh yeah, so
disruptions are kind of a problem. Now
when I say that the nuclear fusion power
plant uh can experience a sudden loss of
confinement uh you might picture
something like this.
Fortunately, that can't happen. And this
is one of the few parts of the fusion
propaganda which is actually true. So
tokamac disruptions actually look like
this. So there's zero risk of a runaway
chain reaction leading to a Chernobyl
style accident because if anything goes
wrong, the plasma rapidly expands and
cools and the reactions stop. So one
instant your plasma is there and the
next it is gone.
Now while disruptions pose zero risk to
anyone outside the tokamac, they are
still a concern for the device itself.
So future tokamax like spark will have
hundreds of megaj of stored thermal
energy and megaamps of plasma current.
So when confinement is lost all this
energy and current have to leave the
plasma and they it goes into the
surrounding structural materials
extremely fast um causing large heat
flux and halo current forces. Uh to put
these numbers in perspective, the heat
shield of an Apollo capsule during
re-entry experiences a peak heat flux of
only 1 gawatt per meter squared and a
Saturn 5 rocket first stage has 35
megatons of thrust. So we want to avoid
disruptions in spark because they pose
significant materials challenges.
Um so preventing disruptions means you
need to avoid instabilities. So you want
some dynamics model so you can predict
how the plasma will evolve in the
future. As I said before, tokamax have
existed for over 60 years at this point.
We must have comprehensive methods of
determining exactly how plasmas will
behave in a variety of circumstances,
right? Well, yes and no. There are some
models that have proven to be extremely
valuable, such as ideal MHD, but there
are others that continue to present
challenges. These are things like
turbulence, um, plasma material
interaction, magnetic reconnection, etc.
In addition, any solution that you
develop must be compatible with real
time operation. As it stands,
disruptions are a problem that cannot be
solved with theory alone. So, we must
look for an alternative.
Uh, in 1687, Sir Isaac Newton said F=
ma. News flash, it's 2025. Sir Isaac
Newton is dead. It is time for a new
paradigm. F= MA plus AI.
Let me give you an example.
Say we wanted to have a predictor for
the plasma beta. Beta is simply a ratio
between the magnetic uh sorry between
the plasma pressure and the magnetic
pressure. The beta limit is an important
consideration for keeping the plasma
stable since if the plasma pressure is
too high, you can't confine it with a
magnetic field and instabilities will
rapidly form. Beta can also be written
in terms of plasma energy versus
magnetic field energy. So to predict the
value of beta over time and ensure we
don't exceed the beta limit, we just
need to predict energy in the plasma
over time. Good so far. All right, cool.
We can write out a simple equation for
the change in stored energy over time
according to various power sources and
syncs.
As sources we have things like omic
power and auxiliary heating and sinks we
have radiate power and conductive power.
Most of these terms we can measure
decently well in real time. Uh the
conductive power is tricky though
because it depends on energy confinement
time or how long it takes energy to
leave the plasma. That means it depends
on turbulence, micro instabilities,
pedal physics, blah blah blah, whatever.
This is really annoying to work with.
And even our best codes cannot really
estimate it well in real time. So let's
ignore all that and replace this term
with a neural network.
So here's our new equation. All we have
done is replaced the energy confinement
time term with the output of some
datadriven model. And when we train the
network, the loss function will be in
terms of plasma energy. So it's not
machine learning, it's scientific
machine learning. Setting up the problem
in this way has several very real
advantages over traditional machine
learning which would attempt to predict
plasma energy directly.
Um first off, it's interpretable. we're
following the structure of this
equation. I can easily see how the
output changes based on the inputs. And
again, we can measure most of these
inputs. Um, second, it makes training
easier. A fully blackbox approach would
require a larger model, which would need
more data, and that's difficult to come
by when we're first commissioning new
token.
Um, another thing that this does is it
mitigates overfitting. So because we're
restricting the influence of the model
to just this one component, it means
that our results are more likely to be,
you know, physically meaningful in some
sense.
So here's an example of the model in
action. Uh this instance in particular
is a full shot roll out. So we
initialize the stored energy at the
measured value at the start and then
extrapolate for the entire shot. And as
you can see, it works rather well for
predicting the plasma's energy. Also, I
chose this example because it highlights
what the model is trying to do and what
it is not trying to do. The output of
the model may be the predicted energy
confinement time, but it's not trained
to get an accurate energy confinement
time because even our best simulation
codes have difficulty determining what
that should be. Rather, we're staying in
the realm of well understood physics. In
this case, it's just power balance. Um,
but we aim to extend this to other parts
of tokome operation such as magnetic
control which operates with ideal MHD
which is an area that has proven to be
at least decently robust during routine
tokamac operation.
So in conclusion,
instabilities that lead to disruption
are a major concern for the operation of
future tokamacs. Preventing disruptions
will require the ability to forecast if
and when the instabilities appear. so
they can be avoided.
Predicting complex plasma dynamics from
theory alone is extremely challenging,
but scientific machine learning is a
promising path forward, allowing us to
combine physics with datadriven methods
to improve our modeling capabilities.
Thank you.
[Applause]
Any questions for Xander?
Thank you for the talk. I was wondering
whether you can reverse the problem. So
from the from the machine learning that
you're doing, can you learn back the
physics of the system from reading the
Yeah, sure. I mean, you can kind of see
here that's essentially what's happening
at least in this regime, right? Like the
model doesn't know what the correct
energy confinement time should be. But
you see that by predicting the evolution
of stored energy, you kind of back it
out here. Yeah. I mean like this this
calculated measurement is from a code
running in post-processing from this
particular shot. So it's like your like
the best estimate from codes like what
it really should be. But again you know
like you can see there's disagreement
even though the model you know it's
accurately predicting the energy confine
sorry it's predicting the stored energy
but there's disagreement in the
confinement time. So something somewhere
isn't adding up. So which do you trust
more I suppose?
I was just wondering when you know after
you run your model and you get your
feature importance out after it is there
anything that disproportionately like
any inputs that disproportionately
affects sort of what's going on in
predicting your stored plasma energy or
are you saying sort of all inputs are
weighted equally the feature importance
after for when you get your predicted
plasma. It isn't so much that we're
doing feature importance like we're just
picking one term which you know there
isn't really a good model for there
isn't a good first principles model for
and replacing that with data driven
methods.
Let's thank Xander again for the sake of
time
Henry come up.
You want to see
All right. Henry's going to talk to us
about UFO disruptions in Tacoax. Cool.
So, I'm Henry. I'm a graduate student at
the Plasma Science Infusion Center here.
And today I will be talking about UFO
disruptions in tokamax, which sounds
very mysterious.
Screen split or zoom.
Oh, you're the speaker view.
Oh, yeah.
That's a good idea.
[Music]
Is this right on screen?
Share screen or Oh, yeah. Yeah.
back into presenter. If you share your
screen rather than sharing um window of
PowerPoint. Yeah,
your desktop one.
That worked for me.
Okay, now it looks good. Now it looks
good. Okay, cool. Sean.
Um, so as others mentioned earlier, so
uh so tokamac is this tooidal
um plasma where we have this tooidal
strong toroidal magnetic field produced
by external magnets and then we drive a
current in the plasma produces this uh
weaker ployal magnetic field.
Um and so
uh as you may have learned in like an
introductory physics class, you know, a
charged particle will approximately
follow field lines in its helical
trajectory around a magnetic field. That
roughly holds for tokamax. So particles
can travel quickly in the troidal or
poloidal direction along these field
lines. But any particle transport out
radial perpendicular to the field lines
towards the wall is restricted. Um so
that's the principle of magnetic
confinement. Um and as Abby and Xander
mentioned you know we want to to do
fusion we want to hold this tokome
plasma in equilibrium for at least a few
seconds hopefully longer. So that means
you need our plasma to be stable. So a
common analogy for stability is
picturing like a ball at the bottom at a
valley or peak of a hill. So in a stable
equilibrium that's like a ball at the
valley of a hill. You know give the ball
or plasma in terms of fusion a little
kick and it'll return to its original
state. Um but in unstable equilibrium
that's like the ball at a peak of a
hill. Give it a little kick and it'll
move uh far away from equilibrium.
uh and that leads to Fabian and Xander
mentioned disruptions. So there's uh
plasma goes unstable and we have a
sudden loss of thermal energy and
current and you know as both Xander and
Abby talked about that poses severe
risks to machines especially as we build
larger devices with higher thermal
energies and currents to do fusion.
Um, and as Xander talked about, you
know, from a controls perspective, if we
notice the plasma going from this nice
stable regime to some unstable regime,
we need to take a control action. Uh,
either that could be we have enough time
returning our plasma to a stable regime
or at least mitigating the damage of a
disruption.
So, one type of disruptions in tokmax
are called UFO disruptions. So in uh
fusion UFOs don't have anything to do
with flying saucers. Uh instead they
mean a flake of a metal impur usually
like from the wall like tungsten or
malibdinum uh as others talked about
that could flake off and fly into the
plasma and that'll radiate a lot of
power and so much so that it could uh
radiate a significant fraction of the
plasma thermal energy away and lead to a
disruption. So if you're operating a
machine, you might see some like glowing
speck of metal fly in and enter this,
you know, kind of transparent plasma and
you'll just see it pop like a balloon uh
as Xander showed.
And so here you can see uh on uh a
picture of CMOD uh potential origin,
suspected origin of a UFO disruption
where you can see that a piece of the
wall got misaligned. You can see there's
this leading edge in the yellow box um
that uh where uh which experienced an um
unusually high heat flux uh since that
piece of wall was exposed and you can
see there's some melting probably some
liquid malibdinum droplets entered the
plasma and quickly caused a disruption.
Uh so what does this look like if uh
your operating machine? So here's an
example of a time trace from an
experiment on Alcatore CMOD, our old uh
tokamac at MIT. So in the top panel, we
have the plasma current that's nice and
steady around one megaamp. Um and we're
about here, we're about like 1.2 seconds
into the plasma pulse. So in CMO, a
typical plasma pulse would be two
seconds. Um the second panel is the
malibdinum content uh in the core of the
plasma. So that's nice and steady, which
is good. We want that to be low. We
don't want any wall material into our
plasma. Um the radiated power is steady,
which is nice. And then this bottom
panel is the uh electron temperature of
the core of the plasma, which has this
um kind of funky sawtooth thing shape,
which is the sign of a healthy plasma in
the token. Um but then you can see in
this red box, uh there's a sudden, uh
spike in the malibdinum content in the
core. the radiated power rapidly
increases to about 8 megawws and that's
uh totally exceed exceeds the heating
power. So we see a quick uh thermal
quench and then quench of this current.
And what's particularly concerning about
this is if you look at the time scale of
this event uh the time we have from the
you know any noticeable sign of the
injection in this panel um to the
disruption is about 5 milliseconds. So
that is too short to take any control
action. So on Spark we'll need at least
something like 10 milliseconds of
warning time to at least mitigate the
damage of a disruption. We want to avoid
the disruption we need longer warning
time. And so this poses a serious
problem because on in like a power plant
if you have all these UFO disruptions
like we had on CMOD um that could really
damage the machine and that's not
compatible with um an actual the
economics of a power plant.
The good news though is that not all
disruption not all UFOs on CMOD cause
disruption. So here's another example of
um a malibdinum injection on CMOD uh
from piece of the ball and this did not
cause a disruption. So we have the same
for signals here. Um you can see a
sudden spike in the radiated power and
malibdinum content. Um and the radiated
power here only slightly uh exceeded the
heating power which isn't shown. So you
can see the core temperature decreased
but the plasma did not disrupt. It also
decreased over a longer time scale.
Um and so this is you know this is okay
and it also gives us a picture of maybe
what a stability of a camod plasma might
look like uh to these uh UFOs or
radiative events. So maybe a you know
small injection like in this one is like
the ball in a valley you know give it a
small kick it's stable but if you give
it a large enough injection like I
showed previously and the ball uh the
plasma will move to some totally
different state and lead to a disruption
um and you know so what might set these
stability limits this is something we
want to figure out to these radiative
events you know basically you know what
sets the height of these peaks versus
the depth up to the valley. So that
could be things like the you know
external heating power we're supplying
to the uh plasma. It could be like the
stored thermal energy of the plasma.
Higher stored thermal energies will take
longer to radiate the energy away. Um it
could be also proximity to like fluid
instabilities
uh which can depend on like the current
profile and it could also just be the
operational history of the device like
you know how damaged are the walls from
either previous disruptions or just
accumulated damage as you know others
have talked about earlier that can
happen to these walls. Um so that's kind
of led to the project I'm working on. So
we'd like to find some you know
parameter space both of plasma
parameters operational parameters where
um in which plazas are more robust to
these UFO disruptions. So maybe it takes
a longer time for the plasma to disrupt
where there would be ample time to uh
mitigate the damage um or maybe where
plasmas would just you know not disrupt
and be able to recover. So we're
labeling uh UFOs on thousands of uh
discharges from Alcatore CMOD. You know,
for each UFO extracting relevant uh
plasma parameters and uh operational
parameters and maybe doing some fancy
machine learning to identify any
correlations and then uh we'd like to
compare to uh UFOs on other tokamac. So
we recently started a collaboration with
West a tokamak in France that on a
recent campaign experienced lots of
similar UFO disruptions
about to say we've got about a minute
left. Okay. Yeah. So thank you
questions.
[Applause]
Time for a question or two and then we
should call it.
So these UFO based disruptions, they're
basically like a thermal quench of the
plasma. Is that right? Yeah. So you
wouldn't need to worry about like
runaway electron generation or anything
from a UFO being tossed in. Well, so
what can happen is so like one question
is maybe you know how severe is the
damage to a UFO because it is something
that like radiates energy away and that
radiation is uniform. Um I don't know if
like that's kind of what you're Yeah.
like what is the damage to the machine
from these UFOs besides just like you
lose your plasma? Yeah. So uh often
what'll happen is it might not radiate
quite all of the plasma thermal energy
away. So it's not it won't radiate as
much as like if you do some like massive
gas injection um or like shattered
pellet injection like uh machines use to
mitigate the damage. It might radiate
like half the stored thermal energy, but
uh since that radiation is localized
where the UFO is, that might change the
like temperature and therefore current
profiles, which can lead to some MHD
instability um like some you know kink
mode or uh tearing mode and that can
then cause a more typical disruption
where you have the um heat fluxes uh
high heat fluxes on like diver on the
diverter And um yeah these like current
uh halo current stuff like that.
Thanks.
Any other quick questions? If not we
have gone close to overtime. So let's
thank Henry again.
Thanks to all of you again. This was
amazing and a lot of fun for me. And I
will now end the Zoom recordings.
Live your lives.