Um Dr. Rafoski began imaging live cells
and visually uh and visualizing
intracellular dynamics in 3D when she
was only 17 and hasn't stopped since. So
her longstanding scientific mission is
to uncover the underlying patterns and
principles and organize the complexity
window cells into functioning units of
life. To that end, she takes an
quantitative interdisciplinary approach
that integrates lives imaging, molecular
genetics, and computational analysis to
study the spatial and temporal
organization of center structures. So,
please join me to welcome Dr. Suzanne
Rafoski. Thank you.
Okay. Thank you for that beautiful
introduction. Wow, I sound really loud.
Hopefully, it's not too loud. And thank
you for inviting me um to talk. Um I
want to start by thanking our team. We
work um in a team science way. We're
about 80 people. We've been around for
now about 10 years. Um and we do
everything in an open science manner as
well. So everything that I tell you
about today is done by all these various
people at various times in those 10
years. So um I'm going to tell you guys
a talk in a couple of parts. First I'm
going to talk about establishing a
conceptual framework for holistic cell
states and state transitions which is
based on a perspective that Julie Tero
and I wrote and published last year. Um,
and then the second part I'm going to
talk about how we're actually testing
some of the ideas that are in that
perspective by summarizing the new work
that we're going to be doing at the
institute and telling you about one
proof of concept project that gets at
some of these points uh related to
endothelial cells that are derived from
our stem cells um and their response to
sheer stress. So so much about what we
know about life of course comes from
understanding the interplay between the
genotype, the phenotype and the
environment. And that is also true for
our cells. And in this talk I'm going to
take a very self-centered point of view
with the cells as the basic unit of
life. the agents that we're focusing on.
Nothing larger than a cell is any more
alive than cell and nothing small
nothing smaller is alive and so cells
are an ideal level of organization to
try to bridge all of the scales that go
from the molecular to the cellular and
the extracellular to look at these
observables. So what do we need then to
know a cell? So um if we focus on cells
in one particular organism so we can
just keep the genome fixed and not worry
about the genotype. Then we can start
defining the cellular phenotype. So now
again focusing in on the cell, this is
not the the phenotype of the tissue.
It's not the phenype of the organism,
but um all observables, everything we
measure and see about a cell that is
intrinsic to the cell, we'll call the
cellular phenotype. And everything that
is extrinsic to the cell, including the
interactions with other cells, we'll
call the cellular environment. So again,
if we're in an organism um that has uh
you know, many cells um there are many
different cellular phenotypes that come
from one genotype. And we as humans like
to classify those in some way so that we
can wrap our minds around them. So we
have epithelial cells or muscle cells.
We can define that into something that's
about cell states whether they're
proliferative, quiscent, epotic and so
on. But defining cell states is
challenging because of the continuous
nature of the cell state landscape and
the hogenity between cells in a
population. When is the cell in one
category that we have defined
arbitrarily versus another. So um
traditionally cell states were entirely
defined by what cells look like where
they were and what they do. And for
example that would be for example
squamas indothelial cells or columner
you know epithelial cells. Then in the
molecular era we identified molecular
markers that allowed us to associate
molecules with what these uh definitions
of cell state were before. So for
examples isopforms of masin heavy chain
that distinguish different types of
muscle fiber cells. Then in the genomic
and now postgenomic era, we of course
have the advent of a lot of large scale
gene expression profiles and gene
laboratory networks and all of the
beautiful sort of atlas style clustering
that we get that gives us a very
molecular view of that. But as we are
now facing this next step in the
postgenomic era where our single cell
imaging and analysis and all of the huge
and beautiful types of data science and
AI that we can do is what's facing us,
we have an opportunity to both circle
back to that traditional concept as well
as move forward and really work on
updating the concept of what a cell
state is to what we like to call a
holistic cell state where we take
spatial quantitative observables and
molecular observables and bring them
together. This is a perfect talk to go
right after the previous talk because
everything was already set up for me. We
have wonderful examples. Um, so this is
going to be sort of taking an
abstraction of a lot of what you saw and
then bringing it back to a particular
spot. So where uh Julie and I started
saying, okay, let's just use categories
of observables that sort of match the
ways that people tend to study cells. So
what cells look like, we're going to
call cell organization, that's the
spatial temporal arrangement, all of the
molecules inside cell, also the
structures inside the cell. Where cells
are located, that's the environment,
including other cells. uh what cells do
very important to biology and evolution
the actions and behaviors of the cell
and then of course what the molecules
are. We're going to term that the
molecular census because we're going to
think about this as a list that also
includes the number not just which
molecules there are. So if you take the
podium for example you can have a list
of individual proteins from one cell to
another. That's very straightforward but
we're going to say observables that
relate to postellational modifications
foration acetilation may fall into that
category too. If you take cell
organization, you can think about the
location of all of the proteins just by
themselves. Um, you can think about them
as locations of structures that have
functional sort of purpose to them. You
can think about the genome organization.
I love the fact that I come right now
after the previous talk all the way up
to cell shape. And importantly in all of
these observables, we really want to
think about these in the context of
dynamic observables and how they change.
So for cell organization of a structure,
you can do you know size, shape,
location, etc. You can take two
different cells, you can get the average
volume of GG as an example of a
measurable observable that you might
want to use in this sort of datadriven
framework. A note about categories
before you spend all your time as many
of us did at the institutes telling
Julie and me where this all breaks down.
Um any discretization of a continuum is
imperfect. Whether putting complexes,
molecular senses or cell organization or
both is not actually the thing that
matters. Um the cutoffs are intended to
create categories for us to talk to know
that we've thought about these different
aspects of biology. Biology does not
separate what it does, you know, by
these categories. They're just for us as
humans to work through. So if we tell
take cell function, what would
measurements of that be? You could have
cell type specific functions or you
could have more general cell functions.
So for example, for the migration of a
neutrfil, you could start doing
centroidid based, you know,
quantification of the speed at which
these cells move or how they turn. For
environment, you can think about the
chemical composition, how that changes.
You can think very importantly about the
mechanics as we just heard as well as
the other cells and how they're
arranged. So for example, you could
imagine measuring and having numbers for
the extrinsic push and pull of
neighboring cells on a cell or how that
affects cell shape. Great. So how do we
define holistic cell state? We would say
well if you imagine that each of these
categories of observables represents
sort of a type of state. Everybody here
who works on cell states and if you ask
someone what is the definition of cell
state they'll sort of gravitate to
usually one or a few of these. So
there's the organizational state perhaps
the molecular state which we spend a lot
of time thinking about the functional
state and we say we put all these
together it's a holistic cell state. So
what do we then need to know? know this
and what do we I am stumbling over
myself. What do we then need to know the
cell? We need to understand the nature
of the interactions between all of these
observables and we need to understand
them in time. That's how we're going to
get to understanding the cells. So for
example, if you take something like
directive migration wave, it is a direct
output of uh cytokeleletal polarization,
the phosphorilation state of singling
proteins and substrate mechanics. But
it's also feeding back on the extent to
which you have polarization of cells in
a dynamic way. which other proteins make
it phosphorolated and even you know the
subsid mechanics because if the cell
moves faster or slower it secretes its
CCM more or less and that's going to
affect the the environment. So these
birectional um the birectional interplay
is a limited framework to think through
this. What you really need is all of the
interactions and and how they correspond
to each other at this holistic idea and
the nature of the feedback that is set
up for any particular set of observables
for any particular question is mutually
reinforcing to generate those healthy
cells and understanding that is how you
can understand when things go wrong. So
we created a conceptual visualization um
depending on the audience people like
this one or the one on the next page
more or less. Um, if you just take those
four categories, you make them vertices
of a tetrahedrin, you can think of the
springs symbolically as birectional
feedback for these categories. And so
then they can have a push and pull. And
we even have a little animation of that
in a moment. That is of the values of
the observables and how they interact
with each other. Again, for lots of
people, they say, well, what in the
world are you talking about? There's a
lot more than four categories. Yes,
there are lots and lots of measurements.
You can imagine the observable space
we're talking about is any observable
that you could have. Um and so then of
course you have all the interactions and
it is the nature of the combination of
these that gives you the dynamics and if
you study neuron dynamics or systems
biology you know this very well. It
tends to generally not be including all
of the types of observables of cells. So
really this is just saying we need to
take these approaches and we need to
think about how we can have numbers
beyond the numbers we generally have
when we do this sort of work. Usually
those numbers relate to things like gene
expression. So this is how we get to a
dynamical systems framework for holistic
cell states and their dynamics. And we
acknowledge and know and all of you know
that we will never have a complete set
of observables. So we also need to
figure out how to do this to identify
which observables matter most and to
work with sparse data. So therefore in a
stable hostic cell state this is our
little dancing tetrahedrin. The vertices
may fluctuate. The vertices represent
the measurements. So for example uh not
all levels of particular protein stay is
constant at time. Not all uh positions
of an organel or speed of a cell. Um but
altogether the nature of the
relationship between these and how
they're tuned in a particular for a
particular cell or particular situation
mutually reinforces them to maintain a
stable holistic cell state. Okay. So you
have all the observables for all cells.
Um but not all combinations of
observables exist. So you don't just
have one giant space. You actually have
a subset of that space. All right. Not
all combinations of all number of
proteins are achievable. Not all
combinations of cell shapes are
achievable. And sometimes there are
dependencies. You can't achieve a
certain function if you don't have a
certain organization. So this is our
very poor man 3D representation of a
very very highdimensional subspace or
manifold within the overall space. Um
and that is static. So a location on
that is going to represent the
combination of all of the measurements.
Um and you're going to have sort of an
attractor state. You can have
fluctuations around it. And you can
start analyzing this in a more
quantitative and even theoretical
manner. And so other locations on this
massive, you know, holistic cell
manifold are going to be other cell
states. and where you study and what you
do. You may spend all your time in one
state learning about the variations of
what causes something to be healthy or
move out. Or you may care about the
overall landscape of all the possible
states that might be in a human body or
that you might want to study in a dish.
That's you know we're we're not
describing any sort of judgment to where
or what you should be studying in this
context. Just a thinking about how how
do we all talk about this in the same
language. So if you have this the
question
becomes why would a cell be at a certain
location and how do you move around on
that location? what what helps the cell
what dictates what the cell's going to
do. So we have the manifold the entirety
of achievable states achievable states
that's static and now we're going to
have probabilities where more likely
more common cell states are equivalent
to high probabilities on the manifold
and we're going to call this for now a
probability landscape. If you want to
have a long conversation about issues of
that uh come find me which would
describe the probability of being in a
location and that is dynamic or we would
like to propose it may be dynamic
meaning that as a cell moves along the
manifold it may reshape the landscape
the cells being an active participant.
What what do we mean with that? That
sounds sort of funny. It just means it's
equivalent to saying there may be memory
in the system. We already saw and heard
there's memory in the system that a
cell's past history affects his future
behavior. That also needs to be
accounted for as we want to then say
let's say we're in some part of this
probability landscape. What's going to
happen? You can't just take that static
snapshot and say now we can predict what
cells do. So this is just a framework.
Its purpose is not to tell you how cell
states work. It's intended to be
datadriven and practical and a way for
all of us to talk together to enable
integrative computational analysis and
modeling across many different cell
types and to bring together the cell
science community to build the tools,
make the hypotheses, do the tests um and
build on the momentum on what we can
have right now in this current era as a
stepping stone to somebody else's future
definition of how one should deal with
cell states. So where does AI fit in?
Well, our obviously our holistic cell
state, you know, um, uh, manifold here
is going to be very very highly
dimensional and we can't as humans wrap
our minds around what that means if you
want to have sort of understanding uh,
interpretation of what's going on. But
of course, AI is a perfect beautiful
pattern detector and especially is very
good at doing that in highly complex
data. And so it can help create um, cell
representations which really are just
uh, appropriate reduced dimensional
representations of the location of where
you are on this um, manifold. and then
perhaps the movement that you would
have. We believe very much that the
generative component is so key because
we have to determine when those
representations are appropriate and if
we use generative approaches, we can
recreate those patterns that the machine
has told us exist towards interpretation
towards using all the biology knowledge
that we have, you know, ourselves, you
know, uh, collected over the years to
actually make sure that we're doing
something reasonable and something that
we can build upon and talk about. um
because our goal is not just predicting,
our goal is predictive understanding uh
and going beyond that. So what are we
doing at the institute to try to take
some of these very conceptual ideas, put
them into practice and do it in a way
that hopefully we we will inspire some
of you to build on these as well. So um
obviously the genomic era transformed
our access to molecular census data and
uh in part even though it's very hard to
actually do the work and to standardize
it and to do this analysis the data is
very straightforward to analyze. You
know what you need to analyze there's
ATCG there's cell one cell two there's
genes there's how much there is it's
great um and it gets streamlined so that
you know everybody and their friend can
can do this now and knows how to analyze
it. But of course we want to bring in
the spatial component and of course
spatial contoics is a great way to do
that as are other approaches that allow
us to even get measurements of
organization at the same time and that's
beautiful. Um, but there's still this
problem that that's one approach in one
context. And what we're really missing
and facing as a challenge is there's a
lot to sell organization in time of all
of these complex structures that all
interact that have all these shapes that
need to go where they need to go and we
need to figure out how to measure those
in some sort of comprehensible and
generalizable manner if we want to
integrate them with other categories.
Here I'm focusing on cell organization
because of the next slide or the next
two slides. But this is also true for
cell function and cell environment. We
are not going to be able to think about
cells in a holistic way if we don't have
the appropriate measurements to actually
then use those to identify which of
those matter in the context of these
dynamical stable states. And so if we
want to get that and get at the
mechanisms underlying cell states as
well as normal cells and disease then we
have to figure out how to do that. We're
really good now at molecular
representations like right bal single
cell genomics. There's all sorts of ways
to do that. We are not so good at
organizational representations. And yet
something like nuclear morphology is a
hallmark of the progression of prognosis
of cancer. And what about all of the
other organels in the cells? What about,
you know, all of the sort of details of
the ways that they change in time? So,
this is what we mean when we say we want
to push towards holistic cell
representations that are also dynamic
and again to invoke that we know we're
not going to have all the data. And so,
we need to explore whether it is enough
to have certain data and to show that
rigorously. So, at the institute in the
first uh 10 years of the institute, we
focus very much on trying to create
these measurements of cell organization.
And so, here are sort of two papers. one
that's sort of creating a a map of how
do you even measure organization in 3D
in cells. We started with our stem cells
as well as correlating measurements of
organization that are functionally
needed in cardiammyioytes to gene
expression showing that there is not the
correspondence that you would expect
between the very obvious genes that
control cardiammyioaside differentiation
and the actual organization that you
get. But we want to now move beyond that
um and focus on a new initiative where
we are going to be more formal about
invoking the ideas of this holistic cell
state framework bringing in dynamics
which we meant to do already 10 years
ago but it's hard to do that properly
and moving more into 3D so not 3D within
a cell but now 3D structure. So this is
a overview of our new initiative that
I'm going to walk you through. Our
mission statement is that we seek to
uncover and I do have to read this
because I'm still getting used to it. um
the principles that govern multisellular
systems by exploring cell states and the
metaphorical landscapes they traverse
across spatial and temporal scales. We
will leverage our stem cell models. So
the institute focuses entirely on human
induced flop potent stem cells because
they're a great system for this um and
imaging. So here for example are our
stem cells in the format that we tended
to study them in the first part of the
institute which is in 2D sheets and here
is what we can do with them to turn them
very 3D and ask questions about now 3
fleet morphagenesis where this is a
single layer these are the nuclei of a
single layer of cells um so we're going
to leverage stem cell models integrated
imaging modeling and then synthetic
biology to achieve this goal so if we
take these luminoids we call them we're
now going to also try to precisely
decide we've we've learned something
about cell states and engineer those in
to ask questions about whether we
actually have understood them via the
holistic state framework and then the
information that we learn we with others
in the community would port into tissues
or organoids. So at the center of this
is our holistic cell state
framework. Um and for that you need to
have state transitions you're going to
focus on. So we have a couple of state
transitions that are going to be our
focus. One is the formation of these
luminoids which as you can see is a very
very obvious state transition but these
cells are still undifferiated
epithelialike hips. there is no major
well there will be some I'm sure at the
protein level but you know gene
expression change that is driving this
this is a change that is also invoking
all of these other observables that
we're talking about the other is um you
take the luminoids and you do very very
first steps in differentiation you're
going to get an EMT an epi ep epithelial
transition and it's one uh that now does
have a very strong you know gene
expression diver across it and so we
have these two beautiful model systems
that allow us to explore with or without
having really major gene expression
networks driving the process. What what
is it that you you you do in order to
ask the questions about what is state A,
what is state B and how do you get from
one to the other? What is intrinsic in
the cell and what is not? What is needed
in the context of collective cell
behavior in tissues? But what we care
about is really getting to these
computational approaches. And the thing
that glues them together is figuring out
how to create these appropriate cell
representations so that we can
iterate. We create all sorts of data. We
have a second part to our mission
statement that is to work with the
community in order to to do all of this
and to bring things back to the
community. And so we will continue to
develop solutions and tools as we have
already done. Please check out our
website uh to to to do this with all of
you. Um we love people who want to use
our poaches. Um it's very easy. Uh get
in touch with us. We can't help everyone
but we love to get everyone started and
build a community of people helping each
other with some of this as well.
So an example proof of concept project
that I'm really excited about sharing is
actually not about the systems I just
showed those are being worked up now but
is actually to say how do we get at this
question of can we test and build the
dynamics of these state landscapes and
so we're going to use as a model system
for this proof of concept HIPC derived
endothelial cells which by their nature
we can actually reduce their
organization a little bit more to 2D and
focus less on sort of the left side and
more on how we get representations. Am I
messing this up now? Um to get to the
right side and do a proof of concept of
that. So um these endothelial cells are
differentiated from my HAPSC's. They are
akin to the cells that line your blood
vessels which undergo a lot of flow. So
we image these in flow chambers so that
they have that flow. And here you're
seeing cells that are expressing um
fluorescent veterinar which are um the
is the kadhirin that sort of labels also
the outlines of the cells. Here we've
blasted the um contrast just to use it
sort of as an outline of cells but there
is are actually also really cool
patterns of how the V kit here organizes
around the cells but I'm not talking
about that today. So this is low shear
stress the cells they move upstream they
align very parallel they have a very
stereotypical behavior a very
stereotypical organization and that's
actually what you would imagine that
they're doing also in your blood
vessels. We actually were had a hard
time getting to that because the the
value of sheer stress that is used in
other endothelial cell systems was
higher. So we started here and we kept
getting ourselves aligning parallel to
the flow which is something that is
known but it's just the value of sheer
stress that happens in our cells is much
much lower um than we expected and so we
actually took a long time to sort that
out. So we have these two really
beautiful um states for these cells one
that is absolutely moving upstream and
and very parallel and very stereotyped
and one is which is the opposite and so
now we have a really beautiful again
just endothelial cells all the same
cells doing something completely
different just in response to that one
difference in environment. So can we
understand that better? How where do we
start? Well, the traditional way that we
would start and that you know we did
start was let's take these movies, let's
do feature extraction, let's look at our
biology, let's look at our science,
let's take raw data, let's you know
there's all these beautiful for 2D image
analysis. This is why we went into 2D,
you know, we it's solved, right? So just
let's go through this. Turns out that
the success rate of the segmentations is
about 50%. Once you want to do it in
time and analyze dynamics, everything
can fall apart. And so we asked this
question, we could have refined this.
We're we're specialists at this. It's
like what I do, right? Um but we said,
can we instead learn the features that
are most important for the biology that
we're seeing, which is this one state
versus this other state. So, uh we said,
let's develop a framework um to extract
the features that we're going to care
about um in a segmentation and tracking
free uh way. This is the very first time
I'm presenting the slide, so let me
stumble through it with you a little
bit. I will get better at it every time
I do. We have two different types of
data. We have our vader uh GFP. The
reason these cell this looks so long is
because we actually take multiple um
fields of view and stitch them together.
Um and we also have the bite field. When
we do the the projections into 2D, it
makes a lot of sense to do a maximum
projection for the via adherent and a
standard deviation projection for the
bite field. And it keeps so much of the
information, the rich information that
is in the bitefield images and has been
just phenomenal. So then we said well
what we really want is to get these
features out and we want to do this in a
model that is generative and we tried
several different things including the
sort of sparsity model of how can you
fit this in um and we landed on the
diffusion autoenccoder that worked
really well for us. So we have one part
which learns to move gaussian noise from
an input image which happens to be the
via khiran input image and then we have
another part which is a semantic encoder
which is working to identify what exists
in the bitefield standard deviation
image that helps this process and
therefore generates a latent space.
These two are trained together and we
then get a um feature representation in
low dimensions that I will show you is
also interpretable that defines what it
is that's in the image that allows us to
actually uh do this process and once
we've trained this we can do this all
from the bite field itself which is very
powerful. So we have three conditions
that you're going to get used to in the
next few slides. no flow which is sort
of an intermediate you'll you'll see
that in intermediate sort of
organization uh high flow and low flu
flow um we have our encoder we get a
latent space it's eight dimensional we
can do another dimensionality reduction
just to make it even easier for
ourselves we are exploring the eight ad
space as well um and we're calling this
a threedimensional state space because
99% of the variance in the data for the
thing that we're looking at which is
what the pattern is when you have the
vader is taken care of in those three
dimensions and if you plot these you can
see that the three conditions can
separate out beautifully which is great.
So now we can interpret it. We can uh
use the generative ability of this model
and we can recreate what these patterns
of these images would be and we can see
that along PC1 which is good that the
primary axis of variation you get the
parallel to perpendicular sort of
aligned image. These are just snapshots
right now. We're going to get to
dynamics. Um the second one is still a
bit of a mystery. having a grand old
time learn figuring out what the model
has seen but it's very likely related to
how much the cells overlap with each
other and so in the different flow
conditions or in different moments cells
have a little bit more or less overlap
and we're going to sort that out. The
third one is very clearly density which
since cells continue to go over time and
they continue to move is something that
you always have to deal with. There is
no such thing as one steady state.
You're going to have to always think
about it in the context of where where
the cells are in their in the coding. Um
so this state space is only a static
view um of the system. How do we get to
dynamics? Well, we can take two time
points. Um, we can, uh, look at a
particular cop. You can see how it
changes in the state space. And then you
can populate that for the whole space.
And here, um, you can see that for each
of these three different conditions and
where they lie in there. Then you can
say, does it have any reality? Well,
this is a 3D space. So, let's have Matos
um, so our our director of image
analysis and machine learning. Um, he's
a long-term collaborative of mine. He's
also a great visualizer. So he of course
figured out how to make this something
that we can all sort of wrap our minds
around which is if we start with various
different cops and we look at the
trajectories over time um where do they
go and so if we look at where they go
they go exactly to what we would imagine
is an example image of the stable state
in um the first case uh which is the
noious stress you have a mixed
orientation rounder cells then you have
horizontal alignment elongated cells and
vertical alignment and less round cells.
Okay, these are just images of crops.
These are not cells yet, right? But you
can say, okay, what about a sample
trajectory? So, we're putting sample
trajectories here. You can sample them
um in different spots and you can see
sort of what a sample pattern change, a
dynamics of change would look like. And
it actually does exactly what you would
want. If you happen to be a cell that's
starting out not aligned this way, over
time you would get more aligned and vice
versa, over time you get more
perpendicular. Those are again just
cops. These are not cells. We have not
tracked cells. So is there any bearing
to reality? And the answer is yes. You
can pick whatever favorite cell you
would like. If it starts out a little
bit more looking like this, you will see
that those cells tend to get parallel
and elongated. And um if I play this
other movie, that is also true uh for
the other
state. So we will do more than just this
little example. We actually are tracking
individual cells and bringing this all
together. But at least that gives us
confidence that what we're finding for
these crops which are only five minute
minutes apart. And I I should have said
that early on. I need to label my
slides. This is what happens when you do
this for the first time. Um, every frame
is five minutes apart and this is about
24 hours of a movie. So, in summary, the
diffusion autoenccoder um learns
interpretable features from small cops.
The three different flow conditions are
well separated and the predicted
trajectories seem to be have some
bearing in reality. So, what are we
doing next? Um, well, we want to see
intermediate flows both as steady states
because it's actually really hard to
create landscapes without having sort of
points to to move from one to the other.
um but also the dynamics from one to the
other directly to ask the question of
what is this state transition really
look like and is it reversible. We get
to explore all of the variations and
trajectories to learn something about
the biology. We're very excited about
the fact that we can start asking what
aspects of these dynamics are due to the
non-equilibrium aspects of the system.
Those of you who like that, come find me
and talk to me. Um it's actually pretty
cool. And in order to know that we've
had an understanding, we're also doing
our usual good cell biology. We have
other structures we're looking at. we
know about endothelial biology and we're
building biohysical models to test this.
I'm going to leave you with what I think
is the coolest and funnest thing to look
at and you mull on this question as
you're watching. Is the state transition
reversible? So, first we're going to
have a one movie second which is um uh
going to be the low flow and then you're
going to see a switch in behavior and
that is when we change the flow in a
sudden way. So we moved all of the cells
from being on one sort of uh dynamical
uh flow field to another in a sudden
manner. And you can watch that behavior.
And this is a total of 20 hours. But
it's the first the first like sort of
second that you're watching. And and
you'll see that loop play again there.
And you can see that this is a temporal
process. And the cells do a set of
behaviors to make that transition
happen. And now the same thing in the
other direction. These are the cells
that are perpendicular. we reduce the
flow and they're going to realign over
time. And I'm going to play that one
more time as well. And so this um we I
can tell you I'm not showing you the
data, but we already know that this is
not a directly reversible process. And
so the question of you know, what is
this hysteresus due to? Is it just time
scale? Is it something organizational?
Um is going to be really fun to to think
about as well. So with that, I want to
thank you all um for your attention and
take questions.
[Applause]
I think we have time for one question.
Thank you so much. That was a fantastic
talk. I always wondered what is a cell
state. So regarding that you said there
can be so many ways to define cell state
and you are trying to incorporate all
different like cell environment and
morphological features and so I still
didn't understand how will you for for
if you have all the information are you
planning to just concatenate let's say
how do you plan to let's say there is
there are different ways so there are
morphological features there are RNA
seek features let's say let's say you
can measure all of them cell environment
cues how will we finally define a cell
state I'm still. Yeah. So, I think we're
saying uh because this is a continuum
and cells don't care about states. If
you take something very well separated
like completely different cell types
have completely functions, you're just
very very far apart in this manifold.
And so, it's very easy to draw a line
and make an arbitrary line. But if you
actually want to understand how you get
there and you care about the continuum,
you want to know where you do or don't
have uh whether it is in healthy cells
or in unhealthy situations filling in of
of these different spaces or of the
paths that you take. So our answer is
that we're not going to predetermine
what that is. We're going to say, can we
have a data-driven way to actually get
the continuum and then depending on your
question, decide where you're going to
focus and set up your question and use
the data to answer that question. If you
need a category in order to define it,
that's great. If you think back um one
of the things that you know the the
UMAPs give you is cell types, right?
Those are um completely validated and
then extrapolated from where is a cell,
what does it look like, what does it do
from all the traditional sort of
definitions, right? So there is there is
um a view of those that is then
molecular and then there's a view that
is being missed by those. If we add
those other dimensions in, depending on
your question and your system and what
you're asking, you may care entirely
about molecular, you may care entirely
about non-molelecular, right? Those
state transitions I showed you are
absolutely valid and important state
transitions that may not have at least
on the say RNA level uh the molecular di
maybe all phosphorilation which is
actually hugely important and maybe
something else and may have nothing to
do with a change in what the molecules
are initially and only eventually builds
up. the time scale and the spatial scale
of your question is what's going to
determine how you define that state.
Okay. So, let's thank our speaker again.
[Applause]