[Music]
I'm Cara Miller and I'm Rob Stoner and
this is what if it works coming to you
from the MIT energy initiative and
looking at the energy solutions to
climate
[Music]
change today large parts of the world
just don't have enough energy so how do
they transition to cleaner sources when
for many people
that's not the real
priority in the work I do I have to very
actively recognize that I am very
ignorant about many facets of a problem
and actively try to educate myself from
the perspectives of different
stakeholders around the problem that's
Amos winter a professor of mechanical
engineering at MIT and he's got a knack
for looking at technical problems a
little bit differently than most people
and he's tackled a lot of technical
problems
from designing a wheelchair that's
usable and affordable in Tanzania when
you're working in a resource constraint
setting that often means lowering cost
or using maybe a more constrained set of
Parts like bicycle parts for a
wheelchair to creating a prosthetic foot
that fits the market in India can we
have something that's mass
manufacturable and cheap and rugged but
as developing countries seek to solve
more problems need more power and
consider the pros and cons of renewable
energy one of Winter's big beliefs is
that you have to tackle a whole system
and when you've got a system that's
created for a set of circumstances and
resources in Tanzania or in India
sometimes you uncover solutions that
provide significant insights into how to
make systems in developed countries more
energy efficient approaching these
large-scale challenges often brings into
play the idea of design thinking which
has gotten a lot of attention in both
business in Academia over the last
couple of decades making energy work for
a community means you've got to
understand people's lives if you live in
a place where you're not on the grid for
example can solar panels meet your needs
well it's an interesting question and
actually it kind of depends let's say
you want to just power lights in your
home and charge your cell phone that
doesn't require very much energy you can
have a relatively small array of solar
panels
it's low cost you can implement it when
you start wanting to run appliances in
your house the energy load is much much
higher and the power load is much higher
and that becomes a much trickier problem
and then the other thing that we face
all the time is there's a certain level
of power and energy needs that ends up
justifying having a
standalone power generation system so
for example it doesn't make any sense
probably to have a solar panel just to
run a single sprinkler on your
lawn but if you have that solar panel to
run the sprinkler and your TV well then
there's a stronger value proposition and
there's there's companies that have done
this they figured out additional power
uh needs that justify the capital cost
of installing that that power system for
us when we're talking about a community
scale or even Municipal scale and we're
working on that as well desalination
system those are plants basically and
they they are often in areas that have
enough spare area either on the roof of
the building or the surrounding area to
put in a solar array but if we're
talking about let's say a home scale
desalination system which are very
widely used across India for example it
doesn't make sense to have a a little
tiny solar panel on your roof for just
that one device so where's the energy
coming from where's the energy then
coming from for that homebased
deselenization system those are bought
by typically middle class or above
households that have grid access and
those systems don't need to run 24 hours
a day so even if you have intermittent
grid you can you can turn it on when you
have energy
access Rob do you have thoughts on that
notion of you know whether in emerging
economies people are skipping a
generation in terms of technology or or
they're scaling up by relying on many of
the things we've relied on coal and oil
and you know well I I think I don't know
if it's so much skipping a generation
yet but it's it's getting there before
the conventional electricity generation
and distribution Technologies are
economically viable for you so what's
happened is we've we've seen Villages
and remote communities or even even
parts of provinces and states and
countries that aren't that rural but but
are still
far from where the the infrastructure is
we've seen them get electricity sooner
than they would economically because of
these new options becoming possible for
them Amos talked about the idea of
electrifying individual homes with a
very small amount of solar power it
didn't work out well solar prices and
battery prices were higher than they are
now but as they've Fallen it's become
more and more possible for poorer
families to be able to buy these systems
not the poorest yet
I think what he's really
done that's That's so exciting with with
desalination and we'll talk about
Irrigation in a minute is is figure out
how to make the systems work as systems
so much more efficiently that you can
get to even yet another layer of poor
people and and also by making them in
some cases Community serving you can
access people that who individually
couldn't afford them but as a community
can afford them and I think that's
that's exciting it's a providing public
infrastructure using these engineered
systems Rob is touching on such an
important point and I boil that down to
the question of how can you do a task
but with less energy than we do it with
in the US in Europe and I think I I
talked to like consumer product
companies and they realize there's just
massive fortunes to be made to figure
out who can make the air conditioners
and the refrigerators and the you know
ovens and and these these higher power
appliances and amenities that you can't
run on small micro grids right now just
because of the power draw you know we're
going to talk more about irrigation but
also desalination that like we are
always trying to do the task with less
energy to drive cost down but in this
regard too just make the energy that can
be viable and available more usable to
do more tasks that add value to people's
lives so are you saying that there's a
race right now kind of behind the scenes
even in wealthier countries to pull bits
of energy out of air conditioning or
freezers or whatever and then money is
to be made at scale are you thinking are
you talking more about in poorer
countries so that race is there of
course like you know the energy star
appliances and all that stuff that's
been around forever and that's you know
Rob can speak more knowledgeably about
this than I can but but that you know
that's appealing to Consumers because of
cost energy it's it's appealing for like
a green mentality I think there's
there's subsidies for some of those
things I'm talking about step changes
though like thinking about how can you
do a task with like half to a tenth the
amount of energy as we use in the US and
that excites me and that that is what we
have done in in a lot of our work like
in the desalination work I talked about
previous ly you know we've lowered the
power system size well we've cut all the
batteries out of it that that's a
massive massive Capital cost sometimes
we actually want to use bigger solar
panels that are less efficient because
of the overall benefits of the rest of
the system like it's often it's often
cheaper to buy more solar panels than
you need than trying to buy batteries
and buffer all the energy you need in
batteries so you can use it at night
it's just better to get more energy
during the day and and blow it then so
yeah all these energy drivers that
dictate design decisions I think are
fascinating human behavior comes into
making that system work well sometimes
too right I mean absolutely you can you
can overpower the system during the day
with bigger solar panels and get the
batteries out of zero but people have to
decide to use the system during the day
and and you know it's interesting to
watch how communities adapt their
behavior to the availability of energy I
wish we did that more in developed
countries yeah like in our irrigation
systems when we did our first Pilots we
found that many of the farmers would
miss irrigation events they were
supposed to do because they had to pray
these were in Muslim countries and we
hadn't we hadn't built in those blackout
hours
yet and so you're exactly right rob you
you have to you have to design all of
this around the people's behavior it's
not just a tech problem we have the idea
of demand response in in the west where
people are paid to modify their behavior
because it's cheaper to pay them than to
add extra infrastructure investment to
make it possible for them to do any old
thing any anytime they want uh it hasn't
hasn't really had the impact that we've
we've wanted it to have uh because well
they want to do stuff when they want to
do it I think this is such a good point
too to to bring this back to talking
about design thinking I think as we look
to a green future in climate change and
energy reduction and all these things I
feel like tooo often we depend on well
people will change and people don't
change very easily and people tend to do
what they want most of the time so I
think the real sweet spot is if you can
find Solutions where people can still do
what they want and have what they want
but just by default they do something
better for the environment I find that
people are much more willing to do these
things when they're off grid than when
they're on grid and I think the reason
is that when you're connected to the
grid
you're you're buying electricity from a
system that's being managed by Financial
Wizards and people who are building the
system with the idea that it's going to
be paid off for many many many decades
so a unit of electricity that you buy is
inconsequential but you wouldn't of
course be willing to personally make the
billion dollar investment that it took
to get the electricity there when you're
building a offgrid power system you're
faced with that capital investment even
if you're able to borrow the money and
pay it off slowly you're not going to
pay it off for 50 years the way we pay
off the grid you're going to pay it off
in 3 years and it's painful to do that
and so they're they're much more willing
to buy into the idea that they're going
to modify their behavior if they can get
away with this much smaller upfront
capital investment and I've seen that in
in micro grids in rural communities in
solar home systems in solar pumps it's
an interesting phenomenon it's too bad
we don't have to pay with cash up front
for the the wires that come into our
homes where I bet we buy smaller ones
I've noticed it a lot in electric cars
in the last year where I think we there
was a slump in sales over the last six
months or so aside Amos is a huge car
guy so
yeah but but Car Guy aside I think
what's happened is that you initially
had early adopter who liked the new tech
and want to be green and so they were
buying electric cars and then as you get
near the mass Market electric cars right
now cannot deliver in all the use cases
that a gasoline or diesel power car can
do still in terms of range and fill up
time and towing capacity and all these
things and I think that is has slumped
the market and so probably most people
recognize that internal combustion is a
is a real negative contributor to
climate change they also have other
needs in their life and they they can't
you can't be a a farmer in Iowa that has
to pull a trailer 500 miles a few times
a week with an electric truck it just
the energy doesn't work out and so in my
work we have to very much recognize this
in like our irrigation in that we can't
really ask the farmers to do anything
that would be looked at in their eyes as
a detriment to their business or put
them at risk or like not grow as many
crops or be arduous to
use and it's a very similar dynamic in
that I think most Farmers recognize
climate change is a huge issue for the
agriculture industry they know water is
stressed but they also want to maximize
their crop growth so if they have access
to water they're going to use it right
and so we we have done and we'll talk
about this more but a a huge amount of
work on water saving irrigation methods
that you can use less water but Preserve
crop productivity and and also ideally
instill that confidence in Farmers that
when they adopt this thing it's not
going to reduce their yield it's
actually going to make their life better
and and actually maybe enable them to
grow a lot more crops with because given
the water they have allocated to them
they can use it on a bigger area and and
grow more yield so talk about that I
mean how can you use less water to water
the same plant I mean doesn't plants
need water so water saving irrigation
methods have been around for many many
years the the technology called drip
irrigation where you just drip out the
exact amount of water a plant needs so
you minimize water loss to evaporation
and drainage that was really popularized
in Israel in the 1970s and that's a very
effective way to reduce the water
required to grow plants so if you
compare drip irrigation with
conventional Furrow or flood irrigation
or even sprinklers often times you can
reduce water consumption by upwards of
60 % by using drip versus those
traditional methods so a big portfolio
of our work has been on how can we
promote greater adoption of drip
irrigation the big barrier to drip
irrigation adoption is cost it is more
expensive than just getting a diesel
pump and flooding your Fields um and
particularly in the markets where we
work where we don't necessarily have
grid access power cost is really the
biggest cost driver and that power can
be a diesel pump both the capital cost
and recurring cost of that energy or it
can be a solar power system both are are
about equivalently expensive when you
look at it over 10 years so a big area
of our work has been addressing how much
power and energy does it require to move
water through a drip irrigation system
we can't really change flow rate because
the plants need so much water but we can
change pressure and so because we cut
pressure our drip irrigation emitters
that we've designed cut pump power in
half compared to existing products so if
you're an on grid farmer Cuts your
energy costs in half if you're say
pumping from a pawn to your field if
you're an off-grid farmer it cuts a a
solar powered irrigation system uh it
depends on a lot of factors but anywhere
from like 10 to 40% Still Still big big
uh reductions and then also again going
back to design thinking we had to think
about what would incentivize companies
to make distribute this and our big
commercial partner on this project is
toro they make lawn tractors and egg and
landscaping equipment and they really
instilled in us that for the bread andb
butter markets like the US farmers are
not so sensitive to energy even though
they can save energy costs but what Toro
was sensitive to was the size of the
emitters that they make and if we can
make them smaller they're cheaper and if
we can make them smaller as well we can
ship more of them in a container to a
production facility where they're put
into the pipe so they're much cheaper to
distribute and so we have come up with
drip emitters that are half the size of
Toro's previous products and that
completely changes their business model
so now they can centrally manufacture
these emitters and do it under very high
Precision quality control and then put
them inside a box ship them anywhere in
the world and then insert them into the
pipe locally and you do that because
when you when you ship just emitters
they're really densely packed in a box
but when you make piping there's a lot
of air in the pipe so you never want to
ship that over a long distance and it's
been really fun working with Toro's
marketing department in the Middle East
in North Africa where we do our work
because they've instilled in us that
this ability to accommodate a much wider
pressure variation and run much much
longer lines has huge economic
advantages to Farmers because they need
less piping like big piping what are
called sub mains between the fields they
can just run longer hoses basically and
get rid of some of that infrastructure
so even though drip irrigation emitters
are more expensive they can actually
save costs on other Capital Equipment by
running longer lines so ironically these
these countries are getting wealthier
people are getting wealthier and moving
into the middle class as they get the
benefit of having these
Technologies how can we ensure that in
the future as as they become become
advanced economies they don't adopt our
bad habits and give up all these lovely
Frugal habits and and you know system
scale thinking that is required with
these sorts of systems is it possible in
other words that we're going to skip the
Revolution and go back to the same old
sloppy habits that we've adopted the way
I think about this is is a few ways one
when you're talking about water stressed
countries you have an incentive to to
not be wasteful like like the Middle
East in North Africa just doesn't have
the spare water we do in the United
States so you know that's a totally
different scenario the second in in
terms of being a designer is thinking
about how can you save water and
incentivize Farmers to adopt your
technology because the benefits of it
are are so much that it would be foolish
to go back to a more wasteful practice
and that has been critical in our
irrigation work in how we designed
system control
so I haven't talked about this yet but
the other big portfolio we have is how
we very judiciously use water and use
energy so at every point in the growth
cycle of a plant we're figuring out how
much water does the plant need to
maximize this growth potential how do we
not waste water to evaporation and
drainage and how do we account for
weather variation every day and how that
affects evaporation and transpiration
and water loss out of the soil so what
we've created is a a control system that
every day is predicting weather using
machine learning is knowing where the
plants are in the growth cycle is
figuring out the exact amount of water
the plants need in order to get water to
maximize productivity but not waste any
and it does that every single day as the
weather changes and it's also tracking
what the farmers do let's say they
forget to turn on the pump or turn on a
valve or something it will accommodate
for that if they a water deficit and so
what we've shown now is that with that
very judicious tracking of water and
energy we are cutting water usage by
more than 40% compared to normal drip
irrigation practice so that already Cuts
water enormously we can cut it by
another 40% and we're also cutting
energy use by about 40% compared to
traditional solar irrigation Solutions
so you know that has huge benefits
energy and water but what's cool about
it as well is hearing Farmers feedback
about it because we were really wary of
of whether Farmers would want to adopt
something that kind of steps in for them
and makes decisions for them and we in
that work we had to go through a huge
amount of um farmer interaction and
storyboarding how the controller would
work with like a pictorial uh uh
diagrams of how they would interact with
it and get that confidence that farmers
were saying yeah you know we could use
this this makes sense we could interact
with it this way on our phone and then
the feedback we keep hearing from
farmers who have interacted with it is
that they like that decision-making
capability they they want ways to reduce
water and reduce costs and reduce energy
and they also know that they can
override it they still have manual
control but they've actually wanted that
intervention that that can help them
grow more crops in save water or use the
water they have on a water field to grow
even more crops
there's a long history around like
service learning programs in Academia
where you have students going to a
village to you know work on some project
and the villagers are like well what do
we get out of this in the end and
companies look at it and they're like
well there's no scalable model here but
I think if you go at it from the
standpoint of saying hey company there's
this massively underserved Market that
has tremendous purchasing power that you
could you could engage and it would
dramatically grow your business and then
also discuss with Farmers like what
would make a meaningful impact on their
lives and why would they be incentivized
to adopt a solution that that informs
you in such a powerful way to make
something that's actually viable and I
like I literally have these meetings
with Toro where we're doing Market
projections in in the Middle Eastern
Market versus the US market and the
market size is smaller in the Middle
East but the growth potential is much
larger than in the US so in terms of
absolute like Revenue increase they're
actually pretty similar with our
technology
[Music]
portfolio I wonder if there's enough
groups of people with the right
incentives as you see it to be
innovating in the way that you think
Innovation Works best or do you know
what I mean like or academic doing one
thing because they have a career
trajectory and then companies are doing
another thing because they have a profit
motive and then like there's this sweet
spot but not enough people are hitting
it I think there's two big barriers to
better aligning academic Innovation with
real world impact the first is the
incentive structure you can be an
excellent accomplished academic by
having ideas that that you can raise
some money around writing papers on that
getting your colleagues to site them and
repeating but there's nothing inherent
in that process that necessarily
translates out to real world impact and
the second I think is is a lack of
skills necessarily to do what is really
product design where like most most
great technical Minds who are in
particularly fundamental scientists
they've never done ethnographic work
they're not working you know on field
sites interacting with end users it's a
totally different skill set and it also
takes a lot of time and money to do that
upfront problem definition work but also
the development of a technology um in
collaboration with stakeholders in a
real life
environment we spend crazy amounts of
money setting up desalination systems
across the world but the information we
get is so valuable because we're not
only seeing how they run technologically
we're seeing how people interact with
them and what they like about them so
this is actually a really good segue to
how I've been trying to address this on
a more holistic scale at MIT and so a
year ago um I I became the director of
the Kisa yangang Global Engineering
Research Center or gear Center and the
point of this whole Center is to help
grow the impact potential of academic
research by addressing these barriers
that I just talked about so the main
tasks of the center are first to have a
team of people well-seasoned researchers
that can go out do the field work to
find really compelling high impact
problems but also distill the research
questions out of them that they can be
brought back to MIT where we can then
engage collaborators and say do the
great research you're amazing at but
please focus on these targets we'll
we'll fund you and we'll also have our
team integrate with you so we can have
your students working in the field we
can help you build field prototypes so
we keep evolving the technology towards
impact and then the final part of the
center is having a lot of applied
engineering ability to not only make
prototypes but also do technology
transfer because an Achilles heel off
and of academic Innovation is let's say
if you This brilliant idea but you don't
have a student who wants to start a
company around it we have staff that we
can bring in as uh future founders of
companies or who can work with existing
companies to facilitate technology
transfer through licensing
agreements I I think what what you're
talking about Broad is how we can
provide people with products or services
that are delivering the the capabilities
and characteristics that they
value it's the best blender or it's the
best lawnmower or it's the best
irrigation system or the best prosthetic
knee it doesn't have to be best though
it has to be one you want to use it's
good it's good where I want it to be
good I'm not making a tradeoff that I'm
conscious of that seems to me the sort
of gold and fleece of engineering design
if if we could really get there with
everything then we could be not
knowingly making sacrifices in our
choices and yet doing the right thing
doing the right thing In Spite of
Ourselves or is that a stupid objective
no I the reason I chimed in about the
word best is that best drives so much
product development in in wealthy
countries you know you hear about the
new whizbang features of the new iPhone
whatever 15 and you trying to get that
little bit better or like you know
horsepower in cars which is just so
arbitrary and I think a a big part of my
job and in other innovators jobs that
want to work in resource constraints
settings is you want to distill what is
the core value that consumers want that
that make them want to use a product and
derive value from that product and try
to trim out all the extraneous stuff all
the unnecessary features but then the
other side of that coin is you can think
about what specific features May
resonate with users from different
markets so an example of this is going
back to the wheelchair we talked about
at the beginning in developing countries
people would not ride in cars very often
particularly in rural areas in the US
they riding cars all the time so we had
to make our wheelchair frame collapsible
and the wheels removed really quickly
the chairs look very similar between us
and developing countries but that
feature was critical
to engage the US market so it's
transportable in a car and yet it still
has all of the other advantages it might
cost a little bit more not a lot yeah
well and and it retains the core value
which is the ability to propel yourself
on a diversity of terrains very fast and
efficiently and with an architecture
that's easy to repair using bike parts
so when you think about the energy
transition just from what you've seen
you've seen a lot of the world both here
in the US and um in poorer parts of the
world what's your thinking around um how
well we're doing how well we will do at
creating the systems to make that
transition I think it all depends on
what the pressures are that will drive
that adoption I think when you can
create a cleaner solution that doesn't
introduce any drawbacks and is easy to
adopt that's the best win you know if if
a rivan truck could pull a 7,000lb
trailer a miles in a day oh my God that
would be amazing but it's not there yet
it can't do it I think in the absence of
those like one to one or even better
Replacements you have to add pressure
from from other standpoints and it and
it can be policy pressure economic
pressure what I think is a bit myopic
sometimes is when the governments get
together and say okay we're going to hit
these goals but there's not a real game
plan of like how to get there or even
when like GM says oh we're going to make
all our our vehicles electric by like
2035 you know I think that's a great
goal I'm not knocking the goal but
without thinking through like not only
how you get there but how are you going
to actually satisfy existing needs and
requirements and desires and not create
drawbacks or impose really harsh
penalties you know so people accept the
drawbacks I I don't know how you get
there yeah you got to pay the piper too
much yeah
it it reminds me of what you talked
about with ethnography too like you
can't necessarily criticize somebody for
having range anxiety about their car
even if you can show them on a
spreadsheet see you don't normally drive
very far so you shouldn't worry but also
that one time you go to the in-law's
house a thousand miles away for
Christmas and you can't get there and
you're stuck charging in the middle of
the night that makes a big difference
even though it's one time
yeah we we look at this actually like
all our like our Dell systems are never
100% reliable because of the cost
implications to produce a given amount
of water every single day like even when
it's cloudy and R out with the solar
powered system is nuts so we have to
figure out kind of feel out well what's
good enough and I actually love working
in agriculture because plants through
Evolution have figured this out a plant
doesn't need an exact amount of water
every day otherwise it it dies no
they've got buffer built into them so if
we just play Within that buffer we can
actually be pretty sloppy and still do
pretty well so there must be those
natural buffers built into anything I
mean cooking yeah you don't starve to
death if you miss a meal heating your
home or cooling your home well you know
you don't need to be at 72.0 degrees at
all times you can tolerate all kinds of
excursions where where do you think the
big opportunities are to kind of think
this way and take advantage of those
buffers besides the one you've already
mentioned I think it always depends and
and it's so culturally it depends on
cultural context every time I'll give
you an example one of our our big
lessons we got out of a a partner we
worked with in India on
desalination is how people in India over
the last 20 years have developed a
pallet for very low salinity water that
had been treated with reverse osmosis so
brands that you would know like Aquafina
or danani in the US they have very very
low salt content in them and you can
they you can maybe pick up the taste a
little bit different than than say like
a well water which may be higher so why
this was important to us is we had
designed our early systems around World
Health Organization standards of what is
healthy to drink and we realized from
our partners in India that healthy to
drink water would have too high of a
salt content and you and I probably
wouldn't pick up on it but people in
India would so we had to lower the salt
content of our Pro produced water which
had an enormous energetic cost it
literally doubled the energy we had to
put in to desalinating the water but I'm
glad we caught that because it would
have very likely created rejection of
the product water we make now that's not
the case everywhere if you in a flip
side contrast we also work in the Navajo
Nation and in the Navajo Nation people
will often drink quite salty water
brackish groundwater and so there it
might be very acceptable to have World
Health Organization standard water that
you know would taste normal to us taste
normal to people in the Navajo Nation
but not taste right in India knowing
your
customer yeah definitely and customers
are different everywhere have you ever
done focus groups in a rural community
in India or a Navajo all the time oh
really all the time yeah not only focus
groups we we do we will take storyboards
of particularly new technology that we
haven't designed or invented yet and say
Here's how we envision you would maybe
interact with it what do you think and
and we go through that kind of
imagination game and that was
tremendously valuable in refining our
controller for irrigation systems and
how it interfaces through a cell phone
that is what created the app that we run
now and we're we're finding it now to
make it even better but yeah we do
farmer field days where we get people
together and present the technology and
demonstrate it and get feedback we do
lots of focus groups and one-on-one
interviews so we've done that very
recently in the Navajo Nation uh which
is also very water stressed but is a
incredibly unique Community because
people are so disperse the advantage
India has is you have much higher
population concentrations even in rural
areas so there's an economic
justification for having like a
community scale system that can serve a
few thousand people who are all within
walking distance in the navoo nation you
have like three families in walking
distance and so to do a centralized kind
of big Capital cost system there doesn't
make any economic sense and we recently
did a study we're we're finishing a
publication on this now where we do the
economic modeling and we found that
individual home scale systems make much
more economic sense including the
service model of like how many repairmen
do we need for this community where
they're driving all over the Navajo
Nation but with a few service people we
can actually make sure these systems run
reliably and we actually learned that
service model from an Indian partner
that makes homes scale desalination
systems so we knew the frequency and the
type of repairs and the cost of repair
that was actually economically viable
what is the project you're really
excited about like what's next what are
you working on well with the Advent of
gear Center that I'm leading now we are
focusing on three primary thrusts which
are the water energy food Nexus climate
change mitigation and adaptation and
Global Health Technologies and we're
building out portfolios of programs
around those themes so in the water
energy food Nexus we we are currently
trying to bring to fruition our
desalination and irrigation Technologies
and the new project right now is
actually converging them do doing
desalination for agriculture cuz there's
a huge demand for that not only in very
water stressed places like the Middle
East but also if you look at big a areas
even the in the US the central plains in
the in the center of the country in the
Central Valley of California they have
rackish water so a good robust lowcost
solution for desalination for egg would
be tremendously valuable so we're doing
that we will start a project this year
on hydrogen combustion
and the goal is to do a retrofit of
existing internal combustion engines so
they can easily burn hydrogen and
ideally be able to switch back and forth
between their native fuel of gas or
diesel to hydrogen and that is trying to
replicate the model that's been very
successful with compressed natural gas
used on like taxis in Big polluted
cities where you can just switch between
gasoline and CNG and so we we've got
some ideas of how we could do this but
the ideal would be a bolt-on retrofit
where you don't have to change the
engine at all and you can run it on in
either hydrogen or a petroleum Fuel and
then we're also um over the last decade
we've learned a lot about taking a Time
variable power source like solar or wind
and producing a product from it in a
Time variable manner be it desalinated
water or like Distributing water for
irrigation we are also looking at that
for hydrogen production and then the
other the other area where we're just
starting to conceptualize is looking at
the services and products and amenities
that at risk communities due to climate
change are going to need we are working
with Gabriela carolini and the
department of urban studies and planning
who studies these populations in Brazil
is her Focus area and so we this is very
early we're we're going to go in and do
that ethnographic work to understand
what are the likely migration patterns
these communities might have
what does their future look like where
will they live what sort of jobs might
they want to do and see can we innovate
to try to maximize the productivity and
and Health and Welfare of these
communities and that gets back to what
we talked about earlier in can we do
that with renewable sources where you're
you're doing your job but with less
[Music]
energy wow a ton of work a ton of
projects to check back in on Amos winter
professor of mechanical engineering at
MIT thank you so much this is great
thank you thanks
Amos what if it works is a production of
the MIT energy initiative if you like
the show please leave us a review or
invite a friend to listen and remember
to subscribe on Apple podcast Spotify or
wherever you get your
podcast you can find an archive of every
episode all of our show notes and a lot
more at energy g. mit.edu
podcasts and you can learn more about
the work of the energy initiative and
the energy transition at energy. mit.edu
our original podcast artwork is by
zeitler Design special thanks to all the
people at Mighty and MIT who make this
show possible I'm Cara Miller and I'm
Rob ster thanks for listening
[Music]