really excited to be with you all today
because uh we like lined up with some
new exciting results that we can share
today uh so you guys are going to see
some new stuff I put at the end though
so you have to listen through all the
other normal stuff but I think I think
you'll find it exciting um so yeah I'll
just start by introducing future house
so um future house is a a nonprofit
based in San Francisco funded primarily
by Eric Schmidt um and uh we're about 20
people we have a wet lab that's what's
in the background um and uh we're trying
to basically solve big problems in in
automating science and a lot of it is
focused in the domain of
biology so uh before we talk about Ai
and science um I think over the last
maybe 20 years or so the kind of nature
of science has been changing so this is
a plot of the number of papers submitted
to Archive uh as a function of month and
you can see sort of around where chat
gbt is introduced we don't really see
that much of a change in this sort of
trend of increasing number of papers um
there's a little bit of a dip during the
pandemic and then you know sort of
picked up right around when chat gbt was
released but basically we've been seeing
more and more papers now and actually I
think just a couple days ago archive
announced they hit 25,000 monthly
submissions um this access only goes up
to 23,000 so you can see it's out of
date um uh six months later lat and also
the kind of papers there's more papers
being published every year also the kind
of papers being published is changing so
in 1980 the number of paper authors was
about one and now the number of
co-authors is reaching uh about five I
didn't have data all the way up to today
but I think it's it's pretty close to
five now and so it's not only more
papers but also the complexity to the
number of sort of Specialists that's
required to get a paper published is is
increasing um and so basically from a
from a perspective of someone trying to
just do science you know forget AI
you're having an increase in the sort of
intellectual bottlenecks of doing
science basically you need to consider
more and more papers every year the you
know the reference sections and papers
is growing the number of papers in your
field is growing the number of journals
in your field is probably also growing
as well and so we see you know about
five million papers per year um and I
think it's now going to be seven million
for this most most recent year and
there's about 250 million papers out
there today so you're seeing like you
know pretty big percentage growth in the
number of research papers
and also the cost of data is is coming
down as well so I have here a number of
$200 for a whole genome sequence of a
human um is about a dollar per gig of
sequencing I hear from Pharma companies
that it's actually closer to like 80
to100 per per whole genome sequen so
we're seeing you know a rapid drop in um
in the cost somebody's shaking their
head in the back disagree yeah
$500 all right we can we can we can
quibble on this I talked to to the to
the VP of AI of uh of Ro I think it was
and he was saying they were down to $100
but but interesting all right so maybe
$500 it's fine um and then also there's
there's less disruptive paper so along
with basically the increase in in like
literature we have to go through there's
multiple measures of basic that decline
in the productivity of science I think
this one is maybe a little more
complicated complicated there's this
paper put out by um uh uh Park and Funk
and
basically they tried to contr for the
number of papers that are that are
coming out and they basically looked at
you know a few top journals and saw how
often like a sort of canonical citation
was displaced by another one so like
maybe there's something about you know
how the ribosome works and there's
another paper that comes out that has a
better description of it how often does
that displace the previous one and we
see that in biology specifically the
number of these these disruptive
disruptive papers is going down I think
you know it's hard to measure things
like disruptive papers um but you can
also see this in in sort of productivity
in the pharmaceutical industry right so
this this thing called eooms law which
is kind of out of date is not as true
but still we're seeing you know over a
billion dollars per per FDA approved
drug right now in research expenditures
um I've heard people argue that's you
know an R&D tax loophole and and also
it's no longer holds but uh anyway
there's a lot of signals I think that
show that it's getting harder and harder
to to make you know uh advances in the
frontier of Science and so basically the
conclusion of all of this is that modern
science is hard okay and so when we
think about what are the next kind of
big breakthroughs uh that that are going
to come out um they're really hard to
even conceptualize as fitting in one
paper or one equation or one sort of
breakthrough right and so I think the
the kind of scale of science is reaching
a point where it may not be just one you
know group or may not be one or two
groups and even if it's a Consortium it
may be difficult for a whole Consortium
to work together coherently on a problem
and so that's sort of where future house
comes in is that you're set up as trying
to take some of the advances in in Ai
and apply them to automate the processes
of these intellectual bottlenecks
growing in scientific
discovery so um that's sort of the
mission right so so a lot of the the
work that I'll talk to you today about
is different ways that we can try to
accelerate Discovery so before we get
too far um you know I think uh everyone
talks about large language models and
they're doing programming and they can
schedule your restaurant reservations
and book a plane ticket for you so can
they just do biology with with no effort
at all um so I mean obviously it sounds
ridiculous but we did want to see to
measure it like you know is there some
like Benchmark we can look at to see the
progress in biology and so we looked at
some of the existing benchmarks so this
is MM Pro this is kind of one of these
commonly used benchmarks to see how good
language models are here is one of the
questions from the biology category so
as of 2017 how many one-year-olds have
been vaccinated against any disease so
when people say you know these models
are you know getting 80% or superhuman
performance on biology these are the
kinds of questions you're using to
measure it and um I don't know about you
all but I don't come across this kind of
you know difficult intellectual task on
a daily basis
um's another one from the data set I
just thought was interesting uh title of
this album this one I found very
interesting it's find lthm of 3 to the
two okay see I feel like if you pulled a
group of scientists they would disagree
on what the logarithm of 3 to the two is
right the base two could be base e could
be base 10 I actually unfortunately I
didn't write down the answer in my slide
notes so I don't know what is the
official official answer that large
language models choose for this
question and so you know people have
recognized that and so the sort of like
best effort model or sorry Benchmark
right now is something called Humanity's
last
exam catchy name can't forget it um but
really even look at the questions the
questions are still textbook questions
like these are questions which have a
clear correct answer and it's like
you're trying to just you know solve
some kind of known problem it doesn't
really get at the frontier of
science so at futur s we put together a
a benchmark we put down put together two
now I'm going to talk about one we put
out in June but we put out a new one a
couple like a week ago but what we tried
to do is capture some of the things that
we come across in our own work so I have
one on the right hand side which is
cloning Center this is made from like
PhD students lab notebooks questions
that they actually faced um and then we
convert them into like questions that we
could measure uh uh with multiple choice
answers multiple choice answers is a
really hard thing to do I'm going to
talk at the end of my talk about how to
get away from multiple choice answers
but just it's so much easier to evaluate
the models with multiple choice answers
so a lot of the work in these things is
making sure they're good distractors as
they're called um but then we also have
things like lit QA L QA was built to be
a bunch of um questions that you could
only answer by finding some specific
paper in the literature and reading the
full text paper of that the full text of
that paper so the ideaas to get away
from like the memorization we don't want
to measure if the models have memorized
all of scientific literature we want to
see if they can answer a new kind of
question and then cqa is just like uh
just working with biological sequence
data we also did things that are
multimodal I won't really talk about
those but um basically can you read a
table and not just like convert the
table into text but can you actually
answer a meaningful question about the
table so we put out this Benchmark and
we measured we hired a bunch of PhD
biologists if any of you want to make
some money on the side you can also be a
future house contractor to take tests
and pit yourself against AI but we hire
these humans as in in the green bar and
you can see that the humans are just
destroying the models in every single
category except for reading tables which
I find to be very interesting but I
think also like um uh it kind of makes
sense because we really couldn't have
that hard of questions on reading tables
uh but anyway so I think and you know
this is random right so this is the
random line here so most of these models
are right around random and I think this
captures much better the experience of
someone who does science with what
happens when you go to chat gb.com right
if you go to chat gbt and you put in
your questions a lot of times it's just
like not missing or it's not getting the
point and I think this Benchmark kind of
captures that uh experience uh better
whereas you know you you see other
benchmarks they're all you know the the
AI is super human already um I do want
to mention like one interesting thing
that we found in this is that uh um you
know these reasoning models have been
coming out now and even though reasoning
models actually help with some
benchmarks like protocol QA which is
basically lab protocols we make a very
clear mistake in the protocol such that
it would be impossible to do reasoning
models get better at that spotting those
mistakes but other ones these like lab
these cloning scen which is coming from
Lab notebooks reasing models don't do
any better right so there's really
something missing from these models to
to accomplish these
tasks okay so um basically we have to do
some work and so at future house we've
been trying to build AI systems and so
AI systems are things like agents that
as language models connected with tools
that you as a scientist might use um
like Google Scholar or like you know uh
benchling or um leod Dynamics and so you
know basically what we're doing future
house one two steps one two three we
built an organization that is built
around trying to to build scientific
agents that can use these tools uh we
measured human uh performance on these
things and we are able to exceed Human
Performance and now we're trying to get
to like making scientific discoveries at
scale all right so what is an
agent this is a real question here um so
uh I think we try to use the the like
nomenclature from reinforcement learning
if any of you know a little bit about
reinforcement learning basically you
can't really describe an agent without
describing the Environ en that it's in
so we have um an environment here and we
have the agent that is is using tools
inside of an environment and it
communicates back and forth to this
environment using natural language and
so instead of like you know I have an
arithm arithmetic question here and I
answer it using a calculator rather than
just trying to do the arithmetic itself
and this agent is a language model that
uses these tools to answer the question
and sort of an agent is basically
coupled to this environment which is a
set of tools that are specific for
solving a task um this is super tiny but
basically we we tried to put out a repo
um I we succeeded in making a a code
repository to Define your own agents and
use them uh in code uh for your own
tasks like if you have a bunch of tools
you want to use you can combine them
with uh with the language model
question yes are all the questions text
based questions um so uh in our like
repository no you can use uh multimodal
inputs um most stuff I'm going to talk
about today is mostly text but some of
it and has like uh molecular structures
which are graphs but usually we
represent the graphs as a string so it
ends up being text in the
end um so a lot of the work that we've
done at future house is basically how do
we go beyond just taking a language
model putting it into an environment and
praying that it works so a lot of the
work is basically how do you train these
things to do better and you know in the
interest of time I'm not going to get
into a lot of detail about how we
actually train these things but it's um
it involves you know just sort of normal
uh deep learning methods like you build
a computational graph you take a
derivative you propagate through the the
the graph so before we you know get into
the training thing like if I just take
an an agent one of these agents that on
the previous slides you saw were doing
very poorly and I give them some tools
we see there's some gain so basically I
have here like this is how well the
models did without tools and then I give
them tools and they get a little bit
better okay I give them tools they get a
little bit better not huge game right so
so it's nice that if you just tell the
llm no you don't know how to do
arithmetic use the calculator tool or no
you don't know how to read you know you
don't know how to translate from a
nucleotides to amino acids you have to
use the nucleotide translation
tool but then what we do is we actually
take these these models that can do okay
and then we basically let them try it
out and this is showing you like uh this
little diagram showing you all the
different tool calls that they make so
each color is a different tool and then
in this case they're trying to do
molecular cloning anybody who done
molecular cloning before but
uh I to learn that quite a bit for this
project but essentially um we have a
bunch of questions about M cloning and
then we let these agents go give it a
try and then the ones that are
successful we Mark with green and the
ones that are unsuccessful we Mark in
red and then we throw away the red ones
and then we just train on these
successful
trajectories and at the end you
basically can start doing these cycles
of let the agents go try it out see if
they make the right uh plasma um or get
the right insertion and then if they got
it right we like take those successful
trajectories and then we train the model
to do like this is good job and over
time this is just like GPU hours and
this is like what a Frontier Model is
like you know if you take these Frontier
models we get better and better and
these are our own models these are 14
billion parameter models sounds like a
lot but actually you can run that on
your laptop no problem and so we can get
past these Frontier models which as you
know are like hundreds of billions of
parameters and you can't run them on
your own laptop they have to be run on
you know special data center GPU uh
servers and we did this on these two
tasks one of these cqa this is the one
about molecular cloning lqa is about
using tools like Google Scholar citation
graph uh basically to to answer
questions about
literature what's interesting is that
when you start this is like what the the
start looks like these are the
trajectories that we just get from
randomly trying it out and then over
time it looks like this and so basically
we start here and it's exploring a whole
bunch sometimes it's calling like the um
the annotate plasmid tool like five
times you know and doesn't really help
to annotate it a bunch of times and then
here it gets much more focused and then
it does a better job at tasks It's
actually an 8 billion Prim Mon it's 14
it's 8 billion Prim model
yeah great question um we basically have
some so so the question was how do you
define successful trajectories um the
tasks are things like um I don't know uh
uh how many what's the longest open
reading frame in this plas okay and then
so we know like what is the longest open
reading frame in the plasmid from like
doing it by hand we can see if the model
can figure that out from uh from looking
at it that's example question like I
think the they're more like how do you
clone M Scarlet into this uh into this
plasmid so it'll go into eoli and
express um and then it has to go like to
add Gene and find the right sequences
and download them and then come up with
the protocol then result an expression
so uh in the end we get these agents out
they can run to do these M cloning
things and they're costing you know a
very small amount of money so these are
basically our models here and then these
are the frontier models so we're like
two or three orders of magnitude lower
in cost one of the cool things you can
do with that is that if it's this cheap
you can actually just run it a thousand
times and then take the consensus you
can just have a majority vote so you
have thousand agents and they all try
like what's the next step and they vote
like I think we should you know I think
we should do uh um Gibson assembly and
then some like no I don't think we
should use Gibson assembly I think we
should do know restriction enzyme
cloning and they take the the vote and
then they go with whatever is voted for
and that actually boosts accuracy by
quite a
bit so when we're done with this we're
done with training we have a trained
agent what we do is we connect it with
the environment and we package the whole
thing up and we call it a crow and so
it's a crow because crows the birds can
actually like speak uh English you guys
know this you go to YouTube you can see
videos of crows speaking they can speak
like a parrot can speak but they know
how to use tools and so this is like you
know the the bird part and this is the
the tool use part all
right uh so here are some of the crows
which we've uh launched at at future
house um I shouldn't say that we've
launched so protein Crow is something
that's coming soon made by Manu here so
if you have any questions about protein
Crow you can talk to Manu um it's a
really exciting uh tool for basically
just doing protein design in this kind
of environment um and then we have uh
molecular cloning Crow it wasn't
actually cool enough that we called it
Mo cloning Crow because um I don't know
I we just didn't find MC cloning that
exciting so we didn't really push too
hard in it then we have chem cro which
uh Sam who's going to give the next talk
who maybe here soon is she did the work
on chem and then paper QA um which we've
retrospectively called Wiki Crow which
does literature research oh I so I do
have a couple slides on protein Crow um
I'm going to go through this super quick
um uh but basically protein Crow has
some uh existing deep learning models
existing tools uh like bioinformatics
that can call our literature research
agent and then here's an example of like
design 92 binders for
pdl1 so we have a video here yes so here
is like uh proin Crow uh calling the
tools so this is sort of the steps that
the the agent is taken here uh sometimes
the models will emit like a rationale
for why they made the decision so this
is like what it's thinking it's doing in
the in the trajectory and then it's
calling these different tools that call
these underlying deep learning models
like protein M protein mpnn or RF
diffusion and you can see it's basically
reading through the output from these
tools and then over time it's Gathering
into these into like a library of of
known binders that we want or sorry of
binders that thinks are good and at the
end um because we're uh oh did I lose my
internet connection well anyway there
should be like a video of a protein
rotating here
um but anyway uh we did do wet lab
validation and found that some of these
binders actually did pl1 so it's very
exting I have a question yes I'm
actually just curious why you didn't
sort of pursue the molecular cloning
tool a bit more because I mean people
are doing a lot on protein design and
chemical design and to me actually I
think the most interesting thing and the
molecular cloning if you were to make it
a tool is it's one of these common lab
techniques that I mean it so often fails
um I'm sure everyone who's done cloning
has an example of something that you
know looked like it was going to totally
work and then it didn't and uh I'm sort
of interested if there were any
conversations you and people on the team
had about having a model that actually
gave you like success rates of of
cloning and speeding that up I think
that's sort of actually the most
interesting thing to pursue in that
space a lot of people know how to do the
cloning but yeah predicting whether it's
going to work uh I don't know if there's
a lot of tools out there that really
tell us that so there is um uh
a
um yeah basically the reason we didn't
really pursue it is we have to make this
kind of calculus of like how impactful
is the work like where you know are
people going to be really excited about
it and I think mro cloning is a great
thing for a lot of you know molecular
biologists they will be excited about it
but I think it's just harder to make it
understandable as high impact work so
I'm happy to go back to it but it's like
one of these things too where you need
somebody on the team to be really
excited about a project to push it
forward and everybody in the biology
team is just like not super excited
about doing let I'm like to validate
these models but if anybody you know
yeah right if anybody has the passion
for cloning Crow email me and I I we
will happily send you designs and you
will know that your cloning experiments
will be leading to a greater
cause okay so I want to talk now about
paper QA so this is again an agent in an
environment and here we're I'm going to
show you basically a complete sort of
measure against humans eat humans and
what can you actually do with these sort
of automated scientific agents so paper
QA has uh a few tools one of them is
Citation traversal so basically I have a
paper I think is relevant who cited this
paper and what does this paper site um
paper search which is like a Google
Scholar
query um gather evidence which is where
like okay I have a bunch of papers I
think are relevant let me read them Page
by page and see if there's any passages
in that paper that could be helpful for
answering my question and then it
generates an answer basically takes all
the information it knows and tries to
answer a question and I probably should
have said this but the input to paper QA
is a question like has anybody studied
this before or List you know three
hypotheses for how to make a room
temperature super
conductor um and in fact actually now
this is out of date is that we now
actually have clinical trials as a way
can search to can search through
clinical trials and we also have like
open targets so we can look at things
like gws vas you know henic data um
that's put together into a nice API by
open
targets which has dep map as well which
came from the rooad um so here's an
example of what this looks like so um we
have here like Has anyone used llm
agents to automate the discovery of a
novel molecular chroma for that's the
question I asked it um you can see the
basically the the decisions the agent
makes at the top left so it's finding
papers these are some papers it's found
and it's trying to download them from
various sources like preprints uh from
uh Open Access literature and then now
basically it's reading Page by Page each
of the the documents that it downloaded
and um it's basically decided okay these
were interesting passages so hold on
them and then so now it's giving the
answer to the question okay and then yes
somebody's done it in fact it brought up
a paper called chro which Sam Cox will
be presenting on the next
one okay so um when we started this
project we were this is January 1 2024
we have a benchmark L QA which I've
described before we were getting like
35% with our agent and then um you know
over time doing a lot of changes
improvements making the tools better
like getting uh our ability to get more
papers um we able to get to basically
right around where human level
performances and we hired like
biologists like PhD level biologists to
do this and then after that we were able
to do this training procedure on it and
we brought it from 70% up to you know
90% so basically if you ask a PhD
biologist and we pay them like $10 per
correct question like answer this
question you have unlimited time you can
use any tools you would like you can use
Google Scholar Etc um they get you know
a 70% accuracy or so and we get 90%
accuracy on this so yeah pretty cool I'm
sure if we charged $1,000 you know like
if we give him ,000 the question I'm
sure the accuracy would go up but I
think it's like reaching the point where
it's like okay for $10 like I'll put in
this amount of effort and we're able to
beat that effort now answering like
these lit QA questions which are
multiple choice questions that are on
you know Niche topics that is not really
represented of doing science so we
decided to try to find like a task that
we didn't train on that is like uh still
maybe better representation of
synthesizing knowledge and so what we
did is we basically had our system write
Wikipedia articles and then we took
human Wikipedia and just to set a
control we looked at the human proteum
so we have every single Gene that
encodes for a protein and we basically
found which ones have Wikipedia articles
written by humans and which one and then
we wrote corresponding ones written by
our system then we extracted fragments
so like a paragraph or a couple
sentences from each Wikipedia the AI
gener Wikipedia or the human Wikipedia
we had PhD ologist again grade which
ones they thought were more accurate and
we beat the human Wikipedia on
accuracy um and then we did another
project which I think Sam Sam you g talk
about this yeah okay great so I won't
get into this too much but one of the
cool things you can do with this is you
can actually take a claim like uh I
don't know um uh the peak uh intensity
of light of the sun is green um and then
you can go see if anybody's contradicted
that literature before by the way it is
green it's crazy if any of you have
little kids like my son is like you know
what color is you know the sun it's like
oh it's yellow and it's like okay but I
heard at school that it's white because
the astronauts on the International
Space Station take a picture and it's
white and then I'm like trying to figure
it out apparently it's also green
because I feel like it's black body
radiation but the peak intensity is that
green color so I don't know what Co sun
is
anymore yes question just just I just
wanted to follow to follow up on that I
actually had this question on the AR
slide like
yeah you if you're training the models
on the like existing Corpus of the
science
papers what's your opinion on the
reproducibility crisis like is there any
way to mitigate that because if there
are like thousands of papers especially
on archive where they like not be
reviewed significant like maybe like 10
in the worst case 20 20% of those are
like just not good yeah yeah this is a
great question so um I I'll give five
answers to this question because I think
about it a lot okay answer number one is
that we use something called the
finished publication forums ranking of
Journal tiers so these are things that
identify if a journal is predatory or if
it's like you know a pure reviewed
Journal so we use that on all sources
that come into our system obviously
won't catch archive but that is like one
big issue is there's a lot of journals
there's a lot of like papers in like
mdpi or something or or even like posos
there's like a lot of papers that are um
just like not good quality so we try to
use that we also use citation count you
know um I'm sorry and I hope we come up
with a better idea at some point in the
future but for now um citation count is
a good measure of if something is like
you know just not really I don't want to
it's just not in mainstream so it's like
there's a lot of paper you guys may not
know this but if you go search like has
anybody shown that like putting a magnet
around your neck is going to make you
like cure your can answer there are
Papers written about that there are Pap
about the cosmic memory of water you
know there's papers about all kinds of
crap it's crazy but these journals these
like bottom tier journals that just
publish anything and so you have to have
some kind of system and citation count
is one signal there but I've written on
my blog plugging my blog here I have
blog diffuse .1 where I put my unserious
academic work so I've written I made
some tools and I've had thoughts about
how to do how to spot fraudulent papers
but I just don't I'm not an expert in
this topic so I just have some hobest
ideas but I don't think we've solved it
and it is something that's even more
important for LMS because LMS are
extremely
goal
question yes so the question is is it
aware of retractions and Corrections yes
we do use retraction watches uh DB which
is hosted on Cross ref to check if
something is retracted I will say that
retractions are very like like it's a
volunteer run database it's not always
up to date and so that is not really
well done but we do we do use the the
existing sources there question yeah so
um I know one major challenge for those
large language models is integration of
new information and in research I think
this is like a super important thing
since the new development in the last
two years would be very fundamental for
people to solve the new biological
question so how do you plan to tackle
this yeah so this system that we're
talking about this this agent system um
we tell it to only use information from
the sources we provide to it and so
we've really tried to make sure that the
model is only using scientific
literature or the or the clinical trials
or the henic data is only trying to use
that to answer the questions and one of
the reasons why I don't know if I should
mention this but like every time it
emits a sentence every single sentence
has a citation and that citation is to a
page number on a source so you can track
the Providence of everything that comes
out of this model down to like the
individual page in a research paper uh
sorry I think what that means like oh
like if you want to build like a um AI
biologist how do you make sure that he
how do you feed new information to it
without retraining the big
model right so I guess what I'm trying
to articulate is that um this model
tries to only reason from information we
present to it and so we just make sure
the information we present is from like
recent papers or from sources that we're
confident in and so we're trying to I
mean you're getting at a good point is
that like the dream is that you can
separate out the model's knowledge
Corpus from its ability to reason
because right now they're somehow
coupled so you need really really big
models to do reasoning but then you like
have all these problems like then you
need a really big model and if it's like
three years out a date it doesn't know
more recent stuff and so yeah we try as
much as we can to separate out like the
ability for the models to use
information and reason from their
ability to memorize all of
science related question yeah is it
possible to validate the this notion
that like whenever it is telling you
something it has the citation that's
directly from the thing ET yes so in
fact this is like the majority of this
eval here was to make sure that the
citations and the claims that are in the
Wikipedia articles it writes are
consistent with the site sources that it
cited and so this like 86% those 14%
like failure that is when it cited a
source but it either mischaracterized
the source or it made a claim that um
didn't site a source and it should have
been cited so those are examples of of
failure so that's the sort of failure
mode of of that and actually that's how
we this whole eval is just are you
consistent with the sources you site and
are you accurate within the context of
those sources so humans hallucinate at a
higher rate than than the language
model wait one more question and then I
have so many more more exciting things I
about that you trained the model from
scratch or do you use a pre-trained
alignment ont to only look at these
sources because if it's the letter it
may be difficult to tell if it's indeed
only looking at those sources
or this is a good question so this plot
I'm showing here this lit QA Benchmark
we made lit QA two different ways we
made lit QA like we made a set of 60
questions or 55 questions or something
where all of the papers were published
after the cut off date of the
pre-trained language model so those
papers were not in the pre-training
Corpus and then what we did is we asked
it questions that it had to look at the
paper to answer okay so then we're like
measuring you know does does it really
like look at these papers or is it just
trying to recall and then like attribute
post Haw and the second thing is that we
also check on the on the data set like
we go to these pre-trained models and we
ask the questions of the pre-train model
without access to these tools without
access to the papers you know what's the
answer to these questions so let's we
have a measure of like a baseline
performance and I think it's like 25% on
this on this Benchmark of how good the
pre-train model does without access to
the tools and then so the other point is
that when this bump from like here to
here is when we switch to our own model
that was um you know like 8 billion
parameters and of course 8 billion is a
lot but that's not enough to fit all of
scientific literature so it's not really
at the same scale of something like you
know um GPT 4 which is um you know over
100 billion
parameters awesome great
questions um I just want to show you
guys like uh one quick application here
so like here's an example a question
that you can ask this is there genetic
evidence supporting tr2 association with
tated neurog generation uh speculate on
the plausible mechanism and your
response okay and then it gives you know
some ideas about this and it cites these
and this is these this is about the
sources say like on page one page eight
to nine um so you can trace back to see
where it came from and then if you look
at the sources here um you can see you
know which which sources it came
from and then you can see all the
reasoning process like why it shows
different ources what score it gave the
sources how it came to the conclusion of
them etc
etc cool so I have one more which you'll
show here is we have this website has
anyone.com and you can ask a question
like okay has anyone ever made split gfp
that's one's too easy okay let's see has
anyone determined the specific mechanism
by which pfna disrupts thyroid function
so we can click over to this one and
then it will go through and basically
give you an answer like no no one has
determined this conclusion and it has
you know some description why it came to
that conclusion and it has these sources
cited and then you can go back and you
can see okay like what did it site it
cited this paper which has five
citations it's from a peer review
journal has 81 citations from piew
Journal this is 250 and from the highest
quality piew Journal etc etc you can see
like how long it thought for this was a
a cached question but it took you know
three minutes to answer this question
cost 32 cents I don't know why you guys
need to know that but that's how much we
paid um yeah cool so then um the last
sort of application I'll mention is is
this Wiki Crow so there's a website Wiki
crow. and what we did is we basically
finished off Wikipedia for the human
prodium so there's about 2,700 articles
in Wikipedia for the human prodium um so
there's quite a few missing there's
about 20,000 protein coding genes uh in
human genome and so we basically you
know finished writing uh about 177,000
articles took about 48 hours and so then
you have like a an upto-date version and
I'll mention too that some of Wikipedia
is out of date we can run this every 48
Hours you know to update the knowledge
of of science on the human so if you go
to the website you can put in any random
gen that you you want like lipg um and
then it has you know some some
information here uh about uh the the
Gene and the structure and then it has
the overview here and this is all
generated from our system and you can
read through it and basically if you
ever come across a gene from some kind
of screening and you don't know what it
does uh you could try this out and maybe
you find it's
interesting one of the cool things about
this work though do I have this slide
yeah okay great so one of the cool
things about this is that there has not
really been a text embedding of human
proteum right so like you can obviously
embed the proteins where you can embed
the genes but what we're able to do is
actually since we have now a text
description of what is the function
what's the disease interactions like
what are the physical interactions of
all these different person coding genes
we can actually embed them all so like
you know take all the words in it and
then find out which ones are similar
they have a complete embedding of the
human proteum and you see like things
that you expect like here's a bunch of
receptors right here's a bunch of DNA
Associated ones and inside the DNA
Associated ones or a lot of
transcription factors and so what we did
from that is we actually took that
embedding data and we built this uh
related Gene section so these related
genes are genes that have like a close
text embedding that you wouldn't like
find from any other way except for
synthesizing the knowledge of the genes
anyway kind of cool maybe
interesting so if you embed the entire
text summary of the gene I imagine you
get something very different from taking
each section or or subsections and
embedding those and
you get much more diverse neighborhood
trying to find okay you know these set
of genes are membrane proteins in these
types of cells versus the entire more
average out thing is that an experiment
you ran um so actually I think these are
run on just the overview okay because
what you're getting at is is important
because for some genes we don't know
what like disease associations they have
so that section is empty so this is
around the overview which is like a
summary of all the sections but you're
right you could do something like I only
want to know the physical interactions
and then you can build like a new
physical interaction graph that is up to
date you know and and covers you know as
many papers as we possi can but it might
be more interesting uh as AOL for you
know probing like what kind of you know
Gene uh or which protein protein
interactions should I be looking at yeah
cool so um you know like I said one of
the things that's unique about future
house is we're like an Engineering Group
and a science group so rather than just
make this like a demo thing we like uh
built it into a platform and so we can
run I think this is these are out ofate
numbers basically we can run 25 things
per minute um we have about 150 million
papers we can look at and so we could
write a Wikipedia page for every human
disease every 3.5 days so basically
every three and a half days we summarize
all the new literature rewrite it for
all the 25,000 human diseases um we
could also check for contradictions in
every single paper on archive that comes
out every month basically summary of
where this fits does it disagree agree
what's consensus on literature um we're
getting there but we're almost you know
10x in this capacity and so we could
check every single Paper that's
published every year for contradictions
uh literature disagreement literature um
we could rewrite all of Wikipedia every
3 weeks as
well cool so now that I have exhausted
almost all of my time I'm going to tell
you about exciting new results okay so
um over the last like couple months
there's been a real big change in how uh
language models work so we have been
stuck in this Paradigm called
pre-training for a long time this is
probably something many of you familiar
with it's basically to get a smarter
model you need more data you need more
compute and they got to get bigger this
is like gpt2 3 4 right GPT 5 and it's
become a really difficult thing to scale
and it also is very interesting
phenomena is that um pulling all of your
compute into one big model and then
serving it for a very tiny cost to you
is a great business strategy and that
means there collectivization basically
all of the compute is being concentrated
in just a few organizations because they
can make these really big models that
then have a low marginal cost and then
there's this thing called scaffolding
this is mostly of the work that I
presented was that we basically used
domain knowledge to put together some
tool tools and information that help the
the language models do better in
scientific environments there's a new
kind of Paradigm which has come out
recently which is reasoning models and
so reasoning models require domain
knowledge but they require much less
data and they require much less compute
and so I think we're going to see like a
real like a reverse of the trend where
it's basically becoming more and more
Out Of Reach for academics to do any
kind of work in this area because big
models just win and so now things are
actually flattening back out where you
can actually have small models that you
can use at a more expensive compute like
it takes 10 minutes for them to answer a
question rather than 10 seconds but you
can get the same performance and you can
make them domain
specialized um so I'm going to skip over
this but basically I'll just want to
show you some evidence of this new
dimension of scaling so this is sort of
this is a benchmark comm's last exam
again so basically here's the sort of
typical scaling we have like gbt
40 pretty big model then Sonic comes out
it's a little bit bigger model and then
01 comes out and then we have this like
change from traditional pre-training
models to now reasoning models and you
can you can see this Benchmark went from
being whatever 8% to then becoming like
30% in a just matter of a few weeks as
models were released that were reasoning
and you have this like new dimension
where you can basically make the models
um not just bigger but you can make them
think for longer you can make them
specialized in domain by training them
on reasoning in in one topic and this
has exploded into the open source
community so here's a plot of a bunch of
recent models from Mostly open source
groups and this is model size and then
this is the accuracy on mathematics and
you can see that we are getting models
this model here is 1.5 billion
parameters it is matching V3 which is
680 billion parameters so this model
cost probably $100 million a train this
model cost about $500 a train and so
we're able to get this huge flattening
of these language models with reasoning
and you can see everything at the top
has reasoning and so reasoning is just
completely you know just destroyed our
predictive uh Power in this field these
quen models these qu models are like as
you increase the model size the
performance gets better right and even
it starts to diminish in returns as you
make them bigger and bigger these are
all trained in the same pattern
completely gone so now we have like a
real big you know disruption in how we
think about language
models and so the question you know for
for us at future house and I think many
people in the community is can we do
this in scientific reasoning because
it's only been shown for mathematics yet
but there's now this opportunity to try
to apply this kind of new I don't know
new economics of of language models in
scientific domains so here is some
output from a reasoning model we've been
training on chemistry so what happens is
that you still have these sort of like
chemistry specialized models where you
can give it molecules and predict the
property of it or give it a reaction
predicts the reaction outcome but now it
gives you a reasoning Trace about how it
came to the conclusion and so what
happens is we're building these domain
specific models that have these scaling
Properties by reasoning in a very long
thought in English
so this is uh one where it's just you
know this kind of a simple chemical
reaction but you can read through like
how it reasons to the reaction I think
it's very exciting as a scientist to be
like oh yeah I can see how it came to
the conclusion but also these reasoning
tokens improve
performance um I'm going to skip over
this plot here but basically the blue
one is is our reasoning model this is
very early this is like literally
trained for like uh like three days so
it's going to need to be cooking for a
little bit longer but the red is 03 mini
High which is sort of the best Frontier
Model out there and so we're beating it
a lot these different tasks I'll show
you guys some examples of tasks in a
moment we have human comparison for one
of these things and so we beat humans on
on predicting the outcome of a chemical
reaction um and uh it's very exciting
very exciting time for us future ask
right now so what the idea behind
reasoning models is that we don't
actually have to have a bunch of like
prompt completion like a bunch of work
through problems we need instead as
verifiable rewards so here's an example
of a verifiable reward propose a
modification to this molecule to
increase its solubility by about One log
s it's about like you know log s s is
the solil water without affecting its
scaffold so this is kind of like a
question that a medicinal chemist might
ask is like okay I need to like a adjust
the solubility molecule but I know it
has drug activity so I don't want to
adjust the scaffold so this is an
example of a question where there is no
one right answer but we can verify a
proposed answer and what's exciting
about this is this kind of represents a
lot of the tasks we do in biology or a
lot of tasks we do in chemistry is like
not often there's like one solution but
we might be able to characterize a
proposed
solution and it's also possible of doing
new tasks that was just like never
possible before so there's an example of
a task which is totally insane it
shouldn't work okay I'll read you the
question the reasoning is kind of
detailed but it says um a a c17
h157 metabolite from lais lolus was
identified what's a biologically
plausible compound for this as Smiles so
this is the molecular formula you can
get molecular formulas Dirt Cheap you
get these from MPC there's you know
probably millions of these formulas of
of things extracted organisms finding
the molecular structure is actually very
hard and it requires like an expert to
look at NMR data it takes a long time
here the model reasons through like
knowing about the metabolism knowing you
know this kind of organism class what
are possible structures that could fit
this formula we gave this task to humans
and they were just like this don't be
silly no one can do this right basically
it's it's really hard as a human to sit
there and reason about all this while
building up a a molecule that has the
exact stomry of what you want and this
is the reason very interesting to to
read through it basically it comes to
the conclusion about what is the right
structure and this is one of these tasks
where when you see the training curve if
the model gets z% 0% 0% after like
whatever 12 hours no Frontier Model gets
anything nonzero and all of a sudden
starts to be able to do this task it's
super exciting
question I can just repeat your question
if it's short oh there you
go I've uh worked with people before who
have actually been trying to use you
know who found it difficult to get
actually maybe this last year maybe the
world is different now yeah um uh have
found it difficult for to produ get LMS
to produce Smiles that are actually like
syntactically correct yes so let me show
you this this right here this is can you
make a molecule where I've completed
half of it okay so I have a molecule
I've completed some fraction of it can
you complete it and make it sure it's
valid okay so it gets 96% of this task
in the Frontier Model o03 mini gets % on
this task and so you're right now to be
to be fair like if you do O3 mini on
like a small molecule or like you know
something simple like what's the smiles
of arginine no problem but these are all
very large like natural products and
they're very hard to close all the Rings
and satisfy the valencies so is this
something where this is like a sub one
of these subm modules that you were
talking about before where you can you
can call a no this is a completely it's
just a one language model one purpose
built reasoning language model only for
these tasks so no tools involved here
very exciting and it's also small enough
that it can run on a laptop so I think
when we get this model finished people
can find tune it on whatever chemistry
domain tasks they want and I think we're
going to set up a recipe that people can
repeat for you know protein function for
enzyme function for genome
models awesome so I think this is you
know an example of like just one of the
things that's been I think one more
slide yeah so one of the things that's
been difficult are we out of time oh
okay sorry one more question
um I think what might be interesting
with this um and really show its power
is um sort of like zero shot is kind of
cool um so like with EVO right and they
have the cast system do you know how
many samples they drew uh I think they
drew 1,00 two million they drew two
million cast yeah to do the the invivo
validation right so they drew two
million of them oh they sampled two
million yeah and then and then they did
U alignment and all these things then
they got 11 but then only worked yeah
because they have 11 you know that they
didn't initially pick 11 they probably
picked 10 the 10 didn't work and they
picked another one because no one picks
11 so I think so I I think one and you
know it was called zero shot but
whatever um so I think this is kind of
cool if you could
demonstrate chemistry just to match them
and show no it's like truly zero shot I
know sorry it's a bad question it's but
I think that that's kind of cool
actually if you can do truly zero
shot um yeah so
I think I think you're on something
there but I do want to say is that if
for me if I'm given two models one model
is really good accuracy and one model
gives me a long like page reasoning
description in English about how it came
to the conclusion I would rather have
that one and it really is very
interesting to see the conclusion what's
really nice about the the reasoning is
you can see where it makes mistakes
right or like maybe it doesn't get it
right and you can say go back but assume
this right I think the reasoning itself
I think is just so powerful as a
scientist because these models that are
put out like like Evo 2 is great and I
think um there's been some great
chemistry models out there there's some
good you know protein there protein
structure prediction models but imagine
if you went to Alpha fold and you asked
to fold something and it gave a bunch of
reasoning about why this fold goes here
why this fold goes here right or why it
thinks this should be Helix that would
be Monumental right I think that's one
of the missing pieces for all of this
stuff is like okay great you can do
blackbox accuracy but explain why and so
I I think this model even if it maybe
it's not as good as the the best model
in some of these tasks maybe there's
going to be there's probably a better
model that's out there for some of these
things the fact that it reasons in
English and that it can do all the tasks
right you can combine 15 different tasks
in here make sure the solubility is here
make sure it's not carcinogenic make
sure it's commercially synthesizable in
one step it's really exciting stuff all
right I will just mention that we
actually gave the reasoning traces to
Medicinal chemists that are in the
pharmaceutical industry we don't know
how to die with these things so we've
did way too many like rubri too big of a
rubric but we checked to see like is the
reasoning relevant to the question like
does it go from the you know prompt to
the end is it faithful are there any
like reasoning jumps or it just ends
halfway or doesn't go all the way to the
end um how much is it like a human
reasoning uh is it make any mistakes
like does it hallucinate a structure is
it propos something that's not the right
name of a structure um does it explain
it I actually don't know there's between
this and humanness but I'm not sure and
then readability is like uh are all the
smiles valid or things like that so
again we don't have a baseline we're
figuring that out but the medicinal
chemists were all very impressed and
thought it was a really interesting
useful tool to be able to read the
reasoning in these
predictions awesome so we will release
the model weight soon um and a technical
report but I think it's just such an
exciting breakthrough and I think it's
just going to like this topic of being
able to build these models like we're
talking 50,000 verifiable rewards so I
think in the past it was like okay you
need to bring me 50 billion tokens for
me to train a model in your domain now
you need to bring me 50,000 verifiable
rewards which I think is very achievable
by many different groups
awesome uh yada yada yada uh I will just
mention the last thing is um we actually
I think have made a lot of really great
scientific agents like cloning Crow um
like protein crow like uh paper QA we're
going to be releasing a platform soon
where you can go and by soon I mean like
within weeks where you can go and use
these things yourself and it will have
an API so if you want to like use these
things as Tools in your own workflows
you can call the API or you can use them
and we have a super cool design design
is so cool it's like driving a spaceship
I don't have any pictures of it but it's
going to be
great um cool so uh obviously huge team
here Sam Cox uh is g to give a talk next
about some of this work Mike skinsky uh
led a lot of the paper QA engineering
work um and then Manu God I hope you're
still on here Manu oh
no were you on here ever okay we gotta
get manu's picture Manu did did the work
on protein Pro um and then uh Sam is the
uh director of future house and um yeah
we have big team contributing to this
and uh with that I'll take any
additional questions and thanks for your
attention thank you so uh yeah I'm Sam
I'm at teacher house and also at
University of Rochester and I'm gonna be
talking about work and happened in both
of those places um on automating
chemistry workflows with llm based
agents um I'll start with Kim cro this
work is kind of old now so I know that
all of you have read it and studied it
very
deeply uh but this is kind of silly but
um when I was starting this project I
was like I don't really know how good
llms are at these things I don't have a
good intuition for this um but LMS
probably do because they're very
self-aware so I asked um what are you
good at and what are you bad at when it
comes to science so they're very good at
doing like basic fact retrieval um very
simple problem solving and they have a
high level understanding um but they're
really bad at like obviously any updates
so if you do any computational work or
if you need to reference any literature
it can't really have it doesn't have
updated information um it's really bad
at Advanced problem solving and also it
tends to make errors very
confidently so when we're thinking about
like trying to implement these when we
were thinking about trying to implement
these into uh chemistry workflows um we
started thinking about
agents so kcro follows a chain of
thought process where you give it a
bunch of tools and prompts the tools are
just like python functions like convert
selfies to Smiles or convert the name or
check uh look look up the price plan the
synthesis and it thinks okay what do I
need to do what have I done where am I
at in this process um which of my tools
is best suited for the subtask that I
need to do um what should my input be
and then it uses the tool and decides
and tries to figure out what the tool
told me and where do I go from here so
it's able to iterate and like um react
to failures and do like a react
process when we were developing kcro um
the way that we thought about this is um
we really wanted to kind of make it an
assistant where it like completes um
chemistry tasks so we thought what kind
of questions do chemists even want to
answer um what tools are needed to
answer these questions and then where
does the agent fall short because when
you're developing an agent it's only as
good as the tools that you give it and
it can only do what the like the tools
that you give it and so we ended up
giving um all of these tools here where
we have search tools like paper QA like
um Andrew mentioned web search a bunch
of conversion molecular tools synthesis
tools safety and then some basic link
Chang tools like um man I don't know let
me ask the human or let me try to run
some python
code um the thing that's really
difficult that um we all probably know
and Andrew also mentioned is how in the
world do you even evaluate these things
uh the first method which is really
popular at the time is just asking gp4
um hey you're in the role of a chemistry
teacher evaluating two students one is
gp4 and one is Kim Crow your task is to
basically give them like a review
highlight the strengths and weaknesses
and then also follow give it some grade
um this is a really unbiased method um
all teachers are very unbiased grading
students um but we found that gp4 can't
evaluate the responses that it can't
answer so if you ask it a really hard
question and it gives you a nonsense
answer it doesn't have the knowledge
obviously to evaluate it and so it ends
up um grading based on it like tells you
that it's really good chemistry but
actually it just thinks that it like
flows very nicely or the grammar is very
nice and it evaluates kind of nonsense
so we needed another type of evaluation
and we Ed humans so we gave a team of
chemists and chemical Engineers the
questions the question and then both uh
final answers formatted
identically and so what we're seeing
here is on the left we have the um delta
mean expert scores for gb4 and chro and
in each category we have increasing
difficulty going down so for organic
synthesis task Tas 13 is much more
difficult than task seven where
difficult ulty is like the complexity of
the task the number of steps required
and we see that in like dp24 is not bad
it's able to complete some of the tasks
humans actually prefer it on like 14 and
four and two and 10 um but as the tasks
get more complex it really drops off um
we see that in um both organic synthesis
and chemical logic and knowledge um this
is not surprising I don't know if you've
ever tried to ask like gp4 to plan and
execute a synthesis it can't do that so
this is not super
surprising um and so we found that uh
gb4 gives complete responses which is
great but it has a lot of
hallucinations um that are very
believable in some cases it's hard to
interpret so it doesn't tell you like
how it thought about it necessarily it
just gives you an answer um and it
doesn't have access to any up-to-date
information so some of these would
require like reading a specific paper or
running like a python package that it
just wasn't able to
do uh whereas Kim cro with Kim cro we
found chemically accurate Solutions um
it's great because it's modular and
extensible so all a like all agents so
if you provide like you decided hey I
really want to do protein design you can
provide it with some protein design
tools to do that um although chemistry
is easier and then um it still
occasionally has F flawed conclusions
because it's limited by the llm right
like it still is going to make mistakes
um and it's very limited by the tools
quality um but one of the coolest things
we did with kimc is um we gave some
chromophor data and we said gave it some
instructions all the way on the top left
clean the data um use only the data with
a specific solvent So Pro uh filter it
process it train a random Forest machine
learning model make predictions and then
suggest a synthetic plan for one uh one
with the wavelength closest to 369
nanometers um it did everything that we
said and we get a final answer and then
humans actually synthesized the proposed
molecule and we had it sitting in the
lab and it followed all of the
instructions um so we actually able to
synthesize like a novel chromophor with
kcro where the only human intervention
is giving it the data telling it to do
it and then testing it in the lab
um so with Kim cro we found that LMS can
use tools to complete chemistry tasks
which is not I think like a super
trivial thing um and it can also
complete novel Discovery and design so
we can do novel things with it which
llms can't do on their own um but we
also found that agents are limited by
Tool quality and I didn't go into this
but you can read the paper uh safety is
a really important concern when you
start giving llms the ability to do
chemistry and um like hook it up to a
lab obviously um so that's a big
consideration so the next thing we
started thinking about is like okay Chim
informatics is cool and super difficult
but what if we wanted to do like a
really complex task that maybe runs for
a really long time or has to handle tons
of files or has to do um interact with
like multiple packages that are very
heavy and so we started thinking about
automating molecular Dynamics workflows
with llms
also um so the way that this works
similarly is it follows like this react
framework where it thinks acts observes
and then it decides if it needs to
complete the next sub task or react and
troubleshoot um with this one
specifically compared to Kim cro that
reactive troubleshoot is really
important because um MD is pretty
finicky and so it has to react and like
update its parameters and change things
as it goes um this one had or MD MD Crow
has currently about 45 tools um
including again paper QA for literature
search and then using um databases like
unipro and that sort of thing to get
upto-date information downloading pdb
files and then also interfacing with the
pdb files um simulating with openmm
using Paco and then also some analysis
tools using um MD trash all of the
things that we implemented were in MD um
open mm and MD trash because it was easy
to evaluate if it's all in one package
but again these are modular modular so
if you wanted to do growmax you could
implement it into gromax but that would
be more difficult um we did a series of
uh 25 tasks ranging from one to 10
subtasks where one might just be
download the pdb file for protein IL YZ
IL YZ um and then a 10-step one also is
shown here where we have to simulate at
two different
temperatures we have to do a bunch of
analyses and then we have to look at
before and after and do some
comparison okay so what we found in this
uh this project which is super
interesting is if you look all the way
on the left we have accuracy which um
were just uh evaluated by humans if it
was able to do it in a reasonable way um
and get like a reasonable
response um if you look at the purple
line gp24
like we kind of expect out of these
models that gp40 would be pretty good
but actually llama 3 which is open
source model is pretty act equal um I
had a question about the task initi uh
the MD like initialization yeah um and I
was curious like how does the L pick the
parameters and also I don't know because
I remember from um Andrew's presentation
also there was like some like logic to
how it picks and decides which task to
do how like if there's like how do you
approach changing parameters like if it
like does it do one set of parameters
and then change to another set of
parameters if that doesn't work or yeah
yeah so we have like default parameters
for a lot of them um
because just defaulted in the code like
all that's all the software does also um
but we it chooses the parameters based
on the The Prompt so you might say like
the temperature or The Ensemble on the
prompt otherwise we kind of let it
choose one thing that we found really
interesting um is that if you don't
specify The Ensemble it just kind of
picks whatever it wants obviously um but
the models have favorites so like Claude
consistently always no matter what wants
to do npt um and you kind of have to
like force it to not do it which uh to
its downfall and then the other models
like to like diversify a little bit so
this is something that actually with m
also we're thinking about um building
like a more stringent eval set for to
make sure that every single like uh
minute parameter is defined correctly
thank
[Music]
you you said something like oh it's
surprising that um LMA actually
performed uh as as good as other bigger
models but then to me okay the test here
is like pretty straightforward um like
procing getting pdb processing pdb is
something like you can just you can just
write you can hard code those processes
so I wonder in that sense maybe it's not
that surprising that the smaller model
works as good as the big
one um I think it's not not necessarily
the case that it's super simple because
there's are like super straightforward
and
actually here we test um with this is
with GPT 40 but we test with like just
actually having it write the code like
hardcode it which is the direct llm and
then also just having it do a react
where we don't give it any tools but
it's able to write python code and it
actually performs pretty poorly on these
um so I don't think it's necessarily the
case I think that where some of these
other models um fail so I mean GPT 3.5
never stood a chance but the other
models that are more medium um they
really just fail in using the tools
correctly um and choosing the parameters
wait so so I'm trying to understand like
where do they fail so like choosing um
like code coding that part to me is it
should be like there only this few
common lines you can you can write for
running MD simulation so do they mostly
feel like the choosing right parameter
part and what do you mean by wrong
parameter yeah yeah so um for instance
it would like forget to choose
parameters a lot of the ones the ones
that perform more poorly like um
actually the medium ones like the claws
and the like gp4 turbo and the Llama 70b
um a lot of what they do is just because
the process is so long right like
running an MD simulation and also like
if you ask it to do 15 analysis steps it
just kind of forgets things um and it
will just hallucinate so it will like or
it'll give the when I meant with the
wrong parameters is not what I not how I
said it but the um like wrong file like
it'll try to
run um if it runs two different
simulations it and then it's supposed to
do rmsd on both it'll just do it both on
one and it just mixes those things up
okay interesting yeah like very silly
mistakes
yeah there is one question online can
you unmute yourself and ask the
question oh yes um I'm curious what is
the contribution of largel model um to
MD CR is it used to convert human
requests into a pipeline of existing
tools and how does um your pip uh your
tool compared to a pipeline of tools
thank
you yeah so the MDC is an llm agent so
it takes the user request and then like
reasons through what tools it wants to
use all of the tools most of the tools
are not llm based they're like just
computational tools that are built on
regular software um but it does the
reasoning process of choosing the tools
and then the inputs to the tools as
well got it
thanks
cool Okay cool so um one of the other
things we found and this is Sim uh
getting at with the question I was asked
a second ago is um all the way on the
bottom left we have each of the models
and then the accuracy as the number of
subtasks required increases um and you
can see like GPT 40 even which is like
one of the best models still kind of
dies off after a while and only gets
like as it gets more complicated and we
ask it to do more things it still is not
100% um and so there's still a good way
to go with this um a lot of what we saw
with um GPT 40 is it doesn't really skip
steps it's really good about like
completing the right steps and actually
the same with llama 3 uh 405b it's good
really good at like completing the steps
say like checking them off calling the
tools um but again it like gives the
wrong parameters and it makes silly
mistakes like using if it runs at two
different temperatures it uses only one
temperature and just runs it twice for
RSD um whereas like uh Cloud 3 Opus and
even Cloud 3.5 Sonet will give you kind
of silly things where it's like it won't
run RSD and then it'll just give you a
number like it did um it's very honest
that
way um I kind of talked about this but
just to come back to uh the MD Crow
built on gp24 versus react and just
asking the LM to write the code
similarly we see a trend where again the
performance drops off even for empd Crow
as the complexity increases um but for
the react and direct llm it can complete
some of them uh certainly the one step
one it can write code to to fetch a pdb
file and then it drops very quickly with
um like no performance after that sorry
just
question if like
how would this table look if you added
the recent reasoning reasoning models
like gep CH
the O 03 from open AI like in your
opinion would it would it like strongly
improve or jtic margin I definitely
think so because I think um we have not
run um MD Crow based on reasoning models
yet um that's something that we are
doing now let me answer question because
actually we've been thinking about this
in future houses we we tried 03 mini
High which is supposed to be the best
model in like paper QA we tried it in um
the molecular cloning tasks and it got
0% every single time and um the reason
why is that it just uh it doesn't seem
to handle tool descriptions very well
and I don't know if there's some like
additional work they need to open a eye
or something or it's uh just like not
ready for for calling tools but it but
it um it would basically always forget
to submit the answer or it would like
always forget to like uh download
something um so I think that one's still
iring out some Kinks but I think in
theory yes reasoning model should do
better um and I think we also tried
Cloud 3.7 thinking and we didn't see any
difference with Cloud 3.6 so we haven't
seen a gain there and I don't know why
but uh I mean I think that I mean it's
kind of obvious that the next step for
these things is to let them think for
longer because it's such a complicated
environment but yeah we haven't seen any
gains zero shot
yet so the question was deep seek R1 uh
no deep seek R1 um doesn't seem to call
tools very well and um one of the
problems is reasoning models are very
very long Generation Um and then when
you do an agent you have a very long
long prompt because you have a whole
bunch of tools you have to describe and
so actually run out of context quickly
in these settings but certainly I think
yes not the using tools would not do
well but in this comparison if we asked
it to do the direct Lim call it
certainly would be
better I'm trying to understand like
okay I understand this might be um like
a first test case for something that
will be more complicated later but then
U just in the case of MD I'm roosing
over your uh preprint and then I
realized that this workflow is what most
MD Scholars would do and and have um
have code for already so it's a pipeline
that you can basically fully hard code
MH so then what's the point of using
large language model to to recode each
of those steps like for example ret Tri
pdb is literally
just yeah with w g with a pdv ID yeah so
what's the point of asking the to recoe
those kind of rep repetitive
lines yeah so I think the if I
understand your question correctly the
point uh that we were trying to get out
with mdro is trying to see like we we
did chro and we saw that it can do some
chemistry TK but those are relatively
simple um and the like you get the
answer back immediately there's no file
handling it's it's very like simple
string in string out and then with MD
Crow we wanted to kind of test that and
bring it to the extreme of seeing it can
llms do the more complex um processes
with the more complex tool calling which
part of the process is something that
requires like reasoning for example um
yeah like for example I I think um
download uh pdb or run simulation or uh
run says those are pre-existing packages
um so what which part is the reasoning
part coming so the reasoning then comes
in in the like choosing the parameters
for the tools so if we don't give it all
of the parameters for the simulation for
example or if it has to look up like if
we say run this at appropriate like run
some simulation at appropriate
temperature based on this paper and
literature and doing that piece and then
also like breaking down the task into
subtasks and actually making sure it
completes all of those um but we weren't
necessarily trying to evaluate its
ability to reason about MD on this on
this project oh yes thank you
yeah uh I'm curious if you looked at all
and I know this this also was this
project was maybe a couple years ago but
if you've looked at all at memory or at
storing memories um I just thought of it
when we were talking about the reasoning
models kind of
for getting things that go out of the
long context window
yeah that's a great question so we also
implemented memory in IND Crow um we
implemented it as kind of like a chat
feature because um like you don't want
to sit there and have a chat bot that
runs a simulation that you have to wait
on um but we also store them so this is
like an example of how you can like chat
with it but the way that it implements
memory is it takes the entire trajectory
that it ran and its thought process and
then just uses an llm to summarize that
and store it into memory um the way that
this is like a kind of silly example of
breaking up the steps but the way that
like I ran this in practice is if it
like really screwed up I would be like
hey remember when you did that that was
wrong can you try again with some like
uh change to it so we did Implement
memory in this as well
yeah
okay um the other thing that we tested
with MD Crow is really diving into that
like increasing complexity and the way
we did this is we built another small
set of 10 tasks where they like
literally build on each other like if
step one is just download a p2b step two
is download and clean it step three is
download Clean and simulate so it's just
literally building on each other um and
again these are like relatively simple
tasks um but we find that uh some of the
models like TPT 40 and llama 3 still
have a pretty good the diagonal is
perfect where the number of subtasks
completed versus the number of subtasks
required is like pretty diagonal um but
interestingly we see that like all of
the Claud models really are not great um
and the reason for that is we tried to
be very objective TR and we didn't like
look at the performance of one model and
then adjust our system in any way we
tried to just have like okay we built
the system can they do the tasks but if
you were to fix it and look at the cloud
models and say like hey they're really
bad at these four things they keep
making the same mistakes um we didn't
see this with gbt 40 or any of the other
models where like consistently all make
the same mistakes um Claud just really
really likes npt but is really bad at it
and so if you do make some adjustments
like you kind of default the pressure to
a reasonable reasonable pressure or you
make some like not great adjustments uh
you actually can get the performance
like pretty decent and get it to match
and get it to bump up there um all this
to say like even with we see like pretty
good performance with the open source
model but even like just with Claude you
can get pretty decent performance if you
really wanted to use Claude by making
like model specific adjustments um to
the
system
okay so with MD with Kim Crow we found
um the same conclusions and with MD Crow
we found that like even the new llms
can't handle these like complex MD tasks
again the tasks are not complex to like
somebody who does MD regularly but
they're complex complex for an llm
um and also open source LMS are pretty
comparable to the frontier models for MD
Crow which is very interesting because
MD Crow still struggles with these more
complex tasks these more like multi-step
these like long um these long
trajectories okay so the last thing that
I'm gonna talk about is contro which
Andrew I think kind of hinted at um and
this is using paper QA to detect
contradictions in biology literature so
this is thinking about how we can use
these llm agents um to a scale that like
humans can't do because like like you
said humans can run these MD workflows
humans can do these cheminformatics
tasks um but humans can't detect like
contradictions in every single Paper in
literature against hundreds of
papers so contro combines claim
extraction with paper qa2 to detect
contradictions and literature so you
input a paper and it chunks out it
splits into chunks extracts claims and
filters them and then puts them into
contrad uh contradiction detection
prompt and paper qa2 and it gives you an
answer like a reasoning that you can
read um with sources and then also a
lyer scale of yes there's explicit
contradictions to in literature um all
the way down to five which is I have no
idea I've never heard of this before and
zero explicit agreement like everything
really agrees so we took the L QA data
set that Andrew introduced and split
half of them into true statements like
the sky is blue and half into not true
statements like the sky is not blue um
and put them all into uh contrac and
we've got a uh Au or of
0.842 it's like a proof of concept that
we're able to actually detect these in
literature so the next thing we did is
we were like okay let's just put it
let's run it on a 100 random papers so
we went in our database and found 100
random biology papers from all over the
place all sorts of journals from like
1982 to current all over the place um
and we found that all the way on the
left here most papers have pretty few
contradictions that we found um which is
great and expected if we found like 15
on every paper that would be insane but
if we look at the number of papers with
each number of contradictions we have
Zer one two three being the highest
which is pretty reasonable and we
actually found
2.34 uh contradictions per paper on
average in the papers we looked
at um then we use human experts so the
PhD students again
um and ask them to First Look at uh the
claims that Contra looked at and the
reasoning and its score and just do you
agree with it based on its reasoning
based on the literature it looked at do
you think this is a contradiction and so
for these scores of eight n and 10 which
are we consider a contradiction if it's
above that humans agree with 70% of them
um which might seem a little bit low to
you so then we asked humans okay you can
look at every paper that we're not going
to ask you to look at every paper paper
ever but you'll look at every paper that
paper QA even considered and see if you
think there's a contradiction and so
what we're looking at here is I sorted
it so that it's pretty but there's no
like correlation along the x-axis um the
stars are contrac scores so these are
ones that it scored eight nine and then
like four below so agree it all agrees
or it all contradict contradicts and
like you can kind of tell that humans
don't really agree with contra all the
time right like on the all the way on
the left you see that it gave it a nine
and humans gave it like a a one but if
you look at the horizontal lines we had
like three humans on each claim humans
don't even agree with each other on in
the large um some of them literally gave
like yes 100% this all of the literature
agrees and on the same claim another
human gave 100% they all just they all
contradict it so I think this shows that
like humans in general agree with contra
were able to find contradictions in
literature um and this is a really hard
task to do so this is something that
we're um using llm agents to do that
humans can't do in fact one of our
contractors even said this is the
hardest task we asked them to do and
they don't want to do it anymore so this
is something that's it's a great example
of how we can use these llms to scale
into areas that are like not feasible or
um like good for humans to
do really like this uh this
contradiction because I feel like a lot
of the papers I write are like almost
like spite papers where I see at a
conference someone claiming something
and then you go and then someone
disagrees and you're like I could prove
that right like I could prove that wrong
and so I think it's really cool because
like a lot of you know science comes
from contradictions I was wondering if
you've done any like structured searches
like that like let's say you know I go
I'm a neuroscience I go to like nature
reviews neuroscience and like for my
topic which is connectomic I just
download every review that mention
conics and put it in can you start
getting like scientific Concepts and
then like testing them have some Metric
of that yeah this is a great question so
this is something uh we actually Dove
we've dove into this a lot actually um
for different topics um originally when
we started this we thought we would find
really like hotly contested areas of
science or like places to do research um
a lot of what we found is like authors
don't do their job finding literature
and reading it before they write their
papers um but certainly we also did look
topics and this is the font is very
small I'm sorry but we looked at across
different
journals um and so on the bottom it's
like kind of like topics um I don't have
any plots of like the specific areas but
you can see like nature aging nature
biotech nature chemistry um and this is
not public data yet uh we see that like
nature aging uh the contradictions
number of contradictions per word is a
lot higher than like nature methods
which is great because why would there
be so many contradictions in nature
method methods and then we asked an llm
to take the reasoning that the contrac
outputed and the claim plus a little
context that the claim came from and
whether it's a contradiction or not and
categorized it as inherited so is this
like introduction like it like cites a
paper and the paper has been refuted or
it incorrectly cites it um has this
something that said that's like a
speculation that was later
disproven does it overstate the evidence
so if it finds like um pitbulls really
like bananas and it says all dogss like
bananas
very like absurd because it has that
context um if it's just like an outdated
claim or if it's empirical disagreement
which is very common right like paper
can just find different things maybe
they use different samples maybe they um
like just find different things that's
very common in science um and we find
that like nature aging is really high
and that's because it's like you can
kind of split it out and see the
different ways and how but we did look
at different topics as well yeah
but then you have to download all the
papers which is which is the the thing
yeah sorry if you go back two slides for
that Benchmark Au you see it's 084 what
is uh the contradiction struggling to
detect and are you guys how are you guys
addressing that yeah so um this was I
don't remember what the recall of like
QA was at this point but it was also not
100 do you remember
yeah so the recall of lit QA meaning
like can it if given the question did it
find the right paper in general because
there's only one paper was like 60
67% um and so we're getting 53% so it's
possible that it's literally just not
finding the paper um in most cases um I
didn't dive really into farther into
that because this was kind of just like
a proof of concept that it's able to
detect
them but the recall of these papers in
general was not 100 so it never a chance
there
either any other
questions okay yeah I think that's all I
uh mostly have just final conclusions um
we kind of with Kim Crow we found like
okay cool these LMS can do science um
but they're limited by the tools uh with
MD Crow we found it we can do more
complete more complex tasks but it tends
to kind of struggle and open source
models are kind of equal still to the
frontier models and then with contro we
found uh hey this is a really hard task
but it's necessary for science um if we
use contrac humans agree with 70% which
is a pretty good amount um and then also
pre-printed papers shocker have more
contradictions than most peer-reviewed
Journal papers um so that's kind of the
uh and then obviously we can scale much
easier with contra