So, one of the genes that we started
working on turned out um after we had
sort of figured out that it was a
synaptic protein and that it regulates
synaptic strength through modulating
receptors at the syninnapse, uh it
turned out in a
uh a G-W was or a genetic screen for uh
genes that um confer risk for
neuroscychiatric for uh schizophrenia,
depression
uh bipolar. Uh it turned out as the
number two hit for bipolar disorder. And
basically people see this hit, they have
no idea what it does. They look up what
the gene is and it turns out to be this
synaptic protein that we've been working
on. And um
it's unusual in the sense that many
genetic hits for neuroscychiatric
disorders
uh because they're also symptomatically
have features that are common. Also
genetically there's a lot of overlap
between schizophrenia bipolar and uh
major depression. But the gene that we
were working on, the protein that it
encodes, um that risk is really specific
for bipolar and it doesn't cross over to
the other two. So that in itself is um
is unusual and very interesting.
Um and then you know what one of my
postocs said like let's see what this
protein looks like in you know patients
from bipolar patients and I said oh I
I'm not sure we'll see anything because
sometimes mutations they affect function
of the proteins but the amount of
protein is the same so just looking at
what the protein levels it's not going
to tell us anything but you know people
in your lab don't always listen to you
thankfully
Um and she basically we ordered all
these brains from uh um these uh um data
banks that have uh patients and we
ordered schizophrenia and major
depression and bipolar and of course uh
healthy controls and we looked at them
and sure enough in the bipolar patients
specifically the level of this protein
that we had discovered um was much lower
than in any of the other groups.
Um and then that really kind of changed
our thinking because we started thinking
well the amounts of protein means that
potentially the mutation is not related
to the protein itself but to the
regulatory region that um
that sets the amount of protein being
made or the transcription of the gene.
And so we started looking at the
regulatory domain and we could identify
mutations in the regulatory domain from
patients that affected the
transcription.
And so and then we saw that there was a
uh
there was a correlation between the
presence of these mutations in the
promoter or the regulatory region and
the level of proteins in these patients.
Um so now we're thinking about using
that kind of as a diagnostic tool
potentially
and um so that's one of the projects
that I think is super exciting in terms
of translational potential
um and uh um where we also can have a
test a lab test which is sort of a
transcriptional test where we can insert
any human mutation
into our assay.
Um where we have the promoter of this
gene uh the human promoter that we have
in front of a reporter that we can
monitor and we can test its
functionality.