So today we're going to continue our
discussion of uh producer Theory
remember the first few lectures we
developed consumer Theory and where the
demain curve came from now we're turning
to producer Theory and where the supply
curve comes from drawing on a lot of
parallels from the math and techniques
that we use for Consumer Theory so we're
going to start today by talking about
the key construct a key construct of
producer Theory which is short run cost
curves remember the short run is the
period of time over which some inputs
are fixed in our case capital and other
inputs are variable in our case labor
okay so basically we last time developed
a firm production
function now I want to translate that
production function into costs and why
do we want to do that because remember
the way firms maximize profits is by
minimizing costs by producing Goods as
efficiently as possible at minimum costs
remember a production function from last
time was little Q equals the square root
of L * K
okay that was our production function
now what we want to do today is write
down a new function which is what does
it cost to produce little Q for any
given L and K what's it cost well the
cost of producing producing little Q
which is a function of Q is equal to the
amount of capital you have which is
fixed which is I'm sorry which is fixed
times the rental rate of capital
remember that's the price of machines is
their rental rate plus the amount of
Labor which is a function of Q times the
wage so basically your choice variable
is how many workers you want to have to
decide how much Q you want to produce
you're going to decide how many hours of
Labor or workers you want to employ by
the way I will talk
interchangeably between hours of Labor
and workers there's no right measure of
L it depends on the context Etc so don't
feel like it's just two different ways
of measuring the L input so uh it
matters less when I say hours of work
versus workers if it's an important
distinction I'll tell you but right now
I'm using two different ways of
measuring L the bottom line is it's a
labor
input okay so now
we want to um say what is the explicit
expression for the cost function well in
fact if we know a production function
and we know W and R we can write down a
cost function so we know this production
function and let's assume for this case
let's assume W equals 5 and R equals 10
okay where those come from I'll teach
you that in a few lectures remember we
sort of peeled the onion in this class
we're kind of revealing the m slowly
right now just take those as given in a
few lect I'll tell you where they come
from okay so we know the production
function is qal squ of L * K so we can
take that from that production function
we can just flip it and say Lal Q ^2
over K bar right just squaring that
moving to the other side okay so then we
could say that we can rewrite the cost
function as C equals 10 K
Bar okay because 10 is the rental
rate plus five q^2 over K Bar because
plug in from this equation five is the
wage
rate okay now K bar is a fixed number to
make life easy let's just assume K Bar
equals one it could be any fixed number
in the short run let's assume K bar is
one to make life easy so that says that
the cost function we could simply write
as 10 + 5
q^2 that's our cost function to get that
cost
function which is a relationship between
the cost of the firm and the quantity
they produce okay the cost function
relates the quantity produced to the
cost all we do is start with the
production function plug in these
parameters and we end up with a cost
function okay so that's how you
translate production to
cost okay
now let's look at this cost function for
a second and and I want to give you some
key definitions that we'll be using
throughout this
course okay we are going to
call fixed
costs fixed
costs are going to be costs which are
not variable in the short
run fixed costs are costs which are not
variable in the short run here it's 10
the fixed cost in this example is 10
there's nothing you can do in the short
run to change your fixed cost because
capital's
fixed variable
costs are the costs that can be varied
in the short run in our case variable
costs are 5
q^2 so your variable costs are 5 q^ squ
that's the part of cost that you can
move in the short
run and total costs is the sum of those
two as expressed there total cost is the
sum of fixed and variable
costs now the
key the the single key that will drive
production theory is what we're going to
call marginal costs marginal costs is
the
differential of total costs with respect
to
quantity okay so marginal cost is DC
DQ which G given that fixed costs are
fixed in the short run it's the same as
saying D variable cost
DQ okay in the short run D total cost DQ
is the same as D variable cost DQ
because fixed costs are
fixed okay so marginal costs are the
marginal cost of producing the next unit
what is the cost to produ of the next
unit it's the change in variable costs
for the next unit
produced and then finally we'll Define
average cost is what they sound like
which is C over Q total cost over
quantity produced that's average
cost we can graph these various cost
Curves in figure
61 so figure 61 in your handout shows
the cost curves for our sample cost
function which remember is really our
example production function given in RW
and K Bar what you see here is the
marginal
cost that is D variable cost DQ
is equal in our example to 10 Q just
differentiating that with respect to Q
is 10 Q our marginal costs are are the
line with the equation 10
Q our average
costs are this expression over Q so it's
10 over Q + 5
Q 10 over Q + 5 q is average cost
okay how did I get that it's divide the
cost by Q okay also on this graph you
can see average variable costs and
average fixed cost so you can see that
the average cost line is a combination
of two pieces an average variable cost
which is everywhere up sloping upward
sloping and average fixed cost which is
everywhere fall which is everywhere
falling okay so average costs themselves
first fall then rise
PR average cost First fall then rise why
is that well that's because at first you
have these big fixed costs you have to
sort of pay off but over time the fixed
cost gets small well the variable cost
so over time it
rises okay so average costs are the
first fall because the first couple
units your costs are very high your
costs are super high at the start
because you got all these fixed costs
each unit you those fixed costs per unit
fall and fall and fall that's the AFC
loan
fixed cost per unit fall and fall and
fall whereas Mar variable cost per unit
rise and rise and rise and the
minimum of average cost is where it
crosses the marginal cost curve it's
just mathematical the minimum if you
take a function the minimum of the
average is going to be where it
intersects the margin okay because
wherever the average cost is wherever
the marginal cost is above the average
cost the average cost is rising wherever
the marginal cost is below the average
cost that's falling therefore marginal
cost intersects average costs at the
minimum okay in other words if average
cost if you're to the point to the left
of
1.5 if you're Rising less than 1.5 units
marginal cost is below average
costs okay so by producing more you
drive average cost down because the
marginal cost is less than the average
cost so as you increase production from
one unit to one and a half unit you
drive average cost down but once
marginal cost is above average cost
increasing production drives average
cost up and that's why marginal cost
hits average cost at the
minimum okay questions about those
relationships are those
graphs okay so
now let's go back and note a key
relationship between marginal cost and
something we discussed last time the
marginal product of
labor okay remember
cost
equals uh K Bar * r+ L *
W if you differentiate this with respect
to Q to get the marginal cost you get
marginal
cost equals W * DL DQ okay because this
term drops out and so you just
differentiate differentiate by the law
of of you get W time dld
DQ okay so the marginal cost of
producing the next unit is the price per
unit of
Labor times how many units of Labor it
takes to make the next unit this is the
price per unit of Labor W this is how
much labor takes to make the next unit
so the marginal cost of the next unit is
the product of those
but we also know from last
lecture we know from last lecture that
DQ DL we had a name for that we called
that the marginal product of labor we
defined that last lecture how productive
the next unit of Labor is was
dql so we can substitute in to write we
can substitute that in to write that
marginal cost equals W over the marginal
product of labor
that is the marginal cost producing the
next unit of the good is higher the more
you have to pay each worker and lower
the more productive each worker
is okay so as marginal product of labor
is very high unless wages very high
marginal cost is going to be
low okay so basically what's going to
matter is the marginal uh the
marginal product of each unit of Labor
and the wage of to pay for that
unit okay now last point I want to make
here on on definitions I want about
something called sunk
costs I'm gonna I'm GNA already
contradict something I said last lecture
last lecture I said in the long run all
inputs are variable in the short run
only some inputs are variable we have
some costs which in the we have some
costs which in the long run are not
variable those are called sunk costs
those are costs where once you make them
you can never get them
back a fixed cost is something like a
machine if you buy a machine and you
want to get rid of it you can sell that
machine or a building if you buy a
building and you want rid of it you can
sell that building a sun cost is
something you can't ever get rid of or
sell the best example would be med
school if you want to be a doctor you
have to go to med
school having gone to med school school
you can't ever ungo to med school you
have paid that cost of time and money
and you're done it's
sunk a sunk cost is essentially a long
run fixed cost it's something where once
you make that investment you never get
it there's no way to get it back now you
can get benefits from it I'm not saying
it's not a good idea I'm just saying
unlike a building which you could sell
or a machine which you could sell med
school you can't sell your med school
experience okay and this is very
important important because it leads to
a very
counterintuitive difference between sunk
costs and fixed costs something that
trips people up all the
time which is that sunk costs are
irrelevant to decision making once
they're
paid once you've paid your sunk costs
they are relevant because you can't get
them back anyway it's done or does The
Economist say sunk costs or sunk doesn't
matter it's
irrelevant now here's why that matters
in real life
let me talk about a simple example many
of you have heard of the band Journey
classic 80s band a few years ago Journey
was touring and they have a new lead
singer this guy they fat actually
through YouTube who sounds he's from the
Philippines sounds just like the old
lead singer it's kind of cool so uh they
were playing down in uh uh Mansfield
Mass and I bought a couple of tickets
for my wife and I for 125 bucks each
good
seats then I looked at the set list and
I thought you know I don't actually like
that many Journey songs M there's hour
and a half concert for like the three
songs as I like it doesn't really seem
worth it I don't think I want to go I
think I'm going to try to sell these
tickets on the secondary market so I can
go to Stubhub and sell the tickets the
question
is I had paid $250 for those tickets how
should that impact the price I set on
StubHub the money I paid for those
tickets how should it that money forget
everything else just the money I paid
how should it impact the price I set on
StubHub
yeah it shouldn't why
not it's a some cost I paid it already
it's
irrelevant it's done I already paid the
250 it's gone I might feel sad but it's
gone how should I decide what to put the
tickets on salale for subhub well it's a
function of two factors first is I can
look at what things are selling for and
try to use the
market that's one thing but let's add no
information let's add no information on
the market leave that aside it's just an
internal decision decision on what what
I'm willing to sell the tickets for how
should I
decide
yeah you well that's one way to think
about it you'd not be a to pay the buy
tickets that's one way but there's sort
of a that's sort of a confusing way
there's another way to think about it
what's another way to think about it's
related to that sort the flip of what
you
said how should I think about how much
I'm willing to I'm willing to how much
am I willing forget the price that I set
which is a function of what I think the
market is my willingness how much should
I you willing to sell those tickets
for well think about it if I if I sell
the tickets what am I not
doing I'm not going to the
concert so how much should I be willing
to sell the tickets
for yeah yeah go ahead white shirt you
had your hand up
yeah yeah basically I should sell them
for how much I'm willing to pay to go to
the
show if
literally I don't want to go that I
should be willing to sell them for zero
I should willing to give them away not
saying I will sell them for zero because
I might make money on it but there's a
my underlying opportunity cost at zero
because I literally would rather sit at
home if I say yeah I don't want to pay
250 but if you said you get Journey
tickets for 50 bucks each I'd go then I
should set the price at 50 bucks each if
someone will pay me more than 50 I sell
them if they'll pay me less than 50 I go
so the amount I should will be willing
to get should be determined by the
opportunity cost of going not by what I
paid for them that is a very confusing
logic
yeah but
some like
think you would because that's the way
humans think but it's
wrong it's not a real
thing but it doesn't matter they're
already gone so once again let me think
of it this way let's say that um you
the fact you've paid the costs makes you
sad you've you've paid those costs you
made them sad but right now if you
whatever you sell them for okay that's
all you can get back so let's say let me
put this way let's say I can go online
and sell them for 500 bucks each should
I only sell them for 250 because that's
what I paid for him no sell them for 500
so it's irrelevant that I paid 250 if I
only sell them for 50 I sell them for 50
I've sell them for 500 sell them for 500
what I paid is some amount I paid in the
past I may be sad about it and look let
me be clear the way you're thinking
about is the way that the world thinks
about it and it's wrong okay um you know
I got chastised by my advisor in
graduate school because I had plane
tickets that I was going to cancel and I
was suffering from the Sun cost Val I
was going to say well I paid this much
for him and he said doesn't matter what
you paid for him what matters is the
value to you of flying
home okay the sun costs are
gone okay
yeah s selling what
build oh so the difference that's a
great point the difference is um with
the
building when
I the difference is um with with the
building I buy it as an investment that
I intend to use for a while and then
sell with the tickets I just bought that
I wasn't thinking about selling them I
was thinking about buying them I mean
for example I could have bought the
Journey tickets as an investment like a
building I could have bought the Journey
tickets and said well look I'm going to
pay this for them because I at that form
I plan to sell them but I wasn't plan to
sell them I just bought them I thought I
was done then things changed so from my
new perspective they were
sunk It's a good question good questions
yeah some costs are basically Goods that
you didn't want to sell in the first
place some costs are things Investments
you
make you decide I want to go to med
school I want to go to Journey okay and
you make and you make those decisions
and then things change and you may or or
they don't change but the point is
whatever you want to do next it's
irrelevant that you made that decision
you already made it now the question is
what to do next it's it's it's it's not
it's not an easy concept but it's an
important one
yeah oh you use it and journey buy joury
tickets was the kind of investment that
I would have used to go to Journey the
difference if I decide I don't want to
be a
doctor let's say being a doctor is
composed to three things going to med
school buying an office and working
every day if I decide I want to be aor
doctor I can stop working every day I
can sell the office but I can't ungo to
med school it's
done so my decision tomorrow do I want
to stay being a doctor it's irrelevant
if I went to med school I just say well
how much do I like it how much money I'm
making Rel to the cost of the office and
the cost of what I have of my time and
working every
day
okay that these are great questions
because this is exactly kind of concept
that I want you to be able to think
differently about coming out of this
course yeah
or at least for some cost does intent
matter what's that intent matter well
it's it intent matters and whether we
label it fixed or sunk that was the
question here intent matters if you
intend to eventually use it and sell it
then it's fixed if you intend if it
can't be sold or you don't intend to
sell it then it's sunk but that that's a
fuzzy
line okay all right great discussion
let's go on so now let's talk talk about
the long run versus the short
run the long run versus the short
run the difference in the long run let's
put Sun cost aside now how many choose
let's put them aside okay that's more
just sort of a fun thing for you to be
thinking about in your life but for but
for the rest for most of us class we'll
talk about cost being fixed or variable
not sunk so let's go back to where we
just fixed and variable costs and we
want to ask how do costs differ in the
long run to short run and here there's a
relatively simple but important
intuition which is that long run
costs will always
be at the lower bound of short run
costs the cost of production in Long Run
are always the same or lower than the
cost of production in the short run to
see this let's go to figure 62 this is
sort of a hard intuition let's go figure
62 in this figure there's a firm that
has three possible scales of production
think of this is three different K bars
they can
choose and the way production work is in
the short run you choose a k
bar you then decide how much l to use
and that's what you produce but in the
long run you can change your K bar so
think of a firm who has three different
K bar options and those three different
K bar options give three different
average cost curves because you can see
if I change K bar from one to two my
average cost would change my average
cost would no longer
be uh would no longer be 10 over Q + 5 q
okay my average cost would be 20 over Q
+ 5 q okay if Kar changed so think of
these three curves as three different K
bars now the firm in the short run has
to choose which one it wants so for
example
sr1 that short run AC cost curve one
that would be the average cost curve
they choose if they think they're not
going to produce that much they think
they don't have much demand for their
good as opposed to src3 that's the cost
curve they choose they think there's
going to be a lot of production they
think there going be a lot of demand for
the good so think of this about how big
you build the plant if you think people
are going to want much of your good you
build a small plant think they're going
want want to want want a lot of your
good you build a big plant and sr2 is in
between okay so in other words if the
firm wants to produce the amount little
q1 the most efficient K Bar to choose is
the K Bar that yields
sr1 right if the firm wants to produce
little Q Q3 the most
efficient K Bar to choose is the K Bar
that yields
sr3 but in the long run no matter what
since it can reoptimize over K it can
always do better than the short run it
could do or at least no worse so if it
turns out that in the long run demand is
q1 and you chose src1 great the long run
cost is the same as a short run costs
but if by mistake you chose
sr3 you can do better in the long run by
reoptimizing your Capital it's just like
any general scientific rule the more
variables you have to toy with the more
you can optimize okay here you can toy
with two variables labor and capital so
you can do better in terms of minimizing
costs this is is not just a theoretical
concept let's talk about one of the most
important uh companies in America today
which is
Tesla when Tesla was founded in
2013 Elon Musk had to decide how large a
battery production plant to
build he built a plant which was the
size such that he would sell 20,000 cars
in 2017 he figured his demand be 20,000
cars in 2017 so he buil a plant let's
call src1 cuz he expect Ed Q little
1 what happened was he got Q Little
3 by 2017 there was a 200,000 200,000
person waiting list for Teslas because
they couldn't produce the batteries fast
enough so Elon Musk realized he'd built
too small a plant so he then has built
the largest electric battery plant in
the world in Nevada he's gone from src1
to
src3 this clant can produce 500,000 cars
a year
but what if people decide Elon Musk is
an idiot and they don't want to buy
Teslas anymore okay and all of a sudden
Tesla sales Fall well that one could be
too big and maybe next time he'll sell
that plant and build one in
between the point is he can always
reoptimize depending on how demand turns
out to be so you can always do better
Elon Musk did not produce most
efficiently in the short run so he built
a bigger plant will he now produce most
efficiently it depends when the demands
set up a Q3 or somewhere else
okay questions about
that so basically the point is in the
long run it's just like the short run
except you get to choose K bar which
means you take multiple shots at what
average but having chosen K Bar you're
back in the short run all you can do is
value the number of
workers okay so think of the long run is
a set of Short Run games in the each
short run you choose K Bar you produce
as efficiently as
possible okay if if you turns out you've
chosen the wrong K Bar you then choose a
different on the next period the next
long run
period
okay so now let's talk about long run
costs let's talk about how we think
about firm production decisions and
costs in a world where both labor and
capital is
variable okay so remember last time we
developed an ISO
Quant the isoquant was the choice of all
L and K that give the same same little
Q the choice of all L and K that give
the same little Q was the
isoquant and you could
choose um and basically the point was
along any given isoquant there are
different combinations of L and K that
can give you a little Q just like along
an ISO just along an indifference curve
there are many combinations of pizza and
cookies that make you equally happy so
the question is how do you decide which
combination to use well to do so
we create just like in consumer Theory
we solve the problem by creating a
budget constraint in producer Theory we
solve the problem by creating an ISO
cost
line the iso cost line which is
basically the firm's budget constraint
if you will isoc cost line is the line
which gives you the cost of Labor and
capital uh that help you choose which
combination you'd like to choose so I'm
not saying it well in words let's go to
the graphs okay here's some isocost
lines remember I assumed that the wage
was five and the renovated Capital was
10 okay so basically these lines are
combinations of capital and labor that
yield the same total level of costs the
combination of capital and labor that
yield the same total level of costs so
you see the $50 Isa cost says if you
want to spend $50 you could either have
10 units of Labor
and no Capital five units of capital and
no labor some combination in
between but if you want to spend
$150 you could then have 30 units of
Labor and no capital or 15 units of
capital no labor or some combination in
between so it's basically the
combination of capital and labor that
yield the same total
cost okay and what is the slope of the
isocost line well the slope is minus W
over
R minus the ratio of the price of Labor
to the price of
capital okay what does this say this
says that you have to give up half a
unit of capital to get a unit of Labor
it's back to opportunity costs for a
given total cost of production if you
want one more worker you're gonna have
to give up half a
machine okay for a given total cost of
Productions that's the slope of the
isocost line so then we say the firm to
minimize
costs will use the efficient
combination of Labor and capital to
produce any level of goods and how do we
get that we get that by the tangency
between the isoquant and the iso cost
the tangency between the iso Quant and
the iso cost gives us the efficient
combination of capital and labor for any
level of production little Q so so for
example going back keeping these isocost
lines and going back to our production
function and our therefore cost
function we can draw the
isoquant okay uh for production okay so
we start with the production function we
start with our production function qal
of L * K okay we know that the slope of
the isoquant the isoquant slope we
defined last time is minus MP L over
mpk MPL over
mpk so at the tangency we set these two
things
equal we set npl over mpk equal to W
over
r that is in the optimum with this
example okay you set these things equal
you you always set the slope of the
isocost line equal to slope of the
isoquant but in this example that is
such that you want to use half as much
Capital as labor you want to basically
use because basically if you look at um
MPL if you use our example we defined
last time set these equal says remember
from last time the MPL was minus L over
K here we're saying to equal to minus W
over R okay if you remember last time we
solved for the marginal the mrts I'm
sorry K Over
l k over
l k over l so minus k lus w Rus k l we
defined last time as the marginal rate
of technical
substitution okay which is generally
this formula but in our specific case
it's that minus WR is the price ratio
the the margin rate of technical
substitution is the slope of the
isoquant minus W over R is the slope of
the price ratio here in our example
example we know that equals minus a half
so in this example you want to set K L
equal to minus a half you want half as
much Capital as
labor okay why is that well same
intuitions with
consumers okay you can the market is
telling you it's going to cost half as
much to have a worker as a
machine your technology is telling you
okay that you are you're basically
indifferent that basically you at the
point you're at you are um you're
basically the tradeoff between workers
and machines is K Over l so you set
those equal and that gives you the rule
that you want to set in our particular
example K Over L equal to minus W over2
so let me review again a the isoquant
Curve comes from production function and
delivers the marginal rate of technical
substitution which is this step one okay
step two the iso cost has a slope of
this step three you set them equal so
you get minus K Over L which is what
this is equals minus a half which is
what that is so use capital and labor
until using half as much Capital as
labor and once again you can use the
same kind of examples we use for
Consumer Theory to show you why if you
weren't using half as much Capital as
labor you'd be getting it wrong should s
yourself at home remember last time we
had points on we had points where the
where the indifference curve wasn't
tangent to the budget constraint we show
why they were wrong you can do the same
thing here you can draw points where the
isoquant is not tangent to the isocost
and show you why that's inefficient why
it's inefficient
production okay now questions about
that
yeah oh that's a okay oh Jesus that's
that the uh let me make sure I I get the
uh get the inversion right it's
MPL over mpk sorry about that that's not
any better mpk MPL mpk thank you for
asking once again 70% of the class had
no idea what those were so you did a
good service yeah go
ahead for this example yes the general
formula is that the mrts equal to the
input price ratio
that's the general formula so general
formula is you set minus m
l over
mpk equal to minus W over R that's the
general formula in our particular case
that amounts to K Over L equals a
half yeah
is there
version that's a really interesting
question um that we won't really get
into I think the difference is actually
I will teach you why I won't get into it
because firms you're it's a good segue
to why firms are not the same as
consumers and I'll talk about that in a
minute other questions okay well that's
a great segue which is when we did
consumer Theory we were done here we
said well I just find the point where
this is true
that's the optimal
bundle then I think comes substitution
effects and all that as was pointed
out this is why producer theory is
harder because we're not done why aren't
we done because I didn't tell you the
Right iso
cost with per consumer Theory I gave you
a budget
constraint I'm not giving you an ISO
cost here I'm just saying there are
multiple possible ISO costs therefore
there are multiple possible
tangencies so with consumer Theory I
gave you a budget constraint and
therefore I told you two equations and
two unknowns gives you the answer here
two equations two unknowns does not give
you the answer it just gives you a
formula but how you apply that formula
is going to depend on how big you want
your firm to be which isocost you want
to choose well how the hell you going to
choose that that's where we have to add
one more step that's where producer
Theory gets one step
harder to see that let's look at figure
65a figure
65a shows for different ISO
cost how much capital and labor we want
to use for our example so the previous
example we were at Point a we were
choosing to spend
$50 that allowed us to produce square
root of 12.5
units okay at a tangency of five units
of cap labor and two and a half units of
capital okay flip back and forth to
figure 64 you'll see that's where we
were
right however I could have said instead
no I want to be bigger I want to make
more I'm going to choose to spend 100
then I would be at point B where I could
have 20 units not 100 square of 50 it's
uh four times yeah yeah I'm going to
spend 200 okay so basically here if I
spend 200 I can have 20 workers and 10
machines I I spend 200 have 20 workers
of 10 machines and then I'll produce
square root of 50 which is right I don't
know I haven't told you yet how do you
choose as a boss remember capital's
fixed I'm talking about this is not the
Elon Musk example it's not Capital this
is within the short run this is how many
workers do you
hire well you don't know you could hire
10 workers 20 workers 30 workers it
depends how much you want to
produce how much you want to produce
that is the extra step we have to add
for Consumer for producer Theory
we call this the long run expansion
path this is
essentially the combinations of Labor
and
capital at every single Quee that you
would choose in other words you can map
out I haven't yet to told you which
queue you're going to choose but I've
told you how to map out for each Q how
much Ln K you want to
use if you decide the que you want a
square of 12 A2 you choose 10 workers
and five machines if you decide it's a
square 112 A2 you choose 30 workers and
machines ultimately the question is how
much you want to
produce now in this example the long run
expansion path is linear but it doesn't
have to be for example consider figure
65b this is a long run expansion path
where capital is is becoming less
productive as you produce
more okay in 65a no matter how much you
produce you always want to use half as
much Capital as labor that ratio never
changes in 65b it does change that means
it's a different production
function I haven't written down the
underlying production function for 65b
but it's a different production function
the iso costs are the same the cost of
Labor and capital labor is always TW
half the price of capital but it's a
different production function which has
the feature that as you produce more and
more Capital becomes less productive you
might think of this as something like a
McDonald's long run expansion path once
they' got the fryolator and the
building then what really matters is how
many more workers you have you employ
there cranking stuff through so that's a
case where in some sense each additional
unit of capital the fry later isn't that
productive okay it's really labor which
is really the thing which you want more
and more of as you
expand alternatively you could have
something like figure 65
C which is an expansion path where
Capital becomes more productive and
labor becomes less
productive that is so that is you are
choosing relatively more and
more Capital compared to labor so let's
compare 65b to 65c in
65b when you go from point A to point C
you go from four workers to 15 workers
but only three machine to S and a half
machines okay go from point A to C and
65b the number of workers goes up almost
four times the number of machines only
goes up two and a half
times on the other hand with figure
65c the number of workers going from a
to c goes from 7 to 16 which is a little
more than twice the of machines goes
from 1.5 to 7 which is almost five times
as
much capital's becoming more productive
workers becom less productive in 65c
this might be something might Happ for
like a heavy machinery
plant okay where over time more you want
more and more machines and you fur and
fewer workers to run
them the point of this is not to say
that I can tell you what these speciic
examples are and each of these obviously
have different production functions
under them it's just to show you that
long run expansion paths can vary in the
real world it's basically a question of
as you want to produce
more does labor and capital become
equally more
productive okay questions about
that
yeah down if I can't I haven't got
talked about shutdown yet you're you're
a bit ahead of me that that is related
to how you're going to decide on your
que and I'm gonna get to that next
lecture okay so next lecture I haven't
told you how you choose q but next
lecture I will I'm going to choose the
one extra step that lets you choose q
but before I do I want to ask a sort of
existential question which is how do we
actually measure
costs in the real world step four
measuring
costs and this is where I get to tell
you that economics is just cooler than
accounting and let me explain why
okay accounting only considers the cash
flow costs that you that you have when
you start a firm economics more
appropriately considers opportunity
costs as
well okay so
profits is revenue Minus cost we're
going to focus on the costs here costs
and accounting are literally what you
spend in economics they're what your
opportunity cost is and those could
differ so let me give you a simple
example you're going to start a website
design firm when you gradu that's kind
of out of date but you know whatever
okay you going to start a website design
firm when you graduate okay and that
involves you working
full-time plus some slave programmer you
can hire for $40,000 a year okay so
you're going to work full-time and hire
the program for $40,000 a year moreover
you the program you don't even need to
buy a computer for the programmer
because you have an extra computer
that's got one more year before it
becomes useless so you can give that
computer to the programmer and they can
use that for the year so you're going
have a one-year company okay you're
going to pay it's you're going to work
full-time you're going to pay your
programmer $40,000 and you give your
program or this computer you have that
one more year to work and let's say your
goal is by the end of year one I want to
be making a profit okay my parents will
be mad at me if I take more than one
year with this by the end of year one I
want to make a profit and let's say at
the end of year one your revenues are
$660,000
we could say to your parents who are
accountants well gee I earned
$60,000 I paid my programmer
$40,000 that's my cost so I made profit
of
$220,000 see my company's great your
accounting parents we's say an
accounting mom and economics dad the
accounting mom is fool but the economics
dad is not because what does the
economics dad point
out
yeah yeah well go on what about let's
talk about your
time there's an opportunity cost of the
year you spent with this firm and you're
an MIT graduate for God's sake who knows
you could have made like I don't know
100K 200k who knows what you guys make
these days okay let's say you could have
made
100K you did not make 100K by starting
this firm that is a true economic cost
it's not an accounting cost but it's a
true economic cost it's an opportunity
cost you gave up 100K to do this
moreover that computer is still one year
left you could have sold it for
something there's an opportunity cost
giving to this guy you could have sold
it let's say you could have sold it for
,000
bucks so your opportunity costs are
101,000 plus the 40 your total costs are
141,000 this was a terrible
idea okay your total cost of $141,000
you've lost
$81,000 okay opportunity costs are real
costs opportunity
costs are the value of the best NE the
next best forone alternative remember
that's why we call economics to dismal
science we point out nothing's free your
time wasn't free the time you dedicated
to this firm meant you could have been
doing something else and that's not free
okay and as a result you are not making
money in this company even if you think
they are you are okay it's not saying we
shouldn't do startups that lose money in
the first year obviously most startups
lose money in the first year okay we get
to that later in the semester about how
you think about money companies that
lose money in the first year and make
money in the second year we'll come back
to that but in this simple example you
shouldn't fool yourself to think that
you actually made money because of the
opportunity costs okay questions about
that all right let's stop there thanks
again for all the great questions today
and we'll come back Wednesday and figure
out how we pick our queue