the MIT energy initiative presents
making aviation fuel from biomass a new
MIT technique could be the key written
by Nancy W
stoffer in 2021 nearly a quarter of the
world's carbon dioxide emissions came
from the Transportation sector with
Aviation being a significant contributor
while the growing use of electric
vehicles is helping to clean up ground
transportation today's batteries can't
compete with fossil fuel derived liquid
hydrocarbons in terms of energy
delivered per pound of weight a major
concern when it comes to Flying
meanwhile based on projected growth and
travel demand consumption of jet fuel is
projected to double between now and 2050
the Year by which the international
aviation industry has pledged to be
carbon neutral many groups have targeted
a 100% sustainable hydrocarbon fuel for
aircraft but without much success
part of the challenge is that Aviation
fuels are so tightly regulated this is a
subclass of fuels that has very specific
requirements in terms of the chemistry
and the physical properties of the fuel
because you can't risk something going
wrong in an airplane engine says Yuri
Roman leskov the Robert T Hassam 1911
professor of chemical engineering if
you're flying at 30,000 ft it's very
cold outside and you don't want the fuel
to thicken or freeze that's why the
formulation is very specific
aviation fuel is a combination of two
large classes of chemical compounds some
75 to 90% of it is made up of alaic
molecules which consist of long chains
of carbon atoms linked together this is
similar to what we would find in diesel
fuels so it's a classic hydrocarbon that
is out there explains ran leskov the
remaining 10 to 25% consists of aromatic
molecules Each of which includes at
least one ring made up of six connected
carbon atoms in most Transportation
fuels aromatic hydrocarbons are viewed
as a source of pollution so they're
removed as much as possible however in
aviation fuels some aromatic molecules
must remain because they set the
necessary physical and combustion
properties of the overall mixture they
also perform one more critical task they
ensure that seals between various
components in the aircraft fuel system
are tight the aromatics get absorbed by
the plastic seals and make them swell
explains Roman l cuff if for some reason
the fuel changes so can the seals and
that's very dangerous as a result
aromatics are a necessary component but
they're also a stumbling block in the
move to create sustainable Aviation
fuels or safs companies know how to make
the aliphatic fraction from inedible
parts of plants and other Renewables but
they haven't yet developed an improved
method of generating the aromatic
fraction from sustainable sources as a
result there's a blending wall explains
Roman leskov since we need that aromatic
content regardless of its source there
will always be a limit on how much the
sustainable aliphatic hydrocarbons we
can use without changing the properties
of the mixture he notes a similar
blending wall with gasoline we have a
lot of ethanol but we can't add more
than 10% without changing the properties
of the gasoline in fact current engines
can't handle even 15% ethanol without
modification no shortage of renewable
source material or attempts to convert
it
for the past 5 years understanding and
solving the saf problem has been the
goal of research by Roman leskov and his
MIT team Michael L stone PhD 21 Matthew
S Weber and others as well as their
collaborators at Washington State
University the national renewable energy
laboratory enr and the Pacific Northwest
National Laboratory their work has
focused on lignan a tough material that
gives plants structural support and
protection against microbes and fungi
about 30% of the carbon in biomass is in
lignan yet when ethanol is generated
from biomass the lignan is Left Behind
as a waste
product despite Valiant efforts no one
has found an economically viable
scalable way to turn liant into useful
products including the aromatic
molecules needed to make jet fuel 100%
sustainable why not as Roman leskov says
it's because of its chemical
recalcitrance it's difficult to make it
chemically react act in useful ways as a
result every year millions of tons of
waste ligant are burned as a lowgrade
fuel used as fertilizer or simply thrown
away understanding the problem requires
understanding what's happening at the
atomic level a single ligant molecule
the starting point of the challenge is a
big Macro Molecule made up of a network
of many aromatic rings connected by
oxygen and hydrogen atoms put simply the
key to converting lignan into the
aromatic fraction of saff is to break
that Macro Molecule into smaller pieces
while in the process getting rid of all
of the oxygen atoms in general most
industrial processes begin with a
chemical reaction that prevents the
subsequent upgrading of ligant as a
ligant is extracted from the biomass the
aromatic molecules in it react with one
another linking together to form strong
networks that won't react further as a
result the ligan is no longer useful for
making Aviation fuels to avoid that
outcome Roman Le Calin his team utilize
another approach they use a catalyst to
induce a chemical reaction that wouldn't
normally occur during extraction by
reacting the biomass in the presence of
a ruthenium based Catalyst they are able
to remove the lignan from the biomass
and produce a black liquid called lignan
oil that product is chemically stable
meaning that the aromatic molecules in
it will no longer react with one another
so the researchers have now successfully
broken the original lignan Macro
Molecule into fragments that contain
just one or two AR atic Rings each
however while the isolated fragments
don't chemically react they still
contain oxygen atoms therefore one task
remains finding a way to remove the
oxygen atoms in fact says Roman leskov
getting from the molecules in ligant oil
to the targeted aromatic molecules
required them to accomplish three things
in a single step they needed to
selectively break the carbon oxygen
bonds to free the oxygen atoms they need
to avoid incorporating non-carbon atoms
into the aromatic rings for example
atoms from the hydrogen gas that must be
present for all of the chemical
transformations to occur and they needed
to preserve the carbon backbone of the
molecule that is the series of linked
carbon atoms that connect the aromatic
rings that remain ultimately Roman
leskov and his team found a special
ingredient that would do the trick a
malum carbide
Catalyst it's actually a really amazing
Catalyst because it can perform those
three actions very well says Roman
leskov
in addition to that it's extremely
resistant to poisons plants can contain
a lot of components like proteins salts
and sulfur which often poison catalysts
they don't work anymore but malinam
carbide is very robust and isn't
strongly influenced by such
impurities trying it out on lignan from
popler
trees to test their approach in the lab
the researchers first designed and built
a specialized trickle bed reactor a type
of chemical reactor in which which both
liquids and gases flow downward through
a packed bed of catalyst particles they
then obtained biomass from a popler a
type of tree known as an energy crop
because it grows quickly and doesn't
require a lot of fertilizer to begin
they react the popular biomass in the
presence of the ranium base Catalyst to
extract the ligant and produce the
lignan oil they then flow the oil
through their trickle bed reactor
containing the malum carbide
Catalyst the mixture that formed
contains some of the targeted product
but also a lot of others that still
contained oxygen atoms Roman lesov notes
that in a trickle bed reactor the time
during which the lignan oil is exposed
to the Catalyst depends entirely on how
quickly it drips down through the packed
bed to increase the exposure time they
tried passing the oil through the same
Catalyst twice however the distribution
of products formed in the second pass
wasn't as they had predicted based on
the outcome of the first pass with
further investigation they figured out
why the first time the ligant oil drips
through the reactor it deposits oxygen
onto the Catalyst the deposition of the
oxygen changes the behavior of the
Catalyst such that certain products
appear or disappear with the temperature
being critical the temperature and
oxygen content set the condition of the
Catalyst in the first pass says Roman
leskov then on the second pass the
oxygen content in the flow is lower and
the Catalyst can fully break the
remaining carbon oxygen bonds the
process can thus operate continuously
two separate reactors containing
independent Catalyst beds would be
connected in series with the first
pre-treating the ligant oil and the
second removing any Oxygen that remains
based on a series of experiments
involving ligant oil from popular
biomass the researchers determined the
operating conditions yielding the best
outcome 350° C in the first step and
375° C in the Second Step under those
optimized conditions the mixture that
forms is dominated by the targeted
aromatic process products with the
remainder consisting of small amounts of
other jet fuel aliphatic molecules and
some remaining oxygen containing
molecules the Catalyst remains stable
while generating more than 87% by weight
of aromatic molecules when we do our
chemistry with the mbum carbide Catalyst
our total carbon yields are nearly 85%
of the theoretical carbon yield says
Roman leskov in most lingin conversion
processes the carbon yields are very low
on the order of 10% that's why the
Catalyst Community got very excited
about our results because people had not
seen carbon yields as high as the ones
we generated with this Catalyst there
remains one key question does the
mixture of components of forms have the
properties required for aviation fuel
when we work with these new substrates
to make new fuels the blend that we
create is different from standard jet
fuel says Roman leskov unless it has the
exact properties required it will not
qualify for certification as jet fuel to
check their products Roman Lov and and
his team send samples to Washington
State University where a team operates a
combustion lab devoted to testing fuels
results from initial testing of the
composition and properties of the
samples have been encouraging based on
the composition and published
pre-screening tools and procedures the
researchers have made initial property
predictions for their samples and they
looked good for example the freezing
point viscosity and threshold sting
index are predicted to be lower than the
values for conventional aviation
aromatics in other words the material
should flow more easily and be less
likely to freeze than conventional
aromatics while also generating less
soot in the atmosphere when they burn
overall predicted properties are near to
or more favorable than those of
conventional fuel
aromatics next
steps the researchers are continuing to
study how their sample Blends behave at
different temperatures and in particular
how well they perform that key task
soaking into and swelling the seals
inside jet engines these molecules are
not the typical aromatic molecules that
you use in jet fuel says Roman leskov
preliminary tests with sample seals show
that there's no difference in how our
ligan derived aromatics swell the seals
but we need to confirm that there's no
room for error in addition he and his
team are working with their enal
collaborators to scale up their methods
enal has much larger reactors than other
infrastructure needed to produce large
quantities of the new sustainable blend
based on the promising results thus far
the team wants to be prepared for the
further testing required for the
certification of jet fuels in addition
to testing samples of the fuel the full
certification procedure calls for
demonstrating Its Behavior in an
operating engine not while flying but in
a lap clarifies Roman leskov in addition
to requiring large samples that
demonstration is both timec consuming
and expensive which is why it's the very
last step in the strict testing required
for a new sustainable aviation fuel to
be approved Roman leskov and his
colleagues are now exploring the use of
their approach with other types of
biomass including Pine switch grass and
corn Stover the leaves stocks and cobs
left after corn is harvested but the
results with popular biomass are
promising if further testing confirms
that their aromatic products can replace
the aromatics now in jet fuel the
blending wall could disappear says Roman
leskov we'll have a means of producing
all the components and aviation fuel
from renewable material potentially
leading to aircraft fuel that's 100%
sustainable
This research was initially funded by
the center for bioenergy Innovation a US
Department of energy doe Research Center
supported by the office of biological
and Environmental Research and the doe
office of science more recent funding
came from the doe bioenergy Technologies
office and from NPA through the MIT
energy initiative Michael L stone PhD 21
is now a post-doctoral scholar in
chemical engineering at Stanford
University Matthew S Weber is a graduate
student in the Roman leskov group now on
leave for an internship at the national
renewable energy Laboratory