Welcome to the annual R&D conference. Um
I hope you find it interesting. We have
several tracks. So the track this
morning here, track number three is
going to be about the new space economy.
And so in this talk I want to give you
an overview of what that is. Uh give you
some numbers. We'll also talk about some
recent events because 2025 so far, we're
not done with 2025 yet, has been an
extraordinary year for the new space
economy and for all segments of it, for
the launch segment, for the space
segment, really for all aspects of um of
the new space economy. Um I'm also going
to tell you a little bit about our
research at MIT in our lab. Uh we really
look at it from a macro perspective. So
we just completed a a study of the
launch industry. Uh we looked at the
last 20 years of launches. We looked at
the statistics um the countries the
success rate. So just to give you one
number um it still is not absolutely
routine to launch to space. The overall
success rate is about 95%. So 5% of
launches still fail. However, those tend
to be uh the smaller launch vehicles and
those that don't launch as frequently as
for example the Falcon 9. Uh the other
uh key number that I can give you is uh
Starlink. Starlink has really been a
gamecher. Starlink launched 2,000
satellites just this year. So the total
uh complement of satellites in the
Starlink constellation is now over
8,000.
Um, I've actually been a user of
Starlink since the beta trials which
started in 2021 and I've seen the
performance of the Starlink
constellation go up consistently. Uh, my
only complaint really with Starlink is
the power consumption on the ground
terminal. The power consumption of a
Starling terminal is about uh 100 watts,
110 watts steady state, which is not a
big deal if you're wired into the
electrical grid, but it is a big deal
for mobile applications.
Great. So slides are up. Wonderful. And
now I just need to be able to advance
them, but maybe you could advance them
for me. Could you do that? Awesome.
Thank you. So, uh, so let's go through
some of the key events that happened
very recently. So, New Glenn um last
week had its second flight. Um and it is
really a big deal for a number of
reasons. Um the biggest the biggest um
takeaway for me is that there is more
than one way to develop uh new rockets
and new launch systems. New Glenn was
not a fast development. It took over a
decade to develop this rocket. uh but
having this level of success so
successful deployment of actual uh
satellites so the escapade mission are
twin probes to go to Mars so an
interplanetary mission um by rocket labs
rocket labs is the manufacturer of those
having a successful recovery of um you
know of the booster stage on the second
flight is really exceptional and so it
shows you that this kind of go it slow
and get it right approach approach is
still a valid approach to developing
space systems, not just let's launch
quickly, let's fail, let's learn and
let's redesign. So we have really two
different approaches to um to space
systems development. So kudos to Blue
Origin and New Glenn and a number of our
MIT students um from our department are
actively working on that program. The
next slide please. Um [clears throat]
the other um event and this is October
13th. So just a month ago uh Starship
had its um Starship had its 11th test
flight. So this is more the you know
let's launch frequently uh let's
understand what failures happened uh and
let's uh let's repair let's redesign.
This was the last flight of the second
generation of Starship. Um they deployed
eight mock Starlink satellite simulators
during the mission. The launch site is
also different. Uh, so Starship launched
from Starbase, which is, you know, it's
like out of a science fiction. It's
basically a a city that has sprawled up
from nowhere in West Texas. Um, really,
really impressive. This is the largest
uh rocket ever built. It's larger than
the Saturn 5. And it's going to have a a
capacity Dellor orbit, which is well
north of 100 metric tons. It's it's
really a gamecher. Um the next stage for
Starship will really to fully achieve
operational readiness. Um which then
also means refueling in orbit. So next
big challenge for the third generation
of Starship will be to uh go to orbit,
stay in orbit and then rendevous with a
second Starship and demonstrate uh
spacecraft to spacecraft refueling. Also
a major success. Next chart please. Um
uh coming back to Blue Origin um an
event that happened earlier this spring
in April uh the [clears throat] New
Shepard mission. So New Shepard is a
suborbital vehicle um that's been
operating for a number of years. We for
example had a payload on New Shepard 17
which was in 2021. So you can tell the
launch cadence is about you know um 6 to
10 flights per year. But what was um
what was remarkable about this flight uh
was it was the first all female crude
space flight since Valentina Teroskova
the Soviet um cosmonaut uh who had a
solo mission in 1963. Uh there were some
very illustrious women on that flight.
It also caused a lot of discussion
online. And uh my my take on this is
that if we want space tourism, we need
to embrace it in all of its forms. And
um I really applaud this mission for
promoting diversity and ensuring that
future generations remain engaged in
space tourism and in in this whole
enterprise. Uh next chart please.
Okay. Now let's switch gears slightly
and look at the evolution of cubats. So
uh what are cubats? Cubats are small
satellites. Uh the traditional cube sets
are 1 U 2 U or 3U. So 1U is a 10x 10 by
10 cm form factor and then you multiply
that by two or by three. So we're
talking roughly shoe box sized
satellites. One of the trends has been
to uh move up sort of the size scale. So
uh you'll hear from professor cooy later
this morning. She's launched 3U cube
sets. 6U and then 12U is is kind of
becoming the new standard. So uh we're
moving up in scale uh because at that
scale you can do more things like
propulsion uh you have more in
interesting instruments. The point of
this chart is this is a running total.
So it's cumulative number of cubats
launched and you could see it was a slow
growth slow growth until about 2013 2014
almost exactly 10 years ago the curve
starts really shifting and that has to
do with launch opportunities as well and
we're we're actually now well over 2,000
of these these cubats. However, I want
to point out one thing. This lower curve
here, this this light green curve is the
fraction of cube sets that have actual
propulsion on board. So most of these
cube sets because of their small factor
do not have propulsion. So you launch
them, they're in an orbit and then
they're subject to the pertabbations of
that orbit primarily drag and they will
gradually come down. Recently we've had
uh you know we have the 11-year solar
cycle. So because of the increased drag
during solar maximum, a lot of cubats
have come down sooner than expected. So
the lifetime of these cubats if they're
launched say from 400 kilometer like an
ISS like orbit is only a few months or
maximum a couple of years. However,
there are cubats that have been launched
in higher altitudes like the Swiss cube.
Um the Swiss cube was launched in 2008
to about 750 kilometer altitude. It's
still up there after you know after all
over 15 years. So the altitude of
insertion is extremely important for
cube sets. But look at that curve. Uh
next chart please. Now another thing
that's really changed is um if you want
to do your own cubat mission um how do
you go about this? There are there is
now an ecosystem a supply chain for
satellite components and parts that did
not exist a decade ago. An example is
this company here, Endurosat. Um, it's a
company from, are you ready for this?
Bulgaria.
Endurosat is based in Bulgaria. They've
recently opened a US office, but uh, you
can go to their website. This is a 6U
cube set. We just talked about the form
factor. 6U cube set. Uh, and you can buy
hardware for cube sets like on Amazon
basically. It's incredible. There's a
configurator. So you can have modific no
modifications. You can choose a version
of it with ADCS mean meaning pointing
accuracy less than one degree less than
0.1 degrees. And then here's the price.
It's a range 153,100
to 284,400.
So for basically the bus and some of the
basic components, you can now buy Cubat
components basically off the shelf.
That is absolutely new and was not the
case a decade ago. Uh next chart please.
Uh okay. So we've talked about uh the
launch vehicles, we've talked about cube
sets, we've talked about c space
tourism. Is new space only about
billionaires space tourism and cube
sets? No, it is really an economy. So if
we go to the next chart, there's a
number of um organizations,
mainly consultancies that really um do a
a pretty good job, I would say, of
trying to capture what is the space
economy, what's in the space economy,
what's not in the space economy. It's
actually not easy to do because unlike
terrestrial economies, you know, like
agriculture or semiconductors,
um the space economy is kind of spread
out throughout the regular economy. So
if you're looking for those um codes
right there's the North American
Industry Classification Codes NAKES some
of you might be familiar with that and
you look for the main category called
space economy you will not find it
because the space economy is kind of
spread throughout nevertheless so uh
this this prediction here this is a an
organization called Nova Space uh
there's several of them out there their
estimate for 2024 last year is that the
total space economy globally speaking is
about $600 billion.
Um, and what does that include? It
includes different subsectors. So, it
includes satellite services for example.
It includes launch. Uh, PNT is precision
navigation and timing. So, it's a mix of
launch, satellite manufacturing,
operations, but also data services. And
especially on data services, the
question is how broad, you know, how far
downstream do you go and still count
that as part of the space economy. Other
things that are noteworthy is the growth
rate. So the 5-year compound annual
growth rate is about 7%. I've also seen
studies that claim it's about 11%. So
it's somewhere between 7 and 11% which
is significantly
higher than uh the global economy
overall.
And um it's also more than double the
growth rate of aviation. So just to to
put this in perspective uh all of
aviation so aircraft manufacturing,
airlines, airport operations, all of
that together is about $1.8
trillion globally. 600 billion is about
onethird. So you could just to remember
the space economy is about currently
onethird the size of aviation. However,
its growth rate is more than twice.
Those are kind of the big takeaways. And
a predict prediction here by them is
that by 2033
uh given those growth rates, we're going
to be very close to $1 trillion globally
in in that space economy. Uh next chart,
please. Um okay, so what is in the space
economy? How can we understand the
structure of the space economy? Again,
there's uh quite a bit of information
out there. I particularly like this one.
This is an uh interactive mind map. Um
uh and you can uh you can actually go
and click in these different sectors. So
at the center we have the traditional
government organizations NASA, issa,
JAXA and Japan. Um we have investors, we
have uh R&D centers and hubs. And then
uh around here we have different
companies in robotics in space services
uh data down linking from space
observation
um we have space manufacturing that's a
very small sector but it's growing
satellite communications which is uh
probably the most profitable and and so
forth. And each one of these little
things here is a logo of a company. some
very wellestablished, some are startups
and um and it's a very dynamic evolution
of that industry. Uh next chart,
next chart please.
Okay, so one of the trends I just wanted
to also make the point that uh things
are not static in the space economy.
some businesses that used to be very
profitable that you would say this is
the most profitable part of the space
economy have gone down and other parts
have gone up. So I draw here and I will
I will tell you it's not always easy to
get accurate data. So this is an
estimated crossover between two
companies Direct TV and Starlink. So,
Direct TV, if you remember, their
business was broadcast television from
uh space, particularly from
geostationary orbit, and you put a a
fairly large dish on your roof and you
get direct TV, right? Uh and that was a
big business. It still is a kind of a
big business, but it's definitely
decreased significantly over the last
decade. By the way, this is 2025, so
everything to the right here is a uh
projection. The orange curve is the
revenues, the estimated revenues of
Starlink. Uh Starlink's revenues um have
grown substantially. Um it's a little
bit unclear whether they are because
Starlink is still a privately held
company. Um the finances are not always
as clear as for publicly traded
companies, but we're pretty sure that
the $10 billion revenue per year
threshold for Starlink is is going to
happen very very soon if it hasn't
happened already. But this crossover is
important because what does Starlink do?
Starlink provides us high quality, high
bandwidth internet almost anywhere we
are on the globe, right? Airlines are
starting to have it. Uh residential uh
mobile users are starting to have it and
the quality of the service again is very
very consistent 150 megabits per second
uh at a relatively attractive price
point. So the point is this is a dynamic
industry. Next chart.
Um, all right. So, I told you in the
introduction that we recently completed
a um a survey, a pretty in-depth study
of the international space launch
industry. We just published that in ACTA
astronautica.
And um this is an open access article.
So you you have access to it for free.
Uh and what we show is essentially again
the last decade is really where a lot of
the action has happened. uh China is is
very has been very active but has really
been growing. The big story here is
Falcon 9. Falcon 9 has you know close to
50% of the global launch market at this
point but there's others as well. Russia
of course has been shrinking. This is
related to the war in Ukraine and and
and and the Russ the isolation
essentially of Russia on the
international stage particularly
commercially. uh that also affects the
proton launch vehicle and then Europe
has really really suffered in the last
decade with the retirement of the Aran
5. Arian 6 is now here but the launch
rates are very low. Uh my prediction is
at the current growth rate that by 2027
so two years from now we are going to be
launching to space every day.
We're over 250 now. So project that out
for a couple of years, which is not too
far. We're going to be over 300 launches
per year and very very close to once per
day to space from somewhere on this
planet by 2027. Uh next chart please.
Okay, so I did mention China. Um I think
we just need to be uh particularly in
the west, we need to be cognizant. We
need to be um aware how uh how much
progress China really has made not just
in uh deploying unmanned satellites but
also in human space flight. So Shenzu 21
um is the recent mission. You might have
heard that the astronauts, there's three
tyonauts we call them, are uh on the
station right now and they've having
trouble coming back to Earth because
their return capsule was damaged by
space debris. The exact nature of the
damage is unclear and China has recently
launched just a couple days ago a rescue
capsule to get those astronauts back. So
that is that is actually impressive that
they have that capability. Uh Long March
is the main workhorse rocket. You saw
that on the prior chart. Um they've been
have they had a uninterrupted human
presence in Earth orbit since 2021. Um
and uh and they have strong ambition. So
China has announced uh that they are
going to land uh tyonauts on the lunar
surface. They've announced a joint lunar
research station with uh with China,
China and Russia together with a nuclear
fision reactor providing the power on
the lunar surface by 2030 2035 time
frame. So that is very significant
because it shows the growth and the
maturation of China's capabilities in in
crude and uncrrewed space flight. Next
chart please. Okay, this is also
exciting and this is probably the the
most um recent trend. Uh you'll you'll
hear more about this from Professor COY,
but uh StarCloud 1 launched uh also this
month, right? This has been an
incredible month, right, with with um
New Glenn with Starship and StarCloud 1
launched on a Falcon 9 out of
Vandenberg. That's a third launch site,
right? We've talked about Texas. We've
talked about Cape Canaveral. This one
launched from Vandenberg in California.
And um this is the first satellite that
hosted a G um uh high performance GPU
from Nvidia to deliver um inspace
computation. As you all know, the growth
rate of AI, the use of uh large language
models like chat GPT, uh Gemini and so
forth has been increasing a lot. But
this computation is not coming for free,
right? You need to power it
electrically. You need land. You need
cooling. You need electric power. Well,
it turns out in space, land is kind of
free, right? Once you're in space, uh
except if you're in geostationary orbit,
you need to get that slot, but otherwise
there is no land that you need to like
buy or rent. So, land is kind of free.
Power is also free from the sun. The
solar constant is about 1,360
watts per square meter and on Earth we
get about 100 watts per square meter. So
10x more power per unit area. And then
cooling
um particularly during eclipse when your
satellite goes through the shadow of the
earth it gets very cold. So cooling can
be free as well. So one of the big
questions we have is does it make sense
to launch major data centers and
computing in space because a lot of the
issues and costs for having these large
computing centers on Earth don't exist.
Of course you need to launch you need to
operate those satellites and there's
plenty of issues but you're going to
hear a lot about this in coming years.
AI edge computing in space and we've
already had the first thesis on these
topics here at MIT. So, we're happy to
share more with you. Next chart.
Okay. I haven't said much about Europe
in this whole picture. Uh again, also
this month in November, in fact, next
week, November 26th and 27, ISA, which
is the European Space Agency, is going
to have their uh ministerial council. Um
the last one was in 2022.
And this one is going to be very
important uh for a couple reasons. one
is uh you've seen that European um
launch capacity has really um has
declined and the European share of the
global launch market has declined as
well and at the same time the war in
Ukraine has made it very clear for
example because of the use of Starlink
on the front lines that having uh your
own satellites having your own capacity
in space is really important for
national security. So for the very first
time, ISSA at the ministerial level is
going to discuss the role of ISA in dual
use technologies and this might actually
require a change to ISSA's charter
because founded purely for civilian
purposes. So this is going to be
something really interesting to watch
toward the end of this month. Next
chart, please. Okay. So the other point
I want to make here is let's not call it
new space and old space right old space
is a bit sort of peorative but this new
space economy that we're talking about
and let's call it traditional space they
both coexist so they're like two cogs
working together um we will still have
large spacecraft programs we're still
using geostationary satellites you know
those large van or Even school bus size
satellites, they're not going to go
away. We're still going to have them.
There still is a role for geostationary
satellites. There still is a role for
satellites in medium-ear orbit. Those
are the 12-hour orbits that are used by
say GPS or Galileo. And um Newspace is
injecting though innovation into this
traditional market and in some cases
disrupting it and in other cases
complementing it. Next chart.
Okay, so here's a way to maybe visualize
uh the difference between traditional
space and new space. On the left in
blue, we have the traditional approach
to space. An agency or an institution,
usually always a government, issues a
call for tender or request for proposal
and that tender imposes requirements.
Companies re respond with proposals to
that call for tender. Uh a winner is
declared, the work is performed. um
revenue is earned through milestone
payments and then you repeat right
that's kind of a linear process on the
right side we have those six pillars of
the new space business product process
the funding model the business model the
technology and the market and what's
really interesting is to look at what is
the starting point some comp new space
companies they have you know IP they
have new technology uh in communications
in quantum encryption whatever it is
that's their starting point. Others uh
they start with the business model for
example a transcript or subscription
type service um in the as a BTOC market.
Starlink is essentially a subscription
service and it's clearly a BTOC business
direct to consumer market. So um very
very different. Next chart.
All right. So are there this sounds
interesting large growth over the last
decade. So is there are there any issues
are there any problems? And the answer
is yes. Uh the biggest issue we're
worried about right now is uh the the
rapid growth of the resident space
object population RSO population. This
has been growing even faster than the
number of launches than the number of
satellites. And so you can see this
colored curve shows you the tracked.
These are only the space objects we're
currently actively tracking. There's
about 30,000 of them. And you can see
which countries they come from
originally, US, Russia, China, and then
the others. And you can see some big
jumps. Uh and these big jumps happen
either because there was an
anti-satellite test. We the US by the
way we do criticize other countries for
doing anti-satellite tests but we are
the first ones who demonstrated it. So
we have to keep that in mind. There have
been five anti-satellite tests so far
and uh every one of those tests creates
an enormous debris cloud that is really
uh a problem. Um and then the other is
accidental collisions between satellites
or debris in satellites. The most famous
of these is the Iridium cosmos collision
that happened uh back in 2008.
Um so we need to do a better job
tracking this population. Next chart
please. Um and so we're doing some
research uh in my group uh together with
DARPA and Lincoln Lab on um the sensors
for tracking space objects. Primarily
we're talking about ground radar and
we're talking about uh optical sensors
as well as inspace sensors. What is the
value of getting more and more and more
sensor sensor data? Uh we believe that
in order to quantify the marginal
utility of these sensors, you need to go
all the way to decision making. So
specifically we're looking at the
maneuvering decisions for uh for
collision avoidance. Since Aridium
Cosmos the number of collision warnings
that operators are getting has just
skyrocketed
and um the question is
will if you get more information about
potential collisions and conjunctions
will you change your threshold at which
you will maneuver next chart. And and
that's really what we're looking at.
Here's here's a nominal threshold. So if
if the risk the probability of collision
is above this threshold, you would
maneuver and if it's below the
threshold, you would not maneuver. The
tricky part is and you can think of this
as two ellipsoids intersecting with each
other that um there there's what's
called the diluted region. So if the
uncertainty is very large, you can
calculate a low probability of collision
but it's not because it's actually low
but it's because you have poor
knowledge. So the ellipsoids of
uncertainty are very large. So you want
to make sure that whatever decision you
make you are not doing it because of a
lack of knowledge but you're doing it in
the what we call the robust region. And
I want to point out um Chris Tomla who's
a major in the US Air Force is doing his
PhD uh currently on on this topic. Next
chart.
So that's space traffic management. Of
course the other uh thing we have to do
is catalog maintenance. uh the catalog
of space objects is growing like we said
and uh we've shown with uh particularly
for geocynchronous orbit that there
could be a lot of value in observing not
just from earth but also having
observers in lower earth orbit looking
up at geo and uh and basically getting
much more frequent and much more um
accurate updates on our population in
geocynchronous orbit. Next chart. We're
almost there. The last point I feel an
obligation to also tell you about this.
Um, we talked a lot about the commercial
aspects of space, the scientific aspects
of space. But, you know, despite I think
a desire to keep space reserved purely
for commercial and scientific purposes,
I think we have to be we have to be
realistic about what's actually
happening. uh space is becoming
increasingly contested and there's
adversarial events like uh for for sure
the anti-satellite tests. So uh you see
the five ASAT tests that have happened
1985 the US 2007 China 2008 the US again
2019 India and 2021 Russia uh that
that's the most hostile aggressive type
of interaction in space so therefore
it's on the right side uh and then the
international space station on the blue
side is the most symbiotic kind of
interaction we've had and there's a
whole spectrum in between. So, we've
been working also with Lincoln Labs on
wargaming in space. Um, the picture that
you see there is, uh, Major Michael
Jones, who graduated last year with his
PhD, developed a um, it's essentially a
strategic game. It's a computer game
that you can play between a blue and a
red player, human versus human, AI
versus human, or AI versus AI. And it's
really interesting. This is uh, way more
complex. Think of this as chess in
space. But there are three big
differences with playing chess. In
chess, when you move a piece, it stays
there unless you move it again. In
space, all the pieces are moving all the
time because of orbital dynamics.
Secondly, in chess, you can only move
one piece at a time, right? When it's
your turn. Here, you can move multiple
pieces at once. And thirdly, in chess,
say uh queen takes rook, you when you do
that move, you know the outcome. Here
the outcome is uh uncertain and there's
probabilistic outcomes. So it's
significantly more complex than
traditional chess. Okay, so I think I'm
at the end here. Next chart. Uh I just
want to do if you allow me a little uh
plug here for our course uh through MIT
professional education. It's called the
new space economy. Um I co-e this course
course with professor Alessandro Golkar
who's a professor of space systems at TU
Munich. So what's good about it is he
sort of brings the European perspective.
I bring more of the US perspective and
the course has been offered for about
three years now and we've gotten really
good feedback and we keep refreshing it
because as you can see this is a very
very rapidly evolving uh domain.