Uh so it's my my great pleasure to uh
introduce the second keynote speaker of
today uh Robert Plenge who is the
executive vice president and chief
research officer at Bristol Myers Squib.
He came to Bristol my script from
Seljian that was acquired by BMS and
before that he was head of translational
medicine and vice president at Merc. uh
he began his journey in academic
medicine training for his MD and PhD on
the west coast at UCSF and UCSD and then
he came to the east coast to do a
fellowship in clinical rheumatology and
he liked the climate so much that he
ended up staying here I guess uh and
this is also of course uh both clinical
rheumatology and genetics of course and
not just at the at B at the Bighamin
Women's Hospital but at the broad
institute as well so I think your mentor
here was David Alill is that correct I
couldn't quite remember that piece and
he also has uh brought brought this
unique voice to our community through
his blog that I really recommend that
you guys read called Plench Gen. If you
hadn't read it, if you haven't read it
already, it's about uh impact in
genetics and medicine uh and really has
some interesting thoughts about how we
should approach drug development uh
through uh those types of approaches.
And I know that this is also what his
presentation will be about. And a fun
fact which for those of you who know me,
I love fun facts. Uh I actually was had
the good fortune of interacting with
Robert when he was at the broad and he
when he transitioned to Merc gave me an
opportunity to get my first industry
collaboration and grant that actually
launched my lab. It was my second grant
ever I think around 2012 or 13 and it
was a real gamecher for me and I don't
think I ever told you that but uh it was
really great interacting with your team
at Merc and uh the funding was
fantastic. We actually did some really
good work with with that money. So, it's
just an enormous pleasure to welcome you
back. I've been excited to hear your
talk and I love the title. So, can't
wait to see what you're going to tell
us.
I I I did not know that. So, so thank
you and I'm glad we were able to help.
So, um first of all, thanks for inviting
me and uh for all of you who are still
here, thanks for uh hanging in there. I
know it's been a been a long day. Um, so
I'm I'm going to start in the same way
that uh Ben actually started, which is
to thank a number of people who actually
contributed to the talk. So Joe
Moranville, who's part of Bristol Myers
Squib I've worked with for a number of
years. He contributed a lot of the the
data that I'll show you today. We had a
great pleasure to work with a company
called Octant. Uh Shri Kosuri uh was a
posttock with uh with George Church. So
kind of starting in the beginning and
the end of the day and they did a lot of
the work on on saturation mutagenesis
that I'll show you at the end of the
talk. Uh and then lastly, I'm going to
give you a number of examples that have
come out of our Bristol Myers pipeline.
Um I have worked on the minority of them
until recently. So there are a lot of
people who have worked on these programs
uh for a decade or more. And I'll be
able to share some of the examples uh
with you today. Um so this is a talk I
haven't given before. So you're going to
have to tell me if this concept of a
billion dollar bet actually works. I'm
going to start in the way that Molina
actually started the day as well uh
which is to frame the concept of some of
the challenges that we fra face in drug
discovery and development which is we
take we spent all of this time doing
what what what VJ talked about in MSI 2
and trying to understand the genetics
and the functions of a particular
protein and we do it in animal models.
We make molecules. We take them into
human clinical trials and the vast
majority of those things just fail and
they fail because the drugs don't don't
work. Somehow we pick the wrong target.
So what you can actually see on the left
hand side of this graph is is that
simple pie chart of why most drugs fail.
Most drugs fail because the drugs don't
work despite many many years of hard
work leading up to making the medicine
and testing it in in humans. And I think
on the right hand side, this sort of
frames at a high high level uh one of
the reasons that drugs don't work
because we just don't have enough
insight into human biology to make all
of the right choices that are required
to identify a target, make a molecule,
take it into the right patient
population, test it, and to see this
PKPD relationship, and ultimately get a
drug approved. So hopefully as we can
focus more and more not just on human
model systems but causal human model
systems, we'll begin to improve uh the
rates of efficacy in clinical trials. Um
so I think we've heard about this a
bunch already today and I think I'm sure
you're all very familiar with this is
that human genetics is a very powerful
tool uh to help predict the success of a
drug target in clinical trials. So Matt
Nelson um had a paper a number of years
ago. Eric Minl expanded on this a couple
of years ago. And basically the
take-home here is if a drug if a drug is
against a validated genetic target, it's
at least a two to threefold increased
likelihood of probability of success in
clinical development. Um we've done some
work on this. Uh Joe Moranville and his
team have done some work on this uh
within within BMS. And one thing in
particular is we've added on this kind
of proteomr
approach which if you can actually have
proteomic data link with genetic data
that's also a good predictor of of drug
success. But as I go through the talk
one of the things that I really want to
emphasize is yes genetics is a powerful
predictor of success for drugs. But
there are properties of human genetics
which can actually be extended into
other areas that we call causal human
biology that also can be powerful
predictors of success of of clinical
trials. And so we want to take those
principles in human genetics, apply them
in other areas. So Khloe talked about uh
some of the work in profiling immune
cells. You know, if we can identify
those pathogenic immune cells, for
examples that are driving diseases like
lupus and figure out how to selectively
deplete those cells, that's causal human
biology. Potentially, that is another
way to actually come up with new drug
targets. Okay. So, we've tried to
distill some of these very complex
topics for drug discovery and
development into five principles. And
behind each of these principles, there's
a tremendous amount of information. And
one of the nice things about going last
in the day is you can kind of pull on
the examples over the course of the day
to kind of really emphasize the these
concepts. So when I made the move from
academics to industry, it was really
because of that first principle. I
thought human genetics could change the
way that we do do drug discovery
development. If only we worked on the
right targets and use human genetics to
pick those targets, everything else
would fall into place. I think the
biggest education that I've had since
joining industry is I realized that yes,
picking the right target is really
important but there are a lot of other
things that come after it uh that are
really important as well and again VJ
gave a great example of MSI 2 show that
how much time goes into understanding
any individual talk any individual
target you don't want to just understand
in this case a genetic association but
what are the details of the of the
biology of the particular target how do
you want to modulate it. What are you
going to measure once you get into the
clinic? That's all captured by that
single concept of of causal human
biology. But it's a really really
important starting point for drug
discovery and development. So the second
step then is to match a therapeutic
modality to a molecular mechanism of
action. And Ben just gave you a great
example of how to actually do that in
the form of of crisper cast 9. If you
understand a mutation that is causing
the disease and it's expressed in the
liver, you can figure out how to give
that drug into the liver and correct it
in the liver and make the mutant base go
back to a wild type base. That's a
perfect example of matching modality to
mechanism. We also heard about
manipulating BCL11A
and there it's actually not introducing
something new but it's taking something
out preventing the binding site of a
transcription factor that allows the
repression of fetal hemoglobin. So by
removing that site that's matching
molecular mechanism. You're basically
recapitulating human genetics to turn on
in this case fetal hemoglobin that's
shown to be a very protective and
effective way to um help patients with
cickle cell anemia. But it's a third
category that I've been spending more
time on recently. So if you pick the
right target, you match the right
modality to a molecular mechanism of
action, then you take that molecule into
humans for the first time. And this is
when you really begin to get at dose.
How much of the drug is required?
Schedule. How often do you give it? Do
you give it once a day, twice a day,
once a week? What's the frequency with
which you give the drug? And then what's
the relationship between
pharmacocinetics, the level of drug in
the body, and pharmacodnamics, what that
drug is doing to the target or the cells
within the body. And then how does that
relate to clinical efficacy? So we call
this path to clinical proof of concept.
And as I'll talk about in just a few
minutes, this is the point really for
the first time that you know if a
molecule a medicine is working as you
actually predicted. And so it's this
really important flection point in a
drug discovery journey. Then once you
see clinical proof of concept, step
number four is to accelerate clinical
development as many indications as as
you can at as fast as you can because
there's incredible competition uh to
make not just the first drug but also
the best drug and there are a lot of
people that are doing this across the
entire world and being first and best is
incredibly important. And then all along
the way what you want to do is the fifth
principle uh which is to uh build out a
complete uh compendium of information uh
that will allow this drug to be used in
the most number of patients so the most
number of patients can benefit. So
that's uh maximizing a market access. So
these are the five principles and so
what I thought I would try to do today
is to describe this in a way that uses
poker as as a metaphor. So just before I
I start this m how many people actually
play poker.
All right. So a decent number. So Texas
holdem. So this is going to be based
upon the game Texas holdm. And I'll
describe the game to you. And again this
is the first time I've actually used
this metaphor. So you'll have to tell me
if it actually works or not. So causal
human biology matching modality
mechanism. If you play Texas holdm each
person is given two cards. Those cards
are private to you. So I'm playing
against Jesse. I'm playing against Ben.
I shouldn't pick statisticians because
they're really good at this stuff. But
but I I'm playing against them. I've got
my two cards. They've got their two
cards. And I can see mine, but they
can't see my cards. And in this case,
I've got two. I've got an ace and a
queen. Two pretty good high cards. So
this is the target and matching modality
to mechanism. So I'm feeling pretty good
about the hand. In this case, the hand
that I'm taking from research into early
development. Any ideas on what the
average cost of a drug to take from
research into early development is about
how much do you think that costs per
drug taken into early development? Any
estimates? Anybody want to shout out a
number?
100 million. That's actually right.
Yeah. 100 million.
Wow. This is this is a great crowd. Yes.
About hund00 million uh to make that
medicine and take it into humans for for
the first time. So you have to be very
very careful about how many of these
medicines you you take in into early
development. All right. So then you
start to do your early development
study. This is where you're doing dose
and schedule. You're giving it to the
right patient populations. And this is
when you see a really big inflection
point. So at the start of a clinical
trial
until the end, it's about a 10%
probability of success. At this point,
you go from about a 10% probability of
success. If you do the right trial,
you're going to about a 20, 30, 40,
potentially even a 50% probability of
success after what's called, at least in
poker, the flop. So now you get three
cards. So Jesse and Ben, there are three
cards that we all can play together.
I've got my two private cards, they have
their two private cards, and then we
have three in the middle. This is the
flop. I'm feeling pretty good because I
now have a pair of queens in addition to
ace high. This is a pretty good hand. So
basically what I'm trying to say here, I
hope this metaphor is working, is that
in early development, I'm feeling really
good at this point. I've picked the
right target. I've actually matched a
modality to a molecular mechanism of
action and I've done this early clinical
development study and it looks really
positive. But now I need to complete the
full hand. We do accelerated full
development and we start to see in this
case an ace. Now I got a pair of aces,
two queens, two pair. That's a good
hand. But at the end of the day, it's
about having a great label the FDA can
approve. And in this case, a queen,
that's a full house. That hand wins
almost every single time. So basically,
you need all of these together in order
to have a winning hand, in which case
this is a an approved drug. I mentioned
about hund00 million um to take a drug
into humans for the first time, and it's
over two two3 billion to ultimately get
a drug approved. But it's not the cost
of the successes, it's the cost of the
failures that really drives up that
price. So this is why human genetics can
help us with these billion dollar bets.
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going
to go through a few examples of of
programs in our pipeline. And I'm going
to go through them relatively quickly,
but the points are really going to
emphasize everything that I've just
talked about in the last few minutes.
Picking the right targets, matching
modality mechanism, seeing that early
clinical data, and ultimately doing what
you can to accelerate full development.
Now, and just one other example here,
you could have a competitor that goes
after the exact same targets. They pick
the right target, they make the right
molecule, but they stumble in early
clinical development. They don't design
the right early development trial. They
don't have the right biomarkers. They
don't have VJ on their team to really
understand details of of the mechanism
and how to understand if this drug is
working the way that it should. And so,
ultimately, uh, they're they're not
successful. So again, it's more than
just picking the right targets and
making the right molecules. Uh there's a
lot that happens in early development as
well. Okay. So the first story that I'm
going to tell you very quickly is a
story that I worked on when I was back
in academics. And this was understanding
the genetic basis of a molecule called
tick 2. And what this is showing is the
causal human biology for this is very
compelling. There are at least two or
three different common alals that are
loss of function and protect from risk
of multiple autoimmune diseases
including psoriasis, lupus and
rheumatoid arthritis. Uh there was a
study that was published by Lars Fuger
and colleagues Khali Dendrew that showed
that one copy leads to about a 10 to 20%
reduction in tick 2 signaling but two
copies that is in the homozygous state
leads to about a 70% reduction in tick 2
signaling. So it's loss of function at
about a 70% level that protects from
monmunity. And then this was one of the
first studies that actually did a few
was to look for few waswas as a way to
predict adverse drug events. And what we
saw with those same variants is they did
not increase risk of infection or other
blood disgraases. So it seemed like not
only was a good target based upon
efficacy, but it was a potentially a
safe target as well. But it was really
hard to make a therapeutic molecule
against this target. on the left hand
side is the regulatory domain. That's
where that that triangle is. There are a
lot of other molecules like tick 2, Jack
one, Jack 2, Jack 3 that have a lot of
homology in that orthosteric domain. So
every single time a company tried to
make a binder against the orthosteric
park pocket, they hit Jack one, Jack 2
and Jack 3, and that was associated with
side effects. So what BMS chemists did,
what BMS biologists did is they designed
a phenotypic screen and they uncovered
this alossteric pocket. Um actually I
got it backwards. The active site is
where most of the homology is. The
regulatory domain where the triangle is
that's where we identify the BMS
scientists a drug could bind to this
alossteric pocket but it could lock the
active domain in the inactive state. And
so BMS discovered a small molecule that
really rec recapitulated human genetics
in a very faithful way. And then in the
first in human clinical trial in this
case uh looking at an interferon
signature in psoriasis you can see about
a 70% reduction. So really precisely
phenopying the human genetics. So about
70% inhibition for human genetics and
about 70% inhibition uh for the drug. So
there's really nice phenopy of the drug
on this particular phenotype. Um and so
so tick 2 is now approved in psoriasis
and we have ongoing trials and other
autoimmune diseases specifically lupus
and and chogrin. So really if you go
through the metaphor you know you have
full house this is a successful drug and
an approved drug and we have other
ongoing trials as well. Okay. So now I
want to go to that second principle
matching modality to mechanism. And to
me again if I go back to where I was
about 15 or 20 years ago in academics I
was really focused on the target and
then I came to appreciate how much there
is now in our therapeutic armamentarium.
In the late 90s basically 90% of drugs
were small molecules. There were a
handful of more conventional auto uh
more conventional antibodies. Fast
forward today you've got and this is
just the BMS portfolio. You've got a
bunch of different ways to modulate
therapeutic targets. And there are a lot
on this list that we just don't pursue,
including many of the the genetic based
approaches that you've heard about over
the course of the day. But what I'll do
is I'll walk through a couple of stories
starting with small molecules, but I'll
touch on on a few of these. Um, so here
is a genetic target TLR7. Uh, there's
very strong human genetics as shown on
the far left. So TLR7 gain of function
mutations lead to a lupus-like phenotype
suggesting that inhibiting TLR7 could be
therapeutically beneficial. There are
some challenges in actually inhibiting
this target and that you had to get it a
small molecule to actually inhibit this
within the context of the endoome and on
the far right is that first in human
clinical study where we also saw a
change in an interferon signature uh for
a drug called aphimatorin. Um this drug
is now uh has just finished phase two
and is entering into phase three
clinical trials. Uh and this is some of
the clinical data uh that shows a very
nice separation in a subset of patients
uh with lupus that are called cutaneous
lupus. So CLE and what you're actually
seeing in the graph in the bottom row in
the purple is a nice difference between
a clinical score in patients with
cutaneous lupus compared to those same
patients who received a placebo. Um I
want to spend just a few minutes on a
different therapeutic modality target of
protein degradation. This is a way to
actually not just inhibit a a target of
interest but to degrade that that target
of interest. Um so the idea here is
there are a lot of uh validated uh
targets a lot of human disease
associated targets but most of them are
not amendable to more conventional small
and large molecules. In the case of
certain types of uh of proteins such as
transcription factors or those with
scaffolding functions, there's no
enzyatic function to inhibit. You have
to actually degrade or get rid of the
target, which is often difficult to do.
Um, and there's also benefit uh in terms
of using uh protein degraders uh to
overcome resistance of uh of small
molecule uh kynise inhibitors as well.
Um so this is a story that actually
builds nicely on the story that VJ told
in terms of um being able to induce
fetal hemoglobin. Um what I'm showing
you on this slide is that we actually
have identified two um uh one uh two two
targets that are that influence fetal
hemoglobin production. One of those two
is a genetically validated target. It
goes by the name Pokemon, also known as
ZBTV 7A. The other target is Whiz. And
what we found is that we can identify a
molecular glue molecule um that can bind
to an E3 ligase on one part. So it's
basically one molecule that's a
therapeutic molecule binds to an E3
ligase and then it recruits these two
transcription factors to a single
complex. It shuttles them to the
proteosome and leads to degradation. So
we can basically degrade these two
transcription factors turning on fetal
hemoglobin in our pre-clinical models
and we are um in clinical trials today
and I think by by the end of the year
early next year uh we should know the
extent to which this turns on a fetal
hemoglobin. Um so if it does work it has
the potential to be an oral small
molecule pill that achieves the same
level of efficacy as cascade which is an
Xvivo uh gene editing uh approach.
Uh here's another example where the
target BCL6 is a well-known um uh
ankcoenic driver. Here the genetic data
is not from germline genetic data but
it's from sematic cell genetic data. So
there's a lot of great sematic cell
genetic data in oncology. Again, you
heard about it from VJ in terms of a
clonal amount of poesis, but many of
these encogenic drivers can actually
lead to to uh to cancers and BCL6 is a
known encogenic driver. Um but like many
transcription factors and other targets,
it's just very difficult to drug with a
typical kinase inhibitor. So what
scientists at BMS did is they created
what's called a heterobifunctional
degrader. So one arm binds to BCL6, the
other arm binds to an E3 liase called
cereablon. It brings the complex
together leads to BCL6 degradation. So
very strong human biology in this case
from from sematic cell genetics. We've
got a really interesting uh degrader
that's heterofunctional by degrader. And
this is also a program that's advancing
in clinical development and we'll know
probably within the next year if we're
seeing the PKPD relationship that we
expect. Okay, just a few more quick
stories before I go on to the saturation
mutagenesis part of the talk. Uh and
that is biootherrapeutics. Uh and here
again another story of causal human
biology. In this case it's T-regs and
cancer. There's no really strong human
genetics to implicate CCR8 positive
T-regs in cancer. But through single
cell sequencing, and you've heard a lot
about that today, what we've been able
to do is to identify that a subset of
T-regs uh that are identified in
patients with lung cancer and other
types of cancers are a negative
predictor uh for for outcome. that is
the presence of these highly um uh um
suppressive inflam or highly suppressive
CC positive T-regs are uh a negative
predictor of response to checkpoint
inhibitors and so we predict is by
binding to CCR8 on the surface of cells
and degrading um uh the basically
getting rid of these CCR8 positive
T-regs will be able to allow anti- PD1
and other checkpoint inhibitors uh to
work more effectively. This is also a
program that is in in first in human
studies now and we should know more in
the next year or two whether we've
achieved clinical proof of concept. All
right, I'm going to go through one more
example and do this very quickly because
we talked about small molecules and
large molecules but we're also in an age
where we can actually engineer living
cells uh to be therapeutics themselves
and this is in the form of of autotogus
carti. Um and then to me this is one of
the most exciting areas of science and
biology right now. Uh because I used to
practice clinical rheatology. Patients
would come in young women childbearing
age with lupus. They would they would
give them a very strong
immunosuppressive which could get their
disease under control and inevitably
they would ask well when do I come off
of these medicines and the answer was
almost always never. So imagine being,
you know, a young healthy person
suddenly getting this new diagnosis and
being told you're going to be on
imunosuppressants for the rest of your
life is pretty devastating. So this
concept of being able to reset immune
memory to deplete the auto reactive
cells to get rid of them completely and
allowing a new immune system to
reconstitute and basically that new
reconstituted immune system is healthy.
This is what we're able to do with
auttogus cartis. for these carti cells.
Um, but by the way, just on the bottom
left, there wasn't a whole lot of
genetic data that implicated C19.
Specifically, it was a human
pharmarmacology study where an
investigator uh, uh, George Shet
actually took CD19 CARTT, which is
approved for lymphoma, tried it in a
very small number of patients with
lupus, and sure enough, it completely
reset their immune system, and they've
been off all of imunosuppressive drugs
for now for several years. um we've now
treated multiple patients uh dozens of
patients with not just lupus but other
autoimmune diseases and we've been able
to recapitulate this finding as well. So
causing biology from human
pharmarmacology matching modality
mechanism it's an autotogus engineered
cell that actually kills the CD19
lineage of B cells and we now have
clinical proof of concept and we're
entering into registrational trials. Um,
so these are the examples that sort of
show how the sort of framework of these
five principles work in action and how
we're using them all the time within our
portfolio today. Okay, so I have about
10 minutes left and I'm going to go
through uh how we're trying to expand
our understanding of individual variants
uh to basically build out this toolkit
even further. Um, so when I moved from
academic to industry, this was kind of
my simplistic view of how I thought we
could use human genetics to identify new
targets. Not just identifying a single
alil at a particular gene, but with
sequencing, we'd find more and more
alals. And we could say, all right, each
one of those X's that's meant to be a um
that's disease associated. Along the Y
ais is a human phenotypes. Imagine high
LDL cholesterol, high risk of disease,
um, as examples, you know, high body
mass index. And if you could find alals
that were associated with a human
phenotype that was an appropriate
surrogate for drug efficacy, and you
could understand the function, gain of
function or loss of function, you could
begin to estimate these dose response
curves, an efficacy curve, and also know
if there was an adequate therapeutic
window. Um the challenge has been and
we've been talking about this all day is
we can find that sort of x-axis pretty
easily using bioank. So we can look
quantitatively at whether an alil is
associated with high or low cholesterol.
What level of risk um is contributed in
terms of risk of autoimmune diseases.
But what's incredibly hard is getting
that variant uh to function. Uh and um
just a really quick story when I just
started my posttos Pierre I don't know
if any of you know ick um but we had
just done one of the first like a thou h
100 thousand snip chips for math metrics
on the hatmap cell lines and we could
actually identify 30% of common variance
and that was a number that totally blew
my mind and I remember I saying to me
and we were sitting over there in one
Kendall Square up in one of the
conference rooms he's like can you
imagine if we could just annotate every
single variant not just by its where it
is in the genome but by its function.
Imagine how much more powerful our
genetic association studies would
actually be. So not just looking at
linkage to singleian and the static is
it associated or not but you could add a
coefficient that tells you something
about function. And I remember thinking
wow is that's a great idea that sounds
really hard. And sure enough fast
forward to where we are today. I think
we're getting po we're getting to a
state where we should be able to
incorporate these types of weights into
our association study. So I'm going to
tell you now a story that's going to
build on the tick 2 story that I told
you about earlier. And so the question
here is can we take a known validated
genetic target that has an orthosteric
pocket and an alossteric pocket. Can we
mutate every single amino acid uh at
this particular protein and can we
uncover the known alossteric and the
orthosteric sites where these drugs
actually bind and can we learn new
things about um this particular molecule
that could potentially help with large
scale association study.
So um just just quickly in terms of what
we know about the genetic variation
across tick 2 and the upper graph is the
clinbar variants. So there are three
variants rare variants that can when
when tick 2 is knocked out completely
causes primary immune deficiency. The
next graph below is the nomad uh
variants uh and there are several
hundred uh variants and that's shown at
the top part of the bar graph and above
a particular frequency spectrum is
what's shown below. And if you blow this
out and look at the fre frequently
spectrum what you can see on the far
right are the four common variants.
Three of these are associated with
protection from autoimmunity. But if you
take a threshold of 10 to the minus 4th
or less, they're about 447 misses snips
from the UK bioank that are within this
particular category. Um these are all
below you. 01 in terms of the minor
little frequency threshold. We know
nothing about the function. But can we
use saturation immunogenesis to assign
function to each of these 447 variants?
So this is where we worked with Octant
um to do a deep mutational scan where
again we mutated every single amino acid
by every other possible amino acid
across the entire protein. And we did
this with two different assays. The
first assay that I'll tell you quickly
about is an interferon signal signaling
assay. Uh what you can actually see uh
is there's a cassette that's inserted
that has different tick 2 amino acid
changes that codes for uh the uh tick 2
that will bind to the interferon
signaling receptor. It'll signal down
through and there's an interferon
signaling response element which can
then be read out in the form of a
barcode. So about 11% of amino acids
when mutated by this assay could lead to
changes in interferon signaling. uh and
you can see uh in particular this line
uh where a stop variant was introduced
but you can also begin to see domains
and I'll describe these domains in just
a minute. Um the second assay that we
did was a protein abundance assay. to a
simpler assay and I'm going to come back
to this because I think this has some
application as we think about scaling
this approach up but a protein abundance
assay where we also introduce um every
single amino acid variant into tick 2
and then we measure we can sort by GFP
also with a barcode and just measure
relative protein abundance. So about 20%
of amino acids uh when mutated lead to a
signal in this particular assay and what
I think you can appreciate is there's a
lot of overlap uh between uh the two
different assays. And when you look at
where where the um alossteric site and
the is located, this is the name of the
drug dravisitib. You can identify the
alossteric binding site with this
functional assay and you can also
identify very clearly the catalytic
site. Uh and at least in the protein
abundance assay, you can identify the
disease associated P104 A variant. Um
although it's not quite as clear I know
it's difficult to see it's not quite as
as clear that that variant has an effect
on on interfere on signaling.
So there are other positive controls
that gave us confidence that the assays
were working including uh different
annotations by alpha missense some
literature associated loss of function
variants and then three variants that
were reported as as pathogenic. Okay.
And I'm going to come back to the three
starred sites because these identify
potentially novel aloseric sites. So um
this identifies again um a number of of
variants that could be loss of function
or gain of function by protein
expression along the the y-axis or
interferon signaling along the x-axis.
As I mentioned P104A which is one of the
disease associated varants comes up with
a good signal by protein expression but
but not by uh interferon signaling. Um
and I think with these types of assays
we can begin to model um where these
mutations are occurring on the two
domains of tick 2 the the the the
regulatory domain and then the uh the
the kynise domain. We also refer to
these as the the catalytic and
non-catalytic domains. Um and you can
see again the active site alsteric site
and the location of P104A.
Um but there are these variants that
look like they have an effect on
interferon alpha but no effect on
protein abundance. um could this be a
potential way to uncover novel
alossteric sites? Um so what we did is
this filtering mechanism to look for
variants that affected interferon alpha
signaling along the top uh whether there
was evidence of destabilization.
If not, could this be potentially a
catalytic alesteric site? And you can
see here we're just annotating a few of
these potential sites, which actually
two of these sites are right at this
kyna pseudocinase interface as shown by
the blue stars. Um, and there are and
this is a fulllength view of the
protein. um where you can actually see
in in uh yellow here is the kind of this
ribbon of where the receptor itself is
uh is uh is is going through uh the
protein and the protein is binding
around it. Uh and there are potential
sites uh not just on the where the
protein binds or interacts with the
plasma membrane but also where tick 2 is
engaging with the the interferon
receptor.
Um now one other way that we actually
use this data is to actually look at
where the drug dravisit binds and can we
actually map um residues that are b
interacting between the the the gene the
protein tick 2 uh and the known
inhibitor at the alossteric site. Uh and
the quick version of this story is yes
we can as we actually go through and use
different concentrations of the drug. So
lower concentration of the drug you
really find only those sites that are
direct directly interacting uh with the
drug itself and at higher concentrations
of the drug um you identify um other
other sites as well. So it provides a
nice kind of functional complement uh to
structural data. Okay. So we started by
saying if we could only just annotate uh
the human um phenotype data by by
function and what I've told you at least
for tick 2 we've been able to use deep
mutational scan to begin to assign
functions to each of those 447 variants
and so now I want to go back to
basically the question that I had
proposed 20 or so years ago is if we
begin to incorporate this information
into our genetic association studies you
know can we actually have more
wellpowered powered rare variant
associations. And so we took these um uh
these these variants uh and we annotated
uh whether not just by common and rare
but by level of tick to 2 um expression.
And we used a couple of traditional
burden test methods that are shown here
without any waiting and it didn't find
an association with the 300 or 35,000
cases from the UK biioank compared to
308 uh uh controls. uh but we began to
incorporate the output from the um the
DMS variant scores into a model, we
began to see more statistically
significant associations with this
genetic burden test. So again suggesting
that as our methods of assigning
function to each of the variants become
more and more powerful, we should be
able to improve power of rare variant
association studies.
Um you know I will say in listening to
the talks today sort of occurs to me
that if we can do this more and more uh
not just with these types of functional
data but with the predictive data and
the modeling data that has been talked
about today hopefully we'll be able to
do a better job of basically
incorporating these types of weights
into our association studies. And in
fact, here are a few newer methods that
don't use um uh functional data directly
uh but do appear to have uh stronger and
more wellpowered um statistical results
uh using the same uh data set. Okay, so
just two more slides and then I'm going
to stop. Uh I want to then sort of talk
about genetic associations and how this
is used. We're using this information to
guide indication selection. So what I'm
showing you on this particular chart is
three v are three variants within tick
2. And you can see for psoriasis, RA and
lupus, these three variants are
protective at a very high level of
statistical significance. Inflammatory
bowel disease has just a different
pattern here where one of the three
variants looks like it's a risk variant.
And this is something that we haven't
really able been able to figure out. Um
but it does look like it has a very
different pattern in inflammatory bowel
disease. And at least the clinical
trials to date have been successful in
psoriasis. They have not been successful
in inflammatory bowel disease. That is
so tick 2 did not work in treating
patients with inflammatory bowel
disease. And as I've mentioned, studies
are ongoing with lupus. So we think and
hope that it'll work in this particular
indication. Um but we'll know more by
the end of the year. Um but if you
actually sort of plot out uh the the the
different variants uh in a slightly
different way um and look at um the
opposing effects across the proteome
again you see in some cases the variants
act in the same direction in other in
other instances they act in in opposite
direction. Okay so I'm going to stop
here but just to conclude I know I went
through things pretty quickly. Most
drugs fail because of lack of efficacy.
Hopefully human genetics can help. I
talked about placing billion-dollar bets
using these principles to think about
making the right decisions not just for
the target and the modality but how do
we actually do those early clinical
studies and ultimately how do we do full
development for drug approvals. Um
genetic dose response curves um can
hopefully be used to define uh exciting
targets and these alyic series and the
deep mutational scans in tick 2 um have
the ability to further build out these
genetic dose response curves. And so I
guess you know the question that I would
leave you all with is what what should
be done next? Is there a way for us to
do saturation mutenesis across a larger
proportion of the proteium or are the
computational methods sufficiently uh
strong at this point in time that we
don't need to necessarily do these types
of of functional studies. Um so there's
a lot I think um we could uh we could
certainly uh discuss. Um before I do, I
want to let you know that um the paper
on deep mutational scan should be posted
on bioarchchive uh this week. Uh here
are the authors and again a special
shout out to the scientist at at Octant
who did really all of the saturation
mutagenesis work but working closely
with Joe Moranville and his team uh to
work through the associations that I
described to you. So thank you very
much.
>> Thank you. Any questions?
Lovely talk, Robert.
And I'm very fond of it sick, too. Uh,
so I I feel like there's like a butt
coming here.
>> Ben,
the question ask is that the question
I'm gonna ask is um about the tick 2
functional essay.
>> Yeah. I think, you know, to me a lot of
this turns around the quality of the
gene specific assays and how well we
think they're actually recapitulating
the function that may be perturbed by
the variance that we're introducing.
Right? So, you got to really trust the
assay part.
>> And so, I guess the question is how many
genes do you think we have that caliber
of assay for? Is that assay capturing
all of the functions for kick 2? And how
do you think about approaching it in
that way versus I think a lot of what
we've heard about today is you know
transcrytoics and general cellular
properties but they're maybe not
specific about the function of the
protein itself.
>> There there was a lot of calibrating the
interferon assay. There was a second
assay that actually never worked
measuring 23 signaling that we never you
know were able to sort of validate with
the positive controls. P4A is a known
functional variant and it didn't come up
in the interferon assay. I mean I kind
of intrigued by this protein abundance
assay. So maybe that is something that
could be done um at scale and is
sufficiently agnostic to sort of nuances
of biology. So that's the one that I
sort of wonder is that something that we
could actually scale up and make
relationships to circulating um pro
proteins as well.
>> Yeah, Brad.
>> Yeah, this is me. Oh yeah, nice talk.
Remember David Alcheler talking about
the arrow of time so many taught me
about that 15 years ago or something
like that. It's a beautiful application.
One the one exception was the CCR8
or the getting rid of the T-reg
populations. And there's so much data
now on changes in population of cells
and micro environment cancer and other
diseases. That's not quite causal
though, right? It's just associated. So
how do you you're you're clearly using
that in one of your as a premise for one
one of your studies.
>> Yeah. How widely are you using that and
how do you get at causality in those
cases?
>> Yeah. So I think I think in that case so
you're totally right. I mean you're
basically looking at an association the
presence of these T-regs in patients who
don't respond to checkpoint blockade.
That's a that's a correlation. There's
not a causal relation. We try to
actually look more longitudinally to
understand you know what do we know
about the phenotype of those T-Rexs? You
know when do they infiltrate? Um but at
the end of the day it's more of a
correlative relationship than than than
the causal relationship in that specific
case. So I think you know I we often say
you know causal human biology yes no and
it's far more I think of a gradient and
I would say something like tick 2 very
strong that's probably a you know three
to fourfold increased probability of
success. CCR8 I'd probably put it as a
you know you know 50 you know 100% maybe
a 50% increased probability of success
but not the same level as I think some
of the genetics that we actually talked
about
but one right here uh
very cool talk and um on the tick 2
screen I was wondering about the
in the case where you don't have changes
in abundance but you do see effect in
activity and how much of those changes
were uh due to disruption or creation of
denovo phosphorilation sites altering
you know protein activity which is an
old you know a way that a lot of these
kynases are actually regulated by and
how much of those actually exist
naturally out there and you know just
yeah it's a great question I'm not
totally sure um so I I I don't know I
mean the way that we kind of frame this
is maybe these are novel um alossteric
sites but I think that that particular
biology is not entirely clear to me so I
think that's going to take more work to
sort of sort out. Thank you.
>> All right, a question in the or question
in the back there.
>> Uh thank you that was really
interesting. I was wondering you know
when you when we talk about how genetics
informs drug discovery my impression is
it's mostly on the sense of like one
variant going to one trait but as your
example in the last few slides showed we
have a lot more much richer phenotyping
of individuals now like and now we have
the opportunity to look at variant
plyotrophy do you have any comments on
whether there's something that we what
can we do with plyotrophy now that we
have this data like you think it will be
useful
>> I think I think plyotropy can be used
for a couple things one it can be used
to guide indications as a way to say it
works here, it's going to work in the
next two or three indications as well.
But I think plyotropy can also be used
to begin to predict you know adverse
drug events and so plyotropy can work
both ways. It can help you with
phenotypes that are good surrogates for
efficacy but also help you for good
phenotypes that are surrogates for for
toxicity.
>> And I know we're over time so maybe we
can we can stop here and head over to
>> maybe one last I think there's already a
mic out in the audience. Thank you uh
Robert to to my question is related to
your last comment about what's next
should we do the deep mutational scan
maybe more systematically so while
you're talking about it that's really
remind me in oncology field I came from
oncology field right that when we
discover all the somatic mutations in
patient and indicating maybe certain
genes is uncleco gene and having a deep
map where every single gene are knocked
out and functional effect measured
across thousands of cells lines where we
can correlate. So that's really a deep
kind of knowledge base we use to build
that kind of a functional relationship
and confidence of a genes a causal gene.
So in some way I would think if we can
have this kind of systematic functional
data that will really help us to
interpret the genetic data in a much
more objective way.
>> Yeah.
>> I don't know if it's feasible but I
think that would be great to have.
>> Yeah. I think I think the more I mean we
talk about how we train and build these
models. I think we often train them off
the data sets that we actually have. Um
you know I sort of imagine a world in
which we actually um you know try to do
far more like say mutational scans to
look at protein abundance to uncover
alesteric sites and maybe then that
could help us feed you know the models
that we actually use to identify um
alsteric these regulatory domains in a
way that's it's kind of difficult to to
do today. Um but it does go back to some
of the assays as Brad mentioned. So I
think in oncology for example um you
know for for cell cycle growth and and
basically things that you know
accelerate growth or decelerate growth
those are some assays that I think are
amendable to this type of approach.
>> Thank you.
>> Great. Thank you so much for uh the
presentation Robert. Uh please join me
in giving him another round of applause.