how are you all feeling today very that
was a rhetoric question I want to show
that you know health and Healthcare is
so close to every person and how we all
have deeply personal relationship with
health so uh I want to talk about a new
program starting with MIT on uh Health
Science semiconductor Ai and advanced
biology and uh what is exciting about
this project is that we are addressing
not only one of the most press topics of
our time uh for those of you who have
been in the meeting yesterday or the
presentation yesterday about 20% of GDP
more than $2 and5 trillion dollars is
spend on healthc care and still uh we
are talking about kind of growing faster
than GDP and the expectation is that
based on the chart I have here by uh
sorry by by uh 2040 is going to be 30%
of the GDP just Healthcare so that see
shows the enormity of the problem and
how we can uh Change the World by making
an impact
there uh I didn't know about that I got
the information from some of the people
who work in Pharma and bio drug
Discovery cost about a billion dollar
per drug and that is enormous amount of
money and diagnostic is about 10% of the
total cost of healthcare and as I said
uh these things are growing one thing
that I couldn't put a dollar sign in
front of it is the value of not being
sick that is enormous because I'm sure
there is a lot of interesting topics we
can cover on that front so um one thing
that I want to highlight is that so why
we are trying to focus on nanotechnology
aspects of the healthcare the chart on
the right shows that how semiconductor
technology is growing uh today
semiconductor technology is about half a
trillion dollars and it took us about
60 something to 70 years to get to here
and the expectation is that by 2030 it's
going to be a trillion dollars so it's
doubling in 7
years compared to what happened last uh
last seven decades so that is an
enormous opportunity to have
semiconductor and I'm going to use nanot
technology rather than semiconductor
because covers also Ms Technologies and
this could be very exciting why because
it's extremely affordable and extremely
powerful
look at what's happening around you in
terms of capabilities of your
smartphones your doorbells and
everything around you is becoming so
intelligent and so connected the other
of course Revolution that is happening
is the data Revolution on the left side
of it what you see is that the amount of
data is introduced to us is about a
thousand times more than the server
power that is supporting data so we are
we have to grow 1,000x on server power
to keep up with the amount of data that
we dealing with so how can we leverage
these two revolutions to change or come
up with transformative opportunities in
healthcare AI is already changing
Healthcare I don't have time to go
through that but each of these are very
interesting topic this genomics is
becoming very exciting part how to get
all this data and use AI for that
identifying potential drug targets
that's a fascinating topic um detecting
and analyzing 20 ,000 protein molecules
and use the machine learning how to take
it to the next level of information and
Drug Discovery phenotyping and genetic
heterogenity and robotic surgery robotic
surgery I don't know if you have seen
this but I was in one of these major
robotic surgery companies and with 11
needle size arms going inside the
patient in the less than half an inch
opening and does all the surgeries while
doctor is sitting the other side of the
room in front of monitor controlling it
and Recovery is a lot faster Precision
is higher and machines are controlling a
lot of diagnostic aspects of it and one
of the things that are very close to my
heart because I was involved and working
on that one is the development of this
uh patch which is clinical quality
continuous glucose monitoring and U now
with the amount of data you can offer on
a real time you can not only use it for
Diagnostic but for many treatment
purposes so Confluence of three topics
and three Innovations in science and
technology put us in a very unique
position to offer new solutions for
health semiconductor nanotechnology Ai
and biology again since time is short
I'm going to briefly talk about that the
fact that you can have a minimally
invive bio sensor with a lot of advanced
electronics on the patch on your arm or
your chest or your neck that can
revolutionize a lot of things what you
see in biology on therapeutic on
proteomics and some of the
pharmacogenomics it's amazing how you
can come up with a different insight
into Diagnostic and therapeutic sites of
molecules so the question is how
technology can break this continuous
growth of the healthcare cost without
compromising quality the answer is
personalized Healthcare that has been
around for quite a while how we can
individualize healthare so that we can
tailor the diagnostic and treatment to
individuals and the way to do that is
really to have a real time information
close the loop with AI and offer
treatments that are optimized for the
individuals so this chart came from a
work between imch and IBM or another
company I mean nature publication but
it's interesting to show that
in addition to mors law which is now
getting to the limits uh really there
are a lot of other branches that are
even more relevant to healthcare because
a lot of these devices like this glucose
patch that I showed you uses about a
couple of 100K Gates it doesn't need 2
nanometer technology or anything like
that in fact we are happy with 45
nanometer for these devices plus the
fact that the RF side is a Bluetooth
that is using 45 nanometer technology as
well but it requires silicon germanium
it requires some sensing devices like
nanowires it requires Nano pores and a
lot of technologies that are not
necessarily A next generation of the
seos but the derivatives that we think
is very important for this technology so
again in the interest of time I'm not
going to spend a lot of time on that one
but I want to highlight the fact
that semiconductor magic is unparalleled
with anything else in the human history
the fact that we get get a $2 million
radar about 25 years ago and make a chip
that is doing exactly the same thing for
less than
$10 what other field do you know that
over 30 years can save the cost four
orders of magnitude with the same
functionality can you imagine if your
car your or the plane was like as
efficient as we're talking semiconductor
we have been traveling a speed of light
or a cray superc computer becomes a
laptop and here are examples that you
see in the real world we have a lot of
interesting opportunities to bring
Electronics to the healthcare at
clinical quality to close the loop
between sensing Ai and
transducer so let me I stole my thunder
already let me tell you how we are going
to work on this thing there are two
elements to that or two approaches one
is bio Inspire I don't know if you have
noticed in your recent flight I'm flying
every week so I've noticed a lot there
is a winglet these days around the PLS I
mean the end of the wi goes up it's a
famous theory of finite elements that
you can reduce the drag by using
wingless boing invented that a lot of
scientists work on the on the um finite
element techniques to come up with that
you know that Eagles have been doing
that for about a million years they have
been GL already they know how to reduce
the drag why don't we learn from these
and we try to invent the wheel I don't
know if you're creationist or you're
evolutionist but either way there's a
lot of intelligence there and the beauty
of that is we can learn from that the
problem is we are stuck with old ways of
doing things one noan served us well
since 40s so every architecture we are
trying to mold it into that architecture
why don't we learn from the fact that 10
to the 16 flops in the brain only Burns
10 Watt and a typical GPU requires a
nuclear power reactor so something is
wrong in in terms of processing
capabilities there is one tiny issue we
don't know how brain works still all the
billions of dollars there but we know
that brain is not working based on one
Oney machine I mean it doesn't digitize
data it doesn't have memory and
processor separately and we can learn a
lot lot from
that uh I don't know how much time we
have but we have a project that is very
interesting because our ears the way
that our ears analyze voice the ear can
has these 2,000 tiny muscles and when
the air goes through the canal it
already depending on stiffness of these
muscles it does an automatic fft so what
it sends to the brain is not raw data
it's the pulses that are signatures of
the frequency domain of data that is
fascinating and the power consumption is
orders of magnitudes less than a typical
microphone and Tia and sigma Delta and
processor and so on and so forth so
there is a lot to gain from there the
challenge is how to make it more
platform than kind of Niche so here's a
typical sensor that we are thinking
about in the future neumorphic
neuromorphic processing of course
Optical
interconnect power from the
backside uh
cim Computing memory and of course a
range of sensors that you're are putting
on top of that so the vision we talking
about in this new center which is
collaboration with IMC linol lab and
Mass General Hospital is how to close
the
loop sensing modality on the left hand
side that's where we have molecular
sensing RF sensing impedance
spectroscopy um vital sensing and so on
of course doctors and Physicians are not
comfortable with this massive amount of
data so we take it to a learning machine
how to take that data translate it to
information and then fit it to
actionable uh kind of uh clinical plan
so that we can have a drug delivery
optimized based on individuals
metabolism or other ways of stimulation
that uh is very practical today uh and
it was just a dream 5 years ago there is
no timer here so let me know when I'm
minutes another three minutes no not
negotiable okay
so I have another 10is slide so
5 Second for a okay
so so what's happening on the bio
semiconductor and nanotechnology we see
that detection of the molecules analysis
of dnas and uh proteins diagnostic uh
protein isopor that you know you have
heard about a lot and yesterday we
talked about that drug delivery cell
culture and general cell manipulation
all of them not necessarily with
transistors but some combination of
nanotechnologies and SOS readout or or
maybe some stimulation through acoustic
waves or
Optical uh so you know mems guys like
caner liers because caner liers are very
sensitive when you get to Nano level the
problem is they are very sensitive to
everything temperature pressure
everything so it takes a lot of work to
make it reproducible but now you can
imagine a mems with multiple caner lers
functionalized for different molecules
and depending on which molecule you
absorb you get a different stiffness and
you read out the stiffness and you can
have
a lab on a chip so lab on a chip which
was a dream now is very much practical
and
doable since I have three minutes I'm
going to skip some of the most exciting
stuff out so it was your call you know
so anyways so uh we have this up to
acoustic ultrasonic and cardio patch
just watch it and then I'll talk to
about that later so five modalities that
we are focusing on in this talk and in
this lab one is chemical clinicians and
scientists in BIO love molecules so one
way is that bringing molecule right on
top of the semiconductor exposing
semiconductor to molecule and then
detect variations for example threshold
voltage or variations of characteristics
of transistors it's very
powerful and we love it because we are
working on a minimally invasive way let
me tell you a secret about semiconductor
semi conductor industry loves
scale Texas instrument shipped more than
50 billion chips last year it has to be
millions and hundred millions and
billions because scale brings
affordability cost and functionality so
when things are minimally invasive they
scale if they're invasive they're very
important but they don't scale how many
people are willing to inject
Semiconductor in their body if they are
healthy so that is why we are focusing
on minimally invasive stuff magnetics
they have some fast so the way that you
can talk to molecules is not just
chemistry that's the main message that
we are trying to give jointly with IMC
and lincol and MGH it's not just
chemistry you can interrogate molecules
through photonics you can interrogate
molecules through Ultrasonics or
magnetics and there are examples of that
but again I'm not going to cover it so
so here is what uh Dr Jaffer shared with
me that was very interesting uh concept
to combine
the um continuous monitoring with a
digital twin of
organs and with that you can have a
profile of organ of individual patient
and see what's going on in terms of
Diagnostic and Drug delivery there is
one biological problem here in the body
organs don't work
independently so what happens in your
liver and heart and brain are very
tightly coupled that's why you get
higher blood pressure when you're
anxious so what we need to do is that we
need to expand the concept and making it
a little bit more
holistic uh I'm going to skip lab on a
cheap microfluidic and I want to borrow
a statement from yoga bear the future is
not what it used to be anymore and
that's why because of the all the
combination of new uh ways of doing
biology machine learning
nanotechnology and new materials and
even Quantum biology
can open a new horizon that we have
never seen before thank you for your
attention thank you for this Visionary
talk Ahad um we have time for maybe two
or three questions oh I need to stay up
there yeah I wish you would have more
time to hear the extended version of
your talk
yes any questions in the room
got to throw you a question about uh
what do you think is going to be the
biggest challenge to take this Vision
forward because it's a very exciting
Vision how much time do we have so okay
so I think uh the biggest challenge is
that and I'm realizing that the more I
spend time on it Healthcare and medical
is the most complex ecosystem I've ever
seen I mean if you think about
autonomous vehicles we need to work with
two groups of people tier one suppliers
and OEM car manufacturers and that
you're done in health you have to talk
to clinicians hospitals Pharma Labs
Medtech doctors and everybody should be
happy with the adoption of new
technology because it's not just about
technology so I see two major challenges
one of course we need to make sure that
our users or and customers acknowledge
and appreciate what we are doing
so we have two types of users here for
this technology one is Physicians and
clinicians that is a little bit more
straightforward because they have a set
of protocols if you go to your
cardiologist there are five biomarkers
they check in addition to your blood
pressure and then they prescribe things
now we can tell them okay we can do it
more frequently and we can close the
loop more intelligently like do and all
that the other part which is even more
interesting is scientists who come up
with the next drug or next dosage of the
drug and they want to monitor tons of
stuff like tens of thousands of proteins
and stuff so we need to make sure they
are in the loop from day one otherwise
we get into this cycle of I have a great
solution I don't know what problems I'm
solving so but then the other thing is
the
incentives you cannot change the
ecosystem you have work within ecosystem
but incentivize people to adopt it and I
think the good side so the question is
why it hasn't happened yet for two
reasons one technology the second one is
that now Healthcare the way it is is so
burdensome that cannot be sustainable
you cannot have 30% of GDP just on
Healthcare so something has to be done
so people have come to that realization
and personalized Healthcare everybody
admits is a way out of that have
multiple hands you decide who go maybe
one one more question because we are a
little short of time need to un move on
to my next
talk thank you so much Professor B so
one of the reasons that digital has been
scaling up is because of the abstraction
the year we talked a little bit about
that notion of digital twin earlier uh
I'm going to use an analog example in
semiconductor and I'll connect it to the
can you speak up a little bit yes can
you hear me now yeah so let's say you're
trying to build a simple analog circuit
you have to use H Spice in fact you can
use it do it without HS spice you can
take a model for
upamp which is which has infinite gain
and put it there and build your circuit
but if the same circuit is going to be
on a Hypersonic missile you're going to
have to use a different model for that
up because it it's exposed to a extreme
temperature so when we think about the
health you did talk about the modeling
aspect the personalization which is very
challenging it needs to be personalized
you're also looking at sort of a
multiscale modeling starting from
molecules going to tissues going to
organs so how do you think the
abstraction layer should be viewed here
to uh so that we can start building
feasible Solutions yeah I mean with my
limited knowledge about biology I don't
see any ways that you can have a Cadence
for biology I mean that is very
difficult and uh the reason for that is
unlike a typical semiconductor device
that we know where the electrons and
holes are and how they are traveling
across it's such a multi-dimensional
body in the yesterday's meeting one of
the questions was that how spirituality
impacts your health or meditation
I mean how your brain or mindset is
going to change our I mean there are
studies shows that I mean in fact I was
reading a paper in Scientific American
just a couple of days ago that five
minutes meditation every day can impact
almost every organ in the body how do I
model that so there are things in the
body that is extremely
complicated and the or or another
example I used yesterday that a tiny
Magneto stimulate in your ankle can
control your bladder I mean these things
are so complex in the body I think
abstraction needs to be at the level
that can add Insight but not uh intended
to be comprehensive because impossible
it's such a complex Machinery I mean
with all these billions of dollars on
brain study we barely know what the heck
is going on in our brain so there's so
many things now the beauty of that AI
with minimum physical model AI can deal
with unknowns and find correlations that
sometimes is amazing and sometimes very
insightful thank you so much thank you
thank you