Yeah. Next up, we'll welcome to the
stage Nicholas Fry, who is the thermal
energy networks market lead for Jacobs.
All right. Uh, good morning everybody.
Uh, as mentioned, I'm the thermal energy
networks market lead for Jacobs in North
America. So, I primarily deal with, uh,
district energy systems, uh, ambient
temperature loops, things of that
nature. Single building systems is
something that I consult on every once
in a while, but we have other design
teams for that generally speaking. So I
will go through uh some basic
differences. I think it's hard to follow
uh Connor for a better introduction to
ground source heat pump systems for
standalone building systems. But uh this
should give you an idea of when we
transition to networks, the advantages
uh that we can harness uh and use to
optimize uh our building heating and
cooling systems across large scales. So
citycale systems, regional scale
systems, neighborhood is easy in my
opinion. Um so back to the basics just a
little bit. I'm sorry I wasn't here
yesterday. Hopefully you got a little
bit of this. There are different
completion types for vertical ground
heat exchangers that are important in
considerations when we're thinking about
a utility scale product. Right? So this
has to be something that is uh less
capital intensive and can be paid for
over the duration of the system
operation. Typically uh a utility wants
to look at a 30 to 50 year time scale.
Gas networks they go out to 70-year
projections. Uh so we want to make sure
that we reduce the capital costs at the
beginning. Uh the typical ground source
completion in the United States right
now is conductive closed loop vertical
systems. Those are actually uh capital
cost intensive by comparison to openloop
systems. Of course, you're you're uh
leveraging uh a reduction in operations
and maintenance costs by using the
closed loop systems
uh and going with conduction dominant.
You're sacrificing the potential of
taking uh the groundwater directly and
using that heat exchange uh and the heat
capacity it's offering to the system uh
to reduce the amount of drilling that
you have to do.
But we can also consider geothermal
networks as being multi-source and
multi-sync, right? So we don't just have
to do drilling. We don't have to meet
our entire load with the drilling. And
the the buildings around us have their
own histories. So we have some uh relic
structures that are are designed around
our steam systems, right? and to
retrofit those uh for example Empire
State Building quite a task right you
can imagine that that thing was built
around a steam system and you don't want
to just gut the iconic structure itself
so over time we're going to have to
think about expanding on the peripheries
of our existing central systems so
you're going to encounter uh various uh
requirements on building entering water
temperatures that are going to kind of
dictate how you have to put this system
together. The temperature regimes are
going to vary.
So, you're going to encounter perhaps
combined heat and power systems when
you're looking at building stock
decarbonization.
And uh this goes into something that is
already a district energy unit. It's
it's considered very high efficiency,
but you're also um exposing the owners
to a variable fuel cost. So, in this
case, I've got biomass systems shown. Uh
but you can also have you can also have
everything from coal to natural gas for
these combined heat and power systems.
And you can think about expanding with
geothermal energy networks at the
periphery where these district energy
systems exist.
And so going into the sources and syncs
that exist across our geographic area
that we can leverage to decrease that
capital cost at the beginning of your
your project consideration and your
feasibility studies. Uh one of the
majors uh that's that's taking its place
in geothermal and hybrid systems is
wastewater energy transfer.
Uh there's a few different manufacturers
out there. You can either do interceptor
connects which is those u fluid conduits
that are exiting each structure or
running down uh your your neighborhood
uh in a in a main collector. Or you can
do an effluent heat recovery. So in
effluent heat recovery, you have to go
directly to the the sewage facility
itself to recover the heat that they
need to reject. So all of those affluent
facilities are now exposed to
regulations that say they can't
discharge to surface water as they have
uh without meeting a a minimum or rather
a maximum temperature differential over
the year. So we're seeing time and time
again they have megawws like hundreds of
megawatts of thermal just from single
sewage facilities that they need to
discharge
uh and they don't have a place to go
with it. So imagine the possibility of
reducing your capital costs on drilling
and making these geothermal energy
networks more viable.
You can hybridize it directly with the
surface water that you want to um
perhaps harvest heat from or reject heat
to. But again, if you're going to reject
heat to that surface water system, you
have to operate within these future
confines of the projected regulations
that say you have a maximum temperature
differential. It's actually quite simple
uh for new construction
uh to meet that minimum of standard
because you can imagine that we built a
city on top of the earth. We're actually
influencing the ground temperatures more
than anything and so our our influence
on surface water nearby surface water uh
resources is quite high already. So you
have to just prove or disprove that your
system discharge is operating within
those environmental regulations. And if
you reduce the operating temperatures by
implementing geothermal energy networks
for your HVAC systems, it becomes much
easier to meet that norm.
and geothermal energy networks. If we
get into a lower temperature regime like
Connor had mentioned, somewhere between
40 and 90 degrees of operating
uh across a season between your highs
and lows, you can also introduce load
sharing. So as that heat pump is
rejecting to a hydronic network then
another u building along the the route
may be extracting heat from that network
and that in fact does reduce primary
energy consumption across our cities.
So that's a a resource that you can tap
into uh to decrease again capital costs
but also mitigate your emissions from
the system even in scope 2.
And uh then we can consider all these
sources and syncs in aggregate. I'm not
sure if you saw this slide from
yesterday but very simply put we know
that we're electrifying building heating
and cooling already. It's just a matter
of doing it right responsibly or we're
doing it irresponsibly. And this is
based on a a you know system by system
basis. Connor mentioned that Seattle
might be a good place for some cold
climate air source heat pumps to operate
efficiently, but you also have district
energy operators that have to switch
over to electrification strategies of
their own. oftentimes you'll see them
putting in electric boilers with a
coefficient of performance of one or
less. Right? So that has impacts on our
uh electrical infrastructure. The grids
scale impacts are a consequence that we
all have to deal with. If we can
implement geothermal energy networks and
uh achieve more passive heating and
cooling opportunities, load sharing
across our cities, then our coefficient
of performance can increase from the co
cop of one for the electric boiler uh uh
up to about 6 to 14 for most systems
that have been measured so far. And of
course, passive cooling opportunities
exist where you have surface water
bodies because the uh the temperatures
that they require
uh are sufficient
uh to leverage the the the water source
itself. So you might think of between 42
degrees Fahrenheit and 50° Fahrenheit,
you can use the surface water directly
as a cooling source and your coefficient
of performance can then exceed 20
perhaps reaching as high as 60. So
that's energy in versus the thermal
energy that you get out.
And really quickly these are network
topologies that you have to consider.
uh ringed network is the ones that we've
been talking about more more commonly
for this workshop but there are other
variants that you see as you get to
larger and larger scale systems.
Uh meshed networks can be uh an an
evolution of that but they have more
hydraulic disadvantages in some cases.
You can have stagnant loops and radial
grid systems are the most commonly seen
in conventional district heating and
cooling.
So in this case, you can also have what
is an a near ambient distribution system
in a radial configuration with
distributed heat pumps, but you're going
to also have to have a central plant. So
you can either have distributed
equipment, you can have central
equipment or you can have a
hybridization of these.
And you can also in this example connect
uh existing high temperature district
heating and cooling systems with their
own near ambient energy exchange loop.
So there are ways to decarbonize and
leverage ground source systems without
always having to go to ambient
temperatures.
All right. And these are uh again the
many process uh heat recovery sources
that you can encounter such as data
centers, the wastewater energy transfer
uh and existing CHP systems that you
already have existing uh across the
cities.
So, uh, the the heat sources and sinks
themselves are numerous and these have,
uh, design consequences,
uh, that Brian is going to get into next
and describe with a case study and then
give you some decisionmaking points to
think about next.
Uh, final thought here, if we skimp on
design, we we sacrifice everything else.
are operating and and maintenance is
going to be abysmal and we're going to
be stuck with these systems for the next
50 years. So that's why having this
conversation now as we're transitioning
to electrification and building heating
and cooling is important. We're going to
live with this.
All right. Thank you.
[Applause]