my name is
Francesca and we all work with this
dyamic data promic data transcriptomic
data and we know it's super complex to
work with high dimensional much so much
noise um so our job is to try to find
the important relationships in that data
and we find that with more data and more
computational power we can make more use
of deep learning models that really um
work with our data to find a more like
concise
representation so for example um we've
been interested in protein language
models so a type of foundation model and
well so for example the es esm2 model is
this protein language model and it is
really only trained on the data to
represent that so in our case that would
be protein
sequences
and what we get with this model
is um
a representation of each data point in a
vector
space and that can be of a model defined
Dimension and that's what we call the
embedding and we would want to hope that
points that are closely related in the
initial data would be closely together
in the Spector space but we still want
to retain that information about the
differences as
well okay so this is very helpful
because now we can use this Vector space
to train models that are more task
specific so like smaller machine
learning models on top that will be task
specific we've been interested in um
looking into understanding where within
a cell a protein will be located so
would it be like in the nucleus or would
it be in the cell membrane so that would
be like a task that will be
train down um on top of these
embeddings the problem is that what is
what is learned by the foundation model
or what is captured is often not very
clear and that's kind of the information
we want to know um it's nice to know
that they work but it be even nicer to
know why um so one thing that we can
compare the growing amount of foundation
models with different architectures
different training data at the moment is
what we do is we take the foundation
models like the first one and then we
take the next one and we train them on
all these Downstream
tasks we get an embedding again we train
machine learning models on each of the
tasks and then we start to compare how
well they are performing on specific
tasks and that's how we say okay well it
captures the subcellular localization or
it doesn't capture that as well so this
is kind of the State ofth art but the
more models we get and the more
benchmarking TS we get we're going to
run into more problems of of doing all
these Tas specific models so we were
interested in how much can we already
already see in this point when we just
compare the embedding spaces of the
models so we we want to share some
thoughts and strategies that we could
have a look into the embedding spaces
and we summarize that in our framework
is called
M okay so what we do
here is really
compare embedding spaces from different
foundational models and I'm going to
draw it in 2D so we can all kind of
perceive all the dimensions but please
imagine that to be a very high
dimensional Vector the problem is that
if we have our sample being projected
into two spaces we cannot compare the
vectors itself because the spaces will
be different have different dimensions
and so forth so what we try to uh so
what we are coming up with how we want
to do is that we project a set of
proteins in our case into the space
and then we look where they end
up and what we now see is that if we
compare like the distance between the
different um data points in the
embedding space is that for example the
circle and the triangle will be very
close to each other in both spaces but
suddenly this this like Circle and the
square get very far away compared to the
other ining space so this is what we're
basing most of our um analysis on these
pair wise distance
is
um
and also we really want to work with um
developing quantitative measures in
metrics and how to quantify those rather
than just
visually and on top we found that we
looked into natural language processing
there are some interesting approaches to
compare embedding spaces but they often
work with just looking at the individual
data points with just their name and we
realize for proteins or damic data it's
often not very helpful if I just tell
you to UNI prod names and ask you to say
if that's relevant that they're close
together it might be more difficult
rather than if I tell you that they're
both from like a common protein family
so we really want to
include um what we call feature data or
metadata so any kind of information you
have on those on those samples you look
at so if we have our data
points um any sort of classification
that we already know from our data point
um databases so for example on these
subcellular
localizations then we know okay there's
like sample one is in the membrane
sample two as well sample three is in
the nucleus it could also be something
like we were looking at here like
information about the function of the
proteins or the family
okay so what we're analyzing now in this
framework is that we have a set of
samples that we choose that we're
interested in in our case that will be
protein sequences we put them through a
range of foundation models and we get a
range of embedding spaces so these could
be these could be just um models that
are trained on like slightly different
data or um models pre and post
fine-tuning or even models uh trained on
different data modalities so protein
language models they're also structure
aware versus not structure
aware okay so we end up with different
inverting spaces I'm just going to call
them V1 V2 V3 and we also have a our
feature
data so there are many things we can do
with this we want to draw your attention
to two things we've been working on
which is the first one is if you have
any of those two embedding spaces
similar to what we did here you just
want to know like do they capture the
same information or did they think that
our samples are somehow differently
related so we call this a
pairwise space
comparison
um and the second thing we're looking
into is more if you're specifically
interested in specific feature like we
were in subcellular
localization how is that distributed in
the different spaces
um so really going starting with the
with the feature and looking at its
distribution
okay so looking back at this first
approach again this is really what we
did here we look at the pairwise
distances in one space that V1 and then
the pair distances in V2 and maybe two
points are very closely
together in V1 and V2 so we see them
somehow here but maybe another point is
very far away from from the point one in
one space but very close in the second
space so far away in V1 but like close
on V2 it would end up somewhere here so
all the points that have like similar
relationships or pair of points that
have similar relationships will be on
this diagonal and points that are
somehow differently will be
off okay now we can identify those kind
of outliers and use our feature data to
understand is there any correlation of
these data points with a specific Gene
family a specific location is one model
learning something that the other one
didn't capture or is this more like an
artifact that we did not expect so we
can start asking these questions about
the
models this is the first approach the
second approach again talking about like
a specific feature
here for example the subcell
localization what we can go do is look
into each of the
spaces
and now we're interested in how is this
um feature captured in the distances of
the space so say we look into V1 and
then we pick a data point and say it's
in the
plasma then we choose a k and we do a k
nearest neighbors approach and we find
all the three neighbors of the data
point we then look at the um classes for
the feature that we're looking into for
these data points and we see oh okay two
out of the three neighbors are also
triangles and one is not so we assign
this um this data point a score of two
2/3 two of them have the same feature
and that's what we call the cane and
Alignment score
um and if the score is higher that means
more more similarity is in the
neighborhood of each point now what we
can do is that we can look at these
scores and the distribution of the
scores across different um embedding
spaces from different
models and see if they are like
generally higher so more of this featur
is captured in the in the local
neighborhoods in one space compared to
another so maybe maybe that information
is already more Rel relatively easy
available in the distance metrix of the
space further what we can do is we can
stratify that information the scores for
each space again but this time for each
class so say we look for all points with
a triangle like what is the mean score
and maybe it's very high for the
triangles meaning the triangles are
generally close to other
triangles um maybe in all spaces but but
the the another class might be very
poorly represented in its
neighborhood so a last approach that
we've been working on is looking then
back into the embedding
space um and saying okay if we have this
data point if we look at each data point
again and we look at the nearest
neighbors of each data point now for
each data point we don't want to count
how many have like same feature but in
generally like how many have like any of
the feature
classes for this data point it would be
like two would have also a triangle and
then there's zero squares and one one
Circle and again we can aggregate that
and and we get a metric and a matrix
that will tell you how close different
classes are in an embedding
space okay so these are some thoughts we
gathered
on already looking at into the embedding
spaces before you do more resource
intensive um training and we found that
for person language models we could
really for some task look into Which
models might be more worth taking into
more uh into F tuning which one models
have already like a very good
representation in the distances of the
features we're interested in um and we
have a python implementation of that if
you're interested
um and if you have any embedding spaces
that you are very excited about I would
love to hear about them it's very task
and data agnostic so you can just use
whatever embedding space you have if you
have some feature data um we'd be very
interested to hear how that looks like
for
you I used to work on latent variable
models for gene expression and um
multiomic data uh so we I guess all know
there you get a latent representation
set which is usually highly compressed
with maybe 20 to 200 Dimensions um and
typically this will be visualized in a
PCA or map um and the extent to which
this is interpretable is usually
clustering maybe bat effect removal to
see if integration is good um and we had
been working on things like making
models more flexible to be able to do
things like in cical perturbations where
you'll be able to see how uh a cell
changes I don't know if you can see this
tiny Arrow but how the Laten space and
expression profile changes uh of a cell
if you say they change a gene or a set
of genes um but I found that well or
many people find that this is still not
really enough to understand what these
models actually learn um so fairly
recently there was this really cool work
um that hypothesized that there are no
super
positions and superpositions basically
describe that especially in sparse data
which we often deal with in multiomics
that you have let's say two Dimensions
D1 D2 um that could be two neurons and
these will actually encode many more
features than just um two so let's say
in this example we
have four feature vectors uh that are
squished into these two Dimensions so
these are superp position vectors in two
dimensions and what do I mean with
features this can be pretty vague uh so
you can think of many things whether it
be some sources of variation in the data
or um specific patterns so we can think
of let's say we have face images uh we
again have two dimensions and we could
represent for example one feature is a
circle then there's some features with
dots and a curve and now we have a
smiley represented by four features in
biology this could also mean uh a
transcription factor or a pathway maybe
a protein function or domain um or this
has first been applied to text where we
see that some features are just like
single characters like an at or um a
whole citation uh as a
concept uh so the question now is how
can we extract these features in superp
position and this has been presented by
taking an old trick out of the box uh
that's called a sparse Auto
encoder and what this does is basically
we take our two dimensions in Laten
space now very simplified um and then we
basically
build an
overcomplete auto encoder so we just
blow up this Dimension into multiple
fold um we'll call this activations
these latent vectors because it's really
hard to tell about multiple embeddings
um and then we enforce sparsity uh so
that we make sure a lot of these neurons
are dead and we'll have only a few
neurons that represent these different
vectors in superp position and this is
actually really really simple to train
in the most basic form uh it's simply
trained with the loss as the mean squ
error or anything for reconstruction
plus an L1 Norm on these activations and
this enforces the L1 Norm enforces
sparsities and this is applied to these
activations and then ideally we should
get activations that in this case have
four so-called active or live
neurons and they can then disentangle
separate uh these
features now that we've separated them
we still have to actually be able to
interpret them and um you can do this
manually if you have a given concept
that you think you should find in your
model but this can be quite tedious um
so a good solution is uh so-called
reverse
engineering um where we will basically
build a concept
Library so let's say we are in the
protein space which uh this has already
been uh done for um there they took all
functional and structural annotations
from swissprot and built a concept
library of a certain set of these
Concepts so it could be a specific
catalytic activity um even just s single
amino acids or charges uh are included
we have all our samples and then we take
all our
activations um for each
sample and in order to like
automatically assign some information of
what each feature might represent we can
simply uh compute either correlation or
similarity Matrix M metric between uh
the concepts and our
activations and this as I already
mentioned has been applied already in
biology uh to protein language
models uh where we have Concepts
represented by at the moment Swiss prod
annotations um but this can already be
very useful you can think of as if you
have these disentangled feature vectors
then you can do some function steering
so uh they tested it for example on
these repeat glycine um uh patterns and
you can basically uh change in a given
model that hasn't been even trained on
function you can change a certain
pattern or functionality uh with
steering these vectors or uh what I have
been working on were um omix latent
variable models because I had that lying
around um and basically what I did there
is and I am very inspired by Isabella to
try this out next is I took for each
activation the highly active and the
lowest activity feature uh sampled sorry
and then performed a differential gene
expression analysis and Gene enrichment
with this case as an example just Gene
onology but basically um with having
these Gene sets from Gene from
differential gene expression analysis
and then the enrichment I was able to
annotate over 80% of a model that I
think is not even that good yet so I
think with better omx models we'll be
better uh we'll be able to get much
better functionality um and yeah if
you're interested in some of the uh
specific cases of some features uh you
can read the paper or if you have ideas
of more interesting biological um
problems that this could be applied to
uh feel free to reach out to me I'm
happy to
explore today I'm going to be talking
about a project that started with a
collaboration that we have with Jeff
moffit's group at uh Boston Children's
Hospital um and it start started just as
a collaboration on one data set and then
it's really sort of grown into a more a
more General method um so first I'll
explain the problem that they they came
to us with so they have this very large
Mish so spatial transcriptomics data set
um consisting of measurements from from
the mouse colon and so they have
hundreds of of slides and thousands of
genes profiled and here I'm just showing
you example of one of these slices so
each dot is a cell and then colored by
the expression of of two different genes
and what they noticed is that the the
genes that are spatially variable they
tended to fall into one of two
categories the first is like this gene
on the left um they call patchy so you
can see that there's a burst in just one
region of the colon there's a burst and
expression and it's it's it's low in the
other locations of the
colon um on the the other hand this this
these other genes have a gradient
pattern where the expression is high on
the outside and then as you move towards
the inside it goes from high to low um
or alternatively there are genes that
are that go from low to high and the
question that they they wanted us to
answer is they wanted us to just go
through
the all 200 slices and just find genes
that have either the patch or the
gradient pattern of expression and so
what we found is that so what I would
say the standard approach to find
spatially variable genes is is to use
right a hypothesis test for for spatial
variability and what we found here is
that's not really that useful because
right the P value for both of these
genes will be like 10 the minus 100 or
something incredibly small they're both
spatially variable but the hypothesis
test doesn't tell
you uh how they're spatially variable
and so that's sort of where we started
Des uh a method um and so the idea is to
use what we call
morphologically relevant
coordinates
so what is that it's a transformation of
the original coordinates for each cell
so
right this might be the original XY
coordinates and we transform
it into these two new coordinates out
called T and R and in this case
T would
summarize right I'll say
longitudinal position
so where along the colon are
you and
RJ would give the the radial
position
right so how close you are from the
inside or versus the
outside and if you are able to make this
transformation then now the problem of
identifying patchy versus gradient genes
um is uh very simple so right so if you
just plotted now as a 1D if you plotted
the expression of the patchy genes as a
function of T right as a function of T
the expression right it'll be low and
then there'll be like a burst and then
it'll be low
again so this would be like
patchy whereas for uh
for
gradient right the variation is in the r
direction if you ploted expression as a
function of r right it might start high
and then and then go low that sort of
the general idea behind these
morphologically relevant coordinates so
now I'll tell you how we can estimate
these so
[Music]
estimation so
we start by assuming
that right the mean of the
coordinates right is given by some
unobserved parametric curve F of T subj
So Right
f is some smooth parametric
curve so it takes as input the the first
coordinate and then
gives me an output in two Dimensions um
so there are many identifiability
constraints in this model um one very
important one um that we need for our
estimation algorithm is the
so-called uh unit speed
constraint
so right in a parametric curve fime of T
is like velocity this is just saying the
magnitude of the Velocity is one at
every Point otherwise we could just
reparameterize T and get the get the
same
curve um and so the way that we can
leverage this constraint for estimation
is that we can note
that
um so I'll do the simpler case where
it's not a loop so where
the curve is not joined at the end um
the idea for extending it to Loops is is
very similar but in this case where the
end points are not joined you can see
that TJ minus TI right we can write this
as the integral of
one right this is just one by the unit
speed
constraint but you might also recognize
this as the formula for arc length along
the parametric
curve between cell I and cell
J along F and this arc length is
something that we
can get a high quality estimate of for
instance using the shortest
path in a k nearest neighbor graph of
the cell
coordinates with K
small so by using this shortest path we
get a a good estimate of TJ minus TI the
distance between TJ and TI then what's
the final step so we have the distances
between every Point how do we get the
original points back well that's exactly
the problem that multi-dimensional
scaling aims to solve so the final step
then
is multi-dimensional scaling and so I
won't go too much into the details but
basically you take this shortest path
distance Matrix
D
so you transform it in some some simple
way and then the top igen vector
of that distance Matrix D that's your
estimate of T your estimate of the first
morphologically relevant
coordinate um and so I said this is for
the case where the parametric curve is
not joined at the end but
right of course in the example that I
showed it it was a loop um and so for
Loops um the only
differences right um so I won't go too
much in the math but you take the top
two vectors of
D the top two igen
vectors and then you take the arc
tangent of the ratio of the second over
the first so the same way like you do
the conversion from cartisian to
Polar it's
like the AR tangent of the the second
one divided by the the first gives you
back your your estimate of the first
coordinate so that that's how how we get
the the first coordinate
then so how do we get this this second
morphologically relevant coordinate RJ
um
well the basic idea is that it should be
the sign residual
from
uh the the cell's coordinate to its
position on the curve so the magnitude
of RJ that should just be the
distance I'll just write the distance
between the
uh the cell's coordinates and its
position on the
curve and then in order to get the sign
of R subj um so
basically if this is the curve
F you have right some velocity frime of
T then you can just look at a vector
orthogonal to this velocity vector and
then you can look at right
cells on this side could get a positive
sign and cells on that side could get a
negative sign so you just need to to
choose the orientation in order to
assign the sign of this this second
coordinate R
subj
um
okay um and so the final step then is
once you have these two morphologically
relevant coordinates how do you actually
do the what regression model do we
recommend to the spatially variable
genes
well right we call that in gene
expression right we're typically dealing
with count data right so y subg could be
the counts for for G G so we recommend
using a generalized additive
model um so right using a count
distribution to to model the expression
data we choose negative binomial
with Su so the J cell with some
mean some
dispersion and the log of the
mean right is equal to some baseline
expression
plus some two unobserved smooth
functions one of the first
morphologically relevant coordinate and
one of the second morphologically
relevant coordinate and then right so
this model can be fit by standard
methods and now like really all you have
to do is then just extract the estimates
of this function H subg and S subg and
that's like
um that's like what we we drew over here
would be like this would be like h of
G and that would
be would be S of of G Prime for the for
the different
Gene um and
uh yeah and so basically in in our paper
we show that like depending on the
scientific question right you can really
do whatever you want with this model you
can look at summary statistics of the
function to see oh like maybe
Expressions we want to look at genes
that have a very specific shape um or or
whatnot um so it's a very
flexible model that allows you to to
answer partic particular scientific
questions about spatially variable
genes hi so my name is OA and today I
want to talk about uh kind of similar to
Philip also some methods for looking at
spatial gene expression
dat so the way that we can study the
spatial gene expression as Philip had
shown some pictures of before is through
a technology called spatial
transcriptomic and so what this looks
like um kind of laying it out in a
picture is that you have like a tissue
slice maybe it has like a weird shape uh
I'll just draw in this box um and you
should imagine this as like the X and
the Y directions and you have you can
measure different quantities at like
different points in this uh
tissue and so you should you can think
of these for example as like different
uh cells sometimes they might contain
more than one cell but that's not too
important you have a bunch of these
points and what you can measure are two
things one is that you can measure the
coordinates uh kind of these
XY and then the other is that you
measure this uh what's called a gene
ression
Vector which is this High dimensional um
Vector it's not too important what the
kind of quantity is but there's about
let's say like 20,000 different
components so it's very high
dimensional um and
so if you have kind of this data in
space typically in single cell omix as
some of the previous talks looked at you
just have these gene expression vectors
but while now we have these measurements
in space and so one of the very natural
questions that you can ask is if you
have this data how does it vary
spatially um how do these different
genes vary um throughout my tissue and
space and so this is a very kind of
General problem and kind of what I would
say a good way to think about it is you
should think about this in terms of a
function so let's say you have a
function in space this uh F and this
function's Vector value so each uh Point
XY each of these coordinates you measure
um let's say d g different genes each of
these is like a kind of scalar
function and each of these functions
should tell you in practice how your
different genes vary in space and so for
example maybe this is one gene here you
could imagine if I just looked at how
this Gene looks like in space as a
function of X and Y
um maybe this Gene kind of increases in
space and so maybe um
sorry I should have prepared slides I
guess but I'm going to try and draw this
like you have a bunch of these points in
space these are your different cells and
maybe this Gene it's
like it's increasing this direction so
maybe it starts out let's say like it's
10 here it increases to 11 maybe it
increases to sorry these are kind of
hard to see it's like 12's here maybe
there's like a
13 it's like 14 so it's sort of
increasing I'm plotting here F1 of XY
and you can see it's sort of like
increasing sort of in that
direction you can have other spatial
patterns too so maybe I didn't quite
write this out but maybe let's look at
like a separate Gene x uh
F2 maybe this gen has a different
pattern maybe it's kind of decreasing in
this
direction so let's say instead maybe uh
it kind of starts out really high it's
it could be like 99 and it's like maybe
70 I don't know I'm just kind of writing
numbers maybe it's like 50 here and it's
sort of getting small smaller as you go
in this direction it's like 20
here so kind of intuitively at least you
can see that you might have these
different patterns in Space the way that
you can quantify all these different
patterns though is through this uh
through the language of calculus and
namely you model spatial variation in
terms of a something called a spatial
gradient so this spatial gradient is
really just
uh the gradient if you recall from like
multivariable calculus at every point
and so this gradient gives you the
direction of uh maximum
change in your measurements at every
point in space and so for example maybe
for this Gene at this point from 99 to
70 the gradient kind of points in like
this direction because
uh I guess it should be the direction of
Maximum
increase so maybe here uh if you go from
10 it's kind of increasing in this
direction so at kind of this point XY
this gradient Vector this gradient of FG
of I guess this is
F1 points in this direction and if you
plot all of these gradients um at
different points in space you get this
Vector
field and so maybe in this Gene Gene one
this Vector field kind of points in this
direction and this is telling you uh
this Gene is increasing in this
direction maybe for this Gene the
radians kind of point in this opposite
direction because from 70 to 90 is the
direction of increase and so you get a
vector fi that kind of looks like this
instead and you could imagine General
you could have many different types of
vector Fields depending on these
different genes and how they look like
in
space one of the major Challen and so
what you would want to learn are these
different spatial gradients at different
points and space but one of the major
challenges in learning this uh these
gradients is that in most tissues your
data is really
you have like 70% or more zeros at many
points in space and so in practice you
don't get these very nice neat pictures
but um instead your data Maybe looks
like this
where there's just going to be a bunch
of different
zeros maybe I did see a 10 here but
there's like a zero here instead and a
zero here maybe there's a zero here and
it's like a 12 a zero it's like most
most Zer and like maybe for this gen um
I also don't see all of these like kind
of nice large
measurements instead maybe for this Gene
it's like I saw this 90 down here but
there's another zero maybe this was like
I forget the numbers I put 70 I
think 30 I I don't remember but now when
you have all this data with many
different zeros it's very hard to tell
what direction should these gradients be
pointing in because here looks like it's
increasing from 0 to 20 so it's the
gradient pointing this way um maybe it
should be pointing that way in general
learning these gradients kind of hard or
very impossible if you have very sparse
or general like low um dynamic range
data and so over the last several years
we've kind of found that even though
learning each of these gradients these
like this measure spatial variation can
be very hard for individual genes if you
actually place a few geometric
assumptions on these function these
gradients then you can learn them um
even from highly sparse spatial
data and so I'll briefly describe some
of these
assumptions and so the first assumption
that uh we make is that for each
gene uh all genes share the same uh
directions of these
gradients and so if you imagine what
this looks like in your tissue you have
a point XY
maybe Gene one kind of
points in this direction maybe Gene 2
kind of like looking at this that tissue
for example you have a gradient that
points in the opposite direction but
like kind of in the same plane maybe a
third Gene Gene 3
uh maybe Gene three points like also in
the same direction but we assume that
they all point in like the same 1D plane
and that in fact there's a single vector
field uh capital V that's shared by all
genes and so you can write this out um
as the gradients for each gene are
proportional to a single Vector field
this like shared Vector
fi and then the second assumption is you
also have to place some assumptions on
what this specific Vector field looks
like and so kind of motivated by
physical applications we assume this
that this Vector field is something
called a conservative Vector field which
again these are kind of maybe Notions
that at least I forgot from
multivariable calculus and what this
means is that this Vector field doesn't
really curl around its space and so you
can't really have a case where your
vector field sort of looks like this
like you can't have it like loop around
in space intuitively maybe that makes
sense because if your gene expression is
kind of increasing in a loop it should
like increase forever that's kind of a
case that we don't really
want it turns out um this is equivalent
to actually a different assumption that
this Vector field is the uh sorry this
is again a bunch of calculus but this
Vector field is the gradient of a scalar
function and in physics this kind of
function is sometimes called a potential
function so for example you have like uh
gravitational potential which is like
your height um there's electric
potential and here you can think of this
as maybe like a gene expression
potential and the nice thing here
actually is that under these two
assumptions you can actually show that
your gene expression
which um is a function of these two
spatial coordinates X and Y it'll really
be a function of a single spatial
coordinate this potential function D of
XY so here you have this kind of
dimensionality reduction where you start
with two coordinates XY and then you
place some mild assumptions and you get
this single
uh uh coordinate that describes your
gene expression sorry this is kind of
the extent at which I can write but um
and so what's nice then is that I guess
once you have everything in terms of a
single spatial function it allows you to
aggregate measurements across space and
so for example maybe this potential
function Let's uh of use this like Gene
maybe this potential function looks like
this it's like zero here maybe it's like
one here it's two it's like increasing
in this
direction then what you have are you
have these like different Contours so
this might be the line D equals Zer this
is the the line D equal 1 this the line
D equals 2 and by writing expression in
kind of your function as a function of
the single spatial coordinate you can
aggregate gene expression your
measurements across these different
contour lines and so for example here we
have a bunch of zeros but if you like
aggregate gene expression along these
different contour lines and you sort of
visualize how gene expression varies as
a function of this potential it's very
sparse in 2D but if you look in 1D you
might see that gene expression if this
is like 0 one two maybe it kind of looks
like uh it's like decreasing in space
and so you can visualize this kind of
like pattern this would be like a
negative gradient and maybe for this
Gene instead it looks like this
instead and it lets you visualize these
different gradient
directions um and so finally you might
ask how can you actually learn this kind
of potential function from data and over
the past several years we've worked on a
couple different approaches to learn
this uh this potential function run out
of space but
uh kind of
here and so kind of in a paper from
2022 a couple years ago we first
developed a supervised approach to learn
this function D where we modeled it uh
using the heat equation so you can think
of this as potential function as sort of
measuring a heat potential in your
tissue and then more recently um this
was an algorithm for a layered tissue so
we called it the layer because it's
supposed to be a plan words on rock
climbing um and then more recently we
developed an unsupervised approach uh
using deep learning where the idea is
that if you parameterize these two
functions with neural networks it turns
out to be equivalent to training a
neural network on your data that has a
very specific form where the input is
spatial
coordinates the output is your gene
expression
and then there's a hidden layer in the
middle and maybe a bunch of like other
hidden layers but there's like one
hidden layer in the middle that has a
single node and this single node is your
potential
function and so yeah this is this kind
of General framework we set up and we
looking at many different uh extensions
for example relaxing these two
assumptions so you can find multiple
coordinates multiple gradient directions
uh you can also relax the assumption
that maybe this Vector field doesn't
have to be conservative maybe it doesn't
have to vary continuously in space um
but yeah this is kind of General
framework and we called this uh gene
expression
topography because one example of this
potential function is height and in
topographic maps you often see like
height in space and so if you look at
these kind of maps with these different
Contours they kind of if you like squint
your eyes maybe they kind of look like
topographic maps for example when you're
going hike it