Hello. Hi. Hi there. Uh today I'm
introducing our uh startup Dexmate. So
we are a AI robotics company who solves
the physical AI problem. We have three
co-founders. Uh the CEO Chao is I'm MIT
SISO aluminina. The COO Chongyang is I'm
MIT
and Yuzi I'm the Dexmate CTO.
So physical AI solve a very important
problems. So in all over the world there
are 3.2 2 billion people working to
perform physical labor worldwide and we
know that in US there are very
significant labor shortage over the past
few years. Digital AI like coding agent,
AI tutor and a lot of other digital
agent provide 10 times productivity in
the digital world and the next 10 years
must belong to the physical AI which can
perform the human labor and change the
world with 10 times transformations.
The transformation from automation to
physical AI is very low compared with
traditional automation solutions like
industrial robotics arms. For example,
if you have a sampling line, you you
want to change it change it with a with
a conveyor belt
arm in the traditional fashion, you need
to change all your all your assembly
like structure and deploy sensors,
computations and all at once with six
months. However, with our physical AI
solutions, you do not need to change
your warehouse or factories, you all the
sensors, all the computations powers,
all the batteries is owned by the robot
agent and they has the AI capabilities
to adapt to your environment which makes
very little environment modification or
even zero modification to your
factories.
In order to make this physical air
possible, we need to have a very strong
body. In Daxmate, we design and
manufacture Vea, a humanoid robot
without lag. Compared with traditional
robotic system like Aloha, we have 10 a
seven times stronger payload and we also
have dextrous manipulating capabilities.
Compared with the lagged human robot, we
can get three times faster locom motion
and five times longer operation time
than the lag robot.
We also cares about our user experience.
We make our robot easy to transportation
with affordable design. With all of
that, we we are in a painting
application of 10 and also ready for
mass production. Now,
here is our robot vea as you can see
here. So this is like a uh humanoid on
the view robot. It can perform a lot of
uh different operations like the view
motion and upper body manipulation.
Here we showcase some of our
collaboration with our partners in US.
So this is some typical task in
warehouse and industry. We have
partnered with one of the biggest uh uh
warehouse company in US
to perform some box flipping tasks and
box moving tasks
in the in the bottom. So there's like a
box flipping task where you need to make
sure that uh the top of the box is can
be scanned by Q scanner on the assembly
line.
On the upper right, we are also
collaborating with one of the biggest uh
car parts manufacturing company in
Europe to uh to perform the car part
placement task.
So now we are also asking for more
pilots in manufacturing and logistic
industries. So we want to working on the
task like material handling, box moving,
part soldering, object uh object
picking. all this task with our
partners. So we target at manufacturing
and warehouse applications. So primarily
we focus on United State industry but we
can also do partnership with Europe and
Japan company. So if you are interested
maybe you can join our uh threeour room
or contact for our email.
Okay. Thank thank you.