So, I'm Tom Lowry, CEO here at Satellite
Bio. Uh, we're founded out of the
laboratory of Singita Bacha at MIT and
I'll share with you briefly how we're
developing off-the-shelf cell therapies
that boost liver function and protect
the brain of patients in their time of
need. So, severe liver disease, whether
it's genetic disease or metabolic
diseases, alcohol use disorder,
infections, all affect the primary cell
in the liver called the hpatocy. cause
it to go from a healthy state shown here
in purple to an unhealthy state shown
here in yellow. And that leads to a
buildup of toxins in the blood. The the
most uh typical toxin that builds up is
ammonia. And uh the unfortunate thing
that occurs for folks that are suffering
from insufficient liver function or
hpatic insufficiency is that the the
toxins build up and they affect the
brain. In fact, people that have uh
severe liver disease can have
manifestations of it that look like
dementia uh where their brain function
has been compromised due to the blood
toxins that haven't been processed by
their liver. Patients that suffer from
cerosis uh over a third of them will
develop a phenomenon called
hpaticanphylopathy.
And once you have this
hpaticanphylopathy, you have a 50%
one-year mortality rate. And the only
cure today is transplant. Our therapies
deliver a therapeutically active
hpatocy, therapeutically active liver
cell to patients that need a boost in
their liver function without requiring
the need for a transplant. Uh we can
infuse the cells directly in the liver.
That's SB 101 on the on the left hand
side where the cells engraft and then
support and boost liver function. Or we
can infuse what we call a tissue seed.
100 micron diameter heteroscellular
aggregate that allows us to create
satellite liver tissue in an organ
outside of the liver because the livers
are serotic and won't accept a cell
infusion. One of the key breakthroughs
at satellite is that we have a
sustainable and scalable cell source for
decades. People have been trying to get
to apatocite either from IPS-C's or
other cell sources to be able to provide
a boost in liver function to these types
of patients. We actually source cataric
cells but then we expand them in the lab
using the regenerative cues that
hpatocytes are responsive to. We can
maintain adult and and mature function.
The other innovation is that we can
stabilize that hpatocy and get it to
engraft outside of the liver. That's one
of the key innovations because
apatocytes obviously they're they're um
have been evolved to develop and grow in
a liver but with this tissue seed uh
that we can actually get the cells to
engraft outside the liver and provide a
boost in liver function to these
patients that are serotic and have very
scarred and and hard livers. We have a
very large pre-clinical data set that
supports our ability to get these
apatocytes to engraft and function in
terms of our pipeline. So our first drug
that we'll take into the clinic uh we'll
be dosing our patients next year. That's
in pediatric ura cycle disorders. These
are patients that are born without a
functioning liver and they need a boost
in their function to protect their brain
until they're old enough to receive a
gene therapy or receive a transplant.
And that hypermia that's the blood
toxins that build up. That's the
unifying theme for our pipeline. Our
next drug is for adult patients
suffering from apatic sephylopathy where
we begin grafting the cells outside of
the liver. We have a very robust CMC
package. Cryopreserve drugs. They're
centrally manufactured, shipped around
the world for our clinical trials and to
customers. We have very low cost of
goods uh due to the engine cost
engineering that we've implemented along
with our innovation uh when we've
developed the biology and the drugs. The
kind of partnership opportunities we're
looking for. So co-development
partnerships, we as we approach our
first multinational clinical trial, we
have clinical sites around the world and
some that are coming to us through
partner interest. We also have
outlicicensing interests and in
discussions that we're um interested in
having with folks around our rare
disease uh indication and then uh and
then our adult indications of
pre-clinical partnership opportunity.
And we just always take a moment to
acknowledge the donors because we are
using cells derived from from organ
donors and we're committed to delivering
these therapies to patients in need.
Thank you, Tom.
So, um, let me start with, um, if you
could expand a little more. You're
touching on partnerships, but for
bioarma companies, what what are you
looking for? What would work best?
>> Yeah. So, so yeah, biotech or pharma
companies that have a focus in um liver
disease or metabolic diseases, genetic
diseases, uh rare diseases or cell
therapy, particularly if they already
have a um a commercial footprint with a
sales force that's calling on hospitals
and those those indications, those could
be very interesting. Our drugs very much
unlike a typical cell therapy, it's off
the shelf and availably shipped and
treated like a traditional drug.
>> And I was just going to touch on that.
What's your your competitive advantage?
Can you expand a little more on that
what you're saying?
>> Yeah, competitive advantage. So, there's
there's no other uh cell source for
liver cells. So, we're really the only
one that has a full GMP cell source
that's scalable and ready to be able to
be used. And then it's offtheshelf carb
reserve and extremely low cost of goods.
So, we're talking single-digit thousands
of dollars. Typically, cell therapies
are in the hundreds of thousands of
dollars or higher.
>> Thank you for that. And one final
question, how long does the administered
cells live in the body?
>> Yep. So the our first clinical trial
will have a six-month endpoint. Uh we
expect that we'll be able to go out
multiple years, but in order to have a a
streamlined clinical development pathway
and bring value to these patients, the
the first trials will be six months.