Let's uh let's start a so first the
homework assignment is out as I
said uh it's due right before
Thanksgiving if anybody needs an
extension just let me
know a and
uh the instructions are on the on the
site essentially uh each one should
write like their own solution to make
sure you understand it's okay if you
talk among one among one another as long
as it's fruitful and please type it up
in latch and submit it through great
scope questions
[Music]
yeah
oh you what why can't you do don't you
use grade scope for other classes yeah
but I have not seen this class oh no it
is it is now when did you check
oh yeah it's recently uh yeah if there's
issues let me know yeah this class is
assigned to there is a great scope site
for
this uh any any other questions before
we
start okay so uh just a quick a quick
recap uh so last time we talked Al about
the kilan mikali protocol it's an
interactive argument it's a succinct
interactive argument that which you can
use to prove uh membership in any NP
language okay if you recall the idea was
we started before that was kind of our
entrance to to cryptography so we said
the idea of the K mic protocol is that
you take any PCP which is very very
large but very efficiently if you just
have Ram access to it you can verify it
very efficiently
and the idea is you take this very very
large PCP and you kind of shrink it to
kind of a you uh you know uh digest it
down uh using cryptography to this kind
of suing digest this is done using
what's called using hash function but in
particular mirle hash or hash function
that are sixing but can be opened
locally so I'll recall what this is in a
second and once the prover sends over
kind of a uh squished form of the PC
then the verifier now behav like he's a
PCP verifier he tells the Prov open this
PCP and the location that the PCP
verifier would want to open and he gets
back the openings so uh so that's kind
of what the Kil mikali protocol is but
in order to to uh when I said you know
it squishes down and then there's
opening really what we need is a we want
to take a hash function so if you
remember a hash hash function is kind of
consists of a key generation algorithm
that generates a hash key and an eval
algorithm that take a hash and an input
and generates kind of a digest or a hash
value a last time we uh we talk we
showed how to get a a hash value uh how
to construct from uh the discrete log we
showed how to construct a hash function
uh uh from two Lambda to Lambda it takes
2 Lambda bit Lambda B actually was z p
to the 2 Lambda to zp to Lambda but
anyway one can encoded to have to be 01
to the 2 Lambda to 0 1 to the
Lambda but this is actually not enough
for the Kil M protocol what we actually
need is a collision hash function first
it needs to be much bigger because we're
taking a gigantic PCP we want to squish
it way more than like half this takes
you know make squishes the size reduces
the size from two Lambda to Lambda so it
squishes it by factor of two we actually
want to squish it to much bigger Factor
okay so we want to take kind of eval
what we what we use actually is an eval
algorithm that takes strings of size two
to the Lambda to Lambda so note here the
Lambda is upstairs it's very different
than two Lambda it's exponential
difference a so we take a a hash
function that goes takes gigantic
strings to lamb
and moreover another property that we
want is we can open locally remember we
said the way the mikali protocol works
is that the verifier asks okay you
committed to the gigantic PCP open it in
location you know 37 and 15 now how do
you open it so we also want kind of a a
opening algorithm so really what we
needed when we talked about Miracle hash
or hash hashes with local opening in
addition to having a key generation and
eval algorithm we also have a open
algorithm that generates kind of a
succinct
opening and you which can be verified in
a verification algorithm that verifies
it so last time we we kind of
constructed this morle hatch I'll recall
it today quickly and we ended without
kind of proving that it's collagen
resistant so that's where we're going to
start today we're going to just wrap up
the K mikali
protocol by explaining the thing that
was left is kind of to argue that this
Merkel hash
construction is indeed Collision
resistance so that's where we're going
to start today but then uh so once we do
that once we argue that the we have this
Merkel hash we put that it's Collision
resistant then we're done with the kill
M you actually proved that it sound
under this
assumption so so okay so where are we
heading today after we finished the
Merkel hash now we we actually showed a
succinct argument for all of NP this is
great however it's
interactive and interactive proofs or
arguments are really they're not very
useful and the reason they're not very
useful is for many reasons a there's
latency to talk back forth back forth
but another reason perhaps much more
important is that it's per per verifier
so if I want to just prove to the world
some statement I can't prove it using I
I'm not gonna go to each person in the
world and give him an an interactive
proof so it's really verifier specific
interactive proofs are verifier specific
it convinces the specific verifier you
talk
with okay and we want to prove that
convinces
everyone so that's kind of where the
segue we're taking today how do we
construct actually
non-interactive R now to reduce
interraction okay so what we're going to
show is how to eliminate interaction and
this is going to be done using a really
beautiful Paradigm called the F Paradigm
so I'm going to explain what it is it's
very very simple and then we're going to
introduce the random Oracle model which
is a model that was invented in order to
an attempt to analyze or to understand
the security of this F Paradigm uh it's
an ideal model okay we're gonna prove
the soundness of the Kil mikali protocol
that we we saw last time we're going to
actually show that it sound uh even if
you apply the F Paradigm to it as long
as you rign this random Oracle model and
this ideal
model and then we're going to probably
this we're going to only get till next
time but we're going to try to we're
talk about the soundness uh of the F and
the standard model okay so again we're
going to talk about eliminating
interaction using F talk about the
random orical model show that actually
the random oral model of this Paradigm
works well often uh we'll see exactly
when it works well when it doesn't and
then we're going to talk about if we
have time maybe start talking about uh
about Security in that standard model
because the random work model is not
it's a it's an ideal model so is it
secure is it sound like in when used in
actual
reality that's the plan questions yes
you shouldn't be able to do two of the
land you're something that long you find
a oh okay so um uh okay uh of course of
course you can find the Collision the qu
okay so I we Define it okay so the
question was about this two two to the
Lambda let me get let me now we'll see
the definition the construction I'll
explain but the the we get we get
completeness for two to the Lambda now
you're talking about soundness okay
soundness says that any poly adversary
or t time adversary yeah poly Lambda
adversary or po or t poly in t Lambda
adversary
cannot find a collision now if this T is
two to the Lambda then you're not going
to be secure so that I mean the
Assumption R so there's this is for
completeness for soundness the
assumption is for Collision resistance
the the definition is that no poly
Lambda time or poly T Lambda depending
on if you want standard Collision
resistant or T Collision resistant which
is slightly stronger assumption cannot
find
collisions great thank thanks for the
question any any other
questions I like questions just
reminding you
guys okay yeah so during this whole
thing I'm trying to imagine like how big
are the parameters so n like inside of
the input is something that's like like
normal people can read right yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah exactly okay so let
me yeah let me talk a little bit about
the parameters that's a great question
that's a good good thing to start with
so we want succinctness okay now when we
say succinct really what we want is so
we that's the things by using
cryptography once we use cryptography
things grow with the security of the
that we want so things will grow with
Lambda which is the security parameter
what the security parameter is depends
kind of how paranoid we are in the world
okay you can think about it is 256 bits
sometimes it's more depending on also
which crypto systems you use but that's
a good it's kind of independent of the
input okay just you want as succinct as
you can get and you know if you want to
use cryptography it's it's like security
parameter now the input it should in
some sense it should not depend on the
input but of course the input is not
going to be like more than two to the
Lambda because you think of Lambda is
such that two to the Lambda is like more
than the number of of molecules in the
universe so nothing is that big in our
world okay so you think of the X can be
bigger actually the input can also be
small you know but then sometimes you
don't need cryptography so so tiny it's
like phography is useless uh you can
just give the witness um so usually we
think think in our head of the input as
being can be much bigger than Lambda can
be poly Lambda and maybe even be like
Lambda to the log Lambda it can be you
know but it's not as big as two to the
Lambda that's doesn't exist okay but it
can be kind of anything that's kind of
real world number in in the sense um and
so that's kind of what what we should
think of okay does
that okay so when we do we're trying to
reduce the amount of the side of the pro
from like still a reasonable polze thing
but just like a 26 exactly exactly or or
right so you can think of it you're
trying to when when you do and let me
just repeat it also for the mic uh when
you're trying uh when you do this
interactive argument you think of you
take an X that's still real world you
can think of it polom l but it can be
more but as long as a kind of real world
thing and you reduce it to kind of 256
bits okay that's kind of the um the
Practical idea you should think of and
the more theoretical idea is to say you
can take any input X but not more than
two to the Lambda because that's like
you know but something anything less and
we make it as small as as po
Lambda okay great any any other
questions yeah and verify that row is
like the opening is that what it
is yes yes yes yeah yeah sorry yes this
is yeah I'll I'll go to it now yeah yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah let me let me okay
so good so let me uh just finish wrap up
what we where we left last time which is
the Merle hash so we use ml hash in the
kilan mikali protocol actually we don't
need to really remember the kilan mikali
protocol for today we're not going to
actually really use it but let me still
finish the Merle hash because it's a
very important primitive it's kind of
used everywhere in cryptography so it's
very important to know so uh so what is
the miracle hash it takes any hash
function not local opening just a
regular hash function that generates a
hash key and has an eval algorithm
evaluates just generates hash value such
that it takes two Lambda bits to Lambda
bits okay you can actually you can make
it more you can be even one plus Epsilon
Lambda bits to lamb you can play with it
but let's say two Lambda to Lambda
bits and we construct from it a hash
function with local opening so let me
tell you exactly what this hash function
with local opening what it looks like so
that then the hash key is exactly the
same as before we take the same hash key
as our underlying so first we started
with a hash we started with this hash
family what is it last time we saw we
can take for example I gave an example
with this discrete log but you can even
if you don't remember it doesn't matter
take think of it someone gave you a hash
family with this domain and range okay
now I'm gonna do a domain extension I'm
going to make the domain much bigger and
get local opening how do I do it so this
is the miracle hash
construction the idea is so the Gen is
as I said just generate the same hash
key as the original gen no change to the
Gen algorithm the eval algorithm on the
other end of course changes because the
domain is much bigger okay it takes
strings of size at most two to the L
bits and what does it do so what it does
is the following it takes his input X
let's suppose for Simplicity that X is
exactly kind of 2 the L time Lambda
bits
okay a so it's uh you don't have to
assume this this is just easy to assume
and you can always get it with padding
kind of take any input and Pad it so
it'll be of this form and I'll hash it
okay I I'll say a word if it's not of
this form uh but if it is of this form
what do you do you take your input X
just partition it to blocks each of
length Lambda so you have two to the L
blocks okay you have an input X of
length two to the L * Lambda you
partition it to chunks each of length
Lambda so you have two to the L chunks
let's call the chunks X1 X2 X3 X4 and so
on up to X2 to the Lambda each of them
up to X2 to the L
sorry each of them of length Lambda and
now what you do you take two blocks this
is two Lambda bits and hash it using our
building block hash that takes 2 Lambda
to Lambda you take the to Lambda you
hash you take these two you hash so in
other words you take the two to the L
blocks to two to the L minus one blocks
you hash every every pair you hash every
pair you hash every pair you hash every
pair you hash you got two to the L minus
one blocks then you take these blocks
and again every pair you hash every pair
you hash every pair two to the L minus
two blocks and so on for so forth until
you arrive to one block at the end
what do you output you output the top
the final I guess it's going to be
somewhere
here uh block which is often called a
root you output the root and you output
the depth of the
tree okay that's the output of the hash
so the output is the root the hash value
here it's Lambda
bits and D which you also think of it as
being Lambda bits even if it's less just
encoded using Lambda bits so if you're
mad now at me because I promise you
Lambda bits and you see here two Lambda
bits apply this hash one more time and
you'll get your Lambda
bits okay but how two Lambda bits is
also fine yeah um why are we Bing the
input L to two to the Lambda instead of
just arbitrary good good good good good
great because last time great question
so last time when I mention I said oh
just take STAR here anything so why am I
why am I bounding out to to the Lambda
so this construction bounds two to the
Lambda because as you I take every
Lambda I can't take that's all it gives
me so that's all I get now you can say
wait what if I want more maybe I more
than two Lambda you can actually get
more than two to the Lambda for example
you can bootstrap this so now you can
take two to the Lambda to Lambda you can
kind of create a Merkel hash of this
Merkel hash you know you can kind of uh
uh but actually you never it doesn't
come up because you never need to two to
Lambda is like nothing is more than two
to we choose Lambda to in our world
nothing is more than size two to the
Lambda but you can think of like um you
you can get if you just as a kind of
mathematical curiosity you can uh apply
it you know so once you have from two to
the Lambda to Lambda you
can chop your things to two to the
Lambda and and do this kind of use this
as a building block to a bigger morle
high so you can kind of amplify it you
know uh but we're not for us 2 to the
Lambda to Lambda is good enough great
great question
any any other question yes why does the
need to be included in the like should
it not just be a function of the left of
X ah good great great question why do
why do I insist on including D is it not
a function of X it is a function of X
it's a deterministic function of the L
not even X of the length of X yes
however nobody knows what x is so you
know at the end of the day I want
Collision resistance and so the property
we want from this hash is that it's
Collision resistance what does Collision
resistant means it means that you cannot
output a hash value with two different
openings now when you outut a has value
nobody knows what the x is actually you
may not even know well if
you um okay when you open you know but
uh you know when you give someone a hash
value there's no X
inherently a part of it if you don't
include the dep actually there's an
attack it's not collig resistance it's
really not it's not just a why is it not
Collision resistance for example just as
an attack let's say I publish this route
even this is my root okay this is my
input my input is X1 X2 X3 X4 and the
output is root now let me break the
Collision resistance I'll give you two
different openings one is X1 X2 X3 X4
you do the hash you see yeah you're
happy it's a good opening now let me
give you another opening just this and
this that's also a good open opening so
I open it in two different
ways that's not okay that's a collision
if you include D however then so that's
exactly what will allow me to argue
Collision resistance it's this D great
question thank you any so so this is the
construction
questions okay let's see how do we open
so now this is this is just so far great
we managed to go from two to the Lambda
to Lambda I didn't argue Collision resen
but at least we did domain extension so
we extended the domain but I also want
especially I need it for the killan M
protocol and for many many other uses in
cryptography I want to be able to do
local opening so remember what does
local opening mean I may not want to
open when with I may not want to give
you my entire
input I may just want to give you to
convince you that this hash value in
some location I of the of the of the
input the value is some bit B but I
don't want to give you the entire
because the entire input is gigantic you
can't even hold it so I want kind of a
succinct opener I want to convince you
in a kind of a very succinct way that
what's sitting here in this bit is zero
or it's one so how do I do it so this um
a uh construction is actually really
nice it gives you a local opening in a
very nice way so what's the local
opening suppose I want to open this kind
of the bit here sitting here what I'm
going to do I'm going to actually give
you this entire Block it's only L the
bit so it's not that big okay I give you
this block what do you do with it so let
me help you convince you that this block
is indeed the block related to the root
namely it's the it's the block that
indeed sits here next to how do I
convince
you I give you the sibling so this block
has a parent I give you the sibling and
the
parent this parent has a parent I give
you the sibling and the parent and so on
so forth until you get to the root I
give you all these blocks so in each
layer I open two blocks which are the
two siblings so I open two siblings you
get this I open the two siblings you get
this I open the twoing and so on
yes so I don't know if it matters but
you strictly you to return the ancestors
you can only return the sit ons right
good good good right right right you're
totally right you're saying well if you
really want to be what you're saying
which is completely right thing this is
wasteful because actually all I need to
give you is the sibling so why waste
communication I if I want to open this
I'll give you this and this sibling I
don't need to give you this you can
compute this on your own so compute this
on your own I'll give you this I don't
need to give you this you have these two
so complet it on this on your own and
then I'll only give you this and then
and so on you're 100% correct I actually
just need to give you
one okay I wrote two because it's just
easier to say something but yes exactly
one is enough and you can compute the
yeah
fantastic uh so that's the so I I I
denoted by so what does the open do it
gives you for each layer it gives you
two blocks for layer J denoted by ZJ so
ZJ is two blocks okay there's on the
leaves it's two blocks J equal zero it's
on the leaf layer one layer two up to
layer D it's actually just the root so
you don't you can actually go to D minus
one if you want okay but I I'll just in
in my mind I want to include the root
it's just you'll the reason I include
both and the root is now when I analyze
it it's notation wise it's just very
very easy but really it's enough like
you said to have the sibling and the
roots of course you don't need to
give okay but let's just think this is
how I open and now how do I
verify I just take each two sibling
compute the hash and make sure it
corresponds to the relevant the relevant
Z is indeed uh the parent so again you
gave me all these things I compute these
two I check that it's consistent with
the what you gave you if you didn't give
me fine I'll compute on my own I get
this I'll compute this and give and then
they'll check that all I need to check
it then is consistency with the
root okay that the
verification question about the design
the the
algorithms okay so this is kind of where
we left off actually last time and what
I want to do now is do the Collision
resistance I'm happy that actually we
got a chance to do it again because it's
a very important primitive so it's worth
kind of having it ingrained in your mind
a okay so why why is it collagen
resistant
so to prove Collision resistance what do
we want to argue that an adversary
that's given a hash key cannot produce a
hash value namely root and D with two
different
openings okay so
Suppose there
exists a poly
size adversary that does find the
Collision okay such that the probability
that a he gets a hash key hash key is
from
gen and somehow he manages to Output a
hash value which is root and D that's
just a hash
value and he gives me some
index uh I and he managed to open it in
two different way he gives me an open
opening that says oh I is zero and it
gives me another opening that says the I
bit is one and such that for both of
them such that for every B for both zero
and
one there will accept there and hash
key uh root and d i and row b outputs
one so suppose I have an algorithm
that gives me a hash value an index and
a valid opening both to zero and to one
valid I mean that the ver will accept
both of them oh sorry
B so ver takes hash key a value an index
I and a b bit B saying whether index I
is zero or one and a proof an
opening and suppose he accepts
both suppose he accepts both with
probability at least I know
Epsilon okay so Suppose there exist an
exists
Epsilon so Suppose there exist epon so
that for any L that the probability that
a managed to find the Collision like
this is at least Epsilon I'm going to
argue then then you can find a collision
in the underlying H in the small H with
probability Epsilon
okay so if you you if you have an
algorithm like this
then there exists an algorithm uh uh
poly
size such that
b such that the
probability that b he gets hash key the
probability that he outputs
a I don't know x0 x and x Prime such
that the original eval HK x equals
eval hkx Prime and X is different than x
Prime is at least
Epsilon but we assume that this is
Collision resistance we started with an
underlying hash function that's
Collision resistance so the Epsilon has
to be
negligible okay that's what we're going
to show so we're going to use if an
adversary can find a coll a local
opening that collides for the Merkel
hash we can use them to actually
break the to find collisions in the
underlying kind of two Lambda to L to
Lambda uh hash function in the little
hash
function so how does B work what does B
do B takes it a hash key he just run a
so let me so we claim that there exists
a b so let's see
B an input hash key what does it do just
run a so get root d i row0 Row
one which is just a and hash
key now
he got row zero and Row one what are row
zero Row one each row is this kind of
two uh pairs of siblings I'm going to
assume that both exist because it's just
easier for me that's why I wrote both of
them so each
opening so row zero is for each level
you have
z0
J from zero to D and Row
one is let's call it z uh one
J now what do we know in the leaves so
we know that
z0 Z is different than Z One Z the two
leaves are different because in one
leaf okay suppose suppose verify access
to both of them in the case that these
are both accepted I'm going to argue
that I found
collisions okay so now suppose row Z and
Row one are accepted so
ver ver accepts both of
them now if there accepts both of them
so we know that the leaves are different
because in the leaves in one case I have
here one and the other case I have zero
so they have to be different so I know
the leaves are different I also know
that z0
D equals z1d these are both a
root now of course I said we don't need
to include it because but I'm just
putting here because I want what the
reason I want to include it is just for
clarity to say look we have kind of D
layers of information on each
opening the leaves they must be
different because one opens to zero one
opens to one the root the last one must
be the same it's the root
it means that there must be some kind of
two adjacent layers on which one of
below they disagree and above they agree
okay we know here they disagree here
they agree okay they disagree do they
disagree here disagree here at some
point they're going to agree so we say
there must
be a layer J such that zj0 is different
than zj1 but ZJ + one 0 is equal to
ZJ + 1
1 yeah okay they disagree here how about
one layer above do they agree if they
agree great then that's going to be our
J plus one they disagree let's go up
until at some point they'll agree
because they agree
yeah oh thank you very much thank you uh
great thank you yeah it's not just for
the video it's also for you guys so I
won't uh confuse you more than it thank
you a one J One J + one thank
you okay yes I I is
it I did I miss
I yes
my God okay no there zero one
ah okay did I get it right yes okay so
there's a layer J said that in layer J
they disagree in layer j+ one they
agree that's it this is a collision why
what is layer J + one one of them is the
father is the
parent so we have two that they
disagree but both of these they agree
on in particular they agree on this so
done so we found a collision this must
mean
that the hash
eval hash key of
z0j is equal to
eval H key of z1j because this value is
one of the it's you know one of this and
one one of this and one of this
depending if it's the left or the right
depending on the tree but and they're
both equal so done I found a
collision okay with the same exact
probability so it's
uh now as I said this I wrote here
supposed to exist P Lambda I could have
if we assumed that the underlying hash
function is t- secure namely you can't
find collisions even if you run time
poly T of Lambda then we get that the
Merle hash is POL secure because B all
it does really is just run a it doesn't
run much more than a it just runs a and
then it does something very trivial so
the complexity of breaking the miracle
hash is really the same as the
complexity of breaking the underlying
hash so if the underlying hash is tsec
Miracle hash is TC
secure
questions okay so where are we so we
prove the Merkel hash as we saw the
Merkel hash was used to give an
interactive a succinct interactive
argument for all of
NP so now if you're willing to you know
to you're happy with intrac
protocols thank you very much I hope you
enjoyed the semester and we're
done if you're not though but as I said
we're actually we're not happy with
interactive protocols it's really
interesting actually to think of the
evolution of of this because you know it
before all this interactive proofs and
arguments and so on we had just
mathematical proofs which were not
interactive but they were very very
long and people were not happy like kid
like oh they're so long and then
interactive proofs were defined I think
they were defined only for the sake of
zero knowledge they were defined just to
get zero knowledge proofs I'm GNA
actually mention we're going to talk
about zero knowledge later
today and this motivated kind of the int
to introduce
interraction and then people like wow
you oh what a great forget about zero
knowledge forget about cryptography this
is such a great model using intraction
we can prove a lot more right and we saw
the Gare protocol you can can do like uh
you can prove actually any any circuits
that are really really huge as long as
they're kind of have dep you can do PE
space or any computation that has poly
depth you verify can be any depth V you
can the verify runs in time deep great
not it doesn't run in the sign so it's
much much more powerful wow wow wow and
then people like actually with
cryptographer can do much more great but
now like but wait there was a big price
we actually don't want ction so where
are we are we back at
NP NP is very we're back in the
mathematical proof that are way way too
long so I said
no we're actually going to circle back
in a very interesting way and get suin
non-interactive
proofs so how do we Circle back okay
so so this idea of how to Circle back
actually was
um put forth by fat Cham this is in the
mid 80s and
86 they proposed a really really nice
Paradigm actually they didn't think
about this is this is 86 this is kind of
before intractive proofs it was just
when zonal was introduced um interactive
proofs just came about but no you know
there was no PCP no interactive argument
none of that okay this is an 86
F they proposed the method
of actually reducing interaction of
constructing signature schemes now I I
stand behind what I said that this class
will not require a lot of cryptog crypto
background you don't need to know what
signature schemes are but the what they
did their idea is there was there's a
primitive called identification scheme I
want to prove to you that I'm y okay how
do I prove that I'm y I have a public
key corresponding to my name and I'm
going to prove to that I know the secret
key
me knowing whoever knows the secret key
has my identity essentially that's how
things work in the digital world so I'm
going to prove to you that I know the
secret key this proves that I'm me okay
this proof was interactive okay
identification Protocols are like three
round protocols I give you a message
Alpha you send me a question beta I give
you an answer gamma you verify that's
how it
works now they said let's convert this
identification scheme into a signature
scheme instead of kind of interacting to
make sure it's you every time you sign a
you want to send a message kind of use
this use this message take this
identification protocol together with
some message and kind of eliminate the
interaction I'll explain exactly how
they do it but but they do it in a way
to construct signature scheme that was
their
goal but now after several years after
we use it all the time to actually
forget about just the specific
application of identification skin to
signature that's one application
but actually we can show we can use it
to reduce to eliminate intraction not
only from identification scheme but from
any interactive protocol that is public
coin so let me explain so now take any
protocol uh so so this is a this is a
paradigm for eliminating
[Music]
interaction
from
interactive
protocols that are public
coin so not all protocol but ones that
are public coin so what is a public coin
protocol take any protocol let say a
proof so I have aover and a VAR
verifier and suppose for a second it's
so the suppose for Simplicity that it's
three messages okay so the verify the
prover sends a message Alpha the
verifier sends beta which is random okay
that's public CO mean the message of the
ver far is completely random okay let's
say it's kind of Lambda bits if it's
less then just P it to be Lambda okay
and if it's more just call that Lambda
make that the security parameter just
increase the security parameter
okay now you send
gamma and maybe it's more round so maybe
then he sends
Delta let's say random bits and then you
say epsilon and you can continue okay
let me stop here for the sake
of okay now I'm going to eliminate
intraction how do we eliminate
intraction it seem like intraction is
very important I mean the entire kind of
if you remember the surack and G
I mean it's tempting maybe to say oh
tell the prover compute Alpha Beta GMA
just compute the transcript on your own
you simulate the verifi messages then
he'll
cheat so how do you get rid of the
interaction seems
really really hard actually it's so easy
I mean there idea is Trivial so what is
their idea they said they say the
following
how does the verifier how does the Prov
get this
beta the verifier chose it so you know
what let's comp let not have the ver now
we don't have a verifier it's not
interactive there's no verifier so how
to compute this beta let's compute it as
kind of a hash function applied to the
transcript so
far so let me explain so
how here's how you convert it
to p f CH
V this is associated with some hash
family okay there's some It's associated
with a hash family so the F Paradigm you
can take any hash family and use that to
reduce interraction how do you use it to
reduce intraction now there's some hash
key that's chosen once and for all
everybody knows it either the verifier
sends it once or if you think about
public like everybody can verify I don't
know the
the US government publishes this hash
key everybody uses this hash key okay
there's some fixed hash key everybody
uses it now once we agree on a hash key
what does the prover
do he computes Alpha that's let's say he
wants to prove that X is in some
language so he let's say he want he's
telling okay I'm going to prove to you
that X is in the language let me prove
it to you okay I compute the
alpha now I'm waiting for a beta but
there's no verifier fine the I'll tell
you what the beta is beta is just has is
going to be EV Val of hash key on the
transcript so far X in Alpha that's
currently what's in the transcript the
the statement and the first message
Alpha now the proof is like okay this is
the beta I got from the verifier he's
interpreting this as the beta he got
from the verifier and now he computes
gamma my answer
the Pro's answer now he's waiting for a
message a query from the verifier some
Delta but there is no verifier so he's
going to compute
Delta as eval of the hash key using the
transcript so far so X Alpha Beta
gamma once he has Delta he's going to go
back to being aover and
compute Epsilon
and then you can continue next message
he goes computes a hash value of all the
transends of so far compute the next
Pro's
message another ver and we go that's how
we
continue any questions about so what
what did we go we got we started from an
interactive
protocol can have many rounds and now
all we need is to agree on a
haski and once we agree on Hashi the pro
just gives you this is one message
that's
it
yeah good great question is it important
to include beta actually you don't need
to include beta at all because the
verifier can compute beta so we you only
need to know beta so you can compute
gamma you actually don't need to include
it great question great great
question so note for example if you
think about kilan mikali protocol you
may not remembered but let me just write
it here just to refresh your memory why
not you don't need to actually to
understand this but uh since it's such a
nice protocol and so how does it go
there's a prover and a verifier the
verifier sends a hash key so he wants to
prove that X is an
L he does a Merkle
hash of the PCP so he computes a PCP Pi
is a
PCP for x and
L and he sends you the Merkel hash so he
sends you root
and the and the depth
that's that's just the so he takes the
PCP and he does a hatch with local
opening for example mer hatch actually
can do any hatch with local opening that
you want this is the most common one and
then he gets kind of the randomness from
the PCP verifier so this is R from our
correspond to the PCP
verifier this determines a few locations
to open so now he opens so he gives so
this may this you know this Randomness
corresponds to like some locations i1 up
to I L and then you just Open PI i1 with
open one up to Pi i l with open
L that's the protocol note this is
completely
random it's the randomness of the PCP
verifier so we can uh eliminate
intraction this you if you think of it
this is just kind of a protocol where
you send a hash key and then you have
kind of Alpha Beta
gamma okay so let's eliminate
interaction so how do we eliminate
interaction well there's this hash key
let's we can use this hash key to do but
we can also use another hash key hash
key and
now the well this can be now you give
Alpha beta is going to be simply you
don't have to include it but it's going
to be in your in our head it's going to
be eval of hash
hash of X in
Alpha and then maybe hash key is also
part of the
transcript and and uh this gives bit and
now you compute the GMA which is the
opening okay so you can
you can take any so now if what does the
F give you it gives us a away remember K
mikali was very succinct right you can
take X any let's say NP
language n can be very large it can be
Lambda to that thousand I know it can be
what it can be even super poom Lambda it
can be almost as l two to the
Lambda
okay and look how sucing the protocol is
you just send a hash key the root which
is Lambda bits and the opening and this
the PCP is all L the bits poly L the
bits so very very succinct and now you
can even just make it
so what is this you can all send it all
in one round so what what does it give
you what does it tell us that you we can
take any NP
statement and give a proof of size poly
Lambda doesn't matter what size X
is that's
amazing without cryptography we need po
you know these G Witnesses
yeah
prob imagine ofd hash family where there
exist hash keys that are really bad okay
and so I guess here it's fine because
the verifier chooses the hash key but
you might imagine if the US publishes a
anything else what if it happens to be a
bad one or to be a bad one okay you two
things first you're saying who chooses
this hash key of the F how do we know
that we trusted but you know it's much
worse than that is it secure let's say
let's say it's chosen randomly from the
hash
family is this
sound it's so again what did we do here
we started with an interactive protocol
we proved it sound let's say k m sound
we proved it ass we have Collision in
hash we prove that it
sound it sound assuming the prover gets
the ver the messages of the verify
randomly that's one 20 it sounds that's
we used it to Pro Sound is
now what am I saying what are we doing
now I'm saying oh forget about it it's
not random actually you comput it on
your
own from some hash key that someone
chooses even honestly from let's say we
agree we all agreed on some hash family
and someone honestly chose a hash key
but now you know this hash key now you
compute who says it sound I mean is it
still sound maybe it's not
sound okay so
first of all okay so first of all of
course there's one can think
of this hash this hash functions need to
have some property okay Collision
resistance like at the minimum if if you
can find collisions for example here
you're screwed it can be it can be ID it
can be trivial okay so you need some
property now the question is what
property do you need what property do
you need from this hash family to argue
soundness yeah
very very okay good so it seems like
well what do you need it need to be
random like in the protocol like okay we
we want to say take any what is our goal
our goal is to say take any
protocol that is sound public coin and
we want to convert it to non-interactive
that's what we're trying to do now I'm
saying what property do you need well
look here the our guarantee was that it
sound if this was random so need this
has to be somehow
random stand for reason so this is okay
but look hash functions are not random
it's a hash function by the way let me
say this Paradigm is used all over the
place it's a very popular Paradigm it's
used a lot in in signature schemes and
also in in uh um proof systems it's used
all over the place and which hash
function is used some of the Shelf hash
function sh 250 six like
these engineered type you know hash
function that are
optimized so is it secure with shot
256 it's definitely not random
it's so we actually don't know that so
let me be honest that is it
secure I don't
know
yeah extension
yeah right yeah you right right right
right right so actually let me good so
let me just say a few
things okay maybe I'll cut to just to
the
chase I do know let me tell you it's not
necessarily secure actually
unfortunately we have counter examples
so I said this is used in practice all
the time you know it's uh one of the
great inventions of cryptography is it
secure
no okay so what do I mean by no okay let
me is it always secure no so yeah let me
say let me take back my know thing is it
always secure is it always the case that
when you start with an
interactive protocol and convert public
coin and you apply is it always secure
no moreover let me tell you we have
protocols so that no matter which has
family you use for for all half families
the protocol becomes
insecure hey let me tell you even more
than that that will kind of really
you'll be
mad you know the K mikali
protocol that we kind of built
up even that's not secure the the F
won't be secure on it but this let me
actually put an Asters
there it's what okay so let me let me
tell you what's known about the
insecurity
of the F Paradigm for this protocol what
is known is there are some contrived so
the F the KE mikali protocol says take
any hash function that's Collision
resistance and uh and take any
PCP we get
tness there are examples of specific
hash functions or specific pcps that are
sound of course because it's so I mean
there are example of collision resistant
hash functions and pcps such that this
of course it sound it sounds for any
Collision hash function PCP but such
that no matter which hash function you
use for the phia this will be insecure
not
sound no matter what you
use
yeah what break yeah I I'll say a little
bit what break
in a second yeah example or okay good
good good same question so the example
for why it so why it breaks the example
for why it break is very contrived
actually so that's why am is the message
here don't use f CH we have a break no
that's not the message you should use f
because in practice it works very well I
don't have a single instance that people
used F practice and it broke so it's a
great paradigm use
it can we come up with a general proof
of security no because we have counter
examples so what did we learn okay so
maybe I'll start by saying I'll say very
very high level not in detail but about
the counter examples okay how can we
build counter examples and as opposed to
going to the K mikali protocol because
there you need to work a little harder
to fit it in uh I'll say a word how you
fit it in there too but the idea is the
foll let me try to give you a a proof
that is or an interactive protocol that
is sound but when you convert it to uh
when you apply F soundness
breaks so the idea is the following it's
going to be a very contrived protocol
okay so my what I want to do is
construct a contrived
protocol that is sound
but when you apply F no matter which
hash function you use it will
break and intuitively the contri
protocol is the following take any sound
protocol for example f for example kilan
mikali whatever or gkr whatever sound
protocol you like and I'm going to
change it I'm going to tweak a little
bit that the sound will still remain I'm
I'm going to tweak it so that I the
soundness will still
hold but on the twick protocol when you
apply for will
fail okay so start with PV for example
gkr for example k m whatever you like
and I'm gonna kind of tweak it a little
bit how am I going to tweak it I'm gonna
say tell the tell the verifier you know
what accept if you accept it before but
accept also if something very weird
happens but don't worry it will never
happen Okay when else are we going to
accept so remember the verifier let's
say he sends kind of a random beta
if the prover let's say ahead of time
guessed your beta he told you I know how
you're going Compu your beta so if the
pro ahead of time sent you kind of um
sent you a message that will kind of
tell say kind of I can
predict beta and kind of will predict
bet ahead of time then you accept him
this is random what's the property that
you can prct my bet
if beta is like random and 0 one to the
Lambda there's no way you can predict it
so if by any chance you predict I'm
going to you know you can won the
lottery I'll accept you no matter I
don't care if that's in the language or
not it only adds like a negligable
probability of you know because the
probability that you can predict beta is
one over two to the
beta now what happens in the F meal
Paradigm oh I can tell you oh I know bet
I'm I can predict it I'm going to tell
you exactly how I predict it beta is
going to be eval hash key and this
message that's the idea now to implement
this idea it's harder it requires some
work I'll tell you why this idea is not
trivially
implemented
because when we do F we say we
start with a protocol and now the
question question is does there exist a
hash a f has family for which it's
secure now we start with a protocol this
protocol can say can say Okay Alpha is
Hash key for
example and then you accept if you
originally accepted or if eval of hash
key of alpha which is also hash key is
equal to Beta now this will not happen
but in the future me it will happen
I'm going to just send the F in haski
that's what I
do okay but then someone will say okay
so you give me a protocol what is the
length of your Alpha it's Lambda bits
I'm going to use a hash function that
the hash key is longer and now you can't
send it because here I'm like I'll send
the hash
key so then you need to use a hash to
kind of Squish this hash key it it's
more
complicated but the the basic idea
is this does not work if somehow the
verifier accepts you if you kind of
convinced him that you can kind of
predict his his beta that's really
and so we can construct kind of
contrived um protocols that achieve this
or we can cont construct very contrived
hash function that do this weird game
inside the hash function like the hash
function becomes trivial if you feed it
something that kind of so so it requires
more work but it's all very
contrived okay so I hope I convinced you
by with these examples the counter
examples are so contrived so when you
when you say oh we found the p is not
secure and you show these example the
reaction should be come on okay nobody
uses these
protocols but what it does tell us you
can't apply F blind you can't okay what
it does tell us is for all of us who are
upset with trying to prove the Paradigm
there's no General proof because we have
counter examples at least
that question you need to
start great great question okay I that's
my next so I I'll I'll uh
yeah I'll the answer is yes but I'll
I'll I'll talk about that next the
question was about negligible soundness
but we'll get to that next so any
question though
before okay so but you know still people
use the F Paradigm and there's a
question
of is it sound for natural protocols is
it
sound and the answer is actually it
would have been nice if we can come up
with Pro nice protocols and say at least
a large class of protocols and say yeah
if you use this hash function this
specific hash function which we know is
Collision resistant under discret log or
under some other
then your scheme is sound that would be
very
nice we're still not there yet but we
made a lot of progress in recent years
and I want to tell you about the
progress but before that the first way
the first a
a uh kind of way we try to analyze so
the F gained popularity very quickly
okay uh and because it's so simple and
so efficient uh it became very very
popular
and people really wanted to understand
its uh security is it sound is it not
sound and then in
93 Bela and rway introduced kind of an
ideal model called the random Oracle
model and this model said you know
what by the way this was before we had
any counter examples okay this model was
introduced by Bel and rway in I believe
80 uh
93 this was before we knew any counter
examples for the Paradigm and they I
mean except for some which goes through
your question Leo but I'm going to get
to it and they wanted to ask can we
prove security of of
the uh what do we need about the hash
function what properties do we need
about the hash function to prove
security and the first property they
said you know what what if the hash
function was completely
random so when you use we use a specific
there's a circuit that computes the hash
function it's like a touring machine a
polinomial Time touring machine or a
polinomial size circuit takes a hash key
and okay they say you know what what if
the hash function is completely
random Okay so the r welome model says
suppose we
apply Fe to
Paradigm with
truly
random function
H so this is completely completely
random so what do I mean by completely
random so now I
guess let me
instead of
choosing a function from a
family we don't choose a function and we
just say suppose they have a truly
random they have access to both of them
to a truly truly random function and
they can ask so when the prover computes
Alpha he asks he has Oracle this
function and he tells the function give
me the function apply 2 x and Alpha and
he gets back a beta and every time this
hash this Oracle he gets a query he
chooses a completely random so think of
this as like a database of all like size
two to the Lambda of all like just
random random random elements a really
really truly random
function so now the question was okay if
this is truly random now can we get
security at least like that's the
minimum and moreover it seem like the
answer should be yes because in some
sense what was their what was their
intuition the intuition is what does it
matter if you're talking to a verifier
that gives you random queries or you're
talking to in terms of the prover so the
prover is trying to cheat what does it
matter if he's talking to a verifier
that give him kind of random vas or he's
talking to a random function that gives
them random betas both of them do random
betas what's the
difference so it should at least be
secure in the random Oracle model let's
first establish
that so is it secure in the random
Oracle model
no and this goes to Leo's
question and I'm going to tell you why
it's not secured the random oracal model
and actually let me take a little
detour and uh tell you I'll I'll show
why it's not secure in the random oracal
model via a little protocol
this protocol actually is going to be
useful because actually later we will
show that the f is sound for this
protocol it's kind of weird but let's
this protocol by the way is very
important
protocol so so let me quickly do let me
do a little detour I think it's a really
interesting detour so I hope you enjoy
it um it takes us a little bit into the
land of
cryptography but not too bad
a little further than we went so far so
far we just talked about hash
functions okay
so what I'm going to say now is going to
be a little bit of a high level
a so a protocol that I want
to talk about is actually a zero
knowledge protocol so you know so far we
just talked about verification
verification you know synness and
efficiency but uh as I mentioned
interactive protocols were actually
invented for the sake of zero
knowledge so what was the goal the goal
was forget about sness now it was not at
all about sness all we wanted is a
prover that has let's say a witness for
some there's some there's some language
and let's say the language we're going
to be interested for today just as an
example is the language of hamiltonian
cycle
that's just an example so this language
consists of
graphs so this is the language that
consists of all graphs graph is just
consists of nodes and
edges such that this graph has a
hamiltonian cycle so that g
has
a
hamiltonian cycle what this means is
just
you can just there's a kind of a a cycle
of all the nodes so it means that
there's a cycle of all the nodes so
let's say you start with node i1
I2 up to i n and then go up to I in said
that there's an edge here Edge Edge Edge
Edge Edge an edge all the way back
that's that means it if if you can if
there's some such um uh uh a setting of
The nodes for which you can kind of set
them in a way that there's edges that
kind of complete a cycle then we say the
graph has the hamiltonian cycle okay
this language is NP complete okay now so
now going back what is a zero knowledge
proof a zero knowledge proof is a way I
want to convince you that a graph G has
aonian cycle now I can give you the
cycle I can give you see here's the node
you can look there's a cycle there but I
don't want to give you any information I
don't want you to learn anything I don't
want you to to find the cycle I don't
want to reveal any information but I
want to convince you that it has a
hamiltonian
cycle how do I do that so this kind of
so there's a a celebrated result it
started with gasali and ROV in mid 80s
and uh where they defined this notion of
zero knowledge uh and constructed some
protocols but later very shortly later
uh uh by gold gold mikali and vigone
showed that actually any NP language has
a zero knowledge
proof okay let me give you one specific
zero knowledge proof for the aonian uh
cycle language uh and this is Du to blam
okay so I'll show you the the proof it's
very very nice okay and it's going to be
useful for us uh to show NE to show why
the random oral model fails and then
also to show the security of the F so
this is actually we'll get back to this
protocol okay so what is this protocol
there's a prover in a
verifier the idea is the following the
prover will he knows he will first he
has a
g the first thing he's going to permute
completely permute that the nodes okay
so he's going to choose a random
permutation Pi let's say n is the number
denoted by
n the number of vertices in G he's going
to to choose a a random
permutation of the
nodes now he has kind of the permuted
graph in his head so he has pi of G in
his
head now this it has this P of G has a
hamiltonian cycle because G has and I
just renamed the nodes now I'm going to
I want to give you I want to give you
just this hamiltonian cycle so I want to
give you the nodes here that form
Hamilton so I want to give you H I would
like to give you the nodes that form the
ham just the hamiltonian cycle but I
can't give you that will reveal
information okay so I don't want to do
that instead I'm going to give it to you
kind of in a safe okay hidden this is
what called in cryptography call this
commitment scheme so I'm going to give
you a
commitment of the cycle C
so think of this I'm for all the
possible edges I'm put 0 0 0 0 only in
the cycle I'm going to put one that's
what I mean here because this so this is
like think of it's a
matrix uh of n byn uh
sorry yeah n
byn for any possible Edge for any
possible node I and J I'm going to put
zero like there's no Edge only if it's
in the cycle I'm going to put an edge
there yeah is on the label of the like
permuted gra exactly on the permuted
graph okay this the reason I permute the
graph is to ensure zero knowledg this
even though when I send the commitment
really think of it I'm we're going to
later talk about how to do this
commitment but for now think of it
there's a safe I'm putting my commitment
inside the safe I leave the key to
myself and I give you this box so you
learn
nothing okay so here really you learn
nothing but now but you but you're not
convinced either because you just got a
safe what are you going to do with it so
now here's how I'm going to convince you
that actually this graph is is has a
hamiltonian cycle without leaking any
information so you the verifier you're
going to give me a random bid
B this is going to be
random random bit now
if B is
zero I'm just going to open this so if B
zero if B is zero open I'm going to open
the safe and now you can see that what's
sitting there is a hamiltonian
cycle okay now what did you
learn well because I permuted it's just
a random cycle actually it has nothing
to do with the graph I can even first
just choose a random cycle commit to it
and then kind of post kind of choose
this permutation to align with this uh
with this cycle so really because I G I
chose you a random permutation it's just
a random cycle so you didn't learn
anything it's just a random cycle you
and yourself can put a random cycle in a
safe so really no
information what if B equals
1 if B equals 1
I want to first I want to give you Pi
okay so I give you Pi but now I can't
open this because now if you know pi and
you see the cycle you know where my
hamiltonian cycle
is so what I'm going to do I just want
to convince
you
that this cycle only
has edges that were in this
graph so I'm G to open only the non
edges so instead of opening everything
I'm going to
open non
edges
in the the permuted
graph so note here we have so I have
here like okay so there's a question how
do I how do I open so think of
it I I commit to N squared bits okay for
any possible IG I have a bit saying is
it zero or is it one is there an edge or
is it not an edge think of it as I'm
giving you N squared safes okay like now
if B is zero I open all the safes I open
all the safes and you see oh there's
only there's just a cycle you know
there's everything is zero except for
you know i1 and I2 are there's one and
then I2 I3 that's it everything else is
zero if you send me a one then I open
something else I don't open everything
now opposite what I do is I give you
pi and for every nonedge in pi I open
the nonedge safe and I show you see
there
zero so all the all the safes I opened
are just going to be
zero so you really didn't learn anything
I just opened zeros you can simulate
that in your head what do you learn in
some sense you know if if you you know
that if you accept me oh I'm going to
open to do zeros
there and the pi doesn't reveal anything
it's just random
permutation so note you the verifier
didn't learn anything if you open to
zero if you send me zero I just open
random cycle has nothing to do with the
graph nothing just random cycle okay
that doesn't get that that's not helpful
for you if you open one I gave you
completely random permutation
you know p on your own and I open to
zeros all the n edes i open to zero you
learn
nothing
still you are somewhat
convinced that this protocol that that
the graph is hamiltonian why are you
somewhat convinced that the that there's
a hamiltonian cycle why are you someone
convinced because if there is no
hamiltonian cycle in G I cannot open to
both zero and
one why why is it the case that I cannot
open let's
see I'm a cheating let's say the graph
is there's no hamiltonian
cycle now I sent you these N squared
safes case one there's indeed only a
hamiltonian cycle there like indeed when
you open all these end saves what you
see is everything is zero except for
hamiltonian cycle
if that's not the case I cannot open to
zero if I open to zero you catch
me now suppose I did succeed in opening
to zero namely there's just aonian cycle
there that's
it then I claim there's no way I can
open to one why if there is a
hamiltonian cycle there I know the
hamiltonian cycle is not on the
non-edges because the non-edges are zero
if I open on one the non-edges are zero
so Theon CLE is on the edges but there
is noonian cycle it can be on the
edges so either I'm a chover either I
can I I may be able to open to zero I
may be able to open to one but I can't
open to
both so with probability half you'll
reject
me half is not that great but it's
something okay so at least now we know
with probability half I'm going to be
rejected
okay you like The
Detour okay let's go back to the random
or but
yeah I so what no what I commit to is
actually I have N squared commitments
everything is zero except for a random
cycle I don't I only commit to zeros why
is it important that I only commit to
zeros because
when I open okay I want to make sure
that there's a cycle
here but when I open to one I don't want
to reveal anything and the way I don't
reveal anything is I show that all the
non edges in pi in pi of G if you open
them here you'll get a
zero just with the cyle like outline
exactly exactly what I commit is a
matrix what I commit to is like a matrix
that only has like a hamiltonian cycle
and that's it everything else is
zero yeah so in the second case the
verifi cannot use the permutation to
figure out what edges are not in the hon
ccle for the original right so in the in
in the b equals one case you're talking
about yeah in the b equals one case the
verifier what does he learn he learns Pi
the permutation that's just a random
permutation
and then I'm just telling you I'm
reassuring you that I didn't lie what do
I mean by reassure you I open everybody
you can compute Pi G on your own that's
not a secret G's given Pi is given you
can Pi G you see all the non edges
that's not a that's not and all the N
edges I'm going to open only the N edges
and show you
zeros okay because the point is if I was
honest what I should do is put on only
on edges and not only on edges only on
hamiltonian and the edes that former
hamiltonian cycle that's what I should
do if I'm honest and what I show you I
don't show you that because that will
give information but at least what I
show you then all the non-edges here I
committed to
zero and that gives you no
information but if indeed I the
non-edges are zero and there's
hamiltonian cycle then it means Honan
must must be edges and then it means
that P G has a hon cycle and that can't
be if G doesn't have a hilon cycle 5G
doesn't have a honi cycle and that's why
I can't succeed in convincing
you in answering both
questions yeah is there a formal way to
say what it means to be zero knowledge
like good good good good good so the
question yeah actually I plan not to go
into the the but it's so beautiful so I
will
a yeah so the question was uh what is
the definition actually of zero
knowledge and the definition of zero
knowledge
says that what does it mean you don't
learn anything so the definition says
that so this is the definition of zero
knowledge what it says
is the verifier actually it's it says
it's stronger it says for every verifier
not just the honest verifier even
malicious ver there's you can talk about
honest verifier you an object the honest
verifier who just does what it should do
and just listens doesn't learn anything
but actually there's a stronger notion
of malicious so I say even for malicious
verifier you want to say what he learned
he could have simulated on his
own so the definition says for every uh
so you okay for every verifier if you
look the
transcript of and and for every X and
L for every X if you look at the
transcript between the honest prover and
the
verifier the prover has a witness but
the verifier
doesn't what he learned from this
transcript or what the verify maybe
sorry let me write it differently let me
say The View
of V Star while interacting with
P an input
X so whatever varar
learned he could have simulated on his
own so it says there
exists a
simulator and this is efficient and
efficient
simulator such
that the simulator efficiently can
generate this transcript on his
own if he has v he needs varar because
of course varar depends what he sends
and so on but he could generate it on
his
own
yeah on
than is it the same SIM for every oh my
God there's so many okay there's so so
many Notions of zero knowledge so for
example first of all it I'll answer your
question the question was is the
simulator only gets V Star as Oracle AIS
does it get as an input is it Universal
is it for there exist for every V is it
for every V there's a simulator moreover
let me continue is V all powerful is V
supposed to be PPT or poly siiz
and the answers there's many definitions
but yeah so
um originally all the protocols we had
used the verifiers of
blackbox uh however in 2001 I think was
it h BOS Barak was the first kind of
construct non blackbox Z knowledge where
the simulator used verifire as a non
blackbox and it was a really
breakthrough result because what he
managed to to get is a new Zer knowledge
proof that we didn't know of before it
was kind of constant round now you you
can say wait this is also constant round
what do you mean we didn't know before
but this is only sound as
half turns out if you want NE sound this
you need to repeat this protocol
sequentially you can if you repeat it in
parallel
it's it's not necessarily zero knowledge
actually yeah this one actually is not
zero knowledge if you're you're
repeating in parallel we we'll talk
about that and so using non blackbox
technique he managed to show the first
kind of Conant round zero knowledge
public coin zero knowledge proof so
there's there's many many variants okay
is is the
a the the
point okay but this is kind of a common
variant to think
about and also um so this is kind of
poly size or or V can have auxiliary
input so for every X and A or V Star is
poly size so we can have like auxilary
information about X even if he has ail
information about X still so V Star is
kind of has may have ex information
about
X still the two are
indistinguishable
yeah what if
the follow with
commitment where he create that matrices
that cycle in that matri Comm that wait
again what if the commit approver
commits to a cycle or no he commits to a
cycle but the cycle is not necessarily
it has nothing to do with G just commits
to any cycle he to CC that then able
to it's zero right yeah he'll be able to
exactly he'll be able to answer zero but
he won't be able to answer
one because that cycle must touch an
edge
because sorry that cycle must touch a
non-edge because if it only touched
edges
there is no cycle so that cycle you give
here Pi now the prover can the cheating
prover can give whatever Pi he wants but
the point is that the graph the permuted
graph doesn't have a hamiltonian cycle
because if G doesn't have a hamiltonian
cyle the permuted G also doesn't have a
hamiltonian cycle so this graph doesn't
have a hamiltonian cycle and that means
that the cycle that's here I don't care
how you generate whatever the cycle was
it must touch such a non
Edge so so the hamiltonan CLE says you
know there's an edge between i1 I2
there's an edge between I2 I3 there one
of them cannot be edge here it can't be
that all of them are edges here because
they're so because it doesn't have an
malonian cycle so one of them cannot be
an edge here and now what the what the
verifier is asking from the prover he
looks at all the I i1 and I all the I
and J that do not have an edge and he
open that edge I want to see that it's
zero I want I want you I want to see
that I gave you n squar safes so for
every inj there's a safe and it should
be one if there's an edge and zero other
I mean if there's an edge in the
hamiltonian cycle and zero otherwise now
with the with the verifier is asking the
prover for every J here that does not
have an edge I want you to open the safe
corresponding to that edge and I want to
see a zero there if there's a one there
I'm not happy I'm going to reject you
because this there should be on only on
the hamiltonian cycle and these are only
places that have an edge on your
graph but the problem
is on one of these I that don't have an
edge you'll see an edge because the
aonian tyo is not all on edges and then
I'm going to catch
you yeah
great any more questions
yeah slightly stronger that requires the
pro to actually
know the hamiltonian cycle right so here
the proof like with the second part say
that only guarante that if G is not
doesn't have a
hon proof
the cannot but do necess like Converse
like
is it possible for G to not know cyle
but still ver good G good good good
great question great question so the
question was or let me just answer the
question is the qu the question was wait
we just proved your soundness that if x
is an non the language on one of the
answers you'll fail but actually doesn't
this protocol give you something
stronger was the question and the answer
is yes so what what do we mean by some
something stronger let's say G is does
have a hamiltonian
cycle doesn't this protocol tell us not
only that g has a hamiltonian cycle if
you succeed let's say you succeed
probability one or you know with h more
more than
half this protocol tells us not only
that g has a hamiltonian cycle it means
that P must know the
cycle you can actually find you can
extract the cycle from from from p and
the answer is yes yes you can you can
actually this is what's called proof of
knowledge it means that P knows now I
can say what does it mean that P knows
what do we this is this is a theory
class mathematics what does no mean you
know so what what what we mean by P NOS
what we mean is that we can actually
efficiently extract the cycle from p and
how do we extract the cycle it's
actually very
easy we ask him he committed to
something he knows how to open both
that's assumption so first we'll ask him
okay open only the
cycle and
then give me the
pi once I know the pi and the cycle I
can I can undo I can I know what py gen
I can see I can actually find the aonian
cycle so it's it's more than just a
soundness it's a proof of knowledge he
must no I can actually use him to kind
of extract the the antonian cycle from
him any any other
questions okay so let's take a five
minute break and then after the break
I'm going to show you why this protocol
is not secure in the roral model but
we'll fix it don't worry okay I'll take
a break