thank you everyone and good morning um
I'm Dr Keith deer I'm former expert
adviser to the UK prime minister on
Science and Tech in the context of our
International in security strategy I'm a
20-year intelligence officer in the
Royal Air Force where I continue to
advise the chief of the air staff on
where science and technology is taking
us and today I speak to you as managing
director of fij Jitsu Center for
Cognitive and Advanced Technologies the
first Insight I want to share though uh
I stress um is probably the most
interesting and I'm going to share it in
a personal capacity for that reason take
a bit more risk our contention in the
center is that artificial intelligence
digital twins a whole raft of emerging
Technologies are increasingly cognitive
Technologies they allow us to imagine
and test alternative Futures which is
the defining feature of human cognition
the thing that separates us from animals
in the way that we think if that's true
you can begin to see it will profoundly
revolutionize how we make decision ision
because decisions is ultimately where
cognition manifests it's what cognition
evolved for to Keep Us Alive by allowing
us to imagine well hey if I take this
approach does it Advantage me socially
does it Advantage me um physically am I
more likely to survive in this scenario
if I do x y and Zed cognition evolved to
Keep Us Alive cognition evolved to help
us make better decisions and in order to
make better decisions you're going to
have to revolutionize the way in which
your organizations are structured which
brings us to the hor old point of
transformation it's going to be about
transformation transforming your
organization that's most
important right now the need for that
transformation is so urgent because of
three principal reasons and antha talked
a moment ago about the deciding what to
bet on well right now the median
estimate on the world's largest
forecasting site for when we all have
artificial general intelligence one at
the 70th percen or more or less of human
performance is
2027 the median estimate for one will
have Oracle AGI one that outperforms
humans in all cognitive tasks one way to
understand that is anything that you can
do sat at a computer 2029 and the median
estimate on metaculus for when we will
reach artificial super intelligence one
that exceeds Us in all dimensions of
cognition and adds proprioception
Locomotion and dexterity things that
traditionally machines find hard and we
find easy that median estimate for when
that will arrive is
2032 and all of those things mean that
the we profoundly need to change how
organizations work we need to understand
that we're going to be increasingly
reliant on machines to advise us on the
decisions that we make to understand the
implications to imagine and test those
alternative Futures and to give us
insights on which we can rely the pace
of change is such as well that one
approach to this saying hey here's one
where we want to get to and we're going
there is not going to work you've got to
be experimenting continuously and so
what I'm going to share in the time that
remains to us is that one approach is
not enough you need to be doing a number
of things and you need to understand
that those things you are doing will be
constantly overtaken by the pace of
change so we'll go through a few of
those things as a sort of Tor reason of
things that are happening at Fujitsu as
we try to wrestle with this profound
challenge of what de cognitive
Technologies mean for the future of all
of our
organizations first of all new market
development if you accept the premise
one that I argued for in the UK's
International strategy in 2020 that
automation Robotics and AI reduce
companies and countries dependent on
people to create wealth um and to scale
AR services to deter or fight so if it
reduces our dependence on people to
create wealth to create products and
services you're still going to need in
these organizations that were able to
churn things out independent of
demography independent of people you're
still going to need new markets to sell
them into and you need to be moving
therefore constantly into the most
dynamic markets in the world we've
chosen to do that in Japan because we
think there's a huge opportunity there
where the UK and Japan complement each
other I won't overdo this but you can
see on the right hand side UK leadership
in a number of areas Japanese leadership
in a number of areas those things where
we are both really strong and we think
those things are complementary where you
can learn from each other but of course
you could put many countries around the
world side by side like that and
understanding those relative strengths
of both and how they might complement
each other is key to understanding which
Market you're going to enter and being
able to to articulate the rationale for
why but it's also not just strength
sometimes it's weakness in the UK we're
first for research globally um every
year since 2007 by research by citation
waiting Japan is 11th
on that same scale so that is real
leadership but our ability to
commercialize to develop the develop of
R&D the UK was 27th out of the EU 28
when we left and we've been going
backwards ever since Japan is 13th
globally in its ability to turn turn
that world leading Research into new to
Market New to firm inventions into
technologies that scale that's a huge
opportunity for any country do company
doing Market entry to the UK and Japan
you can seize on world leading
ecosystems and then you can begin to to
break into those areas to do the kind of
development those countries urgently
need know they need um all of those
countries many countries around the
world well there are no countries in the
world that are achieving the levels of
productivity increase and economic
growth that the US currently is and what
that means for companies in the US
looking to do Market entry into um areas
over overseas is that you'll often find
most of those countries are trying to
build their own MIT they're trying to
build their own Silicon Valley and I
know MIT engages to try and recreate the
ecosystems it has here all around the
world you'll find yourself as a company
doing that market entry if you do it the
right way which I'll come to Next in
remedy being welcomed into the
Ministries in those countries as
somebody that can help them understand
what they need to do and as somebody
that can help them build the kind of
innovative startups that bring that
dynamism to the economy so new companies
are formed in part out of old companies
as as people are recycled through them
and you need that exit rate and dynamism
so getting the diagnosis right and
understanding where the opportunities
are is as important as understanding how
you go um understanding the
complimentary strengths there's a macro
policy level therefore being able to
really understand what the country is
doing to address its economic challenges
but there's also a micro policy thing
here which I think is important like
what you can do so going in with very
clear thought leadership about what the
problems are in a country not just the
product you're offering to sell but how
it might contribute to to wider dynamism
is absolutely key and I'll give you an
example of how we've done that you need
to be partner Le if you're a large
corporate and I suspect that most people
in this room are large representing
large
corporates what most countries are
looking for is not you it's might be
looking for your investment but it's
looking for that investment to drive the
kind of dynamic startups that are going
to disrupt their economy over and over
again to increase the exit rate and
entry rate of new companies and so
allowing those startups to lead and
putting yourself in in support is
discomforting but essential you need to
think interests you need to be interest
L that's not just your interest that's
also the countries and the companies
with which you're engaging in our case
in Japan but it could be anywhere like
what do they want out of this really
understanding those early on is crucial
and then distilling all these insights
into microscripts I think if you do
those you can play a real role in
helping to drive the solution in many of
these countries whilst also exporting
from your own the solutions that are
going to most help um your potential
Partners so an example of one of those
micros scripts we worked with a a small
UK drone manufacturer that's
manufacturing drones that are currently
operating in Ukraine for one the cost of
1 F35 you can buy a thousand of these
drones and what we talk about the dollar
cost dollar damage ratio how much you
damage you can inflict for how much the
equipment costs is vastly in favor of
the drones my friend Mike horovitz
recently wrote an ask in foreign affairs
talking about the age of precision Mass
um and this is exactly that now in Japan
where we were doing business um but I
would suggest anywhere in the world
right now there is still an over
Alliance on these kind of Exquisite
large scale systems and less of the
milit of the military startup ecosystem
that you need beneath that to provide
these kind of things
what we were able to go in is explain
how startups supporting the war in
Ukraine can move with real speed was the
first thing so going from new uh
requirement to a new capability in less
than six weeks and continuously doing
that Innovation cycle how they were
doing that at scale able to manufacture
I can't give the precise numbers but
many hundreds of these every month and
then Supply the need to understand your
supply chains in much greater detail
than many countries currently do so
three micros scripts speed scale and
supply and explaining how there were
lessons from Ukraine for the defense of
Japan starting with a thought leadership
piece that really gave value to our
Japanese Partners in explaining like how
the the war in Ukraine might affect
their own security and therefore why
they might be interested and indeed this
has been so successful that yes we've
moved on of course with the the
nitty-gritty business of sales of
equipment uh in that country and
building Partnerships and building
factories and learning from Japan about
how you do um automation at scale for
the UK company that we've partnered
with but also what we've done through
this process is is create a kind of
repeatable business model where now we
can go in with other startups that can
offer um key advantages that help drive
that dynamism into the economy I've
started having Venture capitalists
coming to me to ask well can you help us
do Market entry into Japan can you
advise on like the thought leadership
piece where we tell our story about how
we disrupt and that helps us to jointly
enable the kind of reforms that these
countries need I think that that's just
as true something you could do equally
well in Korea and I think you could do
it in many countries across the Indo
Pacific and so I I share an example that
is from Fujitsu from UK entering Japan
but I think is globally applicable um
and it relates back to where we started
because many of these countries need the
kind of dynamism in the economy that
these kind of Partnerships can bring if
they're to keep up with that constant
speed of innovation in in cognitive
Technologies the other thing you
obviously need to do is new product
development but often not in the way
that you have been doing it today so um
about two and a half gusting three years
ago in fij Jitsu um before there were
llms we kicked off a neuros symbolic AI
program called cibil and I'll talk a
little bit about what that was and at
the time we were looking at how we could
apply knowledge graphs to deliver
explainable AI when we launched it I was
able to say with confidence that the
only person I knew apart from me
globally speaking publicly about how the
future of AI would be neuros symbolic
and not purely neural networks was yanon
at um at meta um and then
uh llms came out of generative AI with a
um a neural network based architecture
and now we're back with chat GPT uh zero
um to neuros symbolic Solutions so it's
an example of how we started off with
something that was unique we then were
sort of overtaken by innovation in the
things that we were betting against and
now we're back to where neuros symbolic
is actually really important and the
reason it's important is many of the
challenges faced by llms are
inaccuracies biases hallucinations
fundamentally that they are not
explainable in the recommendations that
they give you so you can revolutionize
decision-making but if you can't audit
the recommendations you receive then you
can't rely on them what what we do is we
brought the neuro of neural networks so
often superhuman performance like in
alphao Z for example but fundamentally
not explainable together with the
symbolic of good oldfashioned AI the if
then else structured approach to
encoding um symbolically how we
understand the world and feeding all
that into a knowledge graph that could
ultimately output text but tell you
where that had come from so an abstract
level that's the new product development
another way analogously of thinking of
this is the murder board that you might
see in any kind of movie Thriller right
that connects objects entities and
events with the red string and he's
trying to explain how something happened
by connecting everything up and then
being able to explain both the
individual pieces of data and the
connections between them so cibil was
designed to build that kind of Knowledge
Graph through neuros symbolic approaches
which massively reduces the amount of
power that you need the energy challenge
that we talked about earlier um but also
allows you to explain L um and it we
built it in a way that allowed you to
ask problems in natural language
questions but remember this is before
chat GPT um and so what we found is we
started this workof developed real depth
of understanding and then suddenly we're
overtaken by technology you know we were
um presenting this internally of look we
can now build a knowledge graph from
unstructured data looks a bit like this
when you just take a small extract of it
we were using it for um sanctions um
sanctions monitoring and sanctions
implementation and sanctions enforcement
so this is O der Pasa hello o uh this
was O der Pasa and some of his interests
around the world um and whether they may
or may not be subject to sanctions I
have no idea if they actually were quick
qualifier but that was the example we
were using um then the output that we
would get was ultimately explainable so
it would say bat mining limited is a
company blah blah blah but it would also
output allow you to understand where
that data had come from so now you
haven't got just the generative AI
output that may have also hallucinated
um the sources that it comes from you've
got an explainable output in a knowledge
graph that you can look back at and you
can see how you got to the answer what
I'm trying to emphasize here is not so
much the technology itself as the
importance of investing in things and
keeping going with them sometimes even
when they're overtaken by things like
chat GPT because ultimately that
knowledge has gone into Fujitsu Global's
project called homes hyper relational
knowledge Gras for multihop questioning
answering using llms it's supporting
fujitsu's work with coh here building
their next um llm a multilingual model
which is specifically focused sector by
sector on boosting productivity and
efficiency as a service that's a Fujitsu
collaboration um and so what we have
done here is we've we've built the
fundamental understanding that now can
move into some of these more upto-date
kazuchi solutions that Fujitsu offers
all all around the world and so I want
to make the point that it's worth
investing sometimes even when what you
do is ultimately overtaken by technology
um I think I'll skip over that
one well we've moved to in the fusion
cell within the the Center for Cognitive
technologies that I've I run now is
investing in showing the value of new
technologies from Partners so um
productivity and transformation in the
Long Hall of adoption so for example
there are studies like this that show
the jagged Frontier of AI capabilities
um working in this case with um Boston
the Boston Consulting Group with this
wasn't us this is a study from the wton
business school if I recall correctly
showing that when Boston Consulting
Group Consultants worked with chat GPT
they could produce complete 12% more
tasks 25% faster 40% increase in quality
the point here is not the detail the
point is that this translates into real
world terms the advantages of adopting
emerging Technologies another one here
that shows how you can be much more
creative by using llms what we're
investing in now is not just the new
technologies but partner Technologies
with our customers to produce studies
like these that will be out in the next
12 months that will show when you use
this particular solution here is the
very specific value that it creates but
here is how you're going to have to
change your organization to adopt it so
try to invest not just in R&D in the
technology but R&D in how the technology
is applied is just as crucial for
keeping up um just as crucial for
keeping up with the speed of te
technological advance and also you need
to invest sometimes in spinning out
things that will work better outside
than they will work inside so um many of
you will be familiar with the science of
super forecasting the idea that if you
take the median estima of a crowd
forecast it consistently outperforms
individual forecasts the idea that
humans when we assuming we're not a room
for the super forecasters when we make
forecasts we are no better than dart
throwing chimps we are no better than
chance we're about 50% accurate my
insight a while ago was that super
forecasting is is going to be the future
of forecasting but it's likely to be
driven in part by AI um and also the
fundamental problem we have is that we
often face our forecast in the wrong
direction if you're not forecasting the
right things they don't help to close
organizational blind spots but if you
bring collective intelligence the
science of human and machines thinking
together with the science of super
forecasting you can do fundamentally new
things in fundamental new ways so we
built a product called hive mind which
will likely spin out as a new business
it helps increase forecasting accuracy
by allowing you to ask better questions
to deliver better outcomes it both
crowdsource questions and increasingly
uses AI to generate the most important
questions associated with any given
outcome so it's an elicitation tool
first of all it cuts through corporate
strategy by saying what do you really
want to achieve you need to be specific
in what it is you're trying to achieve
and if you can tell me that I can then
run it through the crowdsourcing and AI
um engine I can break it into the top
five 10 or million factors for its
achievement and then I can use
forecasting both from Ai and super
forecasters to assign probabilities to
it what does that mean for you now it
allows you to put numbers on anything it
allows you to know like what probability
is it that I will achieve the outcome
that I want in a given time frame what
probability is it that these factors
that are crucial for that outcome will
resolve in the way that I want and then
can ask what if questions what if I did
this how would it change the likelihood
of success now we don't think about
decisions like that when we're in the
sea Suite or the um you know the command
group in the military or the private
office of a government department or
whatever you call that in the US um we
we tend to sit around the table there's
only ever so much diversity around that
table that you cannot have all the
diversity you need so you won't have
enough lenses on the problem whereas we
can bring that kind of um that kind of
divers customizable diversity profile we
can use both the AI and people we can
allow you put numbers on anything and we
can allow you to do it to your adversary
or your competitor strategy to
understand what you could do to
maximally um reduce their chances of
success how does it work well it's an
elicitation tool so it elices the
decision makers desired outcomes it's an
aggregation call tool it allows you to
gather diverse Insight um to understand
what the most important questions and
factors are for the achievement of your
outcome and then ultimately it's a
divination tool in that it will help you
to spot factors and and ways of
achieving your goal that you would never
have thought
of a little proof point for some of the
things that we've been able to do within
that program we entered metaculus is um
so the world's largest crowd sourcing
platform they ran a forecasting
tournament for Bots for AIS we built an
ensembl of bots we entered it you can
see Fujitsu researcher there number one
we won that competition the distance
between us and second place is the same
as the distance between second place and
sixth place if you want to imagine what
that kind of a win looks like imagine
Usain Bolt crossing the 100 meter Finish
Line and how far everybody else usually
is behind him it's a useful visual image
for understanding just how successful we
were we were able to cover questions
across such a huge range so question
will the Chicago White Socks lose 124
games in the 2024 MLB baseball season
that was asked on the 16th of September
at the time humans were betting 75% yes
Cassie our bot bet no and the result was
no the point I want to make here also is
that as a Brit my team had absolutely no
idea about baseball but by calibrating
the bot we were able to get a really
accurate forecast and look at the
breadth here I'll sort of dance through
these a bit because the detail matters
less but the the breadth of things here
where we outperformed where the bot
outperformed humans is really
significant so this was 300 measles
cases being reported in the United
States in 2024 then really obscure like
more Spanish Wikipedia articles than two
million by October the 1st like who who
knows that but the bot got a much better
estimate than humans did um a really
consequential one will Intel get dropped
from the Dow Jones Industrial Average
before October the 1st
2024 will Russia control po rosk before
October the 1st 2024 humans thought it
thought they would Cassie said no Cassie
was right um and then here 28%
incidentally is a threshold in the
German election so will alternative for
deuts land a far-right party in in
Germany get more than 208% less than 30
in the brandenberg state election people
bet no Cassie bet yes answer was yes the
point there is that we're now moving
into an era where we can generate 2,500
predictions forecasts in one day against
any outcome that you want we can assign
probabilities we can put numbers on
things you could never put numbers on
before and the point I want to make in
that huge sort of Tor Reon in just just
15 minutes that your R&D strategy can't
be one thing some of the things that you
build will be overtaken and pivot and
need to be Amalgamated some of the
things you need to focus on how you
create value and some of the things on
the far side of that are really going to
revolutionize how we make decisions and
I think that we have built one of those
and I'm looking forward to exploiting it
in the months ahead any thanks
thank you um we'll now um try to have
some questions how will the Innovations
from your research be deployed or
commercialized through the HQ team of
fuk well so if I take the example of
cibil that that project reached the end
of its life in the UK um under um Al
Brown I'd like to give full credit to
her because it was him that led that and
did an incredible job so cibil um for
for what we would Now call retrieval
augmented um generation
the idea of using graphs to improve the
performance of llms he finished that
work he handed it off to Fujitsu
research in India who were doing not to
similar work to us they then integrated
it into homes my understanding is that
all of that work is now in Fujitsu HQ
and being used to directly inform the
work that the global Corporation is
doing with Co coh and sakuna Ai and
others and the point I wanted to make is
that is that when you do these kind of
things like sometimes it doesn't get
commercialized directly as a new product
or a new service sometimes it goes in
and the knowhow becomes what's really
valuable into the next thing that you do
and as a large corporation you just need
to accept that so that's one specific
example they they all have slightly
different stories and we'll take up the
whole five minutes if I try and tell
them all but that's a that's a good one
thank you and next question what did you
learn from your research being disrupted
by open
AI so one of one of the things I think
we learned and I talk about a lot is if
if you if you accept that right now we
need some new information we need some
evidence that scaling laws have peaked
because if they continue we are on a
path to AI like you need new information
now there are some people betting
against the saying no no current
architectures have reached their their
maximum but there's no evidence that
that's the case and until there is we
should probably expect the trend to
continue so so I think the main thing I
learned was a kind of um perspiration on
Palms moment of like right now we really
are on a path to AGI and and and if
you're not betting on it you're betting
against it and if you're betting against
it you better hope you're right so um
increasingly in in what I do and I speak
in a personal capacity here but in the
things that we do I'm trying to think
okay well how how do we make sure that
if AGI were to arrive on the timelines
that I discussed we would be ready for
it because if you're not betting on it
you're betting against it and and that
would be that would be my primary lesson
is is the pace of Change Is Such don't
bet against it and assume it's
continuing and then uh try and build
your plans
accordingly and how much do you think
collaboration with generative AI is
limited by the current um constraints on
real time and realistic user
experiences that's interesting I I think
I'm going to challenge the question
Gabriel wherever you are I'm afraid I
think that the primary constraint is not
about real time and realistic user
experiences it's about changing how we
make decisions I think most most
organizations are used to just having um
well in the military we talk about
bogats a bunch of guys sat around a
table I don't I don't know if that's a
socially acceptable way of describing it
these days but uh like most decisions
that's that's how they're that's how
they're made and what you need is to be
much more reliant on data and evidence
and interrogating the logic and an AI
drives rigor into decision- making that
frankly is just absent in most large
organizations both government and
corporate so I think it's not really
real time and realistic user experiences
that limit our adoption of generative AI
It's a combination of risk aversion um
and kind of calcified practice that
nobody wants to change because that
would mean re redesigning so much more
about your organization than many people
are prepared to but my argument would be
well if you're not betting on AGI you're
betting against it and if you're betting
on it you should start transforming your
organization now
thank you um we'll do one last question
uh is there a first step to jump into
Innovation that you would recommend to
fellow industry innovators yeah um
despite what I've said about the speed
of change I gave a talk and wrote some
stuff on this earlier this year so I I
think when the speed of Advance is such
as it currently is trying to follow
means all you're going to do is fall
fall further and further behind right
like it's like trying to follow an
Olympic sprint around the track they're
faster than you and you're not going to
keep up so if all you're doing is
following Tech Trends in what you do
you're you're probably going to lose I
think you have to do what the US did
with ass salt breaker um in in Dara in
the 1970s you have to say like what what
do we need what's our theory of Victory
how are we going to win in 2030 I think
Jeff bezels talks about working
backwards as a kind of commercial
example like where are we going to be in
say 2030 what and therefore what
technologies are we going to need to win
if that's where we think we're going to
be and start building technology now so
a kind of neat micros script for saying
that you need an R&D strategy
that starts by building technologies
that don't currently exist against a
very clear theory of winning how are we
going to achieve competitive advantage
in for example 2030 because following
Tech Trends is not going to work and the
problem is in most large organization
following Tech Trends is safer trying to
bet on technologies that already exist
you can explain to senior exx well
here's why you should invest whereas
betting in really high-risk um new areas
is much harder to persuade investment
committees to hand you money over for
but I think it's essential otherwise you
are just going to fall further and
further behind
thank you very much Keith for your
interesting talk