so uh hello everyone my name is Emanuel
Ceres I'm the co-founder and CEO of
molon and uh we're an MIT spin off um uh
producing carbon negative fuels and
chemicals today uh both myself and my
co-founder are both alumni as well as um
um uh staff uh we de we developed this
technology and licens it from uh from
MIT
oops there we go so um that's the last
one there we go so um the world um needs
uh Liquid Green fuels to decarbonize
hard to Abate sectors uh that cannot
Electrify these are sectors like
shipping and Aviation um but also uh
chemicals and fertilizer production the
problem is that no one really knows how
to produce these um liquid green fuels
and chemicals um for a reasonable cost
we address this issue at Anolon by also
uh reducing methane emissions uh because
we essentially use wasted resources on
site that we convert to um to these uh
liquid fuels that can be put in a truck
and taken to Market we start with feed
stock like uh biog gas and landfill gas
from um agricultural or municipal waste
uh we also can uh use industrial gases
and we use our portable and mod
chemical plant to convert them on site
this way we're addressing both a
trillion Doll Market that accounts for
15% on the hard to Abate sector side the
liquid uh fuels and chemicals side but
also 20% of global Emissions on the
methane
side I guess I'll do
this oh it's it's this button of course
yeah yeah there we go the big one um so
the the issue however with um you know
harvesting these methane resources on
site is that conventional technology is
not really designed to be coste
effective at this scale conventional
process technology uses economies of uh
of scale it uses one-off designs and
therefore when you try to do something
on a landfill or uh or a farm uh a few
ttimes per day you result in more than
25 years of uh of
payback by comparison Enon technology
can be can achieve a four-year payback
um on site this without any subsidies
this is at market prices for the fuels
um uh this is at for eight tons of
product from 300,000 Scuf per day of of
gas we achieve this by essentially
repurposing internal combustion engines
as small scale compressors and reactors
this is the technology that we developed
with MIT and this allows us to
effectively build a 40 foot container um
chemical plant that is portable and
modular and can be placed next to this
low cost feed stock without the need for
infrastructure
methanol is an established Market $40
billion um used for several different
things such as chemicals and Plastics
however it has been growing um
exponentially as a potential green fuel
for shipping where more than 250 vessels
have already converted to run on green
methanol uh but also potential feed
stock for Aviation there's plenty of um
uh feed stock wasted methane emissions
from just landfills and agriculture not
even including the industrial emissions
in the US to power most of the global um
demand for uh green methanol by 2030 a
$70 billion
Market this is an example a case study
of how Enon is helping both reducing
emissions and generating revenue for a
customer we just announced a partnership
with Monto Renewables on a landfill in
Houston where we're taking flared
landfill gas about a million scuff per
day um and converting it into more than
6 million um worth of um uh shipping
fuel methanol shipping fuel on site
eliminating emissions both on the uh
methane side as well as the shipping
side we're about to announce this New
York um listed shipping
company we started in 2021 um appr the
technology buildt a beautiful 5,000 foot
facility and scaled it up uh we now just
announced our pilot and next year we're
going to a first of aind commercial unit
and we have signed agreements for more
than 10 million Scuf per day uh by 2026
six as well as the off take which is
more than 60 million uh in
Revenue we have lots of um um industrial
Partnerships both on the gas supply side
working with RNG companies large engine
companies um many shipping uh players uh
but as well as U uh grants for many uh
established government
agencies however we're always looking
for more Partners um uh so if you are in
the waste space either industrial
emission
um municipal or agricultural waste
emissions if you're a user or producer
or Trader of green chemicals in shipping
Aviation heavy industry uh please reach
out to us we have a booth we have a
beautiful facility about 30 minutes away
here so come and talk to us and together
let's change the future of green
chemical manufacturing thank you