hi everyone I'm Samy shalabi MIT Alum
and uh founder and CTO of Maven AGI
where we're reimagining customer
experience through AI
agents customer experience is really
really
broken if any of you remember a good
customer experience raise your hand that
you've ever had with a vendor it's a
universally very
challenging uh uh environment to be able
to create great customer first off it's
insanely
expensive we've canvased hundreds and
hundreds of Enterprise organizations and
asked them how much does it cost you to
support your customers universally the
number that comes back it's an average
of $40 a ticket $40 to handle a support
ticket where in general most people are
frustrated with the overall experience
you take that to other parts of customer
experience like customer success every
interaction is over
$100 this is not this is not because the
organizations are not trying to create a
great experience it's because it's a
complicated experience it's got numerous
handoffs the systems are fragmented
there's a lot of lack of Automation and
there's just a ton of really bad
self-service tools on average a support
agent needs to use six systems to be
able to answer any question that
typically comes
in what we're building at Maven are AI
agents imagine if you contact support
and the person talking to you knows
everything about you everything about
the company and is a domain expert and
not only is telling you how to do stuff
is personalizing the experience and is
able to take actions on your behalf to
solve your problems we are a we are
building AI that can do that
in support so how can these AI agents be
used in support and there are three
highlevel use cases for users for our
customers customers uh you can use AI
agents to help drive a self-service
experience where users are able to solve
their own problems that drives an
increase in ticket deflection Which is
less human agents less cost and more
self-service and faster time to uh uh
service
for agents the folks on the other side
AI agents can be used to help with
assist agents to actually solve the the
tickets and in this in in in this
experience it helps for drive at uh uh
agent efficiency and it drives better
consistency for all users submitting
these tickets and then lastly for uh uh
support leaders using AI agents you're
able to understand the state of your
support environment when you have
hundreds and hundreds in some case some
of our customers millions of tickets
it's very hard to figure out what's what
and where the issues are and using AI
we're able to categorize and organize
and present a unified view of where the
issues are ultimately driving better
issue visibility and Al ultimately
fitting it back to the solution and and
and really solving these customer
issues so let's look at a real example
in this case this is a personalized chat
agent that was embedded into a SAS
product and in this case the maven agent
is loaded it see it's able to retrieve
the user's profile and figure out that
the user needs uh to verify their
profile so this is very turning support
into not just a self-service but a
proactive experience and then the
customer asks the question why do I need
to verify and is able to answer that
question in a fairly unified way
ultimately reducing uh the need to
deflect the
ticket this is another example
where the user's trying to perform an
action and hasn't been able to figure
out out and this is using our full full
page chat experience similar to chat gbt
where the user says I just want to
change permissions it's able to
disambiguate well there are two people
with the first name Sammy and the user
is able to select and then the action is
and removing all the complexity
necessary to navigate complicated
products let's look at a different
example in the case of helping agents
this is an example of the maven coil it
coexisting inside of zenis we support
every desk there is Salesforce fresh Des
send uh uh slack twio every kind of
support system out there and the
co-pilot coexists in this experience in
this particular example the the ticket
came in Spanish the or the agent only
speaks English and answer is generated
in Spanish and translated to
English and the agent is able to edit
the answer in English and it's
automatically translated back to Spanish
and when we've talked to many of our
customers uh the multi- language use
case is is where this the costs are
astronomically High English to English
is usually about $40 anything in any
foreign language typically runs around
$120 per ticket at
least and finally AI driven analytics to
help understand overall efficiency and
we have dashboards not only is it just
about solving the problem is mayen
working for you but giving you Insight
we automatically categorize tickets
compute nps's it slice and dice the data
so you have true visibility into your
overall support
experience and these these are some of
the results we've we've had with our
Enterprise customers we' processed
millions of tickets now um uh on average
our AI agents are able to handle
93% of support questions without
humans and the typical savings is 80%
and we've had significant increases in
resolution times uh uh and we've pretty
much integrated with everything out
there and we're happy to integrate with
more and we have uh uh quite a bit of
large Enterprise customers that are
really happy with our solution this is
uh uh open AI saw the work we were doing
with Trip Advisor and if you go open.com
there is a detailed case study around
the work that we've done with Trip
Advisor where in their case they were
able to answer 90% of their incoming
queries without
humans if you are looking to improve
your overall support experience cut cost
we're open for business we're excited to
work across Industries and we're we we
can see you around the corner thank you