I decided to pursue [music] the energy
studies minor because I really care
about combating climate change and
helping the environment. [music]
I feel like my major in mechanical
engineering really helps me on the
technical side of learning about [music]
energy conversion and how to make
systems more efficient, whereas my
energy studies minor really helps fill
in some gaps in regards [music] to
economics and policies. To me,
mechanical engineering is really about
[music] solving problems and creating
something new. To do so, an energy
problem I'd like to be a part of [music]
solving is a transition from using
fossil fuels to using renewables, as
[music] well as learning how to optimize
our existing energy systems. That way,
the energy we use can be both clean and
efficient, and we're not using more than
what we need.