Fusion energy is sort of a miraculous
solution um in some ways to our energy
problem um once we figure out uh all the
engineering challenges to it.
[Music]
It's able to provide uh clean energy um
with a virtually unlimited fuel source
which is hydrogen. It can be turned on
at any time which is its advantage over
um other energy sources such as uh
renewables. I am working on uh additive
manufacturing which is metal 3D printing
to help advance fusion energy by
manufacturing key components with more
specialized materials which are suitable
for the extreme environments which
fusion energy must be produced. 3D
printing allows for the use of more
specialized alloys such as this NASA
alloy which has high strength at high
temperatures. I was interested in fusion
energy because to me it's sort of at the
intersection of two areas that I'm very
interested in which is physics and
engineering. I really enjoy this work
because um I love tinkering with things
like 3D printers. something I can design
on my computer can be in my hands. That
brings me a lot of joy.