good afternoon
everyone good afternoon
everyone all right well clearly we need
to be serving better coffee in the uh in
the lobby to our our friends at ILP um
really excited to be with you this
afternoon and to um engage in this panel
um a lot of the talks that you've been
hearing today have been exploring the
technical aspects of sustainability how
can we improve the technical
characteristics of our manufacturing
processes our mining processes
um some of the critical things that
drive the environmental footprint that
they were all so concerned about um and
I loved the last question in the in the
last session about what will it take to
get some of these ideas from the lab
bench to commercial feasibility and
Commercial scale so that's really going
to be the emphasis of what we're talking
about in this session is the business of
sustainability how can we create
solutions that that for which there's a
strong business case where we can align
the profitability of our Enterprises
with tackling these big social and
environmental challenges that's the
center central question of our work at
the MIT St sustainability initiative um
and it's going to be the focus of our
conversation um and to do that we've got
a really cool um fireside chat that
we've planned and I'll welcome Demitrius
and mahes to the stage um and what the
the design of this is that we have a um
both an industrial company and a
financial company um to get in in to get
us into this topic of the business case
the financial case for sustainability
and what we're going to do is dig into
the questions about um how can what what
is the current state of play in terms of
the business case for sustainability
which are the projects that are getting
us a positive Roi in both financial and
um and impact terms and what can the
capital markets and investors who are
seeking that kind of return what role
can they play in helping to make these
Solutions work um so welcome to the
stage uh Demetrius and mahes thank you
so much both of you for being here thank
you for the invitation um and so first
I'm just going to ask you both to just
in give us a little sense of who you are
where you sit what uh what's the purview
of your work okay thank you
everyone and so my name Dimitri Bonos
I'm the Chief Information and Innovation
officer of for real public TR company in
the naspac Netherland in Spain we are a
global infrastructure player with
different capabilities covering the
overall value chain of the
infrastructure development from the
Inception of an early design that could
be approach with the needs of a
community of an state or a country to
the design Finance construction and
operation of large type of Assets in
particular airports we have been doing
decades in charge of hro we are right
now H investing um remodeling the new
terminal one in in in in JFK highways
all across the the world and energy and
transversally we have the construction
capability in order to interoperate all
those asset we are expanding towards all
the continents and putting a lot of
focus in us where many of the large
asset that you are um interacting as
user um are potentially developed by us
including data center during the last 10
10 years oh data centers yeah data
center people may not have thought about
Federal as being involved in that kind
of infrastruct digital infrastructure we
have leveraged that value chain from the
construction we have been building data
center for many clients including the
hypercal and right now what we are
putting in common all the pieces with a
wider perspective than trying to
introduce many of what we have commented
today know how to expand the life or
repurpose an existing data center
introducing Effectiveness in all the
steps in the value chain from the energy
regeneration from the pure operation
from the adoption of a digital schin
that is allowing us to simulate
different scenarios without affecting
the real environment and data center is
an amazing playground in order to put in
value all those capabilities okay so and
and Ferro is involved in design build
operate of all these different kinds of
infrastructures you just and finance an
important piece because at the very
early stage um to finance required to
the risk all the potential
um unknown situation mainly with a 30 40
50 years many occasions um typically the
resiliency of a physical asset is not
allowing to adapt to the evolution of
technological changes of the innovation
no how to introduce some Factor when you
are running the business case under the
affection of the um policy at that
moment is is is implying and trying to
foresight what would be the evolution of
technology in order to intr use properly
in the business case it's really
relevant no if you are not completely
sure to make the infrastructure
resilient enough in order to be
adaptable without the necessity to
introduce more CeX it's also an
important piece that we should introduce
as much as possible and we are trying to
make resilient H infrastructure able to
be prepared and ready to adapt new
technologies along the life the lifetime
great thank you uh mahes you want to
give us some coordinates no absolutely
and I'm glad it's I love the fact that
Jay tried to wake you up so I know we're
one session away from drinks so bear
with us and thank you for hanging in
there I know it's been a long day but a
fascinating day um uh my name is mahes
jumar I head up uh fixed income
sustainability research for a company
called MFS uh Investment Management
Massachusetts Financial Services we're
celebrating our 100 Years and we're
right across the river um you can
literally see our building from MIT
which is very cool and um I'm also glad
to be back at my alma model so it's
really nice to be back in these hallowed
grounds and listening to all the
professors and and the postdocs and and
graduate students talk about some of the
cool research that they're doing so when
when I listened to the talks today it
was interesting when I just I know I
purposely brought the programming and
all the panels and what was fascinating
to me was these are probably the same
conversations that we are having with
our invested companies be it if we own
the stock of these companies like we own
stock in foval for example it's a public
company um or the bonds of these
companies because we provide financing
and what was interesting is when I think
about all these themes in terms of
Transportation hydrogen nuclear um
decarbonizing transport it's uh sorry
Trucking it's fascinating right this is
the academic side of the commercial
slide as Jay rightly pointed out um uh
what is interesting to us is where as a
mainstream asset manager
we're not necessarily um you can imagine
a VC or a PE that's trying to fund early
these sorts of commercial relation at a
very early mezzanine stage but we
certainly buy um um uh equities and
fixed income once these companies are
either private and issue bonds are able
to do so in a commercial scale you can
imagine this the typically the smallest
Bond size that a company should uh can
issue that we can buy is roughly in the
order of $300 million that's much bigger
than an a average round AN a b or c
round that you might see that one of you
needs to get this technology off the
ground but nevertheless asset managers
like us play an extremely important role
in providing capital in the form of debt
and Equity financing to ensure that
companies can can raise the funding
needed to commercialize everything we're
learning about today so um we play one
small part of that as a public asset
manager yeah yeah I mean in a way if if
we think about you know the MIT startup
exchange is part of the mix of today's
event right and over in the Next Room
we've got a few startups here um and so
we could I I often think of it sort of
like a three-legged stool right which is
that you need the technologies that are
coming out of those startups um most of
those Technologies are B2B right so you
need the customers for those
technologies that are going to provide
the advanced purchase commitments and so
on that are going to get them off the
ground and that means um serious climate
and sustainability equipments by big
companies who are going to be their
customers um and then the Third Leg of
the stool is the financing which as you
said um I I like how you put that that
that there's um part of that is the is
the risk Capital that's needed to lift
the startups off the ground but there's
also the capital and the influence of
capital over the incumbent companies to
help them um along along the journey um
so and you're you're not an impact
investor right MFS is a traditional
financial institution you're helping
Pension funds make sure they're going to
get their long-term obligations met um
so you're really looking for a financial
return so what is the space right now of
profitable sustainability work right I
think that's that's sort of the question
that's on our minds and federal I mean
you this is one particular window but
where are you finding in the projects
that you do that there is the tightest
alignment between the the financial
business case let's say and the the
sustainability objectives there are many
bar that have the target of the
carbonization in 20 30 years and we are
seeing the opportunity wi of acting as
enabler and catalyzer of that transition
for example Energy Efficiency different
type of asset the adoption of new
mechanism at a scale to decarbonize a
bitumin plant could convert that plant
and extend the life spam another 20
years being more efficient reducing
dramatically the conception of um
nonrenewable fuels and at the same time
creating a reference that the side
effect of the heat could be used for
another collateral industry that was not
in that Industrial Area no to approach
with that view in front of a problem is
raising the opportunities for a
profitable business for example to
manage an orchestrate at the scale the
the street lighting of a big city MH
it's a demand it's a public need but if
Beyond the adoption of L that is
something massively implanted we are
adopting um AI in order to simulate and
to adapt with the support of iot um
localize small um Edge servers how to
adapt in a more seamless way you are
creating an efficiency that is reverting
to the city itself and it is becoming a
business where we need to incorporate as
much as possible H technology that could
improve that no so there are so in both
of those examples the bitchman plant
that's making the materials for our
roads and the street lights right in
both of those situations the business
cases I'm going to save energy I'm going
to save money um which is maybe kind of
the oldest business case in the book for
sustainability efforts and what I'm
hearing you say is that there's a NE the
current gener because we were talking
about that since 2005 right um but the
next generation of that is the
application of iot and AI to identify
those opportunities and kind of get to
the at is the the new trend is is
improving incrementally the efficiency
of what we were doing for for years or
for decades there is another example in
the early stage definition of new
materials and if we are able to deploy
in the concrete base or in the pavement
of a big road and a specific type of
material that is able to self heal or
it's able to reduce the friction with
the roads or even to to improve the way
of the the the road um are managed
during the winter with the perspective
of the overall lifespan of that road we
are reducing dramatically the Opex so we
are introducing in the design specific
materials or capabilities to improve the
longevity the longevity at the same time
reduce the carbon footprint and in one
case in the scope two but if we are
talking about the cars and the
consumtion of of the cars um that is
directly connected with the with a scope
three um so let me so let's explore this
example so this is you're saying that
there are um changes to the material
properties of the concrete and Roads
that can improve their longevity and
therefore we don't need to do as much
repair replacement of the materials and
therefore we can reduce the footprint of
the whole thing yep um and so we can see
how we can save that money in Opex over
time is there a higher first cost for
that material than the default like is
it a more expensive material to
implement in the beginning that that's
the the the situation that we need to
compound with
a lifetime perspective no in our case we
have the advantage that the
externalities of a potential higher cost
is introduced in the overall business
case and through the financing of
factors like the one he represent we are
able to pay potentially an extra at the
beginning but be sure that that is going
to be beneficial H to us to the scope
three of the drivers that are going to
consume less in their own Vehicles
probably it's going to generate less
noise and that's going to have a
positive impact in the areas where we
are deploying the infrastructure and at
the end those externalities are very
important to be but if they're
externalities they're hard to capture in
the business case right so if I'm if I'm
running I get like if I'm a city and I'm
running the roads and I don't have to do
as much Road repair I'm going to save
that money on my balance sheet of course
but if the drivers on those roads are
saving fuel because the road is more
efficient to drive on they're getting to
save that money it's not necessarily AC
crewing to me um so that's doesn't that
sort of weaken the business case for the
city manager who's doing the deployment
of that technology no but at the end we
have the responsibility also to
progressively reduce the scope three and
externalities and every time we are
deploying any piece of infrastructure
with that commitment in terms of the
sustainability of the overall life cycle
1% could be in standard basis the CO2
generation during the construction and
we are reducing systematically with many
Technologies the rest 99% is directly
connected with the maintenance operation
but basically is the consumption of the
cars and assuming that we are going to
progressively balance the combustion
with the electric to introduce during
the process measures that will reduce
the Opex but at the same time we have an
advantage for the future users yes I
think is the three as that we are trying
to combine yeah right right just so so
if I just put this question to the
audience for a second how many of you
have seen projects where that have this
characteristic where there's a higher
first cost but it's going to pay itself
off over time if I really were able to
do life cycle costing it would make
sense but sometimes it's hard to get
that initial first cost done just raise
your hand if you've seen projects that
are have that characteristic okay um so
that that's essentially a um a finance
problem right because I want to shift uh
money over time that's like your whole
business right so how can
the investors how can financial
institutions support faster adoption of
this kind of approach that's a great
question I and if you followed um what
Demetrius just said there were some
important things to pick up on that he
talked about capex upfront investment he
talked about Opex you know continuous uh
maintenance if you will and Savings in
terms of costs as well as Savings in
terms of carbon right scope two and
scope three so scope one as a company is
what um I generate from my own
operations scope two is emissions
associated with power and energy use and
scope three is is emissions associated
with product use and and everything else
in the value chain so when you think
about that and and Jason asked so what
do I need to do to give you the
necessary capex the large payment
upfront that will hopefully pay for
itself it's that's exactly what a bond
is Right which is exactly why fixed
income financing drives the world world
I tease somebody I I was telling
somebody that especially in United
States I live in a town six miles from
here I take the train I have water in my
faucet everything happens because of
bonds life happens because of bonds both
at a company level and at a city level
and a county and state level so that's
exactly why this world of ESG themed
financing came about in back in 2007
2008 was this concept of green bonds
which is you can issue a green Bond and
show the investors exactly what you're
going to do with the use of proceeds um
we provide The Upfront financing and
then they pay the coupon over the life
of the project back to the fixed income
um investors so that's the whole idea
and that's why there's so much talk
about scaling up um transition Finance
climate lending using the bond markets
and using a combination of Green Loans
green bonds sustainable bonds Etc and
it's exact the heart of what a very
practical problem that fovel has and
what Jason just described but butes how
are we doing with green bonds and
sustainability linked bonds right
because I feel like you know there's
that famous drawing of the hype cycle
right where it's like things get hyped
and then you sort of then then they kind
of we find out that there's they're not
as big or effective as we thought they
were so the hype cycle goes down and
then there's this kind of increasing
ramp where we then actually sort it out
and get it to work so with green bonds
and sustainability link bonds where are
we in that hype cycle a it's a good
question I mean so if you look at the
cumulative size of the ESG I call the
ESG theme bond market right that's green
bonds social bonds sustainable bonds and
something called sustainability linked
bonds right and there's a little bit of
differences in each one of them um that
if you look at the total cumulative
issuance of that those four types of
bonds over the past 10 years roughly or
even 15 it's roughly at about $4
trillion worth of outstanding right $4
trillion of cumulative issuance if you
consider 2021 as PSG CU everything went
downhill after that and and if you use
that as your barometer of ptsg that year
we had close to a trillion and a half in
issuance so that's a high Watermark if
you will last year we had about 850
billion is in in ESG themed issuance and
I think we've kind of hit steady state
you know so it cut in half yeah and now
so that that that's a pretty good graph
of that hypee cycle right absolutely now
if you think you you think the
subsequent years are going to sort of be
in a similar trajectory I think the if
you look at estimates from from the cell
side as well as Nos and think tanks um
you will roughly see that the the
cumulative is I mean the annual issuance
is going to probably settle at a
trillion just slightly above a trillion
which makes sense because that's the the
ability to absorb the market now what if
you go talk to the policy makers they
want that trillion to ramp up even more
yes right because depending on what
estimate you look at you need 300
trillion through 2050 for the transition
MH you can look at McKenzie's estimate
World economic Forum any of these
estimates regardless of what number it's
trillions of dollars over the next 10 20
30 40 years and so the call has always
been can we ramp up these sorts of ESG
issuance in order to meet that need if
you assume that Equity markets are
tapped out and flat or um what the C's
and PS are doing in terms of the
capacity now the one new innovation in
the markets in the financial markets
that is changing this is this concept of
private credit of of those of you in
finance have seen the rise of private
credit funds in private credit um that
are riskier than conventional fixed
income uh it's direct lending uh direct
fixed income lending to an Enterprise
typically small companies small
companies in certain sectors so and the
private credit Market has also grown
roughly to a trillion and a half and the
the idea not sustainability link just
general in general exactly and the idea
there is that the blackstones of the
world and the Apollos of the world and
Aries capitals of the world who run that
market are also very well suited as
infrastructure investors to help with
the transition so my hope is that plus
the green Bond plus normal financing and
we're talking about costs of capital
that are 4% 8% like where where what
zone are we in here the 7% 6 to 8% like
you said and and is 6 to 8% um cost of
capital does that get you in in a
ferrovial project does that cost of
capital get you to where you want to go
in terms of being able to implement the
sustainable technologies that we were
talking about earlier so we have been
recurrently very high demanding in the
return that we are giving back to our
investor no even before being public
here in in the NASA during the last 10
years where currently we have been
giving back an average around 11% of
higher r so we're putting our own Equity
that is giving us in the game we are
obviously using those instruments we are
approaching the projects in a moment
where typically there is a very high
risk there is risk of demand risk of the
construction risk of the technology that
we are using there are few probably
companies that are compounding all those
factors and that's the reason we are
introducing our our Equity bringing to
the market certainty in those dimensions
and when Al the construction has been
finished and we are operating that asset
there are other instruments more
standard less volatile and super
structure conceiving and incorporating
in the taxonomy more and more those ESG
type of characteristic and that's the
moment where we are opening the
description explaining in in in detail
and managing the asset for 40 50 70
years I mean this topic of risk taking
in infrastructure is absolutely critical
right because a lot of these
technologies that we might be excited
about in this room um run into a huge
wall which is the risk aversion of
established companies established uh you
know the infrastructure projects so do
you feel like Federal relative to other
um infrastructure providers is able to
take more of that technology risk let me
give you um one short answer coming to
to our origin the name of the company
very difficult to be pronounced probably
in English ferial double a um is
connected with a um pivotal moment no at
the beginning of our our birth 72 years
ago we took an
IP um in order to accelerate the
construction of rail track and we were
able to build from outside Madrid to
Madrid 30 kilometers in 30 Days 1
kilometer per day 72 kilo years ago no
translated to nowadays if we want to
assess and manage the risk we need to
use technology we need to use data and
we need to digitalize the infrastructure
iify the infrastructure H simulate all
the scenarios and that is reducing
potentially kind of a digital twin type
of digital twins sensorized but even
during the design stage no so that risk
has to be modeled has to be compound and
has to be taken in in in consideration
and this is one of our strength we are
much more eager to to introduce new
technologies we need to understand that
the regulatory framework the insurance
Market many other externality that have
to be compound inside of the equation
have to also be adapted to the necessity
know we were talking before about
modifying the boundary conditions of how
we transmit energy in the middle of
amazonas or the desert of atakama it
will be ideal to introduce something
reducing the cost and being and CO2 more
efficient no but do we have the right
the right environment in order to digest
independently of the risk yes that
pivotal change so that so that business
case depends on the ability the
availability of the insurance the policy
incentives and the insurance the
regory market the legal framework in our
case being Global there is a lot of
asymmetry between the the policies in
Europe against us and in the state level
no and to approach at a global scale
with a novel technology trying to create
synergies many occasion is blocked
because the lack of yes consistency of
the policies across different areas we
are using in in several domains the more
I would say proactive policy structure
in order to make test validate put the
signature as an industrial partner to
reinforce The credibility of one
technology and from there try to
reinforce scale H yes scenarios to
deploy a technology and to convert it in
the bre and B got it um just a quick
reminder for the audience to um use the
QR code to pose any questions and those
will start to feed up here for us so we
can um begin to um make sure we we we we
get what's on your minds
um this challenge about um having the
right supportive policy environment and
having consistent policy environments to
do that um this is a recurring theme
right and and part of what it means is
that um firms need to have both a market
strategy for getting their um projects
and products to Market but also a
non-market strategy meaning the ability
to engage with policy makers to help set
rules of the game that are going to make
it possible um to get things out out out
into the world and so if we think about
that three-legged three legs of the
stool like that I was mentioning before
the startups the companies the investors
those are sitting on a platform which is
the the the the operating environment
that that supports it and um what what
are we do that that that policy
environment has itself been volatile
right um like you said mahes we had to
Peak ESG in 2021 there's been these
backlashes we feel like obviously we
have in in the US we have an election
coming up in a couple of weeks um which
do you what do you think um what's your
sense of which of the currents are going
to stay flowing in the right direction
to support this kind of um sustainable
infrastructure and sustainable business
and where do we feel like there's noise
and headwinds that are getting in our
way it's it's a good question and I mean
if you think about the cycle the virtual
cycle of where where a company such as
fovial and we're an investor a public
asset manager such as us fit in the
equation the idea the rate of the idea
with this is the following right that
government sets policy in terms of hey
we need more financing towards the
transition how do we do that so they set
the policy the incentives the
Partnerships to get that going they then
set the regulatory bodies then set
disclosure mechanisms to say how is a
company um thinking about Technologies
sustainability in their strategy etc etc
so there standard bodies such as the
issb for example that's quickly becoming
um was the they subsumed what was known
as a sby the sustainab Accounting
Standards Board in order to in order for
companies to disclose their
sustainability mission in a in a
standard format which then investors
like us can use and then the idea is
that we then are able to channel and
show our end investors what kind of
sustainable Investments we have um using
regulation at a fund level for example
or or a vehicle level and then the idea
is that that increases transparency to
end users who say Okay I want to give my
money to this financing vehicle because
because they're helping fund the ferals
of the world and that virtuous cycle
then takes off and hopefully all of a
sudden you have Capital shifting to help
the transition that's what that's what
governments and Regulators want now what
happens is each of those parts of the
value chain has Kinks right regulation
can be extremely burdensome to the point
where there's a lack of clarity or it's
very dispersed across geographies um the
I always tell this I I God bless the
Europeans in the EU they're so far ahead
of Regulation when it comes to
sustainability but depending on who you
are it can also seem very honorous right
in terms of what your obligation is as a
fund manager for example well there's a
backlash even inside the EU right now
around some of it's globally you're
right um and then and then you mentioned
the word taxonomy and and a taxonomy in
the sustainability world is nothing but
helping investors basically disclose
which of the companies they own in their
financial portfolio
are indeed sustainable or doing
something from a sustainab perspective
so the big the big barrier there is
basically too much disclosure you know
or inadequate disclosure it's like
extremes right it's like how do you
clean what is required and then finally
we have to as asset managers satisfy the
needs of the regulator in terms of what
we're doing that we're not committing
greenwashing and claiming that we're um
we're greener than we are on the one
side on the other hand being transparent
in terms of hey this is why we funded
Ferro and this is why we include fer in
our portfolio so each parts of the value
chain that I talked about in terms of
how to drive transition financing you
know has needs to be improved and that's
exactly what if you go to sustainability
conferences for those of you who were in
The Pri the principles for responsible
investing conference just two weeks ago
in Toronto that's exactly what the
conversation was about asset managers
who depend on raising assets from asset
owners the big Pension funds how can
they each work to work with each other
using good regulation using good
disclosure to basically fund the
transition that's the that's the topic
dour yeah but the but the policy
environment isn't just about the
disclosure it's also just about direct
incentives right whether that's the um
subsidy the carrot approach of the
inflation reduction act or the stick
approach of a carbon price the adoption
of new technology that requires a m
stage in order to validate that good
scale no yeah that's important because
when we need to
anticipate five six seven years before
the production of the new asset
something that probably is not under the
right which me you have to be able to
predict what that policy environment is
going to be and and in the volatility of
politics right that means being able to
have things that are what does that mean
does that mean being able to have things
that are have a strong enough business
case regardless of where the policy
winds blow have have resilient business
case that is able to be improved with
decisions that will be clarified along
the way that resiliency in the
infrastructure to be more Dynamic along
the way even having options that are not
able to be triggered since the day one
is essential to reduce the risk to
improve the the yes the terms of the
business yeah we've gotten to zero
minutes on this timer here I don't I
think that means that we're we go to Q&A
or does that mean that we are going to
get hooked off the stage here uh but um
well can you take a couple questions
okay so let's take a couple of questions
um on the minds of folks in the audience
I don't know if we've they've come
through nothing's showing up here I'm
just seeing the QR code for Pigeon holes
I don't see any questions um so does
that mean that none have come through P
oh there's a bunch of questions okay um
yeah I'd have to see them oh great okay
cool um so a lot has been discussed on
how sustainability needs to be
profitable how do you see um risk
mitigation and opportunity enhancement
impacting decisions despite the near
future cost um and um and then what role
does Downstream pressure from corporate
customers with their own Net Zero
commitments play in the business case
for a sustainable investment I want to
pick up on this second question here so
um as companies are setting Net Zero
targets um that means that they're
searching for Solutions um and then and
and presumably that helps to create a
market for those Solutions but there's
all kinds of ways that can break down um
whether those commitments are not seen
as serious whether they don't translate
into purchasing commitments what role
are you seeing in terms of the
translation of Net Zero commitments to
purchasing commitments for the kinds of
things that you're offering um and the
seriousness of those of those types of
commitments in in the I can I can
quickly start out so what's interesting
is
that the when a a company's
sustainability plan is supposed to be
disclosed um not only as a the
sustainability document or annual
sustainability reports but increasingly
what we depend on as investors is
something called a climate action plan
an IAP right the idea is what is what
does your path look like for
decarbonizing and to Net Zero the issue
is sometimes is that there's not enough
content in the I to understand what
exactly that path looks like number one
number two when you ask companies so
tell me exactly how much are you
spending on decarbonization they don't
want to disclose it they don't want to
disclose it for competitive reasons they
just they give you an overall capex
number um that includes everything um
and sustainability but when you try to
pin them down to tell them just tell me
your sustainability spend in capex with
overall capex it's very hard to come by
so I don't know what Demetrius why
companies are hesitant to to be very
open about their capex for example on
sustainability yeah I think because
first of all the standard in the way you
measure sustainability are not commonly
spread when you are not using for that
new type of currency the same level of
rigor you could create like a gambling
game it is very trustable if you are a
public Trade Company the level of
scrutiny in all those measure is is
really really high no we are on a yearly
basis elevating our climate plan to our
share holders they need to approve if
that plan is robust enough is detailed
enough and it's not just representing
aspirational Target without any
actionable short-term uh plan the
granularity and the level of um
implementation that a large corporation
has to deploy in order to convert the
aspirational net zero to a plan that
progressively will be using the
resources of the policy new processes
technology and the Academia to be super
robust otherwise we will create in those
hype Cycles moments where you are not
able to track and to create traction
enough in order to commit with the with
the Target no thinking in the scope one
in our case is is an obsession and it's
something that we self-imposed in the
last 15 years but when we are talking
about what is the most difficult
challenge for everyone how to manage in
our case we have more than 40 50,000
suppliers to synchronize their own plans
in order to be emed in our own strategy
to guarantee that we are not running
ahead because we depend completely on
them is even more essential we have
suppliers in North Carolina South
Carolina or in Virginia that are not
seen with the same lens and with the
same sense of urgency how important is
for them we are not creating synergies
in the way we are using the data where
we we are using circular economy and the
re utilization of the material along the
pathway of a of a highway no and those
externalities will have to be
synchronized at the level of of the
ecosystem otherwise we are not going to
tackle the scope to and never the scope
three yeah yeah and and and there's a
lot of different um tools that companies
are using to um to to do to design that
kind of carbon strategy and they're
they're they're setting they're they're
defining Net Zero and different ways
they're very different in terms of their
seriousness of having a reduction
strategy um and and uh and they're
measuring with a great variety of
different mechanisms as we're learning
through our aggregate confusion project
at MIT Sloan um you know the the
measurement challenges here are are are
pretty substantial um I think we are
well out of time is that right um so
we're gonna we're going to cut this
short um but uh I I really appreciate
the chance to engage with both of you
and thanks to all the audience for for
uh for joining us staying awake cheers
[Applause]