last time. One of the things we we did
were we proved two mean value
inequalities.
So we proved two mean value inequality
and let me call those
And the first one was that. So if you
had a function f on some interval from a
to b into r and this function uh f is
differentiable.
Then it said that there exist some x0
with uh x0 between strictly between a
and b. So that the derivative
at x0 is equal to uh the average of the
function or the average of the function
at the end points. So this is the
average on the end points divide. So
it's it's average over the length of the
interval. So
so this is what the mean value theorem
said.
And then there was a second mean value
theorem and that was the cush mean value
theorem.
So the cushy bean museum
and that was where you had two functions
f and g
on this interval
into r and they are both assumed to be
differentiable.
And then again it was that there exist
some x0
strictly between
uh a and b.
And uh if you take the derivative
uh at x0 of f
times the value
uh the difference in value of G at the
end points.
Then this is equal to the derivative of
G at X0
times the difference in value of F at
the end points.
Right? So that was the Kushim man
theorem. So it was a little bit more
complicated than the actual minium
because you had two functions at the
same time and the point here was that
you could arrange this x0 to work for
both points for both functions.
Let me just make an observation
that if um so if we're looking at so so
so
right so the cushim seems like a more
elaborate version of the mean value
theorem and it really is because if you
if you suppose that g here was the
function
uh that is equal to x. So g of x is
equal to x.
I have f here on the integral from a to
b.
This is again differentiable.
Well, if the other function was just
this sort of rather trivial function G,
of course, G is also differentiable and
we even know that the derivative of G at
all points is one, right? So if you are
now applying the cushy mean then it say
that by the cushy mean
right? there exist some x0
with uh x0 strictly between a and b
and so that the derivative of f so
that's whatever that is that's the
derivative of f at x0
the value of g at these two end points
where g is just a function x so this is
just b minus a
and the derivative of g is one
h and then it's the difference in value
of f at the end point
right and so now if you just divide by b
minus a so this of course imply that
frime of x0 is equal to f of b minus f
of a divided by b minus a. So in other
words and so you see this here gives you
uh this here gives you this the more
standard mean value inequalities. So in
other words, the cushive mean man
theorem is more general than the than
than this mean value inequality, right?
Because you recover this if you just let
one of the two functions be just a
trivial function x, right?
Um
okay, so that was just an observation.
The second thing I want to talk about uh
is something we didn't get to uh last
time and this is uh this is this uh
op uh rule
and I'm just going to state one version
of it. There are two versions
and they're both in the notes but I will
just state one of them. Uh and so this
is so you have so the situation here is
that you have two function uh f and g
uh and they are defined on some interval
say from a to b into r
uh uh the interval does not include the
end point. Okay, so these are
differentiable.
Uh and then we assume that uh the limit
here we assume that g sorry uh of x is
uh and not only g of x but also g prime
of x
are not equal to zero for all
x.
And then we assume that the limit here
of g of x as x goes to a
that this here is zero. And the same
hold for the function
uh f.
So let's here
and then what you're interested in is
what you're interested in is that you're
interested in looking at uh f ofx
divided by g of x. Right? So this here
makes sense. g doesn't vanish. So this
here makes sense. And you are interested
in looking at this
fraction here
as x go to a right. If x go to a then
the denominator go to zero and the
nominator also go to zero right and the
question is does it has have a limit or
not right and so there's one more
assumption here that you need and that
is that um that if you're looking at the
Assume also
that uh that's the limit here uh as x go
to a
of frime of x / g prime assume that this
here exist
[Applause]
and is equal to some l. Okay.
And then the claim is that then so the
claim here is
that the this fraction here f ofx / g of
x
that this does have a limit as x go to a
and that limit is is actually l.
So this is uh this is one version of of
of of this rule. Okay. And there's a
there's another one very similar.
Okay.
And so so we want to prove this. So uh
we looking at so
so we have we want to uh apply the
Kushim mean value theorem to to prove
this theorem and so we're looking at a
interval here.
Uh so you're looking at at uh say y. So
here you have
a
here you have uh x and then here you
have y and here you have b right and I'm
now going to apply so we will apply the
so apply
the kushimi value
But we are applying it on on this
interval here
between uh so so y here is less than x
but it's strictly bigger than a and this
is x is strictly less than than x right
so the function was differentiable on
this open interval. So of course it's
differentiable or both functions are
differentiable on this closed interval.
So we can apply it and so we get that uh
fprime at some intermediate point
uh x0
uh times uh g
of uh uh x minus g of y.
This is equal to g prime again x0 here
is like is some intermediate point in
lie between these two
uh g prime at x0
times uh f of x minus g of x g of y
sorry like that
right this is just uh applying the cushy
mean value
Okay.
>> Uh what what did you say? Oh, yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Sorry about that. Thanks.
Yeah. Thank you.
Right. And so now I just divide. Of
course, this here is supposed to be uh
non zero. So I can just divide.
Um so so we have that
uh that fprime of x0
divided by uh
by g prime of x0
and then I will I want to divide by this
but I just need to make sure that this
here is
um is
um
that I can divide by right that it's not
zero this thing here. So I have this
now think about X is being fixed and do
this for all Y. Right? If I do this, if
I do this for y where y is very very
close to a, this here becomes really
really close to zero. Right? This here
is fixed and it's it's not equal to
zero. Right? So this here is very close
to zero. This is not equal to zero. So
this here if y is really close if x is
fixed y is really close to a. This is
definitely not zero. Right? So I can
divide by it right.
So for
for x fixed
and
y sufficiently close
close to zero.
then you have then uh
then g of x minus g of y
is not equal to zero. Right? And so I
can so I get that uh fprime
at this intermediate point divided by g
prime at the same intermediate point is
equal to f ofx - f of y / g of x minus g
of y
and now you see that as y here goes to
zero right so x is fixed still as y goes
to sorry not to zero But to a this here
goes to zero by assumption. This here
goes to zero. So the whole thing goes to
f ofx
divided by g of x.
Right?
Now the thing is that if you
so this is for all x fixed
Right. So now if you if you
So now we want to use So now you since
uh fprime
at at say set divided by g prime at set
since this fraction here as set go to a
this is assumed to go to l right. So
this means that that uh given
given epsilon greater than zero there
exist a delta
greater than zero. So that if uh if if
um set here is uh is less than a plus
delta
then this fraction here then f prime of
set minus g prime
of set is minus l
is less than epsilon.
Right?
So now coming back here
if you were starting with so this here
again was for all fixed x
right
uh you had this statement right and
again
uh x0 was between y and x right so now
if you so if
if this x here If x is
is delta close to the left end point of
the interval, right?
Then you would have that
x0, right? But x0 remember that x0 is
lying here, right? So since
x0 would lie here, this means that also
x0 here is uh white is is is
uh in this interval here,
right?
And so this means that this thing this
number here you get is is L with up to
some you know it's it's L up to some
error of like epsilon right
so this here is almost equal to L and so
this means that this limit here right is
almost equal to L within a error of
epsilon right okay so this proof this
version of the
rule and there's a second version and
that's in the notes but uh I'll skip it
actually for now just because you know
there was sort of from the last lecture
and it's very similar to this yeah
>> sorry why
Yeah. Okay. So this is because um
g
of x is for is supposed to be not equal
to x for all x.
Right? And now I'm fixing x. Okay? So
this here is non zero. Then I'm letting
y go to a but then this here goes to
zero by assumption.
Right? So you see that if you're fixing
X and you just take a Y sufficiently
close to A, then this denominator is
definitely not zero. Right? You really
want to let this you want to let Y goes
to A because then this here is
eliminated, right? This is not part of
the statement the G of Y, right? Okay.
And so again, as long as we started with
a x that was sufficiently close to if x
was in this interval, then x0 is even
further to the left. So this is also in
this interval. We don't know exactly
what x0 is, but it is in that interval.
And so this means that this is strictly
smaller than epsilon.
Okay. So,
another thing we talked about last time
was this with the tail expansion.
Uh,
and right and that all of these things
really came out of this uh bodice
theorem
uh and and and that was also the case
for the tail expansion.
So, you have a function f. So this is
just to remind you about the tail
expansion.
So you have a function
uh f
and let's say that is defined on some
interval here
into r and the function is so f here is
uh k times
differentiable
So this means that that fprime exist
fprime up to
the k derivative right. So they all
exist.
Uh and then the
statement was so then you looked at the
k minus one this is the k minus one
tail polomium
and uh and it was given by that k minus
one of x is equal to and now you're
summing here from i =0 to k minus one
and you take the i derivative this is
sorry this is the i derivative
uh of f and you do this in a and you
divide by a factorial and then you're
looking at uh at x - a to the power i
right So this was this was the k minus
one tail
and then uh the tail expansion
tail expansion just told you that uh
that um
that uh f here
at some x was equal to
uh p
k minus one it's tail up polinomial plus
and then this is what is usually
referred to as a remainder term
and this was uh the this looked very
similar to one of these terms. It was
the k derivative
of f but then it was evaluated at a
point c
uh divided by k factorial
time uh time um x minus
uh a to the power k
and c here was supposed to lie between a
and X.
Okay. So that was the this was the this
is the tail expansion theorem right
and and so the thing is that so why is
this so useful and it is extremely
useful uh in many different settings
also in much more general settings than
what I'm describing here and that is
because that if you take a function here
then um and it may be a very complicated
function but this tail expansion theorem
tells you that it is it is close to if
you want to evaluate it at some X
you can evaluate the tail polinom that's
after all just a polinomial so that's
easy to evaluate
and then you get within this remainder
term of the right answer okay so that's
how it always is used
and so the question is now the natural
question is how well does the tail
polomial
uh approximate
the value of the given function.
Right? So, so how
well
does the tail upon
uh approximate
the the function.
Okay. and and of course to to um to
understand that you need to estimate the
remainder term. Let me write the
remainder term here. So this the
remainder term
um
right so the remainder term is
um so I write this here as uh so it
really depends on on on x also right but
I would just write it like this thing
here so by this I mean the k derivative
of f
in c divided by k factorial and then x
minus a to the power k.
So again it depends on really also on
it. Of course it depend on a but it also
depends on x right and it's this thing
here. The thing the the catch here is
that you don't really know what c is
right the only thing you know about c is
that c is lying between uh a and x. So
this is essentially all you need, all
you know
about C.
Okay.
So now let's look at some examples.
Let's look at two examples. So the the
first one is like a promising example
and the second one is much less
promising. Uh and so uh but and so the
thing is that that how well it
approximate really depends on the
function. Okay. But the first one is is
quite typical though example.
So suppose that the function f ofx is
the exponential function.
Um and then we have that the derivative
is just the exponential function itself.
So this means that if you take the
derivative k times
then you just get the function itself.
So this means that the k minus one
this means that a k minus one tail
polinomial
right this is just the value of the
function I'll just write it out here so
this is the value and now I do it uh I
do it for a equal to uh zero
and I'm assuming that b here so I'm
thinking about I will think about this
function here f ofx
uh on on the this function the
exponential function I'm going to sing
about it on the interval say from uh
minus1 to one
um
um into r maybe maybe I will maybe I'll
just take it from zero to one into r
Um okay so the and the tail polinomial
so I'm going to so so so the tailum one
also talk about that this
tail polinomium is expanded around a
okay so we talk about that the tail
polom so we talk about tail expansion
around
uh A. Okay. And this just refer to that
when when you plug in A here, well then
of course you have exact equality,
right? And that all of the derivative
are evaluated at A. Okay? So it's really
like the tail polom. It's only a good
approximation near A. Right? So I want
now to tail expand
uh near uh the zero
and so um so right so the value here of
the function is one at zero the
derivative is right so it's the
derivative is also one because it's just
a function itself and so this is so you
get x and then you get the next Uh the
next uh element in the tail expansion is
x^2 / 2 + x^2
over 3 factorial
and then uh x 4 over 4 factorial etc up
to x ^ k minus one over u uh k minus one
factorial right so this is the a tail
expansion
or take k minus one tail polomial
uh around zero. Okay.
And so now if you're interested in
evaluating
p you want to say how well does this
here approximate
uh the original function the exponential
function. So you want to bound this
thing here right? So you want to have a
bound for that. Well the thing again is
that f ofx you know that f ofx is equal
to this tail polomial
and then plus this remainder term
right in the c right
now c again has to lie will c will lie
between
a and x. In this case a is zero.
So it means that c here.
So this means that here here c here is
between zero and x. Right?
And the remainder term here
this here was
was equal to that you took the k
derivative of the function. So in this
case the k derivative of the function is
the function itself. So this here is the
value of the k derivative and this is uh
at c this is the k derivative of the
original function and then you have to
divide by a k factorial and then it's x
to the power
uh k like that
right
and so you see that if if x here is now
between zero and one. This means that
this thing here, this
remainder term here, the absolute value
is so c here is less than one. So this
means that this thing here is less than
e. So it's less or equal to e divided by
k factorial. This here is bounded by
since x is bounded by one, this is
bounded by one. So you're getting this
inequality here, right? And so you see
that if K is is very large, this is a
tiny number, right? So it's a really
good approximation. I mean, you don't
even need to make K very large because
it's exponential, right? Not
exponential, it's factorial. Yeah.
Right.
Okay. So that's a kind of encouraging
example. Let's say that the the tail
expansion uh is is a very in this case
is a very good approximation to the
function.
Uh the another example that is less
encouraging and so again the moral is
that how well the tail expansion
approximate the function depend on the
function. So suppose that the function
here was
uh was a function that was zero here.
When x is less than zero less or equal
to zero and when x is bigger than zero
then it is e to the minus 1 /x^2.
Okay. So you see that when x becomes
very very small
you are looking at one over this
squared. So this here is huge
right but now it's with a minus sign. So
this means that this thing here is
incredibly small right and so it's
clearly it's clear that this function
here is continuous at zero. It's clearly
continuous everywhere else. But actually
it's you know sort of using in this sort
of argument it's easy to see that this
function f here is uh infinite
differentiable.
So it's you can differentiate it
infinitely many times and even at zero.
Okay.
and and by it and of course the
derivative
uh the derivative is right so it's an
example of a function that looks like
this is zero until zero and then it goes
up like this right and so the derivative
at zero
is zero any derivative however many
times you take the derivative of this
function
sorry
this thing here
if you take any derivative and you
evaluate at zero, you always get zero,
right?
So, so this means that if you're looking
at the tail expansion
at zero, so you're looking at this k
minus one tailor polomial.
This polomial is all of the coefficient
in the polinomial are zero right. So
this polinomial is just zero. So this
means that
if you're looking at
f ofx
well f of x is actually equal to this
remainder term right. So it's somehow
you know the teleport number is like too
trivial. It doesn't really help you all
that much. Right? So it's equal to this
remainder term.
Okay.
Yeah.
>> Is there a way of um so like the
remainder like bounding this helps us
figure out how well the expansion
approximates the actual function. Is
there a way to determine like how far
from the point you're approximating like
a or zero in this case you can go a
>> Yeah. by it. That's right. I mean, so
you're asking, right? So you're asking
suppose and you definitely could do
this, right? You you asking
you you you're thinking that you have
you have a
you you you're thinking a slightly
different situation than here but
closely related that you have some a
here
and you have a function f and and you
want to and you are willing to maybe uh
look at you're willing to
take some fixed large k and then you're
asking
um what I'm interested in how well does
this how well does this function this
polomial approximate this but I want it
within an error certain area right so
it's a given epsilon and you're
interested in how far away can you go
from a so that this here is less than
epsilon and so this is so so this
becomes a question of this remainder
term, right? So this becomes a question
of this remainder term. When can you
always say that this remainder term is
less than epsilon
and so like in this particular you would
have to do it on a casebyase basis. Uh
but in this particular case the
remainder term is right if this interval
here in the in that example over there
if if you if you have here zero this was
a in our example and then you want to go
out here to some x
and now you know that c here is between
zero and x but you don't really know
anything else right so then it's like
this remainder term you will have this
remainder term in this example
uh at this c here this again was equal
to this thing here over k factorial
and so you would have that you would
want this thing here
r k
you would want this to be less than
epsilon and so you would have that this
thing here the the only the only thing
you can really do is that you can say
that C is less or equal to to X for C.
>> Yeah, that's right. But that no so so
you would do so what you would do here
is you would say R K C this here has to
be bounded by by because XC is less than
X. So this is E to the X you have to
eliminate C. So, so, so you would do
like this k factorial * x ^ k you have
to eliminate uh c right because you
don't know anything really about c and
so this here now has to be less than
epsilon so now you only have you know
you have fixed your k and so now you
only have one variable and you can solve
that but you you you really have to
eliminate change yeah
uh Okay.
Uh so so so again so so the how well the
tail expansion approximate depends on
the function.
Okay. The next topic is another
important topic and so this is uh
integrals
and there are
different ways of
of um defining integrals.
This here is
um
this here is certainly one of the maybe
the most natural one.
Uh and so this is what's called
reman. So it's after German
mathematicians reman
uh integrals.
And so the thing is that here now you
look at a function
you have a function on some interval
from a to b
into r and this function f here is um is
bounded
and the idea is so the idea is for
integrals is
that so you have a function function
and you want to be able to define. So
define
uh area
below
graph.
So so if this is a function you want to
be able to calculate
what is this area. Okay. Now, if the
function was to if the function was to
have crossed
um the x-axis, then this area here would
count negatively and this area here
would count positively. Anyway, so this
is this is what you want to do
and and you always starting with a
bounded function.
Now, to do that, right? And so so you
want to define that the only thing that
you know for sure is
so so there's only like one ingredient
you have.
So,
so only
only thing
uh no you know
at the outset.
So the only thing you know is that if
you take a right angle so if this length
here is
um uh is let's call it D and this here
is E right then you know that the area
here
so area
is D * E right okay that's that's the
only thing we have so Now
how do we define the the area below the
graph? And to do that we first need to
talk about partitions.
So partition.
So suppose I have a
interval here. A and b are real numbers.
So I have an interval here. Then I talk
about a partition
and and it's useful to have a notation
for a partition. So I call it P of of
this interval here.
This is finite is finally many
many dividing points
and the dividing points always have to
start at A and end at B. So you have
finally many let's say k many and you're
looking at okay take I'll write it k +
one many. So uh the first one has to be
a
and then you have uh x1
up to the last one
and that has to be b.
Okay.
And so
so what you're thinking about is so you
have this interval here from a to b and
you have these dividing points
and you are thinking about dividing the
the original interval into these sub
intervals. Right? So these are the sub
intervals. Right? So you divide
the original
interval
into
sub intervals
and the sub intervals are I'll do it
like this. I will do it the where I take
from it's always from you know one to
the next and I will write it typically
where I'm starting where I'm ending at I
and beginning at I minus one.
So
right so I'm dividing it into these sub
intervals and so in this case here in
this case here where this is x0
uh there's going to be
uh k uh sub intervals okay and it's you
know you only
always go from one to the next right so
so that's a partition
and now we need a second notion
related to this and this is a sub
partition.
So subartetition
subartetition this is also sometime
called uh sometimes called
uh
refinement.
So a sub partition is so if you have a
partition so P1 is a partition
and then P2 is a sub partition of
refinement.
If if
P2
has all
the dividing points
of P1 and then some and then some I mean
it right right I mean of course it could
be a trivial sub partition where P1 and
P2 are the same. That's okay. But in
general, it would have some more points
also, some more dividing points. Okay.
Now,
um, right. So, now let me look at uh, so
what is then?
So, so now let's try to get closer to
try to define this with the area below
the graph.
Okay.
So again we have we have a function f
from a to b
into r. We assume that this is so uh
that is bounded.
We have P here is a partition
of of this interval here.
Then we defined a upper and a lower sum.
Then we define
upper
and lower sums.
as follows
right so again you have a given function
that is bounded and you have a partition
and so we define upper and lower sums
and the upper and lower sum I will
denote like this it depends on the
function of course and then on the
partition that's a upper sum and the
lower sum similar I would denote like
this
and so how are these defined?
So they are defined as follow
that you have here you have your
interval from a to b.
Then you have this here is x0 here I
have x1 and here I have maybe x2 and
then this thing here is then x3.
So I take uh I look at one of these
intervals
or it could be this one here. that's
between in this case it would be between
uh x1 and x2
and I would look at the function in this
interval here and I would so the
contribution from this here would be
that I would take so for the upper for
the upper
sum
with respect to this partition the one
that comes from this sub interval here
would be um would be
uh the soup
of f on this sub interval here.
So the soup of the function
times the length of the interval
like that. So this would be the value
that in the upper that would come uh in
a minute I'll write it out more more
clearly but this would be what is coming
from here and likewise
uh for the lower one
um the contribution from this little
interval here would be the in of f
and then times and The idea right is
okay. So that would be the contribution.
Um the idea of course is that you have
but the only thing we knew was this with
the area of a right angle.
Right?
And so you have this function here and
you have some little interval here
between x i and x i - uh sorry x i - one
and x i right
and you're focusing on this little
interval here
and you're looking at the function the
function was bounded so there is a soup
on this and you try to look at the
smallest red angle angle that kind of
have the graph that fits where the graph
fits inside that right and then you're
looking at so this this is the
contribution
from this little interval
to P to to the upper sum and then you
have right that you're looking at the
largest right angle like this that fits
under the graph and that's then
contribution to the lower one.
Right? And the idea is that if the
function is reasonable, if you're
looking at finer and finer partition,
then you should you should certainly get
a better a better approximation to the
area below the graph, right? I mean, and
and and if the function is reasonable,
these two Okay, so now what is then the
uh let me just define this.
So this thing here
it would be convenient to to the length
of this interval to denote it by by
this. So this is x i x i minus one. This
just the length of that interval.
Okay. And so now written out this thing
and okay let me make one other notation.
MI is the soup of f on x i minus one x i
that's m capital mi and little mi is
then the in on the same interval
like that. And so the upper sum
for this partition this is the sum from
i = uh one to k
of m i * delta xi.
That's the upper sum. And the lower sum
is then the sum
from i = 1 to k of mi delta xi.
Okay. So that's the upper and the lower
sum. Okay. The first thing you observe
is the first thing you observe is is a
trivial fact
and it's you know that really should be
the case because one is like what fits
inside the graph uh below the graph the
other is you know where the graph fits
below the right angle. So you clearly
have just be and this is just because
this number here is the in this is the
soup on the same interval. So you
clearly have
that uh L F
is less or equal to U FP. Right? So this
is
so this is clear. Right?
Okay.
Let's look at uh
let's look at an a couple of examples.
So just to make sure that this is
totally clear
uh let me look at a couple example.
So uh
the um
the first example is so I take a
function
f ofx = 2x^2 + 1
and my partition and the interval here
I'm going to think about this as a
function on minus2 two
to two
into R.
And my partition here
is going to be min -2 -1 0 1 and two
um and um right and so you have so let's
see so this so this here so if I draw
the function
then this is looks like if this here is
one
uh here you have one
then it looks sort of like this. Uh
doesn't more or less like this.
Okay. And so this means that here and
here you have two
uh and this here is minus one
um and
um
and uh and here you have uh minus two.
So now if you're looking at so that the
um right so so this means here that so
this is my partition so this means that
x0 is uh equal to minus2
x1 that's the next one is minus one x3
is the next one
that's zero x4
is uh one and x5 y is two, right? And so
of course all of these intervals here,
right? They all have the same length in
this case. So x i - x i -1. This was
what we call delta x i. This here is for
each of these is equal to one.
And now we have that the
and we have that the
when you're looking between minus2 and
two and sorry minus2 and minus one. So
on this interval here
um the function is the function on this
interval here is decreasing. So the
largest value is achieved at this point
here. Right? Uh so uh m
M1 this is the same as a soup of f
between uh x0
and x1. And so this is the same as the
soup of minus2 to minus1 right of f and
the function was decreasing so the li on
this interval so the largest value is
achieved here and that's five
right so this would be five
and uh on the second interval here
right so this is between minus1 and zero
still decreasing So the value is the
largest value is here where it's two. So
this here is is two and m3
this is now uh between zero and one. So
now it's increasing. So the large value
is over here. So that's again two.
And then the last one is is is again
five. Right?
And then likewise for the the the ones
that are the info. So the first one m1
well the function was decreasing. So the
smallest value is over at this end point
there. The value is true.
So you're getting uh this here is is
two.
And then between
between minus1 and zero it's still
decreasing. So there the smallest is at
this point where it's one. So this is m2
and then m3
this is now here the function is
increasing. So it's still the value
here. So it's still one. And then the
last one
um is between one and two and there it's
the infreom is the value here. So that's
two right
and so you see that in this case the
upper
for this function
uh for this partition
it's this right all of the intervals
have length these small interval have
length one so it's just the sum of these
guys right so this is just equal to five
if you will it's 5 * 1 that was length
of the interval plus 2 * 1 + uh 2 * 1 +
5 * 1. So in other words, you get here
14. And for the lower ones,
it's again this time I want rise times
one. It's a sum of those guys and that's
actually six, right?
So So that's upper and lower sum. Okay.
Now, uh and we had we had one um one
observation that was a an immediate
observation and that was uh this thing
here.
Now,
what is useful is that you starting with
a partition and then you you have a
subartition. So the next one is so I
take a function f on some interval from
a to b and this function here is bounded
and then I have p is a partition p1 say
is a partition
and then p2
is a sub partition.
of P1.
And now the thing that is uh useful is
the following.
[Applause]
that. So,
so the following claim, the following
leham
that if you take a sub partition then I
claim that the value of the upper sum go
down and the value of the lower go up.
So this is the following. So uh so lower
of f * p1.
This is less or equal to the lower of f
of p2. We already proved that this thing
here, this one here, this this
inequality we haven't proved yet. But
this one here, we have that this is less
than
than the upper one for the same
partition. And the second claim is that
this here is then less than the upper
one for the first.
Okay.
Now why is this the case? This is also
actually a trivial statement but it's
very useful statement.
So imagine that you have your partition
P1 here and then you have the dividing
points I minus one
and here you have I
right and P2 is a sub partition. So
there may be intervals like this where
there are no further dividing points
right but in that case the what you the
contribution that for the lower and
upper is the same for the two partitions
right but should there be one or more
let's just say there's one right then
for the upper one you would look at you
would then get so you would get a a a
new dividing point. Let's call it y.
And then you would get for the new one,
you would have you would look at the
soup here on this interval here, right?
But the soup on this interval here of
the function is less than the soup on
the larger interval. So you would get a
soup of f on the interval from i -1 to y
of f
you get that and then you would get
times the length of the interval that's
y - x i -1
and then you would get a second soup but
this is now from from y to x I of f and
then you would have multiple by the
length of this interval. So this is this
here is then from x i to y. Okay.
So this is this is what you get from the
new petition. the contribution from the
from the second
from the this is what this is the
contribution that you get from the upper
sum for this partition P2 from this part
right but now you see that this thing
here the soup over this little interval
well that of course is less than the
soup over the larger interval so This is
less than m i and I just keep this one
here
and this one here is also a sub interval
of this larger interval. So this is less
than m i again time x i - x y.
But now you can factor out the mi. So
you're getting MI and you're getting the
sum of these two Y - X I - one +
uh X I - Y. And so you see that this
here is exactly MI * X I - X I - one.
Right?
And so you see that the
contribution that we get here to the
upper sum from this part here
that was this and this those two things
this is less than the contribution we
get from the upper sum from the first
partition. Right? And so this prove this
proves this inequality here
and this inequality is just similar.
It's just with the instead of the soups.
Okay. So this is this is a this is like
a key point. It's a you know each of
these steps is like completely trivial.
Uh but together it it actually means
that you can really define something
non-trivial.
Okay. So now um and this may seem
cheating. Now we uh well first of all we
define the upper and lower integrals.
So we have upper and lower sum and now
we define the upper and lower intervals.
So our
and lower instruments.
Okay. Um so the upper lower integral so
the upper here is denoted like this.
We take a bar over this and this is the
upper lower integral. So this is the
integral. This is the function. And then
you write this.
And so this is simply defined to be the
info
over all partitions
of the upper integral
upper sum. Sorry.
Right. And so remember again that if you
take a partition and you refined it, if
you're looking at a subartition of the
given partition, then this number here
goes down, right? I mean it may stay the
same, but it's certainly not bigger,
right? So so this is so so the idea here
is that essentially this number here you
get by looking at finer and finer
partition, right? So idea
is that
uh the infirmum uh that this is that
this
is a limit
over finer and final partition.
Right? So that's the idea sort of the
the but the precise statement is is is
that it's just the info right. So this
is the upper integral and then likewise
we define the lower integral
>> asset
many
obviously
>> right there it's it's not you know but
there is a a key assumption is that we
that for each partitions there are only
finitely many divisions
but there's not a but it's but but there
are infinite many partitions. So it's
really and so so when I say that it's a
limit over uh finer and finer partitions
you should really think about that in
sort of quotation mark this not very
precise statements okay so but the
precise statement is just that it's
infome all partitions
and so
so
I mean you can make that precise but
then that require a lot of stuff uh that
we don't want to do here. Uh and there's
no reason to it because there's a
perfectly reasonable way of defining it.
And so that was the upper integral. So
this is the upper integral.
And then similarly the lower integral
the lower integral. And there I'm just
putting the bar below.
And you refine it like this.
And this is now the soup, right? Because
remember that if you took a partition
and then you take a sub partition, then
this lower sum actually went up. So it's
a soup of all partitions of these lower
Okay.
Right. And so now we say that uh and
then we say that
so now here's the the definition. And
again this may initially seem like kind
of we are uh wimping out uh because but
but but it but in a minute we will then
determine when this is the case. So we
define so so f here. So if you have a
bounded function like this
then we say that
that uh f is reman integral.
So
if uh if the lower sum
is equal to the upper sum.
So if this has the case
um and and uh and and in that case
and then
the reman integral
is this this common uh so the reman is
written like
And this is just
this this common value.
Okay.
Now, uh one thing I just want to remark
um is
that
that we have you always have
That's the
so one remark is that so
so note
that so first of all we had this trivial
statement that if you take a partition
then the lower sum is less or equal to
the upper sum Fine. Then we had that if
you took a sub partition, if this here
was a sub partition
of P1. Then this lower sum here
under a sub partition, the lower sum
went up,
but it's still staying below
So you have this inequality here. Okay.
Now what what is this useful form?
So as a consequence of this we get that
the you know whether or not the function
is rem integral you always have that the
lower integral here of f dx is less or
equal to the upper integral.
So this here is for all functions. And
why is this the case? This is because if
you take this here is the soup
of these lower partitions, right?
But if you take any given partition,
then this lower thing here is less than
than the upper one,
right?
And so now so now imagine that you take
so if you take a lower partition
right suppose sorry suppose now that you
take the soup over all partitions then
it means that there is one partition so
that this value here is close to the
soup.
But uh but for this one here right you
have this inequality here right and so
in fact but in fact if you take any so
any other partition you can think about
maybe I'll explain this more detail next
time because I only have a minute but
but it basically come from this
inequality here is coming from from from
uh from this this inequality here it
will take just a few minutes to explain
it clearly. So maybe I'll just leave it
here. But but but a key point here is
that you have this inequality here and
it comes from that
and but but we return to that next time
because it's to make it really clear it
it would take a few minutes.
Now the last thing I want to say in the
is that so this so you may think that we
sort of whimped out of saying when this
uh right because we just define it we
just say that it's reman integraable if
if uh those two things are equal right
and so but then the question of course
become when are those two things equal
right so that's the key question so the
key question is
when are they equal?
And and we'll answer this next time.
Um where we will show that if f is
continuous
then then they are equal.
Okay.
And so uh so anyways I'll return to
this. I will first um um you know we
need anyway some more information about
this upper and lower integral and I will
first show why the lower one is less or
equal to the lower one is lesser equal
to the upper one always and then we will
talk about you know some criteria for
when they are equal and then we will
prove this for continuous functions
>> is that only
>> no no no it's not it's not it's Not it's
um it's uh yeah it's not a total answer.
It's it's a it's a good initial answer
but there are many functions that are
not continuous that are very worth you
know that plays in key roles and they're
still
um and we will also look at an example
it's in the notes but I didn't get to
it. we look at an example of a function
that is u that is not where where you
don't have this equality and this is
like an old