hi everybody today we're going to um
spend the bulk of our time uh making up
for sort of for lost lab time lost time
uh coding and doing implementing some of
the ideas that we have but first we're
going to step back to um just a little
bit on the the quiz apologies for taking
a while to get it back to you but now
you have it and the quiz is sort of the
opposite right of the um of the
Practical side it's the more of the
theoretical side so I wanted to talk
about a couple aspects of that um
somebody's going to remind me put the
screen back down Paul's not here today
um so please do that um some of the
Practical aspects on the quiz in space
um first you know why are authors and
articles important why why am I really
sensing that you know not just you know
what the three contexts are or what
optic is but really whose idea this is
and there's really two reasons one the
field is small the field is small and if
you're working in it and it's it's young
like like not young as y'all or it's
even older than than me but but young
like Mo almost everyone who has come up
with the great ideas that have changed
the field are still living and people
you can meet um the but more importantly
um and so some of the uh some of the
guest speakers that we've had recently
have appeared it's campus preview
weekend so we got to close this um
otherwise it'll get loud okay but some
of the speakers that we've seen have
actually already appeared in articles
that we've been reading and things so
these are names that will keep popping
up again and um when when David here on
talks about Carol Crum hunel who was
after the uh the quiz but you know that
this is a name that oh I've already read
that the other um first reason is that
uh I don't know if you saw on one of our
um guest speakers on music uh cognition
a lot of times there were you know these
nice pretty pictures of I don't know can
I draw a light bulb or something like
that and some idea and things and over
in the corner you you would see like um
Devin's 20 19 or whatever right and
those are just um ways there industry
shortcuts for how you can learn more
about a particular topic so I don't tend
to talk with footnotes maybe I should
more uh Strunk and white
2004 um and uh you know but but these
are things that that people do uh quite
often and it's because um here's the
worst thing about almost every article
you'll read whether in science
engineering Humanities Arts um that like
I'm telling you to read these articles
and things but then the Articles aren't
actually written for you to read I mean
it's so ironic right you why why do we
write and publish research for the most
part we're publishing research to talk
to or to argue with or push back on or
develop the theory of somebody else
who's living so these these um Scholars
tend to talk to each other quite a bit
and so what they're doing when they're
putting these names down is really
there's a there's a seat here today if
you'd like U okay and um what they're
really doing is trying to uh trying to
argue against something that you might
not already know so when somebody's
presenting an idea they're really saying
um hey I've got a better idea than this
other person and so they're always going
to be talking about names of other
people and so it's just just kind of
good to get that so that's um something
there uh the other question I think that
can come up in the context of these um
quizzes based primarily on the readings
and these sort of abstract things is why
are there so many darn old articles in
this class why um are you doing a lot of
citations of things that are 10 years
old 25 years old and then you got the
iliac Suite um what is that 70 77 years
years old now uh so what's the point of
getting into it uh I so I've been
teaching for a while and one of the
there's one lecture that um I love the
topic um and I hope you'll love it too
when we get to it but I hate giving this
lecture it's the lecture on practical AI
in um in music and why is that it's
because the various techniques that I've
um been
teaching have changed so often that
they're not really relevant two years
later so I'm I'm going to be um you know
thinking about oh okay NE this weekend
it's time to update everything from
tensor flow which was so state-of
the-art three years ago and I wrote a
whole lecture around it to um for those
who know this P
torch which I'm using now and it really
means that there's a lot of things that
we'll be spending time in that class
that if P torch ends up not being the
the super great um thing that you're
going to be using for the rest of your
life because of GPT or whatever else
that's coming out those types of
information will get stale pretty fast
but the notion of things like um
equality and equivalence and and how you
can put equivalence classes I hope will
stay with you even if you're not doing
anything with music or or even anything
with comp computation I hope there
things that will stay with you for the
rest of your life and that you'll it'll
sort of change how you make an outlook
on the world so that's a little bit um
why this class has a good amount of it I
figure if it's something that inspired
me 15 years ago and it's still inspiring
me today it has a good chance that it'll
still be relevant inspirational uh in 10
20 30 years from now for those who um
did the work on the Glo Global rule um
somebody somebody remind somebody uh
remind us what the global rule is and
what first where where does it
apply want to take a guess Matthew do
you want to take a guess or calling
somebody else Counterpoint Counterpoint
great super so it's Counterpoint
Rule Rule and um what's it trying to
maximize in Counterpoint
uh just trying to
think let try to maximize in
kind that's it you want to try it um I
guess it's like trying to maximize like
the musical or like how good it sounds
Max musicality absolutely great
super and it does this ironically trying
to maximize musicality came down to
giving a formula right or giving uh
giving a set of formulas and and where
do we begin with the global
rule remember last start from the end
and go backwards and look at um
specifically do you have what three
possibilities of the last
one you're going
backwards now you have two possibilities
because you can't repeat notes in this
context so you can be trying here and
here against some
other thing David Luen would actually
not be happy with me he always did his
counterpoints in Alto cluff but we'll do
it in um in trouble and base so yeah
you're trying to figure out okay if we
end it here and the previous note is
here what are the other notes that we
can do so we have um traditional
Counterpoint rules but we also have this
notion that every note that appears in
the
line must at some point find
what
remember every everybody quiet because
they all know this so easily or because
uh it's a little little foggy
easy foggy okay good that's good good I
I prefer silence when it's foggy because
then I know uh what to do next so uh in
order to get maximum musicality he
talked
about what begins
with he wants what kind of lines smooth
smooth lines so we want smooth lines so
if at some point you have a d here a low
D and we're going to get to see what
kind what are the notes that we need to
see after this oops
just turned red okay what are the notes
that we need to see after
this what's a note we need to see after
after
d what's that e e good good so if we
have an
e then what happens if we have another D
after
that what are we going to need after the
D at some
point what go ahead another E another E
good so
basically whenever you have a note you
have to have after it every note between
here not every uh every dionic note not
right not every chronic note you're not
going to need a d SHP at some point
every dionic note between here and the
final Cadence note that's why it was a
little bit easier to work backwards now
why is this rule um why was this rule
important for this
class this one this one might be a
silent because it's pretty easy cuz is
almost everything in this
class who can do
it
that's what kind of thing can apply this
rule computer okay so that you can have
an Al it can all be done the ironic
thing where're maximizing musicality
through
algorithms um great so that's about all
I want on that
um and people who uh who chose that
problem uh those tended to do pretty
well now let's get
to
second
equality and
equivalence and almost everybody chose
to do this
one um what's the name associated with
this without looking down Dimitri is the
first
name TCO let's try to spell it together
give me a t give me a y give me
a m give me a o
c
z k k q q deat q he'd like that um no D
much Co right uh so it's this one's a
little bit hard and I would not uh you
know whatever uh basically one of the
things I try to do is um I put in optic
and whatever you put and see if Google
could find the author on the first um
thing so that uh on the first page I and
um just remember that if you put in Wolf
Gang Mo mustard it finds Mozart so
Google's pretty good at this but um okay
so Demitri tko's uh optic almost
everybody got uh o optic op uh
octave
t
t i and C
good I know this was like back my hand I
just don't know how to spell the word
optic um and then most people thank you
for including my little contribution of
spelling on the list um a lot of people
great now so people did really really
great on that here are some of the
things that though were a little bit
harder um I think I might have thrown
some people for a loop and I didn't try
to you know grade too hard on this
because I realized oh I didn't do the
greatest job on this in lecture so was
the difference between equality and
equivalence when we talk about sameness
which one do you think we're most likely
talking about votes for
equality same
equivalents we have more un equivalence
yeah I might not have done as well on
this um I think of sameness as having
more to do with equality in some some
sense and equivalence meaning sort of
can be grouped together
and we could say it can be grouped
together in some logical connection or
can be grouped together connected with
some in some logical way and uh the
other thing that I think I probably
Falls a little bit on me because uh
didn't come out as clearly is that when
we're talking about same some people and
you got full credit if you did this
talked about sort of the big picture
this is same in every conceivable way so
are this piece is the same as this other
piece in every conceivable way um and
you know that that's one way that we can
think of sort of a grand scale equality
the problem is um that you you all are
really smart and you all know how to
conceive of things that that can break
that right you know you know I I hit
play on this um on this recording and
then I hit play on this recording again
but one of them happened um 10 minutes
later and one of them was played through
on speakers that had uh had uh 10
minutes more of um wear and tear on them
or something so you know you can always
conceive a way it's different so maybe
that's not as good but but we might
think of equality of aspects of of
something equality of aspects of um you
know that uh I'm trying to think you all
are sitting down so I'm trying to think
maybe maybe Jake is you know that we are
not exactly the same but but I think
we're approximately the same height
maybe we're the same height let's say
that we are so we are same in height or
something like that so two notes could
be same in frequency equal in frequency
so that's we tend to use equality for
some sort of attribute of something that
is identical or the or you know not
cannot be distinguished from each other
whereas equivalents we tend to think
of as things that we can group together
none of us are the same in um in any you
know in in any real deep great way but
we all um could be lumped under the
equivalence class of
MIT 21
m383 students
right and it kind of tells you also that
equivalence classes might be um
overlapping some of you might be also uh
MIT you know 6 uh 042 students together
or you could be in something else um so
they could be
overlapping then the the hardest part I
think on this problem that snagged a
bunch of people is um where um in what
contexts uh equivalence classes might um
you know might uh be used and why not
but we might think of
um as one chord arpeggiated
and as an as the same chord or yeah I
guess I just use same in an equivalent
sense so may maybe maybe I'm less uh
dogmatic that as an equivalent chord
even though one of
them
was going up and the other one was going
down so we might think that the
permutation doesn't matter in that
particular class when we're talking
about what chord did I
apegate and then later we might say well
you know direction is another
equivalence class did it go up or did it
go down
um and contexts for when you might use
one and when you might not use one a lot
of times the context that where
equivalence classes come in it's sort of
a little kind of too obvious in a class
called computational music theory and
Analysis the equivalence classes tend
not come in very as often in
performance than in
analysis so um I think uh you know some
uh more than one person wrote um you
know well that you can think of a per a
performance where um cardinality doesn't
matter and yeah might have written
something like um well if you play that
measure three times because that's
what's written I only play at once uh
it's going to matter for our performance
last way but we might not think of the
cardinality as mattering if if we're
trying to do a search on does this piece
have any diminished Triads you know we
don't really care how many major Triads
and how many minor but in that case we
might just be lumping everything in
under the type of Triad equivalence
class and not counting how many um the
particular uh one but but we use these
all the time in real life so uh the
example that kind of popped into my head
today is um you know if you um if you're
going to uh Taylor Swift um you know if
you if you're going to be analyzing a
Taylor Swift song and you're going to
look at the harmonic structure of it
does it
matter presumably if if if you're
listening to Taylor Swift's recording or
if you're listening to a cover band one
that's trying to be faithful
for harmonic
structure not really right you hope a
good cover band is trying to sound like
that trying to use the same harmonies so
we could come up with a cover
band equivalence
class cover maybe we just call it the
cover equivalence class which applies if
you're doing harmonic
analysis does it matter whether you're
seeing Taylor Swift or cover band if you
just paid 9 $900 for front row
tickets yeah it does so we can think of
live performance as a place where cover
equivalence doesn't exist now we mostly
talked about Pitch equivalence so that's
um a big thing there um that so that we
might be thinking too much about pitch
and not enough about duration equivalent
not enough about bigger
things the other uh thing just to talk
about is that often when we're talking
about these pitch equivalences like
octave or cardinality or things we're
not really thinking about the um the
sort of I don't know the the scale of
the piece right we're not really
thinking does this piece have the same
number of notes as this piece if we
apply cardinality equivalents or
something right but we might be thinking
about does this chord have the same
number of unique pitch classes if we're
applying octave permutation
transposition and card
ity so that level um comes up quite a
bit I think there's one place where we
have um where we do tend to think of
equivalence classes on a peace
level
sometimes that's when you have you know
uh I don't know uh
Beethoven's
uh third Symphony
in no e flat major sorry of course this
is this isn't a music history class on
on the history of ban but that we do
tend to group pieces in classical music
by key um the other place where that
immediately comes ahead where there
might be equivalence classes of um of
pieces is a DJ might have a beats per
minute equivalence class where you want
to group together all songs with the
same BPM so you can switch between them
so uh think on that um any any thoughts
or questions on on this
um and thank you to the person who gave
me the opportunity to explore the um
permutation equivalence class on Happy
Birthday um
okay last last one talk about the three
contexts um this one uh I uh was a
little bit harder some people uh got uh
it was by Elanor suffrage field and some
people um thought it was the decently
similar about the same time in the
semester article by Nicholas cook and if
you wrot wrote that you know you were
getting some credit because you were
really in the in the right ballpark um
so she talks about the three main
contexts he talks about are you can read
them off we're better say them out first
one symbolic the symbolic is one is well
we'll get it is there but not one one of
her terms we can that ends up being the
problematic one but yeah we'll keep that
one else what's that graphical graphical
yep graphical and what's the opposite
what's what do we contrast graphical
things
with sound
good and then the logical is what she
has and and so symbolic will be in there
things um one of the the things that
came up a lot in the quiz was that
people were immediately uh going to a
higher level than what she was intending
so when we think about
graphical this is sort of a graphical
context for representing music right but
in her mind what is the graphical thing
I just created here anyone want to take
a guess don't go too
high Circle in a line Circle in a line
is going to say okay great a circle and
a line so by the time you move that to
um Professor you drew a quarter note
with a stem
down stem down on the third space and
you know with this context you draw c um
you've already been moving to The
Logical
domain similarly when you hear a sound
so I I can only represent sound right
now well I can do I can do it in the
sound domain but you know in the graphic
domain of sound
um you don't necessarily yet hear oh I
hear a c maybe you can say or I hear an
a maybe you can say uh if you're an
oscillator in your head you can say I
hear something oscillating at 440 times
per second but then to move that to an a
for octave 4 is motion to The Logical
domain so this I don't think I was clear
enough on maybe maybe eler selfish field
wasn't enough or we we just need to read
it a little bit more closely and
similarly um even things like instrument
I hear an instrument you're already
moving to The Logical domain you might
uh if you're if you're a signal
processor be saying oh I'm hearing a
waveform where only the odd partial
harmonics are
present and then your memory bank is
saying oh I'm hearing
clarinet so those are the odd partials
right I don't teach that class yeah I
think that's right um okay so because
elements of The Logical domain we were a
lot of our answers were transferring to
the sound or the graphical domain The
Logical domain got uh care sort of um uh
sort of kingled up with the next higher
domain here the next more abstract thing
which in this case I'm going to call it
the
meaning
domain um we can call it the hair I'm
going to actually try to write this
without looking at
mudic domain which is sort of the study
of the construction of meaning or the
conceptualization of meaning it's
actually a pretty cool word if you don't
know it but I don't like it too much
because my whole life I've had I know
blow hards if I can say that word who
who uh who just miss who use hermeneutic
and throw it around everywhere oh I'm
having a hermeneutic construction of
meaning it's like well no that's just
what that means um if you learn up learn
your hermeneutics of hermeneutics so
I'll often just call it the meaning
domain and so you might be um you know
that your logical sound domain you've
heard and your graphical domain you saw
a whole bunch of things on page and your
logical domain said o uh there's a whole
bunch of randomly spaced staccato a or
even randomly spaced might be too too
far down um so at this level you might
say oh the title of the piece is
fireflies and this is a depiction of how
the fireflies are coming and out so
there is a next level of domain to have
there
um difficulty is that um there's this
word semantic that came up a
lot
semantic sorry I'm writing over it but
I'm writing there for a particular
reason that
um that Elanor suffrage field kind of
uses to imply this level of
understanding that that's sort of the
greater meaning of things so it's a
fourth uh context there but over time
it's kind of been migrated up in music
um information retrieval to be closer to
the logical domain so people will s say
you know oh I don't want to you know I I
I I don't want to know exactly how
you're going to draw it on the page I
want to know it's semantically uh
quarter note
C5 or something and so this term I'm
going to try to avoid too much because
it's being used in sort of two very
different um contexts here okay
questions on this or more
discussion okay I know we want to uh get
to some coding and get to some other
things but thanks for um thanks for
sticking with all of this oh and and
there was one thing that came up uh and
a really good answer that made me uh
realize that I I definitely didn't say
this in class that um she says most
notation formats focus on one of these
or represent music representations focus
on one of these things so yeah
definitely the CD um you know focused on
sound and the um you know the this PDF
of Music focuses on graphics and things
like that but um the the one way that
that article has aged is that now
nowadays we have so many formats that
try to do encode two or more of these
things together so that you might have
music XML which is encoding some pixel
placements of notes also and also
encoding um you can do links to the to
the waveform of something and even um
going from CD to MP3 and modern formats
yes it encodes the sound but it also
encodes some of the metadata the year
composed and things like that and
nowadays they can even be um putting you
know recommendations to other songs or
something like that cool okay let's
let's let's come back because with um
want to want to make some things we've
been been in theory mode for too long
um so
we last class we ended by doing some
algorithm composition with random walks
and so I just um here's a random walk
composition that I wrote in 10 minutes
once and I always want to say one or two
things on it maybe you hate it maybe you
like it
[Music]
so one of the things I did in my
aesthetic on the piece just to say a a
few little things on it is that I gave
um a large amount of gravity toward
whatever note which to kind of transpose
to make it more dissonant whatever note
something started on when it went away
it was really really likely to get
pulled back to where it came from so
that's why you'll see just a few things
that kind of get perturbed out of way
and then as the piece goes on in within
each section the gravity got weaker and
weaker and so that kind of let it have
um I don't know kind of the opposite of
a linian global rule that things got um
a little bit farther out as it went the
other thing that um I couldn't believe
when I when I first I was like oh I
think this will be a good idea write the
code write the code generate you know
put and it sounded just a mess tot maybe
it still sound like a mess to you but um
but putting in these art uh staccato
marks made all the difference for making
it more of a percussion percussive piece
so you can um do things like that if you
want your pieces to be a little bit more
uh interesting yeah is there some form
of articulation label that you could use
to avoid having to seado every note
um you could yeah in in modern thing you
would say um you dot dot dot then you
probably say stat Sim staccato similarly
staccato throughout or probably you
would just tell a performer you know if
you're talking about actual humans all
notes smaller than whole notes are stua
tiimo or
something is is it possible to implement
that in this graphical
software uh or does the med play not
recognize it doesn't recognize when you
when you start talking to the thing
you'll ever more expressive as it goes
yeah the midi just ignores that um for
the most part I mean maybe that's the
Great learn uh large language model uh
thing to the the first the first thing
that takes a mer score it's midi and
give it all of the his rehearsal
marks all that stuff it's like oh I must
I must turn myself into fire and perform
this uh in this way and yeah maybe that
would be kind of interesting uh I
thought of that thanks for the idea um
yeah so so we don't have that type of
thing besides when you're doing
computation things one one of the things
is it's pretty cheap to you know in a
loop put staccato on every single
thing yeah great so anyhow want to spend
time of that just a little um amuse Bo
before getting to go ahead and open up
Jupiter
um give you a second or two
and we got we're sort of uh have a bunch
of little things that we haven't uh
gotten to yet that I want to make sure
that um that we can get to um reminder
that the problem set is sort of a
Russian nesting doll of unlocking tools
so that please pay very close attention
on each of the questions on what tools
have been unlocked but um if I'm telling
you well you now have access to cord now
you have access to Roman numeral I
should at least introduce these to you
right I can't remember if I introduce
chord very briefly um or if
um or if if we didn't I maybe I don't
think we did um probably need some other
things uh I'm going to import chord note
pitch for now so go ahead and do that I
put the screen down even it's all good
um okay so what the the hardest way that
you can create a chord is let's say C
equals note. note C I'm giving you the
hardest way so maybe you don't want to
do this because I'm going to give you
the easier way in a bit or if you just
get behind um note G oh I should
probably give them octaves shouldn't I
C4 E4
G4 and then we'll say CH for chord cha
um remember that chord is a bad name for
variable chord. pitch chord. chord uh
lowercase chord indicates it is
a module uppercase means class good and
so we're getting object to that so we
could do c
oops apparently there's a button for
Google
search uh
ceg and do
that um the other thing that you can do
and you can actually thank Dimitri
tachko for for bugging me on Mike why
can't I just do this okay
so that's more often how you're how
you're going to doing things when you're
coding here but obviously um when you're
doing something
algorithmically quite often you're going
to have notes you can also start with
pitches
here um some of the things to say chords
uh you can iterate over them for thing
in ch print
thing and you get the
notes and that each of the notes are
there you can change um the duration of
one note in a chord and not the other
but uh that doesn't work to to too well
you're um let's create a second
chord weird equals chord. cord oh I
don't know uh
E3 G5
five uh what are we going to do let's
put in uh
[Music]
D7
C 8 it's a pry weird chord I know I'll
put in a B9 in there just because I know
exactly what that will put in uh this is
the the function that you're going to
wish you had access to on one of them
the root function
we I'll kind of get that uh this one
might not have a
name common name diminish minor ninth
chord is that
correct we
doow that one went too high okay let's
let's oh because it's an E3 no that
actually might be correct because it has
to fit it all on one staff when you do
this maybe instead of e3 um let's say e
four
five six H octaves don't matter five
five six six it'll sort it for
us yeah that looks a little bit better
uh easier though
is uh close and weird guess I'll call it
equals weird do closed position
oops okay
and so who remembers what closed
position is from 301 or something like
that
yeah it's yeah it's all within within
one octave um there's actually two
different um things some some
definitions allow the base note to be in
a different octave and um and then the
but that the top notes are all as close
together as you can get yeah and that
that can be pretty useful for an
analysis type of task
right so we can oh let's we'll choose a
different um Bo piece today I'm I'm
sorry I'm not keeping up my promise to
do uh a bit more than just Bach but it
make does make things go a little bit
faster this will say Bach equals Corpus
so I'm importing Corpus sorry um I
should be talking around Corpus
bwv 269 this is going to be one of our
favorite ones uh coming up for a
bit I think it's 269 do I have the right
template out yep
great right
um and um so one of the things we can do
is we can get so what I call it Bach
let's do bach.
cify
doow thank you we've encountered this
but we haven't really talked about it
very much and I'm going to need to zoom
out for a second or you can do this on
your own or maybe I'll I'll just do this
bach. measures so we remember this BRS
with a pickup yep 0 through four. show
cify is slow enough so you probably
shouldn't call it every single time
bo. in fact might as well make the one
the part that's faster uh go first bl.
measure 04. cify doow you don't have to
am I going too fast
today yes I am good thank you for having
the courage to nod we do it so we're
going to do the same thing
and I just want to make sure that we can
kind of get I can't really tell tell if
that's a g but it does look about but
that does look about an octave below
that note and I do know that that's a g
and so yep so it's taking at every
moment what's sometimes called a salami
slice which is to say every time
something changes there is a new chord
created so we can see here that there's
nothing that changes here in between
here and here so this is a chord this is
a chord but here this will need to be
made into two chords in order to um deal
with it and we can kind of see here that
this works um it's rather hard to figure
out what chords these things are so what
did we just learn yeah what's MXL um
it's it's a music XML format that um
that is compressed music XML it's kind
of nice that music XML all compressed so
um
music XML takes up a a lot for um
notation format not a lot for video
format or something um not a lot for
something in the sound domain but a lot
for something in The Logical domain um
things so but it compresses incredibly
well anybody who um who works on
compression algorithms might find that
interesting so a lot of people compress
their music XML good question okay so
what's something we can we just learned
that we can do to um to help make this a
little bit easier to
read to figure out what chords are
happening get after to compress yeah yep
somebody want
to what was use to compress the chords
just learn close position good so let's
say uh CHF for cified is
Bach dot here we'll just make we'll just
do a little ex 0 through four. cify
and make sure that that's the same as
before I did type it right yep okay so
how am I going to do
this actually let's let's before I do
that let's just look at it in um text
show.
text an instrument 3 four yep and we
have all these chords within measure so
we want to put all of these chords into
Clos
position what's our favorite three
letter
word that we're going to start with four
four great so let's do this
um
for my chord in what what do we call
that we call that CHF for CHF do
something whisper to your neighbor what
the answer should be and then we'll shut
it out
who votes for the next who votes for the
next thing being a
Colin no nobody who votes for
recurse who votes for
flatten who gos for something
else okay something else but bracket the
cord class ah yeah bracket on the cord
class which is equivalent to anyone
remember recurse recurse and get
Elements by class so yeah that would be
really really great the other thing by
the way this is a case where flatten
isn't going to be too bad either because
we don't really care what order we're
getting them we're going to put them all
into closed position um so for my chord
in this thing we can do something like
this um we say Clos
position oh shoot
but that returns a new thing and we
don't have a stream to put it in um a
lot of these things that that change
streams and change chords and stuff like
that has an in place
option it also has something Force
octave and we'll say Force octave equals
four and that's something that's pretty
useful that says now you're shrinking
everything to be within one octave let's
not have you do your own transpose
function or something after there just
put it all into four so hopefully this
works I don't should that be running
close position on my cour not oh thank
you thank you the this class is like a
like a running um example of how two
people coding code uh faster than two
two people coding together code more
code faster than uh than two people
coding separately maybe not 17 well it's
probably too many but yeah um so they I
haven't
figure out the time to fix this the tie
algorithm when you do close position
because obviously it's kind of cool that
it finds that oh there's there's a tie
that was opened but then this got moved
to here something so great so now we
have a certain number of chords here um
that're Happening Here uh what key do we
think the piece is in now that we can
see it more
easily g g g major good good and so now
we can start putting Roman numerals on
things what we call this in G major the
first
one four four four six four in first
inversion six six
yep six five first inversion five first
inversion now then there's certain
things that we have to be like o but was
that we go all the way back up to
here no okay good that it what's hard to
tell is if that was a passing tone or if
that was which one of these two was the
passing tone in that case can you see my
pointer yeah which one of those two is
the passing tone there great so we can
go um there and we can do this here
we'll get to how we can have the
computer do all this for us in just a
bit
um questions or anything I should go a
little bit more slowly yeah John if we
four OCT to be four in fifth OCT why do
we have some notes in the fifth off
that's that's great it what it says is
it forc the lowest note to be an octave
4 and so since it it can go up to an
octave um yeah so that's that's the the
case where it's the highest here it does
mean if you do uh compositions where
you're putting chords in closed
positions and jumping them around uh it
can it can sound very jumpy so that's
one examples here great
any I think else I should have been
going with this let
me okay um let's dur the chord class for
a
second chord.
chord oops actually I should be just
during the one of the
chords so some of the things um are are
things that you've already seen um
because chords are music 21 object
obviously they have a duration you know
how to deal with it they don't have a
DOT pitch object they have a attribute
they have a DOT pitches which gives you
all the pitches there but there's some
kind of um things can be tonic can this
chord be a tonic in some
key what chords can be
tonics what kinds of chords what
equivalence class of
chords major major chords and minor
minor chords great super so um that's
some of the things um does the chord
contain a seventh I think weird does
right do
contains
seventh true but um do we still have
that first one yep CH contains seventh
so you'll find that there's all these
slightly useful things in here um I
don't know what see is it an augmented
Triad is an augmented sixth is it a
French augmented six is a half diminish
augmented sixth a l of these things here
is it transpositionally symmetrical
these things come up um quite a bit and
you can put the same pitch more than
once into a cord so sometimes you want
to remove the Redundant pitches
redundant pitch classes and so
on um sometimes you might have weird
chords that you want to respell and so
on so these are some of the things that
are kind of useful in here and um if we
want to talk about uh on top ology
errors here CH do3 gives you the third
ch. fth gives you the fifth and ch. base
gives you a bound method of something so
that's something I wish I I wish I could
figure out how to change that these were
done differently early on and it's a
little too late sometimes to change
things just like it's a little too late
to change how certain words in English
are
spelled Okay cool so that's the end of
the introduction to chords unless
there's people want to do something with
this
them what's that Roman numeral Roman
numerals we'll get to Roman numerals in
just just a second so great so we're
definitely going to get to Roman
numerals but first a small um a small
leftover from um from our work on um
cognition and keys and the probone
method by anyone know if you know the
author what Carol Carol Kum hunel great
yep uh py was one of the people who who
referenced um this yeah the proone
method by uh crun Crum hunel car Crum
hunel um and so we're going to do is I'm
going to get us two two pieces here um
you don't have to um do this part if you
don't you you actually at this point in
the semester you don't have to type
anything that I'm typing unless it's
helpful for you maybe in the first part
is good so this is the um a particular
little jig we're going to be working
with a lot of jigs um in the next time
that we do some coding together so
that's a nice little 98 jig a little bit
unusual uh what what key does it look
like it's
in yeah you always have to you can let
let people give us chance to to do it
yep major here and
um and then we'll get a piece by the
20th Century composer Arnold schernberg
um schernberg
Opus uh s h o n b r g slop
us19 movement 6 all on word I know it's
a little bit
hard I wish I had another title that we
can do it's a little piano
piece great and Adam what key is it
in no one
knows okay
um yeah so this is this is a rather
ambiguous piece you know just just so
you can get it a tiny bit in your ear um
just the first couple chords
[Music]
there's something wrong on there's a
cluff change
missing yeah I know there's something a
little bit wrong in in this encoding
anyhow um little bit ambiguous ambiguous
piece so what I want to do is let's get
into uh unlocking some key analysis
things
so um what we can do is we we call it
jig right yep K1 our first key will be K
jig do analy analyze
key so
that's that's pretty good
now in addition to analyzing key there's
specific a number of people have um
implemented their own analysis thing so
we'll you'll have to get this so we're
going to run through a bunch of
different methods crom hunt the key the
standard key
method and um simple
so key is something I put a guarantee to
people using um using music 21 one that
that will be whatever I think is giving
the best results and I'll try to keep
improving it and get that Crum huntel is
exactly Carol k hunel um protone method
with the exact same things there um
which was learned it we learned the
different weights the different amount
um how important the tonic is how
important the third is how important the
fifth is and the key how did she learn
that proone protone so that she was
asking
people just just getting people's um
people's reaction to how far and out so
it's based on cognition the essn um one
was based on labeled keys for the entire
Essen folk song Repertory which you've
um we've used a couple times on things
uh and it's come up in this class quite
a bit and so people used that database
on the ones that were labeled in the key
to learn not from not from people but
from um what number of notes were in a
piece that was labeled as in F what
number of things were labeled as an e
and all of these weights by the way have
these weird um numbers like you know the
tonic 6.2
38 make it too much like Pi 2 pi or
something so these really long complex
um complex numbers on on things like
that um where Craig sap who's come up in
this class A couple times for making the
Rosetta Stone things I think it was
Craig sap who came up with a very simple
he's like no we we can we can just use
one 1 01 .5 and I think everything in
his waiting is either zero or .5 and
he's like it's much easier to remember
much easier to program and it works he
thought uh even better so we have all
these in here so we'll do this
um here you don't need to know python F
string formats but I'm going to give 20
letters for the method and then we'll
analyed using that method here actually
we'll just do
this key out I'll make this a little bit
easier to read so we'll
call Key out equals jig do analyze using
the method
oops method thank you I put method in a
string I'm a string of
methodists so when you put the jig into
there everybody agrees it's D
major that makes pretty good sense right
you would not trust any algorithm that
came up with a result other than D major
for this entire piece this is the whole
piece
right but let's see what happens when we
give it sherberg so I'm going to just
copy and paste the copy and paste method
for coding quickly in class and they
call Se I
think and here we end up with quite a
bit of
distinctions maybe E minor and a minor
aren't too far apart but we even have a
major key in there so depending on how
you do your waiting different things
could be better there's always the goal
of trying to come up with a better key
analysis routine and the other main uh
unsolved uh task in this domain is
pieces aren't always just in one key and
I'm not talking about Charles eyeses
with multi tonality and things talking
about pieces change Keys throughout the
piece and sometimes it's easy they
change the key signature at that moment
but quite often pieces change keys
without giving key signature can you
have a method that says well it begins
in E and then it goes to a then it goes
to C major and then it goes some other
place can you detect where all those key
changes are so that's something that
people have worked on it a little bit
but it's still an unsolved General
problem anything um any questions on
these types of
things by the way you can you can
there's a bunch of other things you can
use uh on analyzing like you can get the
pitch range and stuff like that
but that works oh and I'll just say on
this last one um key
out.
alternative was it I can never alt
alternate
interpretations gives you a list of so
this is one C major gives you a list
from the next most likely to by far are
the least likely in fact let's do that
on The Jig um we'll run The Jig one more
time um what do we call it K1 yeah so K1
is The Jig
key and K1 to Al alternate
interpretations yep so so if it's not in
D Major it might be in B minor yeah it
might be depending on what second
section is very unlikely to be an A flat
major
okay um great with the last 10 minutes
but I'm always happy to slow down
questions come back talk no okay sure
great so let's um let's get um what what
we all want which is Roman
numerals so go ahead and from music 21
import
Roman and try tring to find where I have
this
part broken
up here we go okay within Roman
um we can say RN equals roman. Roman
numeral what are the two parts of a
Roman numeral that computer's going to
need in order
to um in order to to figure out what
pitches there are sorry
the yep
and yep we'll call that the figure the
string representing things like one five
things and the key so what you can do is
if you had a key object I think we still
have one K1 we can pass that
in and get this four and D major the
other thing what what we'll often do
when we're coding in class is I'll just
give it a capital D for D major low D
would be D minor and that works just as
well if you're actually writing a
program unfortunately one of the least
optimized things is creating a new key
object it's about an order of magnitude
slower than it should be in an idealized
world so it is helpful to reuse your key
object if you're going to keep using it
over and over
again okay so we have Roman numeral four
in D
Major somebody this side of the room
what's what pitches are we going to be
expecting Roman numeral 4 in D
Major yep oh gbd gbd you g to say that
good good so what we can do is uh
gbd
and what octave should they be
in do that do that more gesturally so
that we can get back you went doesn't
matter it doesn't matter it doesn't
matter right so there's this weird thing
that happens that when we want to put a
pitch onto um you know onto a staff or
something we need to give it an octave
we need to sort of rify at that moment
but it doesn't matter
right so um here's the first question on
on this is what kinds of when we say
that um we have the same Roman numeral
here as the same Roman numeral here what
what kinds of equivalence classes are we
talking
about if I say that you know well Roman
numeral four equals Roman numeral
4 want to throw through some equivalence
classes on pitches or
notes somebody throw an easy one we just
because we just said one octave octave
good so that's definitely one
yeah go peration permutation yeah it
doesn't really matter what order there
uh there's I'll come back with octave on
on just just a little bit because
there's the caveat but later so everyone
try to figure out caveat on that um what
else cardinality right I mean is I
almost wrote on that
um yeah because
this is one in C major but so is this
and so is this and so is this doesn't
really matter how many notes we have
good now when we're just talking about
uh Roman numeral like four what's the
other thing that were that we sort of in
in there for what do you think about
yeah whether it's major or minor whether
it's major or minor yep so we have
something on
let's let's try to think some of these
things and um do we have the the same
blant um octave equivalent the one that
we've been thinking of that you've
already coded what's what's my caveat on
octave yeah like chord inversion chord
inversion yeah we have this this
different kind of inversion where this
is one
and this
is one first inversion one uh what is it
1 a 1 B if you're um if you're British
one six if you're American yep
um yeah so we um we have we have this
unusual um thing where which is very
usual for us as musicians or as people
have taken traditional class but a
little bit different for the um for that
well the Octave of this doesn't matter
in itself this could be you know we can
move this up to sorry this like all over
in the corner g e g c it's still one six
so there's something about the octave
that doesn't matter but there's sort of
we don't have we might say uh
base pitch equivalents so we always
going to be creating new equivalence
classes on things and so there's a very
unusual equivalence class we also have a
kind of limited
transposition equivalence class right
that I can write ceg and say it's one
but I can also
write D FSH a and call it one
as long as I say that one is one in C
major and one is one in D Major so that
there's kind of this abstraction out of
um that it's that transposition it's
measured according to distance from what
note not not not a note like C or
something a conceptual note tonic yeah
so we want to have things that are the
difference from the tonic
um so I think this might actually be
different on yours than um than on mine
because I'm running the beta version
that I haven't still haven't got the
bugs out uh so you can see Roman numeral
comes from some abstract class called
Harmony which also represents chord
symbols which I will not get to today
and um and it comes from chord I think
you're missing chord base probably for
most people
or maybe no it's there it's there okay
great couldn't remember what version got
that in great um so with our Roman
numeral four we can get back its figure
is four well that's you know not telling
you too much let's get another one we'll
call it
rn1
equals roman. Roman
numeral flat
26 in C major what's another word for
flat
26 remember flat major
26 don't worry if you don't know this
because this is something that some
people may know but it's the next
semester beyond the prere
yep it's traditionally taught the same
week as augmented sixth CHT so everybody
or the week before it
uh that's a type of it's named after an
emperor or no it's not it's named after
City a Neapolitan cord uh so it's named
not not Napoleon chord sorry named after
the city of Naples um very very cool
chord if we had two more minutes I would
play it um so here's something here uh
it's has a six at the end so what do we
call it what's the
inversion first inversion so you can
call inversion and put it as uh one see
it's a little bit strange that it has um
inversion takes some time to calculate
on very complex chords so it's uh method
but we can get that it's Roman numeral
alone this is a little bit wordy I
should have come up with it thing is
two and it's front
alteration
accidental is a
flat so um that it's a two with a flat
in front of it um
so one of the things we can do just
looking at the last moment let's we what
you'll probably be wanting is Roman
dot Roman numeral from chord so given a
chord and a key what's the Roman numeral
so uh we still have weird no we let's
start with ch in C
major my ceg is still there great what
would that be in here let's just do this
for for s
in a b CDE e
FG we'll print
this print the Roman numeral in the as
I'm using S for
step does that make that make
sense some odd odd chords in there right
but you can figure out these types of
things here and so we get um we can even
do roman. Roman numeral from chord I
almost always when I'm using this a lot
um abbreviate this so RN
rnfc FC equals that so I can just do it
romal from chord
weird oops should give it a
key here we go sharp one half diminished
flat 7 6 flat 5 flat 3 um so music 21
will try to find all these things for
you um I've kept you over so I'm not
going to uh show you how you can run
this on every cord in a Bo piece put it
as the dot lyric and then reshow the
piece we'll leave that as an exercise uh
for take home and um might come into a
class later so thanks everybody e