Here at the MIT research reactor, we do
research on finding new technologies
that could be used in nuclear energy in
the future. So, we're here in the
control room of the MIT research reactor
where we monitor the temperature and the
reactor power level and other parameters
to make sure that everything is running
smoothly. So, the goal of nuclear
engineering research is to take the heat
energy that's released from splitting
atoms and use it to make electricity
rather than using natural gas or coal
which are not as clean. We use the
reactor to test new materials. These new
materials that we test here could be
used to build stronger and safer
reactors in the future. We may have
reactors that are on land. We may have
reactors that are floating in the ocean.
We could even have reactors that are
like batteries and sitting on every
street corner. As the price of natural
gas goes up, we may be relying more on
nuclear energy for electricity.
For more MIT moments from MIT Open
Learning, like, subscribe, or follow.