The following content is provided under
a creative common license. Your support
will help MIT Open Courseware continue
to offer high-quality educational
resources for free. To make a donation
or view additional materials from
hundreds of MIT courses, visit MIT Open
Courseware at ocw.mmit.edu.
Some content in this audio is not
covered under our creative common
license. For more information, see the
course materials on the MIT Open
Courseware website
>> to a uh who's going to uh uh give us a
guest lecture on on art games. And uh
today's reading uh the the proc reading
is kind of like part two of a lot of
things that uh Jason Begley talked about
uh when we did simulations. So um kind
if you guys remember his talk while you
were reading that that that sequest and
what that came from. Um, one thing that
I actually forgot to address was that
there are actually a couple of uh
responses to that uh to that article. If
you scroll all the way down to the
bottom of the article, there's these
responses by Arisman and Mizuki and him
back to them. And uh those are kind of
interesting uh you know because it just
sort of carries on a conversation and
people are actually just sort of turning
his article into basically a blog post
and then writing comments. um and they
were pretty good but a lot of that was
kind of the state of art game discussion
back in 999 I think I think it's a
pretty old article um where they were
very much thinking about you know games
can games have to be simulations you
know games and narratives uh you know
storytelling is like some other mediums
do uh medium domain it's all about the
simulation um and um and arguably at
that time there wasn't a big discussion
of an art games movement. There were
other games movements like new games
like like like new games which were
really more about uh people interacting
with trying to get games to where people
were more cooperative, less competitive
and less cut through. Um there were
other mo there were movements about um
people um there were probably
advertising game movements and there
were there were a lot there was a lot of
work in people making mods of computer
games that effectively made it
unplayable but made really pretty images
in the process. Um so that there was a
Doom hack for instance where everything
becomes black and white and and is
striped including the monsters. It's
like there's no way they can see what
the hell's going on but they look pretty
cool. Um,
>> yep.
>> Have you seen I think it's 96 kilobytes.
>> There was a competition to make a full
game in a really really small size. No,
it's 4 kilobytes I think and it's a 4
kilob game in full 3D with multiple
levels and they have extremely cle
including the music and everything
>> like Yeah.
>> And have you ever heard of this or seen?
>> There are a couple of those u and a lot
of those come out from the demo scene.
Uh the demo scene uh which I will put
off to some other
>> very artsy too. It's like very
>> Yeah. It it it's kind of this weird
thing of like computer hacking, really
really fast and really really compact
coding and visual aesthetics and music.
Uh which you know it's more of like a
digital music video. Um only there was
some people who added a mouse control
and gameplay into it and made these tiny
little games. Um but uh that that was
pretty much art that that's very
different from the art game scene that
we have today or at least what is
commonly described as our games. So, uh,
I, um, I'd like to aid to talk about
kind of what happened from, um, since
then, since, uh, since 99.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, hi guys. I'm I'm, uh, Abe. Uh,
I work here at the lab. I've played a
bunch of your games. I've met a bunch of
you. Um, so it's it's nice to be here.
Philip uh, asked me to come in to talk
about, uh, quote unquote art games. Uh I
think largely because it's a kind of um
uh I'll say sector of kind of game
development that uh my work at Gambit
tends to intersect with um especially
recently. Um and I think too that it's
um
>> sorry
I don't know. I think too that it's um I
think too that it's a uh it's kind of a
sector that's that's a little bit
confused and um and possibly confusing
too. And so um just to give you guys a
sense um you know when he asked me about
this it actually made me it kind of made
me think cuz I was like oh yeah cool.
I'll talk about like this art games
movement or whatever but you know then
of course um wait I'm locked into some
kind of weird mode right now.
Sorry. Okay. Um that brings up this
question which is which is our games
art. And just to um just to kind of give
you a a sense for how this this little
talk thing whatever is going to go um
I'm going to talk a little bit about
this question um give you kind of
examples of what people have said about
this um and opinions that I think are
particularly important particularly
valid on this subject. Um I also after
that want to show you some examples um
some historical and then kind of moving
forward examples. I'm actually going to
get some of you guys to to just come up
here and maybe even play some of these
examples that I think are particularly
important. And and I'd really like it if
we can kind of keep this less of a uh me
talking at you and and you engaging me
as you have questions on this because I
it's really like me you know blabbing at
you as you fall asleep is is um you know
maybe good for a nap but less useful for
um you know getting anything out of
this. Um, so we'll try to structure this
as a conversation and and I'll I'll try
to pull back hearken back to any of my
teacher instincts and see if I can get
you engaged, but we'll see. Um, so our
game's art I um I hate this question.
Uh, I will start off by saying that I
fundamentally and I find it abhorent and
I hear it all the time. Um, and it's
aggravating to me because I think it's
it's incontrovertibly yes. Um I think
that you can't possibly come up with any
other answer other than yes, games are
art, games have art. Yes. Yes. Yes.
Right. But um it keeps coming up and it
keeps kind of becoming a question. And I
should say too that this is a um this is
a wholly biased and uh slanted talk.
This is this is my perspective on this
and hopefully by the time you're done
you'll be like wow he is absolutely
right. There is no way that games could
be anything but art. Um or at least they
are art and then some. Um, so, um, this
guy, um, who's a little hard to see
right now, but he's totally blown up.
Um, recently brought this into the for
um, and that's, uh, that's Roger Eert
of, uh, Eert System Eert fame, or since
you guys are some of you younger than
me, probably Eert and Roer. Um, and he
had some interesting and controversial
comments recently. Um, and I I pulled
this quote. Nevertheless, I remain
convinced that in principle, I love that
he put that in uh italics. Video games
cannot be art. Perhaps it is foolish of
me to say never because never, as Rick
Wakeakeman informs us, is a long, long
time. Let me just say that no video
gamer now living will survive long
enough to experience the medium as an
art form. Um, so apparently we should
all be dead already, um, according to
Eert because we wouldn't have lived long
enough to experience the medium as an
art form. But here's a guy who um even
though I don't think he's a particularly
good film critic, he's a popular film
critic and he's kind of weighing in on a
medium that he doesn't particularly
understand. And I think it's important
to look at what exactly is he doing when
he makes this statement. And so he's in
this kind of business of classification,
right? He's in this business of saying,
"All right, well, we've got this subject
called art. What can we say falls under
that subset and what what what does
not?" And so, you know, he says things
like painting, sculpture, dance, opera,
literature, film um can all be
classified as art and and that games um
games are not. Um probably some other
things. I don't know where he stands on
comic books. I don't think he's written
about it yet, but I'm sure he can
probably I don't know where he what he
thinks about pornography. Um although
since it's in film form, maybe he does
think it's art. It's unclear. He hasn't
he hasn't weighed in on that yet. Um but
the interesting thing about this is this
is not this is not new, right? This is
like a high culture, low culture debate
that's been going on for a really long
time. And I think it's particularly
hilarious because he reviews films and
films had to fight out of the low
culture phenomenon to gain respect as a
high culture medium, right? And so he's
he's working reviewing a medium that
that was once conceived as low culture,
had to work really hard to be considered
high culture. And now he's saying,
"Look, my films are high culture, your
video games are low culture." um which
is totally hilarious because you know in
the past 50 years um this has been
completely collapsed by postmodernism
right but this is a this is that's a
whole another talk alto together right
like maybe high culture and low culture
don't even exist anymore um so Ebert
brings this all back and he get
everybody upset and a bunch of trolls
are on his website saying really
terrible things about him and about what
he said but he he kind of reinvigorated
this talk um and so a new scientist
inspired by this eert controversy and
looking for content um on culture lab
asked the question can games VR and they
sent it out to a bunch of game scholars
saying what what is your opinion on
this? Um and Ian Bogost is is a is a
very smart guy and and said says you
know some really interesting things.
This is really long. I'm not going to
read the whole thing but in the first
paragraph you know he brings up things
like fountain uh by Marcel Duchamp which
is you know a urinal um in a museum for
those of you who don't know about it.
And that was, you know, that was a
statement, a piece of art that he was
literally trying to confront what what
high culture defines as art by taking
literally a urinal, putting it upside
down on art and titling it fountain,
upside down on a pedal and titling it
fountain and putting it in a museum,
which is the pinnacle of high culture,
right? If you can make it in a museum,
your art. Um, and so, you know, this is
something that, you know, that he did.
He he mentions Yoko Ono's performance
art where, um, she's sitting in a chair
um, and she has scissors next to her and
the audience is invited to come uh, cut
her clothes off one piece at a time. um
you know a lot of this kind of stuff you
know uh Andy Warhol pop culture
paintings um you know Mandrean's uh kind
of uh you know abstract paintings and
and um you know he says a lot in that
first paragraph but I think this this
interesting part that I sort of pseudo
highlighted down here is interesting um
starting in the middle he says if the
purpose of art is indeed to force us to
see something we thought we understood
in a new light perhaps the most
fundamental move video games have made
in the artistic tradition is in the very
eliciting of the question can video
games be art I I think that's really
interesting, right? So, the fact that
people are even asking this question
suggests that video games are doing
something that aren't we traditionally
conceive of aren't doing. Um, and so
that's, you know, that's I think a
really kind of powerful statement that
that we're even having this discussion.
It kind of renders the question question
moot in some senses, which which is, you
know, kind of I would say classic Bosian
um word play. Um, I think I just made
something up called Bosian.
tweet him about. Um, so John Sharp from
the Savannah College of Art Design um
has had a lot of kind of thoughts on
this. He's and he's actually a great
person to talk about this because he
studies video games, but he does it from
an art history background as well,
right? And that's particularly useful.
Um, and uh, you know, he talks about
some interesting things here. He talks
about, you know, similarly similarly to
what Ian was doing. He's talking a bit
about how um you know video games and
art are are kind of doing some similar
things at times and yet games you know
have certain affordances that other
media do not. Um and so uh he says at
the end here which I think is
interesting all this poses the question
of why are we concerned with giving
video games the status of art? This is
one of the reasons why I hate this
question. Are we simply trying to
legitimize them? Does being called quote
unquote art change the qualities of
video games? Um only if we can answer
these questions can we move the
conversation forward? And I I think he's
you know he's reacting here to the
question itself. Actually he and Ian
both are kind of reacting to the
question. Ian saying the question
invalidates itself and John Sharp now
saying that we need this question it's
not helping us asking you know how does
calling it art what does that do for the
medium? That's the important question
right and so here's some some thoughts
about the question and and some kind of
more evidence for why I think the
question are video games art is just h
makes my spine problem. Um, Mary
Flanigan uh sort of takes it uh takes it
as being assumed that video games are
art, which I think is actually great. In
Critical Play, she doesn't go to great
lengths to define video games as art.
She just looks at art and she looks at
games and and compares them. Um, and she
just kind of assumes that this is so and
I think this is a really nice quote from
from really the beginning of her
critical playbook. Um, where she says,
"Critical play is built on the premise
that as with other media, games carry
beliefs within their representation
systems and mechanics." This is really
important. artists using games as a
medium of expression. Again, good use of
italics. Um, then manipulate elements
common to games, representation, systems
and styles, rules of progress, codes of
conduct, context of perception, winning
and losing paradigms, ways of
interacting in a game. For they are the
material properties of game, much like
marble and chisel or pen and ink bring
with them their own intended
possibilities, limitations, and
conventions. It's a great point. You
would have a really hard time making a
painting with a chisel um and no paint,
right? Like if you were using marble and
a chisel and you were trying to make a
painting, right? Two different things.
Both are art. It's the same thing with
games, right? Games have rule sets.
Games have systems. Uh games have, you
know, win loss paradigms. They have all
these things that are um kind of
conventions and and things that we
associate with with even our definition
of what a game is, which is at times
faulty. Um but but those are our tools.
Those are how we communicate things. And
I think her first sentence is really
important. And um I'm guessing with the
with the stuff that you've been talking
about with them and Gonzalo Frasa um you
know that that's kind of coming through
and and I actually see that in your
games right you're trying to so for
example I I play tested that FedEx game
and I play tested um the game about
marriage right and there's there's all
kinds of meaning in those systems and
meanings in those choices that you get
um that that are being communicated and
that's that's very similar to what an
artist would do with with any other
medium right you're you're communicating
a message through those and and and
sometimes we do it accidentally it's
it's not always explicit Right. It's
like we we make something. I I always
say that the the um the graveyard and
when you get divorced and you put your
your divorced person in the graveyard
was an interesting choice for me because
it was creating an equivalence between
divorce and death which I think is kind
of interesting. Um so that's just you
know kind of one interesting example. Um
so Mary Flang in her book talks about
this art movement called Plexus. Before
I go on any kind of thoughts or
questions does anybody else think does
anybody think video games aren't art
still? It's okay. Oh crap, I'm gonna
fight.
>> Totally different. Like when we were
designing our so our project now is you
have to choose a real world
>> system and emulate it.
>> That's what we're all working on.
>> Yeah.
>> And one of the big things like that
really helped us get started was like
what is the message we want to get
across? So we chose evolution was what
is it about evolution? Do you want to
say that it's random? Do you want to say
that as this? And how do we express
that? How we got into it.
>> Yeah. No, totally. And it gets even it
gets even crazier when you take when you
try to look at systems that are not
particularly tangible, right? So, you
know, um maybe you've looked at it, but
um you know uh Elude is a game about
depression, right? Like there there
there aren't exactly tangible kind of
road maps the way there are with like
FedEx systems for for clinical
depression, right? And yet yet if you're
looking at things like emotions,
feelings, um stuff like that that we
might we might call abstract or or um
just non- immediate um how do you how do
you uh how do you communicate those in
systems? Right. It's really tricky.
>> I find this is a tougher argument for
games which are like more games of
chance or more abstract
zoker art.
>> Yeah, I mean it's it's a really good
question.
>> What do you what do you say about that?
Yeah. I mean, and I think that falls
along the same lines as like, you know,
like like I said, I mean, does does
Ebert consider pornography art? I mean,
it's it's like a really difficult
question. And that's that's such a much
kind of a much larger kind of art
history debate, right? About like about
has high culture and low culture
completely collapsed? Has mass media
proliferation like deteriorated
conceptions of, you know, of what, you
know, really high culture art are versus
low culture? And and and I think that's
um I I don't have particularly good
answers for that. You know, I think just
as as all of the other media that we
look at, like does a Jerry Brookheimr
film count as art, right? Just like we
would look at that and ask that
question. Um, we don't then, you know,
deny the entire medium of film from from
the possibility of being artistic. Um
there seems to be this desire because
the majority of games in our sector um
which I actually completely disagree
with too because if you go far back
there they're most I should say video
games but um because most video games
are are kind of commercially intended
and involve you know fairly similar
themes right does that you know preclude
the medium from the possibility of being
artistic um you know and I go back to
that Eber kind of comment about like you
know he he he says they they they can't
possibly be or at least you know he says
never is a long time but not in our
lifetime apparently. Is it possible? So,
no, it's a good point. Good question.
>> So, there was actually an interesting uh
effects with us the game that we're
designing, which is essentially like
city building and city creation in in
the time of like the Roman Empire.
>> Uh, and we actually didn't intend to
like instill any meaning in the game,
but once we actually designed the
mechanics and stuff, we realized that it
was essentially a game about the rich
getting richer and trying to control the
poor. So, it's like there's almost this
like inherent meaning that came out from
just designing the game.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And you almost can't help,
right, but but have it happen in some
instances. It reminds me of a good thing
of um that uh Brenda Brathweight put in
one of her talks once which was about
the game uh civilization the the mod
colonization for Civ 4 which is a great
mod in which you play one of the
European colonizers and you come over to
the new world and um you know there's uh
there's indigenous peoples there and you
have to kind of negotiate with them at
first but eventually they just kind of
um you either beat them up and take
their land or they just give it to you
because you're more powerful than they
are. She was making the point, you know,
there's this great box art with like the
Native Americans in the corners and like
the concistador in the middle, you know,
the Spanish and the Dutch. And it's
like, if you were a Native American, how
would you respond to this game, right? I
mean, it's like I'm like, "Yeah, I'm I'm
totally making America again, you know,
and other people would be like, "Oh my
god, you basically just, you know, wiped
out my ancestors. Thanks." Um, so it it
it's true. I mean, you kind of sometimes
you fall into meaning. It's it's
something that does. And I think, you
know, again, a lot of art does that,
right? And some art did it quite
purposely. um you know where they
weren't divulging the meaning they were
inviting readings of it. Um so Fluxus
Fluxus is this um this really
interesting uh mid- 20th century art uh
they they rejected the term movement.
They called it an attitude. Um that Mary
Flame talks about a bit in her in her
critical playbook and it's actually
quite interesting. It's it really starts
out early with with John Cage. Have you
guys heard of him? The composer. Um he's
most famous for this piece of music that
he wrote where I forget the duration.
It's like 633.
>> It's four 4 minutes and 33 seconds of
not well like not playing. Right. Like
Yeah. He rests. Exactly. So you'd sit
down at the piano and you'd pull out the
music and everyone would hush and then
for 4 minutes and 33 seconds you'd sit
there possibly with your hands on the
keys and then after the time you would
stand up, you'd take your bow and the
audience would erupt into you know
incredible applause. Um but he was
really kind of testing the idea of what
they what they eventually kind of called
scores or event scores, right? This idea
that like music um music is an art form
where you can kind of uh write it down
and then it becomes performable, right?
it becomes this kind of thing um that
someone can engage with and and um we
don't think of paintings that way. We
don't think of paintings as having a
score, having some kind of you know how
do I engage with this, right? It sounds
kind of like games. They're they're you
know figuring out how does interactivity
work in artistic mediums? Um really
interested in indeterminacy too. Um I
mean I think you'll see in some of these
examples that they're they're really
kind of pushing on the boundaries of
what um of what what art has been doing
to this point. Uh they call it
intermedia uh meaning that the more kind
of um multiple modes that you can use
for for communicating it. Um was really
important to the to the attitude. Um
simplicity was really big right having
you know having kind of basic basic
systems and and basic kind of scores.
And then this idea of play um was really
kind of important. Um Yoko Ono, it's
funny, you know, we sort of just
attached her to John Lennin, but she she
was an artist before she was um you
know, just in a relationship with him,
and she's actually kind of well known as
one of these kind of Fluxus
practitioners. Um this is interesting.
This is the Fluxus manifesto. Um I kind
of wanted to just put this up because I
think you can get a little bit of a
sense for what they were trying to go
for. So um you know they were taking the
word fluxus and or flux and you know
putting the definition but then they
were kind of amending it here. So you
know purge the world of bourgeoa
sickness uh intellectual professional
and commercialized culture. Purge the
world of dead art, imitation, artificial
art, abstract art, illusionistic art,
mathematical art. I like this. Purge the
world of Europeanism.
Don't even know if that's a word. Um
>> yeah. Promote a revolutionary flood and
tide in art. um promoting art, anti-art,
non-art reality. I mean, these things
these things sound like totally crazy,
right? I love the I love the to be fully
grasped, but then it crosses out fully,
right? And and that I don't doubt that
that was completely intentional. Or if
they wrote fully grass, we're like, "Oh,
this is going to be great, right? I'm
crossing out so you can see that I
crossed out fully grasped." We want it
to be not fully grasped, you know? We
want to be partially grasped by all
people. Um not only critics, um talks
and professionals. So, um and it's just
a really interesting thing. And this
sort of like screams kind of the avant
guard, right? They were trying to like
push against boundaries. They're trying
to figure out what is the edge of the
medium and then how can we how can we
just like, you know, jump way off it.
And um
some of the classic fluxist works were
these things called flux boxes or flux
kits. Um and flux kits tended to have
event scores. This is one of the most
famous called Water Yam by George Breck.
Um and basically this is a box with 70
event scores. Um, and these are an
example of kind of event scores. And and
it's interesting. I mean, event scores
really seem like rule systems, right?
Like they're like the instructions to
your board game. Um, except they're
they're kind of wacky. I mean, if you
look at you look at air conditioning,
um, the the rule is move through the
place. Um, which is really interesting.
I mean, if you encounter this game and
you're like, "All right, I'm going to
play water jam." And then you pull out
air conditioning, you're like, "Move
through the place." Um, and I think
that's kind of, you know, pretty
characteristic of the movement, right?
present you with some sort of objective
or some sort of um some sort of
requirement, but one that is kind of uh
abstract or nebulous or just, you know,
kind of strange. This one's even better.
Um on a white chair, a great tape
measure, alphabet, flag, black, and
spectral colors. Um in this instance,
it's not even clear what you're
necessarily supposed to do. Are you
supposed to compile these things on a
white chair? Um you know, are you
supposed to sit on a white chair and
hold all of these things? Um it's not
it's not particularly clear. And um and
this is this is you know this is the
playfulness of this movement. This is
kind of the the energy of this kind of
uh avantgard movement. Um
you can see kind of the relationship I I
hope between kind of rule systems and
these the next example is I think
another one but but you can see how
they're kind of playing around with
these ideas. At least they're
incorporating interactivity into these
art pieces, right? And keep in mind
these are these are being shown in
galleries. These are being shown in high
art places, right? These are um being
sent out to their friends as as works of
of art. Um this one's great. Um this is
white chess by Yokoono and and it's
often kind of depicted on its own and
you have to imagine what the rules are,
but I actually think her rules as they
are written are actually pretty
important to it. So she says, "Play it
for as long as you can remember who is
your opponent and who is your own self."
Um very interesting wordage, but um so
what are the comp what are the
complications with white chess? Anyone?
Any thoughts based on your perceptions
of nonwhite chess or white and black
chess?
>> Yeah. Begin to argue, but that was my
pawn.
>> Yes. Yes. You definitely will be hard to
keep track of, I would think. Yeah. I
mean, that's why she said as long as you
can remember. Any other um any other
kind of weirdness from this?
>> Who is friend and who enemy?
>> Yeah. I mean, certainly, right? I mean,
this is sort of like, wait, was that my
piece? Was that your piece? Not only
does that complicate your relationship
to the other player, right? But but now
it's like to the game itself, it's like,
wait, what was the strategy I was doing?
>> Friendly fire.
>> Yeah. I mean, it's really hard to keep
track of stuff in chess. What about the
board?
>> You might swap the king and the queen by
mistake because you don't have
>> there's not really any like actual boxes
on the board.
>> Yeah, they're all they're all white,
right? So, I mean, that sort of
complicates things a little bit too,
right? Because you need to kind of
remember how you were moving. This one's
really big. This is like a garden
installment of of white chess. And I
think the cool thing too, I mean this is
another example of kind of the movement,
right? Um, as long as you have the
components, you could play this game.
You could create this art piece. I think
for Yokoa, the sense is not go play my
installation of white chess. It's that
this is the rules. These are the pieces.
It can be played. And that screams game,
right? I mean, that that that screams
that kind of portability of a game. Um,
and but again, you know, this was this
wasn't considered anything but art
except probably by people who, you know,
turned their nose at this sort of thing
anyway. stuff. Um
any thoughts on um any thoughts on what
what white chess could be uh you know
kind of about in a in a
>> two different sides between one and
>> to
eventually get why am I fighting? Why
who is my enemy in this situation?
>> Sure. Sure. Any other thoughts?
>> Yeah.
>> Racial relations.
>> Sure. Racial relations. I mean, there's
probably like a whole anti-war thing of
like, you know, are we actually
destroying ourselves?
>> Yeah. And and I mean, that's so that's
an interesting thing. Yokoono was a
decidedly um a decidedly kind of
anti-war activist in the time that she
was making this in the early 60s. I
mean, one thing that you can't take
anything for granted. The pieces aren't
all black, right? They're they're all
white. So, I think the race thing does
kind of play a factor. The inability to
remember who you're attacking and and
who who you are even. And I think that's
actually why I really like her words
because for as long as you can remember
who is your opponent and who is your own
self. There's something about
incorporating your own self in there.
Not just saying who you know what your
pieces are, right? She's not saying can
you remember what your pieces are. She's
saying you know remember who you're
playing against versus who you are. Um
that's very different verbiage. Um and
so it's it's it's I I think it's very
much a game about about who are you
fighting anyway? Um you know what is the
point of war? What is the purpose of
war? Um and how how does war
particularly function? Um, and in the
rhetoric of the time it it makes a lot
of sense, right? Um, so that's Yoko's
white chess, which is which is part of
the Flexus movement. Yeah, it's it's
pretty it's pretty cool. And actually,
Fluxus and and artists in this period
have a really interesting relationship
with chess. There's like some quote, and
I'm going to butcher it, but it was um I
think it was Marcel Duchamp saying that
not um not all chess players are
artists, but all artists are chess
players or something like that. he was
particularly fascinated with chess and
and you could see elements of chess in
his um in his work, you know, either
being, you know, painted or whatever.
And so
>> he was completely obsessed with chess.
He he was a he was he played it really
hard. He wasn't necessarily a very good
player, but he played it a lot.
>> Very into it. Um, so now I'm going to
kind of move out of this sort of Plexus
move and I just wanted to show you a
couple examples, but I think this next
one is actually sort of an interesting
this is a current game that I'm really
excited about, which is called um 16
Tons. Um, and this is a game I
unfortunately have not been able to play
yet, but I've I've witnessed play
because it's it's a game for four
players, but this was created by Eric
Zimmerman and Natalie Py. And it's um so
it's a really interesting game. It's a
little hard to see from these pictures,
but it's this giant circle, I would say,
almost the size of this room of
corrugated cardboard. Maybe even bigger,
a little bit bigger than this room. But,
um, inside you've got this kind of array
of colored um array of colored circles
in these pretty hefty steel uh steel
tubes that have color. Um, and let's
like let's go through the rules. I mean,
the first thing to notice is that they
they contextualize the title 16 tons
with a quote from the from the song. Um,
you load 16 tons and what do you get?
another day older and deeper in debt.
Um, so this is doing an interesting
thing that that actually, you know, John
Sharp, who you can actually see in the
middle, thinks is actually particularly
important for for games and games that
are kind of working in this art
movement, is that they declare their
intentionality. Um, whether they declare
what what their meaning is or not is
less important, but they to be taken
seriously, you need to take yourself
seriously, I think, was one of the
things he said. And and I think um, you
know, this is another great example. We
can talk about how other games maybe in
the digital space do this, but right now
they're already kind of priming you for
reading the rules in a way that is
different than just oo let's play,
right? I mean, could you imagine if
Monopoly had some sort of um you know,
like Marxist quote in the front of it or
something like that, right? Your
experience of it would be completely
different. So, um you set up, you put
the pieces kind of in this array. Um you
stand on a number and that indicates
what color you are. And this is great.
You take out $3. Although you can see in
uh in this second picture, they're
playing um what uh what Eric, the
designer, has deemed high stakes uh 16
times where you pull out three $5 bills.
Um and so it says how to win. You win
when the two pieces of your color are
directly adjacent to each other. Um so
diagonally adjacent does not count for a
win. The way you play is players take
turns starting with player one. When
it's your turn, you say, "Put me to
work." Uh players may then offer to pay
you one or more dollars in any order. So
anyone can just say, "I'll give you
this." um you have to accept the highest
payment except if there's a tie, right?
Because with, you know, with specific
denominations there's very likely to be
a tie. Then you get to choose which of
the highest biders um you can take and
the the person who pays then tells you
what move to make. Um and if no one
offers to pay you, you get to decide
what to do. Um and then it's the next
player's turn and you continue until one
player wins. Um,
just off the top of your heads, having
not even played it, um, it's tough to
critique games when you haven't played,
but just looking at the rules and
hearing about it and even kind of I love
that picture on the left because it it
embodies some of the kind of spirit of
the play, too. But, um, what are some
interesting things about this rule set
that you notice?
>> You play with money, but you don't win
money.
>> Well, that's an interesting question.
Uh, what happens to the money at the end
of the game? Who knows? Do you keep it?
That's unclear.
>> Very, very unclear. And that's one of
the things that's really great about
this game, right? Is that that it puts
you into these social situations where
now you're playing with real currency
that was your own. And now it's like,
well, what what happens to this, right?
And and so it says you win if your
piece, but maybe you you feel like you
win if you move the most pieces and you
have the most money at the end of the
game, right? I mean, you've got this
kind of weird economy in here. Um, and I
think the fact that it's not explicit um
in this rule set is great, right? Right.
I mean, that's that's what creates this
sort of potential for kind of an
interesting social dynamic. Other things
that are interesting about this game, if
you're the only person who has money,
then you basically you can basically win
if you're the only person who has money.
Yeah. So, it does require a little bit
of strategy, too. Um,
>> technically from this that setup, could
you win on the first turn? Because it
seems you only have do you have two only
two pieces of a certain color?
>> Yeah, but up on the right assume the
starting position.
>> Yeah, I know. And so you so on your turn
you could take one p your piece and and
have it be moved to the square right
next to yours.
>> No move to any Oh. Oh, you have to move
it.
>> Read the red.
>> Oh, any adjacent note. Okay.
>> I didn't read the adjacent adjacent
empty square. Um
>> that's actually really interesting.
>> Yeah, it's a really weird I mean there I
think the I also think the the you're
you're not you're the agency you have in
the game to to win is not by moving your
own pieces. It's by paying someone to do
the work for you, right? And so then we
kind of get back to this quote at the
beginning of the ego is 16 tons and what
do you get another day in deeper debt?
It's like what what is this game about?
I mean, it could be about a lot of
things. And I mean, we we we honestly
probably shouldn't dissect it until
we've played it. Um I think too the kind
of corrugated cardboard, it gets hot
inside of there if you're not outside.
And that's a really interesting thing
too, right? like you're in there, it's
hot, it's sweaty, you've got dirty money
in your hands, you're moving around
these fair, you know, sizable, they have
weight to them. That was really
important, too, right? I mean, this
could have been played around a table
with, you know, go pieces or something,
you know, painted go pieces, but these
are like, you know, these are
substantial steel pieces that you've got
to pick up and move. Um, and, you know,
obviously the well, the song was about
kind of manual labor. Um,
so this is a really interesting game.
This was this was released at the art
history of games conference last year
and it did well at indicate this year it
won the uh developers choice award. Um
and it's it's it's really cool. I want
to try to get it up to MIT so that we
can all play it.
>> It occurs to me that you could if you
play by rules where you keep the money
you get at the end of the game. You
basically could throw the game to get
all the money.
>> Yeah. I mean you could try you could try
right but but you know people are going
to know what you're doing you know and
people are going to see your strategy.
So it's it's
>> not going to pay you Jack.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I mean the multiplayer gets
the multi multiplayer the you know the
game gets in this. Um so I mean again
like just kind of cycling back to what
we're talking about. I mean is this art
you know it would be hard for me to call
it much of anything else. Um
so this is like one of my one of my
favorite games. Uh it's certainly my
favorite Jason Norade. Who's played
gravitation here? A couple of you. All
right cool. And a bunch of you haven't.
That's awesome. So I'll get one of you
to play it. Um, one thing I want to
point out with this, I mean, we can talk
after someone's played Gravitation a
little bit about um, uh, about, you
know, what we think about the game
itself, but but I think this quote is
interesting. You know, he has artist
statements with all of his games. Um,
some of them say more, some of them say
less. This one responded because this
was after Passage was released, and I
think you guys have all seen Passage,
right? And you can you can immediately
identify the aesthetic similarities
because the character is exactly the
same. Um, and he was responding to
criticism from people about his pixel
art and why did he go for pixel art? Um,
but he says, "I now see ultra- lowres
pixel art as a kind of digital
cartooning. It stands right on the line
between the symbolic and the
representational, leaving plenty of room
for viewer interpretation. Why draw
sideburns when the viewers can imagine
sideburns on their own? You just need to
give them something to pin their
imagination on, something to guide them
a bit. Cartoons are perfect for that."
And and I think that's a really
interesting point. And I think what he's
what he's also suggesting here, which is
maybe not clear, is that this is doing a
similar thing to what that quote from
the music does. It's priming your
experience of the play. Right? You load
up this game, you see that it's got this
low res pixel art that we now associate
with this kind of art, game movement,
and you're ready to read this in another
way. Um, if I gave you a firsterson
shooter, um, and told you nothing about
it except that it was going to be the
fastest, awesomest multiplayer
first-person shooter experience, but it
looked like this. Um,
you know, would you be inclined to read
it like an art game? I mean, I I don't
know. Um, but but certainly in this
instance with these kind of little
games, right, this this sort of pixel
art aesthetic um that you see being
duplicated in a lot of places is is sort
of um I don't know, priming the pump.
It's it's establishing some sort of
context in which you can read this game.
Um, so who wants to play uh gravitation?
Actually, let me Oops. No, that's not
supposed to happen. I wanted to click on
the link. Oh, because I clicked on my
screen, not this screen. And all it does
is take me out of here.
>> Me not being mirrored might be a
problem. Let's see.
Let's see what screen this loads up on.
Both one. Crap. Okay, hold on one sec. I
got to mirror my screen.
Um, I I should not be choosing who plays
who wants to. Uh, I can't make a choice.
Who wants to do it?
>> Interesting that it's a version zero.
>> Yes.
>> I have to explicitly make that the case.
>> Uh,
>> anybody. It's It's free. It's free to
download. So, if you don't play it now,
you can play it on your own.
>> We have a few games, right? So, what's
that?
>> We have a few games, right? So,
>> Oh, yeah. We have a few. So, yeah.
Getting a few different opportunities to
play. So, anybody jump over and and like
>> we'll start with Jason and then we'll do
kind of jumping into
>> and actually if you wouldn't mind
talking about your experience of playing
Gravitation as you play it, you know,
like like let's play the
>> the live gravitation.
[Music]
>> Okay. Oh, I seem to have restricted you
and it's falling.
>> Oh, it is falling.
>> Oh, wait. Oh, I
>> Oh, I know.
>> Oh, never mind.
She stole your ball. Oh, she plays with
you. She stole it.
>> I hate her. I stole her ball.
>> She seemed to like you, but she stole it
for a little bit, but now she seems to
be playing, which is better.
>> Yes. Hurry up.
>> We seem to be bouncing it back and
forth. My screen gets bigger whenever I
successfully do so. And it's getting
brighter than earlier.
>> A gets bigger when she loves you.
>> Screaming thing
more. Yay.
>> Hit it up there.
>> What happens when
>> you're on fire?
>> You're on fire. This seems bad.
>> Really confused.
>> You should go to the furnace.
>> Oh, now you're not on fire. That makes
sense.
Whoa.
[Music]
Wait, can you bounce the ball up there?
>> I didn't see people jump high. How do I
get up there?
>> Oh, there we go.
>> Not always the case.
>> Whoa.
>> What's that star?
>> Or wall jump.
>> Uh-oh. Well, now you can bounce the
ball.
>> Oh, you can jump higher when she size of
the screen dictates how high you can
jump.
>> Okay, so I guess you'll bounce it more.
Oh, is gra Oh, there.
>> You're just using her.
>> I'm on fire again.
>> How could you?
>> Oh, but you're not on fire.
>> She's not going to love you very soon.
>> Yeah, apparently
star is is also good.
>> At least not she presumably loves me.
>> Oh, no.
>> Yeah, but it's faster and faster the
higher up you get, I think.
>> Yeah.
>> Weird. Or maybe the more stars you eat.
>> And now it's all ice.
>> Oh.
>> Oh, yes. Because she was getting happier
when I bounced the ball. I guess she
doesn't get cold.
>> Oh my god.
>> Oh no.
>> Oh, it's blocking the um
>> There's fire though.
>> I think it maybe push the stars into the
fire so that they melt or something.
>> Arrow pointing.
>> Oh, now it's a star.
>> Interesting.
>> Well, there's been a star there the
entire time.
>> What?
All right, go push. Start with
>> Oh, I see you have a hammer.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, you're dead.
>> It's cuz you're on fire.
>> The numbers on the stars are all
[Music]
>> the ball can't get to you. It says that.
>> But now I can probably what?
>> Push the ice into the fire. And the um
the number on the top goes up every time
you Yeah. The numbers on the star
correspond to how many like
>> you get
>> being on fire seems like it would be
bad.
>> A
[Music]
tried to get rid of the ice. Can we put
the lid? Okay.
Wait, she doesn't want to play.
>> That's because I got rid of the ice and
he was happy, I think.
>> Oh, it's getting icy, though.
It's getting colder.
>> There's no more stars to recharge my
thing, though.
>> I think you just have to go hard. This
is where you were last time, I think.
Yeah, there.
>> Get the star.
Oh no, no.
It's really
you get this too fast and your hair is
burning. That means you're just getting
too much love and it like starts falling
really fast.
>> Oh no.
>> Oh no. Oh, no.
>> But there's a there's a there's a
counter on the ice blocks of the stars,
and you get more points if you get them
into the furnace faster.
>> I think they went down when he started
warming up in the furnace. So, the
warmer the world is less points you get
for the icing. Is this about global
warming?
>> Okay, so this
>> I think it's about drugs. He gets love
from this girl and then like I think
make him happy, but only for a little
bit.
[Music]
Yeah.
>> What?
>> Yeah.
Yeah.
[Music]
>> So, if I'm on fire, it seems to reduce
at a much faster rate.
[Music]
should avoid burning by not eating too
many stars at a time.
>> Just hit all
>> everything is about drugs.
>> I think everything's about drugs.
>> I mean, yeah, obviously I'm crazy.
>> You can actually catch a triple dragon
in that case.
>> Oh no.
Uh two.
>> Really stupid design. Go all the way
back down.
>> There's a column on the right. You can
fall fast.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yeah.
>> The high you climb the further fall.
>> Poetic.
>> Now I probably don't have any stars. So
I think we need to play
>> Oh, she's gone. She's dead.
>> You killed her.
>> That's too sad. And there's not much
fire left.
>> Oh no. And the fire isn't bringing
things back.
>> Oh my god. You didn't get any stars
first, so she died.
>> Oh,
>> she eats stars.
>> Oh, there you go.
>> There you go. Oh, is she there now? The
fire started warming you again.
>> Therapy.
No.
>> No, she's gone forever.
>> You can't play ball alone.
>> Well, she's going Oh, you're going to
go.
>> Maybe she only comes in the spring.
Maybe winter's too cold. So maybe if I
wait by the fire.
>> Does it go faster?
>> Yeah. What? Why is it getting bigger?
>> Cuz he's by the fire. It's getting
warmer. But that wasn't working earlier.
>> Now it is.
>> Go faster.
>> He's a rock bottom. It's like spring.
>> But
she How high can you jump right now?
>> Can you hit the ball?
>> Pretty high. That's a lot of jumps.
>> No, I can't hit the ball.
>> Only she can lift the ball.
>> Well, while you're increasing, you
should probably go up and get the stars.
>> Go up. Go up.
>> There we go.
>> Stop expanding.
>> Isn't it Is it the stars?
>> Stop contracting, too.
>> Oh, you're even on fire now.
>> He's on fire.
>> Can you go infinitely high if you're on
fire?
>> Pretty darn high. That was like pretty.
Uhoh.
>> Four stars.
>> Are you getting all of them? Oh, I Oh,
>> that might have been a bit of an
overdose.
>> No.
>> Yeah, you totally ODed on stars just
there
>> cuz you can always get stars as you go
back.
>> Or you can only hold four and then it
retracts when you get four and then it
turns ice blocks.
>> What?
>> That was intense.
>> They're worth so much.
Wait,
>> and
when
>> you won,
>> y
>> what you want is a good question.
>> That's gravitation. And actually, I
mean, I'm not even kidding. That's
that's certainly my favorite Jason game.
It's it's one of
>> it's one of my favorite games. And and I
think even just the example of you guys
playing is great, right? because because
you're just kind of shouting out all
these different ideas for what it could
be about. Um and um you know there's
some clear intentionality in in in his
uh in his design um with this game,
right? In terms of the systems trying to
communicate something that's other than
just, you know, engagement um or or I
don't know, God, fun. Um I was it fun?
>> Yeah. Oh, all right. Cool. Um yeah,
that's pretty good. Um thoughts on what
it's about? I heard a couple people be
like drugs.
>> Definitely drugs.
>> Tons of analogies. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's kind of like drugs.
>> Well, look,
>> love is a relationship versus like
whatever you're trying to do, your
career, your
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I actually I call this like in
life.
>> I think it's like the ultimate MIT game.
Um if I uh if I uh told you that this
was his daughter,
>> um would it change your interpretations
of of the game and what happened?
>> Yeah. So, so, so now if you know that
this is his daughter, what do you think
it's about?
>> His job,
>> neglect,
>> work, neglect, job versus family, right?
You know, he kind of
>> um he says he says explicitly like
before you played that this is a game
about motivation. Um and he doesn't go
doesn't go too far into telling you what
the game is specifically about. And I
think playing through it a couple times,
but I mean I will tell you the first
time I played and I came back out and
she was gone, it was very upsetting for
me. I was like, you know, and I don't
know if it's just, you know, just, you
know, I was, you know, ready to play it
that way or my life stage or something
like that. But the the idea of, you
know, he's he's playing with his
daughter that inspires him. You know, he
travels and then, you know, one of these
days if you're gone too long, she grows
up. I mean, I don't know if she dies,
but but you know,
>> you didn't bring her any money,
>> right? She cuz she had no money. Yeah,
>> she died.
>> So, I think this is a really really game
and a game about motivation.
>> It is. Yeah. or she wish she owed you on
drugs.
>> So, it's free. If you just Google search
gravitation Jason, you'll you'll find
the links to it. You'll find his artist
statement, which I think is really kind
of good to read. Um, again, with John
Sharp's kind of point about like, you
know, declaring your intentionality,
whether you say what the game's about is
important. Um, again, I I think I think
this qualifies, at least for me, as art.
Um, it's doing things that that I see
other pieces of art doing. Um, okay. So,
Paulo Percini, how many of your time?
Um, uh, Paulo Percini is is one of my
favorite game designers right now, and
this this game actually is is is one of
his newest ones, and I think it's I
think it's hilarious and great. Um, and
it's called Memory Reloaded: The
Downfall. Test your concentration with
Memory Reloaded, a matching game for
these unstable times. History may be
different from that which you remember.
And who would like to play Memory
Reloaded? I'm laughing already because
it's funny. Has anybody played it? I
need someone who's not played it. Okay,
good. Jeremy, you want to do it?
>> Sure.
>> Awesome.
This presentation is so cool.
>> Okay, you're up.
>> I will click.
>> Don't do it.
>> Oh, you're out.
>> You're done. You lost already.
>> No way. That's kind of scary. All right.
Oh, I can already see what they're going
to do. They're You're going to play
Switch on me. All right. Afghan freedom
fighter. He's going to be a terrorist
later.
>> Migrant workforce.
[Music]
Life for the workforce. Yay. Nick. Yay.
>> Iraqi oil. Afghan freedom fighter.
>> I bet if you grab Iraqi oil before
Afghan freedom fighter, he becomes a
terrorist.
>> Global inequality. Peace and
>> global inequality.
>> Global inequality.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Global inequality.
>> All right.
I'm doing well. Ruthless maker
>> loan chart. Rocky was Rocky here.
[Music]
>> Awkward. All right. Universal
healthcare. Man-made global warming.
>> Man-made natural.
>> Hey, not cool. Universal healthcare.
>> Universal healthcare. Sweet.
>> Oh,
one over there.
>> Yeah.
Nice. Hooray. Right under Valentine.
>> Well, natural. Come on.
>> Wait. What?
>> Why? Needy maker. Ruthless maker.
>> Oh, that's the order. You click them in.
>> Ruthless maker. What?
>> What? What are the other ones now?
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, there we go.
>> Nice.
>> So, that means now let's see.
Hey. He's never a satisfied baker.
>> Where?
>> What the hell?
>> Oh dear. Did we shoot
>> better move?
[Music]
>> Oh, I get it.
That's fine. Is it the entire game?
>> Yes, that that is the the whole game. Of
course, you can get different outcomes,
but uh but yeah, that's the idea. Um
>> so I think you guys have seen some of uh
some of Mullet Mysteria's other work
that you guys saw every day the same
dream. I like that
>> which is interesting. Um yeah, that that
one's that one's also one of my favorite
games. Um but this is, you know, this is
kind of uh this is this is kind of
looking at another kind of sector of
art, right? The kind of activist
political statement sector of art and
doing that through games and and it's
something that this music
um something that um that he does
particularly well with his games and I
think this one's this one's particularly
um interesting and kind of funny. I love
I love the um
the kind of reworking of a really
classic game mechanic, right? Like
memory the the entire point of memory is
your expectation that they would be the
same the second time you turn it over.
And when it changes on you, it
reinforces that kind of uh that kind of
perspective uh I suppose imbalance um
that can exist when you're not just
turning over, you know, toad stools and
and Bowsers, but you know, actual kind
of interesting things. I really I love
the the crying sweating polar bear um
and and the well with like a beach chair
actually cracks me down. Um and I think
humor is actually something that
shouldn't be ignored here, right? I
mean, if we remember that was one of the
kind of the central flux things, this
idea of like satire, humor is important.
Um and so, uh I really I I think
Paulini's work is really awesome. And
again, I for me it's certainly arc
enough. Um this game is really cool. Uh
who's played love? We have a few people
that's played Love. All right, cool. Um
I'd love someone who has not played Love
to to play it for a little bit. I don't
know if we can play the whole game. Um,
but uh this is actually a game that I I
really don't like. Um but I like the
things that it does, if that makes any
sense. Like I it bothers me for some
reason. Um and yet
it's such an articulate statement. This
game bothers me. Um but
>> but I think it's worth looking at
because he's he's doing particularly
interesting things.
Alexander has oius. Aus
top right.
>> No, you are a girl. Okay. I'm a girl.
[Music]
If you say yes, will he like not teach
you how to play?
[Music]
>> Yeah.
Don't touch the bones.
It's like Sonic.
>> What?
[Music]
>> There's two paths.
I best way of playing like this.
>> Can you use that? That's what I was
going to do. I make a mistake.
>> Travel the lower.
>> Wait, what's appearing?
We need to slow down.
I'm totally disabled.
>> What? I can't hit the red blocks now.
[Music]
>> Disgusting.
>> This game is not only hard, it's also
positive.
This is our
>> patience.
Yay.
>> Those are red.
>> I know. That means I can't touch him.
>> Yay.
>> Don't do it. Don't do it, dude.
>> Do it.
>> You're just going to have to go back to
the part that was just hard.
See,
there's no red blocks. You get red
blocks when you disobey.
>> Yeah.
You still can't touch
the yellow card.
>> So, if you disobey, it hides from you
what things actually are
>> or or if you obey, they're getting
[Music]
It's so hard. So little buttons to
press.
>> Wait, what are the controls?
>> The keys.
>> Right, left.
[Music]
>> Should this have made
>> What? Can you no longer jump?
>> I was just screaming out.
>> He's doing crouch. Crouch.
[Music]
risky. Oh, I thought that was bad.
>> Yeah, but that kind of looks like you.
>> This game is well aggravatingly tuned
because it's like just build it up.
>> Uh
uh
>> crouch crouch.
>> Why you doing that professionally? I
just like
>> So, it's actually a pretty long game. Um
I I encourage you guys to uh it's pretty
it's all flashbased.
>> What's the message?
>> Uh that's a really good question. Let me
uh let me just jump in and go back.
>> Thank you for playing.
>> Disgusting.
>> You are a changed person because of it.
>> So yeah. So the question then becomes
what the point which you know already
we're in a position now where we're
asking questions like that which is you
know if you were playing Modern Warfare
2 you might say what's the point like
would be to blow a lot of stuff up
right? So um this is
>> this is a response he had in one of his
interviews he gave after it was
released. He said, "I wanted to get
people to wake up and think about the
games they are playing. Much of the
industry appears to be pushing in the
opposite direction. Essay long
tutorials, holding your hand from
beginning to end in subtext, screamed
through pointless exposition. It is
treating players like idiots is
absolutely infuriating." Um, when you
think about it in terms of a tutorial,
right, if this is the tutorial for
playing the game, it's pretty obnoxious.
Um, but it's not that much different
than the kind of tutorials that we
encounter in a lot of games, right? That
just basically hold your hand and tell
you how to do everything. Um, so I think
he's really kind of confronting that.
Um, I guess if I were to say the reasons
that I don't like this game, uh, I think
the control scheme is is actually it's a
weakness. The game is so hard that I
mean, you saw like, you know, you
couldn't even get to the things that he
was trying to communicate. It gets
weirder the farther along you get. I can
I can promise you it's just it's like
you have to get really skilled at doing
it. Um, so there's there's kind of like
a play barrier for entry on it. Um uh
it's also it also for me I think
dare I say it almost gets like too
abstract for me at certain points um
where I'm I'm it's clear that he's
trying to say something but there's
nothing I can latch on to to understand
what it is and it's entirely his
prerogative but for me that's I'm just
like what like I have no clue what what
this is about at all. Um so so that's a
little tricky.
>> He's not you are not fully grasping.
>> I'm not apparently I'm not. Yeah. I'm
partially. So yeah, it's like the
perfect Fluxus piece of art. So um okay,
so I've only got a couple more to talk
about and I got about 15 minutes. This I
think is actually one of the most
important games that we can talk about
today, which is Cow Clicker, who's
played Cow Clicker. Yay. Um so this is
um by Ian Bogos, the guy we saw earlier.
Um and he said, "Cow Clicker is a
Facebook game about Facebook games. It's
partly a satire and partly a playable
theory of today's social games and
partly an earnest example of that
genre." Um, so this is kind of like a
classic sort of art thing to do, right?
You take something that you're going to
satire and you make a version of that
that that maybe does some things
differently, but is fundamentally what
you are satiring. It's like the Andy
Kaufman comedic kind of style, right?
Where you like you just assume that that
kind of character or role. And it's it's
it's something that I think is like kind
of like joyfully subversive um in in in
doing satire. So hopefully I'm logged
into Facebook so you can see and I
haven't clicked recently so you guys can
witness um one of my clicks. Am I
>> Facebook is down? Facebook is canled
forever.
>> Yes.
>> Has no friends.
>> It's also possible that the wireless
Yeah, the wireless in this in that
corner is kind of bad.
>> Oh, should I switch to Google?
Oh.
Um,
so I can actually kind of before we even
see it, I can talk a little bit about
the sort of interesting controversy that
Cal Clicker is is creating. Um, it's
it's making money.
>> MacBook Airs don't have Let me try
Google.
>> Yeah.
>> Um,
I'm not connected. How about now?
It seems to be working better.
>> Um, so the last part of his statement is
about an earnest effort in a game. It it
it is fundamentally a Facebook game. So
you can see I've got um I've got five
Mooney. Um my next click is in a minute
and 40. Oh man, I missed one of my
clicks. But maybe if I if we wait while
I talk about it, you can witness one of
my clicks. Um oh wait, I actually have
some clicks left. I've got uh I've got,
you know, one this week. But that's in
two hours.
>> Uh,
>> yeah, it looks like that's when I get my
next one. So, um, so basically you can
click your cow,
which
why can I not click my cow?
Um, well, you can click your cow and
then you can Oh, it's because I'm on
scrolling.
I don't know. Um anyway, you can click
your cow and then you can use your
mooney uh to buy new cows um that are
fundamentally the same thing as other
cows just with aesthetic differences. Um
so plain cow. Um oh these are the cows I
have. I have a plain cow and a steel
cow. I haven't been playing a lot of cow
clicker. Um if I go to buy a cow, I
could buy a new cow. Um
uh so you can see lots of different cows
um that cost you in-game currency. Um,
>> paisley cow.
>> Yeah. Holy cow.
Um, oil cow cow retire. Sad. It's got a
BP logo. It's cute. Um,
>> I like BSD cow. Yeah, that's pretty
good. Um, so there's lots of different
cows and you can buy cows. You can give
cows. You can invite a cow. Um, there's
cow rankings. Um,
>> invite a cow.
>> Uh, you can So you can see, you know,
Mooney is actually pretty inflated at
this point. You can get 10 Mooney for 50
cents, which is pretty great. Thousand
for $10, which is kind of awesome. um
and you know collect a lot of cows and
you can trade cows and you know you can
go to your friends barns and see how
many cows they have and um and you can
click on your cows when you make make
your appointment to actually cow. Um so
I mean I think you can see how he's
poking fun at um things like Farmville
uh things like Ravenwood Fair which I'm
obsessed with now actually. um these
kind of games where all you're
fundamentally doing is clicking uh and
acquiring an in-game currency that you
can then use for in-game goods. Um but
then of course you reach this barrier
where you don't have enough in-game
currency and you need to use real
currency. Of course, the interesting
thing is like there are like I don't
know 500,000 people playing this or I
don't know if it's that many. It's a
lot. Um here if we go to the cow clicker
front page, right, it'll tell us oh Jera
was at St. Barthol.
>> Um where does it say how many players
there are? ranking.
>> Ranking. Yeah,
>> I did that on board news.
>> Who's milking the cow clicker?
>> You can see this person's Monica's
>> no count.
>> Oh,
>> um
>> yeah, maybe all clicks or this week.
>> Is there like a Oh,
>> here we go. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Um
>> 12,000
>> 12,000 monthly active users. Yes.
500,000 a bit of a stretch, but um but
that's a lot of people and he's making
some interesting money on it. And I
think one of the things that was
important that he did is there's kind of
an active forum where people can kind of
talk about it and so it is a little bit
weirdly controversial, right? Because he
made this game that is, you know, poking
fun at Facebook games and yet it is a
Facebook game and it's, you know,
presumably making some money, too. So,
um but I think it's really good. I think
it's, you know, this is the kind of art
that's also important where it's like
taking what we do and purposely looking
at at at how is it constructed and how
is it set up and and satiring it and
forcing us to kind of be introspective
about the things that we do in the way
that we engage. Um, and so this is a
kind of subversive game design that I
think you know along the lines of Paulo
Pedroini's work and um and even Galafa
is kind of forcing us to look at how we
interact. Um, and cow clicker cow
clicker is really fun. Um uh so that's
that one and I've got like 15 minutes.
Philip asked me to talk a little bit
about um some work that I'm doing in
this space. Um so I'm going to talk to
you about a game uh that I'm it's a work
in progress. It's tenatively titled
before and ends now. Um and it's by me.
Um and the idea from it is it's inspired
a bit by Flexus boxes. Um and those kind
of flux kits. Um, I wanted to I'm really
interested in in like physically
tangible games. I don't know why I'm uh
all of a sudden kind of obsessed with
with holding something, but I was at
indicate and I heard again and it this
is like the question that drives me more
nuts than than the um than the are video
games art question, although they're
interestingly related, but it's, you
know, when will we have the citizen cane
in video games? It drives me absolutely
nuts. I think uh 80% of the time the
people who say that have never seen
citizen cane. Um so I don't really know
what that means. Um, but I had heard it
like for the eenth time in Indie Kane
and I wanted to throw the television in
my out of my hotel room window and I was
like I was going nuts and I was like,
"All right, well well what is Citizen
Kane about?" And I don't want to spoil
it. Who's seen Citizen Kane in this
room? Actually, a handful of people. All
right, good. Um,
>> so so I, you know, I see Citizen Kane
and it's about this very kind of, you
know, interesting
um idea about, you know, presence and
and momentos and and happiness uh in a
very kind of real way and like the
temporality of happiness, right? Like
are you happy now? Were you happy then?
Do you remember being happy? When when
is happiness? Um, and so I was like,
well, I'm going to make a Citizen Cane
of video games, but it's not going to be
it's not going to be known for being uh
uh epically innovative, you know, with
camera movement. Um, it's it's going to
be about the things I think Citizen Cane
are about. Um, so it's it's basically um
you know in this form uh although I'm
I'm rethinking what kind of box it's
going to be in but in this form it's a
box and inside of it are various objects
that start out as uh the starting
objects for the box are things that have
personal significance to me. Um and one
of the rules of the game in fact I think
the most important rule of the game uh
is this one. Rule number one you may
permanently exchange an object of
personal significance for any object of
equal value. So when you're playing this
game, you can take something that
belongs to you and you can exchange it
for anything in the box. Um and then of
course the interesting thing is these
these um these objects in the box are of
varying uh degrees of interactivity,
right? Like you can do them in Etcha
Sketch. So you can draw something on the
Etcha sketch. Um and um you know the
rules are kind of veiled in this moment
now where there's like a couple other
rules that you know are causing you to
reflect. This is actually an extension
of uh Yet One Word, which was a project
we worked on in the summer, which was a
game that um as you're playing, it's a
platformer, and you're typing, the game
stops and asks you personal questions.
And what I really liked about that is it
was doing something that I was kind of
referring to as a um as a mechanic of
reflection where where the the the
activity of play is is reflecting, is
thinking, is you know, just
contemplating. Um it's not interactive
in a very kind of, you know, active way
as we think of it. It's more reflective.
I I liken it to the moments in chess
where you're planning your move. There's
not a lot of action in chess. There's a
lot of contemplation in chess. Um so if
it's personal, you know what if that
were what if that were personal? And so
what I what I don't particularly care
about with yet one word is that it
doesn't it it it inspires you to
reflect, but it doesn't do it with with
tremendous grace. It just asks you a
question. It just comes out, you know,
kind of out of the blue and says, "Hey,
you know, when was the last time you
lied?" Um, and if you, you know,
sometimes you're surprised by that and
that's a good effect, but it's also not,
um, subtle. Um, and so I'm trying to
explore how can we be subtle in in
causing reflection. And so there are a
few things here. I mean, the value
question is interesting. How do you know
what the value of the object is in the
box? Um, do you think of it as a
monetary value? Do you think of it as
value in terms of significance to the
person who put that in there? Um, why is
it significant to the person who put
that in there? Like what is this thing?
Right? you can look at and reflect and
and then when you leave a trace of
yourself in this box, the next person
who comes and plays is is going to see
that and they're going to wonder what
was what was that? And so I'm also kind
of interested in like um the organicness
uh the kind of uh uh the in the the
never- ending interminable nature of a
game that that carries the effect of a
person who's played it kind of on and on
and on. Um, the next iteration of this
that I want to do, actually, this was an
idea that Jason Bean gave me was to use
um an apothecary chest. Um, because one
of the things that we play tested it
here with, I left it out for like two
weeks and and people, you probably saw
it, it was right there. Um, you know,
people were engaging. And this is
actually this is like a photo with
objects that people had left in. So, it
was really fun for me after two weeks to
kind of go into this box and be like,
what is all this stuff? You know, like
like what got left? I was actually
surprised the sketch, you know, was left
and then but I was like, wow, what is
this stuff? Um, and and to give you one
really good example, um, one person at
the lab put in a Nintendo DS flash card,
um, which was really like a wrapped DS
flash card. And so now there's this kind
of this kind of next level. The game has
changed with another level of
interactivity where it's like if I want
to kind of get at what was the uh, what
was the significance of this object to
this person, I need to I need to get a
DS and play this, right? Right. So then
I open up the and it's got it's got
folders and it's got um you know a copy
of the game Lemmings. It's got some
music in it. Right. And so now it's kind
of like you've you've like uncovered
this next layer and it's like you know
the interesting traces of the people who
have played this game are are now you
know uh you know marked onto this onto
this box forever. Marley even said to me
I was like talking to her about her play
after she had done it and I was like um
she told me she wanted to take the
instructions. um she wanted to take the
rules as one of the objects that she
could take out of that. And I told her I
had thought about that actually when I
was designing it that someone might be
like, "Ha, I'm going to take the rules."
And and I was going to put in a rule
that said, you know, you can turn the
exchange for an object that's not the
rule is so that the game could persist.
But I but I didn't want I didn't want to
artificially impose that if someone
takes the rules because that's what they
want. That's what and now the game is
the game has changed. And maybe someone
comes along later and and modifies it.
Maybe they put something in that makes
it a whole new different game. And and I
really like the idea that you can
encounter this game and that it's going
to be kind of in this state of flux, I
guess you could say. Um, and so that's
what I'm that's what I'm working on now.
And like I said, it's going to I think
one of the things I didn't like is that
all of the objects are accessible all at
once. Um, so if it's an apothecary chest
with lots of drawers, this was Jason
Bean's idea, then you kind of have to do
a little exploring. Um, and maybe the
rules are in one of those drawers. And
maybe you see the rules first, maybe you
see the rules way after you've looked at
a lot of stuff. And then you now you've
seen all this stuff and played with it
all and you really like something and
now it's like what do I trade? Um
and um and yeah, so I also am trying to
find a way to give the box a a history
as well. I've contemplated some ideas of
putting in some some kind of clues that
you could then if you felt if you
thought about it or looked it up, you
might be able to find a story to this
box. Like if you did an internet search,
you might come upon a fake website. uh
wouldn't be fake. It' just be a website,
but a website with a fake story that
kind of tells you a little bit about
this box and maybe gives you a few more
hooks into what the meaning of this game
or what the inspiration for this game
inspiration for this game was. And so
this is kind of one of my projects that
I'm working on right now. Like I said,
I'm kind of I'm interested in
tangibility, but but you can see where a
lot of the other things that I was
talking about are kind of inspiring
inspiring this this work. Um and so we
kind of come back to that question of
are games art and whether it's even a
valid question. We only have five
minutes. I don't know if you guys have
administrative stuff afterwards, but um
this is like I said, this is sort of my
viewpoint and I I it's certainly shared
with a lot of other people. Um but it's
not um this is not guaranteed truth.
It's this is an opinion that I have just
shared. So, um, but any thoughts you
guys have about this subject or these
ideas of these games or
anything at all?
Yesterday's football game.
>> Well, cool. Well, I hope this was
useful. I hope it was helpful. Um, you
know, I think it if if at the very least
it causes you to continue to think
about, you know, your own games that
you're developing and how meaning can be
embed in in the play that you might not
even realize is there. Um, but also just
kind of the possibility space. I I
really am excited by I'm discouraged by
the safe choices that a lot of
independent game developers make and
excited when some game developers really
push on the edge. I don't think we have
a I don't think we have a clear
understanding of what the rules are or
what even constitutes a game or what
what degree of interactivity is
appropriate for a you know quote unquote
game. And I think I think some of these
designers are really testing the waters
of the medium. You know, what can we
really do with this? You know, where
where can we go? How edgy and satirical
and on guard can we be? Um,
I think that's always good.
So, I'm a revolutionary
crazy person.
>> Crazy person.
That's good to hear.
>> Folks, um if folks haven't played uh yet
one word this year, which were some of
the games that uh Abe um worked with the
team on over the summer, uh those are on
our gamut website uh just opened 2010
and and you see yet one more in Sier
which were booked about this summer. We
saw us like try to see some of the
digital.
>> Yeah. And please play them and give us
feedback too, right? Because that's the
other thing like these are not perfect
articulations of of game is is the pure
art form, right? Like we're constantly
evolving and trying to improve and so
any feedback you can give us on this
stuff is greatly appreciated.
>> I have one question.
>> Do you still have that box like
somewhere?
>> Yeah. Yeah, it's in my office. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Totally. Yeah. I have a box
and I need to I'm I'm So the other part
of it is is when I do the second version
of it in the apothecary kind of chest,
uh, one thing that's important to me is
that each of the I sort of for the
prototype, I just sort of threw some
like reasonably meaningful objects in
there, but I I I want it to be populated
with objects that are personally
significant to myself or symbolic to
myself. and um and populating that box
at the outset with meaningful objects I
think is important because it it's you
know sort of once it's once it's quote
unquote released into the world for play
right then it's it's constantly changing
and so that first that first instant
instantiation of the game is is the one
that is is kind of about me in some sort
of sense and about my experiences and
then it becomes the world which is play.
So, the way that your games kind of
reminds me of is I'm pretty sure I heard
this similar that some person uh had a
pen and so he just kept he started with
a pen and he kept trading and made
>> red paper.
>> Oh, no. Well, no, no, this is a
different one. Not the red paper clip
for I heard I think it was someone had
started with a pen or something and kept
trading it and over the course of like a
year or two he eventually trade got with
that init from that initial pen he was
able to trade for a house or something.
It was okay.
>> Yeah. No, totally. I mean, and that was
like sort of an interesting what I like.
I think it was on eBay, too, right? Or
something like that. And that's even
using a a pretty well-designed game
system because eBay is totally a game.
Um, and using a game system to and
subverting the system itself to do
something really kind of interesting.
And so, I mean, yeah, that's a that's a
really kind of great it's like a game
inside of a game, right? And I love
that. That's it's kind of like the cow
clickers, right? like making a game
inside of the game that subverts the
>> Are you familiar with the concept of
geocaching?
>> Uh because what when I first saw what
the game you were talking about that you
designed it really reminded me of it. Uh
so initially what it was is when GPS's
first came out, people were like, "Oh,
hey, this is really cool technology. We
should think of something fun to do with
it." So what they did was uh these
people hid started hiding um like empty
tins of like little trinkets and stuff
at various like on hiking trails or
other And you would look up the
coordinates on your GPS finder and you
would find this box and what you would
do is you you trade a trinket and you
get a trinket.
>> And you keep like traveling to these
other
>> Yeah. And in that sense like this this
whole worldwide game becomes really kind
of changed. Yeah. You know there's
there's there's some sh there's some
shared ideas with some location based
games that do some really interesting
things with with that where um you know
whether it's alternative reality but but
maybe not even with a with a narrative.
There was one I was reading about um
that was at uh it was like come out and
play I think in New York City at one
point but it was cruel to be kind. uh it
was called. It was a game where um you
don't you don't know who's playing, you
know who's on what team, but you use you
use you get missions and you get a
weapon that's a compliment like um you
know to kill someone who's on the other
team, mistake them for a celebrity or
something like that, right? And so
you're using these kind of random acts
of kindness, you know, helping someone
across the street and you don't know if
it's like in New York City, so you don't
know if someone's playing the game. So
now all of a sudden you're kind of
wandering around doing really nice
things for people on the chance that you
know on a hunch that you have that maybe
they're playing the game and maybe
they're not. And so you just help
somebody across the street which is
totally nice and and it kind of comes to
this massive conclusion where you just
have these two giant teams who meet up
at a location to nice each other to
death basically. Um and so you know
there there's a lot of really really
kind of interesting stuff especially in
the the kind of location based
>> realm. Big big games are really cool.
There's a lot of people doing really
neat stuff with with big games.
>> Yeah. So, I I I think like in particular
with you know, the box and the
geocaching idea, it's and and you know,
talking about the paperclip for a house
thing.
>> It's really interesting like what how
people value things.
>> Yeah.
>> Like in particular, you know, you have
this very vague rule in it that just
says, you know, something of of equal
value. Like what does it actually mean?
>> Value or
>> Yeah, exactly. It's kind of interesting
like what someone is willing to trade
for for something else.
>> Yeah. And those are those are the kind
of implicit rules like you see in 16
tons, right? Where it's like what
happens with the money, you know, and
and and that's, you know, Jason me
really pointed out because he was
thinking about value when he was doing
the training and it's such a good word,
right? Because value is such a different
thing to different people and someone
might see the like the the flash card
for the DS, right, which has a very
clear higher monetary value than than an
etch sketch. Um, and yet maybe you
played with an etch sketch when you were
a kid and all of a sudden it floods back
these memories that you have. Um,
there's also there's another component
to it that I didn't really talk about,
which is like the sacrificing of an
object. And and I think too that it's
it's we we tend to be beholden to our
material objects um too much um in in in
giving it up in in sacrificing it to
this game so that you don't have it
anymore. If it's something of personal
significance, you're you're letting go
and and being able to say, "Okay, the
memory is one thing. I don't need to."
And that's that's how it relates a bit
back to Citizen Kane, which is a movie
you should see because it is good.
It's everything they said it is,
>> depending on who they are.
>> Cool. Thanks, guys.
>> Thanks.