hello computational musicologists and
music
theorists while you're working on your
own representation formats I want to
introduce one representation format
indeed the most commonly used
representation format for common western
music notation scores and that is music
XML created by Michael good around the
year
2000 looking over at the music XML
website we can see their version of
hello world as you know in programming
Traditions it's become traditional to
print out the word hello world to show
how uh a how a programming language
Works in music notation it's become
common to instead to show how uh note
middle C uh would be represented whole
note or something like that and here is
the example of that middle C whole note
in music XML one of the things you can
see in music XML just like any XML or
like HTML we have these things called
Tags which are enclosed in angle
brackets then we have a content for the
tag and then the tag is closed with
those same angle brackets with a slash
front tags can enclose other tags so the
score part encloses a tag called called
part name and then it's closed later and
tags can also have attributes ID equals
P1 and we'll look at those in just a
little
bit let's scroll down to the note so all
of that is to set up what we might
normally do for a note so a note is a
tag called note within it there's a tag
called pitch within that there's a tag
called step and the step has a single
letter this this is very similar to
music 21 in fact you I borrowed these
Concepts from here and um so that the
accidental would be encoded elsewhere
then the octave is encoded as a single
number then the pitch is
closed after that we have a duration tag
and we'll get back to that in a second
but it's duration 4 and then there's
something called a type which is
different and it says whole so it says
that this note type is a whole
note we have the duration and the type
encoded separately because the type
explains to notation software how to
represent this note what it should look
like and um the duration instead tells
it how long it is so you could in theory
put a a duration of any number and a
type of any number and you can make
things that look looked very different
from how they sounded or how they were
represented in practice most notation
software reads one or the other of these
so that's kind of too bad uh the
duration four does not like in music 21
rep uh represent necessarily four
quarter notes what it does is it refers
back to the last tag within an
attributes tag called divisions and this
says how many parts should uh should a
quarter note be divided up into two so
in this case because the only note is a
whole note we can just divide up the
cord note into one part not divide it at
all and then say a whole note has four
of these um but if we were going to
later have an eighth note then this
would have to be at least two because
the quarter note can be divided into two
parts if we might have 16th notes it
would need to be four because it could
be divided into four parts and if we
were going to have 16 notes and triplets
also then it would need to be 12 because
you can divide it into 12 different ways
um in practice these divisions usually
end up being much higher numbers uh some
people use 16 384 which is you know a
power of two I like using a high power
of two multipli by three multiplied by
five multiplied by seven so I can
exactly represent triplets quets sep
cupets things like that but you can
change this division um with each I
think at least each measure so that you
can make sure that whatever you're going
to be representing will be there we can
also see that there's a key signature
and that's um marked in the number of
fifths from from C so remember your
circle fifths if you want a key
signature of D major of two sharps that
would be two if you want uh B major that
should be five if you want F major well
we're going the other way so that's
going to be negative -1 so we can
represent keys that way time you can
probably figure out beats and beat type
or 44 could be called numerator and
denominator but it is one of these
things about uh about music XML that the
format likes to uh likes to show the um
the musical meaning not just you know
how it's going to be laid out we have
the C
instead of saying it's trouble cff we
say that it is a gclf online
too and so here is some of the um basics
of musicxml you can go to music xml.com
and read more about this we're going to
look at a few other components of Music
XML before going on but we don't you not
necessarily need to learn everything
about it
um so for looking at how music XML Works
we're going to look at us slightly more
complex example than just a single
coordin note we have a vocal part and
then a piano part represented on two
staves here we're using a divisions
that's a higher number than one U minor3
for the key signature and then we can
explicitly encode that it's actually
minor so we're not in E Flat Major or in
c minor right um
there's transposition but we don't need
to know that for this the pitch element
the note element sorry to say sorry can
also have um have Ties on it and can
have lyrics we can say that this is an
end of a syllable that ends M and we end
an extension this is another thing you
can do in XML based formats if you want
to open a tag and immediately close it
you can just put a slash at the end
instead
we look at tide notes even though uh
it's just a little little thing and that
is that there are two different parts in
a tie note in music XML and for a number
of things in music XML there is the Tie
element which
represents um conceptually is this note
tied and then there is the tide with a d
element and that says how do we draw the
tie on the page so you can draw a tie
without having a note that sounds tied
or is conceived of as tied or you could
have science conceived of as tied but
not
drawing and this shows up in other
places namely in uh in accidentals
because you can imagine a B flat you
conceive of it as a B flat but you also
put a flat sign in front of it the next
B in that same measure you cance of it
as B flat but you don't put a flat sign
in front of it so there's a distinction
between how we represent a note on paper
and how we can see of it and this is
very important
also we can look over here at chords and
see that a chord is simply here's a
three note chord we start with a note
it's a c um C and octave 4 and then we
have the next note has this empty chord
tag that says it's part of a chord of
the previous note so in music XML if you
want to know whether something is a
chord uh you won't know it from the
first note you'll only know it from the
second note odd here is an example where
we have E flat altered by negative -1
semmit tones and then the next note
G here's a little example of multi part
music and especially this part where we
have two different voices in the same
measure so we have two chords that can
be represented as just a single um sort
of set of note elements and then we have
chord here and chord here but in between
we have this separate voice with
separate stem directions and so on one
of the things that music 20 uh music XML
does is that when you get to a certain
point you're reading through all of your
durations are all considered to be in a
low row you get to maybe the end of
measure and you can back up a certain
number of
Divisions and then you can go forward
again in this case you would probably
just back up eight but a lot of notation
software seems to only use backup to go
to the beginning of the measure and then
if you need to skip forward use a
forward
again and it is also customary um though
not strictly required I don't believe
but almost um a lot of notation uh
things that read music XL we call them
consumers of Music XML a lot of them
might uh have a problem or might crash
if you don't include what's customary
again then you end at the end of the
measure by going forward until the very
end there's all kinds of other things on
repeats on sound suggestion so on but
one of the things you can see is that
compared to some of the thoughts we had
on compact
representations music XML is very
verbose it takes up a lot of space on
the screen it takes up a good amount of
space on disk though not nearly as much
as this uh video would ever take so
there is a compressed format and we call
it MXL we call XML orm musicxml the file
extension for standard music XML format
and uh MXL if it's just gzipped and
right now we're working on way so that a
gzip archive can include the score maybe
a compressed score a a transpose score
also all of the parts so new things are
still coming out with music XML and we
will turn to learning more about music
XML from the Creator