All right, we'll get started. Um, see,
last time we introduced you to the
definition of martingales.
And what we're going to do the first
part today is to see how useful and
powerful martinale properties are in
solving interesting uh questions and
challenges. So, so just as a reminder,
if we have a stochcastic process xn,
which is just a sequence of random
variables, generally the uh index n
corresponds to time. Then we can
consider another uh a derived process
capital m subn which is a function of
the first n values of the stochcastic
process x. And we say that this second
process, this derived process is a
martingale if the expected value into
the future from time n minus one is
simply equal to the time n minus one
value. So with a process evolving over
time,
we have a an m subn process basically at
time n minus one. We have a value. Our
prediction is that the expected value of
that in the future is mn minus one.
And so some examples of these we went
through last time a simple random walk
and with the simple random walk we end
up having realizations of this
martingale
that uh evolve from say a starting point
zero and what's critical with the these
realizations is that the future paths
that have yet to be graphed um will have
average value equal to the last point on
these realizations.
So there's a notion of there being
flatness in the martingale uh
expectations.
Um with the example here of a simple
random walk with equal probability of
going up or down one step, one can graph
the standard deviations
uh from the average zero for the
processes and um you know basically the
realizations of the random walk will by
the central limit theorem
converge to a normal distribution at any
given time point far into the future.
Now um this second example of a
martingale where we have a random walk
sn but then we square it and subtract n
times the sigma squared the variance of
each of the steps. This is also a
martingale. And so looking at different
realizations of this martingale
um we can see it's very very different
from that of a simple random walk. Um
and you know importantly
um there's basically sort of a lower
limit u of the process it appears for
fixed n and an unbounded upper limit. Um
and uh but this process as well is a
martingale.
Um and let's see a different martinale
can be defined not in terms of random
walks with steps that add but with
random sort of shifts
with factors x1 dxn. So if we have MN
being the product of X1 to XN where the
X's are independent random variables
with mean value one then this particular
uh process M subn will be a martingale
with respect to the original series. So
um so here's an example of our Berni
factors which are with 50% probability
1.5
and with 50% probability 0.5.
This would correspond to the change in
wealth from betting your wealth
in a lottery where you either make 50%
or lose 50% with equal probability.
And here is the uh graph of a
realization over 50 steps. Here's other
realizations.
And what's interesting to see is that
with this particular uh martingale,
there are opportunities to basically if
you're playing this lottery game at each
step to be able to grow your wealth to
five or 10 times its value, its initial
value, but very uh with moderate or even
high probability ility you actually have
lost almost all your wealth. So um yet
another example and this one is really
rather curious to introduce but it shows
you how we can be flexible in uh
generating or constructing uh
martingales. If we have the YN sequence
being IID random variables
and the moment generating function
E to the lambda YN
or E to the lambda Y
uh
YN
is equal to the moment a generating
function and or let's say e to the ty is
in the our notation we're going to use a
fee of lambda here or f of t.
Um
then uh if we consider uh taking
xn
equaling e to the lambda yn divided by v
of lambda
then this xn will be a martingale
uh or this xn rather will the factors
that have expectation
equaling one.
And if we take the product of these x's
um we basically have m subn equaling e
to the lambda times the sum of the y
ends
divided by
f of lambda
to the nth power. This will also be a
martingale.
And what we'll see in a you know towards
the uh middle of this lecture is that
this particular martingale can be used
to solve probabilities of gamblers ruin
when you have gambles that have um
different probabilities of uh success
versus failure not necessarily equal uh
fair bets. All right. Well, with
martinales,
it turns out to be very useful to
consider
this what's we call the information sets
on
the sequence the subsequence of
variables x1 through xn. So if we think
of information being uh progressing over
time, the information up to time little
n can be given by the outcomes of the x
process.
And we can consider
expectations of random variables given
this information set. And the kinds of
random variables we might be interested
in. Z can correspond to say trading
strategies based on the outcomes of
asset prices progressing over time.
And um we if we have uh let's see if if
this original information set is
represented in terms of a martinale
um then
we
can consider um functions of the first n
values given by y
and
relating to
this function of the first n values
which could be say the trading gains
from applying a uh a trading strategy
with asset prices given by the x's.
It will be very useful to use
random variables that are called
nonanticipating.
And so a non-anticipating random
variable
is a random variable an end that is
defined by the information set. It's
non-random given the information set uh
of the first n minus one x's.
So if we wanted to represent the outcome
of
making trading decisions using the first
n minus one values
um this a could characterize how we
might invest for the nth uh trading
period. Now
with such a non-anticipating random
variable
we can consider a transformation of the
original martingale
given by M's with no tildas.
um and consider a transformation of the
MN martingale
by considering this decomposition
of m tilda. So we have an initial value
m0.
Then we have the non-anticipating
uh variable A1 that depends only on
information at time zero times the
increment of the martingale from time
zero to time 1 and we add successive
terms. So these A's basically are random
variables at the beginning of time.
But after observing
say J time periods the AJ uh AJ uh let's
see will be or J minus one time periods
the AJ uh will be defined and non-random
going from time J to J + one. Now the uh
and if you were to look at um this M
tilda subn
definition, we basically have terms that
are given by increments of the
martingale process
which where each of those increments has
expectation equal to zero.
And so if we take the expectation of
those um from time zero then uh by
conditional expectation properties
um the a's uh are sort of fixed given
the information up to time uh n min or j
minus one and then the uh variation from
uh of the martin Martell process from
time J minus one to J uh is has
expectation zero. Anyway,
the martingale transform transform
theorem says that this m tilda n process
is a martingale also with respect to the
uh information sets fn and we often call
this collection of information sets sort
of a filtration
and so when we think of different
processes different realizations of a
process
um up to time n. Then uh whatever the
history is prior to n um that is the
information set we have available and as
we observe successive values of the uh
original MN process um we're basically
adding sort of more information about
the realizations
um and uh That's that's how it
progresses. Now, um with Martingales, an
important concept for us is a stopping
time random variable, which we'll call
TOAO. And so what the stopping time
variable is is a random variable
that
characterizes whether
the uh let's say I guess at any time n
we know whether the the stopping time
has occurred or not. So the event of the
stopping time being less than n less
than or equal to n steps that has to be
known in the information set up to time
n. So the notation here is a little bit
uh tricky. We think of this set or event
being the pro the the the underlying
probability distribution states where
the tow variable is less than or equal
to n
and at any time n we know whether this
set
has occurred or not. So the stopping
time uh is a random variable uh and it
could be infinite. So it takes values on
the set s varying from zero uh up to
possibly infinity if the process never
stops. Now a way of trying to help
explain this is with a stopping time
random variable we have different
omegas
in the probability space and the omegas
can be thought of as indexing all
possible paths.
So with different realizations we have a
different omega.
And so with these uh paths our
expectation
or our event E which is the set of paths
for which
the stopping time evaluated on that path
is less than or equal to n. um this
event is known
to either have occurred or not to occur.
So we have the indicator
of the path being in this set E is
either zero or one.
And so we can uh work with this sort of
random variable
uh the indicator of of the uh of whether
the stopping time has occurred or not.
And with this um setup we can think of
the process that is sort of governed by
a stopping time toao. We can represent
the process at the stopped time towo as
the sum of the realizations xn times a
simple indicator of whether the stopping
time equals n or not. So we basically
have our stopped process being a sum
of
weights time the xns where those weights
are actually zero or one.
Um now in the mathematics of dealing
with stopping times
uh the potential for infinite values uh
of the stopping time makes things
complicated.
And what we can do is consider the
minimum of n and the stopping time
towel.
Denoting that by n carrot towel. So the
minimum of n and toao. And so if we have
a finite value n, this truncated
stopping time
is going to be a measurable
random variable
with respect to the set the information
set script fm information set fm for m
greater than or equal to n. So if we
imagine um basically this time
increasing
um and we think of n
the minimum of n and toao then we will
be considering processes that maybe stop
for a given towo for a given
realization.
or if they don't really stop until
later, we just consider the value at the
end point.
Now um this theorem
can be proven with this argument
and what you can see is that we define
our non-anticipating
variables to be the indicator of tow the
stopping time being greater than or
equal to k.
And so substituting that in to the
formula for the decomposition um we end
up getting that this uh
stopped
martingale at time uh the minimum of n
or toao is actually equal to the sum of
these non-anticipating variables times
the increments of the martingale. So
this is easily a martingale uh transform
u and satisfies the martingale transform
theorem. So this uh sort of stopped
martingale at the minimum of n and toao
is also a martingale. What we then want
to do is consider taking
let's see I'm not sure if we do it here
shortly or or not but we'll basically
let little n grow large and argue that
in the limiting case um we basically
have the stopped martingale without the
minimum of n and
well um let's look at this simple random
walk we had before where the steps are +
one or minus one and we consider Sn
being the sum of the steps. Um, this can
be uh used to characterize the problem
of playing against an opponent and
betting one dollar with each iteration
of the game and you either win or lose
that dollar each uh iteration of the
game. And we can consider uh
having a uh
hit level for the
uh sum Sn being equal to plus a or minus
b. And so um the uh basically this
reflects whether we beat our opponent or
not where um our opponent
uh has
um a uh well let's see
where let's see if we have a bankroll B
and our opponent has a bankroll A um do
we win the entire bankroll control of
our opponent and hit A first.
Um
so we have uh this problem and we want
to know what's the likelihood of uh
basically player one losing
um and the SN is a martingale
and toao the time at which the sum sn=
plus a or minus b um is a mark is is a
stopping time. And so this is a
martingale by the stopping time theorem.
And with such a martingale,
we have that
the expected value of s at the stopped
time is equal to the expected value
initially
and uh that is equal to zero.
starting out at time zero uh sn is equal
to zero.
And so if we take the limit as n goes to
infinity, this converges to
the random variable s tow with
probability one. And this is proven
partly by
showing that
it the stopping time can't be infinite.
But if we assume that this these results
are uh valid then we have zero is equal
to the expected value of s tow. And if
we write out what s tow is at the
stopping time toao, it's either going to
equal a * the s tow hitting a or minus b
* the stopped value uh equaling minus b.
And if we take expectations of this
equation, we basically have zero is
equal to a times the probability that we
hit the level plus a minus b * the
probability that we hit minus b. And
those probabilities are complements of
each other.
So
the chance that we hit minus B at the
stop time is one minus the probability
that we hit A. So using these uh
relationships we get that the
probability that that we hit A first is
B over A + B. Yes.
>> So on the previous slide, can I just
check? I don't know might be an error or
if I don't understand something. Is it
meant to say solve for S to equals plus
A
where this problem involved?
>> Let's see. Can you ask the question
again?
>> So where this problem involved with the
code and then like problem solve?
>> Oh,
>> you meant to say probability that
Stowals plus.
>> Oh yes, it's probably the S to equals
plus A.
>> Yes, definitely.
Um,
>> no. No, that's fine. That's fine.
There's always typos. uh fewer typos on
slides than on the blackboard. I would
say that's the the benefit of having the
slides and easier to fix. All right,
thank you for that. All right, so so we
get this really nice formula for the
likelihood of hitting A before hitting
minus B.
And so
by symmetry, if A equals B, then this is
simply a half.
But if the player sort of B has a larger
bankroll then um the chance of taking
all the money from A uh basically uh
goes to one.
So it makes sense that if you're going
to gamble with sort of fair odds, you
you have an advantage if you have a
bigger bankroll than your opponent.
Now
this second example of uh martingales
which is sort of the square of the
random walk sn minus n um this is a
martingale
as well and if we look at the uh
uh this martingale it's bounded um
by uh the max of a^2 b² plus to. So we
have a bounded uh transformation
of uh the original SN. And so this
martinale is um has expectation zero for
all n.
And so if we look at the expectation
of M towel, this transformation of the
original martingale sort of Sn
um it has zero expectation
which is equal to the expected value of
S to squar minus the expected value of
TOA.
And
if we look at what is the expected value
of S ta squared.
So this term here um we have that that's
equal to
being stopped at plus a * a^ 2 plus the
probability being stopped at minus b * b
^ 2. And this expectation is equal to
zero. So we can actually solve for the
expected value of toao. It's simply
equal to the expected value of s to squ.
So
plugging everything in um it gets a
little tricky until we simplify and it's
simply the product of a * b.
So the amount of time it takes to
defeat the opponent
has an expected time equal to a * b.
So if you're gambling
uh in the in such a situation, the size
of your bankroll sort of times the size
of the other person's bankroll estimates
the approximate time it will take to
finish the game with one dominating the
other. Um anyway what's what's
characteristic of these examples is we
have a martingale
transform of the original series. It has
a zero expectation
um as as it's defined and that zero
expectation applies for all time points
as well as the stopping time.
All right.
Well, um, a really challenging
problem is to consider the random walk
with bias. So we consider
steps + one or minus one with
probability p and 1 minus p
respectively.
And then we're interested in what is the
uh
what is the probability of hitting plus
a say in this case. Certainly as uh p
increases the probability of hitting
plus a first increases.
Um but how does it do so? Now some of
you have taken stochcastic processes
already or how many people have taken
the course in stochastic processes?
Maybe just a couple. Um
do you recall this problem being covered
in your course?
And uh when I uh taught the stochastic
processes course about five or six years
ago, the way this was solved
um was sort of by brute force
understanding
the dynamics of the process and doing
computations with sort of first step
analyses.
And
the solution was really quite complex,
but it got the right answer. What's
really neat about Martingales is that we
can actually solve this problem pretty
elegantly. And so we're going to use
this moment generating function
transformation.
So our XNS have a moment generating
function
which is P the probability of + one time
E to the lambda * + one plus Q the
probability of -1 * E to the lambda *
-1. So this definition of the moment
generating function is very
straightforward.
If we take e to the lambda xn / v, these
are independent random variables that
have expectation equal to 1.
And we can define mn to be the product
of the first n yis.
And this will be a martingale by our
example four.
And
if
we solve for the lambda value
that makes f of lambda equal to one.
Then
for that fixed value of lambda this mn
is going to be a martingale. It's
actually a martingale for any lambda.
But in addition that special case where
f of lambda equals 1.
And so if we graph this moment
generating function as a function of
lambda,
we can see that it's equal to um equal
to one when e to the lambda is equal to
q over p. So this uh so mn for this
particular lambda
for which e to the lambda equals q over
p is simply q over p to the power sn.
And with that we basically have the
initial value of m at time one basically
or at time zero is one and that should
equal the stopped value of q over p to
the power s n at the stopped value. So
it's Q over P to the + A time the
probability of stopping at A plus Q over
P to the minus B * the probability of
stopping at minus B.
And again this equation basically gives
us two terms that are related to each
other that we can solve for. So we get
the probability that this biased random
walk stops at or hits plus a first is
simply the ratio of q to p to the power
b minus one over the same ratio to the
power a + b. So so this result is very
direct and
elegant. Um, if you look at stochastic
processes books that try to solve this
biased random walk problem without
martingale theory, it's a a bit more
involved and tricky. Um,
all right. So, here's just some R code
that will graph these probabilities as
functions of A and B. Um, I think it's
useful only just to know that you can do
something like this. You can graph the
probability surface as it varies with
the hit levels A and B. And here are
contours of the different uh
probabilities which can also be graphed
easily. And that's um sort of finishes
this initial discussion of of
martinales. Now a second uh topic in
stochastic processes
um that um is extremely important is the
concept of marov processes.
And so if we think of a general
stochcastic process xt
um then we will say that
the process is a marov process.
If for any times of the process
s
that's between u and t um that xt will
be independent of all xus
where u is less than s. So when we think
of
a time scale,
so we have u less than s less than t.
If we imagine realizations of a
stochastic process
and we are interested in
looking at the value of xt
Um
the value of XT
given information on times S and before
will be independent
of all of the times before.
And so the conditional distribution
so
so the distribution of XT given all of
the values of X prior to time u is equal
in distribution as the has the same
random distribution as
just the conditional distribution given
XS
So with a markov process
the future
depends on the past
only through the last value of the past.
It doesn't matter how one
arrived at a given value at time s for
different realizations that have the
same end point.
It's only that end point that sort of
indexes the distributions into the
future. So this is a markoff process.
It's like a uh um
it's it's
um sort of a a simple model where the
past
information can be encapsulated just in
the last observed value not in the
realizations of how that value was achie
was achieved.
Okay. So this is just some notation for
trying to say what I just said. Um now
with um marov chains these are
interesting stochastic processes where
we consider there being a state space
s capital s that where where we can
index possible states of the process
beginning say with zero
uh and the integers and it could be a
finite number or a countably infinite
number. And then we have a time index
set um with n varying from zero
to the through the positive integers.
And so the markoff property with this
uh markoff or with this with this uh
stochcastic process
um would have that uh the probability
of the next step
next state being J from time N given
the values of the process X knot through
XN. And um this conditional probability
is equal to the conditional probability
of J state at time n + one just given
that xn uh is equal to i. So this is uh
a nice property
for processes that makes their analysis
um a bit less complex. Um
and
what's important in this definition of
the uh Markov process is that um there's
a onestep
transition probability
from state
I to state J
from time N to N + one.
And these transition probabilities
um together with
the probabilities of the initial states
completely specifies the stochastic
process. Now this issue of completely
specifying a stochcastic process is an
important one in that what we want with
a stochastic process is to have a
complete probability model of that
process.
And so if we have sort of an initial
state x0
and the probabilities over
all states i and s that characterizes
the probability model for
the state zero value. Then if we look at
the probabil the conditional probability
from time n= 0 to n
to to or from zero to one. We then have
the conditional probabilities of moving
from any state
zero to any state and and at time one.
And so those
conditional probabilities together with
the marginal probabilities specify the
distribution of the process over state
zero and one. And we can continue this
computation
uh for successive time points and
completely specify our uh stochastic
process. Now
the general marov process as introduced
there is very complex because we may
have different transition probabilities
depending upon how long the process has
been operating.
A simple case is called a stationary
markoff process where these transition
probabilities one state one step
transition probabilities
do not depend on the time. So we have
the same probabilities of moving from
one state to another regardless of when
that is occurring. And so we can define
a matrix P which is the collection of
all sort of pair-wise probabilities pig
J moving from uh basically state I to
state J
and
we basically
require that these transition
probabilities are non- negative and the
sum over sort of target states J from
state I that those probabilities sum to
one for a stationary uh transition
probability matrix.
and
to sort of define the uh probability
distribution
of the entire process XN using this
stationary transition probability matrix
and initial probabilities.
Um we can compute any probabilities
by
computing the collection of all such
probabilities where we have sort of n
steps of the process or n time points of
the process and states i not through i
little n um there. So if we can
calculate these probabilities
uh we will have specified the
probability model. Now um in calculating
the joint probability of the first
little n values states being i 0 through
i n. Um we can decompose
this probability into
the marginal probability of the first n
minus one
and times the conditional probability of
the last given the others. So
if we think of sort of a equaling x0
up to x n -1 = i n -1
and uh b is equal to um
xn = i
then um
we can look at the probability of A and
B is equal to the probability of A times
the probability of B given A.
And this is basically what's written up
there. Um and this formula on the
blackboard is simply BA's formula
relating sort of the conditional
probability of B given A to the
probabilities of A and B. So probability
of B given A.
Now um with this
second equation we can simplify that to
the red probability which is only
depending upon the n minus one value.
And so um we have that the this
probability is equal to the marginal
probability of the first n minus one
times the
transition probability from state n
i i n minus one to i n and that won't
depend on n
and so um we can basically by induction
basically replace each of the successive
uh state transitions by the probability
of moving from one state to another and
the successive transitions of all those
states. So this joint probability
can be represented in this form
uh exploiting the markov property to
simplify the onestep transitions
and uh using the uh uh stationary uh
property to define these pigs.
Okay. Well, with a stationary transition
probabilities,
uh the multi-step transition
probabilities turn out to have a really
nice form.
And so we can represent
the transition probability matrix over n
steps
as the nth power of the onestep
transition probabilities
matrices.
So this property of uh markov change
with stationary transition probabilities
is very nice and uh gives us this this
result. Um
now um let's see there's
in terms of proving this okay there's
this analysis
called first step analysis in
stochcastic processes that's a really
useful tool for proving different
results
and
this uh first step
uh
prob uh analysis basically says okay if
we want to calculate the probability of
going from state zero sorry state i to j
um in n steps that's like starting at
time zero and state i and transitioning
to state j then we can
consider we can decompose this
probability
into the sum
over all possible first steps going from
I to K in state one and then from state
K to J
by time N. And so this first
equation here is a first step equation
of the probabilities. We can basically
decompose the process of going from
state I to J and N steps as going from
state I to each K state in step one and
then going from uh state K to N in n
minus one steps. So this is um
that
uh
formula. Um and so if we uh
write this out um we end up getting the
uh
xn
equaling or this in blue is equal to the
term above in black because of the uh
marov nature of the marov property of
the process.
And so we basically have this sum of pi
k um
times probability of uh xn minus one
equaling j x= k. And so um so this uh
so we end up basically getting this
matrix equation of the nstep transition
probabilities is equal to the onestep
matrix P * the n minus one step
transition probability matrix in green.
Okay. Well, um these transition
probabilities together with the marginal
distribution of the initial state gives
us the marginal distribution of xn at
any uh time. So um okay so the these
formulas just indicate how we do these
computations. Now where do marov chains
arise
in finance? Well, one example to think
about is how companies have credit
ratings
and those credit ratings range from high
credit meaning which is AAA and low
credit being I guess C D being default
is uh sort of maybe a terminal state at
least in some sense. Uh but companies
are graded or rated by standard and
pores and Fitch and other rating
agencies and depending upon how good
their credit rating is, they can borrow
money at lower interest rates.
And the way corporations borrow money is
to issue a bond paying a certain
interest rate and having that interest
rate be attractive to lenders. And the
way that
such a loan contract is attractive to
lenders is with um a high interest rate
to the lender but um a low risk of
default
uh by the uh borrower.
And so, um, one can think about how
these, uh, credit ratings vary, uh, from
one, uh, period to the next. And here's
a, uh,
table of sort of migration probabilities
from one year to the next. And one can
see that
AAA initial ratings
had only a 43% chance of staying AAA at
the end of that one year. Um and there
was a very low probability of downgrades
to you know C triple C or B. Um and uh
with
say very low credit rating companies the
chance of their basically increasing
their credit rating to be was 41%
staying at triple C is 32% but almost a
20% chance of defaulting perhaps. So, so
these kinds of uh
me metrics um basically can be uh
analyzed sort of with the tools of uh uh
uh Markov chains. Um and uh let's see
then another example um that I put
together is looking at the stock price
dynamics of
any stock but I chose Apple
and using daily prices to consider
states
of the Apple stock price which is is it
an upday or a down day. Is the price at
day t higher than t minus one or is it a
down day? I guess one of those should
probably be a less than or equal to if
they if we want to in incorporate
everything. Um but we can consider
defining a um a two-day
uh state which is
let's see the formatting here is a
little off but we could have two up days
in a row.
An up day followed by a down day. A down
day followed by an up day and a down day
followed by a down day.
and look at trying to model the state
changes for a two-day state um with a uh
marov chain and in R there's a nice R
package that
will do this for us and this u was
distributed in the canvas site
and so you should be able to replicate
this example
with Apple or choose any other stock you
might be interested in. And so
importantly,
okay, this uses the library quant here.
It's sort of hard to see.
Let's see. So there's a library quant
which allows us to collect price data
from the internet. And then there's this
uh package markoff chain which allows us
to specify
Markovchain uh models. And so with this
our code um it basically collects the
data on
Apple stock.
And
yeah, I think what's what I really want
to emphasize for everyone is that these
examples and it's a it's a bit tedious
if you want to go through these examples
yourself. However, the examples should
work just with clicking a button saying
run and you can replicate these. And so
for the Apple stock, we just needed to
substitute in the Apple symbol
and collect the data. And so here's the
Apple stock price from 2014 or 2013
through
um a week ago.
And
I considered just fitting a marov chain
model for these up and down states to
the last uh four and a half years.
And so the code here goes through
and
basically with Apple prices,
Apple closing prices. Here we define
differences in closing prices for two
lags and then talk about
defining up days
in this section here. up down days down
up and so forth.
And then if we graph
these states, say from May of this year
to the end of August, this shows how
this
four-state marov chain evolved over
these dates.
And
we can just use the marov chain function
uh
or let's see we can plot a marov chain
function um or a markov chain trans uh
transition states
um
as this graph here. So what's what this
code does is it looks at transitions
from one day to the next and calculates
the probabilities of going from one
state to another. So the sums across
rows equals 1 and uh this graph this
plot shows basically what is happening
with the marov chain. We have different
states
given by the nodes and then we can
transition from between nodes by which
arrows are feasible and this Markov
chain package will give us the
probabilities empirical probabilities of
moving from one state to another. And so
one can see that um
two up days in Apple are likely to be
followed by two up days
again. So that we'd get a third up day
with that one-step transition. Two down
days are not likely to be followed by a
third down day because it won't go to
that down state. uh with probability or
more than 0.5 or so um so there tends to
perhaps be reversals from double down
days and a continuation of up days as
sort of suggested by by these graphs. Um
now
with with this example I uh thought well
maybe there would be some interesting
structure if we defined three-day
states.
And so the same logic sort of gives us
eight states of up or down on three
successive days. And so sort of 2 * 2 *
2 or 8 is the total number of possible
states.
And one can calculate the probabilities
empirical probabilities of transitioning
and then get um
get this sort of display of the Markov
chain with these eight states. And so
what's rather
curious just to focus on our three down
days are not likely to be followed by a
fourth and three up days maybe are
likely to be followed by a fourth upday.
So um so you get some insight perhaps
into the overall dynamics and uh what's
great to me is that we can visualize
the process
and the graphical representation
of sort of nodes and edges between the
nodes um that have probabilities is is
quite useful. Um
so let's see if if you study Markov
chains
um and uh then one can
classify different states or different
nodes as communicating
states. So can you move from one state
to another or not? And in this case, one
can u move from one state to another
possibly not in one time period but in
multiple ones. And so uh this happens to
be a strongly connected set of states.
And let's see um
there was this this sort of little note
ends with um printing out the uh columns
of the transition probability matrix for
up moves
and down moves. And so
if we wanted to move from one state to
an up move the next uh period. Then
looking at this table, one can see that
the highest probability
of
the 3-day state being up in the third
day given the
prior three
day state. then it corresponds to three
down days lead to an up day the next day
with almost a 60% chance.
And um one can also sort of do the same
for down moves and see under what state
are we most likely to have a down move.
And so this
I think 0 510 is the highest which isn't
much higher than 0.5 but um basically
the past few days being a bit mixed uh
but with two up days um preceded by a
down day give us a higher likelihood of
a
uh down day. So um with let's see with
this note the uh
let's see there's a
okay so here's the uh reference for this
marov chain package and what's quite
convenient with different R packages on
different application
uh topics is that the these articles
often go through the mathematical
background of the models. And so if you
check out this
discussion, this article on the Marov
chain package, it actually will include
issues of the mathematical issues of how
you might classify different states and
do various computations. So that's quite
useful to uh uh have as a resource with
these.
Now um let's see with the uh
R Studio cloud files that were
distributed if you use those programs um
you can change the symbols from Apple to
any other and use different time periods
to see whether these properties may be
strong or not with other stocks. And I
think that that might be an interesting
thing to to check out. our
next topic which is on regression
analysis.
And uh
with regression
uh we want to just review the notation
and setup for multiple linear
regression. Um, if you've taken any
statistics class
uh prior to this, which most of you
have, you're very familiar with simple
linear regression where you have one
dependent variable and one predictor or
explanatory variable. Um we want to
consider the case of multiple linear
regression where we have a single
dependent variable and multiple
predictor or explanatory variables given
by X's and we want to describe the
relationship between the dependent and
independent variables. Now different
regression problems can focus on
prediction.
This is actually one that I find most
engaging at least trying to say predict
stock prices over fixed horizons is is
of real interest. Um but regression
models can also be used to um make
inferences of causality.
regression models arise in uh medical uh
experiments
where one of the explanatory variables
corresponds to a treatment effect. One
can also be interested in trying to um
approximate the dependent variable by
functions of the independent variables
and understand their functional
relationships.
So this is all of these uh objectives
can be um achieved with regression and
we
define a general linear model with
these equations here. We basically have
our observed yi values being a sum of a
fit fitted value plus error. And the
fitted value y had i
um is written here as a linear function
of the independent variables x i with
coefficients beta 1 through uh beta beta
p. And um there's actually a a typo
there. It shouldn't be beta sub. It
should just be beta p there. And um with
this setup, well, we could consider
different
explanatory variables that happen to be
just different powers of one independent
variable x.
We could also consider for a series
of
x variables.
Um, we could also have time series
regressions where
the independent variables x may
correspond to prior
time values of the y series. And in all
of these cases, what's really important
is linearity of the fitted value yhat.
And
what's linear is not
um
is is not that it's the sum of x's so
much as it is the regression parameters
beta are a linear function of those. So
the linearity of yhat
in the regression parameters is a key
property of this model and that
linearity
um dependence on the parameters allows
us to specify the parameters. Now um let
me just uh
go to another example here.
Let's see here.
Okay. Um here's a time series of the
high yield spread in u the bond markets.
And so this is looking at the yield on
bonds with a credit rating of B double A
uh minus the yield on the US Treasury.
And so this
difference in yield tends to be positive
well above two. It means that these
lower credit rated companies have to pay
more interest to lenders when they
borrow money. But that excess rate above
the treasury evolves over time and uh
sometimes you know drops
moderately or rises moderately. Now if
we were to use just
polomials to try and fit these well as
we extend to sort of eighth order
polomials we everyone here probably
knows that with a high enough order
polomial you can match any smooth curve.
No surprise. Um do we expect this uh
spread to actually follow some higher
order polomial? Probably not.
Um
here's another example of using Fier
series with the same
spread uh time series. And so as we add
in more terms in the Fier series, we're
able to model higher frequency
variations.
And what this shows is just how uh
I guess frequency analysis in financial
series potentially can be useful. Um
what's
really surprising though um is if we do
a auto regression
where here is the high yield spread and
then
we
basically have an auto reggression
saying that the spread tomorrow is the
same as the spread today or very very
close. Then we get this blue curve
fitting the black curve which is sort of
over underneath the blue curve. So we
get almost a perfect fit with um with
this auto regression.
So um there's a multiple R squared which
we will introduce you to but of.99
five for the auto regression. So the um
use of historical values of a time
series can be very powerful in
predicting future values.
All right. So, so in fitting a multiple
regression model whether it's with time
series factors or not um what we do is
go through these steps of proposing a
model step one and make assumptions
about the error term epsilon and then
second we define a criterion for judging
different estimators
and that that criterion can things like
le squares or minimum mean squared
prediction error or others and then
characterize the best estimator using
that criterion.
Then we check whether the assumptions we
made are in fact satisfied.
And very often we'll discover that
certain assumptions we make are not
satisfied and we need to revise those
and create a new model.
So
the models that um the model assumptions
we uh apply include
what are called Gaus Marov assumptions
which is where we assume that the errors
in the model have mean zero
and constant variance.
And so with this epsilon hat
corresponding to the n cases in the
series, we
basically
can assume these are mean zero and have
standard deviation sigma. That's a
constant.
And that these are uncorrelated.
uncorrelated.
Um we could additionally assume that
these errors are normally distributed
or not. Um we can generalize the Gaus
Marov to assume
non-constant variances of the errors and
possibly correlations of errors over
time. We could also consider non-normal
non-gaussian distributions. And all of
these cases actually have a role in
different uh in different contexts. In
particular, I guess generalized Gaus
Markoff methods apply with time series
regressions and the non-normal
non-Gaussian distributions arise um as
well uh often with asset returns data.
Now um in terms of what kind of
criterion we should use for specifying
parameters, we have le squares, maximum
likelihood, robust methods, baze
methods, a whole variety of methods. And
what's really important to me is for
people to have an understanding of what
these different methods are and when you
would prefer one method over another.
And so what I think is a really
important question to ask when doing
empirical analyses with different models
is um are your assumptions
uh reasonable if not satisfied by the
data you're modeling and with different
criteria for judging different
specifications of models.
Are you using an appropriate criterion
or not? Are there variations in that
criterion that would lead to higher
performance levels? So that for me is a
guiding sort of question throughout
these different checks. So with that um
we'll finish today and next time we'll
uh finish these notes going through
ordinary le squares uh estimation.
And what's useful about this development
of le squares estimation is that it does
so with linear algebra.
And what we'll see is that uh with
linear algebra we get very
straightforward formulas for le squares
estimates as well as interesting sort of
analytical properties of those le
squares estimates. So we'll cover that
next time.