So with that, here we have the startups.
I know you want to hear from them. So
first up, I'd like to introduce
Defraction. It's inspired by the eye and
its intelligent vision, superpowering
machines. So Christine, take it away.
>> Thank you. I'm Christine Wong, the CTO
and co-founder of Depression. My
co-founder and CEO Johannes Gas Hanosa
is an MIT Sloan fellow and researcher
while other co-founder professor Saka
Guha is an MIT alumnus and a professor.
So the problem we are solving is like
although today visual AI is used more
and more but we are still uh it's still
very slow and of low resolution. Why?
because we are essentially using the
same techniques that has been used since
the 1800s, the pinhole camera. And today
uh the way we do visual AI is not that
much different. We capture the scene uh
through a series of lenses of the
telescope or a camera and project it on
the camera sensor and then we create a
JPEG file and run the visual AI on top
of the JPEG via GPU or VPU. However,
quantum mechanists tell us like by
capturing the image, we have already
lost up to 95% of the information that's
contained in the photons. So, we draw
the inspiration from the eye. So,
contrary to uh what we usually believe
like the eyes are not just like cameras.
In fact, there are a lot of signal
processing and intuitive thinking
directly happening at the back of our
eyes before the signals reach the
brains. So when light hit the uh the
retina, the RGC cells at the back of it
actually fire up and that allows us to
process information very fastly and
react to fast change and movement
and drawing from the inspiration we
developed the visual sensing and
processing unit Galileo. It replaces the
conventional camera sensor plus GPU and
VPU combination and it has a much better
resolution up to 20 times better than
conventional imaging systems and also
about three orders of magnitude faster
processing and much lower energy
consumption.
So the technology we are using is like
we are not c directly capturing the
photon by detector but instead we
pre-process them with a series of face
plates to maximally extract information
and the resolution contained in those
photons based on quantum mechanics.
The uh this uh work has already been
demonstrated
experimentally showing that the say we
want to distinguish two very closely
spaced object and with a best
conventional camera while they are so
closely spaced together they are no
longer distinguishable. But with our
technology we can achieve about 25 times
better resolution and clearly
distinguish the two uh uh closely space
points and estimate their separation.
This uh work has been published in the
journal Optica to this year and was uh
funded by NASA and DARPA.
So looking at the competition landscape
um so our advantage in the resolution
and processing speed is both are both
like orders of magnitude uh better than
the current state of the art com uh
combination of camera sensors plus GPU
or VPU say we want to distinguish say uh
a small drone um then we can In fact,
run the visual AI uh detected up to 20
two kilometers away at a fraction of the
time needed.
Okay. So, um in terms of application
cases, the technology can be used across
many industries in both defense and
commercial. And our go-to market starts
from the uh defense side, the space
domain awareness, earth observation and
the air defense etc. And then while the
technology matures will uh could be also
applied to a lot of industrial
inspection, robotics or autonomous
vehicle. So our beach head market is
space domain awareness and earth
observation. So for example like
observing very small satellites and scan
for space debris uh etc. And for space
domain awareness, we are part of the
space force uh Apollo accelerator and we
have been actively uh talking to space
force for their use cases and for earth
observation in addition to defense uh
use cases there are also a lot of
commercial use cases like financial
services, agriculture or utility
inspections.
So for us um we for the partnership uh
opportunity although we are uh starting
in a more like defense and space domain
partnering with the US government but we
would like to hear from people like to
partner with all sorts of possible pilot
cases. uh for example in addition to uh
space domain earth obsession the other
commercial earth uh imaging
opportunities the um food manufacturing
inspections and eventually uh quality
control etc. So yeah, thank you