I will introduce the next faculty
speaker Dr Stacy Springs is exact
director at MIT Center for biomedical
Innovation St Stacy studied in Japan
during the summer in
2095 and this is her first time back to
Japan since then Stacy we talk about
innovation in manufacturing biom
and uh also uh friendly reminder to use
a pigon horse during her presentation
for if you have any questions so please
join me welcoming Stacy on the
stage uh hi gas it's really wonderful to
be here thank you so much uh for the
invitation uh it's my pleasure to tell
you a little bit about the It Center for
biomedical Innovation specifically we're
going to be talking about uh the
manufacturing or production of
biopharmaceuticals and innovation in
doing that uh in the next 30 minutes or
so and um I want
to just give you a little bit of a a
heads up on what we're going to talk
about so I'll first just introduce you
to the center and its
activities then we'll talk a little bit
about uh the challenges of man
manufacturing biologic medicines and
then we will go through as much as time
will allow some of cbi's
biomanufacturing research which includes
quite a bit of uh modeling including
mechanistic modeling to inform our
approaches to being able to intensify
the process of manufacturing
biopharmaceuticals uh the development of
of Novel process analytical Technologies
and also rapid safety testing
so the CBI has been at at MIT since
2005 and the uh the center was really
formed um with the idea of bringing
together uh investigators both internal
to MIT and external to MIT and
collaborative Innovation
initiatives over time um what we've
become I think is a collaboration engine
at MIT where we are developing V in and
adopting uh and moving toward adoption
Advanced biomanufacturing approaches
through both uh development and
demonstration of new technologies that
are fit for purpose and poised for
translation into industry practice as
well as working with industry to
establish consensus positions uh across
biomanufacturing approaches uh that can
AC you know accelerate the uptake of new
technologies across organizations or in
some cases uh can provide new ways of
drugs being
regulated so uh this is just another way
to look at our Center we are working to
implement Implement and improve Global
Health by overcoming obstacles to
development and implementation of
biomedical Innovation we primarily work
uh in the let's see if I can make this
yeah in this space of uh development and
Manufacturing distribution and Global
delivery and a little bit on the
downstream activities but primarily in
coming up with ways to improve our
ability to do drug safety
surveillance so um I would say that we
are primarily focused on
biomanufacturing Innovation data
analytics and Regulatory science and
everything we do we have an eye toward
trying to improve the access to biologic
medicines which are uh expensive to make
and uh difficult for um all all persons
to have access to so we want to be able
to lower the cost while increasing or
maintaining the quality of these
medicines we do this through three sets
of activities uh pre-competitive
collaboration with industry partners and
sometimes with the regulatory Community
through a portfolio of educational
opportunities uh for practitioners as
well as resident Learners at MIT and
then through our research portfolio so
I'll give you a brief overview of what
we're doing in the pre-competitive space
and educationwise and then we'll spend
most of our time talking about the
research
portfolio so pre-competitive
collaboration we have two uh industry
Academia consorti sorry about that that
we are um working on at CBI one is
called the bioman Consortium one is
called the Consortium on adventitious
agent contamination and biomanufacturing
in other words how do we work together
to mitigate the risk of viral
contamination and other types of
contamination in our biomanufacturing
processes and really the core to these
uh activities is pulling both industry
expertise and data uh and
um leveraging MIT as a as a neutral
third party that can uh collect analyze
anonymize data and learn things that uh
collectively can be useful to the
industry that an individual organization
is not able to uh to tackle on its own
we focus as you can see on the bioman is
more on manufacturing Innovation um
including data analytics and
biomanufacturing sell therapy
manufacturing vaccine manufacturing and
product quality control while the cacb
focuses on uh risk assessment and
management um so creating tools for the
Consortium to use and assessing their
risk of a viral contamination as an
example also looking at new technologies
uh and new challenges for adventitious
agent uh control and developing new
technologies in that regard as well so
we have 10 members uh member companies
in the bioman and and 24 in the cacb and
if that's of interest to you you can
find me later and I can tell you more
about how to
participate typically uh the activities
are around sharing experiences uh
datadriven uh presentations in a uh a
forum where the companies can share
information about what they're doing uh
to network identify best industry
practices provide opportunities to
Benchmark uh we do have collab uh you
know collaborative initiatives and also
um we provide members early access to
data and participation in the analysis
so just to give you an example of
outputs um you know we have collected
the viral contamination experience from
uh all of our member organizations and
publish this as you can see to together
uh in a nature biotech uh article
several years ago now but we continue
also to work on topics such as looking
at the promise of Next Generation
sequencing and potentially replacing the
adventitious uh uh virus test and animal
testing uh that is currently required
and you know what would it what would it
require to do this um uh and and
validate that for next generation uh
sequencing as a as a method and we've
published on that as well with our
Consortium members providing data uh on
both their uh inviva virus test results
and comparatively to the Next Generation
sequencing that they did in housee so um
with that I'm going to switch gears and
tell you just a little bit more about
our educational
portfolio and here we are really um
developing a lot of online and
collaboratively online and Hands-On
content for practitioners primarily but
also we do um some residential teaching
as well so you can see here that there
is a course that runs um
continuously uh on basically principles
of
biomanufacturing and we'll teach you
about the you know manufacturer of a
monoclonal antibody and a um insulin
we run a short course every year on
vaccine bioprocess development and
commercialization that'll be June 3rd to
5th this summer we have residential
courses we have courses on Cell Therapy
manufacturing and we're developing a
course now that'll run uh I think for
the first time in May time frame on
vaccine development and our first uh
thre day just like this but in July
first course on Cell Therapy
manufacturing will be coming this summer
okay so let's move into the research
portfolio so uh this is just an overview
slide to give you an example of the
types of things that we are working on
in our sponsored collaborative research
activities we're looking at multiple uh
biopharmaceutical modalities including
um you know monocolonal antibodies
vaccines Cell Therapy gene therapy
exosomes and so on
we are also looking at postmarket drug
safety surveillance in the sense that we
are working to uh develop predictive
signal detection and analytical tools we
work with a wide variety of Faculty from
across the Institute that's one of the
key features as I mentioned of CBI is
that we work both internally facing uh
across the school of science engineering
the Sloan School of Management and the
College of
computing and externally with uh
industry and regulators and this is just
a sample of some of the faculty from
across the Institute that uh we work
with and uh I will give you examples
from uh some of the work that I do
personally as well as Richard BRZ here
in chemical engineering Professor Scott
manales in
bioengineering uh a little bit from Rie
Ram uh in electrical engineering and
computer science uh and Jan over here uh
in electrical engineering and also
biological engineering
today all right so just let me set a
little bit of context as to why
biopharmaceutical manufacturing is
important um so as we you know
increasingly uh get larger with the
biologic medicines that we're making so
you know moving from small molecules
which have very well- defined structure
uh you know organic synthesis you can
analytically characterize them fully to
proteins monoclonal antibodies and then
now on to viral vectors for delivering
Gene therapies uh large vaccines and
cells as the therapies themselves you
have increasing size of the product
increasing variety or variability and
complexity of the product uh and so you
know we really need more analytical
tools and uh frankly more data to really
inform our understanding of both the
product and the process and uh to inform
process control strategies and safety of
these
products so this slide is kind ofit
there's I've got a couple of busy slides
here but this slide is really meant to
um you know introduce those who may not
be as familiar with
biopharmaceuticals to some of the uh
various types of approved products that
are out there um particularly the number
and type of emerging biological medicine
modalities so this timeline runs from
2011 if you can't see it to
2024 showing the approval of eight new
drug modalities so antibody drug
conjugates Gene modified cell therapies
crisper Gene edited cell therapies mRNA
RNA antisens oligonucleotides and
bispecific antibodies um so you know we
have all these new uh new innovations
that require essentially Innovation and
manufacturing and analytical and in
contrast the initial FDA approvals of
recombinant proteins and antibodies
occurred years ago in the 1980s and
1990s with biosimilar versions of these
drugs being approved later as shown here
in you know 2015 and
16 so it's important to note that these
earlier products such as small proteins
and and monoclinal
antibodies um have become somewhat
platformization in their manufacturing
over the last 20 to 30 years which means
that the the standard processes for
making these are pretty well defined um
and a lot of the Innovation is more in
moving to different modes such as
continuous manufacturing or in Pat that
can be used in line or at
line by contrast um the complexity of
some of the newer therapies such as a
cell gene therapy um you know really as
in the different types of cinge
therapies that are on the market today
and the sources of those starting
materials so on the left here you can
see different types of cell therapies
such as autologous cell therapies which
start from the tissue of a patient uh
who will be receiving the manufactured
drug product and and then is returned to
that that same patient and so it has to
be manufactured for each patient being
treated whereas an allogenic Cell
Therapy could start with the tissue of a
donor and be administered to unrelated
patients um but that also means that um
you know because the limits of the
ability of primary cells to retain their
functionality um upon expansion
typically this is you know used for
maybe 200 patients or less so it's not a
Panacea and then you have xenographic
xenogeneic rather uh therapies that are
basically manufactured using uh tissue
obtained from nonhuman sources
on the right um we call you know Gene
therapies
um can be basically describe describing
two different essentially approaches to
delivering a gene one the X Vivo um
which is on on the left hand side of the
right graph um that essentially is
really to you know you take the the
material the genetic material and uh
administer it into the cells that have
been removed from the patient and then
return them to the patient and these are
you know also called Gene modified cell
therapies and something like a CTE cell
therapy might be a good example of that
whereas on the right you have examples
of delivering the um genetic material
material in Vivo where essentially the
modified Gene is directly added to the
patient using either a viral or nonviral
vector approach
so going back to this idea of
platforms
um this is a very busy slide but what
what it does is it shows you essentially
key features of a monoclonal antibody
manufacturing process and some of the
key things that I want to point out here
um you know are that you have very
well-characterized raw
materials um you know basically that you
start with including the cells
themselves you are essentially um using
a a well-characterized cell bank and
materials that are going to be re you
know reproducible you go through a
series of you know expansion steps and
into you know your n equals zero
bioreactor and then your desired product
end up ends up being secreted from the
cells and can be harvested from the cell
Mass you do a filtration to clarify the
Harvest and then you know some
filtration steps land you in the
downstream over here where you can
usually use a St really stand standard
at this point Affinity column which is
protein a typically for a monoclonal
antibody to uh recover the desired
product from other Harvest fluids that
that uh pass through and then you can do
viral clearance steps to ensure product
safety followed by polishing columns um
usually ion exchange or multimodal uh
chromatography columns here and then you
know on to the bulk um drug substance
which can then either be formulated or
St stored and you know you're basically
producing lots of drugs that are tens of
thousands to hundreds of thousands of
doses in contrast cell and Gene modified
Cell Therapy um really you have wide
variety of the starting material um and
you have uh variability and you know the
material sometimes cells grow well
sometimes they don't you have uh
manufacturing that includes clinical
site
coordination and um you have a fragile
essentially product uh that has low um
shelf life typically and you basically
are you know taking something and
shipping it you know to a manufacturing
plant you have usually another another
manufacturing process to create the
vector that's going to deliver
essentially uh the uh the the the
genetic information you need in order to
modify those cells and then eventually
you're going to ship it back uh and
administer it in a clinical environment
so um some key things are that because
of this the cells themselves being the
therapy there's no opportunity for viral
clearance um again short shelf life and
temperature sensitive products as well
as difficulty in characterizing these
products so this gets us back to the old
dogma of the product is the process
which um we have for many years moved
away from that to trying to create
well-characterized biologic products but
for cell therapies you know really right
now where we're at is the product
product is the
process okay so uh more challenges in
gene uh in in these types of products uh
and I'll just give one example for the
uh gene therapy manufacturing and here
we're showing
using viral vectors to deliver the Gene
and the two platforms that are currently
uh most used today which is the triple
transection of hk293 cells where you
take your Gene of interest you take the
genes that um basic the trans Gene is
here then you take the the the
replication Gene uh rep and cap and
those are made on one plasma and then
you have a helper uh protein on another
you transfect all those and then let
them assemble essentially capsids that
then uh the the DNA is packaged into and
what you get out is essentially fully
packaged uh uh capsids partially and
then empties and unfortunately um we
make a lot of empty capsids these days
so typically you get this uh mixture you
have to separate it typically there's
multiple Downstream purification steps
required and you lose you know if each
step you're only getting 70% by the time
you've done multiple final yields can be
as low as less than
20% um so we're really not where we need
to be to meet the need of
patients um and so there's a lot of
innovation both in how we you know
manufacture these um and how we purify
them that and how and how we measure
them uh that is
needed um as I mentioned furthermore
there's a wide range of applications uh
for Gene therapies that require
different dose sizes um so here you're
just seeing uh an example of Li's
congenital amoros which is localized
small numbers of patients shown in red
total production scale shown in uh blue
and then uh in in green the total number
of patients so you don't need very much
you don't need big manufacturing
platforms for it see if I can get rid of
that um sometimes you have small number
of patients but you need big doses and
sometimes you have a large patient
population such as vericle cell anemia
so we need different scales of
manufacturing for aav as
well so I'm going to go into in the next
15 minutes um just talking with you
about uh some of the Innovation that we
are pursuing um at the CBI to address
these needs and I'll jump back to um you
know first the monoclonal antibody
example and then into the viral Vector
manufacturing example but in general
what we what I want to share with you is
essentially our approach um which
involves four different Focus areas
first mechanistic modeling and that
includes both numerical as well as um
you know other types of modeling of the
biological processes which are very
complex and lack a lot of fundamental
knowledge which is a key barrier in
being able to actually innovate uh and
uh we are trying to create these models
that can basically Drive our
understanding and what the key levers
are for uh improving drug production and
then we can use that fundamental
understanding uh that we get from our
models to optimize the manufacturing
processes uh in fit forp purpose and
scalable
manufacturing pardon me and then uh and
then we're also developing the novel
process analytical tools um which are
needed for monitoring and control
especially for the new drug modalities
um often which often require measurement
of Novel product quality attributes or
sometimes we don't even know what they
are yet and so we need to determine that
and finally and I don't know if we'll
get there today if we have time I'll
tell you about some of our approaches to
developing rapid safety testing
particularly sterility testing where
today you know it requires at least 14
days for the compendial methods to be
able to releasee your product and really
for the cell Therapies in particular
that's just not fast enough some of
these patients are um you know receiving
last line therapy and may only have
months um to live without these
potentially life-saving uh therapies so
we want to shrink that time down to less
than a
day okay so um I'm want to talk a little
bit about what we've been doing in the
area of uh smart data analytics so we
had a program that was sponsored by the
usfda that essentially um looked at
developing a number of tools um both at
the manufacturing process level um at
the manufacturing plant level and then
looking at ecosystem data to ask you
know how can we use all the available
data to ensure re reliable supply of
safe and effective medicines and so um
in order to do this we created some
tools we applied them um both inhouse in
a on a test bed that we've set up for
continuous manufacturing of monoclonal
antibodies we worked with several
industrial uh companies to utilize their
plantwide data both numerical and text
uh textual to optimize uh manufacturing
operational models and then we created
some uh drug safety surveillance tools
that can interrogate um postmarket
surveillance data to uh inform you when
you have essentially uh considerations
in either your manufacturing or your
supply chain um for postmarket um uh
drug safety
signals okay so just really quickly
these are this is just an example of
what we call Smart process analytical or
Spa tools uh Professor Richard Bratz de
developed these tools um and really you
know the challenge in using models in
biomanufacturing is that you have a wide
variety of data and some of it
especially in biom manufacturing is
sparse compared to say like Google or
Amazon scale data um and so you want to
make sure that you're not using models
inappropriately and um that data you
know scientists when they approach this
problem of what model should I use to
fit my data they you know don't fall
back on techniques that are just
familiar to them but they fully
interrogate the data um and select the
best model and so that's essentially
what Spa does is it it basically
automatically interrogates the data set
to ascertain its characteristics um so
you know if you have nonlinearity
Dynamics or multicolinearity then based
on the degree of the characteristics you
select a best-in-class analytical tool
from you know the pre-selected candidate
models that we offer um and that they
built based on literature review and
case studies and then finally you
construct the final model and a you and
using automated selection of rigorous
cross validation procedures um based on
the data attributes so that's kind of
shown on on the
right so an example of this um where we
worked with um we worked with actually
Amgen to utilize the spa tools and
develop a a model that could use process
variability variables to predict the uh
the product quality
attributes and this was for two
different u m monoclonal antibody
products um where we had multiple years
of data provided to us and the results
here are visualized in the form of these
violin plots where the model um
predicted that Alvin and uh also RF
might be uh the best performing uh
algorithms um and this is likely due to
the significant nonlinearity of the data
um however you know you basically if you
look closer at this as uh Richard and
his team did um you know the RF models
are somewhat harder to interpret which
means it's harder to you know identify
what the levers are using it um to
change the process and for that and a
variety of other reasons um you
know related to overfitting as it it
says here Alum was selected as the best
candidate they went on to
um show that you can leverage um when
you're when you're doing this you know
you would think that each batch might be
independent but there's actually strong
batto batch effects um or
autocorrelation which you can model with
tensorial approaches and then combine
that with the you know time series data
as shown here and that gives you
significant prediction Improvement um
that can be achieved as you can see here
for alum where the um the the root mean
square error is much lower for uh Alvin
after this Pro
procedure so as I mentioned we in
addition to um that type of modeling
that was done under this program we
built an endtoend
continuous
manufacturing uh platform at MIT to
allow us to uh collect and interrogate
um continuous manufacturing data uh in
an effort to develop model
that um can look at the gly
glycosilation uh of monoclonal
antibodies and and what's important for
that genetic stability as well as um uh
probar model selection tools and so what
you see here is that we have like four
three ler
bioreactors um a filtration device a
capture chromatography a housebuilt uh
low PH um inactivation skid and then uh
polishing chromatography
um that is shown here everything is sent
by a masked Auto sampler to different
analytical tools for atline and offline
analysis um in this
system and so shown here you know we are
um really interested in for monoclonal
antibodies and sorry this is a little
obuse but but but what this is is
essentially a um a map of glycosilation
uh through the ER that occurs where you
have multiple
reactions um that uh with each of these
being each of these little colorcoded um
shapes is essentially a sugar that as
you go through the ER gets you know
added and so you end up with all these
different glyco forms on on your
monoclonal antibody and you want to be
able to describe and control those and
so you know basically um what Richard
br's team does is he's he's created
essentially descriptions of all of these
and then the model um can be used to
understand the state sensitivity to key
manipulated variables so shown here is
you know how how the model is is
essentially performing in terms of the
measure glycans that we measured in the
lab versus his predictions and then on
the top you can see when we um the
sensitivity uh there's a significant
sensitivity to the galactose
concentration as you would expect but
essentially it allows us to probe when
we you know make changes during the
continuous process to different uh you
know additives essentially whether or
not there's a sensitivity and and the
model performs quite well in that way um
and also you can show you know this is
essentially the model performance um for
glycosilation index um that is uh
showing you know heart perfusion rate
and other factors that we can uh that we
can follow um and and model in terms of
predictive control of
glycosilation and then the last thing
that I'll talk about under this
particular um effort was essentially how
we incorporated ecosystem data um for
you know looking at Adverse Events so
here um what you're seeing here is
essentially our interrogation of whether
or not adverse adverse event profiles of
commercialized drugs could um be used to
indicate whether there was a
manufacturing or supply chain issue so
this was a collaboration with a company
that provided um this data as well as
data that we extracted from the fda's
adverse event report database and the
vaccine adverse event report database
for 26 biologic medicines a number of
vaccines and what you see in the top is
just that you know basically we've you
know found that the um Adverse Events
are definitely not uh distributed evenly
across lots and then what we did on the
on the lower is to develop a tool um
that basically uh interrogates this it's
a hidden marov model and identifies
hidden risk States and state transition
probabilities and then when that was
applied um you know to the when the Tool
was applied to see if it could detect
lot to lot variability in an actual
commercial product that had three dosage
forms um in one there didn't seem to be
any you know anything interesting but in
two of these dosage form A and B we were
able to you know find these most likely
uh sets of um uh you know states that
you can also see over here basically um
are are predicted to be higher risk and
then in dosage form one you can you can
basically look at those um out over time
as well in terms of the uh rate and see
that over time you you the rate is
reduced in both of these dosage forms
but you have more in dosage form a so
again just examples of the different
ways that we're using data um and a
smart way to apply it to different
problems in biopharmaceutical
manufacturing so next I just want to
briefly touch on the mechanistic
modeling and here um you know again why
do we want to do this we need increased
knowledge and understanding to improve
the process development and so this
knowledge pyramid just shows you know as
you go up the pyramid you have more
increasing knowledge the more that you
can work toward first principles or
mechanistic understanding and so for the
Triple transection of hk293 cells um to
uh make aav Rec combinant aav
essentially um we actually modeled this
system and what you can you know see
here is building upon existing knowledge
of basically taking one Plasma in uh to
a nucleus um the team created a model
for basically moving all of them the
vector the helper and the packaging
plasmids
in and um modeled this entire process it
was adapted from the wild type A
synthesis and includes the rep protein
and viral protein synthesis rep protein
regulatory functions capsid assembly
viral DNA replication DNA packaging into
the capsid and capsid um secretion and
so um we took this model and we uh
validated it um and you know basically
were able to do parameter estimation uh
as shown here and I'll just move quickly
due to time um and then when you start
looking at um the species that are the
inter intermediate species you can start
to see interesting things such as here
the discoordination between the the
production of the um capsid proteins
which happens early and the DNA that's
produced and replicated where you have a
lot of capsids around in the beginning
but you don't have much to package into
them which then informed you know some
of our strategies going forward about
how to uh improve that
situation including extending the capsu
production timeline uh to improve the
full to empty ratio of these we did the
same thing for the uh bacular Virus
Infection of uh insect cells of sf9
cells again the model was created and
indicates uh that the production of rep
78 or transcription of it um is what
controls the production rate of the full
capsids uh and we also looked at two
different constructs one is called two
back the other three back and because um
rep 78 is under a stronger promoter for
tuac uh we um um we we predict that that
that is actually the better um system in
terms of making uh recombinate a and
that turns out to be
true yeah okay so I'm going to wrap up
there um and uh happy to talk with you
about these other areas as Mak sense in
terms of uh if you have interest in
process analytical Technologies or rapid
sterility methods please catch me uh at
the break and I'll be happy to talk more
with you about those types of
Innovations thank
[Applause]
you
okay okay so the first question is any
example of startups to commercialize the
Innovations from CBI by collaborating
with industry so yes there are
definitely startups um including a
mechanistic modeling company called bio
cury that is um offering
essentially a service to collaborate
with people to do uh apply mechanistic
modeling uh tools to um improve your
manufacturing processes many of the um
analytical tools that we've developed
the process analytical tools have been
uh you know put into startup companies
that uh various you know uh postdocs or
graduate students started after they
worked on on some of them um some of the
tools that Scott manal's lab has made
for instance have um been uh
commercialized as well as um some of the
work that uh Jon has done so yes the ex
the a resounding yes um okay the second
question is do you think that the
approach you described could be applied
to the man to the manufacturer of
genetic modifications that amplify the
function of existing genes or cells
other than for treatment or uh
prevention so
um yes so I do think that you could um
if if I understand your question which
I'm not 100% sure I I do but if you're
asking could you apply this to say Gene
editing Technologies for instance then I
think you know certainly the answer is
yes you would be able to extend those
models but it might be a lot more
challenging right because those are
happening um you know sometimes X Vivo
which would be easier to model versus
something that you know you want to try
to um describe that is happening where
you deliver the Gene and then you want
to model what's happening in a in a
human um so I do think if that's your
question and please approach me if if
it's not if I didn't answer it correctly
uh or understand it
correctly oh so we are engaged and
committed in education so the question
is how is CBI engaged with and committed
in Education and Training a nextg uh
Next Generation teachers I think and uh
so we are so we we offer as I mentioned
the um different courses that are for
practitioners and that would include you
know teachers uh who are trying to you
know build their their Knowledge and
Skills around this type of manufacturing
so those courses that I cribed or either
available online and you can get
certificates or you can come to MIT for
the inperson courses and they're they're
quite open and available for anyone who
wants to um wants to take
them okay so how do you handle address
analyzing sensitive Health Care data
from your collaborators assume it is
very valuable for your collaborators
once they overcome this question
challenge yeah so um the the healthc
care data that we described um uh that I
described in the hmm tool and I have
another example that I didn't get to
describe um where we partnered with um
another company and we were looking at
actually their drug safety adverse event
data to come up with tools that would um
not only compare their data not only
look at their data but also compare
other uh data from companies that are
making uh molecules in the same
mechanistic class um and you're right it
is sensitive data but actually MIT in
that particular case um that was a a
project with um teada through basically
the MIT teada program where they put in
place um a platform for MIT researchers
to be able to work uh quite closely with
teada and have access to data from teada
so I think if you if you work um closely
with the organizations you can put in
place the um security needed to work
with some of this and then we uh publish
the Articles you know together and the
companies always have the opportunity to
review that for any you know confident
confidential information that they
wouldn't want to appear in a research
article so I think you know in general
what I would say is it's important to
set expectations beginning and at the
very beginning of a collaboration to
make sure that everyone understands that
you know in our case that we need to
publish research and uh and that we also
understand the various sensitivities to
any data but in general we haven't found
it to be a data be a be a barrier as I
said we've been able to get you know
essentially adverse event data we've
been able to get plants worth of
manufacturing data um and collaborate
with our uh members and collaborators on
that
so okay thank you