Um, a a very very warm welcome, but I uh
I'm going to turn it over to our um
hosts here at MIT to do the first
welcome.
>> Cool. Um, can we move the slide one?
>> Oh, I got it. Okay, let's see.
Um, do you want to talk about the flying
the plane?
>> Oh my gosh, I do. Um, all right. We're
going to get our This is actually the
perfect slide for our little start here,
which we coordinated and and rehearsed.
Um, I I love this picture because it uh
basically embodies everything that is
the organization heat and and the
process of um moving forward in
uncertainty. So we are here today um
with this amazing course which you'll
about to hear more about uh building uh
and fixing the airplane while flying it.
Um so I I I really want to know how that
picture came to be but
but it it stands. So it to that end I
want to acknowledge that you know we've
never done this before. Um it's really
can't it can't go wrong because of the
people in the room
and um we're really excited to see where
it does go. Uh and we're also really
excited to learn from it as always. So
for example, there is a lovely
whiteboard outside during your coffee
breaks that has two sides to it. One
side is who are the people and the ideas
and the topics that we need to add to
this conversation.
Please please put your ideas there. Um
and the other one is just general
feedback. Um thoughts, ideas, learnings,
changes, etc. Um please don't hesitate
to give us the gift of feedback. Uh and
now for the part we probably should have
started with. Hi, I'm Zay McAfei. I'm
the executive director of HEAT. And heat
is a um is a a nonprofit that has been
focused on trying to solve climate
change for a lot of years uh from a
community level in the beginning and um
scaling. So
we um will talk more about the topic of
geothermal networks in a few minutes but
first I want to just um express a lot of
gratitude to all of you for being
present and here and offering yourselves
to this conversation and and journey
that might might look a little hazardous
at times. Um, and also I want to just um
thank MIT the inst the amazing
institution and both Chris and Kurt for
being our hosts and I want to turn it
over to them to introduce themselves.
>> Um, thanks Anab. Uh, so yeah, I'm so
excited uh to welcome heat here to MIT.
Uh, my name is Chris Rae. I'm the
education program director at uh MIT's
environmental solutions initiative. Um
the education program mission is to
better understand and expand climate
education across both uh disciplinary
contexts and institutional contexts. And
I'd really like to make sure that our
education our projects and activities
are connecting to real world uh
scenarios. So it's so exciting to be
working with heat and kind of
reinvisioning the way that energy can
work. Um this is a part of a few other
collaborations. So uh we started a new
course called environmental justice
science and technology and that has a
massive open online version and heat
participated with a really interesting
lecture. Um and then also we're working
on some K through2 curriculum in this uh
day of climate uh project through open
learning. So it's just really exciting
to be doing both the K through2 space
and the higher education space with
heat. So again just so excited for heat
to be here. Um thank you so much.
>> Good morning everyone. Um, my name is
Kurt Newton. I'm director of MIT Open
Courseware, another of the co-hosts for
this event. Um, and we're thrilled to be
participating in this, not just to host,
but also because this is all going to
flow out to the world. We're recording,
as you know, we've got video set up here
to um to capture and then share back
with the world this important emerging
knowledge. Um you know we've had the
pleasure at open courseware with serving
this broader mission of unlocking and
empowering people around the world both
learners and educators for over two
decades. Um you see a screenshot of you
know the first engagement that we had
with with heat with Zanb a uh a January
session workshop that we did uh about
gas leaks you know part of the maybe the
origin story for so what we're getting
up to here um and what we do at open
courseware is not just sharing this
knowledge again but to do so in ways
that um encourage practices of sharing
and the feedback that gets set up
through this through this sort of
broader open knowledge ecosystem. So
heat for instance, you know, putting all
of these resources in an open library
and gathering together to, you know, in
a really nimble sort of generative way
create this knowledge new. I I'm
recalling here at MIT in January 2020,
just before all kinds of stuff got shut
down, we we hosted here some design
cherettes to start this process. and
just what a what a thrill it is to us to
be kind of part of this journey
together. And just to let you know if
you're not familiar with open
courseware, you know, the the reach of
this content is considerable around the
world. 70% of our of our visitors come
from outside North America. So that the
interest around the world that's
developing in these technologies, we
want to plug into that. Our website gets
millions of visits every year. Um and
our YouTube channel where the videos you
know also live is also a really
important point of engagement. Um with
over five and a half million subscribers
on our YouTube channel it's the it's the
largest subscriber base of any sort of
educational institution out in the
world. So rest assured that that what we
come up with today you know flowing out
to the world is going to reach a lot of
people and it's really going to I think
further the the work that we're all
trying to get up to. So welcome.
But don't hesitate to talk after that.
>> Thank you. My name is Isabel Varela,
science director at HEAT. And I wanted
to briefly share this is the heat team
that is here to help you. If you have
any questions, uh don't hesitate to
reach out to us.
We've put together um an incredible
program. HEAT takes the aim to look at
uh for solving a problem bring identify
all the stakeholders that need to be
involved to make that change happen and
this two-day course reflects that. As
you see we have eight sessions for each
day and they vary from what is the
challenge that we need to solve? What
are the policies that need to be
implemented to do that? Um what are the
learnings that we can get from the
geothermal networks that are implemented
today? what are the design principles
that should be applied um and learn from
case studies.
We are excited that you're here and we
hope you get uh most out of this course
and participate your participation makes
the course more lively
and
we have an incredible lineup of 28
speakers that are here. Some of them
have come from uh around the country to
be here in these two days. And we have
organizations represented from
universities, gas utilities, regulators,
design firms, and community- based
organizations. So, thank you for all the
speakers uh that are here and making
this uh course happen.
Um
>> just a quick note about the nature of
the recordings that we're going to be
doing. So what we'll be sharing with the
world will be the the talks
um and just the videos of the talks.
There's a really important sort of Q&A
interaction segment that will happen for
each each of the sessions and we will
not be sharing those straight out with
the world. We want to have a you know a
frank um completely un you know
unconstrained conversation here in the
room. Our hope is though that we will be
sharing some kind of notes and takeaways
some summaries and synthesis from those
conversations. But rest assured um
unless you are a speaker up here. We're
not expecting you to show up in these
videos that we share on OCW. If you have
any concerns or questions about that uh
please reach out to me, be in touch, but
hopefully that's all right. Okay.
>> Uh yeah. And um our our format uh is
that each session is going to have a few
brief presentations. Every single one of
the speakers could likely speak for
hours uh on any one of the topics and um
and we're so aware of that. But we also
thought that the most valuable thing
here in the room is the interaction
between. Uh so for um many speakers
there will be a longer recorded piece of
content that's attached to the
courseware. Um but in the room we're
going to keep the presentations brief so
that we can get to that part of
interacting between and talking and
interacting with all of you. Um, and uh,
we've got a Slido. Um, it's a little app
that we'll introduce in a second um, for
you to engage so we can kind of get more
voices involved more quickly um, so that
we can get the conversation going. Um,
and then I've said this already, I'm
going to say it again. You know, this is
this is our first go at this. Um, I I
love that you mentioned the previous um,
wonderful events. The first one was a
hackathon to design a a a tool to
measure gas leaks. Um and the second one
was a sharet. And now we're now we're
trying um this this content. So uh
you you will you will be part of making
it um wonderful today. So please don't
hesitate to participate. All right.
One last comment for housekeeping. We
have uh breakfast in the morning
outside. We'll have coffee breaks. We'll
have lunch outside. Uh food is allowed
to come in here if you want to.
Restrooms are here immediately to the
right and there's another one in the
hallway uh to the left.
>> Thank you. And Isabelle planned this
incredibly. So
>> with the tea. With the tea.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. With with the tea.
All right. So one of the things that we
always do and and I know Kurt is always
in on this. It's open. So, uh, your
backgrounds here in the room are all
over the spectrum. We think that's
beautiful and exciting. And one of the
things we're going to try to do is make
sure that we move between um,
introductory and advanced. And we're
we're it may be a fire hose, but that's
why we're providing coffee. Um, so I get
to start us off with two quick ideas for
the entire two days and then we have the
most amazing panel to get going at a
very like high scale level of you know
the whole the whole world. Um, so
um
our our new our new uh tagline at the
moment at HEAT is think thermal
together.
Um it kind of embodies a lot of the
pieces that we're we've been learning
over the past few years as we move
forward with um networking ground source
heat pumps or geothermal heat pumps. And
um that idea of getting uh a problem
solved by working together that's that's
always been um there. But the piece
where we realized as we as we spoke
about geothermal that thermal energy
itself wasn't always on the table in the
climate solution space that people
weren't thinking, they weren't
measuring, they weren't talking about
thermal energy. So, I'm going to just
briefly start by getting us to take a
moment to put on our thermal energy
glasses. Um and then I'm going to do a
little bit of housekeeping on language
so that uh you know terminology and then
we'll move to our first panel. Um so
think thermal. Let's start with that
part. Uh this is an image. If you use a
thermal camera which actually we've
recently purchased for the sheer fun of
it. Um if you use a thermal camera you
see things differently. um our eyes
don't do that which may be why we don't
we ignore it so often. Um but there is a
huge amount of thermal energy in our
earth and really if you stop and think
about climate change what is climate
change except a thermal energy
regulation problem.
And so if that's what it is and we talk
about the rising temperature in air,
well the kind of stunning thing is that
uh there are a bunch of papers
calculating how much thermal energy the
earth has absorbed since say 1960
um and it's 630
times
approximately all of the energy humanity
uses every year.
So I I was delighted to learn a new
metric of energy, the zeta jewel. Um
apparently humanity uses half a zeta
jewel a year. All the energy we use. And
every year our oceans alone are
absorbing five zeta jewels.
So that's a kind of stunning
gut-wrenching challenge.
But if you start to think about thermal
energy, if start to look at it, if you
start to measure it, it's also an
extraordinary opportunity. It's a
massive amount of energy all around us
that we have been ignoring.
And we have the technology to tap it,
which is what we're here to talk about
today.
Um, a recent report from the IEA had a
rather stunning statement um that kind
of defines part of our our two days that
the technical potential of geothermal
would be more than enough to meet all
heat demand. That's all heat demand. And
they're not even talking about cooling
in Africa, China, Europe, Southeast
Asia, and the United States. So, I read
that and I thought, well, what about
those other places? Um
but I also want to just add into the
conversation not just that geothermal
energy that's in the world all around us
um but also
uh the energy we waste all that energy
we do use combust burn etc um the
majority of it is wasted
uh and a large large portion of that is
thermal energy. So that is where we can
think about yet another untapped
resource all around us. All right. So
taking the optimistic part of like wow
there's thermal energy all around us.
This is really exciting. Um what we're
here to do today for two days is talk
about um the technology we uh believe is
there and ready for us to tap it and
turn it into a solution. Um talking
about that technology sometimes has some
challenges.
Um
we we try to bring everyone together.
Lots of different groups have lots of
different language. Um this is kind of
the heat approach that we've been
talking about uh earlier with many other
events. Um you're now part of it being
in the room. Uh so coming together
around what we mean when we say things
is one way to start get us all on the
same page. Um, and
the first thing we have is a little
quick intro visual, which many of you
may have already seen. I apologize if
you have. Um, explaining the technology
of networking geothermal heat pumps in a
very basic level. Tomorrow, you're going
to get a very advanced level. For now,
this is right beneath our feet. The
Earth is soaking up energy from the sun.
And it's been doing this for a long
time. Near the surface, the ground warms
and cools with the seasons, but lower
down, it stays at a constant
temperature. In Massachusetts, that's
55° F year round. This store temperature
is a source of renewable energy. It can
be access to heat or cool a single
building without using fossil fuels. But
did you know we can also connect entire
communities to that renewable source in
the ground? How does it work? It starts
with underground pipes in the streets,
sort of like gas pipes, but filled only
with water. The water absorbs the ground
temperature of the earth and delivers it
to buildings. Pipes connect buildings
with different heating needs. So, energy
is never wasted. Instead, it's exchanged
between buildings or stored in the
ground until it's needed. Inside, a heat
pump moves heat in or out according to
the temperature you want. This system of
pipes can connect like Lego blocks.
gradually moving us all from gas to geo,
giving us cleaner air, efficient heating
and cooling, and a healthier planet. The
idea for this worked geothermal system
run at a utility scale originated at
HEAT, a climate solutions nonprofit.
Uh, all right, I'm going to really
quickly go through language and then get
out of here for so we can start this
amazing panel. Um the word geothermal uh
if any of you are thinking about uh you
know Iceland and hot lava that's that's
the stuff on the left. Um this is our
one way to try to clarify that
geothermal is like the last name of a
family of technologies and energies
both. Um and that uh the one we are
talking about today is on the right. It
isworked
geothermal heat pumps can provide
heating and cooling is what is typically
called shallow. You'll hear purple hear
people use the word shallow. Um but for
the usual person uh 1,000 or 1200 feet
isn't doesn't sound shallow but I I
promise that's shallow. Um and then uh
it is ambient temperature. In other
words kind of the average temperature of
the air and the ground. not super hot in
any way. Um, and uh, one of the things
that's really critical about this type
of geothermal energy is that it is
everywhere.
Um, you'll hear people talking about the
word district and certainly this is a
form of district energy and the
traditional naming system goes by
generation. first generation, second
generation and the type we are
discussing today primarily is fifth
generation. Um and
the next more advanced level of this is
okay. So why are we calling it a network
then? And uh our proposal which is not
universal um but there is kind of an
emerging nomenclature um is that within
fifth generation um if it has a single
pipe decentralized and renewable and
combustion free then it is a thermal
energy network and if that thermal
energy network is tapping geothermal
energy which changes some of the
outcomes then you could also call it a
geothermal energy work. That's what
we're going to use, but you'll hear
speakers use a lot of different
terminology. I just wanted to give you a
a quick lay of the land. Um, and our
last task before we begin is if you
could please take out your phone. We
have um this QR code you can scan and it
should work pretty easily to get you on
to Slido. And now you have um your first
quiz.
We did say class, right?
No, don't don't worry. There's actually
no test. Uh but um
let's see how you do.
Yeah, I made it too easy.
So, if you have any trouble getting on,
um, Erica back there is happy to help.
>> You can also, you can also open your web
browser and just go to slid.com and type
in.
>> All right.
I like watching them go out and back.
That's how I think.
All right. Are we good?
everyone on slidoh now for the rest of
the day. Okay. Uh so yes um the the
group um the group wisdom is prevailing.
Uh the type of geothermal energy we're
discussing today is ambient shallow and
everywhere. Um which is a lovely
feature.
Um all right. So, we're going to take a
a second and um begin our first uh
conversation.