[MUSIC PLAYING]
SILI DENG: I've been always
interested in science.
I got very much into
combustion because I
think it's an intellectually
challenging problem.
You can imagine in combustion
you have chemistry.
And you have fluid mechanics.
Each subject is very
rich in science.
This also has very strong
engineering implications
and applications.
It's a hard problem.
It's an important problem.
That's why I wanted to
be working in this area.
So still now, 80% of the
global energy production
is from the combustion
of fossil fuels.
So how do we do the transition
from the heavy dependence
on fossil fuels to renewable
energy with storage?
So my group is really
targeting these three areas,
building up the
fundamental knowledge
on combustion processes.
Second is to develop alternative
fuels and metal combustion
to replace fossil fuels.
And the third is to have this
flame-based synthesis that
can bring down the cost of
generating battery materials.
I was first introduced
to flame synthesis
in my junior year in college.
At that time, I realized
you can actually
burn things to make things.
That was really fascinating.
So I wanted to study why and how
does particles form in flame?
Flame synthesis, this technology
actually can be dated back 3,000
years ago in ancient China.
This is a primary way of
making the black ink materials.
So what people did was burn
down vegetables or woods such
that afterwards they can
collect the solidified smoke
on the wall.
For our battery
applications, we can
try to fit in the same formula,
but of course with new tweaks.
We developed a technology called
flame-assisted spray pyrolysis.
So in short, it's called FASP.
We aim at FASP synthesis of
lithium-ion battery cathode
materials.
The cathode material for
lithium-ion batteries
contribute to 30% to 50%
of the cost of the battery.
The primary target
for us is to come up
with scalable
manufacturing methods
to reduce the cost of
producing battery materials.
We are also very interested in
developing alternative fuels,
such as metals.
Aluminum, for example, have
been used for solid rockets.
Nowadays, we are interested
in utilizing aluminum
as a fuel for
similar applications.
Because aluminum is
really abundant in Earth.
And it's cheap.
And it's available
to all the countries.
What we are trying to do is to
understand different regimes
that aluminum combusts and be
able to tailor its ignition
and propagation properties.
When I was a small kid,
when I watch TV shows,
I always got very
interested in detectives.
And I wanted to be one of them.
I feel that by doing research,
we are like detectives.
We are unfolding many
interesting science
and be able to leverage that.
We can also see a greater
impact in our daily lives,
in our society.
And that's what keeps me
going in scientific field.
[MUSIC PLAYING]