so it's a pleasure to be here and it's a
pleasure to share a little bit about the
ideas that our lab is developing to
interface with the body and the Brain to
understand the complex interplay of
signals between our brain and the
viscera and when we thinking about the
brain and Mark just had this absolutely
beautiful introduction of the complexity
of the brain this is another picture
taken by my talented colleague Professor
Casey Chong uh when at the time when he
was still a pooc and we were in the same
lab and there you're looking at
different colors and those different
colors represent different types of
cells each of those cells has a specific
function and together they play as an
orchestra to really make us who we are
now how do we probe this wonderful
complexity there is a variety of tools
that we can use but when we think about
uh look at them in aggregate everything
that we can possibly implant into the
biological system came to our field from
the field from semiconductors and
electronics now those tools can be
extremely powerful and useful they can
have they can be really fast and have
really high resolution but I'm a
material Scientist by background and
when I look at them they all to me seem
to have something in common in terms of
their structure and that is they're hard
they're brittle and they're sharp and
they have very little in common with our
actual tissues so when when we thinking
about the elastic modules of a typical
semiconductor wafer we thinking about
hundreds of gigap pascals while our
brain has elastic modulus of a pudding
or yogurt in the order of kilopascals
maybe megap pascals now what do you
think is going to happen when we use a
device with elastic properties of a
knife and implant it into the brain with
elastic properties of a pudding now also
let's take into account the fact that
your device most likely be fixed to the
skull while the brain moves every time
you take a step every time you take a
breath or your heart beats so now you
have a device and your brain is moving
around it so we're starting to damage
the very tissue that we are trying to
very precisely interface with to extract
those sophisticated signals that Mark
for instance has been talking about so
how do we solve this problem in our
group we draw inspiration from nerves
when we thinking about a nerve
those can of course go on for kilometers
or start from micrometers they can
transmit a variety of signals not only
electrical but of course also chemical
mechanical and other signals and they
goes they're flexible and stretchable
and they span our entire body so
wouldn't it be great to be able to
engineer an artificial Nerf and this is
exactly what our lb is interested in and
to do this we shamelessly steal and
borrow from photonics and
Telecommunications which is more
commensurate with the field that I came
from in opt
Electronics so in opt Electronics we are
all aware with Optical fibers those
carry our signals underneath the oceans
allow us to call our friends in London
and Tokyo but those fibers that are
typically based on glass but it turns
out they don't have to be we can make
fibers from any material that we want in
fact we can bring many materials
together as long as they have similar
thermomechanical properties now we can
imagine a device on a micro scale we can
think for instance that we are
interested in recording neural signals
so we need electrodes we may want to
perform Optical stimulation with a
method called optogenetics that uh Mark
touched on and which means we need
Optical wave guides we want to be able
to deliver drugs which means we need
microfuidic
now we can take this imagination to the
machine shop and incorporate all those
features that we're interested in in a
macro scale using very simple
fabrication techniques then we can take
this macro scale model that we call a
preform we heat it and we pull it and
features that started out as inches
become
microns and we get a Kil kilometers of
integrated flexible stretchable
structure that with all those functional
features how does it actually look and
feel if you take one of your hairs and
imagine that inside it are electrodes
Optical channels microfluidics variety
of other sensors but the size and uh
mechanical properties are very similar
to your hair with these types of devices
we can perform many functions for
instance we can simultaneously stimulate
neural activity and record it in real
time we can then also combine it with a
delivery of a drug for instance here
this pink rectangle is an infusion of
inhibitory compound um which then
reduces the neural activity in this
particular uh brain region and as the
brain starts to wash out this drug the
activity begins to recover and as it
recovers we can watch it in real time
now this experiments we have been
performing them in mice in in context of
various beh behaviors in the context of
fundamental
Neuroscience but what if we wanted to be
able to translate this technology for
clinical use we have to conf confront a
very simple problem and that is the
problem of size turns out Mouse brains
are about the size of your
thumbnail human brain is the size of
your two fists brought together if you
design a tool that you fully test in a
mouse that tool will be probably on the
order of a few millimeters in dimensions
and have can have high resolution now if
you want to take the same style tool
translated to a human it now needs to be
about 8 cm for the same
application which means everything about
your design needs to change if it was a
wafer bound
process however this logic does not
apply to fibers because fibers are drawn
by kilometers
so the same tool that we can test and
rigorously evaluate in the context of
many different Mouse experiments now if
we want to go into a larger brain we can
simply just cut a longer piece and
maintain all the same functions and this
is exactly what we did and we're for the
first time able to translate fiber based
tools for experiments in non-human
primates where it was very difficult to
achieve simultane recording and chemical
neuromodulation the same way we would do
it in a human patient here we are uh
have a a awake um non-human primate
performing a task uh but what matters
here is that we are recording neural
activity with single neural precision
and then we are going to infuse a drug a
Gaba inhibitory compound and as we
infusing this drug at a low
concentration low amount you see
temporary inhibition of neural activity
for a short amount of time if we Infuse
more drugs our activity will be
inhibited for longer and of course this
is a proof of concept experiment
experiment but it shows that we can now
apply this Technologies in translational
models and U uh in a variety of
contexts but what I'd like to talk about
next is our field of Neuroscience in
general it so far we have been focused
on the brain and brain is complex and
we're still trying to figure out how it
works but we are largely been
considering it in
vacuum but more and more we're starting
to learn that brain is intimately
connected to the rest of our body well
if you cut off the head you know what
happens but also that those inputs from
our body may be influencing how our
brain works on a higher level and
there's
a lot of evidence for this for instance
there are now experiments that show is
not only that anxiety makes your heart
Pace faster in fact pacing the heart
faster makes one anxious we also now
know that it is possible to treat
arthritis and which is an inflammatory
conditions by tapping into neural
signals of the vagus nerve a large nerve
that con connects your uh um brain stem
to the organs in your body we also
starting to learn that the microbes in
the gii tracts somehow transmit
informations to the brain and that
information can be can change our
behavior for instance make us more or
less motivated to exercise so how do we
now record those signals how can we now
begin studying those systems and those
connections in a rigorous way and I'm
going to approach this problem starting
from one uh particular circuit and that
is the communication between the gut and
the Brain why those are are interesting
well there's 100 billion neurons in your
brain but there also happens to be a
billion neurons in your gut what are
they doing that's a good that's a good
question why should we know what they're
doing well it turns out we can link many
condition that we typically think of as
neurological or psychiatric to
dysfunctions of U gii tract and we don't
know whether they're correlative or
causitive but what we do know is eight
out of 10 Parkinson's patients would
receive a constipation diagnosis back in
their medical history by 20 years before
they even know that they have moror
dysfunction nine out of 10 autistic kids
would have severe GI symptoms ranging
from food sensitivities to uh cyclic
vomiting and based on the genome wide
Association studies anxiety and IBS
share genetic risks are those causitive
or correlative we don't know we need to
be able to study these neural
connections and while our tools work
really well in the brain we now are
confronted Vis A system that even more
complex from an engineering standpoint
and that is the gut
unlike the brain that moves a little bit
within our skull and it's surrounded by
the skull the gut moves
microscopically the and continuously and
the nervous system of the gut is
embedded in a thin uh gut wall in a
mouse it's only 300 microns and it's not
much thicker in a human if we puncture
gut wall we can uh and cause severe
reaction it can result in sepsis and
deadly at the same time this system is
also full of stuff and that stuff is not
nice now how do we design electronics
that can withstand the assault of the GI
tract but at the same time not damage
its delicate walls in our group we have
previously designed fibers that were not
only flexible but also stretchable and
could in principle accommodate gut
movement M and
deformation however they still had a
fiber architecture where most of the
emission happened at the tip all the
functions were confined to the tip here
the clading is stripped so you can see
it in the dark but the gut nervous
system is actually distributed along the
length of the gut which is about four
times longer than the mouse or seven
times longer than a human so how do we
deal with this distributed radial nature
of this organ we had to completely
rethink how we design these um uh these
devices how do we distribute sensors and
we did this by combining mature
microelectronics with fiber based
fabrication we can now take microscopic
sensors produced on wafers in standard
fabrication processes incorporate them
into the fibers at the level of the
preform and as we draw our fiber El
elodes that are Incorporated can form
contacts with our electronic components
giving us fully functional devices that
can be communicated with within the
fiber here I'm showing you LEDs because
they're really fun to look at but of
course we can do a variety of other
sensors such as photo detectors chemical
sensors and maybe even Computing
components going forward now by having
all our Electronics embedded within the
fibers rather than being interfaced
externally means that we can now use
wireless tools to communicate with this
devices and untether our experiments and
here in these
simple uh uh demonstrations you can see
LEDs lighting up in gut and brain sides
of our device but the same devices also
contain electrodes for neural recording
contain microfluidics for drug delivery
now we have means to interface with the
gut and the Brain and do so wirelessly
what questions should we ask well we're
talking about the gut it's lunchtime we
are all starving so let's talk about
food now the uh and the simple question
we are going to ask is preferences for
Taste and if we are thinking about uh
choosing whether we are going to drink
real Coke or Diet Coke we you think
we're choosing this completely based on
flavor but we can actually make the
flavors in the lab be very very similar
and we can offer Mouse a choice between
real sugar and Splendor and it turns out
mice are not fooled by sweetness and
they learn to prefer the real sugar very
very quickly within seconds and they
will only drink real coke they will
never drink diet so and neither should
you so the um however now we can use our
God
neurotechnology to inhibit the activity
of sensory cells that can chemically
distinguish between sucrose and fake
sugar sucral loes and when we inhibit
those gut cells mice lose their ability
to distinguish between those sugars and
they will drink diet coke just the same
so it's not the taste not only the taste
that decides it but what happens in your
gut the gut loves the calories
now how can how about some more
interesting effects can we turn to
something that we typically associate
with the brain and uh Mark has mentioned
reward circuits which are the circuits
that control our mood and our happiness
how do you think about happiness in the
mouse well we typically think about it
as release of dopamine our neur
happiness neurotransmitter in the parts
uh in this uh in the midbrain part of
the of the uh central nervous system now
when dopamine gets released it
supposingly makes animals um feel
rewarded and uh uh respond to this
behaviorally and this is a very classic
behavioral Paradigm because we cannot
ask mice so we have to perform a
behavioral essay and this essay is very
simple it's a we place mouse in a box
and in this box there are two
compartments and on one side of the Box
we can apply the stimulation and we are
going to stimulate dopamine NE neurons
that will release dopamine and when that
happens mice feel happy in uh or
rewarded in this com uh compartment and
they learn to prefer this area this is a
very robust effect this is a textbook
sort of laboratory experiment and
Neuroscience it's used across many
different stimulation uh
paradigms so now we're going to conduct
a different experiment we are going to
leave the brain alone and we are taking
the same uh Place preference as say but
now we are going to use our gut fiber to
stimulate neur nerve endings at the
level of the durum that actually
lead uh via the vagus nerve to the brain
and ultimately connect to rever circuits
and when we do this we get exactly the
same effect mice learn to prefer the
stimulation chamber just the same way as
they would have if we stimulated their
brain we're now doing it completely at
the level of their GI tract which gives
implications that it may be possible in
future to treat conditions such as
depression or post-traumatic stress not
from the level of the brain but from the
level of the periphery which could be
significantly less invasive now the
message that I would like to leave you
with is that every organ in your body is
inovated every organ in your body talks
back to the brain and now we have the
bioelectronic tools to tap into the
power of this brain body Innovation and
start achieving whole human health and I
have to thank my extremely talented
group of students and postdocs and
generous support from Kisa Yang brain
Body Center as well as national uh
Institutes of Health and other agencies
thank you very much
thank you very much Pina for this
interesting presentation to me you just
explained or gave a scientific basis to
what we commonly refer to as a gut
feeling
right so any
questions I I don't um thank you so much
was such a fascinating uh presentation I
saw the Splender versus uh suus
experiment and I'm assuming the Splenda
versus equal versus everything is the
same right it can distinguish sugar
versus any of those sweeters right so we
have not conducted that precise essay of
trying to do multiple artificial
sweeteners so sucros is typically used
so as long as it's a sucros based
artificial sweetener you would get the
same effect effect if it's uh sweetener
based in a different type of sugar then
we have to look at the receptor profile
in those cells and whether those will be
with it so the types of cells that we
are stimulating they're called chosy
ainin uh and Tero Endocrine cells in the
GI tract and um they happen to have
receptors for both the sucrose and
Sucralose and when they send sucrose
they actually um send a neuronal signal
uh mediated um sort of uh uh
through
um mark would know the excitatory no
it's not a GQ the uh it is an excitatory
neuronal transmission sort of normal uh
yeah so and then however if they when
they send
um uh sucralose they send a different
signal which does not trigger sort of
Downstream neuronal
activity so but if we are dealing with
other sweeteners we might have to access
different cell types that would have
receptors for those sweeteners
hi thank you U you mentioned that um um
the re uh the change in diet had impact
for Parkinson disease um but
um do I'm not sure is there um other
neurological conditions like uh um
Alzheimer's or
schizophrenia it might be associated
with that
too so uh I would like to first um
clarify that it's there is no dietary
link with
Parkinson's um so at least no
well um well-known link so what the link
that we do know is if we look at a
diagnosed Parkinson's patients who is
symptomatic and then if we'll go back in
the medical history by 20 years or some
number of decades we will see that they
had complete ains with their primary
practitioners about their GI function
most commonly constipation what we also
know is that if we take postmortem
tissues from Parkinson's patients they
have Aggregates of a protein called
Alphas nucleon in their gut which also
happens to the be whole Mark of
Parkinson's in the brain
so which together led to this somewhat
controversial hypothesis called bra
hypothesis Post in
2003 where uh he posited that
environmental factors might be entering
the body and triggering precipitation of
alpha nucleon in the GI tract which then
takes the neuronal route to propagate
back from the gut through the neuron
neuronal connections into the brain
where then it then triggers
precipitation of this protein in
substantial where dopamine neurons
end up dying and that's the kind of
parkinsonian
diagnosis however this hypothesis right
now is merely a hypothesis and this is
something that uh was very difficult to
test now we do have the tools to be able
to test this because we can interface
with gut and brain and we're very
interested in this but we should not
treat it as correct as far as we are
concerned those are
coincidental thank you
okay thank you very much Molina for this
super interesting talk
[Applause]