Well, it looks like everybody's
assembled. This is really, really good
timing. Um, we have a great afternoon
session today, a whole series of
terrific talks I'm looking forward to.
And I have the pleasure to um chair our
this session to on regulatory landscapes
and gene controls. I'm Brad Bernstein of
Broad Epigenomics and Dana Farber. Uh
our fe first speaker will be Esper
Madson who's associate professor of
computational biology at University of
Southern Denmark and a member of the NNF
center our NNF center for genomic
medicine of disease. Uh his title is
learning disentangled representations of
single nucleus epiggenomes for variant
interpretation.
Um and then we'll have uh Jesse Enrace
will be talking about uh mapping the
wiring of uh variance to genes and
functions. So, Yesper, you're up.
[Applause]
See,
okay. Thanks uh for the introduction and
uh thanks for the opportunity to talk
here at the at this uh amazing
conference or symposium. What I'll be
talking about today is is methods that
we're developing for entangled
representations
and then I will uh give a vignette of
how we can use that for variant
interpretation. So we've heard a few
talks now talking about QTLs and just
brought one uh broad slide me I should
mention that what I'll be talking about
is not yet published but we hope to to
have it out within a couple of weeks. So
if you feel that uh it's interesting to
you, please have a have a look uh on
bioarchchive in the coming weeks. Um so
how can we interpret G-W was variants?
Um we've heard a few times about uh
QTLs. Uh and there are many different
types. Uh generally we can say that
molecular QTLs are are variants
associated to molecular outcomes. And
sort of where the field has started is
with the EQTLs because if a G-W was lowi
is also an EQL we have a tractable
hypothesis for its function. What has
turned out and was also shown before the
before launch is that EQTLs and and G-W
was hits are different. Um the EQTLs are
mostly in in promoter based uh regions
whereas the G-W was hits are in both
promoters and enhancers. This has been
shown uh here but also by others uh
where the EQLs here are in orange and
they enrich more in promoters. I
included this slide because it also
shows other types of QTLs. The chromatin
accessibility QTLs and histone
acetilation QTLs and as was also
mentioned in the talk before the the
break these seems to be more enriched
for GW was loa and they also have a
distribution that is more similar to to
GW was being enriched in both enhancers
and promoters.
Another interesting uh recent
development in this field is the
response element or response uh QTLs.
I've just shown one uh figure here or
not one figure but from one recent
bioarchchive paper where they have about
50 individuals treated IPSC cells with
different compounds and then mapped
response and non-response EQTLs and they
find that the uh response EQTLs
are more enriched than in the distal
enhancer like sequences compared to the
non-response EQLs and they are the
response QTLs are also more enriched in
GW was uh uh associations.
So we thought uh that what we would like
to do is that we would like to then
combine these two approaches. We would
like to uh see if we can find response
CAQLs
uh and try to associate those with
disease and the disease we went for was
type 2 diabetes. It's a disease that we
study a lot in my group and we went for
eyelets. So the question um I will try
to to talk to you about today is whether
or not we can map type two uh diabetes
response here at QTLs in eyelets using
single nucleus attacking data sets. And
when we undertook this problem we almost
immediately stumbled into another
problem
here I'm showing you the prevalence of
different weight categories among
diabetics and uh the general population.
This is from 2020 data from the US. And
what you can see is that the diabetics
as we all know they are more often um
obese. So this poses a problem which in
statistics is called colinearity.
Essentially when you have a one coariant
you're also likely to have the other QTL
mapping is based on regression. So since
we have uh colinearity in our regression
model, we actually get unstable uh
regression coefficients or betas uh
which is a major problem. This is not
only the case for like population scale
data, but it's also a a problem in real
data. So we looked into various signal
nucleus attack sequencing atlases. So
for example, if we look in the human
lung cell atlas, we see perhaps not
surprisingly that there's colinearity
between smoking and cause of death. and
also smoking and sex. Uh and in the
human retina cell atlas we also have
multicoline uh between here gender and
age uh which is perhaps less
biologically motiv motivated. So what we
really wanted to do is we wanted to
design a method that can handle this
multicolone linearity in single cell
attacking data sets. There are already
regression based methods to do this like
lasso regression. But since we also
wanted to look at response QTLs uh
CAQTLS, we we wanted to do something
different because we can't treat an
individual with type two diabetes like
we treat with ethanol. So we have to do
something different in order for us to
actually map that response.
So Andreas a postto in my group
undertook this challenge and developed a
deep uh learning framework that we call
deep dive.
Deep dive is a um has two networks that
work in conjunction to reconstruct a
chromatin accessibility. It has a known
network uh that takes um
uh see if I can go back. It has a known
network that takes a known coariants
that's disease age BMI so on cell type
and it creates an embedding of those a
latent space which is decoded and we
train this latent space in in such a way
that we disentangle the coariants using
adversarial learning and then we have a
another network is the unknown network
which is essentially a standard
variational out code that learns the uh
remaining latent variation and we train
this network in such a way that we
maximize the information that is learned
by the known network and then let the
let the unknown network handle the
residual variation.
This architecture uh unlocks a series of
downstream applications and today I'll
just be talking about two of them which
is disentanglement and counterfactual
prediction because we need to
disentangle um the the colinear varial
uh the collinear coariantss and we need
to do counterfactuals in order to do
type 2 diabetes response CAQLs.
So in order to demonstrate that this
works, I will first try to convince you
that the architecture overall can
actually reconstruct uh chromatin
accessibility. So we looked at a data
set here from the human liver. This is
just the raw data showing you marker uh
peaks uh and then we trained a a deep
dive model and we reconstruct the
epigenomes and see a really nice and
strong correlation between the MAGA
peaks. So we can reconstruct uh cell
type specific uh epigenomes. This is on
the pseudoborg level. We can also show
on the single cell level that our
reconstructions are closer to truth than
than by random using the yension
divergence which is more similar as we
go to a lower level. So with that in
hand the next question is then if this
framework can also disentangle colinear
coariantss. So to attack that problem we
initially started by simulation. So we
simulate data which has a known
colinearity. So we can essentially we
created a simulation framework where we
can control the uh entanglement between
coariantss. So we simulate data with two
coariantss given a specific um level of
entanglement. Here is shown an example
where we have two coariantss and you can
appreciate that there's a higher density
of points here and here than there is
here and here. So if you look at
coariant 2, if you are blue here and you
have a small A, then you're also more
likely to have a capital A in coariant
one. So these two coariantss are
entangled with each other.
The good thing about this is that we
know which uh peaks are differentially
accessible along this axis and also
which peaks are differentially
accessible along this axis because we
simulated it. So in order to evaluate if
colinearity is a problem in single
nucleus attack sequencing data, we took
the uh peaks that we simulated uh to be
different along this axis and then we
ask if they're different along this axis
as well. And the results look like this.
So here you I'm showing you the ground
truth in coariant 2 and the observed
change in coariant one and if there's no
entanglement no problem with
entanglement we'll have a vertical line
but what you can appreciate is that the
signal from coariant 2 bleeds into
coariant one
okay so in order to evaluate if our
model can correct for this we trained a
deep dive model and then we performed
differential accessibility using that
model and we also did it just using
standard test the vil coxen ranks up
And what we can see is that at 5% error
rate, our model can capture 91% of the
the differentially accessible uh peaks.
Uh whereas the will cox rank from test
can only capture 34%.
Another way of visualizing this is
through vin diagrams. So this is the
simulated ground truth where we have
peaks that are specific to coariate one
and two and some that are shared. If we
do a a will cox ransom test, we get a
result that looks like this. Essentially
all of the peaks are um differentially
accessible across both coariantss even
though they weren't simulated to be.
It's simply that the signal is bleeding
through. And if we look at deep dive, we
can see that we can to a very large
extent correct this issue.
Since we're simulating data, we can not
only we can simulate across all levels
of entanglement, not only one. So if we
do that we can see that this bleeding
effect is dependent on the magnitude of
of entanglement here quantified by
Kramer V. And if we then compare our
model deep dive on the Y-axis compared
to the observed difference we can see
that across the spectrum of
entanglements
we can uh have we can improve the the
recall of differentially accessible
peaks.
We can also see that if there's perfect
entanglement, neither of the models
work. It's just a random guess because
the two coariantss are identical. So the
model doesn't have a chance to separate
them. And if there's no entanglement,
they are perfectly separated. And there
the standardized test is working well.
This was simulated data. We also wanted
to show this in real data. So we took
this data set from the Sander lab which
uh where they did single nucleus uh
miomics on eyelets from donors with
non-diabetic, pre-diabetic or type two
diabetics and they have also clinical
data available such as disease, BMI,
age, gender and so on. We took that data
set and then just looking at one peak
here you can appreciate this peak here.
There's no difference between the two
sexes. Essentially females and males
have the same accessessibility but there
is a difference between the
non-diabetics and the type two
diabetics. Then in order to evaluate if
our method works in real data we did a
non-random subsampling that essentially
creates entanglement by by removing
cells from specific groups. And now we
can see that we can purposely entangle
this data set uh to have the effect from
the disease bleed over into the sex uh
variable. Then we run deep dive and we
on this and compare it to the ground
truth and we can see again across all
levels of entanglement that we can
create using this method that deep dive
is outperforming standardized
statistical testing.
I also told you in the beginning that
there's entanglement between BMI and
type two diabetes. So we also wanted to
try that with this data set since we
have eyelets. So what we did is that we
use deep dive to uh to identify peaks
that are differentially accessible along
the BMI axis and peaks that are
differentially accessible along the
disease axis. These although it doesn't
look like it there's quite a lot of
overplotting here. These two sets are
actually largely orthogonal. There's a
jakard index of about 0.1. So
essentially peaks that are accessible in
one is not really often accessible in
the other set.
So this just means that our method is
finding orthogonal peak sets. It doesn't
actually mean that the peaks that we
call being associated to BMI in eyelets
uh is truly associated to that uh
biological process. So in order to get a
handle on that we use stratified LD
score regression using BMI G-W wases and
also uh type 2 diabetes G-W wases. And
what we can see is the peaks that we
associate to the BMI axis are strongly
enriched also for G-W was associations
with BMI whereas uh the peaks that are
associated to type 2 diabetes in our
model is also enriched for type two
diabetes G-W was associations. As a
control we used handedness which is
depleted in in both uh in both groups of
peaks. So we are quite uh confident that
we are at least partly disentangling
these coariantss and and finding uh
peaks that are specifically associated
with uh coariantss.
So since we can do that we can also do
what we call counterfactual prediction
because the way we have structured our
method is that uh the covariants are
additive in latent space. So what that
means is that when we ask deep dive to
produce a reconstruction of a cell type
A in a batch X, what it actually does is
that it takes the vector in the latent
space for batch X and it add cell type A
and this sum of those two is passed
through the decoder. So that means we
can also decode without batch X. We can
just not add it omit it. That's one way.
We can also if we for example don't
observe cell type A in batch X but
observe it in other batches we can still
add it to batch X. So we can also do
prediction of unseen coariantss or
unseen combination of coariantss.
So in order to evaluate how well our
method works in these spaces we
initially just did a batch free uh
prediction of epigenomes that is similar
to a batch integration which is
typically done in this field. We used a
standardized pipeline for evaluating
called SEIB from the TIC uh group. And
we compared our method to existing
methods in the field. SEIB produces two
uh primary outcomes. It has a bio
conservation score and a batch
integration um score. There wasn't
really a difference between bio
conservation between all four methods,
but we could clearly see a difference in
batch integration where our method
performs on par with standard uh with
with state-of-the-art in this field. We
are performing a little bit less which
is likely because our method is
constrained to be additive in the in the
linear space in the laten space whereas
this method is not. The other task we
attempted was to do a prediction of
onseene combinations. So what we did is
that we simulated a data set where there
was three batches and three cell types.
Then we removed the cell type A from
batch X and then we evaluate how well we
can actually recapitulate um that
epiggenome even though it was not seen
during model training.
And the results look like this where we
on the x-axis have the baseline and the
y-axis have the uh counterfactual
prediction of the unseen uh of the
unseen epiggenome of cell type A in
batch X. And you can clearly see that
our model is achieving a high uh
correlations between observed uh between
predicted and ground truth counts. Um so
we do believe that our model is able to
accurately also do counterfactual
prediction.
With that in hand we can now start to
actually address the original question
that I posed which was to try to find
these type 2 diabetes response CAQLs in
eyelets. So for that we returned to this
data set from the Sander group because
they didn't actually only do this uh
they didn't only do single nucleus um
multiomics and and clinical data they
also provide uh genotypes. So we can use
that to to call CAQTLS based on counts
produced or reconstructed with deep
dive. So what we did is that we took the
data, we train a deep dive model and
then we reconstruct
uh for every cell type just one cell
type at a time and we add the donor
specific variation where the residual
signal from the genotype is is located
and then although we just heard that
that pseudobuling is not the best in the
world that's what we did. So we sum
these counts. The reason that we sum
them is that these counts when we
reconstruct we use a pson target in our
model. So we have an idea that the
reconstructed counts are person
distributed. In reality they are
underdispersed. So we should be using a
generalized person as we just saw. But
we did use a pong meaning that we have a
conservative statistical model. What's
beautiful about the pong model is that
when we add two pong distributions we
get a new pong distribution. So based on
these suitables we can just use pome
regression uh to obtain effect size
estimates only correcting for the number
of cells per donor.
This uh this graph here shows you the
histogram of the effect sizes that we
obtain and we obtain in beta cells
approximately 9 and a half thousand
associations between a peak and a snip.
uh and you can appreciate here that um
the effect sizes have an approximately
uh normal distribution around uh zero
which is obtained without any
normalization or inverse
transformations. It's just modeling
counts as they are predicted by by deep
dive. If we look at an example here, so
we take one of the significant ones and
then we go to the raw data. We normalize
the raw data and we just plot it by
genotype. we can see that there is a
clear effect in the raw data as well. So
the uh cql snip associations we find in
our in our model is also recapitulated
in the raw data as it is. So now we have
done this we can not only do it in beach
cells but we can do it for every cell
type that's in the data set and we did
that and what we see is that essentially
we find only cell type specific CAQLs in
our data. That's not really surprising
because we train our model with an
adversarial loss. So we train it to
separate the variations. Again, if we
look at an example here, we can have one
example of a peak snip association which
has a very b cell specific effect. If we
go to the raw data again, we can also
see that this also holds true in the raw
data that we find a cell type specific
associate peak snip association which is
not present in any of the other cell
types.
We of course also not the only ones to
have ever mapped CAQL and eyelets. So in
order to give us further confidence that
the CAQTLS we're finding based on the
reconstructed counts is uh is uh true we
we went to another data set. This is a
quite old one from this digital group
where they did CAQLs in bulk eyelets
from 20 donors and then we just made a
naive analysis comparing our CAQLs to
their CAQLs
and what we find is that our CAQLs are
enriched above baseline. That's baseline
model here is prediction without any
cell type
and that happens specifically in the
endocrine cell types consistent with uh
the data set that we're comparing to
being whole eyelid CA caqls.
So that gives us again confidence that
we can use this framework reconstructing
counts and using pong regression on
those counts to to identify cqtls.
What's then interesting is of course to
try to compare it to uh G-W was
associations. So we took a recent uh
type two diabetes G-W was and we compare
our CAQTLS again a somewhat naive
analysis I should say this is really
fresh analysis just rolling off of of
the notebooks. So um so it's not
collocicalized it's just naive overlap.
Um but what we can see is that now
there's no really enrichment in the
baseline. So if we don't have any cell
uh cell type information in there, we
don't see any association to type 2
diabetes. But when we then add each cell
type, we canite quite clearly see and
effect. We see that especially beta
cells, but also alpha delta cells are
highly enriched uh the cqls we find in
those cell types are highly enriched for
also being type two diabetic type two
diabetes
associations.
So with that in hand, now we're quite
confident that we can cause QTLs. Now we
can get to the question from the very
beginning which was to find type 2
diabetes response uh CAQLs. So we went
further with the beta cells since they
were the most enriched for this G-W was
associations. And what we do now is that
we take our model then we reconstruct
for beta cells and Dota donor specific
variation and we do as we did before we
get pseudobox. What we then did next is
that for every donor in our data set we
virtually shift their disease label. So
we turn the di type two diabetics into
non-diabetics and we turn the
non-diabetics into type two diabetics to
give us a counterfactual epigenome. So
now we have two epiggenomes and we have
the epiggenome for from the same donor.
We have that in the predicted
non-diabetic state and in the type two
diabetic state. So it's not we're not
comparing different groups of donors but
we're comparing the same donor to
itself. And there what we can do is then
we subtract these two pong distributions
from each other that gives us a new
distribution which is called the skeleum
distribution and then we can use asmtoic
approximations of bessel functions to do
skeleum regression and identify caqls.
So if we look at an example of one of
the hits from this model it looks like
this. So we on the y- axis here we have
the delta count now and you can see
there's association between the genotype
and the delta count. The model is
predicting here that individuals with
this genotype the type 2 diabetics
should have a higher count than the
non-diabetics and vice versa in this
genotype the non-diabetics should have a
higher count than the type two
diabetics. If we don't go back to the
original the raw data we can see that
that is actually also the true uh at
least that's what we observe in the raw
data. So we can identify these uh CAQTLs
where there is a differential response
uh in the in the two disease stages uh
to the genotype.
One thing that's interesting about this
is that if we keep looking at this
example and we just ask is it also a
CAQL for the cell type? It's not. And
that's actually a general tendency that
these two ways of identifying CAQLs are
identifying different signals. So on the
x-axis here we have the all of the CAQTL
effect sizes for beta cells and here we
have all of the effect sizes for type 2
diabetes response in beta cells and
there's essentially very little overlap.
So then the really really interesting
question is of course if these or these
are more associated to type two diabetes
G-W was associations.
So what we did is that we did the same
analysis. We take the type two diabetes
G-W was and we perform enrichment
analysis and what we find is that across
all thresholds of G-W was uh uh beta
effect sizes somewhere around here is
genomewide significant and this is very
significant. we see that this uh type
two diabetes response CAQLs are much
more enriched among G was uh associated
hits. So with that I will conclude uh
that I hope I have shown that um our
model deep dive can actually uh
disentangle colinear colinear coariantss
and that once we can do that we can also
do counterfactual prediction. we can use
counterfactual prediction to identify
CAQTLS by omitting variables or eron
type analysis and that uh these type 2
diabetes response CQTLs we find in beta
cells are highly enriched among type 2
diabetes G-W was associations. So I
would like to of course thank my team
especially Andreas uh who's spearheading
the development of of C of deep dive. I
also like to thank our collaborators,
our senses and funders and you for
listening and I'm happy to take any
questions.
[Applause]
[Music]
That was a terrific talk. Is there
opportunity now to integrate this T2D
response CAQTLS with language model
sequence models? Is there is there
enough power? Are there enough of them?
Is there power that you can then
identify the motifs and upstream
pathways that are specific to the
process?
>> That's a really excellent question. We
haven't dug into it at all yet. So, we
just got these uh results. So, it's
really, as I said, something that was uh
I I made these slides on Monday, so it's
really new. Uh so, we we don't know yet.
>> All right, more questions.
>> Yes. Um thanks yes for for a super nice
talk and super nice work by Andreas. I
have a question regarding the the
correction right like the risk here is
overcorrecting because we are forcing to
find like the the the contributions of
the different coariantss but we are
missing on the shared trends and my
question is like what's the sweet spot
and how do you like basically yeah not
enforce it like not not pass from the
other end kind of of the correction.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um so what we see is that uh our
model is it disentangles but we don't
see that it it captures everything. So
there is a loss of sensitivity due to
disentanglement. Um we could also see
that there was a little bit hard to see
on the vin diagrams but actually the the
number of uh differentially associated
peaks that we find although disentangle
is not the full complement. So we do
lose power by this approach. But I do
think we also gain a lot of power
because for example in this uh response
analysis we're comparing the same
individual to itself rather than having
different groups. So we're asking if all
else all other things being the same
what is then the effect of this coariant
in isolation. Um so there's definitely a
trade-off. we lose some power and we
can't detect all of it but we also gain
power by having paired or strongly
associated measures or predictions.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks VJ. Uh ve very very nice. Um
given that you see this enrichment with
dynamic sort of accessibility peaks.
Have you thought about then subsetting
those based upon dynamics for specific
transcription factor motifs? Like if you
were to look at specific transcription
would you get more power? Could you get
more enrichment? Erh, I mean as as I
said this is really fresh resource. So
we're really open also to collaboration.
If you or others have good ideas of how
we can take this further, we're really
open to to engage in that discussion. I
think looking at the transcription
factors is is a is a really interesting
uh approach and and we should definitely
do that. There might also be like motive
breakage uh going on that we could
identify and so on, but it be
interesting to to dig into that. Yeah.
Great, fantastic talk. Thanks.
[Applause]