so my name is John W I'm the CEO and
co-founder and I I was in the CTL
program at MIT back at the turn of the
century um A lot's changed since then
and one of the things that's happened is
that um the geni side of the world is
really starting to take over and we've
seen a tremendous amount of uh activity
in the public data but inside
corporations and Enterprise data uh that
is still not really accessible to these
gen models and the capabilities there
because it's um essentially incoherent
data it doesn't have the same
characteristics of uh all the
information that's available on the
internet and when humans have applied
all the information uh into these these
data sets so what we do at uh profit
Isis is basically we focus on the
proprietary Enterprise data and because
we're focused exclusively on companies
uh and the reason that corporations
exist is to generate profit uh we are
basically creating coherent data sets
associated with profitability and what
we do in our solution is we create a
full p&l for every invoice line of every
transaction um and that allows us to
make all of the Enterprise data coherent
through the language or through the lens
of profitability so we work with large
multinational companies we're working
with a 10 billion doll retailer and
we're producing at this point uh 1.2
billion profit and loss statements that
allows data sets now to be quite robust
and can can be used to to support uh
many large language models and generate
uh more insights out of corporate
data we have a lot of history doing this
we've uh figured out how to uh basically
uh look at the corporate data through
the lens of 26 data groups uh we've
worked with most major types of systems
and what we do is uh we're based on the
Google Cloud we ingest all that data we
do a massive transformation those of you
whove been around for a while this is
activity based costing now in the fourth
or fifth generation it's fully Dynamic
once we transform that data then we do a
series of segmentations one of the
things that we've seen is that
corporations running on one to five pnls
uh can't see what's really happening
inside the company because uh the the
traditional p&l uh is one large average
and what we know is that underneath the
average um there's nothing normal about
corporations uh they're actually running
the 8020 Rule and once you see the
underlying data you have the ability to
make much better decisions and our
software allows companies to do
that so we basically will uh augment
these data sets so we're taking Erp data
Freight data hris data um all all the
data available uh we're transforming it
into these uh profit and loss statements
at the lowest level we're then
segmenting and adding value to those
data sets and then using that as the
basic for agentic um uh recommendations
on the overall profitability inside the
corporation okay um just continue so an
example for A10 billion retailer uh
we've taken 13 data groups and we've
helped them improve dramatically their
promotional spending uh We've helped
them improve their their um store labor
planning and we've also allowed them to
do much better uh work with our product
supplier mix uh with a$1 billion do
Global distributor uh again we've taken
multiple Erp systems brought it all
together uh We've helped them
dramatically with their private label
pricing which they couldn't see before
we actually showed them the
profitability all the way back to
manufacturing uh We've helped them
identify uh very clear opportunities to
change customer contracts and again
we've shown them the visibility of their
uh product profitability and improved
their mix and finally on the
manufacturing side uh which is more
complex across multiple uh continents
and multiple Erp systems we've helped
them to improve their pricing to reflect
the actual cost of across all of their
production facilities again that's led
directly to new customer contract
negotiations and we've dramatically
improved their sales and operation
planning based on true
profitability um we basically work with
different parts of the company the
office of the CFO uh store operations
management uh pricing teams and
marketing teams as well as supply chain
teams so each one of these is using this
fundamental new data set and providing
uh strong
recommendations uh we're looking for
your help to find a new uh Partners
ideally 200 to20 billion companies and
uh we generally like to talk to the
senior people in the company because
this really does change how companies
operate using financial information to
make better decisions thank you thank
you so much John um and again good to
see see that um you're working globally
with a lot of companies so um does
profit aisle have the data
infrastructure and the data availability
to support AI implementation and what
are some of the foundational elements
for AI um so the found what we do
because of um the transformation that we
do to the profit and loss statement
which is universal um we actually our
output is a is a strong Foundation it's
literally the language of profit and
it's absorbable by large language models
and so uh our transformation uh we can
deploy in roughly eight weeks for a
multi-billion dollar company and so
we're doing a massive data
transformation that is now foundational
for future AI
projects okay and continue with that um
how the current AI initiatives align
with your company's goals as well um a
lot of the AI work that's going on right
now has been focused primarily on using
essentially this public data uh we have
seen and we've spent a lot of time
talking with Google their big challenge
right now is getting Enterprise data to
actually coordinate or connect uh with
some of these other capabilities and the
transformation work that we do for large
companies is really uh uh speeds up that
process and it makes and it achieves it
much more um with a lot less cost than
if they can do it without our solution
okay John thank you