Hello everyone listening and watching.
Uh in this short tutorial I'm going to
give you a demo of how to use the
interactive mapping module of the broad
institute genomics to proteins portal
which is a discovery platform to link
genetic screening outputs to protein
sequence and structure. So this
particular module has two subm modules
as you will see after we dive in and
this tutorial will focus on the first
module and then we will have another
tutorial for the next one. Uh so let's
uh click on the analyze your data button
which is the beginning of the workflow.
So when you click there uh the portal
will prompt you to sign in using your
Gmail address.
So let's do that
and then it should show you a disclaimer
and uh as I continue then we can see
that there are two subm modules within
this uh analyze your own data or what we
say as interactive mapping module. So we
will focus on this particular subm
module here which is uh how does the
workflow look like if we start with the
human gene or protein identifier.
Clicking here the workflow um will
launch which involves this four step. Uh
in step one you will select a gene or a
protein identifier. From here uh you can
search up a gene name of interest or
uniro identifier. Here I'm going to
click on on this example gene name
CDKL5.
Then you will see the faster sequence
for uh the protein. uh we will proceed
and then uh we are now at step two which
is the structure um selection uh part of
the workflow. Here you can select an
experimental structure from protein data
bank or uh alpha fold predicted
structure by both alpha fold 2 and
three. So in this page uh when you click
on a structure you will also uh uh be
able to preview the structure. So in
alpha fold if I now click here then we
have a preview of alpha fold structure.
I'll go back to protein datab bank.
We'll select back the top structure and
we'll hit this next annotation step of
the workflow.
in this uh step. Now um if you uh come
to the annotation view and click on this
link, you will see the allowable formats
in which you can input mutations
or scores that can be numerical values
and features as discrete or categorical
values. And you can map these
annotations to protein sequence and
structure side by side. So let's close
this and uh load some sample annotations
given here such as mutation and scores
and then features. One important note
here is this particular column. The
first one residue position is a
mandatory column because we need this
column to map the annotation on sequence
and structure. And we can also combine
all three types of data that you can map
um and paste the combined annotation um
in this form. So let's download a
template uh which involves
a combined set of annotation.
From here I'm going to copy
these annotations uh and paste here.
But note that you can also upload that
file as CSV or Excel format and can do
the same uh execute the same workflow.
So here now if I submit then it will
give you this preview of the annotation
table. Um now each cell of this table is
editable. For example, let's try editing
this um residue position to 13 here. And
now if you hit submit annotation it is
going to show an error that you cannot
upload a mutation at the position 13 for
the residue position 12. So we will need
to correct it and we can also change
this synonymous mutation lysin to lysine
to um lysine to arginine for example. Um
another important note here is this uh
category of annotation uh is editable
from the column header. For example, if
I now edit this category of data into
mutation, then the portal will detect
that this is an erroriness annotation
because mutations cannot be uh
quantitative values. So I will change it
back to score as it should be and we'll
submit the annotation. But before going
there go um you can also filter your
columns. For example, if you just upload
your data file with hundreds of columns
and not all of them are necessary then
you can uh check off these boxes and you
can filter the columns and also we show
a note that more than 30 columns may
lead to performance issues.
So we'll submit the annotation and then
now the annotations are mapped on the
sequence space and also on the structure
space. Now from here there are um couple
of options. For example, you can edit
the color of the annotations here. The
mutations are mapped in red but I can
click on this color wheel and change it
to a different color blue. And you can
change these colors for all the
annotations. We can also click on this
view additional annotations button which
brings in mutation data variant data
from Nomad cleanvar AGMD. So uh three
different variant databases and also it
brings in a suite of protein sequence
and structural features that we have
available in the genomics to proteins
portal but in the resource module. So
for example um for this particular gene
if you want to map also the available
clinical uh pathogenic missense
mutations in the context of your own
annotation you can select these
mutations from here and can map those
mutations. So now the orange spheres are
the clinical mutations and these blue
mutations are the mutations that you
have uploaded. Now from here you uh have
multiple options to um share the data
and also share this workflow. So for the
uh screen uh shot of uh the sequence
viewer you can click in this button and
you can also download all these data by
clicking here. You can download this
mapping on the structure by clicking on
the pimal script button. But here I'm
going to focus on how you can share this
entire workflow uh to a collaborator for
example and then the collaborators will
be able to load this entire session in
their computer.
So, let's uh hit share. And from here,
I'm going to
share this um with um one of my other
personal email address
and I'll add it um and then I'll create
the link.
So now this link um will be accessible
only to this uh email address. So I'll
copy this and let's try to load it uh
separately.
Um so now you are given a prompt that
you need to sign in using the authorized
email address. So I will do that. Um and
then we'll need to copy that link one
more time and then this same uh session
that we created um is now available to
the collaborator. remember that this
session needs to be accessed uh within 7
days and then um we clear up the logs.
Um so uh this was about the workflow uh
for executing the interactive mapping of
genomics to proteins portal starting
with the gene protein identifier. So
stay tuned for the next tutorial where
uh I'm going to show a demo for the next
module which is start with your own
protein structure.