indeed uh it is tremendous uh to uh have
a chance to uh welcome the next set of
speakers uh led by Joyce swo uh who
manages the stard dot Nano program of
MIT Neno we have asked a set of
luminaries people we tremendously admire
to join us and Joyce please come on the
stage and tell us more about the next
thing we would like to tell you about
and that is how to transition deep Tech
from Academia to
Industry thank
you so the session today will talk about
how we transition an idea into
commercialization um strictly focusing
on deep Tech
investment into hardtech is only a few
percent by VCS and the journey for
hearttech is Frau with many
challenges an idea needs more time and
resources to reach commercialization to
become a product than one can realize at
the time of
inception ideas can be incubated within
a large company but most commonly they
are through a startup um and there are
many points at which a startup can fail
in its journey to to
commercialization first one needs to
find people who share your vision and
bring it to the Prototype or proof of
concept stage this is the first valley
of death
um the next stage to get to from
prototype to the advanced scaleup or de
Advanced element or scale up um is
another Valley of Death where you need
to find customers who see your prototype
your product um that can become a
product
that in this area you also need to find
the right market and the right solution
for that
customer then in the next Valley of
Death you have to find a partner or
investor who will Bank your idea to
commercialization these three valleys of
death have attrition at each stage and
really a successful Journey takes at
least 10 years or100
million so how can we help startups in
their Journey with our tool set at mit.
Nano start. Nano is an accelerator
program to help fill in these gaps
startups Are Climbing this mountain of
hardtech and we can minimize their
needed funds by first giving them access
to existing shared facilities like mit.
Nano and actually giving them a discount
for the use of those
tools this allows them at that first
stage um from IDE prototype where they
don't need to build their own lab and
buy and have investment Capital to do
that and they can use our tools to build
that
prototype also in the next stage they
can continue using our tools for
development to reach those first
customers we have several startups in
our cohorts one is Citra um you'll see
in the startup exchange um they didn't
need to build their own lab um and their
seed round was actually more like a
series A because they were able to build
their prototypes at mit. Nano with less
capital and another example of a startup
is wicked smart they didn't when they
realized we have an immersion lab which
has a motion capture they realized they
didn't need to raise additional investor
funds to build their own motion capture
lab because they have access to the
immersion
lab so this is actually our cohort for
this year of in the start. Nano
accelerator program we have 13 startups
and Counting um and the acceptance rate
was about
42% uh you can see they actually
represent a large and diverse market
segments here a quarter of them are in
biotech and a quarter in climate Tech
and energy and a quarter in materials
this broad area allows that us to tap
into many areas of in the startup uh uh
startup
ecosystem and we can support them with
our diverse tool set at mit. Nano and we
actually even have a few software
companies because we have the immersion
lab so this is a glimpse of all the
startups that have been in start at Nano
since an Inception in
2021 um and some of them are here today
at the startup exchange uh startup sorry
startup showcase um and let's hear now
from our our upcoming speakers um about
their perspectives of how we bring
technology to
Market so first we have Marina AIS um
and she'll talk to us about her industry
perspective of transitioning academic
discoveries to
commercialization she is the board chair
of Latronics Technologies the world
leader in magnetically levitated
bearingless motor technology and the
president of the helenic Innovation
Network which serves as a bridge for
Tech startups expanding from Greece to
the US she's a board member of Berkeley
College of Music Alba business school
and Athens College and on the MIT
Corporation visiting committee for the
Department of mechanical engineer ing
she was the founding CEO of Z
Corporation an early leader in 3D
printing out of MIT and has served on
numerous corporate
boards after meor we'll hear from Mark
hman he is the director of the Northeast
microelectronics Coalition and he'll
give us the regional and chips act
perspective as we work across the re the
local
regions uh nmc is the network of over
200 organizations including commercial
and defense companies leading at
academic institutions ferally funded R&D
centers and startups concentrated in
eight northeast states it was
established in 2023 and funded through
the chips and science Act nmc is one of
eight Regional Department of Defense
microelectronics Commons hubs acting on
a shared mission to expand the nation's
Global Leadership in microelectronics
and accelerate domestic semiconductor
prototyping Mark is over two decades of
experience in commercialization and
Advanced Technologies having held
leadership positions in public sem
compan and Venture back startups in
Boston and Silicon
Valley and lastly we'll hear from
Professor Dame Fiona Murray um so I have
her her bio here um she's the associate
dean of innovation at MIT and professor
of Professor of Entrepreneurship she
also is the vice chair of the NATO
Innovation fund which is a VC fund with
contrib contributors from 24 NATO
countries investing in critical
Tech so now we'll here from
Marina talking about translating deep
Tech from to
Industry thank you hi uh great to be
here I'm going to talk to you about
translating deep Tech from Academia to
Industry and uh I'm going to make it
sound really simple like there are these
steps and you just follow them and then
you're good to go but it's not really
like that and it's not that clean it's
all kind of messy so uh I kind of broke
it down into these steps and I'll just
go through them really quickly so of
course it all starts with research um
this is where there's an Innovative
scientific discovery um and the
researcher might have a general vague
idea of how it might be applied but
usually the application is somewhat
vague and that's fine um the important
thing is that there's something that
differentiates this technology from what
has come before the next is to patent it
and this is extremely important and I
can tell you from personal experience at
zc Corp um we had core patents for MIT
that actually blocked competition until
those patents expired um and that was
competition from HP so those are really
really important it protects you for 20
years from the date of filing and you
need those 20 years because it takes a
really long time to develop new
technology um but intellectual property
also includes Trade Secrets um and
knowhow and so uh it's important to
recognize those and protect those as
well the next step is publication and
generally professors and researchers are
incentivized to publish and this is
considered sort of an indicator of
innovation both for the individual as
well as for the institution um and
that's great to publish but just make
sure you get the order of events correct
you want to patent first and publish
later after you publish it's too late to
patent the next is the proof of
principle and I'm going to show you what
our 3D printer looked like when it was
at MIT it was not a pretty site um but
but the point was they had taken out the
magic they had proven that the
technology could work and that's what
you want to see um you want to get it to
a stage that there's no more magic
required and that straightforward
engineering can kind of clean things up
and make a reliable uh solution the next
is startup formation and it's really
important um to think about the
motivation for your startup why do you
want to do this um often times with a
researcher it's a passion for a
particular ular technology um it could
be to solve a specific problem or in my
case it was a desire to kind of solve
any problem and just kind of make the
world a little bit better um also
Independence is a big factor this was
one for me as well like wanting to be My
Own Boss um the sense of teamwork and
community that comes with a startup or
making money and oftentimes it's all of
these or some combination of these
motivations but the important thing is
to understand your short-term and your
long-term goals are you just trying to
get it to a stage where you can sell it
or to scale it up to IPO um and make
sure that your goals are aligned with
those of your
investors one big mistake that I see
often is that the researcher the
professor wants to continue their day
job during the week and then do their
startup on the weekends and that doesn't
really work entrepreneurship is not a
part-time job researchers need
entrepreneurs entrepreneurs need
researchers it's a symbiotic
relationship of beautiful codependence
and it's really important to respect
what the other person brings to the
table the next step is understanding the
market so typically deep Tech research
um is a solution looking for a problem
and so to figure out what that problem
is requires customer conversations
charting the competitive landscape doing
research at trade shows reading articles
and reading annual
reports one of the mistakes I often see
is the lab is a comfort zone for a
researcher right and so it's always
easier to do one more experiment than to
get out there and find customers who you
don't know how to find them and you have
to have this awkward conversation
because you don't really know what
you're talking about yet um but it's
really really important to do that you
need to understand is the problem
painful enough how big is the market and
not to hold everything tight you can
retain your proprietary information but
still share enough information about
what you want to do in order to get
useful information from the market um
and really at the end it's only a real
product when someone will pay for it so
you need to understand um who's going to
pay for it and if they're
willing um obviously when you're doing
uh an Innovative startup you need to be
doing something different so you need to
learn what's out there and do something
different you can't the state of the-art
is not your end point that's your
starting point so yes you need to get
your technology there but then you need
to advance it beyond that and luckily
you have one big Advantage which is your
ability to take a market disruption or
create a market disruption and pivot um
and when you look at a large incumbent
they have everything right they have
customers they have money they have
experience they have distribution they
have manufacturing they've got it all
the one thing they don't have is the
ability to change course quickly and so
you've got to use that to your advantage
and typically that comes when there is a
market disruption it could be
regulations new regulations old
regulations that are going away um new
technologies that enable some other
technology things like that and so
that's what you always want to be
looking for but you're always making
decisions in the dark and so um and
that's good you need to move forward but
as soon as you get new information you
need to um remake those decisions and
that's why pivoting is generally part of
your daily
process the next is building a team in
culture and I'm very proud of what we
built at Z Corporation we had a very
diverse team of people with different
interests talents experience and we had
a very argumentative culture in a very
positive non-toxic way and I think this
allowed us to um make the best
decisions then you come up with your
plan product specifications value
proposition who's your customer how are
you going to find them um and the
biggest uh challenge I think of all is
finding your your product Market fit as
I said you're a solution looking for a
problem being different isn't good
enough you need to be substantially
better at something that the customer
cares about but the good news is you
don't need to be better at everything so
for example at zc Corp our parts were
not they did not have high surface
finish or high strength but our 3D
printer was 10 times faster than any
other technology and that was something
the customer cared
about then you get to fundraising um so
typically this starts with friends and
family then you go to Angels typically
Equity crowdfunding isn't so good for
this sort of thing government grants are
a great source of funding for deep Tech
and then obviously venture capital and
at a later stage not just Equity but
Venture debt um and don't forget
strategic investors these can be your
customers your suppliers anybody who has
a vested interest in your success and
that can be in the form of an equity
investment an R&D contract or what we
did is we asked for very High customer
deposits at the time of the purchase
order one big mistake I see is
entrepreneurs underestimating the
fundraising process it's a big job it
takes dedication time research and
energy you're faced with rejection and
failure every step of the way um but
it's important to take something away
from every meeting and learn from each
one was it the pitch or was it the
business get some strategic takeaways
don't waste those rejections
then you get to the minimum viable
product and this is something that
you're willing to show the customer and
you can see that our beta machine made a
lot of strides since that first proof of
principle at MIT and this was something
that we uh took to our customers so we
could get feedback from the market and
understand how we needed to iterate on
the design to get something that they
really
wanted one mistake I see is
entrepreneurs seeking Perfection but if
you wait until your product is perfect
you will have missed the market market
so you just need to get something into
the customer hands so that you can start
to get feedback because what you think
might be close but it's probably not
exactly right and so you need to get
that feedback and hear from them finally
you get to sales that's the exciting
part that's when you get money from the
customers um and it kind of validates
your business um but commercializing
deep Tech Hardware has some specific
challenges that make it much more
difficult than your software comrades um
you have manufacturing issues cost of
good sold that has needs to be
controlled quality control issues we had
to add six months to our development
cycle which was already two years long
um servicing equipment out in the field
uh which can be a huge challenge if
you've sold machines all over the world
generally the time and the cost that you
think is it's actually going to be about
three to four to maybe 10 times more
time and cost than what you originally
anticipate and because of this the
investors know this and so this makes
fundraising that much more
difficult when you're in the mck uh the
software uh the startup fog uh you have
too many decisions to make too many
directions to go in not enough
information and conflicting opinions so
your North Star always needs to be going
back to your core technology whatever it
is that you've patented and protected
how do does that create product
differentiation and now use that to help
guide you toward who is your customer
what Market are you going after um how
should you develop the product and where
should you really uh prioritize your
limited resources of time and
money um finally factors for Success um
are different uh defensible product
differentiation a strong diverse team a
healthy culture and lots and lots of of
customer interactions thank
you hello everybody uh Mark halfman
director of the Northeast
microelectronics Coalition I do want to
quickly thank Joyce for the invitation
uh I thought about this on the drive in
this morning Joyce and I first worked
together 16 years ago now at a early
stage mems based display startup so
thrilled to be able to join her today as
part of her panel um as we get started I
thought Vladimir had an awesome quote I
actually wrote it down um from his
kickoff this morning he had asked the
question how do Grand ideas reach the
world and so what I'd like to do you
know in the next nine and a half minutes
now is take you through a regional point
of view on that so from the Northeast
micro Electronics Coalition how do we
view that challenge and what are we
trying to achieve in an effort to help
startups innovators alleviate at least
aspects of that challenge
so uh The nmc Hub is a division of the
mass Tech collaborative uh for those
that might not know the mtech
collaborative has been around for 40
plus years now really focused on
strengthening the competitiveness of the
tech and Innovation economies in
Massachusetts uh we are one of now six
divisions within Mast te uh Innovation
Institute really focused on early stage
deep te clustering uh autonomous
robotics Quantum Computing uh other
initiatives of of that type of of size
and scope center for advanced
manufacturing really focused on how do
they bring industry 4.0 uh into
manufacturing across the board within
Massachusetts Broadband ealth cyber um
we are a bit unique within that
infrastructure and that although the
other five divisions are
largely Massachusetts funded
Massachusetts focused uh from a regional
perspective we the Northeast micro
Electronics Coalition are really focused
across the Northeast which for us is New
Jersey New York State uh and then
everything that we think of is the the
greater portion of New
England uh also from a funding
perspective we are funded through the US
chips and science act uh as I'm sure
everybody's aware us chips act $ 54
billion we've all seen the large
announcements
uh largely from the Department of
Commerce funding tsmc Intel Micron Etc
what you might be less aware of is
within that 54 billion is a $2 billion
allocation being administered through
the Department of Defense specifically
for the microelectronics commons really
addressing uh that second Valley of
Death that Joyce referred to earlier in
her presentation so how do we really
help uh Innovative chips and chips
adjacent Technologies make it from
Innovative concept to something that's a
little more on its way to commercial
Readiness specifically from a
microelectronics Commons perspective
really focused around six key technology
areas that you see in the bubbles there
but really spreading a wide range of
applications from ew to secure Computing
on the edge AI Hardware Quantum 5G 6G
Technologies commercial leap ahead um
really could be called miscellaneous so
the catch all for everything else but to
put a better nomenclature around it
commercial leap ahead Technologies um
but again I think the key takeaway here
is is really how do we help bridge uh
that labto faab Gap if you will how do
we help bridge that value of death and
from a Northeast micro Electronics
Regional perspective for us that's
really about how do we help Innovative
companies uh Innovative Concepts really
regardless of where they're coming from
so whether they are coming out of
University Research whether it's an
early stage startup trying to get its
footing or even compelling ideas coming
out of large multinational corporations
that are similarly trying to figure out
uh how they take next steps um for us
that really means how do we help those
early Concepts whether it's at the white
paper stage whether it's a crude proof
of concept you know built out over a lab
bench something only an engineer could
love um I love Marina's photo earlier um
from her early proof of concept which is
exactly what we think of there um in
terms of you know an early stage proof
of concept but from a Northeast micro
Electronics Coalition perspective how do
we
help accelerate amplify um you know
continue to to move those types of
Technologies forward in what can be a
very different uh very difficult uh
investment environment as as Marina
spoke to as
well so from an nmc perspective
specifically uh we do see tremendous
power in the Northeast region I think
it's important to note that we the
Northeast microelectronics Coalition
don't staff our own team and design
Engineers we don't run a test and
characterization lab we don't have a way
for Fab so our strength really does come
from the capabilities the Capac ities in
the commitments of our membership and
you can see that referenced here um I
apologize I should also note uh we are
relatively new organization uh we just
celebrated our one-year anniversary last
month so I think this is tremendous
progress for now 13 months in to really
a brand new seat of an idea going from
initial concept to now 220 plus
organizations as members 780 plus
individuals within those organiz ations
as contributors you can see on the upper
right hand side it's roughly comprised
of 50% Massachusetts
organizations another 40% throughout the
Northeast and then the remaining 10%
really around the the rest of the US um
from North Carolina to California and
everywhere in between uh I think the
membership by category is also important
because again when we talk about how do
we
help these early stage Concepts get to
some level of commercial Readiness I
think it's important to note that you
can see the the breadth of membership we
have from commercial and Industrial
entities to startups academic
researchers other nonprofits and the
like which is is really important as we
as we work on how from an nmc
perspective uh do we become what we like
to think of as the central point of
curated collaboration how do we help
these innovators come together how do we
help mature the Technologies help move
them from early stage lab environments
to pre-commercial Fab to commercial Fabs
um as you can see uh the core facilities
that we help work with um really in
tight collaboration with MIT Nano MIT
Lincoln laboratory and then spaning the
other organizations that you see they
are referenced and from a strength of
our Network perspective uh you can see
our first year funding operations
funding through the Department of
Defense US chips Act reference there
roughly 20 million uh the vision is
roughly that order of magnitude funding
over the 5-year Horizon of the US chips
act but you can see in terms of real
value that we're bringing to the
ecosystem we've been able to leverage
that that investment uh 40 million north
of 40 million now in private thirdparty
co-investment uh we announced beginning
of this calendar year in conjunction
with MIT Nano uh Applied Materials and
the nmc Hub coming together to be able
ble to provide uh or invest in over $40
million of new 200 mm wafer tool
infrastructure into the MIT Nano
facility 40 million in Massachusetts
state co-investment into our initiatives
80 million plus in additional
Massachusetts capital grants and again
if you look at the overall
infrastructure uh within the Northeast
micro Electronics Coalition it's
multiple billions of dollars of of
regional assets that we're working to
again leverage um and and help from a
collaboration perspective to the benefit
of startups and other early Tech
innovators looking to make that leap or
bridge that Gap from from Lab to
fabrication and in closing what I wanted
to do was just share our uh you know
let's say an initial success story in
terms of what we're able to achieve
again with an eye toward becoming That
central point of curated collaboration
and that is another aspect of the
microelectronics Commons funding in its
first year went toward $270 million of
funding allocated across 33 projects
within the eight microelectronics
Commons hubs of which nmc is one uh this
is a project that started about a year
ago or a process that started about a
year ago uh an open call for
projects through the microelectronics
commons program resulting in the 33
projects that were awarded uh just last
month uh one of the announcements was
held here locally at MIT Lincoln Labs
announcing specifically for the
Northeast micro Electronics Coalition
$38 million for the first year of
execution on six different
projects you can see the names
highlighted there very brief
descriptions um of the Technologies but
I think the two key takeaways are
although you see just one University
UMass Amherst listed as a lead all six
of these projects are
multi-organizational team so all of
these projects have University
researchers involved all of these
projects have federally funded research
R&D centers involved um other startups
providing technology so these are all
teams of anywhere from six to a dozen
plus organizations coming together to
help these to help mature these IC based
Technologies and what I'll leave you
with um is really from the last bullet
not using it to highlight our successes
versus the other seven microelectronics
Commons hubs because we're all in this
together but really to highlight uh the
demonstrated success from the point of
microelectronics Commons really the vote
of confidence from the US chips act that
the regional power within the Northeast
micro electronics are 220 plus
organization members the way they were
able to come together to propose the
topics and receive more Awards than any
of the other hubs really is a testament
to the power of the region and what we
going forward look to continue to build
on whether it's to help collaborate in
network startups looking for commercial
support whether it be University
researchers looking for the connectivity
on how they grow outside of the
University research lab environment or
whether it be large multinationals that
see a gap in their road map and rather
than trying to address it internally or
having their own Tech Scouts go scour
the Northeast to understand what's out
there coming to us and and enabling us
to help them find the right technology
researchers the right startups and get
them to Market much more quickly from
that perspective as well thank
[Applause]
you
right okay thank you very
much I am acutely aware of the time
that's why I just want to make sure Vlad
what time are we trying to um joce what
time are we trying to finish now I've
got 10 minutes but
I I feel sure that other people use more
than 10 minutes and I want to keep you
on time because I know that when you run
conferences it's quite tricky and other
people have a lot more detailed
information to give you than I think I'm
going to um but I think my job is to
really talk a little bit more generally
and try and put what I see as the
extraordinary success of MIT Nano and
the huge success that New England the
Northeast Mast Tech collaborative has
had
microelectronics perhaps into a slightly
larger perspective and the way I think
about this is that the university has to
build a system that is going to support
the kinds of amazing invention and
Innovation activities that Marina talked
about and then we really really need our
ecosystem to kind of step in and to do
its job and you might say well why don't
we just sort of let everybody fend for
themselves and I think you've seen all
the good reasons both from the
perspective of the individual
entrepreneurs and Joy's image right of
those many valleys of death I always
thought we only had one and now we seem
to have about five and that seems quite
treacherous I suspect Professor bovich
that is your fault um that we have those
and then Marina sort of brought that to
life I think in this extraordinary way
with those pictures that I think
probably feel really familiar to so many
of us you know when any of us walk into
a lab we see something that looks quite
sort of chunky and clunky and
interesting and sort of Heath Robinson
and piece together and yet at the end
something extraordinary that transforms
how our industrial processes work kind
of comes out the end and I would argue
that it's because we have ecosystems
around us that that happens but before I
get to that I want to show you this
graph um so I had a debate about this
graph with my husband this morning he's
an engineer I showed it to him at 6 in
the morning and he was unimpressed but
I'm going to try and persuade you that
this is an interesting graph what this
shows us is something that blad and I
have taught about and talked about for
many years
basically trying to ask the question how
long does it take for an idea to sort of
have some important Innovative outcome
for an idea to go from inception all the
way through to impact and I think what
you've heard um already today and what
you heard from Marina was that it often
takes up to a decade and what this is
trying to do this graph it's actually
based on enormous amount of data
millions of data points is asked this
same question the gestation how long
does it take for an idea to get from
that stage of patenting all the way
through to something sort of sensible
what this tells us is it takes anywhere
from sort of a year or two all the way
to 10 12 14 years and what you might be
able to see if you squint at it is on
the left hand side the things where this
happens quickly happen in a couple of
years those are things that these are
all patent codes are Transmissions of
digital information that means this is
software and none of us should be
surprised that software kind of gestates
gets to impact in few years it's really
efficient on the other end we've got you
know production and refining of metals
methods of steam generation
gosh mining quarrying Fusion reactors we
shouldn't be that surprised that Fusion
reactors are all the way at the other
end and those ideas take upwards of 12
15 more years to actually come to
gestation somewhere in between somewhere
around 10 years if you look into the
data you'll find things like
semiconductors right um Quantum
Computing systems and so on now in the
middle of the distribution you get odd
categories like Dentistry I'm not
entirely sure why Dentistry is sort of
right at the middle of the distribution
but it is um and what this tells us is
that it really is some things just take
time and so what we know and the way I
think about this which is really
consistent with what we heard from um
Marina is that it takes time and there's
risk associated with Innovation
particularly in deep Tech things that
are physical right sort of physical
deeply technical instantiations of our
new ideas so the way I would talk about
this is that ideas that are based on
Frontier Science and Technology they
have significant technical Market
production regulatory risks associated
with them and those risks often cause us
to have these valleys of death we went
through some of that architecture that's
mostly associated with hardware and so
you will hear people particularly in
this room I think talk about hard tech
as opposed to sort of soft
Tech because I would bundle the life
science into this the word hard doesn't
always work for me and I sort of want to
say soggy as well and so then I'm trying
to work out what word to use but I'm
thinking about things that are grounded
in life sciences Material Sciences
chemical Sciences as opposed to narrowly
computer science ones and zeros
pitchbook talks about this as
Technologies based on tangible
engineering BCG calls them Technologies
of the future not sure that gets us very
far um the word deep Tech is a word that
is reasonably widely used up the road
our friends at the engine call it tough
Tech um but you know you'll find this
word around the place and what we really
mean are as I say things that are hard
uh that require very deep Wells of
capital and time to go all the way from
idea to impact at scale so how do we try
to reduce the time and reduce the amount
of capital because if we can do that we
can then ensure that more things happen
we have more impact on the world the R&D
dollars that we spend in our
universities in our economies go further
and so what can we do to either compress
the time or reduce uh the amount of
capital that's actually required well we
get a little bit of a hint if we start
to look at maps of where Innovation
activity particularly patenting Hardware
you know uh telecoms and Communications
is concentrated you can see that
Innovation activities are highly
concentrated that doesn't mean that
Talent is concentr doesn't mean that um
let's say creativity is concentrated it
means that Innovative activities are
highly concentrated and you can not
surprisingly they concentrated on the
west coast the East Coast an increasing
amount that we're beginning to see in
Austin and elsewhere around New York
this is a very uncomfortable political
reality and I could show you this for
any country but it is true and you might
say well why does that happen well I
think the reason it happens particularly
in this sort of deep Tech is because
when we're trying to reduce the risks of
deep Tech of these very complex
Technologies of that idea to impact
Journey we often do it by working in an
innovation ecosystem we do it by working
in a specific place where we can find
all the kind of supports that you
literally just heard all about right all
those support systems don't just sort of
appear and are evenly distributed around
the world they are not evenly
distributed across the US frankly
they're not evenly distributed across
Massachusetts and although we try to do
that they actually concentrate and so by
working in an innovation ecosystem one
of these concentrated geographically
bounded locations
when those ecosystems are rich in the
resources that entrepreneurs um need
like many of the individuals in this
room who you'll who you'll hear from or
have heard from what do they need you've
already heard what they need they need
the kinds of human capital the talent
and the expertise both to join their
team but also to help them in the form
of the extraordinary technicians that we
have at MIT Nano and elsewhere they need
funding and not just any old funding
they don't just need somebody with a
checkbook although that's always nice to
have they want expert investors who've
actually been through that Journey who
understand the kinds of Milestones the
pivots the iterative experimentation
that you heard about and they need
infrastructure and this I think is the
piece that we had underappreciated until
quite recently is how important the
infrastructure is because it's extremely
costly for any given company to do that
and so what we find in these special
places like Greater Boston like silic
and Valley um are a system of resources
that are rapidly shared in exchanged by
stakeholders who are in a sort of social
network who know how to find one another
so that each of you can do this sort of
quickly and what that lets you do is
reduce the time and money to building
your deep Tech Venture so the reason
then so for those things that take time
that have those Wells of risk that have
valleys of death that need to be filled
with money and infrastructure and talent
right we basically know that we can we
can fill those Wells we can cross The
Valleys of death much much more
efficiently if we are collocated with
other people who are doing it and we're
in these ecosystems that are providing
these sorts of resource systems to us
and so I'm not going to talk about that
very much MIT does a lot of this this is
my latest slightly mad bugle figure
which sort of says MIT has all these
things that are trying to help all of
you do this gosh there's a lot of them
sometimes probably a bit too messy but
more important than just what we do on
campus although MIT Nano I think as an
extraordinary additional resource that
now has been developed on campus is the
fact that in the ecosystem we have
stakeholders who are together
collectively providing those resources
and if I put myself in the shoes of the
many many entrepreneurial teams that I
work with in the School of Management
helping them get their ideas from the
lab out to the economy who do they need
to help them they need the university
providing that early stage
infrastructure like MIT Nano providing
the you know expert humans they need
risk Capital providers they're not
evenly distributed across the us or
economies they're often here in these
specialized places places but we also
need corporations and so partnering
having ILP here is really important
because large corporations have access
to Key Supply chains customer channels
they understand the regulatory
environment they often have the balance
sheet funding that can be particularly
helpful in Partnership and last but not
least we need the government you already
heard what the state of Massachusetts is
doing it's in the context of the chips
act which is obviously the federal
government but the government can be
very very significant in supporting this
expensive ecosystem wide infrastructure
it can do things like provide funding
everything from the SB and sttr to
things like the vouchers that I know are
extremely important in the semiconductor
Arena at the moment and frankly they can
serve as lead customers right when the
government says they want to buy
something from you like the next chip or
the next um piece of quantum Computing
that can be a very powerful thing for a
startup so we need these five
stakeholders to come together the last
thing I'd say in my minus one minute is
that I think that are some quite complex
Global geopolitical dynamics that are
shaping these things so we can't really
sensibly talk about this without at
least recognizing a few things one is
within the US I think that there's
significant potential to amplify the
support for deep Tech um particularly
deep Tech in Silicon in silico I don't
mean silico Valley um we we are seeing
this already in places like atin Arizona
Oregon but we probably need to remember
that this is not going to be evenly
distributed across the US and we have to
accept that as a sort of price of doing
this kind of business that there are
really important Partners beyond the US
places that we can learn from and who
want to learn from us and I would Point
particularly in this uh domain to
activity in Europe and places like Lan
with iMac uh Copenhagen who are doing
some extraordinarily interesting work in
Quantum Computing not just in the very
famed that rather sort of Gray Building
is the Neils bour Institute not just the
research but also the quantum Foundry
Investments That Nova Nordisk is making
and finally the geopolitical landscape I
think means that we have to um establish
greater control over the stages of
innovation we need to think much much
more carefully about our supply chains
and frankly the US I think is beginning
to make a shift from what has been
described as a sort of small yard high
fence kind of America you know putting
everything in America that's I think a
quite inefficient approach and you're
beginning to see some very interesting
movement towards what I would call
shared Gardens which is engaging with
allies and partners um so that we really
think carefully about some of these
Global Supply chains and pockets of
expertise that can be networked together
but that is probably a discussion for
another day so with that Joyce thank you
very
[Applause]
much thank
you thank you to our three speakers that
was an amazing um Talk many talks about
the different aspects of bringing idea
to fruition um and I'd like to invite
our three speakers up for our panel um
with questions um so we have um the
pigeon hole where you can um put your
questions and then people can upload
them and we can ask do you want to sit
these three and I'll sit here yeah
okay so maybe to start um so you've
talked a lot about startups um bringing
um deep Tech into commercialization and
there are many ways a startup can fail
what are some advice or what kind of
elements would you suggest would be ways
to be a successful startup or bring an
idea to
fruition that's uh well it's a loaded
question I would say uh the number one
thing is uh startups fail because they
run out of money and so uh always
keeping an eye on cash and knowing where
you are what your Runway is and um being
on top of that is uh the top priority
because if you run out of money it
doesn't matter how great your idea is um
it just goes away and you won't be able
to advance it so it's sorry to it's sort
of an uninspiring
answer great yeah maybe building upon
that I think you know given the time
scales that we're talking about in you
know let's call it deep Tech uh
especially we're talking semiconductors
or other technologies that require you
know it's called a third-party Fab to to
manufacture your
devices continuing to focus not only on
the technology development but also on
your commercial or your customer
development because as you move
from small research facility you can
turn all the knobs yourselves much lower
cost the cost as you move forward from a
commercialization perspective you the
cost of moving from MIT Nano let's say
to an MIT linoln Laboratories to a
global foundaries can get exponentially
more
expensive they will also from the
question of why should I support it why
should I give you a discount why should
I put my a team on it rather than some
team that you know is perhaps less
interested in in really seeing you
succeed all comes from the corresponding
customer PLL that you can bring it's one
thing to just bring your technology to
them and hopefully write a check that
you can swallow and develop the
technology but if youing a portfolio of
tier one customers tier one clients
whether they be commercial industrial
government that highlight as soon as you
can build this in this quantity I'm in
as soon as you can get to this quantity
I'm in it just unlocks so much more
potential der risks so many aspects of
that um that I think critical to move
again not only your technology
development plans but your customer
development plans in lock step with each
other the only thing that I might add if
I may is just that I think failing is
okay I mean yes if we didn't fail
sometimes we wouldn't be taking enough
risk no investor assumes everything is
going to work and we sort of know that's
true but it's hard to say that out loud
so I think the the thing to do is to
fail in a capital efficient way so that
you set up the learning milestones and I
think I you talked about this the kind
of Milestones that journey and pivot can
sometimes mean pivot to stop and so I
think just being really um clear red
about that is a very difficult thing for
most teams and a very important thing to
try to do yeah and very hard decisions
have to be made then yeah and and I also
agree about the customer fit like you
also all of them you mentioned that um
showing that you have customers really
validates your your use case um okay so
we have a question here um what's the
best way to access Innovation that is
coming outside the so-called Innovation
hubs such as Boston and Bay Area um take
the Midwest as a case example how did
you yeah I mean I can at least take it
from
uh from a micro Electronics Coalition
perspective um or micro Electronics
Commons perspective so although there
are eight Regional hubs that make up the
microelectronics commons and although we
are regionally distributed um not
surprisingly fairly well aligned with
the map uh that was shown earlier um but
we aren't Bound by those geographical
regions so even if you take a look at
nmc for example about 10% of our members
are from with outside the Northeast and
I think specifically to the the
questions some of those are startups in
North Carolina uh one is a startup in
Arkansas that you know frankly doesn't
have access to their local resources
wants to utilize the types of facilities
that are available in the Northeast want
to start to plug into some of the End
customer opportunities that are
available here and so they are more than
welcome to join our organization and
participate with the assumption that
they're bringing valuable technology
opportunities into the ecosystem so
there are certainly those opportunities
uh for folks outside the Northeast yeah
I mean I do a lot of work in Greece and
um it really doesn't take much in any of
these ecosystems to get pretty plugged
in pretty quickly um and showing
interest typically some place that's
sort of not one of the hubs they really
appreciate outside interest and they're
very delighted to sort of show off what
they've developed and what you discover
is that the difference between those
non-hubs and the hubs is not the level
of inventiveness um at all um what the
difference is is generally the ecosystem
that Fiona talked about uh that whole
infrastructure and the overall culture
of accepting failure and uh just going
for it um so it's been really fun to see
what's happening in Greece and um
there's great stuff happening everywhere
yeah yeah and I would just add that I
think that it used to be so when we
first started looking at this sort of
whole idea of an innovation ecosystem it
was just a Silicon Valley phenomena that
everybody looked at people woke up to
the idea that we do have such a thing
here in Boston um particularly in the
Life Sciences but I would say absolutely
also in sort of hardtech and and
semiconductors that we are definitely
seeing the rise of additional hubs
elsewhere in the country and I think
that is being both supported by some of
the government efforts that you've
described as well as those efforts sort
of to go with the grain and saying all
right we see this concentration of
activity let's say in Texas or Oregon
and let's sort of go after that and I
think you're exactly right we see that
in Europe as well and and that's
definitely so in the last 10 years if
you had been going to Munich for a
period of time you'd have seen
reasonably little extraordinary large
corporations and now you see an
incredibly vibrant Innovation Hub
particularly around things that sort of
build on some of the traditional
strengths that that you have there and
so I think it's actually a um quite a
positive outlook but connecting into the
hubs that exist and and one of the
points about these hubs is they are open
and welcoming and I think that's really
important and I think there are also
hubs opening in the midwest um there is
definitely one in Chicago on the life
sciences yep and um and the start. Nano
program itself actually accept starts
from all over the country so we actually
have some in one we just accepted from
Atlanta um so that's the same case with
the nmc I think they're actually were
funded by the
nmc um so let's see what the next
question um what advice can you provide
to Industrial companies to make
successful and continuous relationships
with deep Tech
startups I'll kick it out I you know be
open um as a serial entrepreneur myself
one of the huge bizdev challenges is
especially with a large industrial
organization is who do you get you know
how do you get to the right person you
could spend months knocking on doors you
know trying to get to the right person
within the right organization to start
to have the conversation that you're
really looking to have um and so being
open to startups helping
them understand where that front door
lies so to speak who can they connect
with how do they get quickly to the
right organizations and start to have
the dialogues that that can really help
form Mutual
collaboration I mean so I've just
finished writing a book about this
subject I think
with my colleague Phil Bud which I think
is going to come out with MIT press in
April although we haven't chosen a cover
image so any suggestions most welcome I
mean the the the advice that I like to
try and give is to imagine if you're a
large Industrial company to try to put
yourself in the shoes of the deep Tech
startup entrepreneurial teeth and if you
try and walk in their shoes what you'll
realize is that they are going through
these Milestones they are trying to
generate evidence of what what of what
works they're trying to be Capital
efficient time is not on their side so
what that means is the thing that they
probably don't want from you is your
entire legal team to show up in their
offices with you know a 200 Page
contract and so I think sort of trying
to balance you know the minimum viable
paperwork for early relationships and
conversations and to be respectful of
that fact understand where the Deep tech
company is on their journey and then
really think carefully about how you can
be a partner with them what do you
actually want from them and what might
they want from you
again it's probably not the lawyers it
may not be your HR department it might
and it is your money sometimes but it's
often something rather different I think
which is your insights into Supply
chains your customer right a contract
right much much more practical and
tangible I think yeah absolutely I mean
I think there are infinite numbers of
ways that you can mentor and advise
startups and get plugged into the
ecosystem through incubators and
accelerators and workshops and shows
conferences things like
that and my previous where I worked
previously we also did a lot of
Strategic investment so that's where we
provide a lot of ink kind um like
Consulting and you know access to our
supply chain so that kind of thing also
really accelerates their development I
think a startup we worked with said we
accelerate them by two years because of
our the gaps that we could fill for them
yeah let's see what's next how can a
us-based startup with Founders who are
not in the US um contribute to the chips
act and participate in any
memc yeah Sor I was just rereading the
question um in general just like
everybody else does and I don't mean to
be GLI about it but I mean you know we
welcome ideas from everyone um although
we're us chips act funded um or although
a large significant aspect of our
funding is us chips act uh we're not
entirely us chips act focus our vision
over the coming years is to to continue
to grow um whether it's DOD applications
non-government applications commercial
applications what have you so I would I
would advise don't um don't let you know
the fact that you're a non us founder uh
dissuade you from reaching out from
having conversations from joining The
Hub and and seeing how we can
collaborate yeah I think that's right
let's see L of what makes the US very
special is that you have lots of people
who are you know themselves born
elsewhere or whose parents are born
elsewhere and you know which is I think
the issue becomes visas I mean that
becomes a very important issue and one
that universities deal with I think
different government organizations
entrepreneurs find that quite
challenging but important to deal with
yeah I think one of researchers in the
US are foreign born or something like
that and like onethird of entrepreneurs
are foreign born so it's um the numbers
are work in your favor and um in terms
of getting Government funding um I work
with a startup that has raised millions
of dollars of government grants and um
the founders are all born outside the
US so uh let's like this question about
um collaboration what are the
opportunities in the near-term for us EU
collaboration on hardtech startups what
would that look
like I mean look I'm I'm happy to um to
go first I I think that there are some I
mean there are some definitely I mean
there are lot of if you think about the
ecosystem model I think there's lots of
opportunities from one ecos to another
and those the sort of fabric of
collaboration I think often the
universities are very good at that they
have very long-standing relationships
with for example European universities
uh MIT has that with a number of major
academic institutions um I think when
you see large corporations they often
have multiple locations I'm particularly
struck in this field with a relationship
with imch um who are in lva in Belgium
but who who have a physical presence
here so you see some very specific um
organizations trying to help make this
possible because we're in a global
market um the US you know is is is
complicated if you're looking as an ally
of the United States from the outside
looking in you're not quite sure you
know how things are going to unfold and
so what you see is a number of
collaborative relationships that might
happen with the US on a country bycount
basis the UK is seeing that partly
because the UK is not in the EU anymore
um and then the sort of us EU and I
think particularly there's a a sort of
interesting tension around the EU having
its own chips and sort of thinking of
itself as entirely separate because they
want European sovereignity over certain
things um the US wanting the same thing
and then at what point do we collaborate
I think we've seen extraordinary
collaboration particularly with the
Dutch with companies like asml you know
sort of acting as that ful Crome where
you have to have the collaborative sort
of architecture to help us and and NATO
has been part of those conversations as
well because some of this is so
important for Global
security see what distinguishes between
a deep Tech startup focus on
differentiation versus new efforts like
uh SpaceX and earling that create a new
market um well I will say Nur um nurlink
there are um other researchers and
companies that have started that have
been doing that for 20 years so nural
link is just more like a big um
promotional thing that like as if this
is brand new but it's not at all brand
new um so um in terms of what
distinguishes um I think you're always
trying to find a hole in the market so I
wouldn't really view those as being
different um there's always a market out
there and the market might be doing
nothing or it might be doing something
different um but you're always as an
entrepreneur looking for that whole
what's what's the need that's not being
met by the current Solutions even if the
current solution is doing nothing um and
so um I would say um you're always
looking to differentiate and um and
create a new market Niche however big or
small that Niche may
be any other distinction I would make is
actually whether something is so new
that it's not clearly regulated I me
that would be I think a useful
distinction um
in the sense of if you're trying to
forge something that's so distinctive in
the way you do something that the
regulatory path is really really unclear
I think that just lays on an additional
layer of complexity and uncertainty and
so you know some of the very early
activities and say autonomy you know was
completely unregulated and nobody really
knew what you were allowed to do and
nobody knew how to test it either and so
I think that just adds but that's I
think that's different than a new market
it's sort of is it in such a new way
that we don't have to Reg at it just
make would makes any investor have more
of a headache I think than we did before
but I think it is a good point and you
agreed it shifts it from the market side
let's say to the underlying enabling
technology side but I think there can be
a differentiator on that technology
side one of which would be if you're
building within an exising technology
set or on an existing technology
platform your path to Market from which
is to say a testing characterization
perspective is going to be fairly well
known you know you know what your you
know what your you know HT your high
temp operating life requirements are
going to be you've got those models you
know how to apply them versus if you're
building from a brand brand new
technology platform where that physics
might not yet be understood those
failure mechanisms might not be
understand you do now have another set
of hurdles to overcome to get to Market
which is to one understand what they are
and then to demonstrate that you
understand what they are so that from a
technology adoption perspective the
customer is willing to take that
incremental risk in theory for the
incremental reward that you're giving
them in return yeah I think to Compound
on that um the more Innovative your
technology the longer it takes to
educate your customer on your solution
and um I mean in our early days nobody
knew what a 3D printer was and so you've
got to start at Ground Zero like why
would you use a 3D printer what's the
benefit yeah it's cool and sexy but does
it really matter um and yeah yeah and I
mean I remember I mean every class that
Dad and I have taught I think V Vladimir
you know what I'm going to say which is
that you know there are times when you
say well if I'm developing it I've got
new technical risk I don't quite know
how this is characterized there's new
markets new regulation which I just
described but sometimes it's not even
The Foundry doesn't exist right we don't
actually know how to manufacture
something and so I actually have to
invent an entirely new manufacturing
process as well and so when you compound
each of those things you end up with
more and more risk that you're carrying
um I think makes it more
complex definely so I think that was the
last question um thank you for all your
questions um and we're all going to be
here for or some of us are going to be
here for today so um thank you very much
for our speakers today and the great
panel um and so here is our startup
showcase um in the Next Room um so we
have a few selections from our current
cohort and some previous cohorts so
please check them out out um and I guess
it's time for lunch and thank you again
so much thank you great talk