Now we'll focus on how disorders of
adipose tissue can contribute to
metabolic diseases. We'll focus on
obesity which is characterized by excess
adipose tissue and lipodistrophe which
is characterized by lack or abnormal
distribution of adipost tissue. Despite
the contrasting effects on total mass
between these conditions, both can
result in lipid overflow and deposition
in other tissues which will lead to
complications including insulin
resistance, which is the inability of
the hormone insulin to properly regulate
blood glucose levels, which can also
lead to increased risk of type 2
diabetes.
Obesity is a complex disease involving
many factors and include lifestyle
components which include diet and
physical activity patterns which also
interact with genetic predisposition.
The plots show obesity prevalence trends
worldwide both in women and men which
clearly highlight the magnitude of the
problem which affects over 600 million
people and also how quickly this evolved
over a time span of 40 years. Now
obesity is associated with a vast range
of health complications. The most widely
recognized are the impacts on endocrine
systems and cardiovascular systems which
will increase the predisposition to type
2 diabetes and heart diseases. However,
there's also many other implications to
the nervous system, pulmonary, immune
system, and even increasing the risk of
some kinds of cancer which then really
shows the wide ranging of complications
involved with obesity.
On the other end, we also have
lipodistrophe which is characterized by
the lack or abnormal distribution of
adipose tissue which then can be
classified in different types based on
its severity, the causes and genetic
predisposition.
Here are some magnetic resonance images
where we have subcutaneous fat shown in
blue and visceral fat showing in yellow.
And when we compare to healthy controls
here on the far left, we can see
different kinds of uh lipodistrophe
cases characterized by both
almost complete depletion of all adipose
tissue and also other patterns of
depletion of subcutaneous adipose tissue
and increased deposition in the visceral
compartment
associated with this abnormal pattern.
patterns of fat mass and distribution.
We see a range of increased risk for
metabolic complications including
insulin resistance which will affect
blood glucose regulation and
predisposition to type 2 diabetes.
And how does obesity and lipodistrophe
affects adapost tissue directly?
Under normal adipos tissue formation
conditions, there is a healthy expansion
that will adapt to normal calorie
intake.
Under conditions of prolonged calorie
access and other preconditioning
factors, there's unhealthy expansion of
adipost tissue leading to abnormal
patterns of hormone, lipid and
inflammatory cytoine release which will
further impact metabolic health
in conditions of lipodistrophe. either
due to the impaired formation of adipost
tissue or due to acquired factors
leading to the depletion of adipost
tissue. We also see abnormal hormone
release patterns that will impact
metabolic health.