welcome
everyone to today's MIT startup exchange
demo day I'm ariatna rodenstein program
manager with startup
exchange and I'm very excited to um for
two reasons particularly today the first
um to introduce the seven startups all
members of startup exchange that will
lead this demo day today and then also
we have a new look some of you might
have noticed that and so um we're glad
to be sharing this today with with you
our active um audience and um demod day
community so I will give a brief
overview of our program and then you
will hear uh from the
startups MIT startup exchange was
created over 8 years ago to support MIT
connected startups as they grow expand
and help solve some of the world's
greatest challenges by fostering
Partnerships and collaborations with
industry and primarily ILP members
represented by so many of you joining us
today also the MIT Innovation ecosystem
and
Beyond these startups in our program are
based on MIT licensed technology or
founded by MIT faculty staff or alumni
and they can also be vetted by some of
our MIT peers including the engine
Ventures the e14 fund Cale MIT Nano or
the mar trust centor for MIT
entrepreneurship just to name a few
and so our program our Network um has
around a thousand startups and they
usually join the program at Pilot stage
or Beyond and they cover all sectors and
all geographies and here you can see
some of the trending Technologies of MIT
startups and I've highlighted in bold
those represented by those that will
speak today of course we'll start with
AI and machine learning also big data
and analytics sustainability renewable
energy energy storage and lifestyle
science and
healthare so as far as
value um when it comes to that um the
startups in our program have exposure to
a Global Network of Industry decision
makers and the corporates have access to
vetted MIT connected
startups also events is a critical
component of this we host over 30 per
year locally and internationally
including demo days like today
conferences where startups have um
participation in lightning talks and
Exhibits also workshops trainings
one-on-one meetings and so much more the
benefit of this for the ILP members is
that we can tailor an event according to
your needs and the benefit to the
startups is that we can take you to
other markets that you're expanding into
and you can have visibility into new
ecosystems we also launch calls for
startups these are what we call
opportunities and they're based on
corporates priorities and intern
internal challenges and so startups can
apply on our website and if they are
selected they can work with an ILP
member to help you solve a problem or
challenge that you're facing in your
industry so all in all um we have a very
curated um and customized approach and I
hope everyone is uh being able to take
advantage of all of these
benefits and so what is demod day it's a
quarterly and virtual Forum where we
facilitate interactions and
introductions between the startups and
Industry and with the hope that this can
happen sooner rather than
later we um have uh also hosted our
first live demo day in s Silicon Valley
in June of 2023 and we look forward to
hosting other Live Events as well but
for now please mark your calendars for
the next virtual ones they will take
place on December 11th and March 19th
and please check out the startup
exchange and ILP websites for all
upcoming events this fall and next
spring the format today will consist of
seven startups presenting for four
minutes followed by 2 minutes of Q&A so
I ask that you please use the Q&A tab at
the bottom of your screen for the
questions post them there indicate which
startup it's for and will'll um include
your questions later on in the program
you'll be able to also um interact with
the startups using the chat and also via
the breakout rooms that will happen
right after the last
presentation and as always reach out to
us if you need help connecting with the
startups so with that a couple of final
reminders one the presentations of the
startups are being recorded and two
you'll see um a brief survey pop up at
the end of the event on your screen so
please share your feedback with us and
thank you again for joining