Some data suggest that lifestyle and
behavior account for the majority of
[music] cardiovascular disease risk.
However, newer data since the
incorporation of high throughput genomic
sequencing has suggested that genomics
play a very large role in the
development of cardiovascular disease
and diabetes. What we don't know is why
South Asians have such high
cardiovascular disease risk.
Some people say that it's entirely due
to our lifestyle and our behaviors.
Other people say it's due to [music] our
genetics, something that we inherited
from generation to generation. South
Asians represent [music] 23% of the
globe and only 1.3% of genetic study
participants.
Furthermore, we know that [music] very
few South Asians participate in clinical
trials, but we don't know the exact
number because South Asians are often
grouped into a larger category [music]
termed Asian other. What we as doctors
worry about is that there are [music]
genetic reasons why South Asians have
such high rates of cardiovascular
disease and diabetes.
Talk to [music] your friends and family
about the high rates of cardiovascular
disease and diabetes in South Asians and
encourage them to join our health.