hi everyone Khan Waring CEO of skyline
nav AI we've had a long-standing
partnership with MIT my co-founder went
to um MIT in got his PhD from there so
at a high level um our background
expertise is in computer Vision
manufacturing patents Hardware
development and scaling and we have been
working primarily with clients in the
United States and Europe last week I was
actually in Taiwan that was one of our
first trips in Asia and we're looking
for um folks who are looking for GPS
independent navigation for cars trucks
drones aircraft that's what our subject
matter expertise is and then you might
ask well why do you need a GPS
independent
solution well there's many reasons why
first off uh if any one of you have
lived in complex terrains think of urban
areas mountaneous regions uh you're
driving through tunnels highways uh
multi- Lev highways you may have
struggled with localization and so
challenge is you're connecting to the
satellite to get your location back uh
and it's not very efficient so that's
one of the reasons you want to think
about not just up GPS but fusing GPS
with other modalities such as the camera
um you you also have the situations
where GPS could be denied uh that's
happening right now in eastern Ukraine
and in Middle East uh it's being denied
spoofed um and so it's very challenging
for folks on the ground um when they're
doing regular things like getting from
point A to point B or opening up their
cell phones and not being able to get
the rides that they need on apps like
uber lift Etc so that's where we come in
we have solved the issue of GPS denial
and a GPS independent navigation system
that can work on ground and also in the
air and we estimate that if a technology
like ours was deployed at scale uh it
can help save people billions of dollars
a year in um a fewer um time that is
saved but also fuel costs uh that people
end up spending a lot of time on because
they don't have good localization so how
does our solution work well at a high
level we use the camera
and we also use the storage and compute
on board a car or a drone or an aircraft
and then that imagery is coming in as
you're moving from point A to point B we
have computer vision models that I'll
talk about in a second that are able to
pick up on different features around you
think of buildings think of mountains
think of trees think of Land Ocean you
you name it just like you and I as human
beings we can figure out where we are by
looking what's around us and comparing
that with map we do the same using
pre-computed pre-processed
two-dimensional and three-dimensional
satellite data sets so you download our
capability and it is designed to run on
the edge so there is no connectivity
required after you have the satellite
data sets and you have our algorithms
downloaded which we recommend doing it
at least once a year because things
around you don't change very often now
if there's been natural disasters think
of earthquake hurricanes Etc things will
change and that's where you want to
bring in the latest um data set around
you and so once you have it and we've
pre-computed pre-process everything
takes a few minutes now you're good to
go so as you're driving or flying the
camera is taking in visual information
comparing that with the pre-downloaded
satellite data sets and our algorithms
are able to give you a location back and
you can now navigate with or without
GPS so here's our secret sauce we have
different types of computer vision
models in the air and on the ground that
are able to deliver on these various
capabilities in fact you go to
skyline.com today and you can explore
the city of Chicago with no GPS we've
also just last night published our first
set of results uh we actually flew a
drone um in different parts of the US
and we are able to geolocate uh simply
by using the camera on the Drone this is
two-dimensional uh what you're seeing on
the left and then the city of Chicago is
using a Skyline train based approach and
you'll experience 95% of the time we can
get you 5 m or under on air or on ground
something we have also recently launched
is a semantic based approach where we're
able to pick up on different restaurants
and intersections and fuse that to give
you more accurate positioning so in this
picture this actually is um not at MIT
but at a competing school Harvard um and
we are able to pick up on different
intersections and restaurants and
businesses in that vicinity to tell you
hey this is where you are now imagine
the possibilities of having more
accurate positioning and navigation so
on the left you're seeing the current
day experience of urban Canyons and um
we have published a bunch of case
studies on our website San Francisco
Atlanta I experienced this in Taiwan
last week I've experienced this so many
times in Boston it's unbelievable right
so the big blue circle I call it that
big blue Circle of Death because you're
like where am I and how do I get to my
location um and on the right our
technology kicks in and simply using
camera we can get you 5 MERS or under
95% of the time and you fuse our
capability with inertial sensors and or
liar and then centimeter level accuracy
is also
possible so you can see on the left the
landbased results and how we able to
pick up on that and on the right you
have air based results again go to the
website you can play with our API um you
can play and see with the uh demo video
we've posted recently of the Drone
footage and our capability the beauty of
it is we've already trained the models
and it's ready to go worldwide uh we've
already proven it out in 40 regions
around the world and if there's a region
of interest that you have please reach
out and I'd love to work with you um you
can bring your own
or or we can fly out to you and and we
can uh prove our the capability Works uh
with you in action so how are customers
using our capability today so we are
working with large companies like BAE
Systems and care for so BAE Systems has
its own camera system and our capability
is running on top of that camera system
to do GPS Independence uh to do object
recognition and autonomy with k for
they're one of the Premier inertial
system companies and RK capability is
being fused with their inertial sensing
capabilities we have published the demo
of our ba systems collaboration so you
can go to our website and check it out
I'm also very excited to announce that
we have an
in-house design of a GL ground robot and
a drone which we actually manufacturing
right here in the United States we just
launched this you're actually one of the
first group of people to um learn about
it so it's called blade next and um
these are tactical robots and drones low
cost affordable uh the ground product is
$5,000 or under depending on the
configuration and we're offering the
drone at $2,000 or under depending on
different configuration and the model
type and it's running our software and
we've also added new features uh for
object recognition um and also for
autonomous operation from point A to
point B and most importantly uh these
products can navigate in a GPS denied
environment and they're secure encrypted
Mission ready um and so what we are here
for is we are seeking customers who have
case studies and and areas where you're
struggling with
localization and these are all the
different sectors but there could be
others as well that you're interested in
and we can help you solve that by using
the camera we just need three things
camera storage and compute and we can
make our software work through the API
and the SDK the API does require Cloud
connectivity but the SDK which is our
software is designed to run on the edge
with no connectivity requirement no
Wi-fi no cell no GPS I'm happy to answer
any questions you have thank
you thank you CER very much um so what
about um
fog and other elements that um could
complicate things a little bit excellent
question so with fog uh there's
certainly special cameras um that are
able to clear up the fog or even in snow
or windy conditions right so we are
relying on the camera uh that you have
installed on the on the edge and the
same thing applies even at nighttime so
you know if you have eoir cameras then
certainly we can pick up on that that's
actually been our collaboration with ba
system where our software is running on
top of an eir camera and can look
through at night so if you're using an
iPhone camera so we have an iPhone app
as well to demonstrate our capability
well these things won't work very well
in fog uh and also at nighttime unless
you have good lighting condition and so
that's the dependency we have on the
camera system that's why we tell fuse
our capability with Imus and liar if you
have available because then you have an
end to end solution that would work in
any type of
environment okay and tell us a little
more about the business model how are
you working with a corporate for example
yeah absolutely so typically clients
would come in and they would purchase
our API and SDK and we charge an annual
fee for that and we don't actually make
money off of the API SDK it covers our
engineering cost so we can ensure that
our product is working with your
Hardware configuration so if you have
specific camera types well it's probably
going to require some calibration on our
side to make it work and so that's all
covered in the API and the SDK and for
every car truck drone aircraft that you
install our capability on um we charge
you a small license fee uh and it can be
uh negotiable uh for example we're
talking to a company right now that
wants to put our stuff on 10,000 drones
next year right so they're not paying
the full retail price and we're
negotiating and we have come to a
conclusion on what that's going to look
like um so that's what we're interested
in you know automobile manufacturers
drone manufacturers if you're interested
in incorporating we'll work with you and
we'll uh would love to have our
technology integrated thank you very
much of course my pleasure thank you