All right. Hello everyone. Welcome. Uh,
thank you so much for joining us for the
MIT Startup Exchange lightning talks.
Uh, my name is Arena Gazva and I'm a
program coordinator with MIT Startup
Exchange. Shortly, you will hear from
four exciting MIT connected startups.
All active participants in our program,
offering bold new ideas shaping the
future of connectivity. Now more than
ever, networks at the core of how we our
world works. that connect people,
devices and systems across every
industry from healthcare to education to
manufacturing and global supply chain.
As we move deeper into AIdriven future,
these networks will power everything
from smarter devices in data centers to
autonomous vehicles, drones, and
immersive digital experiences.
That's where today's presenters come in.
the startups reimagining how that we
connect and collaborate in rapidly
changing world. I hope you'll be
inspired and take the chance to engage
with our presenters today during the Q&A
and afterward. If something sparks your
interest, please feel reach out to me or
your program director to explore
potential collaborations.
And this is just one of the examples of
how our program works uh to help connect
industry leaders with breakthrough
technologies and emerging innovators.
Let me tell you about our program.
MIT startup exchange was created 10
years ago to support MIT connected
startups in growing, expanding and
solving the world's greatest challenges.
We do this by fostering partnerships and
collaborations with ILP members like
many in the audience today as well as
extensive MIT innovation system and
beyond.
Our startups in our network are strongly
connected to MIT. Many of our startups
have founding team that consist of alum
faculty or staff while others have
licensed technology from MIT. Many of
other startups are vetted and supported
by MIT Pierce such as CEO startup plus
uh start.no the engine e14
we have about 800 startups in our
network
join uh typically join at the pilot
stage in beyond and may cover any
geography and sector.
So what is the value of our program for
you and our startups? Well, startups in
our program gain exposure to a global
network of industry leaders, while
corporate members have access to a
curated selection of MIT created
startups. We host local and
international events, including
conferences, forums, demo days, and
webinars, all of which can be tailored
to address your priorities.
We also facilitate one-on-one meetings
between startups and corporate members.
A key feature of startup exchange is
helping members to find solution to the
industry challenges. We do this through
targeted startup goals known as
opportunities.
Selected startups then collaborate with
members to test and co-develop
solutions. Overall, STAX has a highly
customized and curated approach. We know
that some of you already taking
advantage of it and if not, please feel
reach out to me and our team.
[clears throat]
And this is just a few examples of
success stories we've seen so far. From
proof of concepts and pilots to join
developments and even acquisition.
With every event, meeting, and
introduction, our goal to spark those
meaningful conversations. They can grow
into their own success stories. If you'd
like to learn more, please or have any
questions, would love to hear from you.
And with that, let's turn turn to our
startups. Each startup will have five
minutes followed by two minutes Q&A. So,
please have your questions ready. Hope
you enjoy the presentations. First up is
Notch, an innovative antenna company
using Meta Materials.