Uh welcome uh to the first Schmidt
Center colloquium of this fall. Uh it's
jointly hosted by the Eric and Wendy
Schmidt Center at the Broad and ECS at
MIT. Uh in the series we feature
speakers whose work shows how machine
learning uh is driving insights into
important uh questions uh in biomedical
sciences and equivalently how questions
in biomedical sciences uh is spurring uh
foundational advances in machine
learning and we're equally adv excited
about both directions. So we're really
excited to have uh Katherine Heler with
us today. Katherine is a research
scientist at Google where she leads the
context in AI research or care team. Her
work focuses on identifying robustness
and fairness issues and medical AI and
creative technologies. She's made a
remarkable real world impact. Katherine,
I was reading about this. It's
incredible that you've developed and
integrated multiple machine learning
systems into hospitals and clinical
care. That's that is that is hard to do.
These include uh sepsis detection
systems now running in Duke University
Hospital's emergency department. Uh a
system that predicts uh surgical
complications and a nationally released
uh mobile app on multiple sclerosis.
Throughout this work, she is passionate
about ensuring that everyone is included
um in the development of medical eye
technology and I'm sure we'll hear a lot
about that today. Uh before Google, um
Katherine held appointments across
multiple departments at Duke. uh and
this is quite a list uh statistical
science, neurobiology, neurology,
computer science and electrical and
computer engineering. She's been
recognized with the NSF with an NSF
career award and was a first round
recipient of the brain initiative award.
Katherine received her bachelor's in
computer science and applied math at
Sunny Stonybrook MS in CS from Colombia,
PhD um in neuroscience unit at UCL and
she did her postto EPSRC posttock in
engineering at Cambridge and then was
here um across the road uh doing her NSF
posttock in the brain and cognitive
sciences uh department. So we are really
excited uh to have you here Katherine.
Take it away.
>> Thanks so much.
Yeah, I'm I'm watching I'm watching this
video like all all my friends, some of
them I haven't seen since grad school,
like who are coming to talk and I'm so
envious of you guys getting to see them
and finding out what they're up to right
now. So, um this is great. Thank you so
much for inviting me. Um okay, so I'm
Katherine. Um and I'll be talking about
um some of the work that we're doing
right now at Google. I know I'm I'm here
to answer people's questions on sort of
like the academia industry sort of
spectrum because I've I've experienced
both sides of that division. Um but I'm
going to be talking about our industry
industry related work now. Um and uh our
team is called context and AI research.
Um, and so I want to talk about what
they've been up to, um, as well as doing
human- centered AI research, right? Um,
in a healthcare context specifically,
um, at a time when we're talking a lot
about general purpose AI and how to get
general purpose AI off the ground in
industry.
Okay. Um, so at a at a very high level,
um, this relates to and maybe this is
this is more of an industry thing. I
don't know, but I'm I'm going to hope,
right? Um, but like at a high level,
this relates to an ICML paper that we
just had on um, artificial general
intelligence. Um, and the it was a
position paper this year at ICML and we
asked in it the community to stop using
uh, AGI um, as the northstar of AI
research. And so we we talked about um
many of the ways in which AGI enhances
known issues um via what we call traps.
And I'm not going to go into great
detail about it, but but they're all
there for you to see. And so a lot of it
comes down to a lack of definition of
what AGI is um and how it obscures uh
worthwhile scientific engineering and
societal goals. Um and um our work
really advocates for specific
definitions and metrics um and
particularly those that are inclusive of
diversity of experience and knowledge
that people have. Um so that's what
you're going to see from a lot of this
talk. Um I'm going to focus
on a healthcare context, right? So
everything that I'm gonna going to talk
about is related to health but but
always with specific definitions and
metrics in mind.
Okay, so this is this is our team. This
is the care team um at Google. Um we're
a group of people who are dedicated to
developing and evaluating AI systems
that are grounded in real world contexts
and use cases um with a focus on
solutions that promote equitable
outcomes. Having equitable outcomes is
really really important to us um and
really important to the sort of the
broader team that that we're in at
Google. um outreach and inclusion are
central to our work um and um and
everything that we do. And here I'm
going to talk about again about the
healthcare context specifically.
Okay. So I'm I'm going to start with
causal modeling specifically um because
it's it's it's pretty central to uh
formalizing our questions and concerns
and and their solutions. Um, we can use
causal modeling to design valid
evaluation procedures. Um, which we can
use with a lot of technology that's
currently being developed in in AI
fields. Um, and and these evaluation uh
evaluation procedures that that the ones
that are used currently are too often
constructed in an ineffective or harmful
way. Causal modeling provides a way to
formally incorporate important domain
specific knowledge um which is very
important in a health domain um to
ensure synergy between the predictive
task studied in the deployment context
and to more deeply understand data
biases um like label or selection bias.
An important part of this work is
understanding how to design machine
learning systems that are appropriately
grounded in the context in which they're
intended to be used. So this means
clearly defining the intended use case
and the target population. Um later
we're going to see a classifier that
identifies a dermatological disease and
images. Um and so for this for example,
we'd want to define how that model is
going to be used in a clinical workflow.
what the clinical setting is, for which
populations it's intended to be used
for. Um, ideally, we can use this sort
of reasoning to develop contextualized
statements about the downstream impacts
of the models that we develop.
A key issue that we need to address is
that the data that's used for model
development and evaluation reflects
complex societal context which results
in differences in health outcomes,
access, and quality. So this introduces
issues like selection bias because data
sets will be less representative of
populations with worse access to care.
And if utilization of health care for
example is used as a product proxy for
uh the need for health care as we've
seen in a lot of different papers this
is going to result in a worse proxy for
patients with poorer access to care. So
we see this all the time in terms of
like we're deciding on who needs this
healthcare by looking at who's used it
in the past and all kinds of bias
related issues come into play
here. So we're going to focus on issues
that arise uh with basic evaluations of
model performance across subgroups. So
we discuss
where we're interested in evaluating
performance across subgroups defined by
attributes like race or gender. Um but
these can apply to any any kinds of
related context. So it can be different
races, different genders, but it can
also be different socioeconomic groups.
It can be living in different places in
the world, that kind of thing.
Um even in the best case where we have
representative data uh comparison of
model performance across subgroups can
be misleading because the optimal
performance tends to differ across
subgroups um and can be explained by
differences in data distribution across
those subgroups. So I'll explain more
about what this actually means in a
second. Um but we can consider this to
be a p false positive fairness
violation.
Okay, so here we look at some of the
most common classes of fairness criteria
that include demographic parity and
equalist odds. Uh dem demographic par
asks that model predictions be
independent of group membership. Um and
equalist odds ask that demographic par
hold conditioned on the outcome. Um this
is equivalent to requiring that the true
positive or false positive error rates
not differ across groups.
Um, so again, like how well we're doing
should be the same regardless of whether
we're black or white or male or female
or rich or poor or from India or
Pakistan, right? Like it should just all
it should just all those shouldn't be
factors. Um, okay. So there are
variations of both of these criterias
that are defined for the continuous
valued score s uh for and for the
prediction uh the threshold predictor
yhat. Um we can see
commonly used evaluation interpret
interpretations that pop up in the
research around us. So again in people's
papers you'll see a lot of these in some
various form or another. So for example,
matching ROC curves, something that we
see a lot about a lot of in papers,
right? True positive rates, false
positive rates, these can all illuminate
these differences.
Okay, so here's a simulated example. Um
the top left plot introduces the notion
of score distribution. So that's the
distribution of scores that a model
assigns to a population of sub sub or
subgroup. So for example, this could be
like kidney functioning or EGFR. Um for
a given threshold, the classification
rate is the fraction of patients whose
scores exceed the threshold. Um and thus
would be assigned a positive prediction.
So in the plot um the threshold is the
dashed vertical line um and the
classification rate is given by the area
under the curve to the right of the
threshold. The classification rate is
also shown in the bottom plot. It's just
plotted there, right? Um and then
separately in the middle and right
columns, we have um the negative and
positive class respectively, like people
who do or don't have kidney disease. And
so as we slide the threshold from left
to right, the false positive rate in the
middle column goes to zero and the true
positive rate in the right column goes
to zero. uh in keeping with the
underlying distribution, right? We're
classing classifying fewer and fewer
people as having the disease.
So now if we have two distributions,
right, because we have multiple
subgroups, the blue and the brown
distribution, two separate subgroups, um
we can see how we get evaluation
fairness problems. Um the the
distribution in inequality creates gaps.
So you can see those gaps in the bottom
plots. Um a classification rate gap or
an outcome dependent false positive rate
or true positive rate gap signify that
for the same threshold these rates are
different across different groups. And
so what's optimal for one group isn't
necessarily optimal for another group.
Right? We look at the distribution of
scores. We see that we have a gap. We
can identify that and flag it.
So to better understand and model the
different kinds of shifts and
differences that we see, we can use
causal graphical models representing the
kind of independence and conditional
independent structure that we saw in the
table a couple of slides back. Not only
are we capable of formalizing the shifts
given here, but also things like
selection bias, label bias, and other
kinds of confounding. And I'm going to
refer you to the work of Stephen Fo who
is somebody who I work with in order if
you're interested in this line of work
to get more details and to check out
some of their papers.
So one specific care team example of
bias resulting from distribution shift
can be seen in a nerup paper that we had
a couple of years ago. Um assuming that
we develop a fair model, we need to
understand whether fairness transfers um
to the deployment environment. Um, so
all the time machine learning
practitioners run into problems where
it's like they've developed a model,
they've trained and tested in one
particular circumstance and then they
think they've captured a causal
mechanism and so they can easily
transfer to another and then that turns
out not to be the case. And this is a
failure mode for machine learning. Quite
commonly we haven't actually captured
the causal structure that we think we're
capturing. We've captured something else
about our particular environment. And so
we want to be able to recognize that.
So if model A is fair in hospital A,
will it be fair in hospital B? Or if it
works for one race, will it work for
another? Um so what you see here is a
study in dermatology predicting a whole
bunch of skin conditions from images. Um
there are two different clinical
environments. one the one that was
trained on was ter
sorry teladermatology in the US and the
target um is clinic uh it's it's a
clinic and it's taken from incl clinic
patients in Australia
and so this involves a shift on
demographics and also images and labels
and you can see the shift in dem
demographics on the lefth hand side
right men and women um ages of the
patients etc
Okay. So on the bottom right this plot
here um we can see the impact of the
shift on fairness right with model that
was fair in training. So that would be
the one with the open dots that's the
source distribution
um leading to large gaps between
different subgroups in deployments in
deployment. Um so in particular age
right so if we look at um I'm gonna walk
over um if we look at 18 to 29 year olds
we're doing about as well in our source
modeling our source distribution as we
were in the original sorry in the target
distribution as we were in the original
source distribution whereas we look at
if we look at people who are 65 and
older we're doing much much worse and so
this leads to different fairness
fairness um fairness outcomes for those
two groups of people.
Okay. And so recently we looked at
evaluating large language model question
answering around um answers to health
questions. Um so this led to this work
led to evaluation done on the MedP 2
model um which you can see. Um the user
in in in MedP 2 the user asked questions
like um can incontinence be cured?
um and the model gives a particular
answer, right? So this is like the kind
of common thing that you see with a
chatbot. Medpom is Google's particular
uh medically related well it was their
old medically related chatbot model.
Um, and so we look at assessment on on a
system like MedP. And um, we actually we
have a nature medicine paper t looking
at assessing med pom
for disparities between different
demographics and bias that might insert
itself within a medal context. Um, and
the nature med medicine paper that we
have um makes a couple of different key
contributions. Um the first contribution
is that um it develops new rubrics for
the assessment of equity related biases
in LLM generated answers to medical
questions. So um this includes three
modes of evaluation independent,
pairwise and counterfactual and I'll
show you causal models for them in a
second. Um but there are also three
kinds of raiders clinical raiders equity
experts and regular consumers.
And then after we develop these rubrics,
um we collect new data sets. We've
collected seven new data sets that are
enriched for equity relevant domains um
and which are documented and released.
Um and lastly, we run an empirical study
with MedPal. This is the largest human
evaluation study to date, or at least it
was when the paper came out within the
last year. Um it includes um assessment
questions and data sets which allow for
identifying previous un previously
unknown limitations and it also exhibits
different modes of evaluation and raider
types which allow for uh probing
dimensions of bias.
Okay. So first up um I'm going to go
through those steps one by one. Right.
So first up um is rubrics. So in order
to understand fairness and equity
challenges in a health context um a
rubric has to be developed to understand
what the definitions of these terms
means. So like what is fair, right? Like
what fairness means? Big big open
question, right? Um it could be a lot of
different things. And so in order to
tackle that, um we want to ask
a whole bunch of different people like
physicians. Um
okay, so we want to know how it's
related to practical medical systems,
what dimensions are relevant to measure.
And so we get a bunch of physicians. Um
and we ask them um and we look at med
promp prompting and uh we try to
understand what
like what what kinds of um what kinds of
bias might might crop up in the answers.
Um and so we do this using the kinds of
causal models that we've seen in the
previous slides.
Um and so we captured six different
dimensions of bias through our our
procedure. Um and and they're shown on
the slide on the right hand side. Um and
so just briefly um the first two
dimensions capture the idea that the
outputs uh should be accurate and
inclusive of the experiences and
perspectives of all groups of people. Uh
the third dimension captures
stereotyping. The fourth dimension
um assesses whether outputs presented
appropriate social and structural
explanations for health disparities. The
fifth dimension deals with the idea that
some of the questions are explicitly
adversarial and potentially contain a
premise that's itself pro problematic um
in terms of presenting content that
contains misinformation,
offensive or stereotyping content etc.
Um and last we uh aim to assess whether
potentially acting on an output could
lead to disproportionate withholding of
opportunities or resources.
And so as I mentioned we introduced
three versions of assessment uh of the
assessment rubic rubric that can be used
for different different types of design.
These are independent, pair-wise and
counterfactual. And I will briefly show
you uh what these rubrics look like. Um
so here is the rubric for uh independent
assessments. Um the main thing to notice
is that the dimensions of bias that we
define show up as options for the
raiders to annotate when flagging an
output as containing bias. Um
independent assessments ask about
whether the answer contains bias. Just
straight up one question, one answer.
pair pair-wise rubric assessments look
at relative bias between alter two
alternatives uh two alternative
scenarios right so it's like you have a
question here's answer A here's answer B
which one do you like better which one
do you think contains less bias and then
counterfactual assessments ask about the
ideal versus the actual answers and so
what I mean by this is like actually the
prompt can change so instead of having a
white person you You can have a black
person inserted into the prompt and then
you can evaluate what kind of bias you
think comes out of of of the answers to
those prompts.
Okay. So using the metrics that we
discussed that we collected from from
phys physicians amongst the axes of bias
that we discussed um we collect the uh
equity med QA data sets. Um so that's a
collection of second seven data sets of
adversarial questions. Um and a few
thousand of them are unique questions.
Um as mentioned the purpose of the data
sets is to probe for potential bias with
um with prompts that plausibly would
lead to problematic outputs. Um so so
again we expect more problematic outputs
than you would normally find using an
LLM. Um each of the individual data sets
was collected for different types of
adversarial questions and are derived
through a variety of methods both manual
and semi-automated.
So for example, one of the data sets is
topically enriched for content related
to health inequities in the US and
another one focuses on tropical and
infectious diseases.
So this this table gives the details of
all of the data sets. Um for additional
details you can read our nature medicine
paper or again talk to Stephen. Um in
particular um we use the tropical and
infectious diseases data set to
instruction chami and I'm going to show
you a recording of that demo in a
second.
The final component of the study is um a
an empirical study where we applied um
our assessment rubrics and data sets in
practice using the outputs of MEDPOM 2
as a proof of concept study. Um an
important part of this was to understand
how groups of raiders with different
expertise and perspectives uh might
evaluate outputs differently. So things
that we do in this evaluation um again
of MedPM 2 is we apply rubrics to the
equity medqa data set and three other
data sets um with uh three raider groups
physicians equity experts and consumers
or patients. We do pair-wise comparisons
between med 2 and medal and med 2 and
physician written answers. We assess
interrator reliability on a subset um
that mix adversarial and non-adversarial
data. We do a pilot study with
counterfactual rubrics and data sets.
And we analyze uh the demographic
effects um with consumer raiders.
Um, and in general, I mean,
I'm just going to I'm just going to
highlight a a few of the key results and
and takeaways from from from the
empirical study. Um, okay. So, first, we
report
a much greater rate of bias in model
outputs than previous work um for the
data sets in common. So, again, there
were some data sets that were already
collected in other papers. We also run
this on them. Um, and we see more data
set resulting more more bi sorry more
bias resulting from using our rubrics
than than those data sets were found to
have in the previously studied papers.
Um,
so this suggests that the rubrics work
in the sense that um they they prime
readers to to identify biases that that
weren't seen with previous versions of
the rubric that were used in these other
papers. Um, we also find a greater rate
of bias um reported with the adversarial
data sets over non-adversarial data
sets. Um and this indicates that the use
of the data sets are um actually
enriched for questions where the model
is more likely to produce bias outputs.
Um we find that the use of multiple data
sets, rubrics and raider groups is
useful for identifying different aspects
of of bias. Um and then lastly, we we
still think that this approach
underestimates bias since it's a post
hawk analysis.
Okay. So, so that that basically
concludes what I have to say about our
health equity toolbox. Um, again, for
more information about the health equity
toolbox, we have a nature medicine
paper. You can look at it. Um, I'm going
to now focus on a particular data set in
the health equity toolbox called the
tropical and infectious diseases data
set. Um and so
here we'd like to understand how large
language models like Gemini perform on
the diseases the tropical more
globalized diseases like malaria um and
what contextual information like
demographic attributes or location
information impact model performance.
tropical diseases are focused on because
they're less likely to be um common
demographically and geographically and
least likely to be captured in commonly
used training data sets. Um so in the
development of a data set that can
capture underrepresented properties
associated with these diseases, we focus
on four different aspects. Um the first
is specific properties of the disease
itself and we find that in authoritative
sources. Um the second is the
symptomology. The third is the location
and the last one is any different risk
factors. These are all contextual pieces
of information that we want to capture
that we think will lead to like a good
diagnosis um in a globalized setting.
risk factors might include lifestyle,
age, sex, things that are associated
with the disease. Um, and so in this
way, either by manually curating or
generating these details, we construct
our trans data set.
Okay, so here's an example for
tuberculosis.
Um, authoritative s sources are searched
and symptomology is added to a seed
prompt.
Then geographical prevalence is assessed
and a location of focus is selected.
This is if we're generating a prompt,
right?
And then lastly, we search for risk
factors related to tuberculosis. So here
we can see differing occurrences based
on age and sex with increasing
prevalence in men in middle age groups,
right? And so that's something that we
want to take into account when we
generate our our prompt for
tuberculosis.
Okay. So here's an example for sleeping
sickness. Um we have um different
attributes being discussed 28-year-old
male. We have general symptoms. Um so
they have fever, severe headaches, etc.
We have specific symptoms like they've
developed a skin rash and show signs of
confusion.
Um we have the location of high
incidence. Um the patient the patient
lives in the particular province they
do. I'm sorry I'm going to totally
butcher the name of that province. Feel
badly. Um and then um their lifestyle
factors that they discuss like they own
domestic animals.
And so this in general is sort of the
schema that's used for developing the
prompts that that we study that we
generated um for the trends data set. Um
and so the person enters their their
demographic information, their um
a young woman from DAR. Um they enter
any risk factors that they have, right?
So this could be that they slept with
mosquito nut without the mosquito net.
Um and then they enter all of the
symptoms that they're currently
experiencing. So fever, fatigue, sore
throat, etc.
So the next part is going to take a
while and I apologize. It actually takes
a long time in real life too. This is
not it's not just this video. Um yeah.
Um okay. So then they try to use that
that inputed information and they're
going to generate a summary and a
diagnosis of what disease um what
disease they're experiencing.
Um and so basically oh here we go. So
here's a summary of the of the case
file, right? So it takes that
information, it generally generates a
prompt and it says um
what disease what tropical disease the
patient might be experiencing. It gives
some confidence measurement around that
and then you can see um like an
an incident an incidence graph in the
world where it talks about what the
incidence of the particular disease
might be. Um, and so I don't show a lot
of head-to-head comparisons with Gemini.
Um, for those again you can look in the
paper. Um, but
uh
we will just take it for granted that
this is substantially improved. Okay. By
I mean sorry we won't take it for
granted. You can look in the paper. It
is substantially improved. I have plots
there.
Um but and you can see you can see you
can see the improvement that it makes.
Okay. So um again like the these large
language models are have historically
been quite bad at at more globalized
diseases and so this is um an attempt
that we made in order to try to try to
improve them. Okay. Um the next one that
I'm going to talk about is the largest
study to date on uh on African
healthcare. Um I think you know this
paper was published a month ago. So I
guess since since a month ago um and it
collects a different kind of data uh
called the Afromed QA data which I'll
get into in a second. Okay. So that
there's an Afromed QA consortium that
people on my team put together. Um it
includes Google research but it also
includes a whole bunch of um a whole
bunch of uh organizations in Africa like
Sasanki Biotech and Masakane. Um it
involves funders from all over.
Um and the form of this data set um is
going to be something like this, right?
Where you have um um like a bunch of um
questions like those found on medical
board exams where a situation is posed
and then there's like a multiple choice
response. So there's there's an example
here, but this is like med QA is like
often like something used as a prompt
for uh medical situations with um with
large language models, and this is no
different, but specific to the African
context. Um so we have a 2-year-old boy
presenting with a history of vomiting.
So the question is the best next step is
what? And then you see multiple choice
answers.
Um, and so the LLM answer and rationale
is is given and then rated by experts
along relevant axes such as quality um
or um how well it reflects an African
context.
Um and you can see that that that rating
sheet there
and that's collected together and that
makes up the aformed QA data set. Um so
both the data sets of the d the trends
data set of prompts and the aphromed QA
data sets are data sets generally that
that in that capture more globalized
um more globalized uh behavior for large
language models um in healthcare. Um,
and you can find out more information on
them on the Google research blog or by
contacting Mercy Asidu who is the person
again on my team um, who has really been
instrumental in this work. Um, I should
say the Afromed QA data was both used
um, in order to benchmark MedeMema which
is Google's current medical LLM. Um, and
so you can find it in the um the data
sheet for that model, but it also won
the um best so social best, let me get
this right, the best social impact paper
award at ACL um and was published
a month ago at ACL.
Okay. So now switching gears a little
bit um I want to talk about um about
pregnancy intelligence which is the work
that we're doing relating to wearable
devices
um
and time series data uh for maternal
health prediction. um Mercy and Bon
Bonaventure Bonaventure Dell he's a
student at MA um worked on this um quite
a bit um and so I'm going to talk about
here okay so uh in this part of the talk
I'm going to focus on wearable data as a
digital biomarker um time series data
set wearable data gives time series data
sets uh which are measured from wearable
devices that you find uh via pixel
uh Pixel Watch or via Fitbit. Um and
they present um very extensive
longitudinal passively collected data
that can potentially enable discovery of
unknown biomarkers. Um and so there's a
growing interest in using this wearable
data for health agents and foundation
models um because they generate
proactive insights and personalized
health responses provided by large
language model based agents for health
and they create time series foundational
models that they allow the creation of
time series foundation models that can
scale up uh multimodal LLM use. Okay. So
um here sorry um so wearable data can be
of great uh use for maternal health.
It's passively collected uh longitudinal
data that can potentially enable better
understanding of pregnancy and
postpartum journeys um and the discovery
of new biomarkers for maternal health um
and give personalized pregnancy and
postpartum insights.
Um Google or formerly Fitbit has one of
the largest data sets of wearable data
collected during pregnancy and
postpartum. This is on about 40,000
women. Um there's infrastructure that
allows for rapid prototyping and
experimental launching of LM verticals.
Pregnancy um presents significant
changes in biometrics um which can
differ from pre pre- pregnancy baselines
and recommendation systems. Um and
agents need this knowledge to provide
accurate insights. Um we're working
towards the development of a maternal
health sub aent um with the ability to
improve accuracy of Gemini activity and
sleep recommendations.
Okay. So in particular in our work we
were interested in predicting postpartum
mood disorders from multiple collected
time series. So the rest of this part is
going to focus on mood disorders. Um
mood disorders are very very common
during and after pregnancy. Um and
they're underdiagnosed and undertreated.
So one in eight women experience
postpartum depression. There's a three
times higher likelihood of suicidal
behavior. Up to 80% experience some form
of baby blues. And 85% are untreated
with low screening rates.
Okay, so we posit that the biometric
data that we have can be used to make
predictions of postpartum mood mood
disorders um and show us what digital
good digital biomark biomarkers might
look like. Um we aim to leverage the
large amount of maternal health data
that we have to improve on studies that
have pointed to this being a promising
direction. And so there are many many
studies that have pointed to this being
a promising direction, but they've
lacked potentially in numbers um or a
focus on particular outcomes.
Um and here's an example of the kinds of
uh time series that we're using to model
mood disorders. So for example, heart
rate and step count. Um
so um as you can see there are very uh
like obvious differences um in these
time series between women with and
without mood disorders. You can sort of
eyeball a lot of these plots whether
it's resting heart rate or step count
and sort of like easily distinguish the
differences in time series between the
two groups.
Um and so here you can see uh some of
the demographics for the particular set
of people who are uh who our data points
in our study. Um so it's almost entirely
white women. Um and almost entirely
between the ages of 30 and 40.
Um and how long their pregnancies lasted
early term versus fullterm. um as well
as high rates of depression, anxiety and
sadness.
Okay,
so this is the data processing and
machine learning pipeline that we used.
Um so first we narrowed down to a co the
cohort uh um to pregnant women who we
have enough data on. um we wanted to
make sure that like we could reliably
sort of try to do prediction um a full
schematic of the inclusion exclusion
criteria given in the paper if you're
interested. Um
and so we then create features that are
relative to the person's baseline rates.
Um and this was very important. So like
what is their pre-reg resting heart rate
versus their pregnancy resting heart
rate. Um and we found this to be really
useful for prediction.
We divide the data set into testing and
training cohorts.
And then because some of the classes are
underrepresented and this is really key
um compared to others, we upsamp
upsample the underrepresented classes
through synthetic data collection. So in
particular, we use a uh custom time GAN
um in order to do this.
So again upsampling
and this goes back to model training. Um
so we use all the data we train the
model and use the results to interpret
features and subgroup analysis.
Okay. So and we were able to
successfully do quite a good job of
predicting mood disorders from from this
methodology from this pipeline. Um and
so you can see some of this in the
bottom row of plots. Um
the model that we ended up using was a
time um GAN that's a generative
adversarial network specifically for
time for generating time series data um
with some modifications most importantly
um a non-stcastic latent space mapping
for um upsampling the less well
reppresented classes.
um for more information about the work
or on this methodology um basically I'll
refer you to Bonaventure um again at Ma
who's the first author.
Okay. So we can also get a sense of the
importance of each feature used in the
prediction of mood disorders. Um so here
we see that deep sleep is important in
anxiety and sadness uh mood disorders
whereas light sleep and and REM sleep is
more important in depression. Um we can
also see on the right hand side that if
we project the data down to two
dimensions mood disorder clusters
separated out and are quite
distinguishable
hopefully again to the eye.
Okay. So, the last thing I want to talk
about um is the expansion of this work
to underrepresented classes because um
the data that we've focused on so far
here in case again you didn't notice it
when I showed you was is that it's it's
almost all on well-off white women. Um
and so we really we really really want
to be able to run this on other groups
of people. Um so we're running a study
in Ghana in partnership that Mercy Mercy
is from Ghana. Um, and so there are some
great connections with the University of
Ghana there. Um,
and we are using u mobile devices, some
of which I've been working on for for
quite a while and wearables uh on women
there so we can eventually make these
kinds of predictions with them. And we
call this study the Akoaba study. Um, we
want to open source our tools um for
other researcher other researchers to be
able to conduct similar similar studies
and improve the representation of
minority women in um in in the work that
they do.
Okay. So there are several important
questions um to be considered as we move
towards making predictions in lower and
middle inome countries. So how might the
metrics change? what are the impacts of
demographics and geoloccation in
general? Is this even feasible for
LMIC's? Um, as well as things that we
can measure that weren't necessarily
available in the previous data set that
we had access to. So like is there a
positive behavior change um from the act
from the activities of our mobile phone?
Um and so uh the passive signals
collected are given here in this bubble.
Um and they include things like sleep,
activity, heart rate, variability, etc.
Um again, all off the wearable.
Um and so there's also data that's
coming from the mobile the mo the set of
mobile activities itself like the
surveys um as well as clinician reported
outcomes. Um so this would be like
preeacclampsia or hypertension and then
also their observation about birth
timing like was it was the baby born
pre-term or at term
and clinician reports also include pre
and post study analyses um which include
health history as well as demographic
information um that might be relevant to
the setting. It's actually um the
clinician, one of the clinicians that
we're working with is like really keen
to get some of the health history
information which might represent things
like induction which are important to
the setting.
And then lastly, here are some snapshots
of the app that we developed that are
going to allow um the remote collection
of some of this data. So these are just
sort of like the opening screens for the
Akawaba study. um intro and overview and
these are some screenshots um for like
the main screens dashboards um etc. So
um we've started the study in Ghana and
we've enrolled our first 40 participants
but we have continuing enroll enrollment
and we hope to um get more patients
involved and to have more results and if
you know anybody in Ghana who might be a
good participant for this study, please
please refer them. Um but uh we hope to
have more results to report back to you
soon. Okay. Thank you.
[Applause]
Thank you, Katherine. That was that was
fantastic. Uh I'm sure we have a bunch
of questions. We could I could probably
get you started on a few. I was I was
very curious about the about the policy
aspect of it in terms of actually
implementing it. You know, for example,
how does one u establish deployment
thresholds? uh if you have if you have
for example a bias of what 13%
recognized by your evaluation system uh
are there thoughts around what that who
would then decide if 12% is too high um
are those things that your group has
been thinking about?
>> Yeah. No, it does. It it makes it makes
a lot of sense. Um, it's not I think my
group has been thinking more about how
to accurately report this as opposed to
like how to make the decisions about
what to deploy. That's right. Because
like policy and and particularly in an
industry setting is like often
controlled by other people, right? And
so there are like execs who make that
decision and that is not necessarily
really a decision and there are policy
people who are specifically employed to
do that. So there's like in in this
setting like a real breaking up of
different job roles, right? Um and so
our job is more sort of like on the
science information end and less on the
like yes, we're going to do this or no,
we're not going to do this kind of end.
>> Yeah, that that totally makes sense.
>> We have our own personal thoughts, but
>> yes, of course. Uh and in terms of the
role of uh in terms of the ability for
you to go back to the uh to the training
data like are you able to to to uh
identify the biases uh going back to the
training data uh and see whether you can
eliminate that at the training data
stage or is that is that hard
fundamentally?
>> Yeah, I mean that's a good question. I
mean, I think I think to some degree we
could do that, but like what
I mean, I guess it's a good question
about like if we were to completely
retrain some of these models, right?
Like do this analysis, eliminate data. I
think this is something that like
pre-training teams are looking into
quite a bit. Um, but I think it's
relatively unknown generally in
generative AI land like what exactly the
removal or addition of specific data
points gets you right like there's not a
not a fixed answer to that but I mean I
think that is an area of like further
research or can we do some kind of like
influ like influence discovery right
like influence functions can we learn
the right influence functions to detect
like like what data point might actually
be making it behave in a certain manner.
I think that would be would be really
really interesting to find out.
>> And the six dimensions that you
identified, have there been any thoughts
on whether you could potentially bake
that into a loss function uh itself such
that you can eliminate bias in the
model?
>> Yeah. function or is that not
>> No, I mean that is interesting and and
we're we're trying to do work where
we're coming up with evaluation
procedures and you're right I mean act
in order to this is not for collecting
data where you have clinicians like in
mind but if you're trying to do
something automated you're right you
need to be able to come up with a metric
um and we're in the process of trying to
work with people it to do it but like I
I don't know that um it it certainly
wasn't done for this work if that makes
sense.
>> Makes
>> sense. Great. Well, I'll hand it over to
the audience uh if you have questions
going in.
>> Oh, so I work in the cancer program here
and something that I'm thinking about
patient stratification in terms of
patient populations uh is always
uh clinical trials,
right? because there are a lot of people
who are might be eligible for certain
kinds of clinical trials that are not
necessarily taking part in them if they
might want to. uh and there's, you know,
there are efforts in expanding this and
I'm wondering if you have thought about
ways to use these kinds of uh
advancements in um understanding where
these kinds of biases come from to help
do some kind of matching in that regard.
>> Yeah. I mean, okay. So are you like
thinking like when do I know if I've So
one for example one question that say
like people at Fitbit or or other places
have been interested in quite a bit is
like how do I know when I need to
collect more data on a particular kind
of demographic. Is that the kind of
thing that you're thinking of?
>> Sort of but also in reverse where like
if you have someone who is eligible
maybe for a number of different uh
clinical trials
>> Oh,
>> how might you want to sort where they
might go?
>> Yeah. based on availability and what
kind of demographics they might need and
that kind of thing.
>> I think that there are a whole bunch of
really good questions around I I hadn't
even thought of that until now, but yes,
you're right. You have a person actually
and it's not the other way around
necessar I mean to some degree they can
go out and collect collect more data,
but you're right. Often you're presented
with a person and you need to know where
to sort them. Um,
I think that there are
I mean I mean the short answer is going
to be no, right? Like I haven't I
haven't done that. Um, like the the the
opposite of that is something that I've
been trying to do for a long time. Um,
the way that you've cast it is again
like something a little bit novel to me
but also makes sense. Um, I think that
there's a lot of room here for the
improvement of clinical trials in
general, right? Like in general, I mean,
the best I can say is to make a plug for
in general, the people who make up like
all of our clinical trials should be
being determined through methodology
like this. There's there's no reason
that that that that shouldn't be
happening, right? like you should be
able to like like do all kinds of like
assessments where you're like, "Okay, I
think that this particular like there
are also sort of like pair-wise things
where we're running into too many drugs
needed to be triled head-to-head with
like you know that then then we can
actually pay for and staff, right? And
we should be able to use things like
this in order to point us to promising
like clinical trials that we should be
running and running those." Um, why
that's not happening, I don't know. I
think I I I think it's it's a funding
issue. People who talk to me today are
not going to be surprised to hear me say
that. I think there's there's a real
funding issue out there. But but yes,
absolutely. You're correct that that
should be happening and it's not. I mean
in terms of like the particular
demographics and bias for for um for
clinical trials that are already being
run again I would love help at Google
like to be able to actually explore that
because I think it's super important and
actually really valued in a lot of
different contexts. Um, I think it's
actually one of the more important
questions facing Google right now in my
opinion because it applies not only to
like medical clinical trials but even
things like um
again not sure which way it goes but
like things like when do we know when
we've like collected enough data on a
particular language to be able to do
like Google translation well and things
like that right like even outside of a
clinical trial setting. Um but but yeah,
I mean lots of lots of open questions
there and they're great and I highly
recommend doing more research in this
area.
Um thanks for the really interesting
talk. Um is there like a fundamental
difference between say like model
fairness and model generalizability
beyond just fairness being more about
like sensitive attributes? So is do
would you do you go about those problems
differently or are they basically like
very similar? It's just as I was as you
were going through the talk that's kind
of what I was just wondering.
>> Yeah. So I think in a lot of work a lot
of our work we treat um a lot of model
model fairness questions as questions
which can be derived by looking at sort
of like the the causal structure around
sensitive attributes. Um, is there
something particular that you had in
mind that that can't be linked to an
attribute that you think should be No.
Um, so I think in general we try to take
a lot of these questions around fairness
and sort of link them to attributes in
general. Like they don't have again they
don't have to be attributes of a
specific race or gender but to say there
are some attributes of this particular
class and we're going to look at those
and then we're going to use things like
false positive and true positive rate
gaps in order to identify when there's a
problem. Um
I think solutions are coming right like
but um but we can at least that's a well
well paved path for thinking about
identifying issues.
>> Uh thanks for the talk. This is really
thoughtprovoking.
uh how do you think about the
stochasticity in model outputs as it as
you're thinking about evaluating them?
>> Okay, so like sto Oh, so I'm trying to
think of which model you're potentially
referring to.
>> I guess it's maybe more of a holistic
question just sort of if you're saying
given X context, what does the model
output? The fact that it might not give
you the exact same output even with the
same input. I could be mistaken on
whether that's true.
>> No. Yeah. I mean, yes, it's definitely
true. Um
uh so
I think there's like some amount of
variability
inherent to all of this. That's that's
correct. Um, I think that if you think
about things sort of like in probability
distribution land, you're kind of saying
you think that this is modeled well say
like by by a particular probability
distribution. You could represent a
class with a probability distribution
and then you expect the variability to
fall within sort of like the variance
say like of that that specific form of
probability distribution. And I think
it's in that context generally that we
think about um different classes or
different variables
with from which we do this.
>> Yeah. Okay. I think we'll have to close
out now. Uh but Katherine's going to be
around for a bit more. Please feel free
to come over and have a chat. Katherine,
thank you once again.
>> Thanks so much. Thank you all.
>> Those excellent uh questions of the
Thank you.
[Applause]