Moore's law was an observation by Gordon
Moore that when you looked at the number
of integrated circuits you could put on
a computing device, that number was
doubling every [music]
year or two. More recently, in general
purpose computing, we haven't really
seen a lot of performance improvement.
You could argue that Moore's law hasn't
really kept up there. What we mostly
seen recently is what we call
accelerators where chips are designed to
do very specialized operations. AI being
kind of one of the biggest drivers of
[music] that. I think many of us could
not have anticipated the scale of
investments to [music] get the next
level of computing. The largest
companies in the world are very much
involved in this and so ultimately
limits are usually the scale of
investment. Find your MIT moment. Visit
learn.mmit.edu.