All right. How many of you work at
companies that develop or maintain
software? Anyone? All right. Or contract
out for the development of software.
Okay. So, we're
Silverthread and uh we've been around
for a while helping a lot of companies
and organizations analyze the health of
their software code bases and then
improve the health of those code bases.
Specifically, we've been applying MIT
and Harvard research to look at the
architectural health of those systems,
make economic cases for change and um uh
and then drive results. So, if you look
at this graph over here, most software
development projects, I don't know if
you any of you have experience with
this, but they might be a little late,
right? They might be delayed. They might
have some challenges and some of them
might fail. I don't know if any of you
have any of those experiences at all,
but but in but most people tell me that
if that you have a finite amount of
attention, resources, money to apply to
your projects and that and if they are
late or fail then you are wasting a lot
of your money. Um, we have worked with
companies that have good healthy systems
and we have worked with companies that
have
architecturally extraordinarily
challenged systems. And if we could
optimize um by helping people make
better decisions around what to keep,
what to improve because it's financially
rational or it's financially rational to
do so and it's technically feasible to
do so. And if you could, you know, for
the small number that you want to kill
those programs or or, you know, rebuild
them, if you could just make that choice
in an economically rational way, you
could probably double the rate of
innovation within your organizations.
And that's what we've seen uh over a
decade within the United States Air
Force and Space Force doing analysis of
the systems that they've
got. So we've got a product called
Kodmarai. It's based on the research and
development that we did out of MIT and
are now commercializing. The first
aspect of it we call discovery. This is
a tool that can help you analyze the
portfolio of applications that you have
within your organization or if you have
access to code devel of um systems
developed by others for you or on your
behalf you have to do some auditing
maybe you're doing mergers and
acquisitions you can analyze the health
benchmark it look at trending over time
and understand it multi-dimensionally
both technically as well as the business
implications so we can help you use
machine learning and AI to look at um
risk maintainability agility
productivity of your development ment
organization as a function of the
technical health of the code that they
have to understand and work in and
modify without creating bugs. On the
other hand, we also have um I guess the
history of silver thread is we we
started by um criticizing people's code.
People get defensive. Let's face it, if
you go in and you criticize people's
code, they think you're calling their
baby ugly. And so, as Silverthread
evolved, we developed this tool called
Codmarai Modernize, which isn't just
about calling your baby ugly. It's about
helping you give your baby a nose job,
right? So, how do we how do we help you
um systematically with a roadmap
transform your code bases from something
that's monolithic, hairball, furball,
spaghetti, whatever you want to call it,
into something that is a modular system
with controlled dependencies, good
hierarchies, good APIs, um and a
structured way of doing that in a
quantitative fashion where everyone can
audit it and the engineers have the
information they need. Um here's an
example. This is a portfolio from the
United States Air Force and Space Force
of hundreds of systems that we've looked
at. So you can see some are in the
green, some are in the red, some are um
in the middle in the yellow. Um and
we're doing uh predictions. We're doing
benchmarks both around the technical
health of the system. We can track it
over time and we're also looking at
metrics around the productivity of
developers, the defect density, you
know, things like that, things of
economic value that the business people
are going to care
about. Um, codmarai modernize is more
about how do you take your system and
structure it well? How do you um define
the architecture as your experts would
want it to be? And then look for
deviations. Like let's say you've got
someone with 20 years of experience
leading a project, but you hired a
summer intern and they start adding
things in bad places. You want the
person with 20 years of experience to
know that that's going on that day
instead of 5 years from now so that you
can prevent it and so you can remediate.
So partnering with us, the first thing
that I would I would propose is we're
looking for people who would be
interested in running code discovery. It
is a package that can be installed on
Windows or Linux inside your
organization and without any handholding
analyze as many code bases as you throw
at it. Do some benchmarking just see the
results, get a pilot. We'd be very
interested in working with people who
have one codebase that's really
important or lots of systems so that you
can see the difference on different
dimensions uh within them and then see
how that relates to how well those
projects are going. And on the other
hand, we've developed a lot of AI based
technology over the years, whether it's
graph theoretic, machine learning, you
know, statistical, you know, other types
of things that we've been employing, but
a lot of the new AI stuff that's coming
out, uh, can be applied and we'd be
interested in working with people who
are interested in that kind of research.
You know, how do you take a large scale
system, 20 million lines of code, tear
it down and rebuild it in a more
automated fashion? That's beyond the
current state-of-the-art, but it's
something that we're interested in
pursuing. So, with that, um, I'll take
any questions that you might have, but
we're going to have a table outside, so
I'd appreciate it if you would stop by.
Uh, you mentioned that it installs on a
Windows machine, but I'm just curious on
the logistics. So, you put it on a
machine here, and then you've got code
bases that may be running on maybe a
mid-range or a mainframe someplace else.
How does it get access to look at that
code? Our software application can be
installed on any computer inside your
organization. So, if you've got, it just
needs access to the code to scan it. So
as long as it can point at code should
have to bring down the code from
whatever platform it is onto that
Windows. So some of our customers ship
us code. Others of our customers are in
secure environments where for national
security reasons that code is not ever
we're never even going to see it. So
they'll install it in an airgapped
environment. So we can do everything in
between. Okay. Thanks.
No. Most people are squirly about their
source code getting out.
So they they get really upset about that
kind of thing.
Yeah. So can you talk a little more
about how you keep that integrity
software integrity for organizations
while uh using the AI generated code?
Oh, so um our tooling can run completely
self-contained for people in secure
environments like banks or department of
defense. Um it doesn't need to, you
know, typically our typical installation
will make a connection for a license
server, but that's not even required if
if you're in a highly secure
environment.
Okay, thank you then. Okay.