how are you you still have a little bit
of energy for me okay good good good
good I was actually listening to the
last presentation it was super
interesting so culture obviously is a
key thing um underpinning the things
that I'm going to talk about but I'm not
going to talk about culture but culture
is actually the enabler for for these
methods and
um maybe we can use AI to to help with
that but what I'm going to talk about
are how do we design
Solutions in this fiercely competitive
environment we all live in uh how do we
design for the unknown and unexpected so
I come from a program where we are
looking
at how we
might literally change the world if you
will so we get to work with students
from across MIT from labs and Studios
across MIT
who are really trying to engage some of
the most super complex problems we as
humans we have created for ourselves and
how do you do that we need to push the
boundaries of science yes we need to
push the boundaries of Technology yes
but we also need the tools and methods
of design in the mix and I'm going to
try to talk you through why we think so
I'm of course completely brainwashed by
this we've been looking into this for
years and um I was lucky enough to to
help create two Global Life Science
companies where this way of working was
in instrumental in the way we could
scale as fast as we did so now I get to
work with students and they do all the
hard
work so but it feels like we are
innovating in the eye of the storm right
the everything is changing as a much
much much faster Spa Pace than we ever
seen before and to be able to keep up
with the rate of change I can just see
it with chap DBT in the classroom I can
only imagine what it feels like for you
so how might we even begin to keep up
with these changes and um the problem
with super complexity is that it's very
very difficult to Define it's very
difficult to really figure out how these
systems multiple systems moving at the
same time but the Innovation opportunity
often lies right there it lies in the
periphery between multiple systems that
are
moving but as we know there's no one
discipline there is no one way of
solving these
problems and uh there's no single
solution to them but in we can though
begin to chop away at them chip away at
them and figure out a way in numbers how
we can actually do that so uh Accord
according to
McKenzie 75% of companies are really not
ready to to do that
75% and there are surveys coming out now
showing that um if if you talk to CEOs
they say 80% of them feel that they are
not ready to to engage with the world
the way it's moving so it's really a
high number and we also see it's not
going so well I don't know if youve seen
these types of numbers and Harvard for
instance there's a study a few years ago
done by Harvard showing that up to
95% of new Solutions fail to meet
customer expectations
95% of new
Solutions failing to meet users
expectations nine out of 10 startups
fail and out of those who survive only
one in 200 actually manages to grow at
scale think about this think about the
waste think about the waste in time
waste in money waste in resources and
the question is does it have to be this
way and here in the US they do surveys
of this all the time annually they they
look into why for instance startups Die
Why do nine out of 10 startups die and
the shocking thing is it's that almost
half of cases the founders say that they
had to close their doors because they
launched
something there was absolutely no need
for
it can you imagine you go through all
the Hocus Pocus and then on the other
end there was no need for it and you
begin to think about why is
that why is that what is driving the
innovator's mind to drive something all
the way to Market only to find out oops
when you're there also you can see on
the slide there are other data points
there about knowingly launching an
userfriendly
products um knowingly not including the
user in the process so when the The
Innovation hits the market there's no
way for the users to actually engage
with it but my favorite obviously is the
the one on the right there uh that
almost 25% of them dis blame their
team it's just my team's fault so uh of
course team is very important so I
shouldn't be joking about it but the the
ugly truth is that a lot of these
mistakes actually can be avoided so I
brought you a little
picture so this would be the typical
Innovation process as you can see we go
we get an idea we're so excited about it
you and your grandmother absolutely love
it and you stay in the basement and
you're working on it working on it
working on it either in the lab or the
studio or the basement and then only to
find out when you are in the
marketplace that there is no traction
there's nothing happening there's no one
that actually needs
this and as you know when you're out
there it's very very very difficult to
go back and we call it a very scientific
term for this called the
squiggly so this is the squiggly you
don't want want to do this quickly at
the end of the process you want to do
this thing early on you want to do this
in the safety of your lab or safety of
your office or safety of your studio
where you can do all these
experimentations
iterations in the safety of pen and
paper if you will so this is where
design comes in because design gives us
the freedom to test and retest to design
itself I'm not talking about the design
of an object you know I'm talking about
the act of Designing the ability to make
decisions through continuous iteration
and problem
solving and uh by doing that up front
what we see here is that eight out of 10
actually manage to to grow and scale and
launch so there's something that happens
here that can
so we can avoid a lot of the the palls
that we have
so the way we look at it and why we
think design needs to be right there
next to technology and science is that
there's no mathematical formula alone
that can capture all the complexity of
the human mind and all our emotions our
cultural viability and all these things
that's why we need a task of design in
the mix
[Music]
and one way of doing it is to try to
Envision the
future and then work backwards from
there but it's not that easy because as
we know the rate of change is not linear
it's very very chaotic it comes in spur
but then it also goes back and forth
back and forth back and forth back and
forth so it's very very difficult to
understand and know where to play but if
we can do that if we can flow with
complexity rather than fighting it then
that creates certain type of resilience
in your organizational culture but also
in your company as a whole so the way we
do it if you think about it how do you
deal with complexity today how are we
trained since we were in elementary
school to G engage
complexity you think about it just a
sack how did did you do that and how do
you do it
today most of the
time we break it down into manageable
chunks right and we try to solve one by
one by one by one by one and we hope
that the future is still there when we
finally get
there so but in fact this is actually
limiting our Innovation opportunities
greatly because we are making the
choices fewer and fewer and fewer and
fewer from the
beginning so we might be missing the
most critical pieces which is actually
contradictory to Innovation and this is
kind of what it looks like
so we believe that we can do ab C D or
PPA or whatever this is we can break it
down and we can go one by one one by one
one by one and eventually we got this
but in reality what happens is that this
is what it's going to look like when we
finally get there even by engaging
complex systems everything else
changes so even just touching the field
will create a chain reaction so how
might we survive in this Pond how can we
flow at the same rate if this is not the
right way going
forward and
um that's why we believe we can we can
design for this we can create a process
for this so when we talk about design
think process think problem solving
think process of
discovery and there are multiple
multiple ways tools and methods that
design has that allows you to do this
and if you think about design it's very
very different from an analytic
process it allows you to kind of bounce
between fantasy and data fantasy and
data what was the last time you can
actually think fantasy in your workplace
it's like when could you be in la la
land a little bit uh but as we have way
too much data or in many cases no data
we have to be able to create we have to
be able to imagine what this could be so
bouncing between fantasy and data allows
us to be more daring it allows us to be
more elastic in the way we innovate so
it actually helps us get to where we
need to go faster so we do all this
quickly first and then we can actually
go faster so in way applying design as
you solve super complex
problems is a very practical approach
but is also very creative so it's not a
number crunching mechanism you also need
a dash of creativity in there if we are
going to solve any of the complex
problems we've faced such as climate
change Injustice urbanization all these
big problems there's no one
solution The Innovation like I was
saying lies usually somewhere in between
and how are you going to get there if
you eliminate all your options in the
beginning so how can design
help we can design
help we have been doing research on this
for the last few years and
um we've talked to people who walk the
North Pole we talked to people who run
nuclear power plants we've talked to
designers of every corner of the globe
and we kind of ask them how do you do
this how does this work and out of that
work with good help of AI I mind you uh
there are three kind of main principles
that mer merge and um the first one is
when you're facing a super complex
situation maybe inside your own company
or maybe in the world the first
principle is we kind of have to
surrender to
it we have to surrender to the fact that
um every single problem is cont textual
meaning it is different in any given
context and this is where design comes
very strongly in because any designer is
trained to be very comfortable with
ambiguity very comfortable with going in
circles but more importantly being very
comfortable with direct user engagement
we can use a lot of data but there is
something in this human interaction
there's something when actually being
there observing what's happening on the
ground so the first principle is this
every every time we engage super complex
problems it has to be contextual we have
to have the humility to say I don't know
anything I'm going to discover
everything and that is tough especially
in a space that we think we know super
well so contextual is is number one
number two only at Mi T you would call
interdisciplinary
polyic so so to you have to be a
polymath meaning every single engagement
process has to be
interdisciplinary or
multidisciplinary or
polyic meaning that we cannot solve it
alone so the context is very very very
different it's very very fluent so it
means that the people on the team
working on your solution have to be
polyic they have to be able to come from
different uh Industries different parts
of of your organization or different
parts of life even having your customers
inside the
process and I'm lucky enough to serve on
on Boards of companies that are doing
amazing Innovation work and they bring
in their customers they are actually a
part of the process and it's called
designing with people instead of saying
designing for
people
so make sure you're prospecting for
knowledge wherever you can find it so
that's number two and number three is
the one that absolutely the enemy of
anybody who who really likes methodical
processes and that is emergence meaning
we have to have the patience to wait for
the solution to actually emerge through
the
process and for me it was really really
really difficult to learn how to do that
because you are trained and I come from
business school initially so my PhD is
from the London School of Economics so I
was trained to go from a to be as fast
as I possibly
could but in reality when has your first
idea ever been your best idea think
about that has your first idea idea ever
been the best idea I dare to say no it's
through the iteration and continuous
testing against the vision that you have
for this and your understanding of the
context that actually
yields the right solution so it
literally emerges through the process
and it's a combination of multiple
different data points multiple different
ideas that eventually after testing and
testing and testing
merge into something that you would call
a preferred
solution so design gives us this Freedom
it gives us this freedom to experiment a
little
bit to make sure that we can throw
spaghetti at the wall a little bit to
make sure that when we're engaged in
super complexity that even if we are
very reliant on data we are not reliant
on data
alone but we know what to do with the
data and then how we can bounce between
the fantasy and the data as we need to
and the way to do that is to apply these
principles of design so this is kind of
your job if you are in Innovation this
is kind of your job and this is why they
pay you so much
so so if you take a look at this
so any Innovation idea that involves
technology for
instance we cannot only think think
about the technology we have seen how
that ends so we really need to think
about the human in the equation can this
technology of course like I said before
we are pushing the boundaries of of uh
technology we're pushing the boundaries
of Science and a lot of things coming
out of MIT they do not have practical
application until 20 30 40 years from
now even but for those of us who are
kind of
applying in the near future future if
you will we really have to do this we
have to understand the human need what
is called the functional needs and the
emotional needs of people to understand
how might the technology actually help
meet those needs so we have what is
called problem solution fit but just to
make it a little bit more
difficult we also have to have nature in
mind because we also see in how that
goes when we just think about human
needs we have completely destroyed this
planet because we have been obsessed
with fulfilling human needs so we have
to think about nature so as we weave
this web of Technology human needs and
nature you also have to make it work
financially so how can that be done and
this is a process of iteration as you
can see you cannot just come out with
this idea and say I got it this is a
very methodical process but it's also
very different from the stage Gates
processes the menu of you know in
Industry where you kind of pass through
certain stage gauges as you innovate
this is very much a live
process and on top of it what you do
today is very very different from what
you could do a few decades ago so what
we did in the 70s or the 80s we cannot
do
today so all of this is very sensitive
to time place context time place context
because we really need to become an
expert in the context in which we
innovate and if we can do that this
becomes much much much more easy and it
looks like this if we had to
crosssection of our regular Tuesday this
is what it would look like because we
are trying trying to bring together all
these different data points all we're
prospecting from knowledge all over the
place to really try to figure out and
test test test test test test through
prototyping through quick even pen and
paper exercises or quick modeling to see
which of these combinations
actually best meet the future that you
envision when that problem is either no
longer there or if that problem problem
can be
mitigated and
eventually we come to a point where
there might be a solution or there might
be a few
Solutions and that's one thing was very
hard for me also to learn is that every
time you do this there's no one solution
there might be multiple Solutions we
just have to be flexible enough to try
and go and find
them and
um this is what we call choreography
it's literally choreographing a path
forward the least path the path of least
resistance if you will so you try to
figure out a way where is the path where
we have the harmony of Technology human
nature and you can make some money doing
it at the same time
so just thinking about it in those terms
makes it easier to do just see it
visually
makes it easier to
do but it requires a lot of patience but
this can happen very fast this can
happen in a matter of minutes this can
happen in matter of hours this can
happen in matter matter of months just
depending on your the scale and scope of
what you're trying to
do so the sign gives you this freedom to
explore that's kind of what we the way
we talk about it because it really is a
process of discovery
and we are all designers you're all
designers after years of schooling it
has kind of been beaten out of us in a
way because we have become more rational
more rational more rational more
rational as we go but now when the world
is no longer rational we need to go back
find some of that creativity find some
of that ability to
experiment in a more free context if you
will but the first step is really trying
to understand the context and becoming
the expert in your context but it is an
iterative process and it enables you to
really create this problem solution fit
if you understand what are the needs you
need to
fulfill the functional needs and the
emotional needs then whatever solution
you're creating you can create a
solution that is not over engineered we
don't have too many belts and missles or
under engineered meaning there a gap
between so by being able to understand
and create with people you actually have
a much much much better chance finding
that
lock where you might have one two or
even three potential solutions to
whatever problem you are
investigating then you just have to pick
one we're all so just kind of close it
off I think at the end of the day it's
about understanding the context it's
about having the humility to really work
with the people we aim to
serve so we achieve that
luck and all of this will help
organizations going forward and we do a
lot of work both with big corporations
and
startups and interestingly enough it's
some some of them really gravitate
towards this naturally others have to be
trained and they train themselves to
think in this way but at the end of the
day if you have this
combination you're more likely to
squiggle at the right time so you don't
actually have that problem where 50% of
new innovation actually
ends and
uh that is the secret actually is in
that process and in that mind
mindset so having said all of that I
think I'm ready for your questions
anything you have for me happy to happy
to answer any of your
questions on this Spa thank
you thank you so much for a great
presentation there are a couple of
questions okay start at the top could
you please give us a real example of a
previous project where you applied your
fluid context and super complexity
processes and what were the outcomes yes
okay great question so if I just take
maybe example of of teams that we work
with here the startup teams so there was
this one startup team that was looking
to solve a huge issue in urban settings
in Latin
America brilliant team and we're all so
excited about their solution we had gone
through everything and we had what were
the human outcomes where the societ
outcomes and what were the financial
outcomes and we're like this is it we
got it you know but then they go to that
place where they did their pilots
nothing is happening like nothing is
happening nothing is working and they
had initially identified like three
things that they believed was important
they had done interviews they had done
all kinds of observations they had done
a ton of research and they w Really
becoming an expert in this particular
context but they missed one major major
thing it has to do with human behaviors
so they went there to a particular place
and they lived there for a
year and they stayed with the people
they aim to serve and I'm not saying you
all have to do that but that's a very
good example of something that they
thought was number one on the priority
list apparently was at the bottom of the
priority list and what they thought was
at the bottom of the priority list but
at the top of the priority list so
simply going through it with the people
who actually um use and need the
solution and Al actually have them
design it with them completely change
the Chang the outcome and they're
now and they were voted one of the most
Innovative companies in Latin America
but took a while to get there but they
got there so the Squigly took a little
bit longer time than we anticipated but
they got there
eventually
nice okay let's move on to the next
question leaders who grew up through the
era of industrialization tend to find it
difficult to adopt design thinking
largely only in brainstorming but hardly
in envisioning and Innovation do you
have any advice yes great question so
for 30 years I've kind of been guilty of
using the traditional strategic planning
tools you know the SWOT and the planning
and the the the annual budgeting and all
that kind of good stuff and still we
need that don't get me wrong we need all
of that but can you think of a
company that was going like very
strong but suddenly completely collapsed
because they missed
a new wave of Technology coming their
way give me a
name Kodak what
else huh Blockbuster blueberry blue
Blackberry oh I still miss my
Blackberry what happened you know
someone said Google was now experiencing
the same thing with the latest Swift AI
I don't know about that but if you think
about what happens what happens when
this it's because when we do regular
budgeting when we do regular strategic
planning we are always looking at the
future by looking at the
past correct we're doing the like
three% incremental change or we're
adjusting for inflation and we're kind
of drisking ourselves to
death this is drisking we think we're
the risky because we are moving
incrementally you know
but in fact we can be caught with our
pants down
literally uh because we didn't see the
future coming so what we usually do when
we work with companies is that we
combine both tools of design not
necessarily design thinking design
thinking is a fantastic tool that came
literally brought design to the
Forefront of corporate decision- making
but this is the process of design the
tools of design whatever you want to
call it but but you have ways something
like what is called design futures for
instance it's a way for you to stand in
the
future and then plan your way back so a
combination of a
datadriven
drisking but then also having the
boldness to also dare to come at it from
the other
end that usually yields you know more
instead of these incremental
Innovations we get these radical
Innovations so we need both it's like
with so many things in life we need both
there not one or the other but both and
a healthy combination of both is
good okay let's take another question or
two on that note how can you
differentiate between a lack of Market
need and a solution that is simply ahead
of its time
this is about creating the creating the
market so I think it was Steve Jobs that
said that you have to get so close to
your customer that we know long before
they know what they
need
right
so there is a truth in this for sure
so the whole idea of becoming an expert
in the
context is not the ability for the
customers to tell us at least not the
way we see it that the customer tell us
what the solution should be the
customers or the users they are their
experts in their own
lives we are just observing that so when
we talk about being an expert in the
context you are lit literally observing
what's going on where are the needs and
where is that urgency because most
startup for instance they recognize a
need most corporate Innovation
recognizes there is a
need but what we fail is to find that
urgent pain point if you
will that people cannot live without a
solution to to go beyond the most
obvious needs down to these needs that
are unmet and people cannot articulate
that's where your expertise comes it you
map all of this stuff out but then Here
Comes Science and Technology and really
are responsible of creating the
solution so Henry Ford I don't know if
it's true or not but he's quoted to have
said if I had asked people what they
wanted they would have said Faster
Horses right what did they need to do
they need to go faster from A to B
correct or less smelly horse or I don't
know what they would have said but they
needed to go from A to B maybe they need
a little more Comfort or or whatever it
may be but at the time people did not
have any concept of a car the word
probably didn't even exist so how can
you see that so by studying people's
life understanding how people live their
life and figuring out where are these
urgent pain
points we can bring in science and
technology to really create the
solutions so that's kind of how we look
at this and by doing so you might be
creating
a whole new
market in the process of
it thank you Safa okay let's take one
one more question I have it up
here this is from
Enrique your view what is the
relationship between design and time how
free can you be when you are subjected
to Real World Financial operational and
strategic demands
yeah this is a million dollar question
question so whoever asked it maybe you
can help me answer
it so this is I think the most common
question especially in startups have
less worries around this because
startups are naturally iterative they
can they can pivot too fast or they can
pivot too slow uh but most of the time
they're just occupied with trying to
survive and trying to figure out the
solution but for those of us who also
live in the corporate
world this this is the most frequently
Asked question we
get because you guys have time
constraints you have budget constraints
and there is this notion that if we
innovate or we spend like
3% on Innovation 6% of innovation
automatically the compan is going to see
Revenue growth down the road this is
this kind of incremental investment in
Innovation um which def L works for a
lot of companies but then you have these
fluke incidences where there is
something that happens and you're
completely caught um so you have to be
able to do both but what I was saying
this
squiggly it looks like it takes a lot of
time but I can promise you it takes it
can take a very short period of time and
it certainly takes less time and it's
less expensive than discovering that we
launched the wrong thing
I come from the life science Industry
launching the wrong thing is dangerous
you know so taking the time before it
goes into the corporate Innovation
protocol or the gug stage systems that
we have taking the time to really ideate
quickly but then at the same time test
test test test test test test before it
goes into this long extensive uh
expensive
process uh is is the key here so it
takes more time it's more expensive not
to do it I would
say bafa thank you so much I think we're
going to thank you wrap there thanks for
a wonderful talk