Good afternoon, everyone.
Welcome.
So my name is Kaiming
He, and I'm currently
an associate professor
in the EECS department.
And I have been working on
computer vision, deep learning,
and AI for about 20 years.
And I'm fortunate enough to
see how deep learning AI has
completely revolutionized
computer vision,
and then later this
trend has been propagated
into many other sibling
areas such as language,
robotics, speech.
And then today, maybe
it's propagating more
to many other scientific areas.
So in the next 10
minutes, I want
to mainly convey two messages.
First, some of the most
successful generative AI models
today were heavily inspired
by some formulations
from science and physics.
And then in return, some of
the most successful practice
of gen AI today can make
significant influence
to some scientific problems.
So, first, we have been talking
about gen AI but mathematically
or theoretically, so what
is a generative model?
Well, conceptually
a generative model
is a model that maps
from one distribution
to another distribution.
Let's say you have some
noise distribution,
you have some data distribution,
and you train a neural network
to connect these
two distributions.
Then conceptually you can
sample from one distribution,
and then you can map
to another distribution
by this magical neural network.
So this is the
mathematical formulation.
And then this formulation
and a solution
to the generative
modeling problem
is heavily inspired by
some physical models.
Let's say diffusion.
So diffusion process can
be thought of let's say--
you drop an ink into a bottle
of water, and then after a while
the ink will diffuse
inside the bottle.
And then we can do
the same on an image.
We have an image and then
we gradually add noise
and then it becomes
completely the noise and then
if we describe this in
the distribution space,
if you turn a data distribution
into some noise distribution.
So we can also formulate this
problem as a probability flow.
Let's say you have a data
space, you have a noise space,
every single point
here could be think
of as the states in a very
high dimensional space,
and you can sample one
thing from the data space.
You can sample noise
in the noise space,
and then you can connect
them by a trajectory
let's say a straight line.
So very simple.
And then you can do
this many, many times
by just randomly sample things
from these two distributions,
and then conceptually you are
building a velocity field.
But this velocity
field looks stochastic.
It looks noisy.
We can marginalize it,
and if you do that,
it provides us a way to
connect every single data point
to a point in the noise space.
And then if we do
that, we connect--
we build a trajectory that can
connect an image to a noise map,
so conceptually very simple.
But the question is how can
we solve on this trajectory.
So conceptually this is an
ordinary differential equation
or an ODE in a very
high dimensional space.
And we want to find a solution
and represent it as z here,
which need to satisfy
this equation.
Then conceptually if we
follow this trajectory,
we can connect an
image to a noise map,
and usually every single
step in this trajectory
is done by a neural network,
which could be very slow.
So in one of our
recent work, we try
to address this
problem by learning
to do fast forward by a
single neural network.
So the core idea is very simple.
We just try to set
up another velocity
field which is conceptually
the average velocity.
So think about a starting
point R and an ending point
T. We can just set up the
average velocity, which is just
simply the integration between
these two time steps divided
by the time interval.
So conceptually very simple.
Then for some starting--
for some ending points
in the middle, the velocity
field would look like this,
and if we move the ending point
the velocity field will change.
And if we move the ending
point to the entire end
of the entire trajectory,
it will look like this.
Then conceptually, we can show
that this average velocity
field would be connected to
the original velocity field
by this equation.
And this equation can
provide us a principle
to learn a neural
network that can directly
map between two points
in this trajectory
without solving the ordinary
differential equation.
So if we can do that,
then conceptually we
can directly go from the
starting point of trajectory
to the endpoint.
This means we can sample a
noise, and if we go back,
we arrive at an image.
So this is how we can do one
step generation using the latest
generative models.
So these are some of the
images generated by this model,
and they look pretty good.
And if we zoom into
some of these examples,
here I compare the results
between solving the original ODE
versus the fast forward dunder
binary-- by the neural network.
Actually these two
images are not the same.
They look similar, but
they are not the same.
So they are similar at
the high level semantics.
For example, both are the fish.
Both are the fish
of the same kind.
They have a similar pose.
They are under the sea.
But if you look at
their tails, there
are fins and the
background, they
are different in some of
the low level neurons.
So actually these
are the properties
that we may desire for
many other applications.
That is we want to be
accurate at high level
at a macroscopic
level, and we also
want to tolerate some low
level and fine level neurons.
So this is what neural
networks are really good at.
Now it's time to go
back to the physics
and scientific scenarios.
So we have seen how some
of the most effective image
generative models are connected
to some of the physics models,
but the same idea
can also be applied
to some of these original
physics problems.
We want to solve
an ODE equation,
but we don't want to
do it numerically.
We want to learn a neural
network to do that.
So if we do that, we will
have a generation counterpart
of the simulation scenario.
So here is just a very
simple toy example
to illustrate the concept.
So on the left hand side is
the result of simulation.
On the right hand side
is a generative model
which can do fast forward.
So it is worth noting that these
two solutions are not the same.
You can notice that
they are different.
All the particles are different,
but the generative model
can preserve some of the high
level and macro level properties
so such as a wave in this case.
So this is really
a desired property.
So then actually the success
of these gen AI models
in computer vision
in image generation
can actually bring up
many good opportunities.
So first of all, it
provides us some machine
learning models that can model
the data with probability.
That means the model is not only
able to produce one solution.
It is also able to produce many
possibilities, many modalities.
So it also has the
ability to guess
what is the probability
of each solution.
And what's more, there is a very
good, very desirable property.
That is these
neural networks are
very good at preserving
and predicting
the high level, the microscopic
level, and sometimes
the mesoscopic level
attributes such as if I
want to generate an image,
I want it to be a fish.
So if I want to
predict whether there
will be a storm in
one week, I just
want to know there
will be a storm.
The model is able to tolerate
some of the finer nuances,
so it doesn't matter
whether the fish has
a fin or a tail in that exact
same way it doesn't matter what
exactly the texture
that the fish is.
So it's just like when I
try to predict the weather,
I don't need to the
exact temperature
or humidity of a certain
day or of a certain second.
So this is really the
power of neural networks
and some of the latest
generative models.
So now a little bit today's
most powerful neural network
and gen AI models are
good at preserving
the attributes of interests.
And if we can make
use of this property,
we can turn some of the
infeasible problems that
may take a long time to
simulate into some problems that
are very tractable.
And with that, this
concludes my talk
and thank you for
your attention.
[APPLAUSE]
Hello.
Thank you very much.
My name is Phiala
Shanahan, and I'm
very happy to tell you a little
bit about physical predictions
from physical generative AI.
So I'm a theoretical
physicist, and so the problems
I'm interested in
are physics problems.
How can we understand
the physical systems
that describe the
structure of matter
at the most fundamental
level and the interactions
of that matter?
A perspective I want
to leave you with
is that a physical system is
itself a generative model.
So you can think
about the collisions
in a particle collider, for
example, at the Large Hadron
Collider at CERN,
colliding particles,
and the output of that
generative model if you like
is what we observe in the
detectors after the collision.
From a theory perspective,
we can see the same thing
if we look at the
equations that describe
the measurement of some
quantum observable in nature.
So here I'm interested in
a quantum observable, F,
and on the right hand
side of this equation,
I can write that mathematically
as an integral equation where
I have a multidimensional
variable,
I apply F that
describes my quantum
observable to that
variable, and I
integrate with a
known probability
density inside my integrand.
By known, I mean that
probability density
is described by equations that
I can write down that describe
the structure of our universe.
Now a way of rewriting this in a
sampling or Monte Carlo picture
is to say that computing this
quantum observable F really
just looks like evaluating
my function on samples
that have been drawn with
that probability distribution.
So computing this boils
down to a generative model
generating samples according
to a known probability density.
So from this perspective,
this leads us
to physical generative AI.
So that is approaches
to generative
AI that include guarantees
of, for example,
asymptotic exactness that I
will generate samples according
to my exactly known probability
distribution that encode
properties of my physical
systems such as symmetries
and conservation laws and as we
saw in the previous talk that
exploit various
features of physics
to improve the
generative AI model.
So I'll mention Hamiltonian
mechanics in particular.
So asymptotic exactness
is in some sense
an unusual requirement
for generative AI.
So I'll belabor this
point just slightly.
What I'm interested in
here are solving equations.
And so there's only one
thing that any sort of AI,
generative or otherwise,
can do for me,
and that is solve the
equations faster or perhaps
even more importantly
solve equations
that I otherwise can't solve.
But the requirement of
exactness is still there
at the fundamental level.
If I'm solving an integral
and the answer is 2,
I had better get 2 no matter
what I do to solve my equation.
So we require mathematical
guarantees of exactness.
There is no room for
modeling approximations
or any sort of uncertainty that
we can't systematically improve
or remove in the limit say an
infinite number of samples.
So that means that we
have to create scenarios
where if the generative
AI algorithm is
poorly trained or
not optimized at all,
I'm still guaranteed to
get the right answer.
Presumably it will be very slow.
If it's well
optimized, I'm still
guaranteed to get
the right answer,
but it will be much
more efficient.
And that's really what
enables us to do new science.
We've had great
success with this kind
of provably exact generative
AI in applications
to, for example, lattice
quantum field theory
calculations in nuclear
and particle physics.
So this is starting from the
equations that describe matter
at the most fundamental level,
and solving them exactly
using numerical approaches.
One way of doing that
is via flow models.
You saw some examples of
generative models mapping
between probability
distributions in the last talk.
You can do a similar thing,
and with certain requirements
on those models,
you can guarantee
asymptotic exactness and
mathematically rigorous ways.
But there are challenges
in applications
like this that are not the
same as those, for example,
in image generation.
So you can see a comparison
here on the right hand--
right hand part of the
slide from your perspective
of quantum field generation
compared to image generation.
And what I'd like you to note
is that not only do we have
to guarantee asymptotically
the probability distribution
of my samples, which
is quite different--
an image is a good image or not
on its own merits, but for me,
it's the distribution of all the
samples that must be precisely
right--
but we have an extreme inversion
of a typical data hierarchy.
So in the quantum field
generation example,
we have something like 10 to
the 12 degrees of freedom per
sample, but I might have only
one or 10,000 samples available.
The ratio of those two numbers
is extremely different to that
in an image
generation case where
I might have samples
described by just millions
or billions of numbers, but
I might have many billions
of samples of those images.
So it is quite a
different regime,
which means that many of
the applications to things
like image generation can't
apply in this context.
Symmetries and
conservation laws,
again, look very different
in these kinds of settings
and need to be built into
the generative models
from the ground up.
So in this same
setting of applications
to what is called lattice
quantum field theory, so solving
particle and nuclear
physics from the ground up,
you do see symmetries that
have some analogs in the world
of images, such as rotations
and translations with boundary
conditions in, for example,
a four-dimensional space,
but we have other much
more complicated symmetries
that must be respected
by the models exactly.
So one example of that is what's
called gauge symmetry, where
I'd like you to imagine a grid.
In fact, it's a grid
in four dimensions,
so a hyper-cubic grid, where
on every edge I have a matrix.
And there is a
symmetry transformation
that will change a
configuration which
has the same matrix
on every edge to one
which has a different
matrix on every edge.
Every single edge is
different, but those two
are exactly the same from
the physics perspective
and must be generated with
precisely the same probability,
so deep internal symmetries
that the generative AI
algorithms have to respect.
I won't tell you how
you can achieve this.
I can point you to references
where this can be achieved.
So the last point here
on Hamiltonian mechanics,
we can also leverage as we
heard in the previous talk
various properties, the
structures of physical systems
to help develop new
generative AI algorithms.
For example, it's a
fact that following
some classical
mechanics trajectory,
so F equals MA, that we
teach in 801, 809, 8223,
you can, in fact, map
out any probability
distribution with the right
momenta in the system.
And so using these
kinds of structures
can help control
numerical artifacts,
it can help with scaling,
and it has applications
both in physics, where we have
these various requirements
and guarantees that
we need to preserve
and in applications beyond.
I've given you just
a tiny hint at how
generative AI can be applied
in the physical sciences.
There's also a very
good white paper
written by colleagues
in the NSF Institute
for Artificial Intelligence and
Fundamental Interactions that
really maps out
this virtuous cycle,
this feedback loop that
we also saw a little bit
in the last talk of the
challenges presented
by physical systems
and physics problems
that lead to new innovations
in generative AI that then lead
to new scientific discovery.
And so we've seen this
not just in my area
of nuclear and particle physics
but across the physical sciences
that building generative
models with various constraints
and requirements and conditions
and theory built in--
so we can call that
inductive biases--
as well as important
features such as uncertainty
quantification or
in the case I talked
about before asymptotic
guarantees of exactness
feeds back in to new
generative architectures that
lead to new discoveries both
in the physical sciences
and elsewhere.
So the idea I want
to leave you with
is that physics
problems like those
I was discussing present both
challenges and opportunities.
They can be in many ways
very different in nature
from other generative
applications.
I had a comparison of
say image generation
compared to quantum
field generation
with a hierarchy of data
scales was extremely
different and extreme inverse.
We have asymptotic guarantees
of exactness that are required.
We have complicated symmetries.
But building all of that
in to generative models
can lead you to New and
more efficient architectures
that then also have
applications elsewhere.
So this is the idea of
physical generative AI
to achieve robustness,
precision, interpretability
taking inspiration from the
fact that physical systems are
generative models, and so
building generative models
with the structures of
those physical systems
in is not only a natural way
to study physical systems
but can have
applications beyond.
Thank you very much.
[APPLAUSE]
Hi.
So we're going to switch gears
a bit and talk about music.
Yeah, in my past life,
I was a composer.
I wrote for a lot of my
friends, acoustic chamber music,
and then I started
doing computer music.
And then I realized,
yeah, there was
a lot of things
creatively I wanted to do,
but I felt like in terms
of my engineering skills
or my, yeah,
technological skills,
I felt like I wasn't there
to bring my vision and--
yeah, creative vision
into realization.
So I ended up doing a PhD
in machine learning and also
human computer interaction.
So today I'm going to talk--
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Oh, sound check.
Awesome.
So today I'm going to talk
about my recent eight year
of an arc going from the lab to
really bringing this technology
into the concert hall.
And what's really interesting
about this process,
it has been multiple years of
me finding my way is it really--
in additional to
thinking about music
as modeling all the
amazing structure,
it makes us think more
about human AI interaction
and what is needed to build
systems that can be partners
in this co-creative process.
So I'm going to start
from 2017 around June.
The transformer paper
appeared on the archive.
At the time, there was-- it
was really, really impressive,
but there was still a
lot of uncertainty about,
oh, what could this be useful
for and how far it be-- can
we bring it.
I felt it was the
perfect model for music
because in music we have
a lot of self-reference
within the piece.
That's how we build the meaning.
So I thought, yeah, we have
a chance here to really model
that long-term structure.
And how do people
come into this picture
is we wanted also to model
the pianist's expressive
interpretation of
the piece, so all
the micro dynamics
and timing, we
want to be able to model that.
So that is-- after a year
of getting it to work,
there was a lot of
architectural changes
we needed to do
to better align it
to the kinds of multi-level
structure that was in music.
And, yeah, at the--
when it started working,
we were seeing it
generate an amazing structure.
For example, here you see
these grayed out areas,
so this is a sample
generated from the model.
It's able to take these
motifs this, broken lines
tremolo gesture and repeat it
and add variation and really
build out an arc.
So I will play some of that.
So this is going to
be an animation what
you see in real time how the
model is thinking and looking
back as it's generating forward.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So, yeah, this was 2018.
Fast forward to this past year.
I've joined MIT, and
I'm really excited to be
both in the music department
in the engineering school.
And this has really allowed
us to work with musicians
on a day-to-day level.
So this past summer, we
recruited three MIT jazz
musicians.
And it has been really,
really phenomenal,
and it's been a lot of fun.
And I think there's this
unique situation where
these musicians are also
very technologically
savvy and curious.
So we were able to do a summer
long of co-design session
with them to really
take these systems
and see how we can bring
it into the concert hall.
And, of course, there's
a lot of challenges.
So previously Lancelot and
Perry from the Media Lab,
we worked on this system
that in collaboration
with a Grammy-winning
keyboardist,
very virtuosic, to
think about, yeah,
how do you make this happen.
How do you go from a language
model to an agent, a jambot
that the musician
feels like they
have some kind of
agency and partnership
over in this live setting?
So some of the
things we have to do
is think about
this improvisation
so we're all
improvising on the fly
and what kind of coordination
needs to happen in order
to make this duet work.
There's different
relationships, for example.
I can play something and
then you play something
or we want to be
playing together.
Yeah, in music, a lot is like
I'm playing different parts
in the piece.
And, of course, this took a lot
of system and engineering design
to get the system to be
embedded in this kind
of real-time setting.
It had to be able to listen.
It had to be able to
prompt and schedule
everything that was happening
seamlessly on stage.
So here I'll play you one of
the early encounters we had,
and you can see how
are these models
are still trained on piano
music where you tend to play
in the middle of the piano.
So you're fighting for
space a little bit.
So we'll see it.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
So this was our summer, yeah.
Doing this every week.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
I have the pedal for it.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, the model
doesn't how to pedal.
So naturally, the
piano is sitting
in front of the piano
pedals for the model.
So you see it there,
yeah, trying to trade
and trying to make
space for each other.
And then later on in--
a couple minutes later,
the musician found maybe
a little local optima
in terms of how to
interact with the model.
So let's see it.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Thank you.
So notice that the pianist in
this local optima setting was--
ended up just using one hand
because, yeah, the jam bot
was taking--
yeah, the role of the other
things that are happening.
So if we wanted to
do a three-hand piano
or a four-hand piano,
how would we do that?
So some of the things
we tried on the fly
is, yeah, what we gave
the pianist more controls.
For example, it could tell the
jambot which part of the piano
they want the jambot to be
playing or what kind of rhythm,
and at the same
time, we want this
to be a two-way conversation,
a two-way communication.
So the musician's
communicating something,
and then we want the model
to also let the musician,
yes, I'm going to be
playing around here
and this is the density of
what I'm going to be playing.
So I'm going to play
you this last clip.
It is-- it just happened
two Fridays ago where
we had this jambot in concert.
And this is a
musician Andrew Lee.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
I'll stop there.
Thank you all for listening.
[APPLAUSE]