Our
next speaker is uh Will Oliver. Will is
a professor in the department of physics
here at MIT and also the department of
electrical engineering and computer
science. He is also the director of the
center for quantum engineering. So let's
hear it for Will.
>> Well, good morning. Thanks. Thanks a lot
for the invitation to speak today and
I'm really happy to be here. Um I'm
going to give a overview of quantum
computing I guess quantum computing 101
um foundations frontiers future impact
and I would welcome your questions. Uh
so you know let's make it uh somewhat
conversational. Um before we get into
quantum computing quantum technology
generally addresses three primary
topics. the sensing of information, the
networking or communication of that
information from one place to another,
and then finally the processing of that
information. And if we had to give it a
definition, what is quantum technology
as opposed to just technology or
classical technology as we would call
it? Um quantum utilizes um quantum
mechanics at a fundamental level to do
the sensing, the communicating and the
processing.
And we use it because it can do it in
ways that are either practically
prohibitive or even impossible to do
with our current techniques. So quantum
enables that. Okay. Then and that's why
we want to do it.
Um before we get into quantum though um
I would like to talk about the last
century of classical electronic
computing and uh because as as you know
this quote from Mark Twain, right?
History doesn't repeat itself, but it
does often rhyme and and I think that we
can learn a lot from this last century.
Um, so I won't spend too much time on
this, but classical electronic computing
started with um the vacuum tube in 1906.
Was used for radio transceivers for
about 40 years, four decades before it
was finally used in a computer called
ENIAC that I'm sure we've all heard of,
uh, developed in the at the University
of Pennsylvania. The following year, the
transistor was invented in 1947. But it
wasn't until the 50s that we had a fully
transistor-based computer built here at
MIT called TX0.
But it didn't look like the computers we
have today. It was basically these
transistors soldered together to make
the computer. To get to what we have
today, we needed first the integrated
circuit. That was the late 50s. But even
with that, it wasn't until the 70s that
we could actually identify a chip, the
Intel 404bit processor,
um, that we would look at and say, "Oh,
yeah, that that that's an IC, an
integrated circuit." Even with that, it
wasn't until the '9s that we had the
Pentium Pro. I remember using Pentium
Pro, maybe some of you do, too. Um, five
bill or five million transistors, and at
the time that was fantastic. Um, and
advanced 30 years now to where we are.
Um, we have GPUs, TPUs, of course, CPUs,
still XPUs, all sorts of processing
units. Um, and if you look at the latest
uh uh Grace Hopper, all right, from from
Nvidia, it's um 200 billion transistors
on the chip. It's amazing, right? Two
chips. Each one has 100 billion
transistors. Um, and so you think, wow,
we're in a good place today, but it took
us 100 years to get here. That's the
point. Okay, why did I start with that
history? Well, because quantum computing
isn't yet 100 years old. It's actually
quite nent. It's recent. In the early
80s, people said, "Look, if you want to
simulate a quantum system, maybe we
should use another quantum system to do
that because quantum has a lot of
degrees of freedom." And uh it's hard to
simulate. It was hard then, it's still
hard today. By the '9s, people started
figuring out what you could do with a
quantum computer theoretically. For
example, Shor's algorithm attacks RSA
crypto systems. We care a lot about
that. Secure communication. But there
are many other applications. We'll talk
about those. Many of them developed in
the 90s, still being developed today. By
2000, we knew, okay, if we could build a
quantum computer, it will change the
world. And for the last 25 years, people
like myself and others, I'm a hardware
guy, we're trying to build these quantum
computers. Okay.
So, the takeaway is the following. Um,
quantum computing is real. It's
transitioning from a scientific
curiosity to a technical reality that's
happening right now. But the history
lesson here is that um advancing from
discovery to useful machines takes time.
It takes engineering. It's not going to
happen overnight. But who here would not
have wished that they or their parents
had invested in semiconductor technology
in the 50s and 60s, right? And look at
where we are today. All right. Um that
means you've got to be in the game to
play, right? and and so that getting in
the game is happening right now with
quantum. Uh there's a lot going on
worldwide. Uh I won't read everything on
here, but a lot of government investment
primarily for the national security
aspects and the economic security
aspects of quantum. But what's really
changed over the last 10 years, I would
say, is the number of companies that are
engaging in quantum. A few of them here
are building quantum computers. Most of
them here are the picks and shovels that
are going to go into enabling quantum
computers to be built. And then several
of them are figuring out how to use uh
quantum computers. And and we have an
industry membership group with our
center for quantum engineering where
companies come and work with us to
figure out how quantum is going to
affect their bottom line uh in the
future. And if you'd like to learn more,
feel free to reach out to me on that
topic.
Cubits, quantum bits, the fundamental
logic element of a quantum computer. Um
they come in two flavors natural atoms
and then what we call artificial atoms.
Natural atoms we all know because we
know the periodic table of elements. We
pick an element an atom. It has energy
levels and electrons and we use those
energy levels and those electrons to
represent quantum information. Okay. So
that those are the natural atomic
systems. Trapped ions, neutral atoms are
examples.
But we can also build electrical
circuits from inductors, capacitors and
junctions, Josephus and junctions and
assemble them into what looks like a
resonator. And it also has discrete
energy levels and in many ways looks
like and behaves like an atom even
though it comprises
Avagadro's number worth of atoms inside.
So we're not using the atoms there.
We're using the circuit which itself
behaves like an atom. And there's
actually a whole mendlay of table of
circuits that we can design that'll
afford us this property. So, so quantum
computers are built from natural atoms
uh that nature gives us of course or um
artificial atoms circuits that we build
that mimic that behavior.
Okay, two slides. How's a quantum
computer different? One um we can do a
compare and contrast with a classical
computer. Classical computers are
transistors. a bit. It's either on or
it's off. Current's flowing or it's not
flowing. It's like a faucet. We
represent this as a zero or a one. Okay.
Now, it's digital. Discrete states. And
if you measure that transistor, um you
will find it in the state you set it in.
Transistors are almost perfect. So, it's
a discrete measurement, deterministic.
Cubits are also two-le systems. This
state or this state. You pick two of
them and that's your cubit. But the
difference is that it's quantum
mechanical. And the way that we think
about it is you think about it as the
planet Earth. At the north pole is state
zero and at the south pole is state one.
Now if you're a classical transistor,
you're either at the north pole or the
south pole. That's your whole world.
That's all you know. But a cubit of
course it can be classical. It can be at
the north pole or the south pole. But it
can also be in what's called a
superposition of states zero and one
simultaneously. And when it's anywhere
other than the north or south pole, it's
in some combination of zero and one. Now
you're standing at a single place on
Earth. It's a single state. It's a
single state that carries aspects of
both zero and one simultaneously. Right?
So that's weird. It's quantum mechanics,
but that's the way it works. One
consequence though is if you make a
measurement, you'll get a statistical or
probabilistic outcome. So if I'm on the
equator, I'm half zero and half one. I'm
in a superp position state of zero and
one. But if I make a measurement, I'm
instantly going to go to the north pole.
Oh, I'm state zero. Or I'm instantly
going to go to the south pole. I'm state
one. It's just like flipping a coin.
50/50 which one you get. It might seem,
okay, that's odd. How can I possibly do
something useful with that? Um, well,
yeah, it's true. Encoding information in
a quantum computer is different. It's
part of why it can be powerful.
To give an idea of that power, let's
consider this. In a classical computer,
if you have a number n transistors,
okay, you can form an exponentially
large number of states, two to the nth
power. Okay, that sounds great. Except
you can only represent one at a time.
So, so for example, if you have three
transistors, two to the third power is
eight. I can represent 000. They're all
in zeros. one one all ones and every
permutation in between there are eight
of them but I can only represent one at
a time. So if some reason for some
reason I wanted to calculate an output
based on every input I've got two
choices. I can either take one computer
and feed in one at a time those states
and get the outputs an exponentially
large number of times. I'm going to be
doing this for a long time. Or I can buy
a very large number of computers and try
to do it in parallel. All right. But
either way, it's going to take
exponential time or exponential hardware
to do that task. Now, a quantum computer
on the other hand, okay, same. Now, you
have n cubits, two to the nclass states,
north and south pole for each one, but
you can put them all in superp position.
So, you form one state
00 plus 001 plus plus all the way up to
111 and you represent all of them in
that state. And what this affords you is
something called quantum version of
parallelism. And it leverages quantum
interference to do calculations. Now we
haven't made a measurement yet, but this
is how a quantum computer drives its
power. Okay. So how do we take advantage
of this? Well, we need algorithms of
course and and many of the algorithms
that we know today were developed by my
colleagues here whose pictures I show at
the bottom here at MIT. MIT was
foundational in making this happen. Um I
won't read through the whole slide but
the first column of algorithm shows the
major categories where we know quantum
will make a difference. Simulating
quantum systems
factoring that's basically mathematics
that lies behind a lot of our encryption
schemes. Linear algebra anyone who's an
engineer or an econometricist or
everybody uses linear algebra
optimization.
Searching unsorted databases. This is
where quantum computers will outperform
classical computers when we can build
one at a large enough scale. Okay. So,
how do we realize that? And and we'll
call it commercial quantum advantage.
You know, quantum advantage would be my
quantum computer does something better
than a classical computer for a problem
that I don't know how to commercialize.
Commercial quantum advantage is doing
that for something I do know how to
commercialize. And so, first off, there
better be no fast classical algorithm.
If I know a good classical algorithm, I
should just use those fantastic GPUs
that we've already got to do it right.
Those those they're fantastic machines.
If I know how to do it efficiently on a
conventional computer, use a
conventional computer. But there are
many problems where I don't know how to
do that. Okay, number one. Number two,
okay, now I need to figure out a good
quantum algorithm that will solve that
problem. There are lots of problems I'm
aware of today where I don't know how to
do it on a classical computer and I also
don't yet know how to do it on a quantum
computer. And and I often say that we
need more people thinking about the
application space and writing those
algorithms. That's that's a major part
of what we do in the center for quantum
engineering is work with companies to
figure out an algorithms that's going to
affect your bottom line. Okay. So then
the third one is it should be a useful
problem. There have been many
demonstrations of quantum advantage over
the years that are not commercial
quantum advantage because although they
prove the point, quantum computers can
outperform classical computers. They
don't we don't know how to commercialize
it and therefore we don't know how to
monetize it. If we look at this current
overlap, it's actually pretty small.
It's increasing in size, but it's small.
There's a lot of research going on here.
And again, I emphasize that this is the
major task in addition to building the
hardware.
Now once we have a problem there are a
couple types of advantage that we can
gain from a quantum computer. The first
well before I get into the first one
let's basically what we're talking about
is how big a system how big a computer
do I need or what's the time to get to a
solution or how much energy do I need to
get to a solution right all of these are
important it's not just the speed right
and that's proportional to two factors
one is a polomial in the size of the
computer and the other is exponential in
the size of the computer now the
polomial one is an improvement that a
quantum computer can make for example if
it took something that goes as n and
made it square root of n that's a big
improvement especially if n is a big
number right time million years take the
square root okay thousand years that's a
big improvement but that pales in
comparison to exponential improvement
and exponential improvement means n is
upstairs and it comes downstairs okay
and we don't really experience
exponential growth in our everyday lives
and So to give an example of exponential
growth, let's imagine the following.
We're going to use a classical computer,
supercomputer, let's say, um, to
simulate a quantum computer to do what a
quantum computer can do. And you could
ask, how much memory will I need to
store this quantum state that I told you
about that contains 2 to the n uh,
components?
So if I have 30 cubits, that's 2 to the
30th power. You can do that with a
conventional laptop. Okay, I can store
that in. It takes a lot of memory, but I
can do it. If I just increase it by 20
more cubits, now we have 50 cubits. I
need the top 100 uh supercomputer in the
world. Maybe even the top one.
If I go to just 80 cubits, now we start
to get into a fantasy where I need to
somehow network all of the computers in
the world and use all of their memory
just to store this quantum state. Double
that to 160. You can go to Wikipedia. 2
to the 160th power is an estimate for
how many silicon atoms we have on Earth.
And I would need to employ each one as a
me memory element. And now 10 times
where we started at 300 cubits, I now
need all of the atoms in the known
universe and employ each of them
to be a bit of my memory. Okay, to store
this massive state. Now, okay, that's
exponential growth, right? It's almost
unbelievable. Of course the challenge is
utilizing it for commercial quantum
advantage.
So why don't we have quantum computers
right now at large scale? It comes down
to two times. One is the coherence time
and one is the gate time. So let's take
them one at a time. So the coherence
time is how long cubits remain quantum
mechanical. I can start at say time t
equals z. I've set up my computer and I
let it run and I'm I'm running my
algorithm on it. But as I'm doing that,
everything else in that computer's
environment is creating noise and
conspiring against me to take those
cubits to a different place. And so
these environmental disruptions over
time, you can think of it as blurring
the quantum state and eventually it's
lost. Now the cubits didn't disappear.
They're still there. But the state that
they ended up in which is the answer to
my problem and I'm trying to go from
point A to point B on the way there the
noise is taking me to some other point C
and I get a wrong answer right the time
frame over which that happens is called
the coherence time
second time is called the gate time
that's basically I have an algorithm it
has a large number of steps how long
does it take me to do each step right
and and the figure of merit then is how
many steps can I
before this environment overcomes my
quantum computer. Right?
With that, we can start thinking about
different types of cubit platforms and
modalities. There are lots of candidate
technologies. And
I won't talk in too much detail about
them individually, but what I want to
show is how they compare to one another
on this chart. The left vertical axis is
how many steps I can take before things
fall apart and the right axis is
basically one to one in that we call it
fidelity. So one error in a 100 gates is
99%. One error in a thousand 99.9% etc.
So you want as high a fidelity as
possible. The horizontal axis is just
the gate speed. How fast can I take
those steps in hertz? Think of it as
your computer's clock speed. So the
upper right corner is where the best
performance is. And some of the major
players today, one is called a trapped
ion. That's a natural atom. It's held in
space and operations are performed on
it. They have decent fidelities. They're
trying to go faster. I work on
superconducting cubits. We're pretty
fast. We want higher fidelity, right?
That's what we're working on. Neutral
atoms, another upand cominging
technology. They're sort of in between,
right? So there's no clear winner right
now. And if I think about the history of
classical electronic computing, there
won't be a winner necessarily.
We started with vacuum tubes. We went to
bipolar junction transistors that became
too power hungry. We went to emitter
coupled logic that became too power
hungry. We went to cos right we then you
know the dinard scaling ended moors laws
ended. So what did we do? Well we went
to GPUs we 3D integrated right?
Heterogeneous integration right? quantum
computing very likely will evolve in the
same or a similar way. Okay,
just to show that there's so many
different modalities here,
superconducting, trapped ion, photonics,
silicon, etc. And all the companies uh
that are trying to do that, many of them
are blue chips, a lot of them are
startups. One of them, Atlantic Quantum,
under the superconducting, is a startup
uh that spun out of my group here, and
we're all trying to commercialize uh
this technology, make it
commercializable.
This is what quantum computers look like
today. On the lower left is IBM's
Osprey. This is about a 430ish
cubit machine. You can see that it's 3D
integrated. That 3D integration
technology developed here at MIT and
Lincoln Lab. In the upper left, Google's
Willow chip. This is 100 cubits, but
last fall they demonstrated quantum
error correction scaling for the first
time. Major demonstration. I'll show
that in just a moment. Upper middle is
Qeras. Aquila, that is a neutral atom
quantum computer. Uh, and it spun out of
Harvard and MIT. Quantinum, that's a
trapped ion. The lower right D-wave,
that's a quantum analer. Uh, and in the
bottom middle, of course, that's not a
quantum computer. uh you'll recognize
that as the right flyer. Um wasn't the
first time humankind flown. We often say
that but it's not true. We had hot air
balloons. Okay, we had gliders, aerod
drromes, right?
But what did this event show? It was the
first time that it all came together
that you got a person on board,
self-propelled, it took off, it landed.
And I put this picture here because I
think that all of these technologies
that you're looking at, they're
basically at this level of development.
It's very early days, but we look back
at that right flyer and we say that was
the dawn of commercial aviation because
that's when it all came together. And I
as I look at these quantum technologies,
okay, my opinion, but I look at these
quantum technologies and I think, yeah,
we're at the dawn of commercial quantum
computing. It's going to happen. It may
take 10 or 20 or 30 years, but it is
coming.
Okay, so there's a lot of promise, but
to realize that promise, we need to
engineer systems that are much larger
than this. They have to be robust. Okay,
we'd like to have a fuselage on the
plane and put some seats, have some
people in the front, right? We need to
do the equivalent of that for quantum
computers. Okay, and one of the biggest
challenges we face, a grand challenge is
called quantum error correction. Um,
these cubits are quantum mechanical and
they're faulty and they fall apart after
say a thousand or 10,000 operations. You
could then ask, that's what's in the
yellow. By the way, we call them
physical cubits. They're the physical
embodiment of a cubit.
You could ask what do you need for
commercial advantage? How many
operations?
Probably 1 billion to one trillion
operations. So, we can do about a
thousand and you need to be at a billion
or a trillion. So, how are you going to
get from where we are today to that?
Well, my students work very hard at
improving cubits and we've been doing
that for years and we'll continue to do
that. But I don't think we're going to
make up a factor million with material
science, right? Fortunately, we don't
have to do that. Thanks to Peter Shore
and his colleagues, we know how to do
quantum error correction and that's how
we're going to get beyond this gap. By
the way, transistors, why are they
ubiquitous? Because they're almost
perfect. The error rate of a transistor
is one part in 10^ the 20th power.
Right? Almost never fails. If this
crashes right now, almost certainly the
software, not the hardware. Fortunately,
we don't have to be there. We just need
to be in the blue region. And the
concept of error correction is something
we're all familiar with. We form teams.
That's basically it. Rather than using
one cubit to encode the information,
we're going to form a team of cubits. In
this case, nine cubits. You can see the
yellow ones. There are nine of them on
the right. We call that a logical cubit.
It represents one cubit's worth of
information, but it has nine physical
cubits to do it. And the classical
version of this is majority voting. You
basically ask, "How many of you think
I'm in state zero versus how many think
I'm state one?" And you majority vote.
And so that's the concept. You'll you'll
also see some blue ones there. Those
blue ones are basically the referees.
They got a yellow card and a red card.
In fact, they have three cards in this
game. And when they one of their
neighbors has an error, they're going to
throw up a flag. And me as the operator
at room temperature is going to look at
that flag and say, "Ah, one of the
neighbors has an error." And by looking
at all of the referees and the errors
they flag, I can determine which cubit,
which physical cubit had an error, and I
can go back and fix it. This is almost
magic. It's not magic, but it's amazing.
What's amazing about it is we all learn
that I can never measure the physical
cubits. If I do, I destroy the quantum
information. I make them classical, but
I never measure a cubit. I I just
measure those referees,
right? And that's how I protect quantum
information.
Now, of course, none of this comes for
free. If you look at the error rate of
the logical cubit, um it goes as this
formula. There's a C. C stands for cost.
It's not free. If you form a team, of
course, it's not as easy as just having
one person there, right? We know this in
companies, right? Google has 150,000
employees, right? And they're not all
working on the internet or AI. You got
an HR department, you've got a security
department, etc., etc., etc., but you
still do it because we know that by
forming teams that are focused on the
product and all of the stuff and the
cost that goes around it, it still
provides advantage, right? That's the
concept of a logical cubit. And as you
make the team bigger and bigger, it
becomes more and more performant. How
much more performant? exponentially. So
what we're seeing on the right here, the
vertical axis is the logical error.
That's the error rate of the logical
cubit on a log scale.
The vertical axis is the error rate of
the individuals,
individual cubits, and that's not on a
log scale. So one in a th00and is uh you
know just to the left of 0.15%. That's
basically where we're at now. And you
could ask then how does this scale with
the size of the team? Well, that's the
different colors. Distance three is
jargon, but it means 17 cubits. Distance
5 is 49 cubits, etc. If I go from 17 to
49 cubits, I get this improvement here.
Lambda is the is the what we call it,
but from three to distance three to
distance five. If I go to one size
larger, distance seven, my error rate
goes down. And notice each time it goes
down by about a factor 10. I can keep
doing that. I just keep making the team
bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger
and bigger and bigger and eventually I
just make it big enough that I achieve
the error rate that I want. And here we
are down at one part in a billion. You
could ask, okay, distance 17, that
sounds like a big team. How big is that
team?
577 cubits. So I increased from one by a
factor 577 and my error rate went down
by a factor 1 million.
Exponential growth again, right? This is
how we're going to overcome these
errors. The demonstration last fall from
Google is shown here. And what you're
looking at is the logical error rate
versus how many times they did the error
correction, the error detection. And in
red is the uh distance three curve. And
when they went to distance five, they
added more cubits. It goes down to the
teal curve. They go to distance seven,
it goes down to the dark blue curve.
Down is better. Less error per cycle.
And in fact, if you look at this just
above the teal, I think it's in green,
that's the best physical cubit. That's
the best team member. There's always a
best one on your soccer team, the one
who's the star. This is the star cubit.
And the team at distance five was
already better than the best star on the
team. And of course, distance 7 even
better still, right? This is common
sense, right? We know that forming teams
will always if if they're good, they
will always outperform any individual on
the team.
So Google quantum AI demonstrated this
last fall. This will be remembered for
decades. Um it's a major demonstration.
It shows that we can achieve um quantum
resilience.
Now many of you may have seen this in
January. Um of course this is Jensen
Hong um and he's being interviewed. Um
and he was asked when are we going to
have a quantum computer? And he said
well you know 15 years seems a little
early. 30 years that seems a little
long. I think most of us would agree 20
years. And of course all the stocks
tanked from the quantum computing
companies that had IPOed. Um and
come back in June and he was like okay
wait a minute. Um what I meant to say
was that we're actually reaching an
inflection point. I I think these two
things are equivalent. Basically when
Jensen was asked when are we going to
have a quantum computer? He's thinking,
"When are we going to have the quantum
computer that's fully performant and
it's going to help me design new
pharmaceutical drugs?" Right? He's
thinking of the endgame. And he said,
"20 years." I thought that was
fantastic. A lot of a lot of people
complain, "Oh, Jensen, you're killing
the industry." No way. We have we have
the, to my mind, one of the smartest
engineers
in industry today saying we are going to
have the endgame quantum computer in 20
years. That's fantastic. from my mind.
Stocks all recovered by the way since
then. So, and and more if you follow it.
Um, I just want to say that we have this
industry engagement group here at MIT.
If you'd like to learn more, feel free
to contact me. Number of companies
involved. Um, we also do a lot of
entrepreneurship here at MIT. I
mentioned Atlantic Quantum, my own
company, but uh, and also Cuera, the um,
neutral atom company. Labber Quantum
spun out of my um, group a couple years
ago. That's a software company. Anyways,
lots of companies uh are spinning out of
MIT as well. And um again, if you'd like
to learn more about what's happening in
the industrial space uh in quantum, feel
free to contact me. So today's reality,
and this is I think the last slide. One,
quantum computers will not replace
conventional classical computers, right?
Quantum computers solve certain problems
really well, but they're not going to do
Microsoft Word. um for for a lot of
these applications, they're no better
than a classical computer. They can do
it, but why would you go to the trouble
when we've got really good classical
computers already?
Um we need more quantum algorithms. We
talked about that already, but you know,
one of our main jobs going forward is to
find commercially viable applications.
Um
RSA sounds scary that quantum computers
can break it and we got to pay
attention, but it's not going to happen
today. to break RSA encryption public
key crypto systems is going to require a
very large error corrected quantum
computer with millions of cubits that's
still a ways away but but we need to
switch over to a new crypto system now
postquantum crypto NIST announced it
last year goes by names like Kyber okay
um why do we need to do that for forward
security there's there's information
that we are encrypting today that we
want to retain security over not just
today but in 10 years, 20 years, 30
years, right? And at some point we will
have a quantum computer that can decrypt
everything that we're storing on hard
drives today. Okay? Um and we will need
quantum error correction to make this
possible. And I think with the
demonstration from Google last fall, we
saw uh a major step in that direction.
And so that I'd like to thank you uh for
your attention. Any question?
Questions for Will.
>> Hey, thank you, Will. I wanted to ask uh
we're chatting just before um when you
envision uh where these quantum
computers are going. I'm Bruce Hack by
the way from Myithril Technologies uh
and data center days. So what um paint a
picture for us in 20 years when these
first uh workable quantum computers are
in practice. uh where will they be and
how will another question that came up
this morning in conversation is cities
you know if cities got changed by the
automobile and they got changed by the
introduction of the airport as you said
commercial aviation what does the uh
future of and maybe not just today's
data centers but that 20-year trajectory
from today to quantum computers what
does this mean for us as humans and the
future of our cities
>> yeah so so first part is that quantum
computers absolutely as far as I can
tell uh need to run in tandem with a
very large classical computer, right?
And so our data centers will have of
course the classical racks that we all
know today, but next to them will be
quantum computers because the quantum
computers that are doing this error
correction, they need those classical
compute and that classical compute power
just to interpret what the referees are
telling us where the errors occur. So
and and plus some of these computers are
very cold and if I am writing an
algorithm I want to do that at room
temperature on a classical computer and
you know so for very practical reasons
quantum computers will always run in
tandem with with conventional classical
computers and in fact many of the
algorithms will leverage that classical
computer as well. So a large a part of
that algorithm may run on the classical
data center computer but then it gets to
a hard part and then it's going to hand
that off to the accelerator the quantum
computer gets the answer back. So it's
and you know the future I don't have a
crystal ball of course but there are
some pretty thorny problems facing
humankind today and and energy is a big
one. Climate change is another one.
We're living through this now right? Do
we, you know, do we abandon fossil fuels
um knowing that that's going to wreck
the economy so that we can have a
cleaner future or do we buy ourselves
some time so that we can find solutions
to this problem and then implement them?
I don't have the answers, but I think
that one step towards this um is quantum
computers because where they really
shine is in simulating um quantum
chemistries, some better batteries, um
quantum materials, better materials, and
engineers can use this this information
then to develop the technologies that
hopefully will allow us to live in a
cleaner environment.
>> Great. All right. Thank you, Will. Okay.
Thank you. Terrific.