Good morning everybody. Welcome to the
MPG primer. Today we're really excited
today to have Haong Tian. He's a
posttock researcher at MGH and the Broad
Institute in the lab of Perip Natarajin.
He's previously completed his PhD in
bioatistics at the University of
Cambridge under the supervision of
Steven Burgess. His research focuses on
developing innovation I'm sorry
innovative causal inference methods
particularly for mandelian randomization
and applying them to address real world
biomedical questions. He has broad
interest broad interest in the interface
of statistics epidemiology and genetics.
Um and we're happy to have him here
today and again ask questions
throughout. Thank you. Take it away.
>> Thank you. Okay. Thank you everyone. Um
so today let's talk about mundane
randomization. So our story starts with
the a very important question that is
the causal inference question. So we are
not familiar with the general inference
that is about the association between X
and uh sorry the exposure X and the
outcome Y. So in other words, this is
the probability of the Y given the
observed exposure X value. But the cause
of influence is kind of different or
essentially we can say totally different
that is about the probability of Y after
we change the exposure. So that is about
uh the change of exposure not the
observed exposure. In other words, when
we say there exist the cause effect of
exposure on the outcome, it means that
if we change the exposure, we outcome
will be changed accordingly.
So causal influence is very important
and very natural questions in many
scenarios. So the the essential idea is
that the cause of influence will give
you the motivation to give interventions
on the exposure in order to improve your
outcome. So that's the essential ideas
but this is difficult. I remember when I
first took the course of simple linear
regression at that time I really wish
that the fitted parameter of the
regression have the cause of
interpretation but obviously I was
wrong. The reason is that the regression
or the simple linear regression
essentially is about the association but
association between the X and Y doesn't
mean that there exist cause effect of X
on Y in the sense that you change X your
outcome will not changed. So in other
words if you use the graphical language
it means that there's no arrows from X
to Y. So there are many examples that
can illustrate that XY are associated
but doesn't mean that it's causal
relationship. So the most famous example
is the confounding structure. So the
confounders here refers to the variable
that can affect your exposure and
outcome jointly. So that you can observe
that X and Y associated but it doesn't
mean that is causal effect.
So that's why we need the causal
influence methods beyond the general
influence methods.
So there are many important cause
influence methods and I think the most
reliable and convincing examples is the
uh based on the experimental data. So
we're no familiar with this because RCD
is very good and we like RCD because it
do a perfect randomization. It can have
the very good cause interpolation is
very intuitive but it is expensive and
sometimes is not plausible. That's why
in the past 20 years the main
development of coal influence methods is
based on the observational data only. We
have lots of causal impulence methods
now and uh they are using different
models different strategies with
different assumptions to identify the
causal effect of interest and among them
there is one methods called instrumental
variable analysis methods. So what is
instrumental analysis? It's just a
simple method but that can help you to
answer the causal questions using
observational data only. And uh the main
features of the instrumental valve
analysis that it does not requires any
model assumptions about the confounders.
In other words, even you don't know or
doesn't realize that the existence of
the combounders, you can still use the
instrumental web analysis.
So this is the main reason that why it
becomes so popular in many fields and
particularly if you do uh many
statistics work in epidemiology and
genetics analysis. You will encounter
the instrumental web analysis very often
and the main advantage is not only that
it does not require the existence of the
sorry the measure of the compounders it
also gives you very flexible models. So
in other words you can have more choices
than the model not only modeling the
phenotype distribution but also the
distribution of genetic association.
This is particularly important point I
want to highlight today because we are
do many analysis in epidemiology and
genetics and usually in many cases you
will find that the epidemiology analysis
is more sensitive than the genetics
analysis. So the reason is because that
epidemology analysis based on
distribution of the phenotype but the
genetics analysis sometimes are based on
the distribution of genetic association
which is more reliable and stable. So
instrumental variable can be based on
the distribution of genetic association
that is very popular in genetics.
So right what is MR? So technically
speaking MR is nothing but just
instrumental web analysis. So if you are
interested in the MR you can start to
learn the MR and also you can start to
learn the instrumental variable because
every concepts and every problems and
every points in instrumental analysis is
also the points in mandization but the
key difference that mundane
randomization use the genetic variance
as the instrument which is quite
different uh to another uh other
instrumental variable methods. So we
will immediately realize that why MI is
so different because it use the
properties of genetic variance and it
will make
>> sorry I have a question.
>> What do you mean by the four four
analysis? MR is a four. What is the
analysis method mean?
>> M it says MR is a four analysis method.
Oh Ivy sorry is
>> this is in short uh stands for the
instrumental analysis. Um
all right so so technically speaking MI
is just instrumental web analysis
methods and we'll start to first
introduce the instrumental web analysis
and then move to the why genetic
variance can be used as the instrument.
So when we talk about the causal
influence methods including instrumental
verb analysis assumptions are very
important concept because this because
in causal influence no assumptions no
causal influence that's why we really
highlight the importance of the
assumptions and uh so in for
instrumental variable analysis there are
three important assumptions
and uh this my perhaps my personal step
before I introduce the assumptions I
prefer to introduce the purpose of the
assumptions because based on different
assumptions you achieve different
purpose. So today our purpose is just
only one that is we just want to test a
test a n hypothesis. This n hypothesis
called sharp nypsis which means that
there's no unosal effect in any way over
any time. So this is very strong
statement but you will quickly
understand why I can only test this n
because I only made three assumptions.
So
how do we um introduce the assumptions
in co of inference? There are many
different languages to describe
assumptions. Usually there are three
languages
and uh at least all of them. So
in the very beginning let's assume that
there's no I didn't make assumption. I
just want to emphasize that we can write
down the outcomes expressed by the
explosion and other variables. So this
is the first uh equation I want to start
in at this stage I didn't make any
assumption I just uh write down the
equation. This equation refers to
structure equation which represents the
belief of how the data are generated.
So here the the kept U refers to the any
variables that it will be related to the
outcome but we just cannot observe that
we cannot realize that
and the parameter beta refers to the
causive value we really want to test
because under the N hypothes really want
to test if not the beta equals to zero.
So we write down the expressions and now
interesting if we assume
there exist an additional variable. So
this variable is actually uh like the
genetic variant and this variable
once we have this variable we can
updated the graph and the equation like
in this way again at this stage I didn't
make any assumption because I can always
write equation like this way using the
algebra language. So now we will start
to make assumptions. So the capital G is
the instrument and the first assumption
is that I assume that the G that is the
instrument is correlated with the
exposure. And then if I additionally
assumes that the instrument is
independent of the confounders
and the third assumption is that I
assume that the instrument cannot affect
outcome directly. Once we make these
three assumptions, we say that the
instrument G here is the valid
instrument. So this is typically the
three assumptions for the instrumental
web analysis.
Once we have this valid instrument,
we can immediately write down a very
famous equation instrument analysis.
That is to say the genetic association
with outcome is just proportional to the
genetic association with exposure in the
size of beta. So the beta is the
parameter we want to test.
So
the left hand side is genetic
association exposure. The right hand
side is genetic association with the
outcome. So we can use the any statistic
methods to make inference because they
are identifiable in statistics. So we
can immediately know what the beta looks
like. So remember that we are testing
the sharp hypothesis. So we wish to find
the evidence to
distinguish the betas from zero. So once
we found such evidence we can say that
uh there exist a causal effect which
means that the beta not equals zero.
So this is typical idea. So as you may
know that we here made a very strong
statement. So when we reject the sharp
non hypothesis which means that we can
say that there exist cause bad but we
have no idea what this effect looks like
we don't know if or not the so-called
causal effects only
to certain subgroup or certain exposure
level and this is a trade-off this is
because
we only made three assumption because I
don't want my today's presentation too
complicated so in cost of influence if
you make less
assumptions you will only be able to
test very strong non hypothesis. So this
is trade off. If we want to answers more
precise cause of effect for example the
cause of effect for a certain subgroup
we must made more assumptions but once
we made more assumptions sometimes these
assumptions are unverifiable. So which
means that they may be unreliable they
may be related in realistic so we will
end up with unreliable results. So this
is a trade-off and uh so this is the
first point I want to highlight today is
that today we are only care about sharp
hypothesis. We do not want to do the
other things beyond the sharp null
hypothesis because we only made three
assumptions and uh in most I think in
all causal influence methods assumptions
are very important. Um if you want to
test the weak hypothesis or you want to
do estimation you must assume additional
assumptions. So there is a very famous
paper uh published in nearly 20 years
ago in chronometric. So that paper made
additional assumption which is quite
reliable and using that additional
assumption they can identify very
interesting cause of effect which is
deformed to a subgroup of the
population. So that's is the if you are
interested you can look at this paper
and uh that paper is actually ill this
idea in a very good way and this idea is
also the key uh contribution behind the
2021 no price economics so overall this
is about my today's work we wish to use
the IB3 assumptions to test the sharpen
hypothesis
so here uh I just give some examples of
instrumental variable analysis so the
key idea of instrumental relevance just
to form the validate
um instrument that satisfied all the
three IV assumptions
and typically all the scenarios you can
see that the instrumental variable is
kind of good which means that we believe
that they indeed somehow are well
randomized. So randomization
uh is very beautiful word in causal
influence because like the RCT it give
us the chance to do the causal influence
and uh in recent years they are someone
proposing to use the genetic
informations as the instrumental
variable to do the causal inference. So
because they think the genetic
information are well randomized. So in
other words they believe there exist
some randomization in a mandelian way.
So they call it mundane randomization.
So we're back to mundane randomization.
We already know the instrumental
variable analysis and with the three
[clears throat] assumptions to test the
sharp non hypothesis and now we have the
genetic information. So we are really
interesting to know if not we can use
the genetic variance to do the uh cause
inference under the instrumental verb
framework.
So can we do that? Um actually I don't
know nobody can tell you the answer but
this is our belief that many people
think genetic varants are kind of good
randomized. Uh so I want to highlight
that this sentence is the belief not the
conclusion and and indeed there are many
people disagree with the amount
randomization but today I want to
illustrate this point. Um it really
depends on the if or not you really
really believe the genetic variants are
indeed randomized because if genetic
variants are indeed randomized we indeed
can use the instrumental verb analysis
logic to do the causal inference.
So I think there are many good logic
behind the MR. So the key philosophy is
that if if we look at the family level
so the mandala loss I think ensures that
the distribution of the next
generation's genetic factors are indeed
kind of independent so which means that
they are well randomized but most times
MR was contacted in the population
level. So in the population level there
are many ways to think about mundane
randomization assumptions and I think
random mating is the one logic to help
you to invalidate if not the genetic
varian are indeed randomized or not. Um
but again I want to highlight that this
is just one way to illustrate that
because nobody can really illustrate if
not the genative varants are indeed
randomized and the strict speaking also
the random man is not always correct in
practice but again I just say that
usually we're happy to believe that
genetic varants are randomized in the
sense that is typically independent of
the environmental factors because the
environmental factors will serve as the
confounders in our instrumental web
analysis framework.
this first point. The second point is
that um we already used the G was to
identify the money genetic variant that
associated with the exposure of
interest. So which is good because
remember that the first I assumption u
indicated that the the instrument should
be correlated with the exposure and this
is the truth because we already used G
was to form that there's indeed mining
genetic variance associated with the
exposures
so which is good and uh also from the
statistical perspective
um since we have found money independent
snips we can do lots of status works
like the meta analysis to borrow
information. That is to say, for
example, we have 10 genetic variants.
For each one of them, we can do the M
estimation and get the so-called uh
causal effect estimates and we can
easily combine them together to have the
more um narrow confidence intervals or
more confident uh causal conclusions.
This is the very flexible idea um in
terms of the meta analysis for I uh for
instrumental variable analysis
estimation and also since we have the
mutable instrumental variables we can
also have the chance to do many robust
amas and we will return to this point
later. So which is good because if you
really look at the other instrumental we
analysis examples they only have one
instrument but in genetics in MR
scenarios we can have mutable
instrumental variable. So we can have
much space to take advantage of such
mutable instrument
available to us. So this is about second
point and the third point is also very
important. This is also the truth not
the belief is that genetic variants are
usually fixed at birth which means that
if we happy to believe that genetic
variance as the instrument. So the
instrument is very fixed at the very
beginning. It was not influenced by the
later age phenotypes.
So it will give you a quite stable
belief about that your instrument is
very good is very fixed. So if you are
happy with the first point here and the
plus the third point here I think you
should be very excited about the
maintenization as the instrumental web
analysis because it gives a very good
belief to see to believe that the
instrumental web assumptions are well
satisfied.
So this is about the aological point and
also I want to highlight some important
things from statistics. So I I really
show that the really important equation
of instrumental variable is like this.
So the genetic association with outcome
is proportional to the genetic
association with the exposure. So if we
look into this equation you can see that
we actually no need to calculate it the
genetic associations with the phenotypes
by uh using the individual level data
because J was really done this for us
and also you can see that these two
genetic association are separated in the
equation which means that we even don't
need to do the estimation using the one
symbol we actually can finish it the
estimation using the two different
datas. So which means that we can use in
the two sample analysis.
So this give the m quite flexible than
other instrumental variable analysis
methods.
So here this number is that so-called
the two sample summary data mundization
methods which I think the majority MR
methods for the published work in the
recent years and uh I want to
highlighted one point here is that
the two sample summary data MI is very
uh popularized because the convenience
of data but not because this methods
itself is more reliable because this
just because it's more convenient that
everyone can use the uh publish some
data and quickly to do the M estimation.
So that's why you can see if you look
the many published Emma papers typically
they are about to s some related MR
right and another in the end point I
want to highlight is that because we are
the community of genetics when we do the
Emma uh we can do lots of things beyond
the traditional instrumental web
analysis this is because that we use
genetic variant as the instrument so if
we look at the genetic variance we can
do a lot of things using the different
genetic techniques
And uh uh for example we have very good
data sources from GW was and chos and if
you wish to take the U exposure as the
protein or expression level you can also
use many QTL and PQTL and also we can do
lots of works like FS like variance
clustering there school genetic
correlations. So all these methods can
help you to improve the reliability of
your MR analysis. So that is today if
you do Emma you can of course do lots of
instrumental web analysis uh methods uh
and also you can do lots of another
genetics techniques analysis
right this is all about about all the
things and more motivations for the MR
but do we really think the MI is good
instrument web analysis methods and my
answer is perhaps yes or no remember
that if We treat the MR as the
instrumental verb analysis methods and
everything is about three assumptions of
instrumental web analysis.
But even we already know that there are
many good properties of genetic
variance. We still face many challenges
in terms of the violation of the IV
analysis method.
So the first point is that the genetic
association with the exposure is
actually not quite strong as you
expected. So which means that even we
formed that there is some evidence from
the statistics that the genetic
instrument is correlated with your
exposure. It doesn't mean that your
first IV assumption is really satisfied.
So this is this is not a logical
problem. This is about statistic
problem. So,
so because you estimated genetic
association with the exposure is the
estimate. So, you must take into account
the uncertainties
for you in violation of IV strength. So,
there is very there's very famous and
well established metric to measure the
uh I strength that is called F
statistic. So that is to say once you
have determined sorry once you have
decided you instrument exposure you can
quickly calculate the F statistic if the
F statistics is less than 10 which means
that you will suffer from the weak
instrument bas so what's the consequence
of the weak instrument I uh issues is
that if you are using the one sle MR you
typically have inflated type one error
this is very horrible because remember
that what's the purpose of Emma and I
analysis the purpose is just to testing
So you will when you get a meaningful
conclusion you typically want to reject
your null hypothesis but if if you
cannot control your type one error you
conclusion that rejects no hypothesis
will not be reliable that's why we
really care about the f status value
because it determines if not we suffer
from the weak IV issues particularly if
we are doing the one sample MR
If the f star value is slower than 10
this is very dangerous which means that
you any conclusion you get will be
unreliable. So that's why we need to
check f statistics in i analysis
including mundane randomization
analysis. So this about the first
assumption and uh
about the second and the third I
assumption unfortunately I would say
that is typically are not quite um
satisfied in realistic. So here I just
uh pick the eight examples to illustrate
that the genetic variance can still
violate the IV assumptions uh in many
different scenarios which means that
even the truth is that there's no causal
effect of X on Y you can still find that
your genetic variance to be correlated
with your outcome. So that is to the you
will you could end up with the false
positive conclusion.
So here so this is very dangerous but we
cannot solve all the scenarios and um
so the only things we can do is that we
try different strategies to invalidate
these assumptions and we try our best to
improve the quality of the MR analysis.
So here I just give the some my
suggestions to improve the MR analysis
because we we cannot assume that genetic
variance are very perfect instrument in
the sense that typically in many
scenarios the I assumption will be
wellated for the instrument we used for
the cause of influence.
So I randomly pick some suggestion here.
So I think maybe we should be really
clear about explosion definition. So
this this suggestion can doesn't
actually change the MR calculation but
instead is a good habit at least to me
is a very good habit to be first very
clear about exposure definition because
in many scenarios
um the MRI exposure is not the true
exposure but actually the biomarker of
the exposure.
That is to say you many times we are in
we do the MR analysis based on the
biomarkers or the downstream variables
of the lengthened exposure. So in this
case you can still do the M analysis but
you should be really care about the
interpretation.
So that is why when we get the
conclusion using Emma, I suggest to use
the sentence like the genetically
predicted exposure is associated with
outcome instead of to say there exist
cause effect of the exposure on the
outcome because sometimes the exposure
is not the true exposure you can image.
So the exposure sometimes are only the
biomeac of the lengthened exposure of
interest. So this is example about why I
encourage should be very clear about
exposure to vision and there are also
some suggestions. So for example if you
u for example if you exposure of
interest is the LDL.
So for the LDL we know that there are
many biological confirmed
pathway
for the uh generation of LDL. So you can
use the specific power knowledge to
choose the genetic variance that is you
don't need to use that way to choose
genetic variance. You can just pick the
gene regions that most associated with
the LDLC. So this will increase the
reliability of your genetic variant
because in the sense you will truly
believe that genetic varants are
associated with the exposure of interest
and there is a low risk of the wellating
the third and the second IV assumptions
and also you can do uh another check. So
for example most scenarios we do Emma
based on the publish summary data. So
one suggestion could be that uh think
about how the sum data were generated
because there are some scenarios that
the G was
used in um different way than you
expect. For example, they use the PMI
adjusted exposure. In this case we know
that from the GS if we adjust the BMI so
you uh some data could be not quite
reliable. So it will make you some
genetic variance to be well related
sorry will be unreliable and invalid in
the sense that it will violated some IV
assumptions. So that is also the good
habit and we also have some suggestions
is to do uh the robust MR methods. So
robust MR methods were typically
uh
options that everyone can use in
practice because everyone typically can
use robust MIR method. So my next slide
is where I'll be introduce some robust
MR methods. But before I move to the
next I want to emphasize one things is
that uh robust MR method is just one way
to improve the quality of our MES. So
because I don't want to give you the
impression that robust MI is the major
things and sometimes uh robos MRI
methods cannot help you but it's just
because that we can do the robos nearly
all scenarios. That's why I have to
introduce them.
But you can say there are many another
strategies you can consider but not only
limited to robust MR methods.
Right?
So what is the robust MR methods?
Robbert
methods refers to all the methods that
can help you get reliable causal
convolution even some or all I sum are
violated because we know that the in the
MR the I assumption can be easily viated
so that's why we need sometimes we need
the robust MR methods so the robust MR
method is based on the assumption
exchangeability which means that they
proposed the new additional assumption
to exchange the original IV assumption.
So even your original I assumption is
vated but you use the robust methods you
can still get validate conclusion.
That's the key idea. So it use different
strategies. Usually uh I think they can
be uh divided to two groups. One group
is based on the uh snips removal
strategies. Another group is based on
the model based group.
So I give you quick examples. So the MR
model is a very simple method which
means that when you made additional
assumption that you believe the majority
of the genetic variance that generate
the consistent or similar IV estimates
they are the valid instruments. So this
is the assumption under this assumption
you can quickly immediately identify the
true cause effect uh according to the
cluster of the genetic variance.
uh another methods is called the MAPSS.
So this is the compilatively statistical
based uh and the model based methods. So
instead they directly use the algebra
language to describe
uh the distribution of the genetic
association with the exposure and the
outcome and then here they they use the
different assumptions based on the
statistic model and then make influence
to get the true causal parameters. So
this is a very model based methods. Here
I introduce this methods is not because
this is good method but actually it take
the advantage of the ALD score. So AD
school is method to describe the genetic
correlation of your exposure and
outcome. So it also score is also based
on assumptions. So MIAPS is just use
very similar assumptions behind the AD
score to conduct robust uh I analysis
estimation.
So we have so many robust MIR methods.
So can we choose the best methods out of
these candidates and my answer is no. Uh
uh never never never do the selections
on the robust MR methods. Um so the the
idea is that as a side the robust MR
methods is to propose the new additional
assumption to exchange the original I
assumption. Different methods will use
different ways to propose the additional
assumption. You never know which
additional assumption are more reliable
in your scenarios because most times the
coal inference assumptions are
unverifiable which means that nobody can
tell you they are really true. So in
practice the general way is used more
like the triangulation strategies that
is to say you should try multiple
different robust MR methods and you can
say if or not they are really
consistent.
So if we if you we use many different
robust MR methods based on different
additional assumptions
if we don't get the your conclusion is
quite consistent which is good because
they will increase the reliability of
your conclusion but sometimes we may end
up with quite different uh
results using different robos MR method
but it's okay in this case don't be uh
frustrated just report results and this
will mot the future studies to think
about why in some scenarios that you
results are quite different using
certain robust amma methods and it will
improve our understanding on the on new
real uh application scenario. So this is
the key ideas I want to say that
right. So this is about robos and um
here I just give the pipeline um so
actually I'm the really anti pipeline
presence um I have really mixed feelings
about the proposed pipeline for the
comments. The reason is that on the one
hand pipeline auto procedure is good
because it can help us to get rid of
some uh big mistakes but on the other
hand it will give you the false
impression that your M is good because
when we do do the M when when we finish
all the checklist and we do all the
correct things uh we will tend to
believe that our MR conclusion is
relable but actually not um the MR
conclusion really based bas on the uh
designs but not from the calculations.
So even you do all the calculation that
mean that your MR results are reliable
in the end. But here but generally
speaking when we do MR analysis
everything is just based on the question
and your data. So you can have data and
then have question you can also have
first have the question and data.
Usually I would suggest to first have
the question because the question will
make you think about if not you are
doing the right design you are really
answer the question instead of just do
the calculation based on the data. So
there are many ways to start the
analysis. So if you are doing the
epidemology analysis is it's very okay
to directly say that okay we are
interested to the cause effect of your
exposure and your outcome. This is very
good motivation. And if you do genetic
variance for example you have you would
think about the mining mutual protein
candidate you are interesting to know
which or how many proteins are
correlated or have the cause of
connection to exposure. You can also
package it as the mundaneization
question that is so that you can focus
on each single protein and think about
and do the MR for the each single
protein because single protein can be
served as the exposure and your outcome
will be served as outcome in the
instrument framework and also sometimes
you may have two phenotypes
and you cannot distinguish the cause of
direction of the phenotypes. So you can
also do the MR. So in the way that you
do the first Emma using the first
phenotype exposure and then do the
second Emma using the second phenotype
as exposure. So I just do two Emma
separately. So this is all thing is very
flexible. You can you can very flexible
to the MR analysis in any way you wish
as long as you can describe the question
as the uh co investigate the cause of X
or Y.
So the most important things later is
about the snip selection. Snip
establishment is typically the most
important part in MR analysis. Uh there
are many uh strategies I proposed here.
Um again once you have selective snips
you can do the MR uh calculation which
is very simple and straightforward and
packages can do it very quickly
and then I think more important thing is
to the sensitivity analysis. So you can
do a lots of sensitive analysis for
example uh using different robos methods
and based on different data cohort and
uh using different uh genetic variance
because in ML you typically have many
genetic variants can be used for the IV
estimation and then you can also do
positive contra negative control. So
these things will help you make your
Emma results is more informative and in
the end more reliable.
So that is about the conventional assa
pipeline.
So let's um give a quick summary. So
original MR essentially just
instrumental web analysis methods. So
technically speaking uh everything in
every analysis also uh applicable to the
MR but the key feature is that MR using
genetic variance as the instrument. So
this good thing or sometimes a bad thing
because sometimes we are very happy or
excited because of the property of the
genetic variance but sometimes we also
very frustrated because we know that
genetic variance can violated money I
assumptions in ministrals.
So we still wish to the do the causal
influence using the MR but MR here I
think is more kind of explorative
methods if not the very final cause of
influence methods. I understand everyone
is very excited about the causal
influence conclusion but MR can only
give you very initial. So usually the
typical application of MI is to first
highlight the variables you think have
the causal relationship and then later
you do a more another coal influence
methods focusing on those highlighted
exposures. So this is typically
pipeline. Um again the very important
features on my today's present is that
we only introduced three I assumptions.
Remember that in coal inference
assumption is very important. How many
assumption we have determined how
precise conclusion you can get because
we only use three I assumption. You
typically actually doing the uh sharp
non hypothesis test. So that is this is
very uh important concludes that in most
scenarios the purpose of MI is just to
do testing. We do not do estimation. We
just want to test hypothesal effect. So
the main conclusion of MI is typically
that we believe there exist some cause
effect but we have no idea what they
cause effect really look like. So
usually we will use another methods to
solve this problem or use advanced MR
methods.
And again uh the really important
feature is that the difficulty and not
to mow from the computation. I want to
say again is that the MI is very easy
methods on my eyes and it also use very
tiny data particularly if you combine
Emma with other postg methods. Emma is
very simple but I spend much time to
emphasize the design because design is
actually much much more important than
the calculations in Emma.
If you have very good design maybe I
know I understand this is very difficult
because this is case by case but if you
can find a scenario that
everyone are really happy nearly
everyone happy with the IV assumptions
that they are really happy about you
using that genetic variant to do the MRA
or IV analysis
you conclusion will be much much
valuable that's very important because
coal conclusion is very exciting but
they are so many cost convolutions
published by Emma papers in low quality
that is very frustrating.
So we really um happy with the good
design even your final conclusion is not
significant because I understand because
we sometimes we have the pressures to
publishing some papers we really have to
end up with significant results but in
coal influence there is the so-called
publication bs so that's why in coal
influence we really happy to see a coal
influence methods like m analysis with
good design even you find a conclusion
is not significant that is still very
good papers So that is typically all the
summary of the MR for the conditional uh
sorry for the traditional and
conventional MR analysis. But of course
there are also some actually many
advanced MR topics because I cannot uh
look into uh each of them but
there are many advanced topics. I think
they can be again divided to two groups.
So the first group is more from the
methology perspective or say the
statistical perspective. So we can
consider more complicated
uh models. We can answers more precise
causal effect because remember that if
you only do the
traditional MMR we only to do testing.
So the n hypothesis means that you
believe that that there's no cause
effect which this statement is too
strong. Sometimes we are interested in a
more precise causal effect. So that's
why we need more advanced amattopics for
the nonlinear time wirings and the
individual level causal effect. But
again this will require additional
assumptions. When we do coal inference
when we make additional assumptions we
should be very careful about this
because many assumptions could be
violated in your application.
So this is a trade-off and another
direction of advanced MI is based on the
um application considerations because MI
is the genetic epidemiology methods.
Sometimes we used Emma in epidemi and
genetic scenarios. We need to think
about some specific problems. For
example, we need to think about
selection bi. We need to think about the
sample brows. We also need to deal with
missing data. So how can we use the MI
in such scenarios? There are many
methods proposed so that if this problem
is applicable to your application you
can consider this advanced topics. I
highlighted some very good papers for
each one of them. And also if you do the
genetics data usually we do uh mutomics
data and we have the protein or
expression level and uh which means that
if we do the M with them we typically
use CQL or PQDL and it will also
involves many uh start problems and
based on this there are many novel
methods proposed to help you get
to do the better MR analysis with this
PQ and PQR this side and of course we
can also use Emma with few this is quite
flexible. So M essentially is just a
simple method but this is this is
actually the kind of conclusion that if
you find some causal influence method
simple which means that this is better.
So the simple method sometimes is better
than complicated and fancy methods but
the design becomes more important. So
you want to ensure that you do a lot of
MR analysis and you want to convince
others believe that your MR contribution
are reliable.
So you need to think about many
scenarios in your specified application.
So not only just doing MI in a in a
mechanical or in a mechanical way. You
need to think about it like the more
like a more flexible ways to deal with
all the potential problems you think
there could be in your analysis.
and the right I give you a quick
introduction to the one topic of the
advanced methods. So Mway Mi is just um
more generalized version of Emma. So
this is good because once you understand
the MUT if you this is good I mean if
you understand the general version you
can of course understand more special
version. So the M is good. So M is good.
The main reason I think is it can be
indeed used in many scenarios. So in
your application sometimes if you using
the uh cause of mediation analysis you
can use the MMR if you are interested in
some key risk factor selection problems
you can also transform it to MMR.
So here M is very flexible method so
that's why I highly recommend it to you
but again this is about advanced MR
topics. So um if you are uh if your
application really consider very narrow
questions you can use the MMA
right so this is about the Emma part and
I want to extend a little bit to
connecting Emma to other topics um
>> hold on we have like one minute
>> okay yeah I just randomly pick one
topics for example if you um
>> so if you think PRS so PRS is typically
um you can use the PRS with individual
level data and it will have the
individual level MR. Individual MR
analysis is quite good because it can
you can combine with many advanced IV
and machine learning methods because IV
and machine learning methods are many
cases are based on individual level
data. So do not limited your MR to the
summary data level. You can do lot of
fancy things using the individual level
data. So particularly if you have PIS if
you have individual level data and you
will get many interesting conclusions.
So of course we connect Emma to any
other topics like genetic correlation
for collocizations
right this is about all the things I
here I also provide some MR learning
resources and I would say thanks to all
my friends um for this slides. Thank you
so much.
>> So any other questions then be free to
ask.
>> Thank you so much. And if you wanted to
ask yours in person, you're here.
>> Actually question.
>> Well, I get I I put in in the chat
earlier a question that what does it
mean to say that the you know the
genetics is randomized? like obviously I
can get behind that being the case
between the parents but across everybody
else that's obviously false. So
>> yeah. So yeah, this is a good question
and also hard to answer because uh if we
look at the population level the
randomized actually uh means that the
genetic factor of individuals
sorry the individual's genetic factors
are kind of independent of the
environmental factors.
So,
so the environmental factors because we
are typically the confounders and in
every analysis framework we wish to say
that the instrument is independent of
the confounders. That's why we wish to
say that the instrumental variables is
independent of the confounders. So in
other words, it's kind of randomized
because when we say something is
randomized, we would typically believe
that that thing is independent of other
variables. So,
>> yeah, it just seems to not obviously
hold true for humans, right? Just
straightforwardly be false.
>> I mean, yeah, for all of the reasons
that we're familiar with in genetics,
like genetic variation is not random
compared to
>> that's good point because as I said,
this is the belief and there are some
people disagree with mandization because
they don't believe that the genetic
virus are indeed randomized. So this
kind of debate but uh if you are happy
with the random meeting the random
meeting will give you the one motivation
to believe that gener factors are
randomized but that's not granted. Um,
thanks so much. And also just like for a
beautiful talk, I love all your emphasis
on um, all of the assumptions. Um, and I
was wondering for somebody who was new
to this field and you had a, you know,
well formulated research question and it
sort of seems like you were saying that
sometimes people don't have well
formulated research questions when they
come in, but let's say they did. Um, how
would they go about really doing that
work of working out what is the right
method? What are the right sorts of
assumptions? Are there like resources to
uh yeah to get up to mastery of that?
>> Yeah, thanks for the question. So I
think the main development of Emma is
actually all about assumptions. If you
look at the slides, so assumptions is
most important concept in causal
influence. Why we propose new methods is
because that we believe some assumptions
are violated. That's why we propose new
methods. But new methods comes with new
assumptions. So in to some extent you
can say that everything is about
assumptions. Sometimes we don't believe
the assumptions are satisfied. That's
why we do lots of sensitivity analysis.
We want to tell the audience that okay I
do lots of sensitivity analysis and
triangulation strategies based on
different assumptions. My results are
still stable. So in other words they
want to show that okay I don't know
which assumptions are correct but I do
many analysis use different assumptions
my results are still stable which means
that I think they satisfied all the
assumptions or this they this satis one
of the assumptions and I concl ation is
reliable. So that is the key idea. Um
yeah, I hope this answer the question.
Yeah,
>> great. And I think for time we'll end
there. Let's thank our speaker one more
time.