Hello class. Uh welcome to 18200. So if
you're in the right place, uh this is
principles of discrete applied math. Uh
I'll be one of your co- lectures. I'm
Ankor Mitra and the other co-lecture is
Peter Shore. So Peter, you want to stand
up and take a bow? [laughter]
So the basic topics that we're going to
be covering is we're going to top cover
topics like probability counting. This
will be the beginning part of the class.
Some of you have may have seen these
topics before, but really in the later
parts of the class, we're going to cover
some quite new things. We'll talk a lot
about generating functions, number
theory, uh cryptography, coding theory,
things like noless coding, uh linear
programming, and lots of other fun
topics. You know, I want to mention that
um I mean the goal for this class is to
try and teach you how to express proofs
in an understandable way. This is one of
these skills at MIT that uh you know you
can kind of pick up a little bit from
various classes along the way. But
sitting down and conscientiously
thinking about you know what makes a
proof easy to follow. you know, how to
make it more modular and understandable
for the audience is something that's
going to help you a lot with other uh
parts of math and also other parts of
computer science in general. A lot of
the things that go into good coding
practices in terms of modularity are the
same types of things we think about when
we're writing good proofs.
So, uh that's enough boilerplate uh for
me. Uh I can only go so long without
talking about math. So what we're going
to be talking about today is um we're
going to talk about uh the pigeon hole
principle. Actually first let me hand it
off to Susan who's going to tell you a
little bit more about the recitations
and then I'll take it away after that.
>> Thank you very much Anker. So as Anker
noted this is a CIM a communication
intensive class in the major and the
purpose of CAM is to help you to
communicate effectively as
mathematicians. That's for CIM. CIM's in
the math department. So, communicating
successfully in a new discipline
requires expertise in several different
domains. This is based on a model by
Anne Bowfort and we will give you we
will teach you in these different
domains over the course of this semester
in the recitations. So you need
expertise of course with the content and
so the recitations will be designed to
help you reinforce your understanding of
the mathematics in addition to other
aspects of communication. To communicate
successfully as a mathematician, you
need to know the norms of mathematics
because they vary. There are differences
between norms in core six and course and
norms in mathematics and you'll become
familiar with some of those. For
example,
what goes into the introduction of a
paper for the term paper. That'll be
basically a multi-page proof and we'll
tell you the differences what goes in
the introduction there. Um, also norms
of wording like how to use the word we.
Mathematicians use we in different ways
than some other disciplines.
You also to communicate successfully as
a mathematician. You also need expertise
with processes for generating effective
communication. That includes drafting.
We'll have multiple drafts built into
the term paper as well as things like
how to use latte and you'll start
learning that right off with the first
pet. If you're unfamiliar with latte,
please reach out. We can help you in
office hours.
You also need expertise
with rhetoric. And by this I mean um
rhetorical strategies, strategies for
accomplishing your goals as a
communicator.
For example, if mathematicians if they
have a complicated proof, one way to
communicate the logic clearly is to use
modularity, break the proof apart, pull
out a lema. Other strategies that you'll
learn in recitation are um how to
structure the um the ordering of
information within sentences within
sections within the paper to make the
paper flow well to reveal the flow of
the underlying logic so that readers can
easily follow the logic and also how to
use what we call guiding text to guide
readers through the logic. and we'll
give other strategies in recitation
also.
>> All right. Uh so back to me. So I'm
going to tell you the uh about one of
the first topics we're going to cover uh
in class which is um you know very
simple but powerful idea. We're going to
be discussing something called the
pigeon hole principle.
[clears throat] Now the pigeon hole
principle uh let me tell you the main
takeaways before we get into it. It's a
very simple idea. I'll tell you what
exactly it is and then we'll go through
some neat applications of it. Uh it
turns out to be shockingly powerful even
though you'll think of it as a very
obvious statement. I guess the other
thing which you know uh is important to
keep in mind it's also quite oddly
named.
I don't really know the entomology of
why it's called the pigeon hole
principle but um you know the basic idea
let's explain it through an example and
then I'll tell you about where the
pigeons come in. So uh here's a problem
that many of us face every day. So,
imagine that we have five colors of
socks
in your drawer
and it's, you know, early in the
morning, so you're trying to find a
match that you can get dressed and go to
work. And um you know, one of the basic
problems you could ask is how many socks
do you have to pick out from your drawer
to guarantee that even if you're very
very unlucky, no matter what, you must
have a match.
So this is really an example of the
pigeonal principle in action. Uh we'll
see why exactly it's the pigeonal
principle in a minute, but um any ideas?
So how many pairs how many socks do I
have to pull out so that I'm guaranteed
a pair?
>> Yeah.
six. Perfect. Because you know, you
could get very unlucky in the beginning
and your first five could be each
different colors and then no matter what
the sixth one is, it's going to match
with one of the ones you've selected so
far. This is, you know, really uh an
example of a much more general
principle. So, let me explain it with
pigeons and then we'll talk about some
more fun applications. So more
generally,
we can imagine that we've got n pigeons.
I'll even draw them for you.
And we're placing them
in m pigeon holes.
I don't know why they want to go in the
pigeon holes, but they do.
And let's imagine that n, our number of
pigeons, is strictly larger than m. Then
what I claim is that there must
be
at least two pigeons
in the same pigeon hole.
That's the pigeon hole principle.
Now, we're going to talk a lot about,
you know, how to write good proofs. And
honestly, a lot of us professors spend a
lot of time thinking about, you know,
how to teach in class and make it
engaging. I remember back when I used to
teach 042, you know, when I covered
things like the pigeonal principle,
there was a bit of an arms race between
faculty to come up with, you know, the
best props for, you know, how to explain
simple things. And I borrowed from one
of my colleagues, you know, a whole box
of fake dead pigeons, which was very
strange, right? because I was going down
the elevators in the status center with
my box of dead pigeons and I got a lot
of strange looks. You know, people would
ask me what's going on. And then I had
to explain to them that I'm teaching the
pigeon hole principle. I don't know why
it's called the pigeon hole principle.
But then someone asked me when I was on
the elevator, does that really help
people understand the pigeon hole
principle? And I got to say, I don't
think it does. You know, once you get
that question, you have to re-evaluate
your teaching preferences and
priorities. But in any case, this is the
pigeon hole principle. I don't know why
the pigeons want to go into the pigeon
holes, but you know, you can see how the
simple example of socks and finding a a
pair is an example of the pigeon hole
principle. You just have to be careful
about what are the pigeons and what are
the holes. In this case, it's pretty
obvious that, you know, the um the
pigeons are individual socks and the
holes are, you know, colors of different
socks. But there are other applications
that we're going to see where it's a
little bit more subtle how exactly to
get this principle to work. Let me tell
you one generalization which is also
powerful which is in general you know
imagine I had way more pigeons than
pigeon holes. It turns out you can
guarantee that there's at least the
ceiling of n over m pigeons in the same
pigeon hole. So this is a very simple
idea. Let's actually try and prove it
even though it might seem obvious. So it
turns out there's a very simple way to
prove it. Um you know this is one
example of a proof technique we're going
to see you know all throughout class
which is a proof by contradiction.
And you know I'm going to try and
practice what I preach in today's
lecture and show you what are the right
ways to write up proofs. Uh you know
this won't be quite as formal as you do
for your writing exercise but pretty
close. You know, you can see that the
first thing I'm doing when I write a
proof by contradiction is I'm putting,
you know, very clearly the fact that
it's a proof by contradiction. You don't
want your readers to be confused until
the very end where the pieces come
together. You want as much as possible
that they see the blueprint of how the
proof is supposed to go before they get
through all of it. Right? And so what
we're going to do is we're going to
suppose not we'll suppose that the
pigeon hole principle is false. Right?
Then what I can do is I can really just
count the number of pigeons and the
number of holes in two different ways,
right? So what I can do is, you know, n
is my number of pigeons. Now each pigeon
has to be assigned to some hole. So I
can sum over all of the different holes
h that I'm interested in. And I can look
at NH where NH here is just defined to
be the number of pigeons
that are in some particular hole h.
Right? So it's just a count of how many
pigeons ended up in that hole. And all
I'm doing is I'm just counting the
different pigeons in a different way. So
that's definitely equal to n. But now by
assumption, you know, since the pigeon
hole principle is false, I'm assuming
that each one of the holes
has at most one pigeon in it. Right? And
then the total number of holes I get is
m. So now what I claim is I have a
contradiction. Why? Because I've just
shown for you that if the pigeonal
principle is false, then n is less than
or equal to m. But what was my starting
assumption was just that n is strictly
larger than m. Right? So this is my
proof. But
m is larger than n. That's one of the
assumptions. And so we get a
contradiction.
That's it. That's our first proof in
this class. This is an example of how
you might write up a proof by
contradiction. A lot of times in class,
they'll be a lot more complicated than
this, but they all follow this basic
blueprint. Yes.
>> Ah, sorry. N is greater than m. Thank
you. n is greater than m.
Any other questions or that was it?
Okay, good. Feel free to interject any
time with questions. All right, let me
show you one other principle in action.
So, let's talk about some cooler
applications of the pigeon hole
principle. Now that we know what it is
and we know why it's true and we've seen
some simple illustrations of it,
um you know what I claim is that a lot
of times uh writing a good proof is also
about finding the right abstraction for
how to think about something, how to
model it, right? So let me give you a
simple lema that we're going to prove.
So first this lema isn't going to sound
like the pigeon hole principle, but
we'll turn it into the pigeon hole
principle. Let's imagine you're going to
a party. Let's say you're going to the
Super Bowl party this weekend. And
you've got n people.
There are n total people including
yourself at the party. What I claim is
that no matter, you know, who's there,
there are always two people, at least
two people
who know
the same number
of other people.
This is a mathematical fact about
parties, right? This doesn't quite look
like the pigeonal principle, but I claim
it is. And moreover, what we really need
is we need the right way to think about
this, right? And we'll practice this
type of skill a lot in recitations. You
know, this is an example of something
which is a lot easier to prove when you
have the right way to visualize it. So
it turns out that the right way to you
know visualize it is to draw a graph
namely something with nodes that
represent people at the party. So there
are n different nodes in my graph and
then there are edges that represent
different relationships whether the two
people know each other or not. So for
example, you know, I could have that the
people in my party look like they define
this graph. I've got four people in my
party. N equals 4. Again, as I
mentioned, each of these nodes are
people. They're individual people. And
these edges
represent
people who know each other.
And then when I draw in all my edges,
you know, maybe I'll end up with a graph
like this, right? And you can see that
there are two people who know the same
number of people at the party like this
node right here and this node right
here. The number of edges that are
incident to that node which represents
how many other people they know is both
two. So my lema is true in this simple
example. And now I can understand
through this visual you know how exactly
a graph relates to this lema that I
asserted to begin with.
So now uh we can actually prove it once
we have this abstraction in hand. So
let's talk about how that works.
Let me define one more quantity which
will be of interest for us today just
called the degree. That's just the
number of n uh edges that are incident
to a node.
So the degree
of a node
is the number of edges
incident to it
that share an endpoint that have that
node as an endpoint. So now let's try
and prove this using the pigeonal
principle. In fact, the crucial thing in
applying the pigeon hole principle is to
figure out what are the pigeons and what
are the holes. Does anyone have any idea
what we should make the pigeons be and
what we should make the holes be to try
and prove this lema?
>> Yeah,
>> maybe.
>> Okay, that's uh we could try that way. I
might have a little bit of difficulty
that way. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Okay. Because you know
where do I want the collision, right? So
the collision happens between two
pigeons who land in the same hole. So
what I want is I want two people to
collide. And what does it mean to
collide? I want them to have the same
degree. So that tells me what should be
the pigeons and what should be the
holes. So what I claim is that the
degree
of each note.
Well, first of all, it's an integer
that's in this set from zero one all the
way up to n minus one.
And uh you know each node is going to be
this
pigeon,
right? And the way that I'm going to
choose which particular hole it gets
mapped to is what the associated degree
is. So I have a hole. Each name is an
integer from 0 up to n minus one. And
then each particular node that
represents a person is going to get
mapped to whatever their degree is.
Right? So uh sounds like I'm done. Uh am
I done here? Can I just appeal to the
pigeon hole principle and say that two
nodes must collide?
>> Yeah,
>> set of possibility.
>> That's right. So, I'm definitely not
done right now. Right. Because the
pigeon hole principle only works when n
is strictly larger than m. That's when I
picked out six socks for my drawer and I
had five colors. I really needed one
more pigeon than the number of holes.
And the trouble is here, how many
pigeons do I have? Well, it's each node
in the graph. That's the number of the
people at the party. That's n. How many
holes do I have? Well, unfortunately,
that's also n because it's the integers
from 0 to n minus one. But now we need a
clever idea. So I wonder is it possible
to have a node of degree zero and a node
of degree n minus one at the same time.
So who can help me out? Yeah.
>> Well, that means you know everybody and
then
that's a cross prediction.
>> That's perfect. Exactly right. Let me
say it again because I have the mic. So
if there's someone at the party who
knows n minus one people, well there's
nodes and that means he's connected to
every other node and that means there
isn't anyone at the party who knows no
one. So actually these two end points
are mutually exclusive, right? They
can't both happen.
So if I wanted to write this out
formally as a proof, I would actually
have to do a case analysis here, right?
In order to create my contradiction, I
would say, you know, case number one,
there is a node of degree n minus one.
In which case, that means there's no
node of degree zero. And I'm back down
to having n minus one holes and n
pigeons. And then I can appeal to the
pigeon hole principle and call it a day.
And in case two, where there's no node
of degree n minus one, again, I only
have n minus one possibilities for the
holes. So, you know, I'm not going to be
able to write up the full-blown proofs
when we do them in lecture, but you can
see that to really make this a full
bulletproof proof, there are a lot of
steps that go into how exactly you can
lay out the proof, right? So, I'll just
stop here and say that, you know, can't
be both
degree n minus one and zero. And that
lets us appeal to the pigeon hole
principle.
So we're good. So this is another
example of the pigeon hole principle in
action even though it doesn't look like
it at first because you have to figure
out what's the right abstraction, namely
a graph for how to think about and
visualize what's actually happening
underneath this lema.
Let's do another example. We're going to
get harder and harder unfortunately.
Uh so let me give you another of my
favorite examples of the pigeon hole
principle in action.
which is a very easy to state problem
but turns out to be very difficult from
a complexity standpoint.
So let's imagine let me tell you the
statement of this lema and then we'll
get into how exactly to prove it.
Suppose I give you
fourdigit numbers,
positive numbers.
Let's just call them x1 up to x20.
Right? Then what I claim is that there
are
two disjoint
sets of them
and I'll say specifically non-MPT
sets with the same sum.
So what am I asking here? Right? So I
give you any 24-digit numbers. they have
to be strictly positive.
And what I'm going to do is um I'm going
to take some subset of them, maybe x1
plus x3 plus x5. And then I'll take some
other subset of them that doesn't
overlap in any of those integers, x2 and
x4 and x6. And what I claim is that
there's a way of doing this so that the
sum of the integers in one set is equal
to the sum of the integers in the other
set.
Now, moreover, this would be sort of a
trivial lema if I let these sets be
empty because I could just take the
empty set for one and the empty set for
the other. They're definitely disjoint.
They don't share anything in common. And
their sum is zero. So, this would be a
really boring way for this lema to be
true. What I'm saying by non-empt is I'm
ruling out that trivial case. There's
always an interesting way to do this
where you've really created a positive
sum for these integers two different
ways.
All right. So let's try and prove this
and then I'll tell you some interesting
facts about this uh this very simple
statement.
And again what we have to do to you know
write up a proof here is we have to do
the usual things where we have to figure
out what the pigeons are what the holes
are but moreover we have to figure out
the right you know mathematical notation
for expressing what's going on in this
problem. Right?
And so in fact a lot of times the first
step is really to figure out some
mathematical way to express the
statement right here that I've written
out in English. So another way to think
about this is that I claim there are
sets I and J which are subsets of the
integers from one up to 20. What are
these subsets supposed to represent?
just which of the numbers I'm taking in
my sum. I want that, you know, these
sets are both non-mpt. So I and J had
better not be equal to the empty set. I
need that they're disjoint, which just
says that the intersection between I and
J is equal to the empty set. So this is
just the mathematical way of expressing
all of the things I have here. And now
for the most important piece of the
puzzle. I want that the sum over all of
the x subi in this first set is equal to
the sum of all of the x subjs in the
second set. Right? So a lot of times
it's hard to write a mathematical proof
unless you have the right mathematical
notation to begin with because even
though I could have expressed this in
English now to actually prove this
statement I'm going to have to do a
bunch of manipulations on these sets and
this will be a lot easier with this
notation in hand. So, you know, another
thing that we're going to teach you a
lot in recitation is how exactly to set
up convenient notation so that your
proofs will be easier to write, right?
All right. So now, how exactly are we
going to prove this?
Let's see if you guys have any
intuition. So, obviously, we're going to
be using the pigeonal principle because
I've only taught you one thing so far,
so we better use it. Um but what should
we use as
you know the pigeons?
Yeah.
>> Ah [sighs]
okay you're right but for the holes I
think. So let's be care. Yeah. So I'll
take your answer for the holes because
the way to think about it is that we
want a collision among the pigeons. So
we really want a collision among what
objects? Was there a answer in the back?
Yeah.
Yeah. Uh, I like that. I'm going to
strike number of and let's just say
subsets because really it's the subsets
that I care about. Each one of them is a
pigeon. But perfect. All right. So,
that's exactly what the pigeons will be.
They'll just be the appropriate subsets.
So, in particular, I want them to be
non-MPY subsets. You know, that's
definitely one of the constraints I have
in this uh constraint on I and J right
here. I'll have to worry about this
disjointness constraint later and we'll
get to that. And then exactly as you
guys already mentioned, the holes are
going to be the possible sums. That's
exactly right.
So, you know, what can we say about the
possible sums, right? So let's say that
um the number of possible sums let's
just call that m I can just come up with
an upper bound right because I just need
to show that the number of holes is
smaller than the number of pigeons and
definitely an upper bound on this is you
know the largest that the sum can be
which is the sum from i= 1 to 20 of x
subi and this is comfortably less than
you know uh 20 *
10 4 which is strictly less than 10 6.
Was there a question here? No. Okay. All
right. So now we're in business because
we can try and appeal to the pigeon hole
principle again, right? But we have to
be a little bit careful here, right? So
what this is going to do is that um you
know the number of uh non-MPT subsets
well this is equal to
2 to the 20 minus one. So the way to
think about this and we'll talk more
about this when we get into counting is
really through what's called a bjection.
We'll do lots of examples of bjections,
but the way to think about that is that
each subset of the integers from 1 to 20
is really associated with a bit string.
The first coordinate, which is one or
zero, tells you whether the first
element is in the set or not. The second
entry in that string tells you whether
the second element is in it and so on.
So app priori there are 2 to the 20
possibilities because for each
coordinate I have the choice of whether
I include it or don't include it in my
subset. This minus one is because I want
the subset to be non-mpy. So I have to
rule out the subset that takes nothing.
Right? So this is still comfortably much
larger than 10 the 6. So now I'm in good
shape because n is strictly larger than
m. But there's a catch. So what exactly
does this imply? It implies when I use
the pigeon hole principle that there
exists non empty
A which is not equal to B, right?
Because there are different pigeons that
end up in the same pigeon hole. And yet
the sum is equal. The sum of all of the
X I's in the set A is equal to the sum
of all of the XJS in the set B. Right?
So I'm not done yet. Why am I not done?
Yes,
>> because the sets might not be
>> the sets might not be disjoint. Right?
So I haven't proven what I promised you
because I didn't meet this condition.
Also notice something about how I wrote
this proof, right? So I did not use I
injist
this inj and I already know that I'm not
done. So I left myself some slack in the
notation for me to later choose what I
inj should be. You know if I had made
these things be INJ, I would have really
confused my audience, right?
So, how exactly can we now make these
things disjoint? I claim we're almost
home. We just have to fix what A and B
are. So, anyone who hasn't answered yet,
have a fix for how I can fix A and B.
So, I've gotten most of it, they're non-
empty. Uh, have you answered yet? No.
Okay. All right.
>> Take the intersection of A and B and you
intersection from both sets.
>> That's right. That's right. So here,
let's think about a baby version of this
first before we explain it, you know,
with all of the full-blown mathematical
notation, right? You know, A and B might
not be disjoint because maybe they share
one element in common. Maybe they both
contain X1.
But then the point is that, you know,
these two sums are equal and they both
have an X1 in them. So I can just remove
that common element and then I'm
removing that X1 from the sum. when I
take it out, I've made the sets be
disjoint because they no longer share
that element in common. And yet, I
haven't changed the fact that the sums
are equal even though I've changed the
sums themselves. Right? So, that's, you
know, the rest of the proof. You're
exactly right. So, let's uh finish up
with that proof.
So the problem
is
A and B need not
be disjoint.
Now I'm deliberately trying to explain
you know a bit of like how I think about
the pedagogy of explaining these proofs
not just the proofs themselves. See one
of the things I could have done you know
for proving this is I could have just
told you what I want
you know a i and j to be. So in fact
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
define
uh you know i is equal to a minus b and
b j is equal to b minus a. So what this
notation means is I take my set A and I
remove every element that shows up in B
from that set and whatever I have left
over with is I. Now notice B does not
have to be a subset of A for this to
make sense. If B contains an element
that isn't an A, I just ignore that
element. It wasn't there before and I
keep it out of my set. But if B and A
both contain the element, then I I
remove it. So you can think about this
pictorially, right? You know, maybe
these two sets, you know, A and B, they
look like this. And so what is my set I
going to look like? It's going to be
exactly this shaded region right here
because they're, you know, I'm taking
out everything that belongs to B and
removing it from my set so that I create
two disjoint things. So this right here
would be I and this right here would be
J.
So let's think a little bit about
pedagogy again, right? You see how this
visual helps me understand what's going
on mathematically in the notation. If I
just define for you what a minus b is.
That's a perfectly valid definition,
right? But a lot of times these visuals
can help people understand them more
easily. And if you notice the other
thing I did in terms of writing up this
proof, I could have actually skipped
this entire discussion about what
happens when I choose A and B. I could
have jumped first to I and J, right? I
could have said A and B come from this
pigeonal principle and then I could have
defined I as A minus B and J as B minus
A. But then you would have missed the
point about why I needed to do that. So
in fact when you're writing up proofs
not everything you write is
mathematically necessary but a lot of
times it's pedagogically very useful
because you can walk the reader through
not just the formal verification that
the statement is true but how exactly
you arrived at the proof yourself.
Right? And the missteps you made along
the way, but that led you to the right
answer. All right? So, finishing this
up, we can just, you know, the rest of
it is just notation. So, when we look at
this expression, the sum over all x i in
the set a, we can break this up into two
pieces, right? It's the sum for all i
that are in both a and b of x i. And
it's the sum of all x i for i that
belongs to my set a i. capital i, which
is the things that belong here. So I'm
just taking the sum over this entire set
a and I'm breaking it up into this piece
right here and this piece right here.
But now by assumption I know using the
pigeon hole principle that this is the
same thing as the sum from
all i and b of x i. And I can break this
sum up the same way. It's the sum of all
I in the intersection
of X I plus the sum of all of these
things in my set capital J. Right? So
I'm just breaking up the sum two
different ways. And now when I take this
equation that the whole thing is equal,
I can just cross off these two pieces
because they're the same thing. And that
gives me what I want. These sets I and J
are definitely disjoint because I've
made them be disjoint and they have the
same sum. You should double check that
you never end up with these things being
non-MP and you know that's a
technicality you have to check but it is
true and it follows from the assumptions
but that's you know the end of our next
proof right so are there any questions
make sense?
Yeah,
>> the like
the minimum like number
>> it's about the minimum. Uh but since you
asked, let me tell you something
interesting about this, right? This lema
is very easy to state. It's not so bad
to prove. We proved it pretty quickly.
What's kind of shocking is, you know, I
can write down 24digit numbers for you.
And you would have no you could prove to
yourself using this proof right here
that there are two subsets whose sum is
the same. But it would be very hard to
actually find them. So you can do this
for example with like populations of
different countries. We know that there
are you know subsets of countries that
have literally the same number of people
but you know it would be exhaustive to
try and search all possible subsets to
figure out which pair collide and we
don't actually know any faster
algorithms and you know it's related to
some things in cryptography. All right
any other questions?
Make sense? so far. All right.
All right. So, we got to do our hardest
result today and then I'll do a uh fun
end for one of my favorite applications,
the pigeon hole principle.
So, let's do our hardest theorem. Uh,
and I'm going to, you know, tell you
it's the hardest result because I'm
going to call it a theorem.
And we'll be talking about extensions of
this, you know, on your first pet set.
So, you'll get more practice with this
proof.
But let me tell you about a beautiful
result in combinotaurics.
Right? What I claim is that in any
permutation,
I'll tell you what I mean by that in a
second. We'll be talking much more about
permutations later. Any permutation of
the integers 1 2 3 all the way up to
something n * m + one. What I claim is
that there is
an increasing subsequence
of length
m + one or a decreasing
subsequence
of length.
n + one. Okay, so I owe you a bunch of
things to explain what this theorem
means. Yes,
>> I'll get to that, but no, it's not. So
that's one of the things I owe you. But
first, let's start with the simpler
thing. So I owe you this, right? What do
I mean by a permutation? So what I mean
is you can take these integers 1 2 3 all
the way up to nm + one, right? n and m
are just parameters in this theorem
statement and instead of considering
them all in increasing order I can put
all of the numbers in any order I want.
So basically I take this deck of cards
and I shuffle it and I consider any
possible ordering. That's what I mean by
permutation. We'll talk more about them
formally later when we get to counting.
But you know I take any ordering for
these integers. And what I claim is that
there's some sort of subsequence where
the where the numbers are going up by
one at least at least one each time and
that's long or if not there's some long
subsequence where the numbers are going
down at least by one each time. So let's
do an example because I should really be
more precise by what I mean by a
subsequence. So let's take for example
m= n= 3. So then I'm really just asking
for a permutation of the integers from
one up to 10. So some shuffling of that
deck of cards. Let's take an example. We
could take 3 2 1 6 5 4
9 8 7 and then 10.
So now an example of a long increasing
sequence is this one right here. I take
three, then I take six, then I take
nine, and then I take 10. So this
sequence does not have to be contiguous.
These these positions I'm interested in
don't have to be right next to each
other. But what I want is that when I
consider the sequence of integers just
in those positions where I've put the
arrows, that the corresponding sequence
I get is strictly increasing as I go up
the arrows. So that's an increasing
subsequence. So I can also think about
having a decreasing one like 321 and
that's the longest decreasing
subsequence I can get here. So you can
see that this example illustrates a you
know it helps me understand what exactly
these abstract definitions mean like a
permutation and an increasing
subsequence. It also tells me something
even more powerful which is that this
theorem really is tight. Right? Because
in the case where n= m= 3, what I'm
promising you is that there is a length
for increasing subsequence or there's a
length for decreasing subsequence. And
even though I found one that has length
four and is increasing, what I claim in
this simple example is that I can't
create anything longer. And I can't even
create a decreasing subsequence that's
longer than three. Right? Because if I
did 321, then I'm in trouble. Everything
after it is larger. If I do 654 again,
I'm in trouble. Everything after it is
larger. All right, any questions?
So, I claim that we can prove this using
the pigeon hole principle, but we're
going to have the same difficulties we
usually have, which is where are the
pigeons and where are the holes. In
fact, it'll be even more abstract
because if you try and guess things
like, you know, the sequences are the
pigeons or the positions are the
pigeons, you're going to have a hard
time. That's not how this proof is going
to go. Instead, we're going to need a
very delicate definition to tell us
where the pigeons are and you know how
this relates to the pigeon hole
principle.
And the idea basically is that um you
know I can't like this theorem if you
think about it is not telling me which
of them I have whether I have a long
increasing or a long decreasing
sequence. So in some sense what I want
to do is I want to keep track of my
progress on both of them. How long is my
largest increasing subsequence? How long
is my largest decreasing sequence? And I
want to see how those progress measures
grow.
So the proof is going to involve this
very careful you know definition
is you know let's consider
these integers in order and let's
consider the
sith elements
in the sequence
and what we're going to do
is we're going to define these helper
variables. So we're going to let I subs
denote the length
of the longest
increasing
subsequence
ending
at the eth ess.
Okay, that's one progress measure. I is
for increasing. So I've chosen, you
know, notation that uh at least has a
pneummonic associated with it. I have DS
is going to be the same thing, but it'll
be the longest decreasing
subsequence, but again ending at the
Sith location.
Okay,
so uh this is my progress measure. In
fact, this is a little bit abstract. So
let's see what it looks like in this
particular example just to make sense of
it.
So for example in the example we already
did I can plot you know how I and D
change
as a function of uh
oh let's see okay so what I can do is
I'm going to consider this sequence 5 2
4 3 6 1 just to keep it interesting.
And now what I can do is when I look at
each one of these positions, I can look
at this progress measure of what's the
longest increasing sequence that ends at
that position. So when I start off,
what's the longest increasing sequence
that ends at this first position
occupied by five? One.
What's the longest decreasing? It's one,
right? And now if I instead, you know,
consider the position two. So if I
consider the second position that has
the element two in it, what is the
longest increasing subsequence that ends
at that position that includes this
value two? Any ideas? This just a matter
of using the definition, but the
definition requires a little bit of
unwrapping.
Any ideas?
One. Perfect. That's one.
because the longest increasing sequence
that ends and includes two. Well, if I
include two, I can't include five
because it's supposed to be increasing.
What about this position right here? So,
what should I fill in for this entry in
the table? Two. Perfect. So, I can keep
track of this, right? If instead I end
at the position four, then I can include
two. So, I'm fine. Uh here my longest
decreasing would be 54. And I can keep
track of this progress measure. I'll get
2 3 3 1 1 4. Okay. And now you know
here's the key for how it relates to the
pigeon hole principle. What I claim is
that for two locations S and T that are
different from each other. I claim that
this pair is S Ds is not equal to the
pair it T DT. Okay,
so that's the key
and if we can show this, this is really
the heart of the proof because you know
this sequence goes on for you know
roughly n * m length
and you know if my pigeon hole principle
if my the sequence statement were false
and I could only get a value of like n
here and a value of m here then I just
wouldn't have enough possibilities to
pre you know to avoid a collision.
So you can put the pieces of it
together, but this is really the heart
of the proof is proving this statement.
So let's prove this. This is not a hard
statement to prove, but it's a hard
statement to guess is the right way to
go about it. So how are we going to
prove this thing?
So first,
does anyone know what this term right
here means? WLG.
Just out of curiosity. Yeah. Without
loserelli. Okay. So, you know, I told
you that when I was proving things with
um you know, the number of people in a
party that I had to do this case
analysis. Well, to prevent my proof from
being too long, let me just pretend s is
larger than t because you know, if it
was the other way around, I would just
switch what's s and what's t. So yeah,
>> why
wouldn't the most the longest increasing
one with six as the last one be six and
two?
>> Sorry. Uh which entry in the table here?
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Three and six.
>> Okay. All right. So here, right? So uh
we want the longest increasing sequence
that ends at three. that six.
>> So do you want this entry in the table?
Okay. So the longest increasing one that
ends at six. So what would it be?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So it's not required to be
contiguous but it has to include that
end point. So that's why these numbers
you know are not u monotonically
increasing right. So when I have the
longest decreasing sequence that ends at
three, you know, that's pretty long,
right? Because I could go 5 43 and end
there. But as soon as I move over to
this next column right here, if I have
to end at six, that that that makes the
longest decreasing sequence only of
length one. So the key is that I'm
fixing that my end point has to belong
to that subsequence and I'm considering
progress as I go, you know, left to
right. So any other questions? This is a
crucial part. If you don't understand
the table, you won't understand the
proof. Good. All right. So without loss
generality, S is larger than T, right?
And so let's do the following. So if the
element
at the Sith location
is strictly larger than the elements
at the tth
location,
what I claim is that is at least it t +
1.
It's the morning and I'm lazy. So, who
can prove this for me and and justify
this? Why is this true? Someone who
hasn't answered. Especially my back row
is very quiet.
Yeah,
that's exactly right. So, let me say
that again. Right. So, we can just use
the increasing sequence subsequence that
ended at the tth location. And because
the element at the sth location is after
the one that happens at the tth location
because s is larger than t and the
element itself is bigger too. I can just
append that element and make my
subsequence longer. Right? All right. So
how does the rest of the proof go? Um
who can fill in the rest of the proof
for me?
So this is one case in the case
analysis. Right? I've said without loss
generality s is larger than t and um you
know if the element at the sith location
is larger than the element at the tth
location my is at least it t + one
>> uh yeah
>> uh you do the same thing with generality
s instead the element at the s location
is less than the element at e location
then you can do the same for um
ds and d
>> perfect that's
And it's basically the same reasoning
but backwards. So otherwise in
particular if the element at the sith
location is strictly less than the
element at the tth location, I can just
take the decreasing subsequence that
ends at the tth location and append what
happens at the sith location. That's
smaller. So that's a valid decreasing
sequence. And that's the proof, right? I
just proved for you that these two pairs
of integers are different because I
showed you that either this one is
larger than this or this one is larger
than this. Right? And now we're in good
shape because you know how does the
entire thing you know work. So just
returning to the proof putting it all
together
even though I sort of said it in words
let's just be precise about it.
So returning to the proof.
Let's suppose the theorem is false
for the purposes of contradiction.
Right? Then what I claim is that there
are
at most nm possible
values
for these pairs is ds, right? Because
that's what it means for the theorem to
be false. There's no n +1 length
increasing subsequence. There's no
length m plus one decreasing
subsequence. When I look at my pairs of
integers, is never becomes larger than n
and ds never becomes larger than m.
Right? And these are, you know, my holes
is because each one of the possible
positions is going to get mapped just by
this definition that I gave you right
here of isds to the signature of these
pair of integers. That just tells me the
name of my hole. But you know how long
is my sequence? There are n m + one
values in the sequence. These are all my
pigeons.
Which by the pigeon hole principle means
there is s not equal to t with
that collide in some hole with is ds
equal to it dt. That's what it means for
them to collide to the same hole because
they get mapped to the same thing. And
we know that that's impossible, right?
But this is impossible.
So that contradicts the assumption we
made at the beginning which was just
that the theorem was false. Yes.
>> Without loss of generality step, why are
we comparing um if I plus one instead of
directive?
>> Uh sorry, say it again. So why are we
comparing uh
>> compare that to I of T + one instead of
tot? Okay, so just to be careful right
here, this is I subt and then plus one
is outside.
>> Yeah. So this is really just saying that
whatever my length of my increasing
sequence is right here, this value right
here, I can add one to the length. So
the plus one is not in the subscript.
>> Does that make sense?
>> Um why not?
>> Would it hold true that is is strictly
greater than I or
>> uh is is strictly greater? Yes,
definitely. is is definitely strictly
greater than it because these are
integers.
>> Yeah. In fact, you know, is is not
necessarily equal to it + one because
there might be some totally different
other subsequence that's way longer that
just doesn't involve what happens at the
tth location. But all right, any other
questions? This was our hardest proof
for today. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, the pigeons, this is why I
told you you have to be a little bit
careful with this, right? The pigeons
are actually the positions.
So what's happening here is each one of
these positions, the first element, the
second element, the third element, the
fourth element, the fifth, the sixth,
these are my pigeons. How are they
getting mapped to a hole? Is I map them
to the hole whose name is this integer,
this integer.
>> It's just the Paris right here.
>> It's the Paris. So my holes that's why I
drew the little hole right there is that
this is the name of the hole and by
assumption if the theorem is false is
doesn't go larger than N ds doesn't go
larger than m so there are at most n*
you know m possibilities for this
yeah
>> maybe you could have guessed this kind
of thing
as a product
>> but like if
I guess if it didn't have this like nice
type.
>> Yeah.
>> How how would you
>> math is hard? [laughter]
I mean, we're teaching you things which
like, you know, we're not going to give
you this on a test and ask you to
miraculously guess it. But for example,
we will ask you on the pet set to do a
version of this with, you know, three
types of subsequences. and you're gonna
have this as a blueprint to go off of to
try and understand, you know, what's
going on. So, this would be
extraordinarily clever if you just came
up with this on the spot. There are also
twists to very simple problems that will
make things very difficult and open, but
um yeah, let's go with it. All right,
any other questions?
Good. All right. Yeah.
>> Well, okay. That's maybe a bit of um a
digression but you know basically if I
like this really mimics if you've taken
algorithms classes like a dynamic
programming type of solution because you
know if I want to know what is the
longest subsequence that ends here I
really want to piece it together by
answers to sub problems before and this
often has this structure is that you
know once I tell you that the
subsequence includes this element and
it's increasing I don't actually have to
know anything else about which elements
belong to it. I just have to know it's
increasing and its length and the fact
that it belongs to it in order to be
able to piece together what happens to
the rest. So this you know a lot of
these things in mathematics they really
mimic what we do algorithmically in
terms of how we would go about finding
it. And we'll see that more and more in
class. That's true even when it comes to
like writing proof and writing code.
Okay. Good. All right. So, let's do uh
one of my favorite examples
um of the pigeon hole principle.
Does anyone want to be my victim?
Oh, boy. You guys volunteered very
quickly. [laughter]
All right. Uh sure. Can you tell me
about You can stay there. Uh can you
tell me something about yourself? Um you
know, where you're from, what your name
is, introduce yourself to the class.
>> I'm Anthony. I'm from St. Louis,
Missouri. Um
uh I don't know.
>> Do you have any hobbies?
>> Uh
oh. Um I have a two letter curve.
>> Okay.
Wow. All right. [laughter]
There are not many possibilities for
that one. All right. Now I can uh just
based on that using my MIT superpowers
I can tell you something deeply personal
about your you know life history
in your family tree. It's not a tree and
I know that for a fact. So we're going
to prove that using the pigeon hole
principle. I should confess that I once
used this in 042 and I asked for a
volunteer or a victim. That's why I call
it a victim now. And uh you know the
girl raised her hand and told me a bit
about herself and I told her you know
your family tree is not a family tree.
And then she got very red and she said I
know.
And I've been a little bit scared to use
this since then. So that's why I call it
a victim. So you signed up for it. But
it's not really just true about you.
It's true about everyone in class. It's
just a mathematical fact that follows
from some very basic axioms of biology.
things which are you know
you really can't poke holes in and it's
true for all of us. So let me tell you
about this fun application of the pigeon
hole principle. First let me state you
know the lema and then we'll figure out
as usual like how to model it and how
exactly to think about it as pigeons and
holes. So you know what I claim
is that everyone everyone's
family tree
contains
someone
whose parents are blood relatives.
It's just true.
Okay. So now I'm just going to assert
some you know very incontrovertible
things biologically that are pretty safe
but this will be enough to be able to
prove this fact.
So let's you know do the setup for this.
So what are the axioms we're using? So
first of all, you know, everyone
has
two biological parents.
Of course, if I removed biological, it
would be more complicated, but I'm just
saying this biologically. Everyone has
two biological parents.
Uh, no one
has children
after 100.
Seems pretty safe.
Uh, the human race
is at least 4,000 years old.
That's a very safe assumption.
And this is something that can be you
know checked by a bi biologist is that
um you know we have upper bounds for the
number of total humans who've ever
lived. What I claim is that there are at
most 10 the 12 humans who've lived all
throughout history
and just from these axioms I claim that
we can prove this.
So let's prove it
and we have to figure out the right
mathematical abstraction for how to
think about this. Right? It's the same
way as the you know friends at a party
where we had this way of thinking about
it as degrees in a graph right and what
we can do here is we can do the same
kind of thing but we can trace back our
family tree right
in essence what I'm doing when I trace
back this family tree is I'm defining a
whole bunch of nodes who have jobs or
roles in your family tree. So there's
you at the start. Then if I trace it
back, you have your parents.
If I trace it back further,
I have your grandparents.
And when I do this, right,
I'm going to trace this back at least
40 generations, right? Because human
history is at least 4,000 years old and
no one has children, you know, after a
100. So I get at least that my depth,
you know, is at least 40. So what this
means
is that there are at least 2 to the 40
nodes in this abstract family tree which
are just job descriptions right you know
your maternal father of your you know I
mean all the way back of uh tracing all
the possibilities
and the trouble is that um you know but
2 to the 40 is larger
is strictly larger than 10 cub raised to
the 4th power, right? Because 2 10 is
larger than a thousand.
And so this is larger than the number of
nodes all of the possibilities all the
possible humans in human history. So by
the pigeonal principle what we get is
that at least
two nodes two jobs get mapped
to the same person.
So that's pretty cool. This is just a
mathematical fact that uh you can use on
your friends to annoy them. Um please
don't do that.
Uh so this is what I wanted to tell you
about the pigeon hole principle. Now as
I told you we're going to be covering a
bunch of introductory topics in the
first few lectures. So you know pigeon
hole principle will get more practice on
the pet sets. Uh we're actually going to
be spending the next couple of lectures
on probability and then counting. So
we'll also be talking a little bit about
elementary probability in the first
recitation the first homework. So let me
tell you at least about the formalisms
for probability and then we're going to
go into a lot more detail over the next
couple lectures that I'll be explaining.
So let me tell you about you know
probability just as an intro for later
lectures.
Um and we're going to connect all of
this obviously to counting as well.
So basically in class especially for our
later topics everything is going to be
built on counting one way or another.
uh we're going to use it for all kinds
of fun things,
but let me give you a little bit of
motivation before we get there. So,
we're going to be focusing mostly on
discrete probability.
So, why study discrete probability?
Well, it's very useful for things like,
you know, counting.
uh you want to understand you know basic
setups like um you know what are the
chances of creating certain kinds of
objects that are nice when you choose an
object at random. Uh that's very related
to counting and it's intertwined with
you know basic questions about
probability. You know, later when we do
more advanced topics, we're going to use
probability in really cool ways to show
the existence of very strange, you know,
objects that are otherwise hard to
construct. And we're going to be doing
this through something called the
probabilistic method.
It's another example where you can use
the language of probability to show that
these very strange objects exist even
though no one knows how to find any
particular one. So it's kind of like the
way that we reasoned about those subsets
of sums of 20 of uh four-digit numbers
that we knew that there were subsets
whose sum was the same without actually
knowing which ones.
Uh later when we talk a little bit more
about, you know, some topics in
algorithms,
you know, things like primality testing
using some of the elementary number
theory that we do, deciding whether a
given huge integer is prime or not.
It'll turn out that fundamentally these
algorithms are randomized. So really to
reason about it, we'll have to have the
language of probability to begin with.
And you know much later in class uh when
we talk about things like you know
coding theory we're going to use
probability intrinsically to model types
of communication
for example when there's noise between
us like when a satellite is sending
images back to earth you know what are
ways to reliably communicate in the face
of you know errors that are introduced
when one party's communicating with the
other so we're going to use probability
in all of these different contexts.
I want to give you a little bit of the
setup for um you know probability before
we get into a lot of the you know key
rules and definitions next time.
So probability
even though [clears throat] it's
familiar to all of us it uses some very
powerful abstractions and definitions.
So the most important of which is what's
called the sample space.
So in a basic probabilistic setup the
way to think about it is that you know
points in the sample space.
We associate them with you know possible
outcomes
things that can happen
out of the range of all possibilities.
You know, just to do a familiar example,
we could do something like, you know,
roll a dieice.
And if it's a,
you know, normal die, we have six
possibilities. That's our sample space
because that describes all of the
possible things that could happen. What
number shows up?
Now, the important thing is not just
what's the range of possibilities, but
really, you know, what's the likelihood
of each of these different outcomes.
Um so to each point
X in the sample space we're going to
assign
some probability P of X which has the
following properties. These are all very
intuitive. So we need that the
probability is non- negative and this
should be true for all points in the
sample space. And we want that in total
the sum of all the probabilities over
the entire sample space
is one. So these are the things that
define you know the setup for basic
probability. We have a sample space and
we have this probability associated with
each one of the outcomes. We can
certainly do simple examples like
rolling a dice. If it's a fair die then
each one of these possibilities has one
sixth probability. We're going to do a
lot more exotic examples in class. you
know, things where the sample space
might be infinite. That's perfectly
fine. We can still have these axioms
hold. Um, you know, an example of
something we might be interested in is
the number of times we flip a coin
before we see our first heads. That in
principle can go on, you know, forever.
There's no bound on how large that
sample space is. And we can still talk
about all of the basic axioms of
probability and and reason about things.
Um, and we'll be particularly interested
in what are called events.
So events are just subsets of the sample
space.
They're just some subset of
possibilities. And in that case we can
think about this probability of the
entire event as just the sum of all of
the individual outcomes that land in
this event their total probability.
Right?
So for example you could think about an
event like uh you know rolling an even
number.
That's not just one possible outcome in
the sample space, but you know it's the
set 2 46.
And uh you know the last you know little
baby piece of um you know background is
that we'll also be interested in you
know complements
of events.
So for example I could look at the
probability of you know t bar. Sometimes
you'll see it written as not T as well.
And that's just you know everything that
you know is in the sample space outside
the set T. So for example this is
defined as all of the points and the
outcome space that don't occur in this
original event. Um so we can define this
notion of complimentary events which is
you know everything else besides the
events in T. Uh you know basic fact is
that a lot of these things behave the
way you'd expect them to. So the
probability of the complement is just
one minus the probability of the event
itself. There's a very simple proof. Um
we can we're going to stop now but I'll
tell you a little bit about what we're
going to be doing next time. So now that
we know at least the basic definitions
for probability theory, we're going to
be talking about conditional probability
which is always something that's very
counterintuitive. So we're going to
define what conditional probabilities
are. I'll tell you some of the basic
results in conditional probability and
then I'm going to give you a lot of fun
examples of um you know how people get
conditional probability wrong. So there
are a lot of famous examples like the
Monty Hall problem that many of you may
have seen. Uh you know for me this was
always a little bit abstract like it's a
cute mathematical puzzle but I'm going
to give you some scarier examples of you
know real world things that happen with
doctors where they misinterpret
conditional probabilities. So, we'll do
that next time and I'll tell you some
personal stories about that one. So, see
you on Thursday.