(air whooshing)
(intriguing orchestral music)
- So the main research challenge
that we were trying to
address with Thermochromorph
is how do we create multicolored images
that transition into each other?
How do we add more expressivity
to these color changing effects
beyond just single color to
single color transitions?
We're creating this multicolor
CMYK printmaking process
with thermochromic inks.
The printmaking process that we're using
is called relief printing,
and it's this really
traditional form of printmaking
that existed hundreds of years ago.
The main reason why we wanted
to focus on relief printing
was because we wanted to minimize
the material requirements
and set-up times.
Instead of using regular inks,
we use fully thermochromic inks.
There are thermochromic inks
that go from clear to color at
some activation temperature,
and inks that go from color to clear
at the same activation temperature.
So by taking advantage of those materials
with special properties
and using both color to
clear and clear to color,
CMYK thermochromic inks,
we're able to create these images
that shift into each other.
And it can be used for a
number of application areas
from artistic to more
functional use cases.
So, for example, maybe
you have a stove-top
with these prints on top of it
that communicates when the top is too hot.
What we've explored so far
are small-scale applications
on the order of just handheld prints,
but I think that we can apply this process
to say large-scale
installations or signage,
but you can imagine a billboard
that changes the appearance,
depending on the time of day.
And because the sun is
this natural heat source,
you don't even have to use
special electronics or anything
to see the visual change.
I'm really excited to see a world
where we can have more
interactive materials and objects
that can visually respond dynamically
to properties like human touch.
And by providing this
printmaking process for people,
we can empower everyday users
to create objects with those properties.