We have many uninsured individuals in
America, about 30 million uninsured
individuals. You might ask, well, is
that worth doing thing about? We
probably have more than 30 million
people who don't have beautiful flat
screen televisions. Are really going to
do something about that? You got supply,
demand, the market works. Healthcare,
there's a number of problems. For
example, if I don't get health insurance
and as a result I get sick and I come in
here today and I cough on you and you
get sick, then I've imposed a cost on
you that I'm not incurring. We call that
an externality.
>> That's a problem with the healthcare
market. Economic models work best when
markets are competitive. When there's
many competitors trying to compete for
your business, that's not true in
healthcare. If you're a hospital on
Nantucket, you got a monopoly. You're
the hospital. There's no competition.
People aren't going to take a ferry to
get their heart attack dealt with. For
all these reasons, we need to bring in
the tools, other tools to help think
about how we fix problems in the
healthcare markets.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu.