hi everyone thanks for having me my name
is ABI yadav uh co-founder and CEO of a
company called I customer uh at I
customer is a decision intelligence
company basically helping businessing
transform uh from raw customer data into
a modern GTM uh
engine um just to give you uh some
perspective on what we call go to market
which is GTM you know this has been
traditionally very creative heavy and
you know the creative engine has been
around forever since and kind of
distribution engine is what you know
kind of limited but in today's world of
modern marketing where everything
there's a signal there's a click there's
a situation like that there are multiple
engines are required to be done you know
some manuals some automation things like
that we sort of see this to be extremely
complicated in today's world while
maintaining customer experience while
maintaining privacy other effectivity
and not kind of bombing you know
messaging all the time and all all the
delivery of to
everyone so we see this inefficiency is
actually leading for every business for
about 10 20% of their revenue on
marketing which is kind of going blindly
and this this leads to up to about 2
trillion of like you know Money Paid uh
and primary reason is actually not an
effective marketing strategy is actually
the fragmented data chaos and how
businesses are currently trying to do
and this is where it is really stemming
in from is a kind of a self-service data
operation engine and a lot of Team have
like Center of Excellence a lot of data
scientists A lot of people but
ultimately there are still like
disconnected tools data teams any inside
um which leads to obviously a lot of
like inefficient uh
kpis we are taking an approach of
agentic AI which is basically U sit on
top of your customer data connected or
not and basically help you sort of
manage the data chaos at a speed in
which the data is getting generated the
insights can be kind of retri uh we
basically have three pillars um we call
it match decide activate you know match
is really an immutable ID system which
we have kind of built out with a lot of
Decades of experience and working on
consumer identity with privacy and
things like that and basically connect a
lot of tags and Signal which is all
around in the market today whether it's
e-commerce Business Online offline uh
and then help decide and then sort of
activate for um useful uh cases and this
is why we call it this as decision
intelligence more specifically uh we sit
on top of wherever the customer data is
we're we're composable platform with
composable we mean like we sit within a
cloud data warehouse or an non-pr data
set um with some sort of guardrail so
it's not like you know some crazy system
and then leads up to a lot of
application which are activation heavy
advertising martech I'll talk to you in
a moment we we we don't believe in like
AGI here because you know human
expertise is very critical especially in
marketing creative world so we look at
this uh aspect of human experti agent Ai
and customer data is what our definition
of decision intelligence is uh specific
use case customer life cycle automation
orchestration add targeting enablement
with in a in a way you know it is
individualized and not like done in a
spray and preway um lot of insights uh
where one can talk to your data most
more specifically um use case given our
system is very goal oriented uh this is
an example of a large e-commerce cpg
player where a business leader or an
operator without knowledge of a lot of
data data science and Technical jgan
would actually talk to their data not
just at about just finding answers but
also finding like root cause and then
sort of activate uh you know what could
be a corrective measure
so we're here in Japan um specifically I
I'd work with past and lot of Japanese
customer we we've already working very
actively with at least two of them right
now mostly partner Le um so we're
seeking more customer and Innovation
partner um happy to talk beond this uh
at the Showcase uh this is my
information but thank you so much for
having
thanks AB