the MIT energy initiative presents using
Nature's structures in wooden buildings
a new approach enables Architects to use
discarded tree forks as loadbearing
joints in their structures written by
Nancy W
staer concern about climate change has
focused significant attention on the
building sector in particular on the
extraction and processing of
construction materials the concrete and
steel Industries together are respond
responsible for as much as 15% of global
carbon dioxide emissions in contrast
wood provides a natural form of carbon
sequestration so there's a move to use
timber instead indeed some countries are
calling for public buildings to be made
at least partly from Timber and large
scale Timber buildings have been
appearing around the world observing
those Trends Caitlyn Mueller 07 sm14
phd4 an associate professor of
architecture and of civil and
environmental engineering in the
building techn ology program at MIT sees
an opportunity for further
sustainability gains as the timber
industry seeks to produce wooden
replacements for traditional concrete
and steel elements the focus is on
harvesting the straight section of trees
IR regular section such as knots and
forks are turned into pellets and burned
or ground up to make garden mulch which
will decompose within a few years both
approaches release the carbon trapped in
the wood to the atmosphere for the past
4 years Mueller and her digital
structures research group have been
developing a strategy for upcycling
those waste materials by using them in
construction not as cladding or finishes
aimed at improving appearance but as
structural components the greatest value
you can give to a material is to give it
a loadbearing role in a structure she
says but when Builders use virgin
materials those structural components
are the most emissions intensive parts
of buildings due to their large volume
of high strength materials using
upcycled materials in place of those
High car systems is therefore especially
impactful in reducing emissions mu and
her team focus on tree forks that is
spots where the trunk or branch of a
tree divides in two forming a y-shaped
piece in architectural drawings there
are many similar y-shaped nodes where
Straight elements come together in such
cases those units must be strong enough
to support critical loads tree forks are
naturally engineered structural
connections that work as Canal levers
and trees which mean means that they
have the potential to transfer Force
very efficiently thanks to their
internal fiber structure says Mueller if
you take a tree fork and slice it down
the middle you see an unbelievable
network of fibers that are intertwining
to create these often three-dimensional
load transfer points in a tree we're
starting to do the same thing using 3D
printing but we're nowhere near what
nature does in terms of complex fiber
orientation and
geometry she and her team have developed
a five-step design to fabrication
workflow that combines natural
structures such as tree forks with the
digital and computational tools now used
in architectural design while there's
long been a craft movement to use
natural wooden railings and decorative
features the use of computational tools
makes it possible to use wood in
structural roles without excessive
cutting which is costly and may
compromise the natural geometry and
internal grain structure of the wood
given the wide use of digital tools by
today's Architects Mueller believes that
her approach is at least potentially
scalable and potentially achievable
within our industrialized materials
processing systems in addition by
combining tree forks with digital design
tools the novel approach can also
support the trend among Architects to
explore new forms many iconic buildings
built in the past two decades have
unexpected shapes says Mueller tree
branches have a very specific geometry
that sometimes lends itself to an
irregular or non-standard architectural
form driven not by some arbitrary
algorithm but by the material itself
Step Zero find a source set goals before
starting their design to fabrication
process the researchers needed to locate
a source of tree forks Mueller found
help in the urban forestry division of
the city of Somerville Massachusetts
which maintains a digital inventory of
more than 2,000 Street trees including
more than 20 species and records
information about the location
approximate trunk diameter and condition
of each tree with permission from the
forestry division the team was on hand
and in 2018 when a large group of trees
was cut down near the site of the new
Somerville High School among the heavy
equipment on site was a chipper poised
to turn all that waste wood into mulch
instead the workers obligingly put the
waste wood into the researcher's truck
to be brought to MIT in their project
the MIT team sought not only to upcycle
that waste material but also to use it
to create a structure that would be
valued by the public where I live the
city has had to take down a lot of trees
due to damage from an invasive species
of be Mueller explains people get really
upset understandably trees are important
part of the urban fabric providing shade
and Beauty she and her team hope to
reduce that animosity by reinstalling
the removed trees in the form of a new
functional structure that would recreate
the atmosphere and spatial experience
previously provided by the F trees with
their source and goals identified the
researchers were ready to demonstrate
the five steps in their designed to
fabrication workflow for making spatial
structures using an inventory of tree
forks step one create a digital material
Library the first task was to turn their
collection of tree forks into a digital
library they began by cutting off excess
material to produce isolated tree forks
they then created a 3D scan of each Fork
Mueller notes that as a result of recent
progress in photogrammetry measuring
objects using photographs and 3D
scanning they could create high
resolution digital representations of
the indiv idual tree forks with
relatively inexpensive equipment even
using apps that run on a typical
smartphone in the digital library each
Fork is represented by a skeletonized
version showing three straight bars
coming together at a point the relative
geometry and orientation of the branches
are a particular interest because they
determine the internal fiber orientation
that gives the component its
strength step two find the best match
between the initial design and the
material Library like a tree a typical
architectural design is filled with
y-shaped nodes where three straight
elements meet up to support a critical
load the goal was therefore to match the
tree forks in the material library with
the nodes and a sample architectural
design first the researchers developed a
mismatch metric for quantifying how well
the geometries of a particular tree Fork
aligned with a given design node we're
trying to line up the straight elements
in the structure with where the branches
originally were in the tree explains
Mueller that gives us the optic
orientation for load transfer and
maximizes use of the inherent strength
of the wood fiber the poorer the
alignment the higher the mismatch metric
the goal was to get the best overall
distribution of all the tree forks among
the nodes in the Target design therefore
the researchers needed to try different
Fork to node distributions and for each
distribution add up the individual Fork
to node mismatch errors to generate an
overall or Global matching score the
distribution with the best best matching
score would produce the most
structurally efficient use of the total
treefork inventory since performing that
process manually would take far too long
to be practical they turn to the
Hungarian algorithm a technique
developed in 1955 for solving such
problems the Brilliance of the algorithm
is solving that mashing problem very
quickly Mueller says she notes that it's
a very general use algorithm it's used
for things like marriage matchmaking it
can be used anytime you have two
collections of things that you're trying
to find unique matches between so we
definitely didn't invent the algorithm
but we were the first to identify that
it could be used for this problem the
researchers performed repeated tests to
show possible distributions of the tree
forks in their inventory and found that
the matching score improved as the
number of forks available in the
material Library increased up to a point
in general the researchers concluded
that the mismatch score was lowest and
thus best when there were about three
times as many Forks in the material
Library as there were nodes in the
Target
design step three balance designer
intention with structural
performance the next step in the process
was to incorporate the intention or
preference of the designer to permit
that flexibility each design includes a
limited number of critical parameters
such as bar length and bending strain
using those parameters the designer can
manually change the overall shape or
geometry of the design or can use an
algorithm that automatically changes or
morphs the geometry and every time the
design geometry changes the Hungarian
algorithm recalculates the optimal Fork
to node matching because the Hungarian
algorithm is extremely fast all the
morphing and the design updating can be
really fluid notes Mueller in addition
any change to a new geometry is followed
by a structural analysis that checks The
deflections Strain energy and other
performance measures of the structure on
occasion the automatically generated
design that yields the best matching
score May deviate far from the
designer's initial intention in such
cases an alternative solution can be
found that satisfactorily balances the
design attention with a low matching
score step four automatically generate
the machine code for fast
cutting when the structural geometry and
distribution of tree forks have been
finalized it's time to think about
actually building the structure to
simplify assembly and maintenance the
researchers pair of the tree forks by
recutting their end faces to better
match adjoining straight Timbers and
cutting off any remaining bark to reduce
susceptibility to rot and fire to guide
that process they developed a custom
algorithm that automatically computes
the cuts needed to make a given tree
Fork fit into its assigned node and to
strip off the bark the goal is to remove
as little material as possible but also
to avoid a complex timeconsuming
Machining process if we make too few
Cuts we'll cut off too much the critical
structural material but we don't want to
make a million tiny Cuts because it will
take forever Mueller explains the team
uses facilities at the Autodesk Boston
Technology Center build space where the
robots are far larger than any in MIT
and the processing is all automated to
prepare each treefork they mounted on a
robotic arm that pushes the joint
through a traditional band saw in
different orientations Guided by
computer generated
instructions the robot also Mills all
the holes for the structural connections
that's helpful because it ensures that
everything is aligned the way you expect
it to be says
Mueller step five assemble the available
forks and linear elements to build the
structure the final step is to assemble
the structure the treefork based joints
are all irregular and combining them
with the pre-cut straight wooden
elements could be difficult however
they're all labeled all the information
for the geometry is embedded in the
joint so the assembly process is really
low teex says Mueller it's like a
child's toy set you just follow the
instructions on the joints to put all
the pieces together they installed their
final structure temporarily on the MIT
campus but Mueller notes that it was
only a portion of the structure they
plan to eventually build it had 12 nodes
that we designed and fabricated using
our process she says adding that the
team's work was a little interrupted by
the pandemic as activity on campus
presumes the researchers plan to finish
designing and building the complete
structure which will incl include about
40 nodes and will be installed as an
outdoor Pavilion on the site of the Fel
trees in Somerville in addition they
will continue their research plans
include working with larger material
libraries some with multibranch forks
and replacing their 3D scanning
technique with computerized tomography
scanning technologies that can
automatically generate a detailed
geometric representation of a tree Fork
including its precise fiber orientation
and density and in a parallel project
they've been exploring using their
process with other sources of materials
with one case study focusing on using
material from a demolished wood framed
house to construct more than a dozen
geodesic
domes to Mueller the workto date already
provides new guidance for the
architectural design process with
digital tools it has become easy for
Architects to analyze the embodied
carbon or future energy use of a design
option now we have a new metric of
performance how well am I using
available resources she says with a
Hungarian algorithm we can compute that
metric basically in real time so we can
work rapidly and creatively with that as
another input to the design
process this research was supported by
mit's School of Architecture and
planning via the H
award this article appears in the Autumn
2021 issue of Energy Futures the
magazine of the MIT energy initiative