Uh so in my part of the first lecture I
will before I get into the introduction
of some financial concepts and the
investment strategies give you some
basics uh and background information for
this class. I will tell you uh three
things first before that. First is bit
introduction of myself. Second I tell
you how this class was actually formed.
Why we had this idea why we have decided
to have this class. Uh third is before
you actually do the assignment zero
submit your information. I'm going to
survey the class a little bit just get
some idea of your background of the
knowledge of financial markets and math
so we know you know what level we should
target uh you at okay so first about me
uh so my connection with MIT as Vasili
said also quite similar so I have a PhD
from core six electrical engineering and
computer science and uh I worked in the
engineering field uh as a researcher for
a few years. Um then switched to Wall
Street as a quant
means using mathematics building trading
models. Uh back then I joined uh Solomon
Brothers. So that tells you about my age
because probably how many of you have
heard about Solomon Brothers?
Oh, good for you. Okay. Is now part of
uh city group. uh but Solomon Brothers
back then was the pioneer of uh using
quantitative trading strategies and also
hiring mathematicians of doing those
so-called arbitrage models finding uh
one stock or bond versus another uh you
know basically uh finding relative
value.
So I worked there for a couple of years
as a quant then Morgan Stanley recruited
me away uh to be a trader. Uh I ended up
staying there for over 17 years. Worked
as a various uh trading and trading
management roles globally got sent
around the globe. Uh that's where I
worked with uh uh Vasili.
Uh and uh in 2013,
that was the year when we first recorded
our open courseware uh video for this
class. I actually switched uh my job
from Morgan Stanley to uh Harvard
management company which is uh the
entity manages Harvard University's
endowment. I joined as uh as the chief
risk officer to oversee risk management
and also capital allocation. That's when
uh back then we had uh many internal uh
fund managers doing various strategies.
We since then uh changed our model about
seven years ago, seven eight years ago
to focus on investing with external
funds. I subsequently also switched my
focus uh full-time focusing on uh
investing and finding the right funds
and managers. I'll tell you a bit more
about that but I will save that for
later. Uh so that's basically uh about
me. So I tell you a bit about the class.
So back I want to say maybe uh 14 15
years ago when uh Vasilia and I were
working together at Morgan Stanley, we
came to MIT to recruit quite often and
Vasilia was from the math department. I
was from core six. So we met a lot of uh
really bright uh students with
quantitative background but they don't
really know much about finance and uh
they ask many good questions. So we just
felt like in a half an hour or one hour
interview time slot it's simply not
enough for us to answer all the
questions or get to know the students.
So may we figure maybe the best way is
to have a seminar to tell the students
more about how math is used in finance.
So one seminar lecture actually got
expanded to the whole term and uh so we
invited the different practitioners
talking about how math is being applied
in different fields solving different
problems
that the class actually got very uh
popular. I mean one of the first classes
we got students sit on the floor
everywhere they want to know about you
know should they pursue a career in
quantitative finance.
So the math department uh was very uh
supportive and so we teamed up with uh
Peter the following year to offer half
of the lectures in actually math to fill
up all the background knowledge and then
kept the half of the class uh talking
about application cases. We even had a
field trips taking all the students to
New York touring the trading floor of
Morgan Stanley. We did that for a few
years and uh we had uh various uh you
know fun and some students really ended
up working uh in New York. Some of them
are still there uh in various jobs. So
that's how this class came about.
So, let me turn the table around asking
you a few quick questions. You don't
have to state your name. Just raise your
hands. It's fine. How many of you have
watched our open courseware recording
from 2013?
Oh, great. Yeah. See five, six hands.
So, you you have you knew something
about this class. How many of you have
done internship jobs at the financial
firm?
A third. Okay.
How many of you are mass majors?
Most of you. How many of you are
graduate students?
Okay. A few. Uh how many of you actually
are outside MIT? Because we have Okay,
great. I want to welcome all the
students came you know cross from cross
registration or sitting from other
schools. We always had a feel uh from
other schools. So you're very welcome.
If you are unfamiliar with some of the
MIT uh systems, please feel free to uh
seek for help.
So that's all about the introduction. So
let me get into the actual content for
this lecture. So as I said, the purpose
of this first lectures give you some
background information. I realize some
of you already have done intern uh jobs
so you know quite a bit but I but I want
to also uh be sensitive to the students
who have actually not done the
internship uh positions and I can give
you some basic knowledge and uh I I give
you one example in one of the first
years when we had this uh class uh so
there are some students didn't even know
what a stock is what the stock was.
Okay, so you shouldn't feel bad if you
have no knowledge about the financial
markets. We'll make sure you have plenty
of the knowledge when you finish the
class at the in December.
Okay. So what is
you know finance or financial markets
about right? It's really about
there is a market of exchanges in the
original form. people come to the market
you know at the village exchanging goods
you know you have something I don't have
something I need something you know so
let's exchange so the stock exchange was
formed
with the same idea right so some buyers
want to own equity of a company I
explain what equity is equity is
basically ownership of a company uh
meaning stocks and uh they centralize
all the trading of these stocks at a
particular place. These are exchanges,
right? Many cities, large financial
centers have different exchanges.
And in the last few decades, that also
has changed. It's no longer that
centralized. So people do a lot of
over-the-counter OTC trading. So it's
trade by appointment, trade by
arrangement, trade by contract, right?
So you don't have to go to a centralized
exchange to finish a trade
or there are electronic communication
networks or ECNS. You can do that simply
electronically. I mean they also act as
distributed exchanges.
So these are kind of the major uh
platforms of markets. So what are the
products people actually are trading or
exchanging hands? first is simply money,
right? So Peter mentioned bitcoins.
Bitcoin is actually kind of form of
money, you know, not the fiat form but
you know different forms but you know
originally gold or metal or paper money
or coins but or now different currencies
issued by different governments. Those
were basically uh first way of first
essential product to to trade with. Then
you always hear about the stock market.
Stock market represents ownerships of
companies, right? Peter mentioned uh
Nvidia stock going up rapidly you know
because people bet on oh AI applications
the demand for GPU chips and so on data
centers. So to get ownership of a
company you buy stocks I mean also you
can buy equity indices meaning a basket
of stocks. So you probably have heard
S&P 500, right? So standard pool 500 is
essentially
five largest companies uh you know here.
So you can you can get exposure not to
just simply one company, you can get
exposure to many of them at the same
time. These are the ideas of index or uh
you know they can have uh different
forms of that traded in ETF exchange
traded funds also representing often
basket of different stocks
and uh there are also uh two kind of
tiers of markets. So the ex the exchange
traded stocks is called the listed
stocks. So they have to go through a
process called IPO initial public
offering to become listed on the
exchange. So but that's called the
primary ser uh process to go from a
private company become a public company
have stocks freely traded. There are
also private companies which I'll get
into later. But after it it become
listed is traded by many other people.
So it's called the secondary market. So
after primary getting listed is a
secondary market.
So
besides the large category of equity
market, there's also a big category of
bond or fixed income market. So bond is
essentially a loan where it's a
securitized loan. So it become listed
and tradable. So the most uh commonly uh
known bond is the US treasury bond,
right? US government borrows money from
the investors.
You know us or institutions
they pay interest periodically either
quarterly or semiannually.
And uh so the bond issuer has obligation
to pay back the whole principal amount
or the notional amount at the end of the
maturity but they can also default on
that payment on both the principal or
the interest. So bond has a credit risk
meaning that the issuer may not always
pay back right. So, so that involves the
exposure of the credit of the issuer.
So, that's
basically uh related to a whole bunch of
credit related products.
And uh 2008 global financial uh crisis
is really a credit crisis because that
started in the mortgage uh market.
people borrow money to buy houses but
couldn't pay back and also these
mortgages were restructured into
different kind of derivative products
and uh we'll get into that later.
So related to bonds there's a interest
rate curve which is also very important
right depends on maturity of the bonds
the interest payment is or the coupon is
actually different if you only borrow
for three months you pay certain
interest you borrow for 30 years you pay
another interest rate every year depends
on the curve shape of the interest rate
and as well as the supply demand and
many other factors.
The Federal Reserve Bank which is the
policy bank of the United States is
responsible of setting the short term
the the front end interest rate to
affect the whole interest rate curve. I
mean right now as many of you know the
interest rate curve is actually
inverted. the front end interest rate is
higher than the longer maturity which is
not often the case. Okay, we can also
get into that later. uh so related to
interest rates
there are you know uh real estate uh
products as I mentioned the mortgage and
the asset back securities
and another whole category is
commodities you know I mentioned gold
but there's also crude oil Peter's
example of the futures dipping down
below zero and uh agriculture products
right I mean now we're in the era of
electrifying everything electric
vehicles uses a lot of uh copper right
or lithium uh for batteries. So those
commodities were trading uh rapidly
higher and also follows the cycle.
So I I'm just giving you some ideas of
the basic products. But on top of all
these products, you can also have
derivative products meaning you can
derive a other contracts of trading. So
you can have options. So I don't just
buy the stock. I want to buy the right
to own the stock in the future. That is
the option. So it's a right but not the
obligation.
I can also say I don't want to buy it
now. I just want to buy it a year from
now. So that's a forward contract. So I
just want to buy the stock index futures
which is a very liquid and standardized
contract. So you can also say I want to
do a swap. I don't want to really buy
things. I want to say I buy it from you
now but a month later I sold it back to
you. So it's a swap contract. And so
there are many different ways of uh
structuring a product for different
purposes and the needs. So once you
actually land on a job like that you you
become an expert. Your math will be very
useful.
Okay. So who are the players in the
market?
So typically they are the banks you
deposit money with, right? Bank of
America, Chase, uh they take deposits,
they also lend out the money uh to uh
home builders or other commercial uh
projects. There are the investment banks
where you interview, they come to MIT to
recruit, right? So the Morgan Stanley's,
the Goldman Sachs and others, the JP
Morgans's uh JP Morgan was actually a a
commercial bank, but since uh the
termination of glass deagle law in 1999
999, they turned themselves into a
investment bank. in terms so back into
investment bank because many years ago
uh before 1930 they were they were
Morgan Stanley and JP Morgan were one
company
uh so they have essentially three main
uh divisions in the investment banking
business one is called equity so you
when you go interview if you're
interviewing with the equity department
you should know that that's to do with
stocks Okay. When you interview with the
fixed income department, you're going to
deal with bonds, interest rate curves,
currencies,
uh possibly commodities and other
derivatives. You can also join the
so-called IBD investment banking
division which is more about corporate
finance or raising money taking a
company from private to be listed public
company or issuing bonds or some other
ways. So they are doing more services
and the client uh uh relationship uh
planning and other type of uh uh uh
investment banking services. So beyond
the investment banking business of these
banks, they usually have asset
management division. So they produce
products such as funds, right? mutual
funds or other type of uh higher return
funds. They also provide wealth
management services helping uh the
individual or wealthy uh families to
manage their wealth. Uh
so
outside the banks there are hedge funds.
So some of the internship must be with
some hedge funds. Hedge funds are
essentially trading entities, right? So
they use their capital or their
investors capital try to generate
returns. So by the way at the end of
this I'm I'm going to play a assign a
game to all of you which is related to
uh investing and trading. Okay. So
retail investors. So they just simply
open a brokerage account and uh uh you
probably have and and your parents have
and trade central banks. They involve uh
they guiding the markets you know
usually uh providing liquidity or
intervening the currencies or whatever
they are policy driven. They are
corporates. So corporates come in mostly
for hedging purposes. They want to
reduce the exposure from their exports
or inputs.
What is the objective of all these
players involved uh in the markets?
In one sentence, they try to maximize uh
the gain. Why minimize the losses?
Okay, because financial markets are
uncertain, right? So you don't know when
you initiate a trade you will end up
making money or losing money.
So investors have the money they seeking
returns.
The borrowers
or you can think about them as a
managers they actually they need the
money they can take the risk. Okay. So
the trade between lender and the
borrower is essentially the main driving
force of all the financial
relationships. You can always pair them
up this way. And uh another example
right I just quickly mentioned you
probably heard the terms LP versus GP.
LP means limited partners, GP means
general partners or in a simple words is
the investor versus hedge fund manager.
is that relationship. If you one day
want to raise a hedge fund, right? You
need to deal with your investors. So,
you need to uh sort out these kind of
relationships.
So, the trader types that we can
categorize into the three. One is the
hedgers, right? Like corporates, they
want to reduce risk. I mean, second is
the market maker like a lot of the
banking uh the bank trading desks, they
make
buying a price, a selling price or bid
or an offer. Their objective is to earn
that spread but not to take risk. Every
time they try to earn that spread then
quickly flatten out the position.
The last category are the risk seekers,
the proprietary traders or the fund
managers.
So they use their own capital to uh
initiate risk and hopefully they are
betting right to make a return.
So how is this all related to math
right? Why why you need to know all
these things? I assume you are in this
class because you have some interest of
finding out how math can be used uh in
the financial markets.
So the math is used also in the three
different ways. One is to uh come up
with a pricing model because these
instruments especially the derivatives
the options the forwards the swaps
is actually quite complicated.
In one of the guest lectures later on in
the term you will hear from John Hall.
He wrote a textbook many years ago on
how to price options.
you know, Vasilia and I probably will
back then all the, you know,
uh, hungry readers of those books to
figure out, uh, how differential
equations can be used. I mean, he was a
pioneer in this field and MIT actually
is at the was at was at the frontier of
all these innovations back in the 70s,
right? So you probably heard the Nobel
Prize given in the 90s to the black
shows merin model. So that was a model
using mathematics
to price options right. So they won uh
economic prize uh Nobel Nobel prize in
economics.
So that's the pricing model side. The
second part is also very important is
risk management. I mean when you take on
a risk take on a position
you first question you have to decide is
how big the position should be right so
you have certain amount of money do you
want to put all in all your chips on one
stock or you want to diversify put them
into different stocks once you put your
investment in when do you change your
mind when do you sell when do you take
profit when do you cut losses
Right? So
all the things you know your greed your
emotions will drive you and on one hand
your fear will also drive you on in
other situations. So risk management is
actually a very quantitative process.
You should let math uh speak for that uh
process. The last one is I think most
people are interested in especially
sitting in your seats. You say if you
can make a trading strategy perpetual
moneymaking machine using some kind of a
hidden mathematics wouldn't that be so
cool right you just go to the beach and
let the machine make money for you. I
mean that's the dream of uh many
quantitative managers and I would say
some of them are very successful some of
the funds out there they have achieved
amazing outcomes using mathematics but
the problem is once they found those
secrets they would never disclose it and
if you join them they'll ask you to sign
a lifetime non-compete meaning when you
leave the shop you cannot say a word of
what you learned yeah go ahead If you
sign a lifetime long-term fee, don't
they have to pay seven is where they
fire you ultimately?
>> Yes.
>> For a lifetime.
>> Not not a lifetime unfortunately. Yeah.
So, we're not going to get into that uh
for this. Yeah. But I first step you
have to find those secrets. Okay.
Uh so how do you find those secrets?
Right. So people say okay why don't you
just look at the data, right? learn from
the historical patterns then extrapolate
them. Right? The efficient market theory
says that's not possible. If is there
such thing you know $100 bills lying on
the ground there will have already have
been picked up long time ago. Why would
that secret waiting for you to uncover,
right? There are many smart people
before you. The behavioral finance
theory says, "Oh, wait a second." You
know, because people are not totally
rational under certain situations. We're
not thinking rationally. That's why
we're providing these opportunities for
others to explore.
Is this a zero sum game?
So,
I'm getting into now investment
strategies. Okay? I'm not of course
telling you all the secrets, but I'm
laying all the steps for you to think
about what you should focus on. So you
first you should focus on do you want to
do this by yourself or you want to hire
other people to do it for you, right? So
this is the direct versus investing in
other people's funds or fund of funds.
Do you want to focus on publicly traded
markets? As I said, all these things,
stock, bonds, currencies,
or you probably interviewed or heard
venture capital, private equity,
buyouts, uh, re real estate funds,
natural resource funds. I mean, they're
not so transparent, but they seem to
make a lot of returns too, right? You
need to pick. These are very two very
different markets.
Also, passive versus active.
Do you want to do the stock picking,
selecting the stocks, or you just want
to buy the index? Buying S&P 500 in the
last 10 years would have done very well
and beating most of the fund managers,
right? So why shouldn't you
just, you know, do the passive
also systematic versus discretionary? Do
you want to make decisions based on some
systematic or quantitative rules, models
or every time you want to make a
decision by yourself using your human
brain?
Do you want to even you want to follow
the quantitative model using math? Do
you want look for statistical patterns
or some deterministic relationships?
deterministic relationships like like a
lot of physics right if A plus B you
know you will get C but in statistics
you'll have a probability of getting C
right so I would say nowadays finding
deterministic arbitrage or trading
strategies very hot those those $100
bills are definitely have picked up but
sometimes they still show up
do you want to trend following or mean
reversion. That means when market goes
up, do you want to buy more or market
goes up, you want to sell, you play the
contrarian or you buy at the dip?
Do you want to focus on shortterm or you
focus on long-term? short term you're
trading very fast and uh you're trading
in the liquid very you can change your
mind easily or you you make your
decisions very slowly you take your time
I mean the uh startup companies you
invest with your venture capital may
take 10 years to find out if it's
successful or not
do you want to be a Warren Buffett like
value investor right you look at the
current price should be much lower than
its value or you focus on the growth of
the company. You project Nvidia's future
income for the next 10 years. As long as
the future value is going to be greater
than the current value, you you can you
can invest in it. I would say in the
last few years more and more people are
focusing growth rather than value. You
need to figure out why. Okay. and
history versus future, right? Do you
want do you believe history will repeat
itself? So you follow the patterns or
you actually don't simply extrapolate
into the future.
The key is you need to understand your
own objectives.
So your objective is to maximize your
gain, right? Versus minimizing your
loss. But that's not all of it, right?
You need to understand why do you need
the money?
What's it for? How much can you afford
to lose? How much you going to spend
every year and your life horizon of
income versus spending.
Uh this is a whole set of investment
objectives you need to understand about
yourself. Then you need to pick an area
you are the best. You are the best. you
have an edge over the rest of the
market, right? You need to understand
why you are you should make money, other
people should give you the money and uh
you need to find suitable strategy for
you. Ultimately,
if math is your strength, you need to
make math your edge.
Okay, for that uh I'm going to quickly
talk about the uh trading game, then I
will pass on to Vasili. So this game is
about for every single one of you to
pick a stock or ETF
exchange traded funds just traded like
stock or bonds or whatever only to buy.
Okay. So I know some of you are more
sophisticated say can I short? If you
want to go short you buy the short uh
related ETF. Okay. So, pick one stock.
You are hypothetically given $10,000.
Everyone has $10,000. Each one of you,
you need to let us know, email us your
selection. You you pick only one thing.
You let us know before September 14th.
We're going to we're going to give you
the slide on the website. So, don't
worry. Uh the price you buy is at the
close of Friday of September 13.
The price you sell is automatically set
on Friday, November 15th. So about two
month period.
So you need to track on the spreadsheet
how many shares you have bought. That's
easy. $10,000, right? You know, you just
convert into shares uh divided by per
share price and uh your daily profit and
loss in dollar and percentage. That
gives you a practice of how to track
your position. Okay. Every day there's a
P&L profit and loss. At the end of the
close on November 15th, calculate the
total loss or or profit and also why I
want you to do one calculation to sum up
all the daily gains on one side called G
and sum up all the daily losses
called L in dollar terms. So G minus L
should be your net profit and loss. But
I want you to calculate that ratio G
minus L divid by G plus L. That gives
you the quality of your trading
strategy.
A bonus, you're giving one time chance
to change your mind on October 11th
close. You email us your decision if you
want to switch on before October 12th.
You can switch to one other uh position.
You can decide not to switch. But when
you switch, you carry the balance
whatever is left your $10,000 maybe
1,000 left or become five uh 50 grand
whatever roll into a new position. So at
the end of the term we will announce the
top three leaders. Okay, for that I pass
on to Vasili.