[music]
Introducing Dr. Harold E. Edgerton of
the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology. His strooscope light, my
friends, is really something. [music]
While normally film runs through the
average movie camera at 90 ft a minute,
Edgudan's flicker box can handle 125 ft
a second. Connected with it is the unit
containing the thyrtron amplifier
flashing on and off up to 2,000 times a
second. So, it is now possible to get
ultra slow motion pictures. [music] In
normal speed movies, a bullet shot from
the muzzle of a high-powered air gun is
invisible. Now, Edgedan really
photographs a bullet in flight. [music]
And when you recall that all the action
of this bulb smashing actually took
place in the fraction of a second,
[music] you realize that here is speed
in movie photography. Indeed.
>> Find your MIT moment. Visit
learnmit.edu. [music]