uh in the US yes uh but aru it's
temporarily only in the sense that the
grow is linear rather than really show
up only in that sense it's stalling the
actra number is actually growing still
right uh but in China not at all yeah
later will show some number where EV I
would say really matured instead of
stalling uh and then the last thing is
the US One the stalling has to be
temporary unless us really just want to
cut itself entirely from the global
context here right so that's my short
answer to the question uh let me give
you some specific numbers um this in
2023 first of all when I say electric
vehicle here uh I mean pure battery
electric vehicle plus this plug uh
plug-in hybrid electric vehicle that's
what I mean there a two type of that
right by the way who owns one of
this interesting that's about six so
seven about about 10% about
10% uh that's the US average actually uh
the sales in terms only yeah in the same
not not the stock but 10% right that's
interesting uh another thing so who how
many have been to
China about half okay yeah so just get
some context here right so that's us and
China China sending 8 million so
absolute number way better but what's
important the following
uh if you look at the year- on-year
growth in
2023 both country grow by 30 to
40% right the momentum was very nice
this right uh but what happens in
2024 uh even last like fourth quarter of
2023 uh the US side start to slow down
quite a bit while China is keep growing
that that's where the Divergence uh
happens here right um here uh buou our
associ direct research to prepared these
slides moment ago U it triy to show that
the notion of stalling is only in the
sense that is a linear growth yeah
that's is that that's the number you can
see there uh here it's still absolute
number is still growing up this right
but the thing is when a new technology
comes in you want this linear growth at
the beginning but at some point you want
to shoot up right the and then you saty
this is the S curve right the sense of
stalling is we haven't seen the S curve
part this tipping up part
yet uh so this is the market share that
I was talk about uh I compare the two
country in the two the few years right
China went from uh 6% 16% 29% 30% and
this year just reached half so more than
half of the people actually buying
electric vehicle that right later
explain what's behind that but us
remains at 9 to 10% level here as this
audience actually represent right about
10% people actually have a BV or pluging
hybrid electric
vehicle so why this thing matters right
if you're familiar with this uh diffus
Innovation uh there's one Theory called
this uh the chasm right uh we said that
in this
part that can be easy you get this few
minor of this enthusiastic right I care
about enough about the new technology
it's cool I care about the climate it's
important so I'll do that right but when
you cross this one that's where often
many company die and many industry do
not
mature and using this graph you can see
that uh uh us is struggling 10% is about
still somewhere here but China has
crossed that chasm
that's the major difference uh and also
let me talk about the the motivation
when you are here again it's a novelty
it's your environmental attitude is you
want to show to be doing the right thing
to be cool but when you move here to
here those things no longer matters in a
way because the mass public they care
about what they care about cost care
about convenience right that this this
where fundamental St matter let me
explain to you why uh in this Regard in
terms of crossing the this major chm US
is not ready
yet the first thing is price mention
this this basic microeconomics one why
right if you look at the US ongoing
price uh this is IC and this is the
electric vehicle it's still much more
expensive that's a very simple thing uh
you cannot convince average America to
pay $10,000 more because oh I care about
the
environment so when it come down to this
Crossing that critical candom is the
fundamental pricing comen in that
matters right uh in contrast in China
last year 60% of EV are cheaper than
their IC
equivalent right so therefore the result
is not surprising purely in economics
they are cheaper that and and this is
very important also this happened while
China removed the national subsidy for
Ev
purchases there's another Point often
talk about is oh China have a lot of
government subsidy the ETC which is true
well we'll talk a little about but last
year this number is people still buying
electric vehicle on for its own sake
it's not because subsidy it's not
because I love the the the the the
planet Earth because it's
cheaper right that's that's why
important point to make yeah we is I
mean again most that's the common human
decision making process here right the
second so that's the first point the
price the second part is convenience in
electric vehicle convenience measured by
charging process as John mentioned
there's so much problem in us let me
give you a
figure that's the comparison of a
charting point that just got
July uh also give account the China's
population four times
us so even you do the per capita sense
China is four times more char in por per
capita uh so that's the second reason
Chinese buy EV because it's cheaper and
it's
convenient right uh by the way for the
chartings uh uh ports uh the percent
that's this DC fast charger in China is
half and us is a
quarter so there are more charger in
China and they are high capacity charger
fast charger and they are actually more
reliable as
well right so that's the second main
reason right the charting in is not like
fully the problem is not fully resolved
but most of Chinese customer no longer
see this as a major
problem right so cheaper price
convenient charging this is the
fundamentals yes right uh of course this
is all about the vehicle itself to
support the industry you need a whole
set of uh supply chain ecosystem right
let just name a few electric vehicle you
need charging do the charging you need a
grade on the use side on the
manufacturing side to make electric you
need a battery you need a mineral you
need
processing uh so here and also you have
Finance safety Equity all the other
issues here right uh in from the battery
John just mentioned China dominant not
only battery but whole supply chain uh
from here the EV down to battery cell
cell component mineral process
mining red is China you can see that
it's
dominant that so here China solved both
the cheaper price and a more charging
problem but also the entire supply chain
is doing well this right uh a moment
which talk about the private car if you
look at public transit uh China is even
more so in the dominance this is the
number of electric buses in the world uh
between China Europe United States Etc
so that's the to talk
about uh by by the way the I just
mention a little bit on public transit
because that's a important part of the
sector but often uh less understood and
often in the United States I would say
ignored this right uh the
electrification that's a part but in
more in
general uh in China or actually in
Europe in many part of Asia the position
of public transit in big cities at least
uh is
un challengeable there's no ambiguity on
that everybody respect public transit is
the backbone of the urban transportation
system but in the United States is far
from that we have a much difficult
problem physical cliff social agenda of
uh uh the public Transit Agency I
imposed upon
many social issue that beyond the
running the trends for example homeless
issue gun violence issue mental health
issue all this problem Fair evasion even
I will include that but they all kind of
impose upon the public TR system if you
talk to the agency they yeah they try to
help on this but but there's a reality
I'm good at running Trends I don't know
how to deal with gun violence and mental
health many of the Innovative agencies
will collaborate with social welfare
like social workers to collaborate but
still challenging but overall I just say
it's a very difficult situation but let
me come back to
electrification a couple years ago the
electric bus side the issue is there's
no demand the different cities are not
interested in this but in the last few
years every single City if you look at
their sustainable plan or climate change
plan we all say by 2040 we want to 100%
Electrify buses by 2035 by 45 different
Paces but overall all the cities claim
that we are going to Electrify our buses
right at the same time you'll find we
don't produce them anymore in
US I mean exact a little bit this is the
few companies there uh pra declared
bankrupt Nova said we're no longer
interested in us Market we retract to
the Canada there's only one meaningful
player there at the same time China in
byd and youon one with two top public
transit companies they happily produce
and sell to us but they cannot because
of the geopolitical reason that John
just mentioned here right so that's
another episode I to mention right okay
come back to to cars um about the
success right electric vehicle success
one simple theory is the following oh
China is also an terent regime the
president she said we're going to
Electrify our cars therefore we do it
right there there's some truths to that
I mean that's an important part of this
top down approach that that important
but I think that's far from the the the
comprehensive uh uh reality of what
happened here right so let me give you a
few uh examples
the first thing is uh uh in China
there's a group called EV 100 that's a
group that include government officials
uh Scholars EV manufacturers local uh
politicians uh battery makers uh great
great uh people these 100 people have
been talking for years right they
negotiate they have this like meeting
like this let's talk about it they
recognize the importance particularly uh
John mentioned the uh previous mentioned
the minister Wang Gang uh who's a key
person who trained in Germany understand
the Auto industry very well came back to
China uh become a minister who pushed so
much on this but not himself he brought
a whole group together right this e 100
is a nonprofit organization have been
negotiating for years later when you see
uh China formal uh publish this formal
policies about electrification that's
collaboration between Ministry of
Transportation Ministry of Finance
Ministry of science technology those
policy are very much based upon the EV
100's recommendation so when the
government introduced a policy it has
the the grassroot foundation from the
society from the industry already here
right so it's not just like a somehow
the central government is said we do
that we said thing and then other people
listen to that
right so here so what really happens
here right a couple things here this is
overall there's the market size and
growth the supportive policies The
Venture investment the industry players
and the consumer adoption uh let me talk
a few of them let me start with the
policies here you know in the Biden
adion uh this whole BR uh by bipartisan
infrastructure Bild the ra inflation
redu actually Etc in the way for for
Chinese they will look at this oh us
tried to copy our Five-Year
Plan that's again the the The
Superficial view of this is trying to
introduce or reintroduce the industrial
policy or industry strategy right but it
turns out that when you want to do a
industry policy I'm not debating you
should or not it's a matter of two
things one is your attitude oh recognize
we want to do it but the second thing is
competence even you want to do this
National Industry policy it takes effort
takes experience takes talent to do it
China in the past 40 years has been
specializing this they put a lot of
effort developing a coherent National
policy supported by local policy
supported by local industry understood
by the public but us when you try to do
that I think it's a rather rather rushed
right without a broader understanding of
it let me just give you
example uh if you talk to a late person
in the ground oh how many you know about
ra how much you read ra what it's about
most people have no clue what you talk
about mean audience here probably you
would read R look at the the the the
evidence here right in contrast when the
when the central government in China
published the fiveyear
plan in China at least I would say
onethird of the people who are in some
position right either leadership in
politics in academics industry they read
this fiveyear plan as a Bible they read
every single sentence of it right it
takes it seriously on this right so
that's a really important contrast here
uh a few specific ones the there's three
set of a policy that relevant to
electric vehicle the first one is
technology right here you may heard this
notion of made in China 2025 China sees
electric vehicle as opportunity to Leap
Frog uh in the car industry we recognize
if we compete on the industrial U sorry
internal combuster engine we cannot beat
the BMW and Volkswagen those people
they've been down through the four
century we can beat them but electric
vehicle it's not that complicated into
the engine part right the other part
China innovated a lot on battery on
infotainment system or software defined
vehicle customer BRS that's where this
100 experience is very much irrelevant
and China sees the opportunity that's
first one right uh then also nowadays
the auton vehicle that relate to
artificial intelligence that's also area
that China sees significant effort to
push that's first one uh the second one
is on infrastructure that I think is not
a surprise probably if you go to China
you recognize almost every aspect of
infrastructure China is way better uh
high speed rail Bridges highways
internet all these infrastructures uh
the just much more capable to to do that
uh that's the second part then the last
part is this climate
um climate I would say put it this
way neither China or us are sincere
Europe is right for us and China if you
put a society as a whole is not sincere
right neither the country this right uh
but specifically in of policy uh we
China does did announce this goal about
carbon neutrality by 2060 this right but
that's a further way uh policy China
still the like biggest C by far uh in
fact um during the climate
negotiation uh China or or broadly
speaking developing country as a group
even though China is not debatable where
where to put it uh often the debate goes
like this oh I'm polluting a lot now uh
but you guys the referring to the
Western you guys have been polluting
from past two centuries here right uh
when you develop you pollute now it's my
time to pollute you don't want me that's
the argument but just last year China
actually passed a bar in term of the
cumulative CO2 emission you look at the
history entirely China is passing uh
Europe on that right so that argument no
longer flies here right that's absolute
number in the entire historical
accumulation is bigger right it's not
the there but nonetheless from Electric
Vehicle point of view all three policy
combined really have a big push for to
promote this but this is not just the uh
a national policy if it come down to the
local
level uh that's where the uh in the
United States the the different layers
of the government is rather disconnected
they I mean in the in the very positive
they are very independent so therefore
resident but in China it's more coherent
in this way it's not like they they
don't have conflict they a lot of debate
and tensions but overall when the
national government push a general
agenda is to the local government
interest to follow that agenda because
it comes with
resources uh with funding but also comes
with uh the particular individual
politicians future Prospect of promotion
so the interest very much aligned for
the local government to follow so
therefore each cities will develop its
own policies and guideline to support
this broader uh uh policy let me give
you one
example in Beijing and Shanghai uh if
you to buy a car uh you need to join
something called a a vehicle license
quota system uh uh at a different point
uh both cities recognize the two Med
cars in the in the streets so they start
to issue number of
quotas um so basically each month the
government will announce this month we
only allow uh 20,000 new cars onto the
streets right so who get this 20,000
license uh beijan and Shanghai choose
different way of allocation Shanghai
choose a lottery system so you pay and
you bid for the price while Bing choose
a lottery system uh you you you just try
your luck a lucky
draw first of all you can see that the
two City have a very different flavor if
you're familiar with China if ask you to
guess which one is which you probably
guess Shanghai is more Market oriented
approach using loction uh auction while
Beijing is more planning oriented using
Lottery but in this regard it doesn't
matter they both use uh quota control
but then for both cities they will
allocate certain proportion of quota to
the new energy vehicle or here basically
electric vehicle here right uh and then
they gradually increase this quota on
the electric vehicle side so more or
more to the degree that if you want to
buy a car you have to buy electric
vehicle there's no more this the quota
on the n the IC is smaller and smaller
so this is one example of how local
government echoing the national
government policy to promote electric
vehicle uh all right so here the
question they ask so what policy is this
about this electric vehicle is a
transportation policy uh not much at all
yeah because from a traffic management
point of view Urban Mobility point of
view electric vehicle it generate
congestion generate the safety issue
have the acity issue is very similar
this uh so it's the Environmental Policy
uh
partially uh first of all the the energy
mix in China is still 60% co-based right
so if anything is a transfer the
pollution from this distributed in the
urban cities to the source of the
electricity there even though China also
changing quite a bit on the uh uh uh
electrification El electricity
generation part with the solar panels
when power Etc but that's separate
discussion there then the next one is
industrial policy as mentioned to grow
the market many cities see the car
industry as their pillar industry but
finally I want to add uh what really get
to the almost the emotional response to
Chinese is the energy
policy uh China has about one M of oil
preserve so if there's a w China was cut
off you can maintain one M uh you can
imagine that as Chinese leaders or even
late person they understand this
so energy policy is you it hit you at
the guts right so we cannot rely on
imported oil as we do today so many of
them will very much support this shift
uh to electric base why which then
either coas or nuclear or or solar they
can solve that problem right so electric
vehicle really reflect a different set
of a policy intention they very much
aligned uh in that right so that's the
first part on the policy
side but the second part uh
so the the the first of all the the
policy side often being seen as oh this
is unique the the the Chinese government
is putting lot of subsidies and favism
to the electric vehicle uh as mentioned
that that's partly true but I do want to
mention that the part coming from the
genuine Innovation from the industry
right uh I mention three things The
Innovation the diversity and a
competition uh if you look at electric
vehicles if you go to a Chinese market
you you almost be like a it's kind of
Fantastical uh the the level and the
rich of the Innovation here's the three
examples on this battery swap we talked
about here in the US a long long time
which we didn't really scale it at all
uh but in China you see the particular
Neo have thousands of this uh uh battery
swapping station uh where if you look at
the process is amazingly
automated you don't even need to uh get
off your car drive into it uh it will
you had the robotic arm change the
battery within a few minutes you can
just drive out right uh this one this
Comfort entertainment uh you can use the
car as your like personal family uh
theaters uh the the also put not necess
all the innovation in the end Will
Survive but the the spirit of
experimenting uh uh is just dazzling
right you will have a refrigerator in it
uh you can layout as as a bed you can
have the movie all sort of innovation on
that again I'm not sure all this
Innovation Will Survive but some of them
will the point is they're willing to try
and how much new thinking are put into
that related to that is this uh this
cycle like in typical s of every two
years or three years you have a new
model Etc China really changed that
notion on this they inovate in a much
rapider way as John mentioned many of
them are coming from the more software
engineering tradition or every two weeks
I was sending your patch we upgrade
something there right so that's the uh
last one about this super
cheap a couple thousand dollar level
right but it's not the best car but it's
a reasonable car right uh this W huai
remember at that time uh Tata in Indian
developed this tiny car small car
utterly failed but this one actually
really successful many people uh in
China this is particularly in the rural
area uh people love it right tiny car
very cheap uh and also I can pluging
into my household utility it takes a
long time to charge doesn't go that far
but for most of data use is is
sufficient right uh these just three
example for many many Innovation you
will
see the second one is the diversity this
is draw this uh uh diagram being cheap
to expensive this from the B to PL EV to
EV you'll find that uh almost every part
is covered by some company in China
doing it right um the ecosystem just is
so exciting Imagine This Way in the
United States I would say if if not
Tesla the whole industry is irrelevant
there not much going on at all imagine
10 Tesla like companies simultaneously
innovate competing competing with each
other in China as of today yeah the here
this is the examples here they come from
the EV manufacturer Lee Neil cell pone
byd come this are other side of the
smart vehicle ACC we ride pony catel
well and then there's why in the middle
doing both
side uh I think one of our uh M
initiatives advisor uh Mary Chan uh we
had this advisory meeting John hosted
that she mentioned go to China you look
at the streets half of the brand she
never she never thought never heard of
she's a like a 30y year uh veteran in
the car industry knows everything about
car goes to China half of the brand she
never seen right so that's the dynamism
in that right of course uh it sounds
nice what this means is in the next five
to 10 years There Will Be Blood bass in
China right even as big as China's
Market we cannot support hundreds of
these car companies right lot of them
will be retired uh die off but new wi
were coming out but that makes this
creative destruction at the best
right in a way uh we talk often talk
about China is capitalism or socialism
in that particular regard if one spirit
is is creative destruction in the car
vehicle industry I think China practiced
the best and us I would say we lost that
Spirit we the system does not allow
certain company to retire right and it
makes a new new new company to enter the
market so difficult right but China is
kind of opposite in that so for this
case yes so this is the the second part
right I will argue there's the policy
part which indeed there's a lot of
subsidies from the government giving you
uh R&D loans uh giving you uh cheap land
uh tax uh reduction consumer rebate
across the board that that that's very
true right uh but the important thing
is whatever happened
beforehand as of today in a way it's
irrelevant because the Chinese company
are indeed strong now you make debate oh
the process for it to be strong is
unfair or something but that's gone as
of today a Chinese car company it's just
better right that's important thing and
they they independent enough now you can
say our government we no longer need
those type of subsidy which as a
sophisticated industrial policy
practitioner China is actually gradually
reducing those subsidies along the way
right many of them are reti as you
mentioned the national subsid is already
gone this so you know way it's very
ironic when us criticize China saying oh
you're subsidizing your industry well US
federal government subsidized $7,500,000
by EV and Chinese nor does it so this
argument doesn't really fly anymore this
right uh so that's the policy part but
then the second half is the industry
Innovation on own that's the genuine
power shows uh but the second part I
want to talk about the consumer
preferences uh you know the so which
features attracts a car buyer this right
there's a recent uh uh survey down by
McKenzie look at EU us and China the
result really surprised many people
including myself if you look at what
feature do people pay attention uh this
around pricing total cost driving
performance vehicle consumption
efficiency size driving range then
technology vehicle brand experience
sustainability Cutting Edge technology
material zero carbon interior design M
uh driver assistance system connectivity
personalization all these features right
first of all us and Europe they're very
similar they all focus of very kind of I
say classic features right but look at
the
Chinese they interesting of course the
same thing efficiency safety but also Al
They also interest sustainability
Cutting Edge technology in the vehicle
uh driver assistance system connectivity
those things the the I would say Chinese
consumer actually ahead of the rest of
the world
right this uh evolution of this this
preferences enabled by The Innovation
that the local companies providing in
China this right so that the success of
EVS really come from three parts the
government policy support the innovation
from the industry and also the
consumers uh yeah maybe I talk about
this the second part it's about the
notion of Car Pride and the behavior
part of the John mention uh this is uh
um kind of a a uh
prototypical uh uh stereotypical view of
these modal biases of preference uh
particularly in the United States right
but this is true across the board right
uh we actually studied the the notion
called Car Pride where defined the
notion as uh the value you get of owning
the car beyond the instrumental value of
moving from A to B beside moving around
what additional value you get it's
called Car Pride you can measure them
and you'll find that this car Pride will
posi influence car ownership uh buying a
car buying early spend more more luxury
car I use more use more frequently so
that's the general finding on this uh
but what we we did is we compared that
across about 50
countries uh but this is this about 80
years old now so we should update uh we
survey these people in these 50
countries to measure that this notion of
cight here right uh so it labeled as
down in the bottom is a lower cight on
the top is high copright so which
country have a higher copright uh Kenya
uh UAE India Vietnam Philippines
Malaysia
Thailand who has the lowest copyight
Japan Ukraine France Greece Chile
Austria uh Switzerland right you can see
a quite clear pattern
there the uh developed country generally
have a lower car
PR except uh United States here this
right uh
the developing country
there has quite a high Car Pride there
but what's interesting is at the same
time often the people live there they
have high desire but this desire being
suppressed because the lower income so
what this means is when the GDP grow and
income grow as we we hope they do this
preference will be expressed more so if
you really think about the number of
cars people will want into the future
this when this group uh country getting
richer Etc the car consumption will
continue grow in this all right but I
mention Cary back to China right you
know just a couple years
ago buying a BMW buying a dla Mercedes
all those things it's you you acquire
this strong cpride between this premium
car versus the uh the kind regular
family car right and this particularly
reflected on German made cars
right in China That's everyone is
talking about this yeah there's a jokes
of if a young man want to get married
the the the future mother-in-law will
ask you do you own a house and do you
own a car that's the question and
particular which type of car this right
but almost
dramatically yeah in the last few years
this notion of this German premium uh
coprite almost entirely
destroyed yeah Chinese pring buying
local cars right compared to the
technology compared to safety compared
to the efficiency it's just better right
so this is a major change that we
observe in the Years all right so we
skip this one uh but the second
discussion to maybe end the presentation
here is about the relation between China
and the world uh uh as John mentioned
there's a lot of differences changed
first of all the the export China uh
used to be like nonexistent to show up
to be the the top one uh in term of the
the the total uh uh export but here I
just want to say that the E growth in
China is not a
surprise in the following sense China
has done this multiple times in the 80s
we started with shirts toys TVs cell
phones computers either we don't know
how to do that once we knew Master the
the the technology
what produces the way better uh uh cost
efficiency scal it up and then export it
right and this same thing is apply to
high speed rail architecture design
genetic testing uh so I'm not saying not
just the lower level techn but into very
advanced technology so e is not a
surprise to see these type of uh uh
changes right uh last thing I was say
the current response given this where
you're putting this High tariff I think
is not a good strategy for US own
interest uh this is a combination of
high tariff with high
ego uh it's not like you kind of do
tariff China did tariff Korean did
tariff Taiwan all did that the way you
do it is you set a tariff roughly equal
to your technology differential between
the different domestic market and the
foreign market so that you you keep the
dtic market enable to survive but you
still keep the pressure
right so over the time you reduce the
terror so that your domastic can compete
this blond instrument actually doesn't
help anybody here right the only thing
this you make your domestic uh car
manufacturer lose this incentive
continue innovate in this so as as a my
personal recommendation is us should
invite the Chinese one into the US
market so that US market can catch up
and learn from each other uh thank you I
stop here
[Applause]