hello the goal of this tutorial is to
showcase the downstream large- scale
application of apis integrated with in
the genomics to proteins portal note
that the data accessible via these apis
are also accessible via the portal for
example through the gene protein lookup
module and interactive mapping module
but through the portal they're only
available on a gene by Gene basis the
purpose of these apis is to allow for
large scale access of the data for
example for the entire human proteome
this tutorial is aimed for exactly that
and targeted for users with a coding or
bioinformatics
background the apis that we'll talk
about today are the g2p 3D API which
provides a gene to transcript to protein
isopor to structure mapping for the
ident for all of the corresponding
identifiers and the g g2p protein
feature API which provides a rich
protein feature set at the amino acid
level which includes structural sequence
and functional
properties through the Swagger through
the Swagger page we can directly access
the apis for example by providing a gene
and unipro
ID and we can easily execute the API and
view the result in a spreadsheet format
for example with Excel so here we can
clearly see this um the g2p 3D API
provided mapping and here we have listed
the unipro IDS Associated isoforms Gene
transcript and the associated pdb
structures so here we can clearly see
the associated pdb structures match to
the canonical unip protein
isopor so how how will we apply this for
our analysis so as an example um let's
take the shoper own the shoper own
proteins so the panther protein
classification system identified over
100 chaperon
genes and we'd like to characterize
those genes to better understand um the
available data and um and functional
properties so to do this we're first
going to get a list of the of the list
of the genes and proteins which we can
do from the feros portal by filtering on
the panther protein class and then
downloading um a list of the associated
genes then we can Leverage The g2p
Client API which is a python Library
where we could just where we can easily
access the g2p API
programmatically and get the results as
Panda's data frames which are easy to
use for Downstream
analysis okay so let let's jump into our
analysis so here we have a jupyter
notebook where we can easily install and
import the g2p
API and here we'll load in our list of
shop runs that we downloaded from the
feros portal and you can see here um we
have all the shoper own proteins we've
listed the first five and available
annotation
data okay now we're going to use the g2p
API to systematically get all of the
transcript information for the shop
runes so here we'll get the unipro ID
and G name for each shoppr and then
we'll call the this g2p 3D API directly
using the client
Library so now we can inspect our
results from the call and we can see
that we have all of these we have 3 70
entries across the 110 chaperon
jeans and we we can see the the mappings
for each of those entries now in one
large data frame with transcript
information Gene protein isopor and
structure as
expected okay so now let's do some
analysis we'd like to see how frequently
the main select
transcript maps onto the iCal protein
isopor so to do this we're going to map
we're going to
filter for rows that contain the main
select transcript and the canonical
protein isopor to identify what fraction
of genes have that
mapping um this is um this is important
for structure mapping because variants
that are annotated onto the main select
transcript um because variants are
frequently annotated onto the main
select transcrip script and if it's
associated with the canonical protein
isopor which is frequently the isopor
for which structures are available then
we can easily map those variants onto
the protein structure so here we just
went through and we identified that of
the
110 um chaperon genes
95 had a main select transcript that
mapped onto the protein the canonical
protein isopor and we can easily plot
this in our Jupiter notebook so here we
can see
95 of the main select transcripts mapped
successfully onto the canonical protein
isopor now let's move on to the protein
structure characterization so now we'll
again use the g2p API to call um the g2p
API client Library excuse me to
systematically call the Gap protein
feature API and get the rich amino acid
wide protein features for every one of
The Chaperone genes
so here we'll again use the library to
make the API
call and now we're going to look for
each of the proteins we're going to look
at the secondary structure
propensity and so here one of the
features here we have is the dssp three
state secondary structure computed on
Alpha fold
structure and so we can plot the we can
plot the propensity
of each of these and we can see that 45%
of amino acids are Helix residues 43%
are coil and 11% are strand note that we
also have sift secondary structure
computed on the pdb structures if you'd
like to look at pdb structure
propensity um
and um over and you can conduct a
variety of other Downstream
analysis Okay so in conclusion we saw
the g2p 3D
API and the protein feature API
available through the
portal um and we could access these apis
through two Avenues one through the one
we can access them through the Swagger
page where we can test out the apis and
experiment and secondly we can access
them through the python client
Library where we can import um we can
import the library and scale up our
workflows we can also access notebooks
from previous tutorials inside inside
the client Library GitHub
repository and and in that way we can
characterize different sets of genes for
Downstream
analysis in addition we also have
previous
tutorials on the gene lookup module
interactive mapping and a variety of CAS
studies so if you navigate to the
documentation page within the portal
here or to our YouTube
channel you can you can see previous
tutorials and review um other
functionality and last but not least
please leave us any feedback that you
may have and thank you for your
attention