It is my pleasure now to introduce you
to Neil Gersonfeld who is the director
for the MIT Center for Bits and Atoms.
Welcome.
>> Thank you, Jim. So I'm going to end the
day by pointing out a number of
assumptions that have been uh throughout
the day without being considered and the
opportunity to revisit them. So I lead
the center for bits and atoms. We were
uh created to study the boundary of
digital and physical. Over the year
we've done things like the first faster
than classical quantum computations. We
introduced cryptography and materials,
logic and micrfluidics.
uh we were part of creating the first
synthetic life, part of the group
creating what became internet of things.
That that's what's come from working at
that boundary. And so with all of that
experience, uh it leads up to my
observation in this TED talk that
computer science was one of the worst
things ever to happen to computers or to
science.
And uh to I'll be explaining that
because computer science is based on a
fiction that ignores physics. And today
is going to be all about what does it
mean for computer science to embrace
rather than avoid physics.
So uh here are three thesis from my
group that almost surely you'll be
uninterested in. Um one is on optical
pumping for NMR, one is on micros slots
for electromagnetic instrumentation. Um
one is for embedding internet zero. So
those three authors, one of them was
Jason. Jason built uh Facebook's
computers, then Meta's computers. He was
their VP of infrastructure. Um he helped
lead running servers hot. Uh Microsoft
hired him recently to be in charge of
their accelerated computing. Right now
he's pushing the frontiers of
interconnect. So uh that was uh Jason
who studied optical pumping and did
that. Um another one of those thesis was
Rafie. He'll he built Twitter's
computers. He had Jason's job. He was VP
of infrastructure at uh Twitter.
um uh he's done a number of interesting
things since most recently just became
Mozilla's CTO at Twitter. He helped
observe that uh the scaling of their
platform which was exploding
exponentially was very manual. Uh the
cloud was not was elastic only in
limited degrees of freedom and they had
an urgent need to be able to compile
constraints into computation flexibly in
a way that they um just weren't able to.
So another one of those thesis was Yale
and Yale at then at Facebook with Jason
uh founded open compute and so they
realized as they were building out
Facebook that they needed to control
what was critical to the company and
they needed to commoditize what wasn't
critical to the company. And so that led
to uh roughly they killed Sun and almost
killed Cisco. They replaced proprietary
data centers with modular building
blocks and many of you are now familiar
with uh open compute which is uh
arguably the largest open hardware
project uh ever. So those students did
all of that. Uh a more recent one uh
Matt is now
um uh an embedded developer at uh Oxide
where they're doing private clouds. So a
cloud in Iraq continuing that uh
scaling.
And so these students uh I don't think
of myself as a computer scientist. I
didn't teach them computer science but I
taught them to believe in physics. So
this is a class I teach on the physics
of information technology. And to do it
you can't believe in the abstraction of
software from hardware. You need to
think about thermodynamics and mass and
power and time and physical resources.
Uh so now with that as background in
part to help earn the right to say
computer science was one of the worst
things. Now let's start looking ahead.
So that was history up to the present
and you know CBA is not that large. It's
a disproportionate impact in data
centers. Now let's look ahead to where
it's going. So uh here is 11 orders of
magnitude in scaling compute performance
from the CDC to the Cray to Aurora.
And if you look at the circuit boards,
they all look the same. The chips are
slightly different, but it's chips on a
board in a box.
In my lab, we've been studying the idea
of digital materials. So in the same way
that comput communication and
computation became digital, we're
looking at discreetly assembled simple
building blocks, but we've used that to
make the world record for the highest
modulus ultralight structures. Uh with
NASA made the largest morphing aeros
structures with Toyota uh ultraefficient
race cars.
Uh then by routing power and data
through these building blocks, we can
make u structural electronics. So rather
than electronics that goes into
structures, we make electronics that is
a structure but with state-of-the-art
material properties. And then it leads
to a really interesting kind of robotics
where we can make robots that locomote,
error correct and navigate on these
cellular structures to build the
structures. And we've been exploring
that with NASA for space construction.
And we have a really exciting project
with Bhutan to build a city this way
using sustainable forest products to
make building blocks to build a um a
mindfulness uh city.
And um just as a a note uh there are a
number of joint systems we use in those
functional voxels based on whether
they're um reconfigurable or static. For
the static joints, we're developing ways
to create solid state plasmas that let
you join materials at the properties of
the base material. And so that all adds
up to this as one of the punchlines from
today, which is we're building
airplanes, we're building ships, we're
building developing space settlements.
Um applied to data centers, it means
swarms. You see, we have a paper soon to
um be sent out on how this is going to
replace 3D printing buildings. 3D
printing buildings is slow, expensive,
and irreversible. Here we can do it
incrementally and reversible. And so
applied to a data center, swarms of
these relative robots with these digital
material functional building blocks can
build the mechanical structure and the
electrical structure and the electronic
interconnect. And rather than a big
static investment, it can be done
incrementally. It can grow
incrementally. It can be reconfigured
and you can also unbuild through the
life cycle. And so this was just to do
this, we've had to develop new kinds of
design tools. This was just a mockup of
what would it look like for Swarm
Robotics to build data centers that way.
Now, that's the physical plant. Then
comes what goes into the data center.
And so in computing, there's a hierarchy
from chiplets to chips to boards to
blades, the system full of geometrical
descriptions.
in the applications that run there's
naturally geometry in the algorithms
and those have nothing to do with the
almost nothing to do with each other. So
um I started thinking about this years
ago I did a keynote for the annual
supercomputing meeting and that's where
I really came to appreciate to be not
appreciate to be horrified by how you
preserve the fiction that software runs
separate from hardware. So programmers
like Metropolis, programmers frolic in
the garden describing virtual software.
Um the engineers in the basement are
moving the levers to make it work. And
you have to map from the pretend to the
physical and a lot goes wrong there
among many other problems. Uh here's an
estimate that it's two orders of
magnitude of power is in the cost just
of moving data to get from where it goes
in the pretend place to the physical
place. um two orders of magnitude
compared to the actual computational
work. And so uh that experience led me
to start looking at how we align the
descriptions of software and hardware
rather than pretending they live in
different worlds. Uh this was a DARPER
project where we took the blas the
routines underlying high performance
computing and we implemented them
essentially with physics. So this is a
model of computation where the blas has
a dotproduct that has a multiplier that
has an adder tree. This is one of the
core functions in a machine learning
system. Adder tree then has an adder and
then you can fly all the way in to the
devices and fly out to the application.
So when you zoom a map you go from you
this building to a street to a town to
the city state country. It's
hierarchical but you don't change
geometry when you zoom the map. When you
go from uh transistors to micro code to
embedded code to the system architecture
up finally to the application, we go
through maybe five changes of
representation from what you want to do
to what the system does and with you
know tremendous inefficiency at each of
those translations. So here we showed
you don't need to do that. You can use a
consistent representation from the
physics all the way up to the
application. So to start building those
uh there's some interesting seeds.
Post-war NIST a collaborator in this
work started project Tinker Toy which
was robotic assembly of vacuum tubes.
And then a colleague at DARPA Andreas
Olivesson um started the chips project
which is how the whole chip industry has
pivoted to instead of a big chip you
make chiplets and assemble system on
chip out of the chiplets.
But the chiplets are constrained. So 3D
heterogeneous integration is very hot
right now. In a chips solicitation, they
stretch to say we want to stack six
chiplets and the big vision is to
eventually get to 20 chiplets. So it's
really two-dimensional with very limited
three dimension.
Um my lab's done a lot of work on
advanced manufacturing. So in the video
you saw before the session, they showed
the Formlabs printers that came from my
lab among other uh machine companies
that make machines. And so that led to
with DARPA and a few other agencies
asking can we make a cross between a
pick and place and a 3D printer to
compile the 3D construction of
computation.
So instead of chiplets in a package in a
chip on an interposer on a board with
discretets on blades and system can we
consistently just do the whole thing in
one process now that isn't done at a
monolithic level so we've made building
blocks with uh GPUs CPUs MCUs
discretetses and down to base material
properties and the granularity what that
you want to do the assembly depends on
the application
So, we've done versions at each scale,
but what I'm showing here is work done
by Alan in the back. Uh, that's Alan.
Uh, which is a version of this cross
between a pick and place in a 3D printer
that takes these building blocks and
instead of chips on boards and blades
and system, it just fills volumes with
computing structure to compile the
construction of computation in a direct
process. And that has many implications
I'll talk about in a few minutes. Uh
then next to Allan is Eric. That's Eric.
And there's no 3D electronic design
automation software. You you you design
a 2D circuit and then somebody else and
then designing the schematic is
completely separate from the PCB
separate from the fabrication. So Eric
has made sort of CAD and CAM for
computation where you can design the
construction of a computation as a
geometrical structure and so one version
is bottom up and here what he's showing
is an adder and then you can just simply
stack those adders to build a bigger
adder in 3D and under the hood this does
mix signal simulation and then in
parallel top down is compilation where
you can start with verarilog but you can
compile vera log into a 3D construction.
And so here's an example of a uh
compiling the construction of a 3D uh
microprocessor in that design workflow.
And so for the data center again as
concept art what this leads to is the
possibility
of direct write fabrication of 3D
computing structures where you can
compile the construction of the
application into the data center rather
than all of the pain of cache
concurrency and interconnect bandwidth
and levels of cache and the orders of
magnitude overhead in uh data moves. you
can actually compile the geometry of a
computation into the construction to do
it. Starting with these uh base parts
for things that you can't integrate on
chip um then with chiplet scale
integration um commoditized in very much
the same way OCP open compute
commoditized uh what used to buy from
sun. This is now commoditizing to a much
finer grain building block of these
simple parts we can assemble into 3D
data structures and they assemble with
all the properties of digital of error
correction in the construction is what
gives it the scalability.
So uh one of the nice benefits of this
is instead of heat trans heat
dissipation being localized in 2D in hot
processors we can distribute heat
throughout a 3D volume and we can
interdigitate heat transfer through the
volume. So it has nice properties uh for
cooling.
So we're exploring this in a number of
domains. One of them is Arya is the UK
recent UK analog to DARPA and with them
we're looking at can machine learning
systems learn their construction. So
rather than we all use transformers and
Nvidia GPUs, we're looking at very
different heterogeneous architectures
for learning that have a lot of very
interesting properties like um learning
much more efficiently in time and power
um and are not monolithic but are
heterogeneous. So we're looking at
compiling the construction of machine
learning systems with these and uh this
is an interesting proposal we did with a
group of interesting companies
to take
uh circuit boards today are made with
SMD surface mount devices and that's
been true throughout the whole history
of those PCBs I showed you. You can
think about what I'm describing here is
VMDS or volume mount devices. And among
the benefits are uh there's a long path
from a chiplet to design and test with
the system. We can just paste a chiplet
into the system. Um there are a lot of
things you can't integrate on chip high
power high current. For that we can
assemble uh um discretets as uh building
blocks. Uh these are reversible
processes. So rather than when you're
done you make e-waste and you have to
try to melt down the the underlying
components, we can disassemble and
reassemble these building blocks. Um you
don't you can go from system on chip
today you then need to design PCBs and
racks around it. We can span that in a
single process
and uh it's a direct rate process. So an
Nvidia GPU is a billion-dollar
development cycle. Here we're
commoditizing. You can think about it as
the cores in the GPU. And then it's a
direct rate process to fabricate it.
Analogous to injection molding versus 3D
printing. Instead instead of significant
capital overhead, it's direct assembly
are all opportunities with this move
towards uh volume mount devices.
Now there's an overhead to discreetly
assembling. It's a strong function of
dimension. This is looking at uh time
and power cost of this discrete assembly
rather than integrating on chip. And
when you get down to roughly micron
scale um as the feature size is where
the overhead becomes competitive with
how it's done today. And so one of the
most interesting for me projects in this
collaboration is with another group at
MIT Farnas Naroy and Schmidt Foundation
where we're looking at essentially when
Lego becomes quantum. So looking at the
crossover between mechanical joints in
these building blocks and um bonding in
these building blocks scaling the
building blocks down to uh tens of
nanometers. So that's much finer scale
than what I showed you in Ericson
Allen's work. But in the road map, we're
filling in the limiting point where you
can assemble um all the way down to
nanocale.
So first step in this path was this
discussion today has been about data
centers as static things. With these
digital materials and these swarm
robots, we can build dynamic physically
reconfigurable data centers.
Then the second assumption is the chips
are static. You know, you you wait for
Nvidia to burp out their next chip. Um
we're leading to a world where that's
just not true, where the computation
itself is discreetly assembled,
reconfigurable, and can match workloads
and grow with workloads.
Um the biggest step then after that is
uh my lab I mentioned did the first
faster than classical quantum
computations. We did um uh or searching
an unordered list and part of the
collaboration was implementing factoring
uh based on spin resonance techniques.
Once we push the scaling as I showed you
down to the um feature sizes, we then
run into quantum effects. The quantum
effects can be a bug, but they can be a
significant feature. And so
I'd say the most exciting graph you're
likely to see today is upper in the
upper right corner and that's from Alex
in the back. That's Alex from Lincoln
Labs.
Uh with Lincoln Labs we've been looking
at what are called adiabatic quantum
flux parametrons.
And so that's using uh quantum mechanics
in superconducting circuits to do logic.
And the wiggly lines at the bottom are
showing schematically
the superconducting quantum. So to be
clear, we're using quantum mechanics but
not for quantum computation. We're using
quantum mechanics to do classical
computation much more efficiently. So
the AQFP acts like a double well
potential and then you can dynamically
um tilt the potential to move the state
in those wells. And so in today's CMOS
logic, it's insane.
Every bit at every clock tick in every
transistor is destroyed. And uh all that
power ridiculous power going in is to
destroy every the energy in every bit at
every clock tick. It's just crazy. So
these adabatic quantum flux parametrons
store state in these double well
potentials and then carefully move it
around. And so what the graph in the
upper right is showing you is KT is the
minimum unit of thermodynamic energy
sort of that's in a thermal system
that's as low as you can go. Uh COS
today is about 10 the 5 KT these AQFPs
not as a projection just in the lab are
just over KT within a factor of a few of
KT.
So this is a 10 to the5 improvement in
the power efficiency of a logic device.
Now before you get too excited, I'll end
by telling you about the overheads. And
with the overheads, conservatively, we
might lose 10 to the three. So I can
only give you a factor of 100 power
gain, but very conservatively I can give
you a factor of 100 power gain. So what
makes this possible is Lincoln Labs has
probably the leading superconducting
chip fab and that's what we were using
to be able to uh develop these uh AQFP
chips and there's a very close
connection between the previous work I
showed you on discrete assembly and the
superconductivity and this is how it
started because of both yield but also
the underlying physics there's a limit
to the complexity of a superconducting
chip. We're not going to make a billion
Josephs and Junction superconducting
chip. And so we need an architecture
that can take much smaller chips and
build big systems out of that. And
that's what led to this collaboration to
use these electronic assemblers to make
superconducting systems. And so now what
I'm showing you is we've implemented
everything you need to make a computing
system. So it includes control
architecture,
um, math units, uh, memory, both larger
and smaller memories. Um, on top row are
chips we've designed and fabricated
through Lincoln's fab. And then in the
lower left is what looks like
simulation, but is data coming from the
chips. Um, you know, if I gave this talk
two years ago, it wouldn't look like
that. They were very homely. At this
point, um, the process technology is
really dialed in and works beautifully.
And part of the idea of this is we don't
need to go now to billion-dollar fab to
make um giant chips. We can yield these
smaller super superconducting chips and
then uh build larger systems out of
them.
So then given all of that, what we're
now up to is we we can measure
all the the individual adabatic quantum
flux parametrons and we can measure
um the the math processors, the memory
units, the control units out of them.
And then we can take all of that and
push it through simulation tools and do
simulation of full computing systems
where we're simulating the full
computing system but it's based on the
experimental uh measurements at the
device level. And what that gives us is
the factor of 100. So the factor of 100
starts with the 10 to the five and then
we lose about 10 to the three again
conservatively from cryogenic overhead
and various inefficiencies of the
system.
And so it leads to the opportunity for
cryogenic uh data centers. And so in
this sketch what we're showing is
surprisingly there is an existing market
for rack scale cryogenics.
Uh I suspect a lot of that is classified
applications we can't know about. That
includes things like optics and radios
um that have to work at physical limits.
But at rack scale you so um th this runs
happily at 4K and we're you know inching
a little bit above that but at rack
scale you can have a 4K cryo system
where you put in electricity and it's a
closed system and then we'll fill the
rack with these uh VMDs
uh to build uh physically reconfigurable
superun superconducting electronics and
then what we get is a ballpark 10
kilowatt rack doing the work of a
megawatt rack today. So there's a lot of
work to commercialize that. We haven't
yet come anywhere making this at full
rack scale, but we validated all the
steps that come into it. And it's it's I
think by far the most dramatic
opportunity for a 100x win that would
radically change a lot of the
calculations about cost and power for
data centers. So we're left with this
hierarchy of
uh MIT made the last great analog
computer, Venever Bush. It was a room
full of gears and pulleys and the answer
got worse the longer you ran it. And uh
the student working on that wrote the
best master thesis anybody did ever. It
was Claude Shannon and he invented
digital in his master's thesis because
he was so annoyed at the differential
analyzer and crucially digital
uh he went on to help show what are
called threshold theorems where in a
system where you can restore a state
digital doesn't mean one and zero. What
it means is if you restore state
uh for a linear increase in the physical
representation of the state there's an
exponential reduction in the error um to
decode it and that e there's very few
engineering exponentials that
exponential is what lets uh us compute
reliably
you know now on exoscale then uh uh
after uh so Shannon did that for
communication van uh developed it for
computation.
State-of-the-art chip fabrication is
fundamentally analog. Um, it's it's feed
forward. There's no information in the
construction. Your ribosome, 4 billion
years old, is digital. It detects and
corrects errors. And so, at heart in
what I'm describing is building
properties of digital state and error
correction into construction. Uh, it's
true in Lego bricks. Lego is more
accurate than the child. Um, uh, you
don't need a ruler for Lego. And there's
no Lego trash. And those are also
properties of ribosomes. And they're not
properties of chip fab. And so these
assemblers I'm describing start from
simple building blocks, make
micromechanical systems that build
larger systems that build microobotic
systems that build still larger robots
that build u macro systems. And we've
shown that at each of those scales.
And before Jim invited me for this, even
though my lab has done so much on
previous work on data centers, as I
showed you at the beginning, I hadn't
really thought about pulling all this
together in this context. But it leads
to this radically different version of
the future of data centers where swarm
robots are going to build the macro
structures, micro assemblers are going
to build the reconfigurable computation,
and we're going to use superc
conductivity to save orders of magnitude
and power. um addressing many of the
crucial issues you've talked about
throughout the day.
Now, all of that may sound
like a big stretch from from where you
were, but what's interesting is
Vanoyman is credited for Vanoyman
architecture.
Vanoyman wrote beautifully about many
things. Computing architecture was not
one of them. He he only wrote about the
Vaniman architecture in a dreadful memo,
the Edvac report. Um that was just kind
of an hack.
What he did write about towards the end
of his life is self-reproducing automa.
So you this pioneer of computation
towards the end of his life was studying
how a computation can communicate its
construction
and he was asking that question towards
trying to understand life.
uh other pioneer of computing touring
again well known for computing
uh towards the end of his life what he
was studying was morphogenesis
was the evode deeo problem of how genes
give rise to form so the founders of
computation
towards the end of their life were
studying fabrication they were studying
the construction of computation
you know in a computer science
curriculum you're unlike ly to ever hear
about the physical form of computation.
The pioneers of computing saw that as
absolutely essential of describing the
construction of computation as integral
to understanding and developing
computation
and ignoring it has led to orders of
magnitude of efficiency, waste and power
of e-waste of just all kinds of problems
you've been talking about today. I
embracing rather than avoiding the
construction of computation gives you
the opportunity in all these different
areas. And so on the right there's a
magisterial series of uh papers from the
Santa Fe Institute on classics of
complexity. This is an essay I wrote on
revisiting uh Vanoyman's ideas in the
Santa Fe complexity series.
And so to follow up on the left is uh my
most recent book where I describe this
research roadmap um and a long form lex
podcast where I talk about it. And the
challenge now is we've proved out all
the things I've shown you. There's a
challenge now and an opportunity to
really scale to do that at data center
scale. But uh it it's something we're
eager to tackle. And I think by
revisiting the assumptions through today
of a data center, you build a data
center and it doesn't change and
somebody else makes chips and they don't
change and we use CMOS. By revisiting
all of those assumptions, it has just
profound impa implications for being
faster, better, cheaper, more
environmentally friendly, more scalable
uh through life cycle.
So thank you
>> here
question over there.
>> That was a very interesting
presentation. Um, one question that I
want to pose is um what's can you give
me a sense of the largest uh processor
I'll call it uh of this sort that you've
run any kind of input and output on some
kind of algorithm and I'm also curious
if something physically happens to one
of these assembled structures does it
degrade gracefully what's that behavior
look like
>> when you say well for the first question
so Alex what's the biggest chip in fab
right now
How many JJs?
>> Okay. Um, so you know in the history of
IC industry right now we're at the um
sort of MSI era at the be you know sort
of at the edge of the VLSI era. So so
we're roughly at this this is about the
almost exactly the complexity of the
Intel 404 is is roughly where we are
technologically.
But that that's slightly unfair just in
that the the modeling I showed you is
what you do when you uh model a billion
transistor chip in that you prove out
you don't in one go make the billion
transistor chip. You prove out the
device physics of you know your two
nanometer process and then there are
these very sophisticated modeling tools
that take the physics measurements and
use that to do the system modeling. And
so, um, the biggest we've made is
roughly the equivalent of the Intel 404,
um, microprocessor. And that, but we're
using industrial strength modeling tools
to predict the full size system scale.
>> 30
again.
>> Okay. 30 million junction memory chip.
Um, and then you're asking about how
these systems fail.
>> Yes.
Um so one of the um
really interesting opportunities here is
you should view the robotic assemblers
I'm describing as not at the factory and
then you send it to the data center but
you you view this as part of the data
center. So central to this project is
the reconfigurability. So if something
breaks or you want to change application
you can disassemble and reassemble it.
And so the re reconfigurability is a
central part of the project. So you you
should think view this as robotic
assemblers running around uh fixing and
rebuilding systems. We started looking
at that just for structural failure for
things like airplanes. But it then is I
I should explain that the sequence was
we were making discreetly assembled
record setting micro robots and we had
to put brains into the robots and then
when we put the brains in the robots we
realized we were building computing
systems and that's what started this
whole lineage.
Let's see. I think he um Yeah, I think
he had his hand up next.
>> Jim, come on. Jim, start.
>> So, uh Neil, this is this a fantastic. I
wonder I was very interested by the um
cryogenic computer but more from
conventional computer and I wonder you
mean earlier today we heard about the
prediction of Jensen Wong around quantum
computing being 20 years out. Is there
an opportunity to leverage some of the
technology that's developed for uh
quantum computing in cooling wise but
leverage that for conventional cryogenic
cooling on the racks and do you have any
sense of a time frame?
>> Oh, you mean cryogenic cooling for for
conventional racks
>> for Yeah, the one that that you that you
show wasn't qu you said was not quantum
computing.
>> Oh, no. But but the it was quantum No,
let me say it really carefully.
>> Okay. Um so real quantum computing like
the the the first things I did use two
essential properties of entanglement and
superposition
and for a subset of problems it lets you
do things exponentially faster than
classical. Now the caution is quantum is
far from universally applicable and
there's a lot of overselling going on.
There's some problems for which quantum
um has radical implications but it's
it's a subset. What I was doing is
quantum computing.
It's fundamentally quantum mechanical
but the difference is the quantum
mechanics is within the logic elements
the thing I'm calling Joseph's and
junctions. So I'm not implementing.
So in in quantum computing the bits
themselves are quantum. They can be in
superposition entanglement. In what I
described the bits are classical.
They're either one or zero. But
crucially, my ability to run 10 the 5
more efficiently comes from I'm
representing the bits using quantum
mechanics and I'm moving the bits using
quantum mechanics.
>> That makes sense.
>> And so the underlying device so in
quantum computing there's about five
competing systems for the physics. One
of them is exactly these same circuits I
showed you. But here we're ignoring the
quantum coherence part. Um, we're
embracing all of the classical computing
applications, but we're saving 10 to the
five by using quantum mechanics, not to
destroy the energy in a bit at every
cycle, but to carefully manipulate it.
>> Yeah, thanks.
>> More questions?
>> I think there's one back there.
>> Yeah,
>> thank you. Um, the Intel 404, I had to
look it up. Um, it's a processor that
came out in 1971 and had 2,300
transistors. Um, what's the density of
that processor that's currently um, you
know, in testing? Is it the same size or
is it bigger? So uh what's so again the
the the reason yeah the the Intel 404 it
it is in very short order became the
8088 which became the IBM PC and then
the world exploded and so it it it was
the the the key complexity scale where
the world diverged and Moors law really
took off that's why it's such a revered
processor and so we're at that
complexity scale now the to the previous
question um our feature size is on the
order of micron scale, you know, maybe
100 nanometers. The feature size we're
using is ancient compared to
state-of-the-art uh semiconductor fab uh
uh but that's limited by the physics. So
the these Josephson junctions
manipulating quantum coherence, we can't
shrink them arbitrarily smallly. There
there's a natural scale length to the
physics. Um but one of the really
interesting things is uh moving data the
two orders of magnitude that comes from
the architectural inefficiency of the
software and hardware disagreeing but it
also just comes from the cost of pushing
bits through wires. Um we heard earlier
today somebody talking about
superconducting power. That's true for
us down at the bit level. There's no
loss in moving our bits through these
wires. So interconnect is um much much
much cheaper in this world and in fact
even in some of these architectures
interconnect is a feature not a bit bug
meaning we have flying bits in these
wires is an interesting architectural
implication. So it's possible there
might be some scaling but for many
reasons we don't need to push the
feature size and we're not pushing the
feature size um we're scaling out in the
system size. Anything you'd add, Alex?
>> I follow that. I mean, the other point I
guess is scaling. One of the reasons COS
had to shrink a lot related to charging
wires. Everything gets smaller. It's
lower power. Uh same thing with
transistor sizes. None of that is true
for us. So, we don't have the same power
benefits. So it's that that's an
economic no that's not
>> what I'm trying to understand is how
much bigger would a computer be um with
the super
>> physically physically it's likely it's
it's quite plausibly going to be smaller
>> because if you look at the megawatt uh
Nvidia rack
the work is actually happening in a tiny
part of the rack and all the rest is
packaging around that and heat transfer
and you know wire interconnect um we can
use space much more efficiently
and so yeah I don't think we've done
exactly that calculation but quite
plausibly um uh
>> so the heat transfer efficiency is it's
something like 100 times better if you
normalize because imagerating
10 the five cheaper. So it's kind of
like 10 the five watts per centimeter
which is sort of a higher effective
power density on the chip than you know
this the surface of the cell. So that's
what sets it at the rack scale. You know
ultimately on the chip it might be super
high power density but you have to
dissipate it over some much larger area
discharge to the ocean etc. And so from
that perspective of how much heat do you
have to get rid of that's what sets
these really big scales like a size
building.
might be possibly smaller.
>> Okay,
any other questions?
>> Okay, then let's hear it for Neil.