All
right. Um, so that's great. Um, thank
you for the introduction. Um, we're so
pleased to be here. Um, the CIRC, uh,
funding enabled us to fund a really
expansive and exciting and amazing kind
of rolling public conversation. Um,
we're characterizing it as a rolling
public think tank about all aspects of
AI. Um, so, uh, we're really
appreciative of this funding.
Um, I'm gonna get us started. Um, I want
to ask how many of you raise your hand
if you were consulted about chat
GPT. Yeah. Yeah. We were not consulted.
Nobody was consulted. Um, and this is
actually part of the problem, right? Um
and so this is part of the motivation
for um our original proposal which as
you'll see we actually have diverged
significantly but we remain focused on
these questions of participation and
voice and who gets a say in which
product which AI products are built how
they're built um who they benefit and
and who they harm um and so you know we
came to this work I'm from the data plus
feminism lab so there's a lab in
department of urban studies and planning
Um and what we do is uh we are
interested in the intersection of on the
one hand racial justice and gender
justice but we think about how do we use
data computation and AI and the service
of those goals. Um and in the past we
have actually done a lot of work in
participatory AI. So in fact we have
co-designed AI systems uh with uh
citizen data science citizen data
scientists who are working on
gender-based violence particularly in
Latin America. Um I have a book about
this if you're interested. Um and it's
been an amazing learning process over
the past five years to be co-developing
AI tools um aligned with the visions of
feminist activists working to really
transform their worlds. But these kind
of participatory methods are not
mainstream um and certainly not
mainstream in AI development. So what we
wanted to do is to think about how could
we create a a framework for this this
sort of mainstreamy work. And so that's
why the original title is a framework
for participatory methods and community
engagement across the AI ML
pipeline. Um and so these were original
research questions. This is what we
submitted in our proposal. Um, how can
AI and machine learning projects
integrate methods from participatory
action research, from participatory
design? How can we um use AI development
and this participatory process to uplift
rather than extract community knowledge?
Um, what are the epistemic and ethical
obligations of AI and machine learning
projects that undertake participation
and civic engagement in this development
process? Um but I think one of the
things I want to ask you to note about
these research questions is that their
scale of analysis is already inside a
pipeline of technical development which
is to say outside of these questions. Um
there has already been a decision to
develop a
technology. Um there have already been
questions around you know and the
questions now are more about like how do
we integrate communities into this thing
that like we are already building. we've
already decided this thing will be
useful in the world. Um, and I ask you
to note that because this is exactly
where we ran into um issues and where we
really wanted to pivot because we we
realized if we wanted to actually build
AI and machine learning that modeled
pluralistic methods and supported
integrating community needs and
community knowledge, we actually needed
to expand the scale of our inquiry. Um,
and we needed to do more systems
thinking. We need to think like outside
of just the pipeline of technical
development. Um but first Nico is going
to tell you about our our first foray
into this literature review of
participatory methods in AI development
which are increasingly are being talked
about. So they are um hi everyone. Um so
very quickly you because we're in urban
planning we started with the classic
Arnstein's latter of participation
thinking of how people can get involved
in uh in the a IML pipeline. Um and we
came across what I've come to call sort
of geometries of participation. There's
the ladder, there's the cube, there are
scales, there are all these um ways to
shuttle people from ideiation through
deployment or maintenance um still
within this AI system
um and and ways to measure right their
participation in the system and and even
their own level of satisfaction. Did
they feel agential? Did they feel like
they were respected and consented
through the process?
Um, but I think like Katherine was
saying, uh, we're still working within
with inside of the technical pipeline.
And my own training comes as a software
engineer. I worked in industry for many
years. Um, and my training was to be a
systems thinker and when there are
problems in the pipeline to kind of step
back and step back and step back and
step back until I could see a big enough
picture to understand what the problems
were. And so to me coming from my own
background um even in industry thinking
about well can I um you know add
participants to make more ethical just
felt insufficient. Um and so we started
to ask a different question which is
under what conditions are people and
communities able to meaningfully
participate in the creation evaluation
and governance of
AI. And I think uh like Katherine said
this takes the focus uh no none of us
got asked if chat GPT should be built
and so creation is also a really
important part of this question right
are we building AI that you want should
we build this at all um so we we started
we didn't intend to build a think tank
but we did and we gathered researchers
from um all of these institutions and
more and I think most importantly we
gathered 25 of us from all of these
disciplines so we have early career
graduate students U masters, first to
second year PhD students all the way to
full professors in all of these
disciplines. And we're all having this
conversation together. And some of them
are practitioners. We have lawyers, we
have studio artists.
Um, and so we're thinking of the project
as liberatory AI. And you'll notice in
this animation, AI continues to change
uh across our disciplines. We couldn't
even really agree on a working
definition of AI. And that felt
important and generative. And so we
didn't. Um, we're thinking about all of
the things that AI can stand for and
we're talking um in three three ways
about corporate AI um about the dead
ends uh within a corporate AI ecosystem
and about ways forward both through and
out of corporate
AI. Um so uh the design by one of our
master students Alicia
Delgado and we um collectively and
individually wrote about 20 position
papers. These are short, they're
accessible, but they engage with all of
the most current academic literature.
They're up on a website that is live
now. Um, and so we're thinking um about
ways for both practitioners and
community members and people across
disciplines to really be thinking about
the systems under which we can
meaningfully participate. Um, and also I
want to mention not all the pieces
really even agree with each other and we
find that to be really important.
Um, so really quickly, uh, thinking
about the corporate AI landscape, this
this landscape in which we've got
billion-dollar global tech oligarchs
setting the terms of our engagement. Um,
Issa Krushian at Queen Mary wrote about
how corporate AI can provoke threats to
democracy. I think we're seeing some of
that in current events right now. Um
Amelia and Hungjin wrote about AI being
placeless and they give these examples
of these um you know systems trained to
identify plant life from across the
globe, right? The AI sits somewhere, the
object of study sits somewhere else or
generative AI being asked to generate
images of cities but all the cities kind
of look the same even though most of us
can understand how cities look different
from each other. uh UA who's a CS
student at Brown uh talks about how in
corporate AI a corporation might market
an AI system as being very performant um
increasing the performance but the AI
system sets those benchmarks they're not
set by the communities in which the AI
is used or
tested. Um, we're thinking also about
dead ends, about all of these ways that
corporate AI, um, not to make it sound
too menacing, but sort of tricks us into
thinking that we can engage in ways that
might reduce harm or might be more
ethical. Um, and so we have we're
working on projects to think about
toolkitification. Richmond Wong has this
wonderful idea about toolkitification
being this seductive way to think maybe
we're making a difference. um thinking
about the responsibility gap at AI uh
systems claiming to take responsibility
for the harms that they cause but maybe
not actually doing so in practice. Um
and always thinking about AI audits and
whether those are the most effective
ways to engage with systems. Um I want
to spend the most time on ways forward
uh because I think it feels hopeful and
optimistic uh amidst a lot of critique.
Um and our ways forward are not these
like onetoone solutions. We're not
saying this over here is a problem and
this over here is a solution. But rather
we can reject these terms entirely and
simply think about ways forward. And
those ways forward might include small
and open-source models, laptop scale,
right? Compute that we own, that we can
repair, that we have access to. Um, it
definitely includes community data
governance, community data stewardship,
and community model ownership. um where
communities can set the terms of their
engagement with that
technology. Um and it includes
communitydriven benchmarks where
communities get to decide if AI is
working for them, if a particular model
is working for them and what the uh
repercussions might be if those models
are not a good
fit. Um and then quickly a couple of
instances of really wonderful AI that is
sort of working in this way already that
some of our members have pointed out. So
the Igbo speech um platform that is
starting to make Igbo language available
to programs like Dualingo. So preserving
indigenous language and making
indigenous language more
available. Um ways that people are
thinking about how to make resource
intensive AI work in harmony with those
who are stewarding our environment. So
thinking about frugal computing,
thinking about water cooling systems,
thinking about other ways to make data
centers more performant and easier on
the planet
um in programs um and projects like
WikiBench where people are community
curating the data that AI models are
being trained on using open source
corpora using open source and community
based methods. Um back to Katherine.
Sure. Um, so yeah, we just wanted to
wrap this up um by saying that we would
see this project is we see it as a
rolling public dialogue. That's why
we're calling it a a kind of a think
tank. We're not necessarily giving
answers. We're not even necessarily
agreeing with each other. Um, but we're
coming together to dialogue and debate
about both problems, dead ends, and and
ways forward. Um, and so we think about
this as this as an invented space of
citizenship. So this builds on um very
famous uh planning scholar farneck
Mafab. She has this notion of invited
versus invented spaces of citizenship.
Um and so instead of waiting right now
for open AI or for Google or for Meta to
you know invite us in to participate um
to on their terms um on the products
they deem worthy to build and invest in.
um then this group of us and then maybe
all of you because you're all invited to
be with us as well. Um we we came
together here to sort of contest the
status quo and to be able to think
larger thoughts be able to think
thoughts that help us reorganize
resources in this AI system to recognize
that the organization of resources
structurally it is was having all of
these harmful downstream effects. And so
how do we sort of think about
reorganizing those right now? Um so
think about how do we re rearrange those
resources in hope of a larger societal
transformation and always in a way with
a belief that we can and should build
systems that work for all of us right
um and so here we are for next steps
where this is going this project um
we've kind of started a snowball that
keeps going this project doesn't seem to
be ending anytime soon um it keeps
acrewing uh new members new people keep
joining us which has been really
fascinating um so now it's going to be a
partnership between Smith College where
Nico is headed next year as an assistant
professor and MIT. Uh then we're
thinking of pitching it as an edited
volume um to like an academic trade
crossover book. So the there might be
like a kind of a book that emerges from
this. Um and then continuing our rolling
public think tank. We have bi-weekly
meetings. We do a lot of uh reading and
discussion. We invite people to come and
present their work and we all discuss it
together. Um we're also thinking about
doing public workshops. We really want
to get students involved in particular
students in computer science um students
in these more sort of technical
disciplines um to think about what are
some of these really interesting
problems even as a research space like
how do we build you know small models
how do we do uh distributed uh model
development how do we have uh
sovereignty over our AI models and so on
and so forth I think actually these are
really interesting sociotechnical uh
research questions and be great to
involve students sort of at the
beginning um And then yeah, you're
invited. So it's it's a very open
project and we we invite you all and you
just have to email Nikki. That's that's
the way to get started. Um and so just
to close out, we want to thank everyone
who's joined the project so far. These
are all the folks who were in community
with and this this think tank. Um and
then many many thanks to CIRC for for
making this possible. um we didn't
really know what the we this the output
doesn't look like the output that we
thought we would get but I think that's
actually the best result of a
pluralistic process. So thank you.
Thank you. or Katherine
questions. Um, thank you so much for the
talk. I'm so excited by this idea. Um I
am curious to to know it seems like a
lot of the folks involved in the um
think tank are folks from higher
education. So is there any intention to
involve stakeholders outside of this
realm of higher education which is a bit
of a self- selecting group?
Yeah, I think that's such a good
question. It's 100% a self- selecting
group. I think um the yes, the short
answer is yes, absolutely. I think the
longer answer is how do we engage folks
who maybe don't want to do readings with
us or want to be we you know we we need
to meet them where they are um we've run
out of funding right and so we've spent
the money and what I I don't want to
bring in people who who want to be
compensated right I get we get paid to
be here all of us academics we get paid
to read together and it feels really
extractive to ask a community member to
come and be here on their free time and
so I think if we get money to compensate
people for their part for their
participation right in meaningful ways.
Absolutely.
Thanks for the talk. Um, you mentioned
that like not everybody agreed on
everything when you guys were meeting
together. So, were there any like
disagreements you found especially
productive or like learned something
from?
Um, you know, I think one of the things
that we've been finding funny is we all
have like like I would say a fraught
relationship with AI, but that that
comes from for different reasons and
it's also to different degrees. So there
are people who have participated in the
project who would characterize
themselves as um I think AI refusers. So
they actually like refuse to engage.
They they from a from an ethical
standpoint like they don't use Chachi
PT. um they're not trying to incorporate
anything with AI or generative AI sort
of in their lives or whatever. Um so
they're kind of these really kind of
extreme um sort of refusal standpoints
which I think is interesting and there's
actually a really interesting long
literature on refusal not just as a no
right but actually as a generative
position. So like we've incorporated uh
contributions from folks who are kind of
in that realm of things to say like if
you refuse like you know it also begs
the question of like can we refuse? I
mean literally can we opt out at this
point? Um I'm not sure right. Um and so
that that has been interesting and
provocative. Um I'm trying to think of
what else. Uh I think one of the things
that's been really interesting is to be
in dialogue and one of the things we've
been careful to try to
structure is to is around that
disciplinary um
diversity um because we didn't want to
have people from purely outside of a
development space like
non-developers outside who have never
say built an application or they've
never trained a model or something like
that. kind of being those like stone
throwers, you know, you like, you know,
you armchair critique and you you throw
stones from outside. So we have tried to
structure the dialogue in such a way
that um we're having generative
conversations from inside from you know
literally students that are PhD students
professors of computer science um and
outside so that we're colliding some of
these disciplines um I think in very
productive ways and also um bridging
some of the language gaps that often
prohibit us from from speaking to each
other even like the same language. Um I
don't know if you can think of other No,
I think I think that's right. The one
thing I will add is to the point of like
being in community with developers. All
of my research and scholarship comes out
of my own career as a software engineer.
And it's really important to me to
remember that working AI developers
can't refuse AI, right? They only they
have such a limited range of choices and
that I want that to always be in
conversation with us.
Um, this is maybe the other end of the
spectrum, but it gets at the insider
outsider idea. Um, as I've been doing
this research and been kind of
fascinated by some of the biggest AI
development companies, you know, Open
AI, Google, one of the things you learn
is those are really big, well-funded
companies and with very diverse
um, uh, employees uh, with lots of
different attitudes and I've encountered
in different contexts I think a number
of employees at companies like that who
I think would be interested and
supportive of the work that you're doing
are working on some really interesting
versions of trying to align their
product and their models with the
mission with democratic governance that
sort of thing. I also think anybody
who's looked at the history of business
would question whether those
recommendations or those initiatives
will survive um an era where at some
point the venture capitalists are going
to expect those companies to be
profitable too. So, I'm just curious
what your thoughts are about engaging
with people inside the big tech
companies uh who are doing work that
might be interesting or exciting or
might be aligned with the work that
you're doing. Yeah. No, 100%. And
actually, um none of the current
contributors,
right, are corporate researchers, right?
Yeah. So, none of the current
contributors are, but I will say one of
the my most generative events that I
participated in in the past year was an
event that brought together um industry
researchers and um scholars to think
about cultural inclusion and generative
AI. Um and and it was fascinating to
understand some of the constraints um
but also to understand some of the
opportunities and I I agree with you
that there really there is alignment and
certainly at the researcher to
researcher level I think there is
alignment and I think there's some um
opportunity there what we would I think
call attention to so what we're saying
with like corporate AI is not to that's
not like a judgment on somebody that
works in a corporation MIT is a
corporation
So, you know, like there there's not
like a some kind of like um purity
critique there or something like that.
Um but more to say exactly what you just
said, which is that the um structures
again the allocation of resources, the
way that resources are arranged in a in
a corporate model favors the production
and decisions around certain kinds of
products being made to serve certain
kinds of populations. Meanwhile, there's
a whole space over here, and that's
that's a space that I've often worked in
is sort of uh community technology,
feminist technology, human rights
technology. There all these sort of
application areas that never get built
for because they are not profitable.
There's simply no business model. And so
like the question there is like is that
who we want the tech to serve? That's a
real asymmetry and innovation. And so
how do we do it differently? How do we
structure things differently to produce
different products and different
outcomes? Yeah.
And I guess my question actually relate
uh somewhat to what you just outline is
as a sin tank uh what is your long-term
goal? Yeah. And uh what is the shortterm
goal and how do you sustain yourself
because just now you saying that the
funding is longing out and how do you
sustain yourself? Yeah. Uh to achieve
that kind of goal and love to hear about
it. Yeah. We want to know the answer
too. Yeah. If you have the answer that
would be great. I don't know if you want
I mean I think like the most honest
answer is like I have some startup
funding from my new professorship and
some of that will go to maintaining this
and then we're going to write some
grants and hope for the best. Yeah,
right. Um yeah, I mean a lot of what
these projects end up being is uh
chained funding. You kind of like hope
to get the next grant and you hope to
move to the next grant. But I mean at a
certain point maybe with enough um sort
of structure and participation we could
figure out like a a longer term strategy
um and actually work on a longer term
plan and then seek a like slightly more
stable funding. Um so I like that idea
but it's it's in information. I would
say it's a it's an emerging think tank.
Hi um I'm very appreciate to hear this
kind of like you know information about
like sharing the community model and
families model and also um help with the
data in uh inframe structure. Um the
questions like actually um some of us
are actually not student or like you
know researchers but we are MIT staff
and also using also utilize AI and also
building pipelines. So um my my
colleague and I we we are very
interested to join and also witness and
also I know like MIT is having new ERP
system yeah in implementing in you know
in the following like five to 10 years
and um I'm looking forward to see if um
anything we can um work together if
possible. Yeah, you're welcome. Yeah,
please join us. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. We we
already have um several folks who are
not uh inside academia as like
professors or students. So there are
already folks who are practitioners who
have joined. Yeah. That would be
wonderful. Thanks. Great.
Okay. Let's thank Nico and Katherine
again. Thank you.