Well, today we're going to talk about
volatility modeling. And this uh topic
in finance is one that um it has really
interested me for decades. Um and there
are a lot of subtle details involved
with understanding volatility, how to
measure it, how to forecast it. And
we've had some uh talks already with the
group u projects about uh dealing with
volatility estimation and uh measuring
volatility in particular implied
volatility. Uh today we'll focus more on
uh realized volatility and modeling
that. And so to begin um here's just an
overview of different ways one might
define volatility. And it's basic
definition is the annualized standard
deviation of the change in price or
value of a financial security. And of
course this this concept is really
important for measuring risk and
evaluating the uh value of options on
underlying assets. Yep.
>> What's it mean by randomized?
>> Um what that means? Okay. Suppose
suppose we have a sigma day that's equal
to um say 0.01
percent. So 1% variability per day. If
we wanted to measure volatility on an
annualized scale, then we could
consider
possibly the square root of 252 times
sigma day.
So it's a matter of scaling the
volatility up to an annual horizon.
And the value of that rescaling is that
we can talk about volatilities over
different maturities and they're
measured on the same scale. Um and uh
with different estimation uh approaches.
There's historical sample volatility
measures which um don't require really
any probability models with them. Then
we have geometric brownie in motion.
That's a very familiar model to everyone
here. Um and we can consider extensions
of that to the pson jump diffusion
model. A group delivered a nice lecture
on lecture note on the pson jump
diffusions. And then following these
cases are cases where volatility
might have some time dynamics in them.
Um with these uh geometric brownian
motion and pan jump diffusion models, we
think of volatility being some constant
which is the same from one period to the
next. But it turns out that there can be
time dependence in volatility. And so
there are ARCH and GARCH models which
stand for auto reggressive conditional
heteroscadastic models. And then the
GARCH are generalized versions of those.
And then there are stochcastic
volatility models as well. Um I know uh
let's see the H uh option pricing model
uses a stochcastic volatility uh term in
its in its formulation. So uh we have
those kinds of extensions and then
finally there's implied volatility from
options and derivatives.
So let's just look at computing
volatility from an historical series of
actual prices.
Um if we have prices PT then we can
define the log returns by looking at the
ratio of price prices from one day to
the next or one period to the next and
taking the logarithm of that. Um this is
a useful way of measuring returns as an
alternative to simply the percentage
change in value using the log scale or
the log return. If we look at the
cumulative change over successive
periods with log returns they just add.
um whereas if we were using percentage
returns we'd have to uh basically
multiply factors together representing
that. Now um in modeling volatility uh
we consider models that correspond to
stationary processes for our returns. So
the log returns of price series are
often uh consistent w via tests with a
stationary distribution of returns and
under the assumption of covariant
stationerity we can define uh sigma to
be the variance of or the standard
deviation of of those returns. Now in
this notation here, this sigma for the
volatility would be corresponding to a
frequency of observation that's daily or
weekly or monthly.
And we'd have sample estimates given by
the square root of the
uh sample variance where we
traditionally use the estimator for
variance which is an unbiased estimate
of the variance. So that factor divisor
two t minus one is included there. And
then if we want to annualize these
values, it's
common practice just to treat these
returns
as independent
or uncorrelated over time. So that the
variance of a sum is the sum of the
variances.
So there are roughly 252
days in a year. So we multiply by the
square of 252
for daily uh returns. For weekly returns
we do the roo 52 time sigma hat and
roo2 for monthly.
Now um
when
measuring uh historical volatility
um we can think of a simple historical
average sort of since the beginning of
our time series. Um so this historical
average would use all available data.
It's reasonable to think that volatility
isn't necessarily stable over the entire
time range of a price series. And so we
could consider just using the last m
values. So take a rolling average of the
last m uh
values of this sigma hat^ 2 t minus j.
Now um if we uh define sigma hat squared
t to just be a single day volatility
that could be like the
square of the daily return on a given
day. Now using equal weighted values
over a window of length m
might be improved upon by using an
exponential moving average.
And so exponential moving averages are
averages where we take a weighted
average of
the previous estimate of volatility
and the current
estimate of volatility using the time
the time t value. So this one minus beta
beta weight allows us to uh weight the
past versus the present um in an
exponential way. And with this formula
it's recursive over t and so it can
actually apply across an entire range of
historical data. um an alternative to
just the regular exponential moving
averages and exponential weighted moving
average where we only go back maybe m
periods but we decrease the weights on
past volatility estimates um according
to the power of beta j. So beta j is uh
or beta is sort of a decay factor in
estimating volatilities.
The uh
so okay additionally one could consider
uh regression models with these
volatility uh sigma hats indexed by t.
Um and
depending on uh the relationship of
volatility to the past, you know, we
might you want use more data to increase
precision of estimators, but use data
closer to time t when we believe that
the volatility may be changing over
time. And what's neat about these uh
estimation methods is that we can
evaluate say the exponential moving
average estimates of volatility over
different assets and different asset
classes.
And uh this
approach was applied in risk metrics. Um
here there's a web link to the risk
metrics technical document. I think I
have it listed here. Um
so actually this uh riskmetrics was um
created by JP Morgan back in the 1990s.
Coincidentally, when I was at the Sloan
School teaching statistics and financial
modeling, I was part of the financial
services research center that was
sponsored by uh JP Morgan and other
groups when this risk metrics document
was um was created. And if we look at um
let's see there's a section here of risk
metrics
um decay factors for volatility.
Basically for different countries,
one can use the exponential moving
average of
uh asset returns for foreign exchange
uh 10year zero prices, equity indices
and other assets. And what's interesting
to see is that the decay factor is
generally well above 0.9. It's more like
0 n5 which suggests that volatility is
changing slowly over time. And the way
they chose these decay factors was to
look at how predictive they were with
mean squared error of volatility. So
these are reasonable uh estimates of
volatility and an important aspect of
these measures
is having benchmark values that people
can agree upon. So it we're not arguing
that these are the best estimators, but
they're a simple objective estimator
that can be applied. And when we
communicate about these other people
understand what we're measuring. So
those are important. Now um
let's see with geometric brownie in
motion turning now to having a
stochcastic process model for the
prices. Um if we have this stochastic
differential equation the geometric
brownie motion one um we see that and
it's totally obvious but if we divide
both sides by s of t we get mud dt plus
um sigma d s of t or d sigma dw of t
where w of t is a uh standard brownie in
motion. So by looking at essentially the
percentage change on an infiniteesmal
level u we basically have a linear trend
that's deterministic and then a random
walk with brownie in motion steps on
that scale.
And with this geometric brownie in
motion, we have um basically independent
increments
with normally distributed increments on
this uh log scale for the brownie
motion.
And with our uh homework exercise this
past week, we actually dealt with um
estimating the drift parameter and the
volatility parameter in geometric
brownie and motion. And so if our
increments of time are unit increments,
then we can estimate a drift term mu
star with the average log return. And we
can estimate the
period volatility or period variance uh
with the the sample variance using n
instead of n minus one. Um now these
essentially are correspond to maximum
likelihood estimates of these parameters
and uh what's important to note here is
that um the
drift term mu star per period
um is actually equal to the mu of the
geometric brownian motion minus the
square of the volatility term divided by
two. And so what's important is that
when we apply this
stochastic differential equation um
there basically comes a an extra term in
the drift that's due to the squared
variation in the process.
So um in working with these stochastic
differential equations, it's important
not to just look at first order terms
but to look at second order terms in
your tailaylor series approximation. And
that's how that mu star gets gets in
there to be different from mu. Now um an
interesting
uh exercise which hopefully was of
interest to people who worked on that
last week. Um if we vary the increments
delta J over which we observe this price
process then
we can talk about how accurate or how
precise are our estimates of mu
star and sigma squared.
And it turns out that
if the delta j the increments between
observations varies then our estimate of
mu star is always the same. It
corresponds to just the cumulative
return over the entire period divided by
the length of the period. So it's the
average rate of return per period.
Interestingly,
if we increase the number of increments,
then our precision on the variance gets
more and more precise
and uh the variability of that actually
goes down uh with a factor of n. So that
was a homework exercise that I think is
is an important one uh to realize.
Now,
a really interesting extension of sort
of maximum likelihood estimation with
normally distributed increments coming
from the Brownian motion process is
looking at
the problem of using more information
than just the close to close prices. And
so what we want to do is introduce you
to the Garmin class estimator.
And let me just turn to
the Garmin class paper. Um these papers
are distributed in canvas in the
volatility notes section. But um if we
think of a period of time with one day
going from yesterday's close to today's
open to today's close.
Then
in thinking about
measuring volatility using the
difference between today's close and
yesterday's close.
That can be very useful.
But it's missing out on other
information that we may have access to,
such as what's the opening price
today, what's the low value today,
what's the high value today, and how can
we use that extra information to have
more precise estimates of volatility. Um
anecdotally, uh when I was studying for
a doctorate in statistics at Berkeley,
um I was a research assistant to Michael
class
and I was getting interested in
non-statistics topics like finance and
so I took a course from Mark Garmin who
co-wrote this co-wrote this paper. So
it's a rather interesting uh to have
that had that exposure actually. It was
a very inspiring set of uh classes that
I took which uh motivated my I guess
lifelong interest in financial modeling.
So let's take a look at some notation.
very simply will think of just a single
period like one day and refer to the
closing price on day J, opening price on
day J, the high and low on day J as
well.
Importantly, the notation here includes
this well includes the time points, but
it also includes the
parameter f which is uh the period the
length of time that the market is closed
on a given day. So the time between the
close and open of the next day.
Um so we have this notation
and if we
consider just focusing on single periods
and in this case the first one um if we
look at the change in closing values.
Now perhaps it makes sense to think of
these on the log scale of the prices. Um
the uh close to close squared return
um
basically will have uh mean sigma
squared and variance equal to 2 sigma to
the 4th. Now this corresponds to the
theory of normal random variables for
returns which are comes from the brownie
in motion and the uh expected squared
value
uh is well actually we can think of
maybe the mean return being zero or
being subtracted from all the returns.
Um but the variance of this sigma knot
hat squared is the variance of a ki
squared random variable with one degree
of freedom. And so in probability
classes we learned that a kai squared
random variable has expectation equal to
the degrees of freedom. And if it's a
scaled kai squared it's the the scale
factor sigma squ times that. And the
variance of a kai squared is equal to
twice the degrees of freedom. So that's
where that formula comes from.
Now if we look at the closed to open
squared return, the same arguments lead
to this sigma 1 hat squared. looking at
the squared return from close to open
uh normalized by the length of the
period
between the close and open. Um this will
also have expectation equal to sigma
squared and its variance will also be 2
sigma to the 4th.
So if the model applies
throughout u the time periods you know
of the market being open as well as the
market being closed then these formulas
u apply. Now we could also do the open
to close squared return
and again get if we normalize the
squared change in
price or log price uh if we normalize
that by the length of the period 1 minus
f then we get the same
properties of the moments for these
estimates of sigma squ. So all of these
have estimate or have expectation equal
to sigma squar and all of them have the
same degree of variation.
Well
the
second and the indexed one and two cases
are estimates that use different
time periods different increments
disjoint increments of the process.
And so these have to be independent if
our Brownian motion model um applies.
And so if we simply take the weighted
average of these or the simple average
then
the expectation is unchanged and the
variance
is equal to basically a half squared
times the sum of the variances and that
equals actually sigma to the 4th. So
we're able to get a more precise
estimate of the volatility using these
two increments separately.
And so it's common in uh statistical
theory of estimators to talk about the
efficiency of one estimator versus
another. And so if we compare um this
sigma star
we can divide its variance into the
variance of sigma kn squared and get a
factor of two. So um we basically have
uh
let's see have I got that correct
right we basically have have twice the
efficiency. um in this case. So we're
sort of thinking of inverse
relationships of the variance. Now um
let's see Parkinson uh came up with uh
considering the high and low values over
a period and showed that this estimate
sigma hat 3 squared um is an unbiased
estimate of sigma squared
when f is equal to zero.
and has efficiency equal to 5.2.
So this
high and low data really has a lot of
information in it compared with just the
close to close returns.
we our precision with estimating sigma
squared basically can increase by a
factor of five with using the high and
low values instead of the close to
close.
Um
and uh let's see. I just posted today
the problem set due next week. Um where
there's an article by Parkinson
discussing issues of high and low um or
high or extreme value estimates of the
variance um which I think it'll be
interesting to read. I think it's
somewhat fun to read the sort of classic
papers in these areas especially because
what the older they are the easier they
are to read I think although sometimes
that's not totally true. Anyway, what
Garmin and class did was um they
considered alternatives
which included the high low uh
volatility estimate
and a simple average or weighted by a uh
and one minus a of this high low
estimate of Parkinson and the sigma one
which is the uh
let's see let's go back and the sigma
one which is the open open to close um
value um this has an even higher
efficiency of 6.2 two
and a rather striking result of their
paper is they were able to derive the
best analytic scale invariant estimator.
So depending on whether you like
mathematics or not, you may like this
paper or not. But it's really
interesting to see how
a property of finding a scale invariant
estimator
that is best
among the class of such estimators. Um
that's actually derived by Garmin and
class. So let me just uh sort of
highlight
how this section five in their paper
talks about best analytic scale and
variant estimators. And you may be able
to see from the derivation here that
their arguments just are dealing with
some quadratic forms and solving for
properties minimizing these quadratic
forms. And so it's it's rather neat that
they're able to uh achieve this result.
Yeah.
>> Why is it necessary?
Because that's just commenting about the
comparative, right?
>> Right. Well, well, with a higher
efficient
uh estimator,
you can have as precise an estimator
with a smaller or shorter time series.
So instead of using say 20 days close to
close,
you could use a week
of data and have estimators that are
comparably precise.
extra assumptions that complicate
things. And in many of these
developments, there there are
simplifying assumptions like um the mean
is zero. But um but if you were trying
to model time varying volatility,
then rather than looking at say close to
close volatility and how that changes
over time, if you use these other
estimators, um the garment class for
example, um you could maybe use a much
shorter time period and be able to track
or model changes in volatility over time
with that.
Okay.
Well, let's see. Um,
so then finally, there's this composite
estimator which uh has efficiency 8.4.
Um, and finally, there are a number of
extensions of the Garmin class that are
listed here. And um the one that is
actually recommended these days is
actually this Yang Jiang uh model which
has a drift independent volatility
estimation based on the high low close.
So the fact that it's drift independent
deals with that assumption that was just
just mentioned. Now um let's see there's
a case study uh of using R to calculate
these different volatility estimates
and uh let's see here.
So here's the uh
case study which um goes through
calculating different measures of
volatility using close to close
Parkinson's all the way down to Yang and
Jang in section 1.6 six and then
comparing those for the S&P 500 index
and
we'll go through these in a moment but
following just looking at these
individually
um we consider time series modeling of
these different volatility statistics.
Um and so in terms of understanding
realized volatility,
a useful um analysis is to be able to
predict how our realized volatility is
going to change into the future. Um so
there may be some predictability there
and what we'll see is that in the time
series analysis of these volatilities
uh time series models such as auto
reggressive integrated moving average
models can be applied and can be very
useful and in particular um there's a
role to be played with seasonal ARMA
models.
So um let's take a look at that. Um
and just as a preview um let's see one
of the problems in uh the next problem
set is to look at this same
analys set of analyses for the S&P 500.
look at the same analyses for uh the
stock ARK
which is Kathy Wood's ETF
and uh just see how different the
results are. Um and uh what's nice is
that the R markdown files that create
this case study can be applied to any
other stocks you want to analyze if you
so choose. Uh for the problem set, I
posted the two versions of this study
for S&P 500 and ARK.
So you don't need to do R at all. But if
you
set up a posit
cloud account for with our studio cloud,
you should be able to just upload the
file, the R markdown file, and rerun the
programs and do so with another stock if
you want. So choose. So so in this note,
the first section just goes through and
looks at the S&P 500 index. It actually
is going through
a couple of days ago. Um it's a good
time to be have an equity exposure. Um
and if we look at close to close
volatility,
um this is a graph of the 21-day
variance scaled up to an annualized
basis by multiplying by root 252.
And what's important
is to see that volatility generally is
well below 25%.
Often it's sort of around like 12 to 15%
when it's low. Uh but it does have
spikes and uh during COVID there was the
huge spike up. Um and uh more recently
there was uh some elevated volatility
uh that uh suggests that volatility is
not constant. Um so anyway this is the
close to close volatility. If we look at
the high low volatility of Parkinson
then we just are averaging the log of
the ratio of the high to low and scaling
it up and so we get this plot which is
very very similar. Um, in principle,
this
estimator is more precise, at least if
if our underlying sort of brownie
emotion model or geometric brownie
emotion model is is true. Um, but it
gives us different values
and then the Garmin class
model is here. So what's what's useful
just in this case study is partly just
seeing what the formulas are for the
volatility estimates
and then being able to compare those and
then finally this uh Yang Jiang model is
a extension of Garmin class and as it
says here this is currently the
preferred version
uh of volatility estimates. Now in
looking at these different volatility
estimates
um
we can uh
create a panel series of all the
volatility measures. This sort of shows
not surprisingly there's peaks at the
same times with all of these. Um what's
more interesting is to look how they
move simultaneously.
And if you look at too much data, it's
hard to see exactly what's going on. So
there's a graph here of looking at just
uh the last year, almost two years of
data and seeing how these different
volatility estimates vary. So
what this highlights is how a choice of
volatility measure matters.
there can be significant differences
between them. And
what would you anticipate is
sort of a good property of a volatility
estimator?
That's a very general question,
but um
intuitively what would make one
estimator better than another?
And there's no right or wrong answer to
this,
but I think it's useful to think about
what you would like to have in an
estimator and whether these estimators
might be consistent with that or not.
any any thoughts?
Well, one of the problems,
I guess I'll call it a problem, uh, with
the close to close estimate is that if
you have a rolling window of close to
close variance estimates, then if you
have a spike in returns, positive or
negative, that spike is going to remain
in that window until it falls off. And
so there can be elevated volatilities
due to from in the close to close series
um volatility series that may uh not be
as persistent
with the other estimators. So when there
are spikes in volatility, often that
those spikes occur when there's some
great uncertainty in the market that
gets
resolved
and the volatility often drops
a fair amount after that. And so, um, I
would think that those volatility
estimates that basically drop faster
following the spikes could be better.
Um, and uh, certainly if we're trying to
use these volatility estimates
to predict future realized volatility,
that property could be useful.
Um now what's
interesting in section two of this case
study is to just consider some really
really basic time series modeling of the
different volatility measures. So the so
what we are modeling is different
volatility measures over a 21-day period
that's rolling through our time series.
And so one of the most basic forecasting
models there is is a model called the
naive model.
And with a naive model,
we have a time series yt
and we basically have that um
y t is equal to yt minus one.
And if we think of yt is equal to y t
plus an error term then our errors are
equal to yt minus yhat
t
which is equal to yt minus yt minus one.
And this specification corresponds to a
random walk model. So there's basically
a random walk model for YT
and the random walk model is consistent
with sort of efficient markets where our
best estimate of what's going to happen
is what's h where things are now. So um
so this naive model uh basically has an
autocorrelation function which has a
very high
or the our data uh has a high first
order autocorrelation. And if we
calculate first differences which are
the residuals from this model then we
get this
residual
diagnostic information the time series
of residuals
um the autocorrelation function of the
residuals and the
histogram of residuals. Now,
would you say that these residuals are
consistent with white noise
that may be Gaussian or normal?
I see some going and others going
um well one thing that's important is
that the autocorrelation function
of residuals
um if the residuals are consistent with
white noise there should be no
significant autocorrelation at any lag
and so there are some spikes of
autocorrelation that break beyond the
critical levels
And so those are suggesting that this is
not a white noise. And if we look at the
distribution of the residuals,
they're unimodal, but they certainly
aren't well described by a normal
distribution.
Um
so
let's see the uh so we can sort of plot
forecasts of this uh naive method
and then um
let's see we can also
fit an ARMA model to this close to close
volatility series
and with the ARMA model. Um actually
there's this package in R
called um FPPP2
and this
was created by the authors of a book
forecasting principles and practice
that's in the references to this. They
have an automated ARMA modeling function
which will take an input a time series
as output what is judged to be a decent
auto regressive integrative moving
average model. And so this
ARMA 310
um corresponds to
ARMA P = 3, D = 1
and Q = Z where P is the order of the
auto regression, D is the order of
differencing. Yes. How is it random? Is
it um like AIC or BIC or something?
>> Yes, it it uses um a criterion that's
called the corrected
AI information criterion.
And so there's this AIC which is equal
to the corrected
AIC. And the corrected AIC is due to the
fact that with shorter series there's a
bias in the AIC that is systematic and
so this corrects for that bias. Um now
when we do this um with any sort of
fitted model what's really
important to check is how our estimated
coefficients compare with their standard
errors.
When the signal estimate to noise
standard error ratio is bigger than two.
We have some confidence that that's an
important factor in the in the model.
And in this case, the AR3 is almost
three
uh has a signal to noise ratio of almost
three and the AR2 has a ratio that's one
and a half. Now um if we go through
let's see this second section sort of
does the same analysis of the the Yang
Xang volatility estimate.
And
I guess importantly here um
we have
an ARMA model now uh for this
Yang Jiang model which is an ARMA 111
and
the coefficient estimates are many
multiples of the standard error. So
these are highly significant.
And this um is our residual analysis
check which suggests that for the most
part the residuals are consistent with
white noise. The autocorrelations tend
to be close to zero. However, there's
this large spike
at 21. And here are the residuals. Now,
why do you think there's a large spike
at 21?
Well, we're computing rolling
statistics
and so the window
is of length 21. So this corresponds to
cases
entering and exiting the windows. And so
interestingly we can accommodate that by
fitting a seasonal arma model. And so
with the seasonal ARMA model, I'll sort
of jump to the uh conclusion here at the
very end which is um
for the Yang Jiang
volatility estimator. Um this is its
simple autocorrelation function before
the model. And then when we
fit the seasonal ARMA model
automatically, it gives us a 213 and a
2011.
And
let's see when we introduced you to time
series models before
um
let's see if we have
an ARMA
model
which is P DQ
um we basically have 1 minus V1 V - V2 B
^ 2 minus V P B to the P power
time YT
turns out to be equal to 1 minus
theta 1 B
minus theta 2 B^ 2
minus theta or sorry 1 plus here plus
theta Q B
to the Q power
times
our error term. So we have this kind of
mathematical equation for an ARMA model
um where we assume that the epsilon t
series is white noise
which means that it's expectation is
always zero and the uh variances are
constant
and the correlation between any
different epsilons
is equal to zero if t is not equal to t
prime. Um the power of auto reggressive
integrated moving average models is that
these sort of auto reggressive terms as
well as moving average terms can account
for all of the correlations
autocorrelations in the original series.
and our residuals which are estimates of
this error sequence should be consistent
with white noise. Now what ends up
happening with um
with uh
actually I should maybe put here yt
prime where yt prime is maybe equal to 1
minus b to the power d yt.
So if we have an ordered D
model, we take the deth order difference
and put that into an ARMA model.
And if we have a seasonal ARMA model,
we actually add a capital P, capital Q,
capital D, capital Q.
And here we have sort of the frequency
of the data. And in this example I
considered a 21 period frequency just to
correspond to um the window size.
And
what this model does is it sort of has
another polomial
of
So this is B to the 2 * 21.
So we basically end up having um
backshift
operator polomials
that work with the
seasonal frequencies
of the time series.
And so um
so uh okay so this is a a polomial of
order Q of order P in B to the 12th
sorry B to the 21
and then we would also multiply this on
this side perhaps
by a one minus
capital theta 1 B 21 or plus theta 2 B
to the 21^ 2
so times 2
and
so so this kind of notation leads us to
these coefficient estimates. So there's
this sort of simple order auto
reggressive terms and moving average
terms.
Order two auto reggressive order three
moving average. But then for the
seasonal auto reggressive terms we have
these terms here. And for the seasonal
moving average we have uh the last term
here. And what's generally important in
fitting models is when you consider the
last terms to enter into a model such as
in this case the seasonal moving average
term it is its estimate is many
multiples of its standard error. So
that's a a very important factor in the
model. Um and
let's see just
as
uh let's see
as an anecdote um
let me just say uh
let's see if we take a series yt
and we look at a seasonal difference
operator and a first order difference
operator.
Um
this turns out to be equal to the first
difference operator multiplying the
seasonal difference operator
and it equals basically 1 - b + b to the
uh sorry minus b 21 + b 22
times yt. And so with seasonal
differences
in
auto reggressive moving averages
whether we take first differences
nonseasonally and then seasonal
differences
subsequently or reverse the order we end
up getting the same transformation of
the data. And so um what's well actually
with economic time series where we have
a seasonal frequency of say months then
the uh
basically the seasonal differences
correspond to year-over-year changes
whereas the simple uh differences um are
just uh period by period differences.
Anyway, with this final uh example here,
this is sort of how the
residual analysis looks. And it actually
um does yield residuals that do look a
lot like white noise, although there is
still this sort of persistent spike
just beyond the sort of window width for
the computation. But the uh distribution
of the residuals looks more Gaussian
perhaps than well much more than than
the cases before.
So um with that um
let's see in in analyzing different time
series models there are these accuracy
statistics that can be computed for any
forecasting model. And so you're
probably familiar with root mean squared
error or mean squared error. Um but we
also have the map which is the mean
absolute percent error. And I actually
find that pretty useful uh for judging
uh how effective the models are. And
what's really nice about the uh FPPP2
package is that one can just ask it to
plot the time series and the forecast
and it generates a point forecast in a
solid blue line and prediction intervals
about that forecast which assume
Gaussian or normal distributions for the
error terms. But one can see how those
evolve into the future. And it's really
consistent for
prediction intervals to get wider the
further out we forecast. And that's
happening here. What's rather
interesting about this forecast
um using the Yang Jang
uh measure and forecasting that into the
future is that it actually after being
at a lower level is predicting that it
might go back to more of a mean level of
volatility.
So that's that's an interesting
property.
Okay.
Well, let's go back to
the notes here
and um
let's see. There are extensions of uh
geometric brownie in motion that we
have uh seen before. One of them is a
pluson jump diffusion model. Um where
the stochastic differential equation has
the brownie in motion part as the first
two terms but then has a jump process as
a last term where the jump process can
be modeled as
a plus process. So a jump occurs
at some rate that is that defines the
plus process and the rate is lambda and
if
an event in the plus process occurs then
there's a jump in the uh stock uh which
is given by this
factor here. So um one can actually
model
uh data with this plus jump diffusion
model and um let's see I I ended up
working with uh David Pickard and Arshad
Zacharia on fitting this diffusion model
and it was an interesting um uh
application in statistics of using the
EM M algorithm. Um
basically the jumps are treated as
latent or hidden values in our data and
those hidden values
occur according to plus probabilities
like the probability of one jump or two
jumps can be computed using the plus
parameter and one can apply this EM
algorithm to obtain maximum likelihood
estimates of all the parameters. And um
in applying this an interesting property
that uh occurred was that um there were
quite frequent
there that or the rate of uh plus events
was quite high like every couple of
days.
And um what the model was doing was
capturing
heavier tailed distributions than a
normal distribution. So instead of a
single
normal model for the return, one has a
mixture of a normal with no jumps, a
normal with one jump, two jumps,
weighted according to plus song rates.
And so the implication of the model
fitting was that one didn't have sort of
rare events necessarily that occurred uh
but one had uh
or there was evidence suggesting sort of
uh a jump process that related to um
trying to capture the excess variability
of the stock price returns. Now that
leads to
um another model extending Brownian
motion and this is the lelass
distribution where if instead of
observing a time series over equal
increments.
So between zero
you know one can think of just equal
increments of time.
So t1, t2 and so forth up to tn say from
time z to capital t. Um, it may be that
we observe
the Brownian motion process at random
times. T1 and then here's T2,
here's T3,
where
the increments of time themselves are
also random. And it turns out that
if the times at which we observe
have
sort of a time
increment that's exponentially
distributed
then the increments of the brownian
motion follow a lelass distribution.
So heavier tail distributions
than normal and this is the density of a
lelass
distribution. It's
depends on the exponential of minus the
magnitude
of the deviation of x from mu as opposed
to the square of that deviation. A
Gaussian or normal distribution would
have a power two there. With the lelass
distribution, it's the absolute. And
with this distribution, we have a mean
mu which is sort of at the center of the
distribution. The variance turns out to
depend on this scale factor B um which
is twice B^2.
So um
So let's just take a look at what lelass
models look like. They basically are
bilateral exponential distributions.
And if we consider fitting the uh daily
returns on the S&P 500, this is data for
I know four-year period.
um this sort of peaked distribution with
exponentially dis decaying density is
fitting the data really quite well and
more importantly much better really than
a Gaussian curve does. So here we have
the fit of the Gaussian
bell curve in red comparing it to the
lelass curve in blue.
And an interesting question is how do we
judge whether uh one model or another is
a good model? And a useful tool
is
to construct a QQ plot
which is a quantile quantile plot.
So we consider points where the vertical
value corresponds to the magnitude of
our data
and the horizontal
coordinate corresponds to the
theoretical value
for
the smallest from a sample of lelass,
the second smallest from a given lelass
distribution. And so um we basically
plot sort of observed quantiles versus
theoretical quantiles for the fitted
model. So this fits quite close to a
line although it's not perfect. At least
if it were perfect it would even sort of
snake around the straight line where uh
the sample quantiles equal the
theoretical quantiles. If we do the same
QQQ plot for a Gaussian or normal model,
this is what our QQQ plot looks like.
And so one can see that this second QQ
plot is not fitting the data very well
at all.
So um this would favor uh using the
lelass instead of the Gaussian
with as a model for independent daily
returns.
Now the independence of or period by
period returns is one that may not be
satisfied by the data. And uh Robert
Engel um proposed looking at time series
um of returns
and considering the possibility that the
variability of these returns given by
the variability of the epsilon t terms
that these in fact
have time varying volatilities sigma t
where
the sigma t squared
evolves according to a sort of moving
average of past squared errors. So an
auto reggressive conditionally
heteroscadastic
model is what he proposed.
And um in looking at this model
um it's interesting to note that if one
normal or one can sort of reexpress the
arch model in terms of this
squared error term
and have this model uh in the second
equation being consistent with the
first. And this second model corresponds
to
there being an auto reggressive model
consistent with the squared returns. And
so this lrangege multiplier test can fit
the auto reggressive model to these
epsilon hat squares and test whether
there is auto reggressive structure or
not. And if we look at the
autocorrelations of the S&P 500 returns
squared,
you can see that the first
almost 10 autocorrelations
are significantly different from zero in
magnitude. So there is strong time
dependence in the log returns.
And so um how does one sort of fit this
model? Well,
the go-to typically in statist in
statistical modeling is to consider a
likelihood approach where we consider a
density for our data
uh specified by the model. So if the
errors epsilon t are uh independent
gaussian distributions with different
variances
then uh this likelihood function defines
um the uh joint density of our data
given underlying parameters. And what's
becomes tricky with this likelihood
specification is that there in fact are
constraints on our parameters. So with
the arch model we can't have a negative
alpha
because with the Gaussian squared
epsilon that could be arbitrarily large
negative
or epsilon could be sorry I sorry if the
alphas were negative then the epsilon
squares could be arbitrarily large
positive we get a negative variance so
we can't have that also we have this
property of the sum of the auto
reggressive parameters is less than one
and this corresponds to the process not
being explosive in its in its movements.
Um and then uh let's see an extension of
the arch models was
done by Bowlers Lev and this basically
adds to our arch model terms like an
order P arch model. It adds an order Q
set of terms on lags of the volatility.
And if we consider the special case of
the garch1 model, this is its form
which is very simple and parsimmonious.
What's rather surprising
is that the empirical specification of
these models is um such that the garch1
model is often chosen or identified as
the best garch order case. So we end up
having a very simple model with just a
few parameters to characterize the the
volatility
and um
let's see okay these notes talk about
how the GACH model induces an ARMA
model. So this is some time series
results that are gone through here and
there's a long run variance
of the Garch model um that uh is given
here and with a GACH one model
there basically is a sort of long run
uh volatility sigma star
uh which has this particular formula
and one uh basically can
okay so one can find the long run
variance of a garch model with this
formula there this formula also leads to
sort of updates of volatility being a
multiple of the long run variance plus a
deviation from that long run variance
and So um
all right so we have a maximum
likelihood estimation for these models.
Now I wanted to
share with you let's see a case study
using arch and garch models with foreign
exchange returns.
And so this note uses data collected
from the Federal Reserve on foreign
exchange uh values. Um section 1.2
actually fits Brownie in motion using
different time scales. So not assuming
time dependence. It actually is sort of
interesting
to
think about different time scales. Um
but um if we go to section 1.3
1.3
and look at time dependence and squared
returns this is uh uh the dollar pound u
returns.
Um this shows the autocorrelation and
partial autocorrelation
of the returns.
So there are sort of strong partial
oiler correlations
um of the actual series and if we look
at the squared returns
um the actual series um has high
autocorrelations over time but the
partial autocorrelations have very high
spikes at low lag. So this suggests sort
of an auto reggressive model in the
squared returns
and the note fits an arch one an arch
two. So one lag or sorry one auto
reggressive
uh term two auto reggressive terms or 10
and then fits the GARCH one
and the results
are highlighted here just showing you
the different coefficient estimates for
these different models. They're all
statistically significant in terms of
the parameters. What's of interest
though is just to look at the time
series plot of the fitted volatilities
using arch of different orders. So
here's the arch one model.
Here's the arch 2 model.
A property of this these arch models is
that you know it never goes below zero.
There's sort of a lower bound. Here's
the arch 10 model which looks like it's
maybe tracking time varying volatility
well. And then finally we can compare
that with the GARCH one model.
So instead of having 10 auto reggressive
parameters in arch the generalized arch
model is capturing time varying
volatility in an appealing way. You know
whether that's really valid or not is is
of interest. Um but it certainly is an
alternative to these arch models that
that is quite powerful. Um and in the uh
well here's just a graph of all three
together.
Um this this note actually does a final
section of looking at what happens if
our error distribution
is not Gaussian
but is a t distribution.
the code there are packages ruarchch
which allow us to specify
parameters and fits using t models t
distribution models for the errors and
what's very curious is
in judging the uh
uh in judging the uh histogram of
standardized residuals
Um, the t distribution seems to do a
decent job.
And
so here's with Gaussian residuals, I
guess.
And then here's the uh Gaussian garch
residuals
and QQ plot associated with uh the
standardized Gaussian assumption.
Then finally um there's the QQQ plot of
standardized residuals with a t
distribution assumed. So what's
significant is just how the quantile
quantile plot suggests that this model
is really fitting the data much much
better in terms of characterizing the
variation and the choice of which order
model to use
for um
let's see for the uh degrees of freedom
there's this um negative log likelihood
function of models for different t
distributions as we vary the degrees of
freedom for the t and a t distribution
has a heavier tail than a Gaussian
distribution
at least if the degrees of freedom is
really high it's virtually equivalent to
a Gaussian but this is suggesting that
there's uh possibly a nine degrees of
freedom for that so that's a very
interesting finding And it actually
arises with some mathematical analysis
that sort of t distributions
are
appropriate
if we think of spherical symmetry
in the number of dimensions equal to the
degree of freedom.
And so if you imagine sort of a joint
distribution
that is spherically symmetric in really
high dimensions when you project that
down onto coordinate axes you end up
getting a Gaussian distribution.
But if the symmetry is just of say nine
dimensions
then you end up having a t distribution
for what those projections are. So, so
this suggests that
in terms of um time periods over which
um the distribution of volatility sort
of is is stable, you know, could be
close to sort of nine dimensions. Um so
perhaps corresponding to nine periods of
data, I believe. All right. Well, we'll
finish there. There's a lot of
interesting material for you to check
out. if you like. Um, and uh, I hope you
can enjoy reading some of the articles
of people who have studied volatility
and see what their work has contributed
and uh, it's a really interesting area
for uh, uh, final papers um, you know,
modeling volatility and predicting
volatility. This is really scratching
the surface of the topic. So there's a
lot of interesting problems you could
study. All right. Thanks a lot.