welcome everyone I will go ahead and get
us started uh my name is Terrell
Williams and I serve as the associate
director for diversity equity and
inclusion in the office of admission at
MIT Sloan um I'm excited about t the
opportunity to host tonight's panel uh
we do have a dynamic group of panelist
and a moderator for tonight's session I
want to transition to our moderator for
the evening uh Miss Selena who will be
able to share a little uh a little bit
about little bit about her background
and introduce our panelist for the
evening Selena the floor is yours hi
everyone I'm so glad to have you all
join my name is Selena fan um I am from
Toronto Ontario I'm Canadian I worked as
a Management Consultant at the Boston
Consultant Group and then this past
summer I was in working in the public
sector doing Glendon Finance at the
Canada infrastructure Bank um at Sloan
I'm focused primarily around taking
courses around analytics
entrepreneurship and Innovation and also
within the department of urban studies
um focused on like cities and
infrastructure and at Sloan I guess at
side of school am the co-president of
the Asian-American Alliance I was a or I
am a community building chair so like
the social chair for our Baltic Ocean
which is like a subset of the broader
cohort um the MIT Canada Club prime
minister um and I was also involved with
mit's 100K pitch challenge which is
focused on um funding startups at MIT
and an active member of the wine club um
our panelists are joining us from um a
wide variety of backgrounds so we have
uh Ken I'll let them introduce
themselves but um yeah so why don't uh
is maybe uh I see I don't know if I see
everybody oh I see um so Kenneth do you
want to introduce yourself sure uh hi
everyone my name is Ken can you hear me
we didn't have a chance to check check
check the mic um yeah my name is Ken pan
I'm from Boston I grew up in right
across the river in Brooklyn and my
background before Sloan is that I was
working in the Biotech Industry so I
created a company as a co-founder called
adene which distributes DNA samples for
life scientists and then I was Chief
Operating Officer of a venture back
biotech company for a couple years
before Sloan um and I think we'll get
into some of the reasons of why I chose
Sloan um after that but um currently I'm
working for a wearable tech company um
Selena I don't know how much more
information background you think is
useful now or do you want to keep it
that short for this inro um actually
yeah so why don't we do I guess name
program year I guess career before and
after Sloan um and then maybe like one
high level reason why you chose
Sloan yeah so um I did the the Sloan
fellows MBA program um in graduating in
in 21 I actually did a visiting fellows
session after that for an additional six
months um and we can go into more detail
but the main reason I chose Sloan is
that I wanted to Pivot out of the
biotech tech industry I wanted um um I
was in my M midcareer um wanted to
actually in explore some new technology
fields that were were not life science
um also wanted a break from you know
being in in biotech for a long time for
over 10 years and I wanted to be
immersed in the Sloan community so I I
looked at the EMA program I looked at
Sloan fellows I really wanted to be um
you know resident full-time um at at
Sloan and I hadn't done a NBA before so
I I really was looking for an MBA degree
and I really only applied to Sloan um
because it really matched my needs I
also want to stay in the Boston area
with the tech focus it was um absolutely
perfect for what I was looking for at
the time
awesome thanks kenon um next up can we
have
Ana sure yeah hey everyone so great to
uh I gu see you all virtually um I'm an
Nia originally from San Diego California
I was the master of business analytics
class of 20 to um so about almost two
years now um I'm prior to Sloan I
actually completed my undergrad in
computer science and cognitive science
at UC Berkeley um kind of had decided I
wanted to do more of the computer
science software side of things um and
then decided um you know soon after my
senior year that I actually wanted to
Pivot um and wanted to go back to school
um and get myself more involved in
analytics and data science which is what
brought me to the mband um I'm currently
working at Warner Brothers Discovery as
a senior data scientist um out of New
York City um I think you said one one
reason that I chose Sloan so the mban
program um was very special at least the
time that I was applying and and
actually I think still is um we had the
Capstone which was um a six month or
like about six to nine month duration
project where we get to work handson
with companies doing data science
projects and um it's a really unique
program and unique structure given um a
lot of the stuff you learn you can
actually apply in a real context um and
a lot of the projects that we worked on
you know made it to production um and so
we're able to get kind of an idea of
what it's like to deploy real data
science models um and you know analytics
um in the context of um corporate um
corporate environment as well so it's a
little bit about myself um but yeah
happy to pass it on thanks Ana uh
Katherine hey uh Katherine um NBA
2021 uh was in New York working before
coming to Sloan and now in Boston um so
prior to Sloan um I started my career in
finance so was an investment banker for
a bit and then transition of private
Equity um and then decided I wanted to
go into industry and so went to fizer's
business development team um and kind of
similar to Ken kind of worked in this
biofarma Biotech Industry um decided I
wanted to take some time off um to go to
school I at that point i' been working
for six years so probably on the like
kind of on the cut of what I thought um
of when I wanted to take that break in
my career to go to school um and uh kind
of at that point I sort of knew what I
wanted after Sloan um and so I knew I
wanted to work in the Biotech Industry
um I wanted to be kind of you know in
Boston at the Epic Center of Biotech um
and I wanted a more technical education
given kind of already the finance
business background I wasn't looking for
more Finance related coursework I was
actually looking more towards kind of a
data analy
um drug discovery type classes and so I
sort of narrowed down my search that way
um so came to Sloan and then I actually
like 75% of my education was actually
during covid uh so it was a lot of
online classes and small group
socialization um and then upon
graduating Sloan I joined um a
five-person team building an oncology
startup um and we're currently on our
way to raising series C so I've been
there for the last three years kind of
just helping build out the company um
and so that's been a really rewarding
Journey so you know happy to chat about
kind of big corporate life or small
biotech
life thanks Katherine and then
hu hi everyone uh my name is Hu Kim I'm
an El class of 22 great to see you all
uh be first Alan I was working as an
engineer at Nasa building the mar Rover
that is currently there um currently I
work at a private Equity Firm called
American industrial partner ERS and one
reason why I chose flone was uh at the
time I was trying to further my
engineering education and also learn
more about the management business side
of the world which I had zero exposure
to and there was no place like MIT where
they really coupled that at a high high
degree of um expertise like they did at
MIT specifically the AL program so
that's why I joined being in a Boston
area was also big plus and I DJ my time
there thoroughly even though I was also
Co class and lost most of my time but it
was fantastic so awesome thanks um so I
think one uh question that we want to
talk about is the community at Sloan and
so there's this whole I guess culture of
like sonies helping sonies um I'm
wearing the Asian-American Alliance like
Swig or sweatshirt that we have
available for um like during the school
year so I guess my first question is
around the community at Sloan so could
you describe the community that you had
at Sloan and maybe any areas that you
were in involved in um and maybe we can
start with Catherine because I think you
were also involved in I guess um the
Asian-American Alliance the healthc care
club and swim which is the women in
management club yeah um that's right so
I was also um I think with Ken one of
the co-presidents of the Asian-American
liance so we were we were really afraid
it was going to die during covid so I'm
really really happy that you're keeping
it going um but it was you know I
remember first semester um
before Co shut everything down it was
super fun like we always had um you know
like we had get togethers we had
potlucks uh we had like a big ski trip
um and I think you know I would just
describe the community as just very um I
guess very close-knit and very low ego
which I like which I you know don't
think is necessarily true for every
single business school I think every
business school has their own
personality um and I like that the crowd
that I kind of gravitated to was kind of
you know like nerdy a little bit quirk
really funloving um kind of like you
know really
hardworking um type of people and I
thought you know that was like very
similar to um to myself um you know I
think in terms of um how I continue to
be involved in the community um I would
say from a professional standpoint um
you know you mentioned the healthcare
Club that's been really helpful
throughout my career so actually my
current job that I that I found that I
quite frankly think it's a little bit of
a once a-lifetime career opportunity at
least at this early stage I mean that
was not posted anywhere and I wouldn't
have found that if it weren't for a SL
introducing me to you know Executives
who worked at that company and I I fully
credit the Sloan network with that um
and I think you know even when I was
recruiting um I wasn't going down the
traditional path of you know rotation
program or applying through career um
the career site and so there was a lot
of um you know leveraging the healthc
care Alumni network as well as the club
members
um you know leveraging like people who
were local to Boston people who were
Consultants who like knew every company
there and so um and I I think today I
still do make use of that community so I
I think you know it's been um it's been
really great both from kind of the
social side despite covid um and you
know and also the professional
side awesome that's great to hear and
yes the triple the we call it AAA but
the Asian-American Alliance is Alive and
Well we have many I think we have like
200 people in our groups um the ski trip
is still happening as well and there's
like a very robust pipeline of events
I'd say maybe like two a week if like
two at the minimum a week it's it's kind
of crazy um maybe Kenneth will join will
jump to you since uh just to follow this
kind of like theme on yeah yeah actually
I wanted to add to cat's story I want to
give her credit for keeping triaa alive
during covid she really held the flag um
actually we graduated the same year but
I I mentioned I did a six-month
extension as visiting fellow and that's
when cat actually recruited me she was
like you have to also be one of the
co-presidents through this transition
period um so I very happy to uh to to do
that too as well and it was great to U
see triaa continue um yeah I I was very
involved in the organization both you
know with with CAD when she was
president and then when I helped with
the transition we had a really big
kickoff barbecue which was one of the
most successful um I think of any of the
clubs that that happened that fall we
had like I think over 100 150 people out
um for for a barbecue and was really
wonderful um so I'll Echo what cat said
too as well I think Sloan is extremely
friendly um collaborative place and I I
I would say everyone's really open to be
able to you know just meet like anyone
from any program that's something that I
I wasn't sure going in so I was in the
SL fell program I wasn't sure like how
easy it was to be able to meet slony
from the two-year program from enin from
outside of saloan just in the MIT
Community but MIT overall I think is
really approachable so actually a couple
of my friends that I met are you know
not even yet slan um you know there in
other programs whether CS or engineering
or um actually the IDM program which was
AC Cross School program at the time and
I feel like that of interaction might
not be common at at other schools but I
was really really grateful that to well
on different programs even you know cat
is is a good friend now and she's in the
two-year program where I was in in snba
and um that's something that I really
wanted uh with you know being resident
in um at Sloan versus the the Ember
program where you you kind of go part
time you don't um you don't overlap
programs um so I was really grateful for
that um but yeah I I would say that the
the community is is really strong and
then after graduation too as well I've
been involved in a couple different ways
uh certainly talking to prospective
students and um you know both in in us
but actually quite a bit in Asia i'
actually been spending more time in Asia
because of family reasons and because of
work so I'm actually in um in Japan
right now but living mostly in Taipei
and um so I've got I've talked to a
bunch of prospective students and Alum
here in Asia and then um it I've
actually used the network too so
actually one of my contacts in China
recently was asking for to do sales and
marketing in the US in a very specific
field in list ICS and one of my
classmates in SLO fellas was you know
exactly in that field I made that
connection and they may do a Big
Business Partnership together so very
happy to be able to connect people from
from the Sloan Community particularly
from Asia and us and that's one of my
interests too uh so it's really been um
wonderful I also go back to um SLO
fellows and embas have this opportunity
to go back for Executive Education in
January um for electives during I AP and
I've done that a couple years and found
that extremely rewarding too
I'll pass the mic that sounds great um
and N can I pass it to you about you
know describing your experience at slone
and the Zone community and and um
anything that you were involved in and
how that helped shape your experience
yeah absolutely um I can definitely
speak to the mband program at the time I
think we were around 60 around like yeah
66 65 students so relatively small class
I think compared to the other classes at
um Sloan for a year however our class
was incredibly tight knit I would say
you know the first semester at least in
the man program is quite difficult we
have to take you know I would say in
terms of academic curriculum especially
since a lot of students come from um a
lot of different backgrounds not
necessarily in computer science or
analytics um it's a lot of learning fast
learning quickly learning a lot of
languages um and we all really lean on
each other so whether that is you know
staying up pretty late to finish up
problem sets but then working
collaboratively and then um you know
being able to enjoy our weekends because
we are um you know we're leaning on each
other to be able to finish um you know
finish assignments um you know outside
of just outside of you know just
academics you know even from a
networking perspective um the mband
roots go very deep I know multiple years
prior to mine um the Alumni network just
stays strong whether it's um you know
alumni dinners or keeping going to
Capstone presentations year after year
um everyone stays connected to the mman
program um which is very nice um and
something that we can lean on and
leverage um as time goes on um one of
the one of the great things about Sloan
is my first um role out of um out of uh
the mband was actually a role that I got
through um a professor um through V
farias who um was far more technical
than I can ever be um but took a product
management class with him absolutely
loved it um and you really got to see
kind of the both sides of like the
technical and the non-technical side of
things and you know he was just a great
person to hang out with um and uh talk
about career and just everything in
general and he was actually able to help
pivot me into my first role um outside
of that socially I mean during the year
was probably one of the best years of my
life had an incredible time in Boston um
originally from Cal I'm originally from
California this is my first winter um so
definitely had to lean on a couple of
the East Coasters or the Europeans who
had seen more snow than I had um to get
through that but um it was a lot of fun
and um you know I would say a good
number of them moved down to New York
City with me so I see you know a lot of
our classmates every single day I you
know we talk about different
methodologies that we're using at work
and how we can apply them um you know in
the weekends a lot of my social life is
um you know meeting up with other M
bands from former classes and the
current class as well and and my class
so um the roots go very deep even in the
Alumni network but then also we stay
together socially and academically so
it's a good blend of both um but yeah
I'll pass it off now awesome that's
great to hear um and hu can I pass it to
you about yeah your experience as an and
how that kind of shaped your experience
in terms of the community and the
culture as well yeah of course um first
I'd like to Echo everything that I've
heard it's it's close-knit it's fun it's
it's just collaborative I've experienced
all the same things maybe maybe a couple
things for from my side that especially
with lgo is lgo is I mean slowo is close
nit lgo is even closer nit we're we're
sort of like a group on our own and we
have a joke that we don't make new
friends which is not true we always we
always try to go extent but you spend an
entire summer together with this core of
40 40 to 50 people and they really
become your family and from from my uh
experience where I didn't have um that
much expansion outside my Asian-American
circle of social code eljo was really
the way for me to experience like
friendship with with other culture
International students a mother race it
it was just a very eye opening
experience and one of my closest friends
now it says people I red with as a kid
from Indiana and a Mexican guy from LA
and a Korean from New Jersey it's like a
just uh it's kind of a partnership that
you kind of don't get um my time is
slown I I was able to really utilize the
whole network I want to say so being
part of Elo I also had the access to
meet students not just from Sloan or the
business side of school but but also
within the technical side of MIT so
meeting with the research uh teams
meeting with PhD students that are
working on like really cool uh
experiment I was able to work with them
learn from them
um so that was really enriching in terms
of experience and then just the
collaborative side of things I don't
think I would be here without the
support of my friends and network who
helped me through the whole recruiting
process uh help me interview help me
prepare um just things that I probably
would not even had the I would have know
how to start without without their help
so all that's very very grateful and at
the same time just like a lot of fun and
really extreme people to be to be fair
like Work Hard Play Hard is like a very
true um true uh culture within MIT SL
and like you meet people who always do
things like extreme like hey you like
mountain climbing well I'm like the
world champion in M climbing oh you like
to play piano I like performed at the
Carnegie Hall it's just like you meet
these fantastic people but we're also
really down to it in genuine it's just
something you don't get uh too much
elsewhere um post alone the community
still goes strong my my friend group
still sends a dad joke every Friday so
that's still going um we help each other
recruiting a lot so a lot of cers which
has happened you know immediately or a
couple years after Sloan and because
your network grows even larger to a
network of networks and it just
connections everywhere it's it's really
strong El specifically we also have Al
alumni conference every year which is
extremely fun like this year it's in
Mexico City so you still get to stay in
touch network uh learn about what's Best
in operation technical management all
these things and still have a good time
so uh yeah in many ways I think
lifechanging is probably the only way I
can describe this community and
experience that's awesome to hear um I
kind of want to touch on a point that
you mentioned earlier which was kind of
around the cultural Dynamics so I think
the question is so how do cultural
Dynamics kind of play into the Zone
experience given how Dynamic and diverse
The Zone population is um I'll take any
volunteers for this I don't want to put
anyone on the spot but I will if no one
unmutes so by cultural Dynamic do you
mean mean like like like ethnic
backgrounds or like something um well
this
was I guess
um it could be yeah I guess like a
background of ethnicity or like where
you grew up I think also counts as like
a cultural Dynamic um I guess like yeah
how um how do the D how does like the
diversity of the stone population kind
of like factor into the stone experience
gotcha um well since it seems like this
is like a Asian focused um conversation
um so when I was there like and I'm
friends with all these groups
individually but I know like there's
obviously Asian-American Alliance I know
there's like a Korean you know like
student group as well there's actually
like outside of the asian-americans
there's like a Chinese another like
separate Chinese group for people who
are like you know like more like expats
um and they communicate in Chinese uh
and and so I I think like you know even
within you know the broader group of
like Asian you know Asian American Asian
identifying whatever I think there's a
lot of subgroups um if you you know for
for people with you know even more
similar
cultures yeah for sure um I I think I
agree like we actually right now in
Triple A um there's a moon cake there's
a mid-autumn Festival event happening
right now and that's actually in a
collaboration with the greater China
club and the South Korea Club um just
because they all have we all have like I
think different but similar Traditions
around this um gonna add to what was
saying too as well um yeah there
definitely some strong sub populations
and sub subgroups too I'm still on a
WhatsApp thread for Taiwanese um
students at loan and it's the same group
that was still active for for me now
three years ago um and very like people
post a lot on help support uh T
Taiwanese students who are going to be
at slan um very impressed by by that
that it's still continuing and you know
quite quite helpful um the the other
thing that at Loan in terms of cultural
diversity are these things called C
functions they didn't happen as much
during the covid years but um you know
were sort of resurrected after covid was
over different cultural groups will host
them um different nights and uh so some
of them are you know could be the
Asian-American Alliance it could be you
know one of the different other um clubs
too as well it's a great way to be able
to share um culture food uh dance too as
well and uh so yeah I definitely
encourage you uh to to to check those
out if you're at Sloan um good way to be
able to learn about other cultures and
people but then also just great way to
have
fun definitely um and then did you have
anything you wanted to add sure yeah
happy to um I think our class you know
specifically I think around 50% of us
were from the states and the 50% or
actually not from the states which is
pretty cool um it was a combination of
Asia a lot of Europeans um but what that
really did brain or class was a diverse
range of perspectives a lot of different
backgrounds um a lot of people who have
lived in multiple different countries um
and are able to kind of give that
Insight um or their own thoughts on how
you know how data I guess in our
specific case how data is being
Incorporated in different companies what
the kind of um narrative around data is
how willing people are to um incorporate
data especially in businesses given that
was such a primary focus of our program
um I know I learned a lot about food
culture um I also attended multiple C
functions which were very fun um got to
learn about a lot of cultures and um and
um practices that I probably wasn't
exposed to um um prior to that um one of
the things I want to talk about I think
not necessarily cultural diversity but
also just academic diversity was a huge
thing um I don't know if that
necessarily TAPS in here but um you know
for example I was a computer science
major so I knew had a code very well um
and there were other individuals who had
math Majors um and they would come in
and we would kind of lean on each other
um and there were some people who
actually just never coded and never you
know hadn't studied math before they
were more social um Sciences oriented
but had a strong incling to um be able
to pursue data science um and that
diversity of basically strengths across
different disciplines um both in the
business side and that could have been
you know public speaking you know
management multiple different areas um
and then also on the technical side um
that diversity really helped us like
lean on each other um play each other's
strengths which I think was um a great
asset or our class especially for the
program hu did you have anything else to
add I know you you kind of brought up
the first point that I latched on to but
if there was anything else you wanted to
add please feel free yeah yeah I think
there is something I do want to mention
just just about how Sloan and and they
facilitate the the discussion around
race and diversity really well um we I I
was in class during the peak of black
livs matter so this what when a lot of
discourse was happening around race
equality and it it opened up an
opportunity for the school to offer a
forums and platforms for people to talk
about how their lives were affected or
how they view the the system and um we
had conversations you know from from
African-American students as well as
like Midwestern Americans we were able
to talk and then we spun that off later
to conversation about uh someone from
International from China and also
perspective from US army military
Captain who who fought in Afghan it's
like you you you you can you able to
merge all these different views in a
very open and honest setting where you
can talk about your your views your
thoughts um and have like a very genuine
conversation about it I think that kind
of environment is very rare and it's
something that flown very well to
facilitate so um just a a commitment to
the to the community there yeah for sure
um does anyone want to touch on I guess
the diversity of their Cor for team CU I
know I think those are those are I think
like carefully designed to make sure
that there's diversity across
backgrounds but also academic diversity
um yeah I can talk a little bit about
slone fellows and maybe a little bit my
core team as well too so slone fellows
is a one-year program which is mid
career a lot actually a lot of the um
people in the cohort come from from
outside the US I think over 50% is
actually out from outside the US and um
they they they're coming with their
families often for for one year to be
resident at Sloan um and so I got a
chance to meet people from all sorts of
different countries uh at at the program
um Team actually we had uh one woman
from Nigeria she worked for Shell um The
Other Woman one one other woman was from
um New Zealand but she worked in Tech
and actually worked in webl which was
very helpful and we actually ended up
doing a project together on my weable
tech startup um and then the the other
guy was from Canada and he worked in in
the tech field too as well um so really
amazing my core team um I'm friends with
all of them still we still do meetups uh
and we we have a pretty strong bond but
it's pretty emblematic of how
International at least the SL was and I
saw that across all the programs but SL
was very International
Focus um so I think mentorship and
Community Support has been like a common
theme
um within different
communities can you share how mentorship
or Community Support has played a role
in your journey I know Katherine you
talked a little bit about um how you
that's kind of how you found your really
like the really cool startup that you're
working on um I guess and and could you
share more about that kind of mentorship
and Community Support opportunity or or
other similar experiences that you've
had related to that um yeah so so I
think I already touched on kind of the
student network but I really want to
highlight the professor Network um
because some of my professor syst some
really incredible things for me um so
when I was recruiting right after Sloan
um you know I was like I was mulling
over a number of options like you know
between Venture Capital um you know kind
of going back to be an investor or kind
of a midsize biotech or you know
starting you know very very like you
know early stage like SE series a stage
so there's a range of options and I
wasn't really sure where to start
um but I just remember like there's a
professor called uh Jonathan Fleming and
he he kind of does the healthcare
strategy course and I took his class um
and I remember just kind of and he's
kind of a like a Serial investor now but
I remember just talking to him and being
like hey like can you just walk me
through these options and over the
course of my recruiting Journey which
probably took a couple months like i'
met with him like you know like once a
month or like I met with him a number of
times um when I had all my options I
kind of laid down front him and kind of
got his feedback on it it I remember um
I saw these two positions one at onum
and one at dierna which if you're in the
space you know these are those are kind
of you know big biotechs in the area
before DNA got Acquired and I saw
positions there that I liked and I told
Jonathan about them and within 30
minutes he had forwarded my resume to
the CEO of both companies and I was like
that was just an incredible like way for
someone for a professor to stick his
neck out and use his personal Network
for me um similarly Andrew low is
another kind of Finance professor and I
didn't even take his class but I had
heard from others that he's sort of kind
of a big name of the industry he knew a
lot of people and you know when I was
thinking about Venture um I had reached
out to him and said hey look like I have
never taken your class but heard a lot
of things about you like like to just
chat with you about kind of you know the
healthcare Finance World in Boston um
and this was like after I graduated he
had no idea who I was and he like you
know immediately like took the call and
kind of walked me through everything he
told me he was like building his own
Venture you know like shop and was like
looking to hire sloes and just so I
think just like um you know just the the
amount of effort that professors put in
to help a student whether or not they
actually have taught you or remember you
um I just thought was kind of
incredible so I just want to Echo that
oh yes I was gonna H it to you yeah okay
amazing um yeah no Echo you know
whatever Katherine said really I think
the professor network is something that
um very underutilized you know we talk a
lot about our F you know friends and and
and students that we um you know work
with and their Network were incredible
as well but the professors are doing
some incredible work you know at least
on in supply chain operations research
at least from the mban was um you know a
lot of the professors that we worked
with um not only are they brilliant but
they've worked with you know some of the
companies that um work directly with
companies and you know leading their
strategy whether it's a business side or
um you know supply chain and you know
operation side um I actually landed my
first job I kind of touched on this too
with um the sneakers app through um uh
professor of faras who I took the
product management class with so he
actually didn't even know my technical
skill I ended up taking a technical
class with him later on um but he you
know was able to voucher me had many
conversations about career um and you
know what the what the path was you know
depending on what what I wanted you know
saw myself four to five years down the
road um you know all of them are they
make time um which is a uh you don't you
get you don't see often especially at
some schools you know professors are
incredibly busy but um a lot of
professors at Sloan have been uh have
made time clear their calendar to make
sure that they are um there to help and
Mentor so that's been
great and you did you have anything you
wanted to add from the perspective of
the lgo program or maybe other kind of
peer-to-peer or faculty mentorships that
you exp yeah definitely so maybe just to
continue the professor one there's uh
Fant fantastic network of Professor on
entrepreneurship MIT um I had a couple
classes there that's not where I ended
up but it was something I really wanted
to do as Lan uh I had no idea what I was
doing really really terrible ideas but
these professors would sit with me hours
after hours just to guide you through
the whole process and try to make
something happen for you and it just
just fantastic fantastic helpful people
but brilliant people who's Will to will
to give their time too so Echo that from
Al perspective the mentioned again the
alumni network is just really really
strong um there's there's uh really
successful people including Jeff FY who
just left the Amazon who built the
Amazon's 2day Prime so very some some
impressive alumni there but uh my my
whole career started because uh I was
looking for mentorship and I was able to
uh get gu mentorship from a few of the
lgo Alumni network one of whom was a
founder of his own PE Fromm and that's
sort of where I started to learn about
what this about like what kind of work
it is and and during my time as slow
when uh in the winter period when we are
supposed to usually have something
called a plan track where we visit
different factories uh because of Co
weeren able to do that he was just able
to offer me a 12w internship with the
snap of his finger and say like hey he's
an lgo who internet discipline and that
was that was the the beginning of sort
of where I ended up with so it's a
really strong Network um also really
strong network with really strong people
who who are very genuinely willing to
help you so um yeah just going the
experience from everyone else nice and
Kenneth did you have anything you wanted
to add about mentorship or um whether
yeah PTO peer faculty alumni I don't
have too much else to add aside from
I'll just Echo The Faculty Point The
Faculty have been extremely helpful for
me while I was there and uh uh as was
said they they're very willing to make
introductions I remember my
entrepreneurial sales Professor had
several one-on-one calls with him he
helped like think about my my problem
for my my start up and made multiple
introductions to me too including to his
own son who was actually working um in
in Tech too and had some good
suggestions um so you know that type of
those type of interactions I I were were
really valuable and you know this is
also during covid where it's even harder
to to build that face to-face personal
connection but professors really went
above and beyond to to build those
connections which I really appreciate it
that's awesome um so there there's a
couple questions that we got separately
from from like the intro on so one of
them was how does being um Asian or
Asian-American kind of shap H how did it
kind of shape your your slown experience
um can I start with you an NA sure yeah
um don't have much to touch on this um I
wasn't part of any of the um uh the the
Asian-American Alliance um and I know
that's I think within our within the
mband we did um we had like our own kind
of activities that we did just kind of
culturally so uh you know coming I'm I'm
Indian I'm Hindu and one of the big
festivals we celebrate is the Vol um and
I remember so distinctly it's a big
holiday for us and a lot of us have
family and especially a lot of the
international students would come from
India um we kind of reminiscing about
this um this time that would you know
usually you get a week off um just to
kind of celebrate this holiday um and
you know we were able to take that
opportunity just kind of get dinner
amongst us and it was not just you know
the Indian Community but it was also um
a lot of other you know friends and um
friends and who were who didn't practice
but were there to celebrate with us um
and so that definitely felt like a lot
more welcoming and and being a part of
it I also um I think there was a lot of
just cultural experiences that I was
able to learn from and um tap into um
that I probably would have gotten
elsewhere but um you know definitely
want to lean on you know pass it off to
Katherine and Kenneth I think who have
um you know work with the AAA American
all I mean the Asian Alliance um to hear
more
sure Katherine do you wan to do you want
to take it for a little bit um sure yeah
I mean I would say um Triple A probably
was like my core friend group um in the
first semester like it was a very you
know nice easy intro into like 400
people where you know you just had like
a small group of people who like you
know with similar cultural backgrounds
whatever um and it was just you know
very easy um you know I don't have a ton
more to add because I feel like you know
my like I feel like I try to Branch out
a little bit more outside of you know
triaa as well it's not like oh I can
only hang out with the asian-americans
so you know it's like that was my
initial friend group and a lot of those
people have kind of stuck with me and a
lot a lot of the first social outings
have been with triaa but it you know by
no means kind of limited or defined my
slown
experience sure
um Kenneth do you want to describe some
of the things that you know how being
Asian or Asian-American helps shape your
experience and or maybe if you and or
maybe your favorite um event related to
triaa well I don't know if this is an
official AAA event but maybe a little
bit of uh this could be a fun story so
um while I think it was like maybe this
the fall or is it actually it was I
think this the the first part of my um
of the slow fellows session uh was
during Co and there wasn't a lot of big
group activities happening it was hard
to actually meet people and I I actually
didn't necessarily have a lot of friends
in in the first couple months um you
know outside this loone fellows program
and in my entrepreneurial sales class on
on Zoom I got to know a couple of the
asian-americans in that class and uh
when they were planning a trip to go up
to Maine in Acadia they reached out to
me and said we've never actually met you
in person but would you be interested to
join us on this trip to Maine and and
actually that's when I first met Kat was
actually on that trip we hadn't actually
well maybe maybe it was the second time
we had met but we we didn't really hung
out with it um and it and and from there
actually the people in the
Asian-American Alliance Group and and
and became friends with Katherine more
and eventually led to me helping with
you know the the leadership transition
as well um but that type of Outreach was
uh I I I really appreciate it and
especially on zoom and you know to to
reach out and to get to know somebody
and um and make those bonds where it
really was harder during during Co um
and then then for me when I when we were
leading when I was leading the alliance
during my visiting fellows here I got a
chance to meet some of the the incoming
students too so actually it was a good
chance to bridge that so I just I'm
know like few like last last year a few
months ago um
and uh so triaa was a good chance to be
able to actually Bridge not just classes
but also different different years um
and and I really appreciate that yeah
for sure and hu um any I guess can you
describe how being Asian or
Asian-American shaped your experience
and or your favorite um Asian event at
Slim So as I mentioned because I started
with lgo and also Co and I also was in
Germany for half a year for my
internship so I I really didn't get to
spend spend that much time at Sloan to
be to be completely Frank but but
through all that time I I sort of stayed
with with within my lgo class within my
slown uh Core Group within within my
entrepreneurship classes and then the
last semester came didn't really know
that many people sort of like similar
situation but I didn't know that many
people so I just walk into the Korean
club or walk into Asian-American club
and then instantly it's like it's like
family um you're you know out drinking
eating you know doing you know fun stuff
and it it's it's just very easy to uh
belong I think and that's it's it's
always good to know that you have that
option and it actually kind of extends
Beyond just slan um there's a ton of
different Asian Affiliated uh business
school network that you can also start
to tap into um so it's all across the US
there's a bunch of events uh so it's
just no no shortage of things to do and
no shortage of people to meet so it was
just a just a lot of good times that's
awesome that's great to hear um so our
panel is coming to an end but we have
one last question which was is there
anything that surprised you about Sloan
and or your um experience kind of like
with the Asian-American Alliance so I
guess more so for for Katherine and
Kenneth but anything that surpris you
about your stone experience um I'll
start with
kenon um well I was surprised how much I
really want to spend more time there I
think um particularly for midc career
the the idea this lone fellows program
is designed so that you can get back to
the Working World um but I you know
that's how I was like okay I just want
to be there one year and then be out
that was my initial thought um but when
I was ending I was like well I'm not
really quite ready to leave yet and
that's why I there's this option to
extend six more months and um I really
want to even stay longer than that too
as well and I was like well might as
well have done the two-year program at
that point or the 20-month EMA um from a
Time perspective
um but it was I I I was surprised how
much I really wanted to you know I love
the academic environment I love the
community at alone I just wanted to
spend more time there um I think
Financial pressure was like I better
better leave they they asked me like do
you want to do another visiting fellows
program like another six month exension
beyond that I wanted to it's just I I
had to had to get back to to earn some
money but um but I was surprised how
much I really really uh enjoyed being
there Anda um what surprised you about
your stone experience sure yeah just to
Echo that I was surprised by how fast it
went I mean the mban is um I guess like
12-month program almost 12 months on the
dot um went by super super fast had you
know had a blast every minute of it yes
it was a little bit stressful at times
but um you know most of the time it was
just a lot of fun um besides that um you
know I really think one of the huge
things that surprised me is how
collaborative um everyone is and how
everyone is willing to help um I went to
a big you know my undergrad was in a big
public school um
by Nature competition is huge usually
you're um it's not necessarily I would
say you're not edging anyone out but
it's definitely you know the focus is on
your own learning um you really got to
vouch for yourself um and you know in
former schools at Sloan I did not feel
that at all I felt like people were you
know offering a hand they were they
wanted to pick you up they wanted to be
there to support you whether that's at
you know whe that's in like you know in
your classes or you know recruiting I've
had so many of my friends mock interview
me you know when I was going start doing
technical interviews um or business
interviews you know I didn't even know
what a case study was um up until you
know second semester and I had to start
interviewing prepping and um send me all
the documents and materials um to be
able to support that and even after um
you know people are so willing and open
to help um which is a great networking
Community to have and you know I think
we're all looking for ways to give back
as well so um yeah nice um and hu what
surprised you about your experience at
sonone and or in involved in the
Asian-American
Community yeah I'll stick a little more
to the slone side so I I I don't think
it should have been a surprise they
always tell you how much um potential
things are there for you to experience
this SL in terms of career paths just um
new new technologies new new Industries
but the extent to which that you
actually get to experience it and also
how much Freedom you get to just go and
explore was was amazing um if if
somebody told me I'll be going to
private Equity after going to SL I don't
think I would have known what private
Equity was so so that kind of pivot is
is allowed as slow and they definitely
encourage it they let you explore it for
the time you're there and just that much
that much breath was just something I
wasn't expecting so so definitely take
advantage of that and also look forward
to it because it's it's really fun
experience and echoing that makes it
feel very short TW years went by very
fast for sure I feel like it's like gone
by like this um and Katherine lastly but
not least um what surprised you about
your experience at slan and or in the
Asian-American community at SL
um well Co was definitely a surprise um
but outside of that I would say I've
actually been surprised by um how my
career didn't like pause when I went to
get my NBA because I think my biggest
fear um kind of taking two years off was
oh am I going to have to you know am I
going to take a step back in my career
am I going to hit pause and am I going
to keep up right um afterwards and and
like going in that was very much a fear
and and I don't know how many folks um
here are familiar with kind of the life
science recruiting cycle but what
typically happens is after your MBA a
lot of people enter into these two-year
rotation programs which kind of you know
circulates you into a couple different
groups within a big Pharma company uh
and then you kind of go out and you know
you go out and you pick a team um and I
was afraid that was my only path which
essentially means I would have to repeat
the two years I did at fiser right
before Sloan um and so I was actually
really surprised by the wealth of
opportunities that was kind of off the
beaten path um and how easy they were to
find like I thought I would have a
really tough time recruiting Because I
was looking for something that didn't
exist like a lot of companies will tell
you like oh or like you know I've heard
like oh people don't hire mbas into you
know like mid-level or senior positions
and I just didn't find that to be true
when I started recruiting um I just
thought the network was strong enough
the professors knew people who knew
people like there's so many Venture
firms in the Boston area like there was
no shortage of companies that was
willing to hire Sloan NBAs into like not
a super traditional kind of you know
life science's career path um so I so I
thought that was a really pleasant
surprise and really alleviated my fears
um you know prior coming to slow