(regal music)
(regal music continues)
(playful music)
(Professor Wallace laughing)
(playful music continues)
(wheels squeaking)
(jazz music)
- Hello, I am David Wallace,
a professor in mechanical
engineering design at MIT.
Go, go, go, go!
(jazz music continues)
Everything is an example.
Everything that we do is an
example of what we stand for.
What do we aspire towards?
(jazz music continues)
In the challenge of
working out every detail,
you'll actually find delight.
I do.
And your work will be
delightful to others.
Delight is in the details.
(jazz music continues)
(students cheering)
(calm music)
So everything is an example.
What that means, and
particularly for me as a teacher,
is that everything I do is
sending a message, right?
You're being watched, so
every single thing that I do
is an example saying "This is okay,
you know, this is how we work."
So that's why everything matters.
And where do those messages come from?
They come from the details, right?
It's all the little details.
Just about, I'm just about to get ready.
Every detail provides an
opportunity for learning.
Teams, may the odds ever be in your favor.
Three, I guess better three two one.
They'll do three, two, one.
Three, two, one, bang.
And the perfect example
of all of those details
coming together, it's the build challenge.
(energetic music)
(students cheering)
Three, two,
one, go!
(energetic music continues)
(students cheering)
The build challenge is our class's
annual obstacle course competition,
which we have been doing for 15 years.
In a nutshell, students
are grouped into teams
and tasked with conceptualizing
and building a functional vehicle
powered only by the
force they exert on it.
Teams then use their
vehicles to traverse a course
and complete a series of challenges
in a themed playful race.
(energetic music continues)
(students cheering)
And it's different every
year. It's extreme.
It pushes limits.
It's kind of crazy, and
it's euphoric, it's fun,
(energetic music continues)
and many students come to
MIT, looking forward to it.
- Woo!
(jazz music)
- There are many reasons
we do the build challenge
every year.
For one, it's a celebration
of teamwork and ingenuity.
(jazz music continues)
(students cheering)
But mainly we do it
because it's a practice
example of mechanical design,
problem solving, and engineering.
Our class's mantra
and guiding maxim is
put into practice here.
And remember, what is our cycle of design?
Let's do it all together.
- [All] Ideate, model, test!
- It's a sandbox where
students can feel free
to generate ideas, build
skills to model those ideas,
and summon the discipline and
courage to test and learn.
We practice so that we can do
it for real in our projects.
It's a message about what
we are here to do, to say,
"We hope that you will
approach your work this way."
(cheerful music)
(cheerful music continues)
The build challenge,
when you come down to it,
it's just a single one hour class
in our fourth year design course.
So why do we need a
massive structural tree
rigged with pyrotechnics and smoke cannons
towering above our field of play?
- Okay, I think we're all set here.
- Why do something on this scale?
It's not just for fun, right?
It's because every detail is an example,
an opportunity to learn, if you look.
- Right. Hey, Jeffrey,
can we test the cryo?
- [Professor] When details
delight, we learn from them,
and get inspired by them.
In short, details are
what make things special.
(cheerful music continues)
The plushies, the pond,
the custom chocolate coins.
- That's pretty good!
- The crab, it's just one vehicle
from this past year's challenge.
All of the unseen person
hours, the blood, sweat,
and tears of the dedicated staff
that pull this event off each year.
All of these details all
go into teaching students
that sure you can make any product,
but if you put enough attention to detail
and care into your designs,
you are going to make something
that people can't ignore.
Something truly memorable.
(cheerful music continues)
Treat everything that you do as an example
of what you believe.
Care about the message of your details,
and that's what you'll achieve.
It's time to play seriously.
(cheerful music continues)
(students cheering)
(students laughing)
Actually feels pretty good.