welcome everyone um my name is ABI yadav
um a co-founder and CEO of I customer uh
I'm in MIT slan MBA
2013 uh so excited to be here and thanks
for having us uh to present uh I
customer story we call ourself a
decision intelligence company um which
is basically a very laser focused on
helping Enterprise and midmarket
customer to do GTM transformation
with GTM we mean go to market um and I'm
going to tell you a little bit on that
uh in some of my rest of slide so go to
market uh is a two trillion Money Pit
it's a huge problem uh lots of
categories here a lot of noise in this
space lot of business call it different
names different thing but ultimately it
all tracks down to who my customer is
and you know helping them manage
customer data chaos and fragmentation is
what is costing businesses more than 15%
of their revenue uh year on year um what
what every business end up doing is
mostly around you know doing a lot of
marketing dollar lot of brand awareness
lot of lead gen lot of AD media spin
primarily basically to create more what
we call F all positive signal Loop which
is may not be relevant but it's more of
like uh basically to put out the name
out there in the name of marketing um
the a lot of solutions which exist to
buying signals data things like that a
lot of companies also spend lot of money
in terms of investing in data platform
and orchestration things like that so
there's a lot of Mumble tumble out there
uh mostly the challenge comes down from
this high level strategic challenges to
more tactical the current Solutions are
mostly very
self-service which are human dependent
requires a lot of work in terms of
setting up
data in set up Insight you know which
which is why there are a lot of
disconnection both in terms of Data
Insights and action um which leads to
very higher C
uh cost of customer acquisition lower
LTB and kind of lower Loi Roi in terms
of the marketing dollar and this is a
rampant problem um across a lot of
businesses which is have invested a lot
in terms of targeted marketing and
database marketing and you know I had
invested in this uh holy triology of you
know um data and customer data
intelligence system um so the way we
sort of addressing this is leveraging
agentic AI uh which is a right
triangulation between what we call is
from you know um a sort of a false
signal Loop to a GTM decision and
optimization Loop and the way to shift
this and we'll explain more in general
but we basically help um customer kind
of match their data set between
different sies
unlock a lot of intelligence create this
reinforcement self-learning loop on
their existing named customer data uh
instead of like chasing a whole bunch of
different database the way we do this is
primarily um these are like three
pillars of our solution match decide and
activate where we actually help them you
know within their environment we'll show
you in a second within their environment
without moving away out their data from
their data warehouse or their CDP MDM we
help them build their ontology real
world data enrichment Universal matching
things like that um we help them enable
bring their own model uh and
productionize them uh and then we have
these agentic Playbook which are
basically best practice playbook in
terms of data decision engine which are
like helpful for customer acquisition
retention you name it um from you know
built on kind of various best practices
built on various kind of speed to value
and which has like more decision Loop in
general um
visually it works out like this where
you know we basically sit on top of any
data warehouse or MDM or any first party
data set and we have this unique open
graph situation where we have our
immutable IDs which helps them in
matching and creating this knowledge
graph um and then sort of helping the
agent take
activation uh with human in Loop which
are mostly goal oriented workflows
instead of existing linear workflows
which we see it um so most of the the
top three key use cases which we have
currently in production where there are
customers which are using us for
customer life cycle
orchestration uh or goal oriented
personalization um there's a lot of AD
targeting enablement we also do in a
central basis so if you assume yourself
sitting on customer data and you could
segment it uh centrally but then
activate it in different attech marktech
in the way um is needed for a lot of
control experiments um that's what we
enable one quick case study I'd like to
talk about is U this is for a large
e-commerce cpg player um who has been
using this more as an you know a next
space thing Beyond bi where we actually
helping them not just identify what is
really going on in their customer data
but also like what's the root cause
analysis and how to improve this all
enabled through you know kind of simple
UI and uh for more business friendly in
the language they they understand um the
traction has been solid we already have
we're about a year old we already have
uh 22 plus Enterprise customer mostly
the kpi is around Ros CAC
Roi um the time to Value we get enabled
to some of our clients is mostly around
you know 90 days um so here's my ask
which is seeking customer Innovation
partner
uh pilot programs trying to get you know
time to Value into 90 days um and then
we have experts around Finance Pharma
manufacturing um I'm around this is my
name email happy to connect to LinkedIn
um and you know answer any further
question thanks so much ABI um again
everyone please post your questions to
the Q&A Tab and we can ask them here for
everyone um let me ask you you you
mentioned self-service and your action
plan so how long is that time to value
for your typical
customer yeah so um we the first use
case uh activation we do that normally
within the 90 days and this is for the
Enterprise setting where assuming we
were sitting on somebody's customer data
access and it's a simple readon access
it happens within their environment um
we already had build integration with in
data breakes snowflakes and real these
are like common data platform where we
can get started and show value within 60
to 90 days great and the um the
customers have to move their data how
does that
work so
um no the answer is no um we are not a
data platform we call ourselves decision
intelligence primally to get the data
chaos into to like activating that data
into for more you know relevant use
cases for a specific goal uh instead of
random orchestration or random
activation and which is actually
happening within their warehouse we do
have enabling a lot of integration where
they have to um give like act activation
access but the data stays within their
environment you know this can be
dockerized it could be deployed within
their um their environment set okay
thank you so much