(inspirational classical music)
(motorbike engine roaring)
(playful music)
(foot pedals whirring)
(David chuckling)
(playful music continues)
(wheels squeaking)
(tranquil music)
(birds tweeting)
(tranquil music continues)
(tail wagging)
(lively music)
(ball squeaking)
- [Narrator] Wow.
(lively music continues)
(avatar whistling)
(chair crashing)
- Hello, I'm David Wallace,
a mechanical engineering
design professor at MIT.
And this is my friend Finnegan.
And like a typical pet owner,
I like to teach him things.
He can throw and catch.
(upbeat music)
(ball squeaking)
(indistinct)
There you go!
(David chuckling)
But does Finnegan teach me?
Of course he does.
He reminds me to feel
playful, positive inside,
even when doing serious
work, to play seriously.
He reminds me that everyone
has something to teach.
(lively music continues)
(all laughing)
- Can you then drive for a second?
- [David] We just need to
have the humility, curiosity,
and respect so that we can actually hear.
We need to have the willingness to learn.
- You seem to think that I
was doing something wrong,
but I don't think I was
doing anything wrong.
(students laughing)
(students murmuring)
(dog nails clicking)
(David chuckling)
(tranquil music)
(David talking indistinctly)
(David laughing)
- In our mechanical engineering
product design class at MIT,
one of the core values
that we teach is called
user-centric design.
It's the idea of placing
the needs of the user
and the user's experience at the center
of our design thinking.
And if we can really
learn how to empathize
with those users,
we're going to be in
a much better position
to do something great,
and that's great for them.
(machine whirring)
That's our job actually,
no matter who we are designing for.
(board clacking)
What was that, hey?
(David chuckling)
Ready?
(upbeat music)
So we're always trying
to learn as we design.
And as we go about our work,
there are some fairly obvious places
that we look for information.
We can consult with experts,
we seek input from our peers.
We hear advice from those
with more experience.
And of course we go out into the wild
and spend time with the users,
asking them for their input.
- [Student] First what's gonna happen
is we're gonna raise the rails of the bed.
- Do we miss opportunities to learn,
perhaps something surprising
or really important that came
from less obvious teachers?
Almost certainly.
(students cheering)
(student laughing)
(upbeat electronic music)
Have you ever judged a
person and dismissed them
simply because they
are different from you?
Have you felt superior because
you are richer or poorer
or more educated or less educated?
Or maybe because you are
white collar or blue collar,
or you're from one culture, not another.
It's really quite easy to do, isn't it?
But in discounting, we miss
all kinds of opportunities
to learn things that some day
might really help us in something
that we are trying to do.
(upbeat music)
Everyone has something to teach,
and openness to being taught
allows us to learn in ways
that we might never expect,
things that some day might turn out
to be really useful in our own pursuits.
- Oh, okay, I see.
(student laughing)
- So keep working to
build your understanding,
your repository of knowledge and insights.
Be humble, curious,
watch, listen and absorb.
When you receive information,
entertain it, consider it,
let it sink in and judge it.
It might be really useful,
it might be a revelation
or perhaps, "Nope, that
doesn't work for me."
Either way, you've gained new insight.
The more that you learn,
the more that you have to work with,
insights to help you realize your goals
to play seriously.
Bye, bye.
(upbeat music continues)
(paws pounding)
(David laughing)