good morning everyone and welcome to
another installment of the mpg primer
Series today it's my pleasure to
introduce uh yon wrong uh she is a staff
scientist in prdeep nagar rajin lab
within the medical and population
genetics program at the broad she's an
expert in polygenic risk scores or prss
and their applications to diverse
populations her research on PRS began
during her PhD at Kings College London
where she developed PR PRS methodology
under the mentorship of Professor Paul
O'Reilly building on her PhD work she
continued This research during during
postgraduate training at the broad
collaborating with um halang Wang and
Tian Tian thank you uh to develop P PRS
CSX an Innovative multi-population PRS
method currently her research focuses on
applying PRS to diverse and AD miix
populations and leveraging these PRS
methods to study
disease uh she has said that questions
are welcome throughout the talk so
please come up to the mic so everyone in
the room and online can hear you um and
the title of our talk today is PRS
methods development and their
application thank you thank you thank
you for the nice introduction and thank
you for everyone to come here so early
in such a cold weather um so I'm going
to talk about uh PRS Masters and uh it's
kind of uh hard to choose a specific
topic because there are already so many
different methods to to calculate the
PRS and it's hard to choose the best one
because as I know in the uh real
application like each method may have
their own like a a more uh favorable uh
situation so I'm going just going
through the uh all the main idea about
how as a master
development about what is important
about that method and I also put the
information of the paper so if you are
particularly interested in any specific
um uh method you can look up the paper
or like you can email me we can discuss
but in this talk in general I'm just
give you a structure to help you to see
how we get all these
methods so uh so the PRS
um the PRS is like I think it's like
almost nearly to say is it can we use it
as a proy of common snip uh genetic
burden and it's uh the ma the mass part
is very simple is
a with the sum of risk Le with the
weight being the uh risk Le effect size
so today we I'm going to divide this
part into four parts inventing
calculating improving and standardizing
and applying PRS so inventing PRS
actually this is a story like maybe
started a little bit earlier than you my
thought so back in
2009 uh when we still kind of like in
the darkness about what the all the
psychiatric disease uh is are they like
a hitable or they purely from uh
environmental or education this type of
stuff so back then they gathered the
largest possible sample which is
nowadays may be kind of like a weird
like three, cases and 3,000 control and
of course we have no uh genome wide
significant heat like anywhere and the
most signicant heat is have this P value
of uh 0 point sorry uh uh 10 minor uh
six so back then people are kind of
like nervous and confusing should we put
more uh energy and the uh funding to uh
continue investigate into the genetic
aspect of the psychiatric disease so
then some very uh creative uh researcher
come up with our hero like a PRS so they
inventing PRS as a proof of uh genetic
polygenic genetic basis so even though
none of the sneff hit the uh genomewide
significant threshold but the P value
they calculated like
schizophrenia uh PRS pre uh uh uh
predicting uh
schizophrenia have a very very
significant P value as you see like 10
minus uh
and besides that they also uh have some
like a positive versus negative controls
they use the schizophrenia pris to
predict a highly correlated trade which
is a bipolar and they also see a
significant
correlation but when they predict the
non psychiatric disease like heart
disease uh Cron's disease and the type
two diabetes you can see like none of
this like a um Association is
significant so basically they show that
uh the PRS can be used as a
genetic uh like a appr proxy appr proxy
of genetic basis and is quite specific
to the disease or to the type of disease
is so here is the summary of the first
part so PRS can serve as a proxy of
genetic burden even when the S stat uh
statistics are
underpowered so let's go to the next
part the uh calculating the PRS how are
we
calculating the PRS score so uh I'll
just like a
uh first like a still go through all
these like a terms and here I will use
the uh like a the term discover
Discovery uh data to uh represent the
summary statis was I provide the
marginal SN effect size and uh then like
a in the PRS method we adjust the L uh
structure and gets the uh adjusted uh
effect size and we use a data called
fine tuning data to choose the uh most
predictive PRS model and then like uh in
the testing data we uh do all this
Downstream analysis like a predicting
the trade with a PRS or some other um uh
some other
analysis and uh here are all this like
uh it's actually just a small part of
the existing method that we can use to
uh calculating the PRS and there some
like a uh type of the of it I Al also
list like the for each time I'll just
like at list one or two example so the
most naive one is the clamping and the P
value thres holding sometimes we call it
uh CT or PT like they use clamping and
pruning here interchangeably so PT or uh
CT method and uh besides that we have
bent methods like we adjust the the
effect size using some like
bent uh uh method and also like a
penalized regression and also uh there's
a like a a mixed linear
regression plus patient method that
based on the individual level data like
uh both hmm
so uh here I only like mainly focusing
on the uh uh CT method and the I'll
briefly talking about the B
methods uh so the C method or clamping
and P value thresh holding is the most
naive and still uh commonly use the
method so here is like a
the the the the pipeline of how you can
calculate the te TRS so I just show like
an over simplified example of like the
uh uh of the the gwos data mahattan plot
uh we can see that like uh in in this
part of the the the the the genome we
have three AUD blocks and from each Audi
blocks we choose the most significant
sniff or the lead sniff which which is
the clamping and then we can
test several
uh several different P values threshold
to decide which sneep to
keep and uh and so as we can see as the
uh P value uh threshold be more relaxed
we will include more snip into uh the
the the PRS method so basically the
um
the the MTH of the the PRS is kind of
like can be written like this if you uh
have the lead snip and that snip have
the P value that pass the threshold and
then you just keep the marginal effect
size as it otherwise every marginal
effect has just shrink to the zero so
basically idea of this method is like we
use the Le PRS to represent the codal uh
sorry the Le s to represent the Cod
SES so here is a kind of like a summary
of this method so it's a hard thres
holding method it only keep one this
snip in each LD block and we keep the
marginal effect size as as it is if like
it is the significant lead snip and on
the other hand we have a more
complicated method B method so basically
it's kind of you can understand it as a
shrinkage method it will keep multiple
snip in one LD block and it will shrink
the uh effect size of each snip
according to the L information and the
also Assumption of what the true
distribution of the effect size
is so this the two like a the summary of
this two m and I will just uh show one
example of patient method like mostly
the B method just vary by they have
different assumption about the true
effect size so the uh here is like I'll
show the method that my uh uh my
supervisor Tang developed is called prcs
CS for continuous drinking cage and uh
uh oops sorry I and like it adjusts the
the E size of course according to the LD
and the the assumption is that the E
siid follow a normal distribution and
the the center deviation part con
contain two like a a group of parameter
one group is the the show shows as the
sigma squared is the overall variations
and the other is
a is kind of like a a shrinkage me that
sorry a shrinkage parameter that roughly
you can understand this as it roughly
represents the likelihood of a
sniff uh being the codal Sniff and uh
that's this uh that's like a uh
parameter
uh F or side I sorry I can't remember so
follows a distribution called gamma
gamma and the shape of the gamma gamma
you
can uh see on the plot shows with this
like a a yellow curve and compared with
the the uh like the the the normal
distribution we show it in the the dash
the black line is have a sharper Spike
around zero and a fatter tail on each
side so it can
have a more realistic representative of
like most of the um the the the snip
could be like a just non Cal but the uh
for the the the Cal uh the Cal sne like
the the amount of CNE may be like a
larger than what the uh normal
distribution would
assume uh and like if you are interested
is like I I can just let you know like
after you have this assumption you may
just like do the calculation using some
like a ma uh like a a mathematical like
trick like a mcmc m col uh Mark of chain
or other methods but I'm not going to
spend more time like to explain all this
like mathematical trick so in summary to
calculate the pris we Main adjust the
the marginal effect size observed in the
discovery G was uh for the a structure
we
can use the most naive uh method
clumping and P value thread holding or
more uh complicated method like Bion
methods and uh also improving PRS so
this is like a a large part of my uh uh
post PhD and the post do so I guess we
are going to we already seen this plug
for like almost 100 of times so we know
that the uh the current G was is like
over represented the over representing
the European population but uh uh to get
[Music]
a accurate PRS we are relying on the G G
was matched the population so all the uh
like the the non European uh population
are like uh suffer from a less accurate
PRS accuracy and the the field has been
like constantly working on how to
improve the uh the accuracy for non
European populations based on uh
whatever data we can
have and uh the reason that is we have
this like a low transfer ability of the
PRS is like of course the LD is
different and also we may have some
population specific uh Cal sneps that
are not uh be that that are almost
impossible to measure in European
population and also different population
have different environmental factors and
like went through different like s like
a natural selection uh uh and extra
but here we mainly focusing on the Audi
difference and I'll explain why the Audi
difference can lower the PRS
transferability across population and
how how we can solve this problem so uh
why it when we use like for example the
European population to predict a
non-european population the PRS accuracy
just Dro that much and uh major uh
reason is the Audi difference for
example in the clumping and P value s
holding we as we mentioned before we use
the significant lead snip as a proxy of
codal snips however like
the because of the A's structure the
lead snip are not necessarily the Cod
snip and also because the LD difference
in different population the relationship
between the uh the lead snip and the Cod
snip are could be different and the
different population can have different
col Snips so um and besides that like
the uh effect size of the Le snip can
suffer from the Winner's curse which is
like it's like a inflated because we we
choose the most significant uh snip
so uh the lead n set we we select it
from uh one population may not as
relevant about with that uh trait in
another population so that's why we can
see this like a the drop of uh PRS
accuracy
or uh or low PRS
transferability so how can we do better
than this so one solution is just like
we use some more
complicated uh PRS method for example
the Bion method because this method can
include more uh snip in uh in the genome
so like uh it will be less sensitive to
like the the the in uh in cons
inconsistency uh of the little s in
different population and also uh we kind
of uh we adjusted the size so we uh
partially solve the problem of the
winers curse and of course we need to
combine more uh gwos data we can have
kind we can think of better way to do
the combination or just combine more
data or we can include other information
so all this like uh the combination part
and also include more information part I
will just show you how we do that in the
field by some
example so uh the for first the better
combination method I'll just uh
shamelessly sh my own word
SSX uh and also I'll also mention
another method that I find very
interesting uh super learning method and
uh so the PSS X is an
extension of the previous master
prscs and it's uh what it's doing is
like uh we are trying to more
efficiently combine information across
different population so what's about
combining the uh different combining the
information across population so uh we
we think that the naive combination me
usually using some oversimplified
assumption for example when we
use uh when we have a very strong
Assumption of about the marginal effect
size which is like we running we run the
uh meta analysis of of of two population
we actually assume that despite all this
difference these two population have the
same marginal effect size and then like
after we have this uh
meod this method G was we can just like
adjust the if size according to for
example either uh the AL of population a
or Al of population b or some other like
U uh uh like AUD panel we made and then
we choose the we can choose the best uh
uh uh SN from all these like method and
get the final result or we can just have
no
assumption which we will call it the the
the the
multi method so the multi me is just
like a because they we have no
assumption we just view Each G was as in
independent we just run the uh the whole
PRS process uh as if we only have the
information of that one population and
from each uh population G was we get a
set of PRS and finally we do the linear
combination to combine these two PRS so
as a summary like The Meta method kind
of consider okay the different
population have some should have some
shared genetic
architecture but the way they model this
shared genetic architecture is not
efficiently but and mul population uh
just never consider that but on the
other hand the motive uh um method
consider the L difference and the
population specific effect size when the
meta method didn't consider so none of
them are like good
enough and uh also according to other
research we know that we should consider
the genetic uh shared genetic
architecture because uh from the
previous results we know that the
genetic correlation cross population of
the same uh traits is usually very high
and so a better assumption is that we
when we do this combination we should
assume that different population share
the same codos s and the F size are like
kind of largely correlated so here is
how we model this this better assumption
so just a recap in the PRS method do we
have all this stuff like we consider the
LD uh structure and do we uh as assume
the true effect side follow this
distribution and the the the
distribution contains contains two type
of uh uh two type of like a parameters
and some parameters like uh uh models
the likelihood of the sneff being coal
so uh but for the mul for for the
multiple population and we if we use the
the multi method like all the parameter
are popul
specific so in the PRS
CSX we keep everything else still
being uh population specific but this
parameter that model the likelihood or
roughly models the likelihood of a sneak
being caal is shared across population
so then we have this like a uh method we
called couple the
prior which basically means like a like
the the the assume the true as
distribution are kind of like correlated
for the different population and so are
you yeah can I ask a a quick question I
with hopefully not derailing you about
using this word population I was
wondering if you could Define what how
how does an investigator figure out what
to call a population when do you want to
make it more granular and when can it be
helpful versus hurtful to lump
versus uh yeah that's a good question so
for like uh just for the the context of
like a calculating the PRS for for now
like I'm talking about like a I would
just say like literally like a by
population it's just like a group of uh
individual that their L follow a certain
pattern or at least like of course this
is a very very over oversimplified
explanation for the population but uh
just for sake of calculating PS here
this is how I would use this
term I admit it's kind of very very over
simplified okay um is that okay
so
um so uh so from
the uh using this cuple prior from from
the uh Discovery Discovery G was from
each population we have a like a adjust
a set of adjusted adjusted effect size
and based on that adjusted effect size
we calculate the PRS and uh we finally
like a a linear combine linearly combine
this two PRS as the final PRS and here
is the some uh results we tested this
this method and compare it with
other existing method back then uh using
uh simulation data we can see that for
both like a we simulate a scenario when
we have a larger European GW was and the
smaller African G was and we can see
that for both predicting European and
predicting uh Africa like uh the green
bars which represent
the uh PRS accuracy when we combine the
two G was is in general uh more accurate
than using a the single uh using the
single population G was and especially
like the uh the African
uh Target like benefit most from the
combination of the GW was and we can see
that from all the
different uh combination methods sorry
uh the our method PSX perform the best
and we also uh like uh repeated this
test in um in B Bank data uh so here we
just show the a relative accuracy
compared with only using the uh European
GS which here oops and we can see that
like uh uh by adding more and more uh
population the uh the PRS accuracy
increase and also like we can see that
uh our method PRS CSX performs better
than like uh other methods but but also
uh as a like the the author of this
method I know this this method or this
type of like a uh combination method
have its limitation uh because when we
combining more than one trait or when we
combine say five populations the shared
codos assumption may not hold because
like the more population you have you
get the more likely you will have some
population specific uh uh population
specific C snip and of course for
different tra the CN should be different
and also the computation time will also
increase when we include more GW so the
com if say we com we want to combine say
20 G was the computation time of prss X
could be quite long so
uh that's the limitation and and how to
fix it I'll mention it later and also
like I'll also meure some other uh
method that can do the better
combination which is a super learn I ask
a question before we move to Super
learning methods uh this is online
looking at the meta or multi the
different methods um it takes into
account the different populations but
what about differences in the gws design
like the way the cases and control were
selected does it account for those
differences as well and sad please
correct me if I um asked that
incorrectly um
the
uh because it's not just the case it's
not just the populations that are
different the selection of cases and
controls or the imbalance like the way
the gwas was designed might be different
between those and that might cause um
some heterogenity between the
two yes I totally agree and uh uh
for like for example like in I'm not
quite sure whether like this question is
about how should we address that
question so I I mean that problem exist
but so maybe like uh
um like if you really con concern that
the marginal effecta size May really not
be that consistent maybe you can just
try more on to the uh multimod or the P
PRX method that can better model the
like G was specific uh effect size is
that
what
okay yeah um and if I'm not quite sure I
can really address all this question
very efficiently so if you want
clarification please feel free to email
me um okay I have uh one more online
okay are there any PRS methods right now
that are based on statistical find
mapping for example from Susie since
those variants might um are more likely
I I I remember there's a method but I
didn't like put it in to my slide there
there is a method like using the fing
information yeah thank you
um and also the super learning method is
kind of like a just so to be brief it's
like a conventionally we only choose the
best set of adjust effect size from each
GW but the support learning is like we
can uh is combine the different set of
adjust effect sides to further increase
the uh the information we can like
extract from each G was so that's a
point and this is one of method that use
uh the super learning methods and uh
okay I'm going to address what if we
want to combine say like a few dozens of
uh GS so uh for now like we uh in our in
our la like uh we developed two
actually one type of two different
methods to do this combination and I'll
just show one example like a GPS mode so
basically it's like com do the
combination in two layer first layer is
like we combine like
say uh
fiveish uh different G was from
different population but of same trait
together and the second layer is like
from each trait uh
uh PRS we then do the combination and
within each layer we do first do a
feature selection which uh you can you
can understand that as like we remove
some redundant underpowered GW was from
the model and next we do a linear
combination of the GW was based on the
selected powerful
uh DS and the result is that by doing
this like com all this combination of
method which show in the red uh in the
red do and bar like is more accurate
than previously published
PRS and also there we can try to con
include other
information um so there are
several I'll just give two example so
basically by including other information
I mean we can treat the different region
differently for example give some region
a higher weight based on the information
of like a gen set annotation biological
function and so some extra we can be
creative and thinking about all this
information to be include so we can so
the
PRS uh peret method is like doing the
um the like
give the PRS weight slightly differently
according to the Gen set annotation and
uh also there's another method called
xwing which includes the local genetic
correlation into the model which means
like the more
similar
uh uh part of the genome across
different population should treat
differently than the less less similar
part of the
genome and so as a summary so to
increase PRS accuracy for diverse
populations we combine information from
different uh population different tra
annotation and all these other
informations and also the the final part
the stand the standardizing and the
applying the PRS which we have some good
news and bad news the good news is like
a PRS can really do a lot of things so I
list the several application of PRS in
like a basic scientific research we can
use the PRS uh either based on the whole
genome or based on part of the genome to
predict the disease or subtype of the
disease we can use the uh PRS uh
sorry I so we can use the
PRS uh as a instead of the the snip as a
as a
uh uh of the to to be the uh instrument
variation in Mandan randomization and we
can use the PRS as to
uh uh analyze all this interaction
either with the environmental or like
the rear
variance
and there could be even more as the
field developed and also how close we
are to apply the PS in clinic there are
some also very promising results showing
that uh in we can really use the PRS to
help in the like a uh in like clinical
trial to see that the PRS can help us to
identify uh the younger
individual uh which around the
borderline or in
inmedia uh clinical risk uh to to
determine whether they should uh
uh start therapy earlier than as
suggested by uh
conventional prediction
model and uh also we have some kind of
like a bad news it's like the current
PRS is kind of like cohort specific the
if we're just looking at the RO PRS
value uh is kind of like uh it's all it
only makes sense in each specific uh
cohort for example if we
calculating the RO PRS across different
uh population we can see that uh even
like our everyday experience telling us
maybe like the African population and
the the European population roughly have
similar age Heights but uh the PRS of
African populations is can be much lower
than the uh European population and also
or like uh data tell us like across the
whole globally the uh prevalence of the
schizophrenia are quite consistent but
also the distribution of RS could be
like a uh very very wildly so we cannot
directly use the RS across cohort which
can be a problem and also the PRS uh
weights uh have inconsistent accuracy in
different population as we mentioned
before the low transferability and
the here is another represent is that uh
we it has the same K Weight and we can
see the uh the accuracy just drop almost
linearly as the uh genetic distance
increase and uh there are some way we
can try to part maybe partially fix the
problem so for example the different
population have different role PS
distribution we can just regress all the
PC so they have more uniform
distribution and laterly I developed the
method that can uh like that uh
interpolate PRS across the whole
spectrum of the PCA so instead of like
just
um like fine tuning the PRS model in the
match the population I fine tune the PRS
in different single ancestry cohort and
use their PCA information to
interpretate the PRS for diverse uh
admixed individual and in our test we
can see
that so this plot shows the uh relative
increase of the the interpret data
versus the uh
pris uh created by the conventional data
we can see that the the interpretated
data have uh similar or and sometimes
slightly better accuracy than the PRS uh
like created by the conventional data
which is like finding with a match the
population and if you're interested here
is the uh here is the the
preprint um so yes we can partially
address this incon inconsistency but
still like there are uh like so this is
like just addressing the inconsistency
using the PCA popul PCA information
however like some other uh research show
that the PRS performance can be
influenced by other factors I will just
show here the the the of take- Home
message uh from this paper I sorry part
of the take- home message uh so the
context such as like age sex income can
impact the PRS
accuracy um with the same uh magnitude
as a genetic
ancestry
um so there are all this uh Factor we
need to uh consider if we want to
further increase the PRS prediction
accuracy and also there are some other
limitations so uh uh despite we have
already some like almost saturated P for
uh for the uh con TR like height but for
a lot of complex disease the PRS
accuracy is still quite uh limited and
also we also notice that the PRS can be
very
unstable on the individual uh level so
here I listed two paper that uh talking
about this phenomenon which means like
even on the population or cohort uh
level like maybe they have very similar
R squar but the high risk individual
they predict can be bued very
differently so we still need to address
this uh uh address this problem if we
want
to uh have better or more stable PRS
which is more suitable for clinical
usage and uh okay here is the summary of
all the
uh uh of of the talk so the last part is
like yes good news is that K have all
this potential for predict within the
cohort and have many useful application
in both basic uh scientific research and
probably very soonish uh clinical usage
but uh however like more works are
definitely needed to improve its
stability and widen is application and I
will thank all my wonderful supervisors
and all my my co-workers and friends
that give me advice and discussing uh
all this problem with me and uh thank
you for listening any questions in the
meantime I was wondering if you have
suggestions for sample sizes or
heritability explain to have a reliable
PRS and if there are dangers or things
to look out for when calculating these
in smaller or underpowered
GS uh like what is the do mean what is
the smallest someh size full crazy yeah
like if if I had a if hypothetically I
studied a rare disease and I don't have
like the heritability explained and the
numbers like a height gwos would have is
there do you feel like there's
recommendations of the heritability
explained or the number of people you
would want in your gws to have the PRS
be more
reliable
uh that's a good question like
for uh
like I I think that depends on like your
uh your aim for the of the
analysis uh it's like if you want to
just show whether the you can if you
want to just see the um the whether
there's a connection between the PRS and
the the the and the the outcome trades
it maybe the you
can like a a quite small G was made
already enough to to show some like a
correlation like in this example but if
you want to um like um say have a more
stable nice results maybe you can you
you need larger sample size and uh one
thing actually like the actual number is
quite difficult to say because it have
to like how the prevalence the gentic
architecture basically like we will say
the the more the better and uh another
thing is that if you really have very
small sample size of the match the
trades you can use correlated trades to
kind of like a
uh to in increase the
power like for example in the you our uh
DPS mode method when predicting the SD
we also use like say uh blood lipid BMI
to increase the power so that's some way
you can use to increase the sample size
because basically my answer will be the
more the better
hi thank you for a great talk um I'm
wondering this context specific
specificity that um like like bogdan's
recent paper shows seems like a really
hard to know how the Field's going to
get around that and I'm wondering what
your views are for making progress on
that
front um and by that I mean like the you
know the fact that the prediction
accuracy just varies so much by all of
these non- gentic factors
is
um it's like
uh
So my answer may be not the best answer
but that's how I see it so if of course
like there are going to be the
interaction between the GW sorry between
the genetics and the
environmental and I think it's
it's kind of like just sucks as as we
because we want to just use as simple
prediction model as possible because
like we can see all this like um the PRS
with the performance would very so
differently and within all this cohort
but I think it's kind of inevitable
because I think that's how complicated
the G G by interaction should be um
maybe like for for my my my current
understanding is like maybe we just try
to cover the genetic part as good as
possible and viewing all this like a um
complicity of gy caused the uh problem
as an opportunity to study the gy that's
my current understanding right and then
does that maybe suggest that as a field
we need to stop thinking so much about
predictive accuracy stop gobbling up the
environmental part of the
variance like not exactly I think at
least uh my understanding about of the
uh instability I think is still caused
by the um the DS is underpowered when
predicting all this like uh uh
uh snep level uh statistics so and
that's why we that's probably like one
of the main reason why we can we see
when we're using different uh GS method
like the the adjust effect size could be
that difference because that's comes
from the method and also the the low uh
Power of sneep level stability so I
think maybe the the instability can be
partially solved when we have more
powerful GS and then
like that's can at least we can fix one
thing we can like uh have one thing
fixed and to see better pattern of how
all this Factor interacts that's my
understanding great um also just wanted
to say I love the name disco Divas for
your method amazing um we're at time so
thanks everybody again reminder that
next week is meeting free week so
there's no meeting and we'll see you in
two weeks stay warm thank you