okay so um should we
continue okay
so where are we so we we did a little
detour to Zer knowledge and we even
showed a zero knowledge proof now I know
I did it very very handwavy actually
didn't plan to really teach zero
knowledge even though it's hard not to
because it's so beautiful um but what I
did want to what the reason I'm pointing
out this I mean we will use it it's G we
will touch Z knowledge some more next
time
but this protocol is at least half sound
is half now let's see what happens if we
apply fimir to it and let's say we apply
even the random orical model featuring
the random orical model because
remember we started by asking the
it sound we don't know and then we said
you know what but if instead of actually
a hash function you use random Oracle
like a completely random function then
of course it should be sound because
what does it matter intuitively what
does it matter if the prover is talking
with a verifier or he's talking with the
hash function it's kind of so if it will
sound when he was talking to the
verifier the verifier sends him random
bits it should be tell when talk to the
hash F because the hash function also
send them random bit
almost almost true but but not why let's
look at this example I'm going to tell
you how I can easily cheat in the random
oral model okay so I have a g it's not
in the it's not in the language it does
not have a hamiltonian
cycle what I'm going to do I'm gonna
hope for the best what do I mean hope
for the best I'm gonna guess your B I
say you know what let me try to guess
what the what the B of the hash function
is going to be I don't know it's going
to be it's a random function let me
guess it's zero so because it's zero I
know I'm going to be asked to open on
the cycle so I'm going to commit to a
random
cycle this is some string Alpha I'm
going to go to my hash function give him
a x and Alpha my G and Alpha and I get
back a bit B if it's zero huh I open and
I'm happy if it's not zero I'll try
again again I'm going to choose a random
I can always choose zero or I can just
choose kind of a random uh bit if it's
one I'm going to you know I can commit
to all
zeros because anyway I just need to open
zeros I'll just commit to the all zeros
and then when you open I give you a pie
and I'll open the non-edges see Zero the
point is I can rerun you in the in in
the in in the actual protocol yeah with
probility half I win but I I can't like
I I can't tell you okay let's try oh
didn't work let me try again say no you
you failed you you don't get to try
again I know that if you try again again
eventually you'll win so you got one run
try with the random Oracle I have the
Oracle so I can abuse it so I can try
many many
times and that's how I
break okay so what did we
learn let's go back to the random oracal
modotto so first it's not
secure or not
sound if PV if the pro if the
protocol has non negligible
soundness if you
can cheat with probability non-
negligible you're going to try try try
until you it works and then you present
that as a
proof so that was Leo's question and the
answer is it's not
sound okay so then you
say
fine is it sound of the protocol has
negligible
soundness and the answer is
no okay so also not
sound if protocol has NE ible sound
is okay that seems a bit sad but let me
give you the counter example okay so
consider go let's go back to our
beautiful zero knowledge protocol here
and it has only sound is half that was
kind of the complaint right fine let me
make the sound is negligible even two
the minus Lambda for you okay how let's
repeat it eventually Le the times okay
so we have a
g I send you
commitment of a supposedly a random
cycle you send me a bit I open
accordingly but then you're like okay
okay wait I'm not convinced let's try
again fine I send you another commitment
you send me another random bit I
reveal then he say no no no not still
not happy let's do it again and we do it
land the
times now if all the time every single
time I'm accepted you're pretty
convinced now the probability that I can
cheat is one over two Lambda because
every time with probity have you catch
me if I did all them correctly so it's
very negligible it's exponentially small
now I want to argue I can cheat in the
random Oracle model how exactly the same
thing how do I cheat I first I do not
have alpha 1 beta 1 Gamma One Alpha 2
Beta 2 gamma two alpha right okay Alpha
let's start I I'm the cheating
po I try I guess B1 is g to be zero
Alpha One no fine I work hard I get my
alpha 1 beta 1 Gamma One good now Alpha
two same thing I choose I guess beta two
but I keep the first transcript I don't
toss it away I keep the first transcript
and then I guess beta
two if I guess correctly good if I
didn't I'm going to redo now and after
count of number of times I'm going to
get the second transcript probably after
twice but whatever and then I always
keep the first kind of I don't
know as many transcripts I had and I
extended so I can convince you
yeah repetition ah very good very good
so the question is what about parallel
repetition okay yeah this this SP thing
is fine if you hash the entire previous
transfer
because you can just you can just get a
new commment until you're
happy yeah so let me let me emphasize
actually that's a very good it's a good
a good a good uh point that you're
making
note when we apply F meal I I'm applying
the hat and what I said is oh I do the
same exact attack I get one protocol I
get an like I get one transcript Le the
transcript I'm done note that every time
I hash everything from the beginning
like the hash is an alpha 1 beta 1 GMA
one alpha 2 Beta 2 but so what I'm fine
if I let's say I got the first you know
let's say three transcript worked out so
I have alpha 1 beta 1 Gamma One Alpha 2
and Alpha 3 now I'm in the fourth I
guess beta
four I choose Alpha 4 accordingly I have
from the beginning like the fash and I
hope to see my bet four my I see it I'm
happy I compute gam four and I continue
I don't see it I try Alpha 3 again with
I I don't ask my first two that I
already did successfully I every time
extend and the point is I can always
extend in conon overhead kind of thing
yeah
B so the run time no okay so the
question look how long it I'm bounded
cheating Pro
how long does it take me every
transcript I it takes me kind of um I I
I do Conant number an average I do
constant number of tries on average I do
two tries so it's actually quite
efficient I I can generate my
transcript quite fast because how do I
generate it again I have G I don't it
may not have it may have it may not I
don't it doesn't have a hon cycle I
don't even know if it has an hon cycle
neither do I care cuz I'm never going to
use it how what do I do I choose beta
one Rand I I guess beta one randomly
very efficiently I commit because if
it's zero I just commit to a random
cycle if it's one I commit to all zeros
that's very easy and then I apply the
hash with probity half I got the better
one that I chose and then I can very
easily compute my answer gamma one which
is just a trivial opening
and I only need to repeat it like it's
only better half so on the overall I won
need to repeat the same one too many
times
that's come from
also that is
where that's why that's why this is not
sound exactly that's so I have
negligible soundness but still it's not
sound
exactly okay so this is bad but that's
the only time when it's not sound that's
it like everything else is sound so that
goes to the question about parallel
petition so now let me actually give you
a the theorem uh let's see
so the theorem is
that the FI CH
Paradigm is
sound finally is
sound in the random Oracle model
if the underlying
protocol is uh first it has negligible
sound it it has negligible
soundness and constant
round okay so if it has negaal soundness
and it has Conant number of rounds then
it's
sound okay before I had I got NE sound
is by repeating getting many many many
rounds
yeah oh yeah yeah otherwise you can't
even apply if the public
coin yeah if if it's not public coin you
can't even like complete until it
doesn't hold uh so I'm always talking
about public coin
protocols okay but let me say this is
not a characterization this is not an if
and only if we do
have protocols with many rounds for
which this does the random Oracle model
does apply in particular gkr so gkr has
many rounds so can we reduce intraction
in gkr and the answer is yes we can even
though it has many many rounds and the
reason why we can do it is because it
also it sound also or more
generally if the
protocol if the underling
protocol has what's
called round by round soundness I'll
Define it later maybe not today
and
any such protocol has round by round
sounds but this is more General and gkr
has round by round sounds so this is
kind of in parenthesis because we're not
going to talk about it
today maybe we will we'll see okay but
let me first prove
this okay so why is it
uh do it
here okay so I want to so let's do the
proof so take a protocol a public coin
protocol with Conant number of BR that
has negligible soundness and I I'm going
to prove to you that it's secure in the
that it sound in the random or when I
apply fe2 me on the random oracal model
okay so uh fix
any
protocol let's call it
PV for you know let's begin let's assume
just for Simplicity of notation you'll
see how it extends that it's three
messages okay so
suppose uh
PV has three messages
and negligible
soundness we'll later see how to extend
it uh more more
rounds so PV let's say there's some X
the question is in the language or not
and you know they both have so before
the hatch there's like Alpha he gets
back random beta he gets me gamma and he
chooses if to accept or
not okay now
Suppose there exists a poly time a
poze adversary P
star that cheats I want to argue that
that it means I can cheat in the
original interactive protocol so suppose
there's P star and X not an L such
that the
probability that P star with h and V
with h this is kind of the fure Mir I
guess it accepts with probability at
least let's say
epsilon I'm going to argue that then I
can cheat in the
original scheme with probability a
little less than Epsilon but not too
small okay so if there exist a cheating
prover that can cheat in the F version
but in the random Oracle model then I
can cheat I can use him to cheat in the
original
scheme okay so how so first note because
uh we're a neg probability this is large
okay so beta is public coin it's random
in I don't know let's call it K but K is
um it's like super logarithmic because
if the only poom many options and one of
them I can cheat so I'll I'll
I can this is not statistical sound it's
um it's uh sorry ah erase what I said
let me try again
so I can these protocols on one of them
I can cheat like for any Alpha I can
always find the beta for which I can
cheat otherwise if I can't cheat on any
beta there's not no point in doing
interaction to begin with I'll just give
you Alpha and fixed a fixed beta I'll
give you gamma and that's it so these
protocols there's always betas for which
I can cheat on and therefore because I
have negligable
soundness beta must come from a super
polinomial Universe if it's only
polinomial then I can play the same game
that I did before kind of hope to
succeed it's like a s
uh too bad in Hebrew we have a very good
saying for this like uh you know the
hope when you cheat with the hope of not
being caught there's a word for it but
yeah Americans are too they don't cheat
so they don't have words for this
what is that a word okay I'm not from
con as like confence oh I see lying to
someone exactly yeah exactly exactly uh
yeah okay so okay so suppose uh there
exists uh fake it till you make it
exactly totally uh okay so Suppose there
this a cheating prover okay now how does
he cheat let's see what this prover does
this prover gives you he this Pro
outputs so this prover outputs some
alpha beta and gamma that like a
transcript right and this
beta is Hash of X and
Alpha that's how we cheats that's that's
a that's a valid transcript that's a
transcript that will such and such that
the original verif accepts right so the
in the the prover he just outputs this
and the verifier checks that beta is
indeed h of X and Alpha and this is a
valid
transcript okay now the cheating
prover he G he gives he sends Oracle
queries to his hash function now this
Prov is bounded he's polom
bounded let's say he sends so suppose
that P
star sends I know Q
queries to the Oracle
Tage okay he's bounded so he runs in
poly time so what does he do he has
Oracle access he's he he trying to cheat
for an a now he can ask his Oracle okay
here's alpha 1 give me beta 1 here's
Alpha 2 give me beta 2 here he saids
that most Pally many queries because
he's poom bounded so there's some
polinomial
Q ques that he sends to H and let's
denote them by Alpha One after Alpha
Q okay now first thing not
that the
probability that he succeeds in Jing
alpab beta G said that Alpha is not one
of the
queries is
negligible if he didn't ask how does he
he doesn't know what beta is the only
way he gives beta which is the right H
is by asking he has no idea what beta is
and so if he didn't ask he can guess his
probability like one like one over two
to the
K okay
so let me maybe I'll go here continue
here so first thing note
the
probability that he that Alpha Beta
gamma are
accepting with
X so meaning the verifier accepts them
and Alpha is not Alpha One up to it's
not one of them this probability is
negligible and this is because k k in
this is or it's yeah it's like something
like 1 over two to the
K
what ah sorry Alpha q and sorry what did
you
say oh no Alpha Al sorry oh X Alpha yeah
right but Alpha needs to be one of the
alpha ones sorry yeah so he sends okay
he sends kind of X comma alpha 1 up to X
Alpha K that's kind of what he sends um
I mean he can send other ones but then
uh yeah it shouldn't help him so okay it
should be one of the queries he yes
first of all because if he didn't ask
that he has no idea what the beta is so
he guesses the beta correct do one over
two to the K that's negligible okay so
this means that if he succees with
probability Epson that's not negligible
almost with this probability or
probability Epson minus negligible
he doesn't only succeed but he succeeds
with Alpha that he
queried so now I'm GNA use him because I
know that he succeeds with Alpha that he
queried I'm going to use him to cheat in
the interactive
protocol okay again I'm really abusing
not I'm really abusing the random Oracle
model because I'm kind of I'm assuming
that the verifier really the only way he
interacts with the oracle is by kind of
queries and I know the queries and I you
know and I can use it to kind of
cheat so let me now construct pble
star that
cheats in the
interactive in the interactive
protocol okay how do I cheat in the in
the interactive protocol
a okay so first I'm going to give you
with I'm going to give the same x with
x the same X so this PD star succeeded
with some X and the language I'll use
the same X now first thing I need so
here here I am p double star I'm ready
to go here's x v I need to start sending
Alpha what do I do which Alpha do I
send now what do I know
I know I want to use this guy I can't
cheat I I'm going to use him he's a
cheater I'm going to use him what do I
know about him I know he cheated with
alpha beta and gamma and one of these
Alphas he used as a
query okay which one I don't know but
here's what I'm going to do I'm going to
guess
randomly and uh what's the thinging
again you fake it so you make it
I'm going to guess randomly in Hope okay
so what I'm going to do I'm going to
guess so what does p star
do first I'm going to
guess a random I in Q so just the index
which so I know he's going to make Q
queries I don't know yet which queries
but let's say I have a bound on his
runtime so I have a bound so p p star P
yeah P star are there runs in time at
most Q let's say so he queries at most
he makes it most C queries to the Oracle
that I know I'm going to choose a random
index like supposedly a random query of
one of the I query to his
Oracle and I'm I what I'm going to do
I'm going to send here Alpha now what is
Alpha ey I don't know what Alpha is but
don't worry what I'm going to do I am
going to simulate the Oracle from him so
I'm going to pretend I'm the random
Oracle okay I'm going to start by saying
okay P I'm going to use you yeah let's
start you gave me X send me
Alpha like generate this generate alphab
GMA now what does p do when he generate
he's like okay let me think Alpha One
I'll give him a random beta one okay
Alpha 2 or X Alpha 2 I'm G give a random
beta two alpha 3 random Alpha Four
random until Alpha I once I get Alpha
I'm happy I'm like ha Alpha I I'm ready
Alpha
I I get a random beta
back what do I
do I tell him oh your answer from the
Oracle is
beta okay so I'm simulating P Stars
Oracle in my and and like I'm I'm
behaving like I'm the Oracle sitting on
top of P star Okay g Alpha One I'm sure
here's a beta one that's your answer
Alpha two beta two alpha 3 Bet Alpha I
for random I it's beta
now he gives me gamma now okay now he
gives answer and I continue alpha alpha
plus one random let do random random
random random
okay and then he gives me a
transcript but with probity one over Q
it's with my Alpha ey if you use with my
Alpha eye hooray I'm going to give the
GMA if it's my
Al I'm gonna you know fa well GNA try
again I mean then I
fail so what is the probability so
that's that's my protocol so if if he
didn't cheat with a gamma ey with the
with the alpha eye if this Alpha is not
Alpha ey I'm going to you know lose and
say sorry I
failed what is the
probability so so guess and then
simulate the
Oracle for p
star
randomly
except for Alpha I
I use the I simulate via the verifier
for Alpha I answer with
beta that's all and then
if Alpha Beta
gamma is such that Alpha equals Alpha I
then a you know
then I guess let's call this G then
send
GMA that's that's the protocol that's
the that's the cheating prover that's
pble star now what is the
probability that pble star is
accepted again what does pble star do p
star is acceptable with probability
Epsilon so with probability Epsilon he
gives me alphab the
gamma but he chooses
Alpha after quering he chooses this
after quing the Oracle Q
times with different Alphas let's say
with all them he uses the same X
otherwise he's stupid uh but whatever it
doesn't really
matter we established that except NE
probability one of these
Alpha is in the I query
so what is the probability that I
succeed very nice so the probability
great so the probability I'm out of
space so the
probability that p double star is
accepted is at least the probability
that P star is accepted over Q if he's
accepted if he chose alpi correctly but
it's random one of them he cheated with
I it randomly so probably at least one
over q i and minus the negligible which
is kind of Min is I guess one over two
to the
K which is kind of the probability that
he didn't even guess just the the alpha
is kind of he just didn't use one of the
queries but that's really small so it's
still pretty big I mean so there is a
loss there is a loss of
q but but Q is polinomial and if Alpha
is non- negligible then Alpha over Q is
also non- negligible and that's a
contradiction any
questions yeah so the actually use like
the random model like where we couldn't
have just put in another half fun it's
like that Top Line there it's it's uh
it's not just it's it's not yes it's
this Top Line there but also
that we the fact that we even have Alpha
One up the fact that we can say that
there exists alpha 1 up up to Q like the
fact that we're able to
observe what he knows about the hash is
is in the random Oracle
model so the poofs on the random Oracle
model it's really means you know one
need to be careful because people want
to okay what's the kind kind
of so okay the Intuition or the the
intuition behind the roral model is to
say let's TR what do we need from the
hash function we want it to kind of look
random we want it to look random like
because the verifiers message are random
we want also to look random and now okay
because we look for and now and that was
kind of the motivation for theorical
model and then it's tempting to say so
now all we need is a hash function that
kind of behaves Rand randomly let's try
to use I know like people say like
pseudo random functions which we're not
defined here
whatever okay but you can but who knows
what
the how will you prove
soundness this proof unless really the
PO what it does is really just runs the
function if all he does if the cheating
po all he does he gets the function he's
like H this really looks like I don't
know what to do I'll just feed him
inputs see what output I get that's the
only thing I can do
then I can this proof in the random
Oracle model Mak sense but as long as it
can do anything else besides like
blindly feed an input get an output I
don't have a
proof
yeah oh one over two to the K yeah the
only reason I added this negligible
fraction here is there's one over two to
the K probability which is Tiny that P
star is accepted with none of the alphas
so maybe it just chose alp that was not
queried at all but you know he managed
to choose better randomly which happens
prob one over two to the K because he
does beta should be H and if he didn't
ask H then he doesn't know what beta is
and beta is random but there is that
probability that he chooses Alpha that's
not one of the Q so here if he chooses
one of the Q I guess the one he chooses
correctly with probability one over Q so
I get Epsilon over
q but if I I guess I should put here
yeah
uh yeah but if he chooses uh randomly
then like I'm I'm out of luck
yeah Q good I how how do I know Q very
good question I actually don't know Q
and The Q can the Q even can be a little
bit adaptive so maybe this cheating
prover he gets he sends Alpha One and
depending on beta one that he gets he
decides how many queries he wants to
maybe he's very happy with his better
one and he's done and maybe he's very
unhappy and sends another so it the
number of Q can be adapted
but since P star is fixed and I know his
polinomial time so let's say the runtime
of p is Lambda squar Lambda to the thir
I know that he cannot ask more than L
that to the third queries because each
query takes one unit time to
ask so I can I can upper bound the
number of queries by the
runtime of P star so
really the probability that is
accepted if if I if I have no idea what
Q is and in the worst case it's the
runtime it's kind of ABS on over the
runtime of P
star which that I know because I'm
giving P star let's say is an as a
circuit that like do
Hal no no I'm I I'm promised that P
Stars pomal size I know it halts so my
contradiction assumption is as
follows Suppose there exist a poly size
poly size I don't know Lambda to the
third size P star now I know that Lambda
to the third asks most Lambda sorry that
P star asks at most L to the third
queries
I I I think of the circuit of P of P
Star as being a circuit that has kind of
H Gates like random Oracle Gates so you
can feed it like alpha or X and Alpha
and out comes and it's like one gate
it's like one time
unit uh but he cannot have more than
Lambda to the third of them because
that's the size of the circuit
Loops no it doesn't no no no it doesn't
have loops it's like it's yeah no I
mean it can have it there the runtime is
fixed like it can compute at most at
most Lambda to the third Gates it has
Lambda to the third gates in
it so any any other questions
okay uh this was three
rounds uh what about
more so what if you have like
a I don't know a c
rounds what happens then any any guess
in
how the probability decays with the
number of
rounds
yeah exactly yeah exactly so it's going
to be if if you have C rounds or C
messages from the verifier let's say if
you have C messages from the F it's GNA
be something
like Epson over Q to the C and to see
why it's just uh it's really the same
argument what we need to do is suppose
that in each
round p star send the most Q queries so
maybe he sends a q Q ques of the form
alpha 1 like XC alpha 1 and then he
sends Q ques of the form X alpha 1 bet
like X Alpha Beta and then he sends
sorry X Alpha Beta gamma and then he
sends qqu of the form X alha so Q quer
for each partial transcript he has Q
queries now if you have C rounds you
need to guess correctly for each partial
transcript the correct I I'm going to
guess that so I'm not going to write it
down but like because it's really the
same but let me just say it in words
pble star what he does is for every
round of the verifier he guesses the
index of the query of he guessed the
index of the kind of the hash the query
to the hash function which is going to
be used in the
proof okay so he's going to guess and
here we said you guess I now we're
actually going to
guess i1 up to I
C okay for each message of the verifier
we're going to guess an index and now we
again just emulate p p star exactly as
before so how do I emulate I go to P
star he asks me just Alpha One like if
he ask me just of the form for the first
message like alpha 1 Alpha 2 Alpha 3 I
give him random random random random
random until he asks for beta for for
Alpha I and then I give beta
I now in between in between he may ask
for bigger he may ask all of a sudden
for X comma Alpha Beta
GMA random then random I give everything
random
but the first point I get Alpha the I
query for like the first corresponding
to the like transcript like the first
message then I'm like aha I got it Alpha
I thank you very much I put my Alpha I I
get beta I answer beta as the as kind of
the answer from the Oracle and now I'm
happy now I start
counting how like for I to I start
counting how many messages are are the
four
Alpha Beta and some gamma Alpha Beta
Gamma 1 Alpha Beta gamma 2 Alpha Beta
until I get I2 all of them answer
randomly once I get and any other
queries for that I don't know what from
random once I get to the I to like Alpha
Beta like Alpha Beta gamma I2 like the
I2 I'm happy I run here I put my gamma I
get a Delta I answer with Delta now I
start counting how many qu of the like
qu of the form Alpha Beta Gamma Delta
Epsilon sorry Epsilon is fixed next one
I can't until I get I3 I3 and the i3d of
them I give the
answer I just do it for as many rounds
as needed but for me to be Sol I need to
make all these guesses correctly and
each guess is going to be probable to Q
so that's why kind of the probability
decays a lot
yeah does that mean that number of round
is like L security parameters you still
secure yeah good good good no it's not
okay if the number is log it's almost
secure but then the probability is Q to
the log it's not two two Q is not two so
you'll get a little negligible however
so it will be negligible but not too too
negligible it's it's going to be kind of
Quasi poly like one over quasi poly so
if you have log
grounds if you know if you happen to
know that the original interactive
protocol has soundness less than
quasi like subexponential let's say you
have the guarantee that a cheating po
cannot cheat except with like one over
subexponential
probability then log rounds will be good
so the number the number round C this is
this is really your your
um your probability of cheating and as
long as
your interactive protocol has the
guarantee that you cannot cheat with
this probability then then you have a
proof yeah yeah
replace good good good yeah so um so the
question was can we maybe replace this
but by Q over C to the power of C
because Q is the total number of
queries the thing is so
it's okay I'm not I'll tell you the
the it's not that simple because we
don't know exactly how many so suppose
the prover total asks Q queries we don't
know how many queries he has maybe he
has all of them on the first message and
then just one may and it can be adaptive
it can depend on his answers maybe he
asks Alpha One he gets with to one he's
happy he's not gonna ask again and all
the answers GNA be in the second
messages or maybe he asks he says he
sees he sends alpha 1 beta one he's so
unhappy all the Q goes for the first
message so how do you choose the
I like how do you choose for me like I
said let's choose them
randomly but you may be able to do
better I didn't you know one can think
can you do better than this possibly a
because you're saying don't forget about
the end end end like the end it's not
gonna most of them you won't go all the
way to the end because so you can
probably choose it more from the
beginning probably you can improve on
this uh I didn't do the calculations
because usually we don't really care
about constants you know uh but you're
saying
oh that's why it's not true in general
like in general you can but I you
probably will can improve it a little
bit you know what I mean uh
because yeah maybe you want to choose it
in different distribution not
randomly more more towards the beginning
because most of them are not going to be
at the end but uh yeah there probably
optimization that can be done great
great
questions any any other question
okay so H let's see so maybe I will do
then I'm debating if to go to the
soundness in the standard model or to do
the round by round you know what I'll do
the round by round soundness because I
wanna so this says
kill oh good yeah thank you uh this okay
good so what did we thank you what did
we prove we proved that the random morle
model is sound the applied to the random
Oracle
is sound if you have constant number of
rounds and negligible air now K and
mikali protocol has constant number of
rounds four to be precise and negligible
error if you have you take the PCP with
negligible air which you can by we have
pcps with neg air you put it in and you
have four round negligible air you apply
in the random Oracle model it's
sound
so is sound in the random orical model
for kilan
M that's
great as I said we don't have a so now
you can ask do we have a proof of f
chamir for K mikali in the standard
model OKAY random Oracle model we have
how about standard
model and it's this is important because
for a long time people believed that if
we have a proof in the random Oracle
model it means there must be some hash
function for which this protocol is
sounded namely the belief
was if you have a proof in the random
orical model and then if you use it with
f something goes wrong like someone
breaks it we need to blame the hash
function ex you've used a bad hash
function for f meal okay so typically
you know when f is used in practice it's
used let's say with SH 256 that kind of
a standard offthe shelf hash function
that's used and now if someone ever
breaks your hash fun your
protocol the conclusion was shot 256 is
not a good hash function use another
hash
function okay
however this protocol is an example of a
protocol it's very natural you know it's
great like it's uh it was invented not
as a counter example for
f yet and it's secured the random oral
model
so f is securing the random orac for
this protocol yet there there are hash
functions
contrived but there are contrived hash
function such that this protocol is
insecure no matter which act in the it's
not secur in the F for any explicit hash
function that you
use it's secure in the anal model but is
not secure with any actual function
family
so what we learned from this is the
renom oral model is a night sanity
check but it's really not a proof I mean
we knew it's not a proof but it doesn't
even guarantee it doesn't guarantee that
there exists a
proof it's just a minimal San sanity
check yet let me tell you in
practice actually that's how people
check that things are secure in the
random work model if it verifies this
check they use it and as far as I know
things never broke because of of the
random oracal model being insecure so
it's more of a theoretical kind of
uh interesting thing but actually in
practice it's not an issue
yeah yeah so you know okay the question
is anybody trying to break the answer is
you know okay things are broken all the
time okay things are hacked and broken
all the time it's very rare that what's
broken is actually the
crypto okay it's not the crypto that's
broken it's but people do try to break
for example one thing that often people
break they use to break is our
cryptography uses Randomness we use
Randomness in in our crypto and in
practice people don't use like are we
use secret Keys we assume our secret
keys are random but in practice where do
you get this Randomness and often the
implementations are not done well and
somehow guess what things are turned out
not to be random or not random enough
and and then things are attacked so
things are attacked a lot actually in
practice there's a lot of breaches
security breaches but
it's very rare that it's in the crypto
itself now why why is it not that on the
crypto
one would believe that just because the
crypto is actually
secure and you know it's implementation
that are the problem and how many people
are trying to attack the crypto it's
very hard to say but my guess is that it
h say there's a lot of people who are
working really hard to attack the crypto
but I'm not you know these are done
behind sealed door so
a I remember the there's a a fantastic
guy chafi go student in our community
called his name is Joe Killian and he
was a a professor and he moved to NSA
and I remember once I asked him after a
long time after he was already at NSA I
asked him so you know do you guys know
how to
factor and he told me his answer was you
know the worst part about my job I'm not
allowed even to joke about these
things so you know so the answer is we
don't know
yeah
exactly okay any any other questions uh
yeah like this just kind of General but
like in general do you think like like
private like the NSA like private like
cryptography I guess like further
than the question was do I have a guess
so I I do not know the so let me let me
phrase your question is do I have a
guess as to if uh the NSA knows more
than we do my guess would be yes because
um they know everything we know because
we don't hide anything
and and they have smart people so why
won't they know a little more you
know do they know how to factor that I
don't know like do they have like is
their world hugely different than ours
that I I don't know but I'm sure they
probably have better something better uh
than we we know than we do and we've
seen it in history like I think even RSA
was invented but actually was privately
known before so we know examples so why
probably today too but it is kind of I
wish I you know be nice to know uh yeah
people
to that that's another thing no people
don't tend to publish their failures so
it's very hard to know going back to
your question how much did people you
know when we say look there's no break
okay what does that mean are there no
how it means we don't know of a break it
doesn't mean there's no break we don't
know of a break okay how much did we as
the community try to break it's very
hard to know because uh like exactly
your question was very good one people
don't say that don't report how many
hours they tried to break and
fail so
um so we don't know yeah yeah if you do
break something are you not supposed to
like publish it like tell privately and
then like wait like six months and
then oh you're saying if you if you do
break maybe you you need to be careful
to publish it yeah I yeah uh maybe
people break something all the time no
one
no I actually yeah I I actually don't I
know so I don't you know my my job I
don't uh that's not art I kind of do I
don't usually break schemes I I uh I
like to kind of construct things I don't
work on trying to break but I know from
like folks here that do more security
work and uh it's like uh people get in
trouble for uh for breaking like uh for
publishing and breaking things and uh I
don't know they always we talk to them
they always mention the word jail in
their conversations it's like wow okay
try to stay out of jail try to stay out
of jail like okay no and you you know
here in theory Land We it's pretty easy
to St out a jail um they don't run after
us uh
so yeah but yeah you uh this can be a
dangerous
business any any other
questions okay H so
um I'm trying to think if I wanna maybe
I'll end with a round by round soundness
it's not as interesting but let me just
say a few words on it because just uh so
I can check the box I think it's
yeah group you cannot do it in parallel
good okay so the question
was going back to the zero knowledge we
said okay so zero knowledge if you
repeat it sequentially it still stays
zero knowledge okay it still say stay
your knowledge because exactly the same
reason as before each time I mean I can
simulate essentially I can simulate this
this transcript exactly the way I can
kind
of attack it in the random Oracle model
it's like every time I so remember what
is the definition of zeron alge which I
believe I
erased ah look at this I didn't okay so
I want to say for every cheating
improver for any cheating verifier I can
simulate the transcript if I repeat and
Peril I can simulate the transcript how
I commit let I'm the simulator I'm going
to simulate a transcript for you I
commit at least at least a physical
transcript with a commitment as a safe I
commit I I I fake it till I make it I
guess better one I commit I oh oh I hope
V and then I compute
varar answer on my commitment hope it's
better one if it's better one I can open
and I continue if it's not B when I try
again and that's how I simulate the
protocol exactly as I cheat in the
random Mor
what happens when things are sequential
when things are
sequential when things are parallel
sorry when things are parallel now with
in the parallel world you get alpha 1 up
to Alpha Lambda so Lambda parall
Petition of the commitments so you
commit all the Matrix kind all the
commitments Alpha One you commit you you
do it in parallel you get all the beta
one up to Beta Lambda tells you if to
open with with respect to zero or one
and then you need to do all the openings
Gamma One up to gamma
Lambda exactly the the i i the thing
that helps me simulate is exactly the
break of the random morical model
exactly exactly now what happens if I do
it in parallel if I do it in parallel
it's not okay if if V Star was was
honest was completely honest then yes I
I'll just simulate each one separately
because he I can do the same thing I I
just choose these like each one randomly
Sim each one randomly simulate the thing
is V Star may be malicious here's a
really problematic VAR suppose V is such
that I give him all the commitment so
it's digital I so I told you in a save
but actually there's cryptography going
on in there let's kind let me just gloss
over the crypto it's the is going to be
dig digital so there's just
bits and now suppose V St chooses beta
and some function of alpha he applies
some he's a cheating proof cheating
verifier he wants to learn his goal is
to learn and how does he learn he gets
all these things he applies some f some
function f to all of them together think
of it like a random function I don't
know like a and that's bet one of to
Beta Lambda and that's what he sends me
that's the cheating Pro
now how do I simulate this I can I mean
I can try I can guess beta
one and try to get this I can't get
guess all the betas at the same time the
thing is I can try to guess beta one
give a commitment here hope for the best
but the problem is if I do alpha two the
beta one may change because it's the
betas are function of all the alphas
together it's really not clear how to
simulate
this okay so the question hold is this
zero knowledge and this was an open
problem for a very very long time uh
over 20 years we had no idea people
really
tried a this we know because people did
publish some partial results and we all
work like everybody worked on it for a
very long time uh we shared our
frustration uh and then in
2019 actually here at MIT uh and buun
our neighborhood uh a bunch of people
I'm going to tell you about it actually
proved that this is not zero
knowledge not Peril zero knowledge and
the way the interesting thing the way
they proved that it's not Zer knowledge
is actually by proving that the f chamir
is sound for this
protocol which is very
weird okay so what they prove
is that this protocol this is
a a uh three round protocol you can
apply F chamir to
it what they proved is if you so you
know there was a question is f chamir
sound you know in the standard model is
it sound is sound nobody knew they gave
kind of a breakthrough result showing it
sound in the random Oracle model so
that's what I'm going to show you next
time next time we're going to prove that
this protocol is actually
sound in uh if you apply F to
it the interesting thing is the fact
that it
sound if you
apply shows so this we're going to show
this is
sound so of course it sound it's sound I
mean if you just do per par petition
you'll get
soundness but it's also
sound with there exists a hash function
so there exists a hash
function such that even this hash
function under LW under a standard quic
assumption known as learning with air
we'll talk about later almost learning
with air with circular security never
mind there's a standard cryptographic
assumption so that under that assumption
there exists a hash
family said that this protocol so so
that uh this so that uh this protocol
is is um let me call is
uh is a f sound so it's sound even after
you apply the
F Paradigm to it yeah
a specific protocol yeah and like not
just any Z no not not any not any there
may be zero knowledge protocols that are
you can repeat in parallel and zero
knowledge yeah sorry let me clarify I'm
not
saying that any zero knowledge protocol
if you repeat it in parallel it's not
zero knowledge anymore I'm not saying
that I'm saying that this specific
protocol for graph uh hamiltonian
if you repeat this protocol in parallel
it's not going to be zero knowledge and
the reason it's not going to be zero
knowledge which is this is kind of
should be really like what you you
should not understand what I'm saying uh
or at least it takes time to absorve
absorb or at least to me it took time to
absorb is the reason it's not zero
knowledge is
because actually this protocol is
secure if you apply the fature it sound
if you apply the
F Paradigm to it and this is what we'll
see next
time so this is weird
yeah exactly so why exactly so why is it
why is it not zero knowledge so what
does it mean to be zero knowledge it
says what's the definition of zero
knowledge zero know says for any varar
you can
simulate but now I'll I'll be a varar
that you cannot simulate my VAR I'm
going to be a f v I'm going to compute
my Beta I'm V Star I want to learn
something my goal is to learn something
so I don't want to be able to simulate
you that I didn't learn
anything my goal is just to learn so how
do I learn I'm gonna choose my
datas as a f I'm gonna H I'm gonna use
the F hash so you told me it sound
there's some hash family that it sound
great I'm going to choose a random hash
key this family and my Beta is going to
be has of
alpha now you're saying you can simulate
me for any ex you can simulate me if you
can simulate me for any ex then you
should be able also to simulate me for X
in the language and for X outside the
language because you don't know which is
in and which is out you're poly bounded
yeah so let's say I want argue there's
no
simulator okay let me let me actually
say this slowly so I'm not going to do
this round by round on this uh today
it's not that interesting uh but it will
come maybe to haunt us later but let
me it's nicer to do and we'll just end
with that we have a couple minutes left
we'll just end with
that okay
so again next time we'll see that Peril
repetition of this specific protocol
with a specific commitment okay with a
specific digital
save is sound when you apply the F to it
okay now here's the
claim
soundness or Fe CH
soundness implies that it's
not zero
knowledge and let me argue that let me
argue that so here's the
proof suppose it's zero knowledge okay
so suppose it's wrong suppose I'm going
to get a contradiction so Suppose there
exist a
simulator a
PPT there's an efficient
simulator such that I'm just copying the
definition suppos it's zero knowledge it
means that there's an efficient
simulator such that for any poly siiz V
Star
for any cheating
verifier and for every X in the language
you can
simulate okay so for every for every X
Sim what does Sim
do see an input
X outputs like Alpha Beta gamma that are
accepted with respect to
X okay because uh
because the prover is accepted he's
honest so the Prov is always accepted
you're talking with an honest prover
that has a
witness okay so so he should also accept
they're indistinguishable real and ideal
like the real view should be in from the
the real view should be inum from the
simulated view the real view output
something that's accepted so the
simulator should out put something
that's accepted okay now so first first
I want to argue this
implies that also for X not an L or for
random I should say for or there exists
at
least such that
Sim and X also outputs Alpha Beta
gamma that are
accepted so this is
accepted I'll write it like and so this
should also be accepted
why why so I want to argue if for every
ACC in the
language this efficient
simulator with orle access to an
efficient
verifier with an expected
transcript there must be one at least
one exent of the language so that he
output something that's accepting
because he can't distinguish in the Ling
it's hard problem and he's efficient if
all the time that it's in the language
he outputs accepting and all the time
not in the language then the simulator
broke broke your language he broke n p
okay so that can't be so there exists X
not in the language for which he manages
the gener valid
transcript that breaks the because what
does varar do VAR this means that this
is hash
of X in
Alpha that's my V Star my V Star applies
F I'm I'm I'm I so okay the V Star that
I'm interested in is the f v star it
takes we assumed that the f is sound
with respect as some
H this V Star this V Star is going to
use that h he's going to choose a random
hash key and he's G to choose that's how
he chooses the
beta or he's going to fix an random hash
key is fixed that's it that's a hash key
it's fixed now Sim has to use that hash
key because otherwise you can
distinguish so he broke the F so he
broke the
F that means he cannot
simulate there's no simulator a
simulator will break the F so it's kind
of an interesting kind of people
believed it was a weird state of the
world because people
believed that in some sense that
parallel zero knowledge should hold why
not you can't learn what can you learn
try to learn but people also learn that
future me is true but these two these
two are not uh don't you can't believe
both you know and it wasn't clear which
one is the right thing and so now we
know at least for this protocol f chir
is is true and it's not zero knowledge
yeah show something stronger like any
non
interactive can be zero knowledge
basically any any interactive proofer
Which F CH holds can add be zero
knowledge exactly
yeah
Usef exactly exctly no interaction zero
yeah that's what the pro I see
yeah yeah yeah okay we're out of time