Hi everyone, I'm Tiffens representing
Inspe today as a chief of staff. So at
Inspe we are developing the next
generation or sensor for synthetic
biology
based on our CEO Jerum mission patent
during his lab at MIT integrate futonic.
We have developed the first ramen system
for bio production industry who is
facing a huge bottleneck.
Whether it is for meat, medicine or
sustainable materials,
synthetic bio production is still a
black bust. Up to 30% of engine therapy
batches fail in manufacturing and more
than 90% of synthetic technology never
scale beyond the lab. But why? Because
we are lacking visibility.
We don't know what's happening inside
our bioreactors.
So at inspec we are bringing light into
those black box by measuring lot of
information directly inside bioreactors
and that's what optic is good at. So we
are developing optical properties on the
chips with spectroscopy
fuescent absorb absorption or
reflection. We are monitoring
temperature, chemicals, biomass or pH
temperature and inside bioreactors
and so we provide at inspec multipar
sensor on one probe compatible with
single use at all scales of your R&D
process for inline monitoring.
To summarize what we are doing at inspec
it's optimizing your bio process with
data that we are giving with our unique
solution and providing a dashboard to
fully visual visualize all your data
processes
and you can see here in action with our
reable ramen specs sensor directly
inside a yes fermentation over 5 days.
With this proof of concept, we were able
to monitor the molecule of interest in
the concentration range with an average
error that we are still working on. For
that, we acquire with a reusable ramen
over 70,000
spectra over five runs in order to
create this PLS model. This models
allows to estimate the correlation
between established concentration and
real one. For that we have monitored
different molecules of the interest and
double the reaction yield.
Our typical use case in partnerships are
chemicals monitoring in complex
environment or data generation for AI
modeling for in biochemistry.
The industry we are working with are
farmer agri food or cosmetics. We
already have all the proof of concept
ongoing with number food or pharma
companies all over the world in Europe
and US.
Our partnership take two forms pilot
testing where we first test the molecule
of your interest in our lab in Paris and
then come into your site or more
long-term code development to adapt our
technology to your special needs of your
industrial companies.
If these challenges resonate with your
company's bio monitoring issues, then we
inspect team would be happy to develop
it with you.