In our case, uh, we developed the whole
imaging platform in order to see what
our activity regulated genes do in the
brain because we knew they had to do
with plasticity. We knew many of them
were synaptic, but we did we wanted to
see what was actually happening at
synapses when these genes are not
present or they're mutated. And so but
the ability to actually monitor uh
synapses in the living brain um was not
there when I started. Um and around the
time that I started was when two photon
microscopy which is the tool that people
use to image deep into tissue was being
uh first implemented in relation to um
biological samples. Um but no one had
looked at it at that level of
resolution.
Um and part of that was being able to
also label the syninnapse so that you
could see them. So it has two parts. One
is the microscopy, the other is the
labeling. And so we could do the
labeling as a molecular lab and uh my
colleague Peter So um could build the
microscopes that we needed. And so
uh some aspects of the technology when
we started there were no commercially
available microscopes of this time you
had to build them and at that point we
started we were imaging only in one
color so we could just see neurons and
that's when we identified the inhibitory
neurons as being particularly
plastic.
Um and then we started thinking well if
the inhibitory neurons are particularly
plastic we want to look at those
synapses specifically. Um but there was
actually no tool available to look at
them. They have no structural surrogate
or something where you can look at the
entire cell. Excitatory synapses live on
these little protrusions that are
spines. And so people even by doing a
cell fill could sort of say, "Oh, this I
see these little spines. That means
that's where the excitatory synapses
are." But inhibitory neurons don't have
that. And so we developed a um a tool
where we actually tagged um inhibitory
synaptic proteins that we could then
track in vivo.
And so then we started looking at
inhibitory synapses. And indeed we saw
that they were extremely dynamic. We
first of all I mean it was really the
first view of where they lived on this
cell. Um and so we found that they were
in all kinds of places that people
didn't expect them to be. So just being
able to see them um gave us a view of
where they target the excitatory
neurons. Um and that also had
implications for how they work. Um and
then
once we started being able to see them
um in order to do that we had to label
them and we had to see the cell too. So
we had to image in two colors. So around
the time when people started the two
photon microscopes
then became available like after we had
done our one color the one color became
available commercially and then we
started doing two colors. So we always
stayed a little bit ahead in terms of
the technology and so now you can buy a
twocolor two photon. They're less
flexible than our systems. Uh but now
we're imaging in three colors. There's
still not a threecolor microscope
available um that you can buy. And the
other thing is that we can kind of
change our microscope design depending
on what it is we're asking. Um and so I
think the um
the technology development um and also
integrating the molecular labeling with
the
microscopy has been very powerful. Um
and I I I think that this is something
that's why I'm I stay here, right?
Because I feel like this is something
special here.