to me now I believe if you ask me who I
am I believe I'm a lifelong learner and
that's what ocw introduced to me being
that idea that if you want to learn
anything you can simply go and look for
the content it's probably
[Music]
there welcome to open Learners a podcast
that tells the stories of Learners all
over the world who use mit's open
courseware I'm
ueli and open myself from Uganda and I'm
Michael Jordan Pilgreen an open learner
from Memphis
[Music]
Tennessee so Emanuel do you want to do
the honors of introducing today's
learner sure today we are going to hear
from Jerry Vance anguzu an open learner
from my home country of Uganda Jerry is
what I would consider a super learner he
took his first ocw class and statistics
in 2020 while he was a student at chambo
University a prestigious University here
in Cala in the past four years he not
only graduated from chogo University
with a bachelor's degree but he also
completed his MIT certification in
statistics and data science he also
earned a certificate in computer and
data science through mit's emerging
Talent program which goes to show the
kind of drive that Jerry has he not only
achieved The Bachelor during that time
but went on to add on more certificates
more degrees and ocw has been very
crucial to that Journey so I can't wait
to hear what the episode well Manuel so
so he's really done a lot of different
programs at MIT it's so impressive for
those of you who don't know mit's
emerging Talent program is a part of the
MIT Jam World education lab it is
formerly known as MIT react and you'll
hear us refer to the program as both MIT
react and emerging Talent throughout the
interview calling the program by its
current name emerging Talent develops
Global education programs for talented
individuals living and challenging
economic and social circumstances around
the world emerging Talent is a year-long
program of courses and workshops its
goals to give participants tools to
advance their careers Jerry was just one
of 50 people to be accepted in the 2021
cohort and he hasn't let the skills he
acquired there go to waste that's right
Michael Jerry started his own business
in September 2023 it's called Eva PESA
it's a banking and investment fintech
platform that also provides financial
literacy resources to people in
subsaharan Africa Jerry's going to tell
us all about that during the interview
but I have to say he's really meeting a
real need on the continent how did you
first meet Jerry Michael it's funny I
think both you and I met Jerry through
Linkedin right after the covid pandemic
and we sat down and talked to him about
his journey through Co and this was
before he had graduated from the
emerging Talent program program and we
were just so fascinated by his story and
his drive to continue his education
despite being the sole income earner in
his household during the lockdown this
is such a great conversation Michael
actually um he talks about doing online
courses without a computer or Wi-Fi
which is very impressive and harder than
it sounds uh he talks about how the
pandemic affected him and his family and
how he grew from entering data to owning
a business in just four years which is
impressive Jerry's journey is really
incredible but let's hear from Jerry
himself here is our conversation with
Jerry vuzu of kalala
Uganda let me introduce myself in my
mother tongue there's a lot of cultural
diversity in Uganda today I think if
this is the opportunity I have I want to
say something in a different language a
Ugandan language but probably one many
people around the world have probably
never never heard of so that particular
language is called L I come from the
northern the Northwestern part of the
country so let me introduce
myself
Ang
MIT so what I simply said is my name is
Jer
and uh fun fact my last name anguzu it's
in the same language and it simply means
long journey that's really cool Jerry in
our first conversation we had when
Emanuel you and I met just kind of
informally before this all became a
thing I'm interested to go back to
before Co you know when you were kind of
using open course where but before
emerging talent and all that maybe you
could tell us like what your day-to-day
life was like I started getting when I
was still in high school or towards
finishing my high school I I knew I
wanted to get a career in particularly
in the financial space to be specific I
wanted to be a Trader I got to watch
this documentary about the black and shs
model which really got me so interested
in the whole financial landscape and
from then I really started going down
into that rabbit hole then very quickly
you if you're interested in finance
you'll get to learn about the 2008
financial crisis so I try to read very
extensively about any kind of
information that I could actually get
about that whole crisis so question to
me was what do I then pursue after
because I was then convinced like I
really wanted to be in the financial
field that's really what I wanted to do
unfortunately there isn't a course of
financial Engineering in Uganda so if
you wanted to become a financial
engineer you have to look for your way
around and get something else and I
think to me the closest thing to
financial engineering at that time was
statistics around that time now when I
started doing the math trying to study
and all that however it very quickly
became obvious to me that I might not be
able to derive the kind of value that I
really want from this particular course
because so happens that the course was
very theoretical in nature there were
really very few practical ways or to see
how you can actually make an application
of all these various Concepts that
you're studying so from then I started
really looking for content looking for
can I get certain types of content which
can supplement me supplement me so that
yes I am doing this course because as a
person I'd always been a very very
curious person so when I was really in
this point that is when I started
looking around online what kinds of
materials are there and growing up as a
child I'd always known about MIT in
particular because I I was interested in
physics a lot so I kept on reading about
famous physicists and many times if you
read about physics long enough you come
across ideas from MIT but you always had
that kind of aspiration there that one
day maybe I want to go to MIT and maybe
study from MIT however that didn't seem
to be something which I could easily
realize in the short term so I started
getting into what kind of material is
actually out there is it possible to
learn from MIT without necessarily going
to campus so that's when I started
looking through and seeing what kind of
content is actually out there and very
quickly you come across the MIT open
coare it's very hard because on the one
hand I have all this classwork I have to
do on the other hand I'm trying to learn
something which is it is related but
then it's not particularly what I am
studying at the University so you have
to create your own time to do that kind
of extra study which was a problem
because you have exams they examining
you on what they're teaching you at the
University not necessarily what you're
interested in learning so I tried doing
the course but several times I I I
couldn't manage it like you watch a
couple of lectures you're unable to
follow because you've never really
programmed a computer Compu so you get
lost in the weeds you don't know what to
do next so you aband on the course what
happened after you took that course lead
us up to the pandemic and kind of where
you were during that time too the
pandemic happened when I was in towards
my final years in the University so now
remember like what I had told you
earlier that it was really hard to
particularly study the course while I'm
also having my class work so to me in a
way the pandemic provided a very great
opportunity because here we were schools
had closed University had closed and we
really had nothing to do just literally
sitting home so this is the time I
really started taking this course
seriously because when I had time on my
hand and I it was indefinite we didn't
know when this was coming to an end now
as soon as I finished the first course
which was introduction to computer
science and programming in Python I was
immediately interested and got to the
second course which I also completed
during that time of the pandemic and
like I mentioned there reason why I
believed I was able to because finally I
had time I had a computer at that time
and I just acquired a computer then I
get all the time I need to actually
concentrate on this course oh wow that's
amazing uh you mean you are doing all
these classes before without a computer
first yeah yeah give us some background
on that so I I didn't have a laptop
initially what I had was a smartphone so
what I will do is uh explicitly remember
my smartphone a Huawei y330 so I love it
because it was my first ever smartphone
that I owned so uh I used to download
the content and keep it on because it
was very hard watching it online so
funny enough there used to be a place
near where I used where I stayed it was
a university not where I went but was at
Medical Institute so they they had Wi-Fi
on so uh you know internet is quite
expensive in Uganda so you wouldn't be
able to download a file of 500 MBS at
least in that time when you have no
income that's a lot of data only 500 MBS
don't even talk about about 1 GB and you
know these courses are a lot of content
so what we used to do is uh we used to
run to the the institutes uh outside
because of course they couldn't let you
in so outside there the Wi-Fi could sort
of reach where we could stand so believe
believe me believe me we there used to
be a line of people who are literally
standing on the road and we ter it as
tapping the Wi-Fi in hindsight when I
think about it it might also be one of
the reasons it was initially hard for me
to complete the course because yes you
go through these videos but you have
nowhere to practice it exactly I used to
download the number of apps the number
of coding apps you can have on the phone
but those I feel like are not the most
effective ways but yeah yeah it's cool
so you mentioned you didn't have any
background in any of this what was your
background like what did you study in
high school and maybe as a follow-up
question I know in Uganda most from like
primary we are using English all the way
was that the same case with you as well
or because most of ocw courses are in
English yeah I you know uh English is
the okay I believe now it's not the
official but it's one of the official
languages in Uganda English and kahili
so for me English has never really been
a problem it's something which I learned
from from way back when I was growing up
so that was really never a challenge in
terms of communication I'd always known
how to speak English for for as long as
I can remember during my high school in
Uganda so you stud a lot of courses
especially in lower high school so when
you get to Upper high school that's when
you specialize I particularly did
physics mathematics and economics yeah I
always I always love physics like I
mentioned I I thought at one point I was
going to be a physicist I love physics
too yeah and chemistry chemistry didn't
love me back
but it's a whole other story yeah and
just you know we do have a global
audience so I'm curious you know Emanuel
or Jerry if you want to talk about this
how was the pandemic in Uganda how did
it impact you and then how did having
access to online education and you know
we'll get into it here in a bit but
having access to that online community
helped you during that time too when the
pandemic started out all schools all
Institutes of Education those were the
first ones which ended up being closed
right so now when that happened we we
all thought believe like everyone else
that maybe this is something which is
going to take a week and this gets
resoled maybe two weeks at most or
whichever now very quickly uh the
situation starts to escalate it's now
not just schools which are closed
businesses get closed down now this
really to us as a from my experience it
presented a very big problem because you
see in Uganda and uh maybe most of
subsaharan Africa particularly for our
case most people leave hand to mouth
right so you go to the market you're
probably selling something so whatever
income you're going to get from that
particular sale of that day that is what
is going to feed you you do not have any
kind of Social Security net or anything
which is looking out for you so you
don't have any savings basically you
need to work to be able to eat you need
to go to work to earn some money so that
you can be able to buy food so when the
pandemic comes and the economy is
literally shut down that became a very
very difficult period because getting
food itself became very hard because
there was now no kind of economic
activities taking place remember
everything Remains the Same there's
still rent which had to be paid funny
story uh because during the time
actually when the pandemic started I I
was renting out a hostel the University
where I was staying but now because of
the pandemic there was really no money
to pay the rent it was a really
difficult and challenging times yeah I
understand that is when I saw that the
online education it was really a savior
to say the least one you didn't have
schools it reached a point it felt like
there's no other opportunities which are
going to come around because you see
your betting your entire life and your
entire career on this education you're
going to get this University degree and
then you start to know people who are
sick then you start to know people who
passed on so it's something which starts
becoming personal I also come from a
family which has several people in it
which is really a typical African family
they're not really nuclear families it's
really an extended family you have
cousins of cousins of cousins all
staying under the same roof so
everything becomes challenging all these
mouths have to be fed so there was a lot
of really strain and to me studying
online seem to be an
escape this is a very interesting
Journey you went from just trying to do
these courses on your smartphone you
know the pandemic happens you have then
you get your own laptop then you do the
actual courses on your laptop
very very powerful story you mention you
many at home have you ever like the
things you are learning and this world
that you had been exposed to have you
like try to pass that on or any impact
in your surrounding maybe your cousins
at home you've introduced them to
ocw the person who are introduced to ocw
is my brother he was doing engineering
so I kept on telling him about actually
there's this platform you could get a
lot of content especially from the
engineering side so as a relative that
is the one key person I believe I
introduced however beyond that here's
something which interesting that
happened I done a bit of python and I
now knew and understood a bit of python
or programming in general so people many
of my colleagues actually didn't know
what python was so several times they
kept on asking me what are these things
on your computer what are these things
that you're studying and all that so
that is when I kept on telling them oh
you can actually learn this content
online you can learn this content online
on this particular platform and in a way
over time I started becoming almost I
like to call myself an ocw ambassador
telling people like actually you can get
this kind of education online you don't
need to pay anything you just need to
have a bit of time yeah I was going to
say that's really awesome I was uh
wondering if you could talk a little bit
about how you found out about MIT
emerging talent and you know kind of
after that I don't know when in the
process you decided to be a business
owner but maybe you could talk a little
bit about founding a business and like
how that looks day to day too after the
emerging talent I remember that whole
quote that uh learning from mits like
trying to drink from Fire Halls so to me
I really got I got I got hooked to the
whole MIT culture because I could see
there something I've actually learned
especially in terms of how they were
explaining the various Concepts to me
they simplified a lot of things which I
really love so from that whole process
of always wanting to see what kind of
free materials MIT putting there what
kind of resources can I gain from MIT
one day I come across this program which
is called MIT react so I start looking
further into what MIT react is learning
further more about it and MIT react
which is now MIT emerging talents F
about it and I realized that I actually
fit the profile to be able to uh study
here uh study under this program so I
write my application I sent it through I
remember it was a very daunting task
because you had to do a virtually proed
exam before so I remember I had to wake
up very early in the morning to try and
do that and uh after I did the exam I
kept on wondering if I am going to pass
or I'm not going to pass waited a couple
of weeks and then I received that
message that had actually been accepted
this should be around 2022 when we still
in the pandemic once I received that
letter that I've actually been accepted
to me now this was this was it I'd
always wanted to do MIT and here now had
a real legit way to actually do this
content so it's a really comprehensive
program which gives you a lot of support
and the community is really very helpful
and very welcoming to really anyone from
around the world uh we were part of a
Cort which only had 50 Learners so that
really gave me a lot of confidence boost
like oh wow I'm part of only a group of
50 people who have accepted into this
program from thereafter we also had the
entrepreneurship leadership boot camp
the MIT boot camps which was really very
insightful which started getting me
excited about the whole entrepreneurship
and what it was because we had a team
where we came up with a proposal for a
project which was called unibody uni was
supposed to be an educational platform
for young kids unfortunately that didn't
eventually come to become a real company
but I'd gotten the key principles in
terms of what a company is what a
startup is I then knew for sure I really
wanted to do entrepreneurship and I
really wanted to apply the skills I have
not just to really do a job but really
also to be an entrepreneur so around
that time I needed a job so I started
really writing applications uh when I
had also finished the MIT react program
one very interesting thing that I really
want to note out is uh I kept on
emphasizing it in terms of my
qualifications putting forth all these
various certificates that I had actually
gained and my MIT react qualification
and this is really what got me into the
interview rooms I'll be frank with you I
managed to get a number of interviews
and I eventually landed on a job with
mopa so what mopa is it's a Solar
Company they have a pay as you go model
for retailing a Solar Products and
mobile devices in a period of about 2
months also I went from being a data
entrance to the bi Department which was
really the data backend and the data
analytic sides of the business because
that was the field that I was interested
in which to me really now puts me into
the trajectory of this career in a
technical field in data science field
how do you see yourself now ever since
you started doing ocw courses how has
your identity reflecting on a journey
how are you Jerry as a person do you
feel have changed because of ocw I feel
like ocw has helped me a lot especially
in terms of my career trajectory because
I could literally attribute what I do
now what I the jobs I have done in one
or another they they have a direct link
to uh me having to learn about ocw where
that is through the first initial
programs I took to Simply learn
programming or through the merging
Talent talents program so to me it
really broadened my view about the world
I was living in a confined world of
where I didn't know all these other
things existed around the world so to me
that was really transformational and I
keep saying this to me now I believe if
you ask me who I am I believe I'm a
lifelong learner and that's what ocw
introduced to me being that idea that if
you want to learn anything you can
simply go and look for the content it's
probably there you can go and use online
materials and then you get to learn that
like in my business for example we have
to start doing accounting recently and I
just figured wait I'm not an accountant
I don't have background in accounting
but then there's online content for
accounting so recently I took another
course especially in understanding the
key financial statements for a business
which is the the balance sheets and the
income statement so learning what are
they how they function and all that so
to me that is really the eye opener I
got from ocw that if you want to learn
anything and if you're interested in
anything there's always content that you
can refer to all right Jerry I just want
to give you time to like elevator pitch
your business and like what it's all
about since you got the skills that uh
at your previous role when you were
doing the data
analytics maybe just to lead into that
after I do data analytics for a while I
almost start to get bored of that
because I felt like I am being
underutilized I really wanted to be able
to build my own products and to channel
my own destiny I wanted to do a switch
into software engineering which I
successfully did got a role as a
software engineer which really gave me a
steep learning up because I could
already program now I just needed to
make feel that those last gaps
especially in learning frontend
Technologies javascripts react so when I
did that for a couple of months and I
figured that I was now a bit comfortable
enough again using online resources to
learn how to c how to to myself when I
figured that I would now do that that is
when I decided that I now need to be
able to build my own products I went
back to my old childhood dreams or my
interest in the financial field uh
looking at the financial crisis and all
that Finance seem to be a black field no
one wanted to go into but when you go
back to the basics of Finance it's
really an enabler to help people so to
us really to how do we best help people
and that is when we came up with the
idea of ever Technologies in Uganda uh
the financial sector is still largely
underdeveloped which is true probably
for the rest of subsaharan Africa very
few people have bank accounts and very
few majority of the population is still
unbanked so they're unbanked in the
sense that they do not have access to
the more formal financial institutions
however they are informal financial
institutions which are available in the
country in which they actually able to
bank their money now these are usually
like the Village Bank the local bank now
one of the key challenges to these kinds
of Institutions because they're informal
a lot of their processes and methods are
also very informal for example the
bookkeeping is completely paper
dependent so what we decided to do with
is how are we able to help and digitize
these informal institutions so how we
able to bring in technology to help and
digitize them so what we are simply
trying to do is to digitize these
institutions and bring them into the
formal line with our banking uh cor
banking system and then what we also
looking to move into is to be able to
provide investment opportunities and not
just any investment opportunities but we
necessarily want green investment
opportunities so that people are able to
invest in sustainable businesses using
this platform Investments have
traditionally been inaccessible field
for most people many people have been
scammed many people have lost so much
money because they do not know or they
do not have ways in which they able to
make various Investments because the
clientele of circles ideally wants to
grow so we decided to build up a
platform which can provide for them a
diverse investment opportunities so they
able to one learn about money they learn
about financial literacy but they're not
really stop there but they're able to
take action
[Music]
that was such a cool conversation Jerry
really is a superer from ocw to Imaging
Talent he has taken full advantage of
what MIT has to offer and he's now a
business owner what's your biggest takea
away from the conversation with Jerry
Michael I think for me the biggest
takeaway from talking with Jerry is that
just as his name implies learning and
growing and discovering who you are as
an individual is a very long journey
Jerry
was willing to stand outside and the
Heat or the rain to download courses
that a lot of us that have it freely
available on our phones would never do
and that persistence paid off for Jerry
and I think it became a beautiful
Journey for all of us and I hope his
journey also inspires others to continue
to persist what about you Emanuel yeah I
I feel you the persistence is what also
got to me you know he talks about having
his fast smartphone a Y3 and I
personally have this experience I know
those are not very powerful phones but
goes to show that whoever you are with
whatever resources you have you can
begin from anywhere and you will get to
whatever goal whatever stage thanks to
everyone for tuning into our
conversation with Jerry vuzi of kalala
Uganda don't forget to check out ever
PESA we will put a link in our show
notes and we'll be back in two weeks
with another story from a different
larner in the global ocw
Community open lers is produced by
alexas hot special thanks to the
supporters and donors who make ocw
possible to learn more about mit's Open
courseware and to check out the courses
mentioned in this episode visit the ocw
website at ocw.mit.edu
[Music]