and I'm I'm thrilled to be here with a
fantastic panel where we're going to
continue the
conversation of a lot of the topics that
Ben and Liz put on the table and we're
going to unpack them so first let's just
introduce the panel real quick so you
heard from Ben and Liz and I'm going to
ask them to say just you know one thing
about themselves but first let's start
with Cyrus here introduce yourself and
tell us a little bit about you sure sure
morning everybody my name is Shaul I'm
one of the co-founders and the CEO of
Leela AI uh Leela AI is an MIT spin-off
startup we've been in operation uh since
2019 and we've been selling our solution
to large Enterprises since 2021 and
we're also part of the MIT ILP startup
Exchange program which is uh the sex 25
it's 25 uh industry ready startups
that's part of the MIT ecosystem so
we've been very deeply connected with
the MIT ecosystem from the beginning
um and uh what we do is we have built a
new kind of visual system an AI system
that doesn't use uh directly gen systems
because uh as we saw you know gen
systems can make weird mistakes like how
many letters RS are there in the word
strawberry um when you're in industrial
manufacturing operations contexts you
can't have things make mistakes 20% or
30% of the time that just does not work
so we had to build an ultra reliable
robust Ma Machine Vision system to
understand visually what's going on
operations particularly we focus on
manual operations places where there's
been uh very little data and so uh we've
been able to shine a light and open up
and create data coming out of parts of
manufacturing and Industrial operations
where there was no data and uh it's been
very very interesting over the last few
years I've learned a lot and I love
working with manufacturers and other
industrial Partners I hope we can learn
find a way to work with some of you
today uh so thank you very much awesome
Cyrus thank you Aurora over to you yes
thank you good morning everybody good
morning everybody my name is Aurora
Kennedy and I work for SLB previously
known as Slumber
J and uh so I've been with the company
for 19 years my background is electrical
engineering well in my different roles
I've had roles in supply chain new
product development manufacturing and
what brings me here today with the
future of work is exciting topic is
because in my current role for the
technology organization within SLB which
is over
23,000 uh employees for the technology
only I look after the recruiting so that
is our new talent coming in as well as
the Learning and Development of our
population and that makes it very
exciting for me to be a part of this
conversation both because I have
experienced different layers of work and
because I'm looking out for what our
future Talent will need in terms of
developing and uh delivering the new
technology for tomorrow so I'm excited
to be a part of this discussion super
Aurora thank you now Ben next up to you
we we already got an introduction to you
but just sort of maybe a comment or
another point that you want to add here
at the
beginning sure in a conversation about
work I think uh just to give some
context on my own work I didn't go
straight from college to Academia I went
and worked in Silicon Valley and uh a
lot of my work that I shared today about
manufacturing was motivated by a
particular experience in Silicon Valley
which was that people were very good at
inventing new products you could get a
lot of people who who design them and I
worked U was leading a a small team that
was developing a remote sensing device
so essentially a really cheap cell phone
that could measure water and power um
use and we were trying to prototype it
in the US around California and I
remember just riding my bike to
different you know like little shops and
trying to put together this prototype
and then I I was talking to people and
they're like why are you trying to do
this just call these fixers in China we
can't do this anymore in the US and it
was it was pretty shocking that a lot of
these inventions that were coming out of
this very small area that I was excited
about motivated by they didn't really
have the capability to see those
inventions into reality even in a small
volume and that struck me as a really
big problem that no one was really
talking about as a problem um and that's
one of the reasons why I'm excited to do
what I do today and excited by the work
that Liz does as well that's so
interesting did I hear that right that
in between high school and college you
went to siloc and Valley for a job or
was it in between grad no College uh
college was after college yeah after
college he was bright but not that I
wish he were I wish you were high school
that would be that would be
nice that's really cool Liz quick story
uh okay well if we're going if we're
going to look backwards a little bit um
I will just share that I am from
Manchester New Hampshire which if uh
anybody knows their uh textile mill
history was was the largest textile
mills at about the early part of the
1900s and um employed uh close to
177,000 workers and of course um like
the Mills around the country uh the the
Manchester Mills amamos Mills along the
river went into decline uh and starting
essentially in the 30s and 40s uh and
then we're shuddering when I was growing
up there uh my my uh shoes were no
longer made in New England they were
made in China but the exciting part of
the story that I feel is uh you know
represents where we are where I
personally am and where I think the
country is is we've seen these Mills
come back and the arguably the center
for um in Innovation and Manufacturing
in regenerative medicine is now in the
amamos Mills um in in Manchester New
Hampshire and uh and one of our centers
uh is there and I see that as sort of a
a a foreshadowing of what we can imagine
in the country again with technology
where we are leading the way as a
country and and hopefully not just um
reshoring which I there's a lot of hype
around reshoring and and it is real but
it is not going to turn around this
country it's really in the investing in
the new Industries and the growing areas
where we have competitive Advantage
awesome okay so I'm going to bring this
back to then Aurora and and Cyrus who I
want to I want them to comment on sort
of Workforce bits I want to ask the AV
guys back there if you could set my
clock here to 40 minutes and then start
it that will help us sort of just be
able to Pace ourselves all right now
Aurora so I I think that we got some
sort of opening comments on the table
around sort of what are the most
important issues around Workforce being
at SB for 19 years which a I think that
is so impressive and in in different
these days
talk to us about some of a key thing
that you think sort of driving Workforce
change now so I think one of the big
things driving Workforce change
especially what I see in SLV we have a a
continued learning but one of the things
that we see is uh adoption is a big um a
hurdle right so we heard from from Liz
and we heard from Ben about how some
people are resistance to the change so
really it's a it's a human factor to be
resistant to change to be be afraid of
things that are different and I think
one of the things that we do at SLB is
we try to make sure that we get
comfortable with the uncomfortable we
have uh been we we call it living our
culture and exploring our behaviors one
of our behaviors is we experiment learn
and grow and I think having that
vocabulary spread across the
organization gives us a little bit of
permission to say hey look we're going
to try things out we're going to see how
they work we don't take unnecessary risk
or changes but we are open to the
possibility and I think that's one of
the things that I like about being here
is seeing the different ways that our
Workforce can change not only in our
skills but in the way we take in what's
new specifically we also have strategic
targets for upskilling so we started
doing this way back but more focused in
2022 with employee any employee can pick
on three scales and these are part of
the objectives which is either
sustainability on um digit
or it could be on the production itself
so we keep that fostering the
growth awesome okay so that's a really
interesting model within a large
organization Cyrus as as someone
founding and running a startup how do
you think about
Workforce yeah it's interesting how
different it is sometimes from big uh
multinational corporations and small
startups uh we we have to be very um
flexible and everybody has to be
multi-roll in in in a startup and I see
that now also happening a little bit in
our customers as well which are giant
customers uh you know hundreds of
thousands of employees but they're also
embracing this idea of uh having people
have many different roles at the same
time maybe maybe two or three we we we
have like 10 because we're tiny but I
think that's a big Trend that I'm
noticing uh that's it's sort of the
startup psychology leaking into
Enterprise uh a little bit yeah yeah oh
no that's interesting um okay so now Liz
I want to bring it over to you and talk
about reskilling and continuous
education you brought that up a bit um
in your talk earlier but thinking
about um Workforce transformation and
how do we scale efforts around that some
of the insights you got from work of the
future
uh well as as I said before we had a um
multi-year effort with work of the
future task force um and we had a whole
range of um MIT expertise brought to the
table uh and one of the realities that
we you know were confronting back then
and today as has been outlined is this
issue of the long-term trends on um work
on the on the workforce population and
the Aging aging Workforce lower
fertility rates uh some constrictions on
on immigration all of those factors
coming into play as we look ahead at our
Workforce and so the idea that workers
uh were you know are dispensable just
has is out the window right everybody's
trying to retain their workers um and
increase productivity and so what that
means is you have to upskill you have to
think about how you're going to get more
you know more time and and retain uh
retain the workers you have let alone
attract the next gener ation so what
work like Ben's work and others have
shown as I said earlier is that by
investing in the workers and I think
creating us a level of trust about ad
technology adoption there's a path
forward for upskilling and when
companies are investing in new
technology they invest in the training
of their Workforce so I think the the
the the question has been well what does
this mean for in the operation space you
know the digital
uh transformation and and how accessible
is that for you know existing the
existing Workforce relative to the force
and what what we found in our research
for production in The Innovation economy
is we would go out and talk to the large
firms and say well what do you want in
your Workforce and they'd say well we
want the grounded technical skills of
the older workers combined with the
Savvy with new technology and you know
interfaces that are of the younger
worker so how do we create that pathway
forward and of course that is a a
challenging pathway but it it shows the
value of that whole spectrum of workers
that we need the you know we need the
grounded skills uh of what the older
workers have seen and understand in
terms of operations combined with the
newer skills the digital skills I think
what's happening with technology uh
right now is that the digital technology
is meeting the worker where they are
yeah right that is we're not asking
workers necessarily to learn skills that
they can't obtain or that require you
know very uh significant long-term
investment we're trying to bring a lot
of this new technology is and Cyrus can
talk about this is is bringing sort of
democratizing the technology and
allowing workers to have access to it
and then actually use it as a tool
because as soon as they feel like
they're problem solving that they're
part of the the answer uh that
technology then becomes empowering for
them so I see that pathway forward right
now uh and the question is the adoption
which I I know others we were talking
about in in the break and and Ben Ben
had comments as well Ben may want to
follow up on that absolutely and I think
Aurora put that adoption on the table
Ben you had some great studies about
this pick up the ball um so adoption of
new technologies across Industries
actually is there's a a long tale of
small companies in particular that are
very slow to adopt new technologies and
take risk on investing in Technologies
particularly those without a clear
return so you'll have some some leaders
a small group of maybe you know 5% of
overall companies that are early to
adopt new technologies and then a l a
large group of uh smaller comp a large
group of companies smaller in size that
are followers and I think that the key
to driving up adoption in the sense that
we want adoption because adoption not
only can improve productivity but it
also is associated with higher wage jobs
in a lot of cases um is to help these
companies take uh either prove to them
that there is a clear Roi associated
with the technology or to drisk the
decision to adopt a new technology so I
think one um industry that has uh been
uh you know a good case for this is
additive manufacturing where a lot of
Manufacturers have been uh able to
experiment with additive by uh having a
low cost 3D printer where they can
prototype some parts or at least get
accustomed to what part production with
additive looks like now the scale up of
additive has been the challenge not the
early adoption whereas with robot uh
with robots it's actually the first
robot that is typically really hard
because you can't necessarily just roll
up a robot and um and have it you know
pick apart just like you be able to roll
in a printer and and make your first
prototype like a little toy or whatever
um would would come pre-programmed so
one of the challenges and one thing we
work on with with technology providers
is how to make that first experience
with the technology positive quicker and
lower cost for a customer um this is
quite separate from The scaleup
Challenge one one piece that I wanted to
note which you mentioned with Workforce
Development there's this real pickle
with um with Workforce Development
organizations in the US because I think
community colleges for a long time
really since the 1960s in the US have
been set up as really a jumping off
point for four years universities their
main um a lot of their funding comes
from how many students do you send to a
four-year college or university and
there's been less funding in
Massachusetts for example there just
isn't much funding at all if you find
someone a good job after your two-year
degree those aren't the incentives for
our community college in some cases our
vocational system so what would it take
to really shift that I think that uh
there are a few models for how this
might be done better one is in South
Carolina where BMW's investment South
Carolina in the early 1990s was hugely
INF influential in Shifting the course
of the South Carolina technical college
system that BMW comes in South Carolina
along with a number of other states
including Tennessee is all bidding for
this big BMW Factory and BMW says one of
the key components that we're going to
need wherever we invest is Workforce
Development this is something that we
have in Germany and we we realize that a
lot of these places in the early 90s
just didn't have a huge uh group of
skilled Automotive workers sitting
around waiting to to join BMW so the
South Carolina technical college system
to their credit said okay well we can
provide that we'll be open to
experimenting with you into providing
the skilled workers that you need so
when BMW moved in they brought the heads
of the technical college system in South
Carolina to Germany to study how the
baru schulen do it in and train
Automotive workers in Germany and they
brought some of those principles back to
South Carolina they set up an
apprenticeship system that wasn't just
for BMW but was for all the you know
suppliers and related companies and
extended Beyond Automotive such that now
um South Carolina went from one of the
lowest productivity States in
manufacturing and before BMW arrived to
one of the highest productivity States
and actually comparatively High wage
state today so I think that is you know
just a state level model that could be
replicated Y no that's awesome and
actually at MIT open learning I run a
learning platform called MIT Horizon uh
and we have a sister organization MIT
expro we work with BMW and and helping
like create across the entire
organization
AI education and we also work with SLB
and Aurora's organization um and
addressing I think uh this gentleman's
question earlier about the
transformation of the education system
because really we need to think about it
as a pipeline and how do we need to
rethink that with the work that we're in
now at
MIT um at up in learning we've created
something called agile continuous
education that is sort of a framework
around how how to think about that in a
new way I'd love to talk to you about
that more later if you'd like um and
then we're just starting a new
initiative around how do we think about
upscaling around Ai and uh we're going
to be working with community colleges in
numerous States um that Ben that's
really interesting to connect a DOT with
that work in in the Carolinas um we're
going to be working with Michigan uh
Georgia and Massachusetts to start and
so I think that there's a lot of there's
a lot of recognition around the need of
the transformation of uh the whole
Paradigm where it's no longer that you
go to school work and retire but that
that there's a whole shift around that
that we need to change the culture Liz
do you want to yeah I was just going to
say I think that speaks to the strength
of the US system the US system is got a
lot of experimentation and a lot of
places for on and off RS right as
opposed to the European model right but
the European model actually takes people
right across these you know these chasms
which is which is problematic so we have
to you know we lean into the strengths
of the system but we need to reinforce
it with uh some of these programs and
things that we we've been talking about
absolutely Aurora I want to come to you
and talk about culture change within an
organization like that that resistance a
lot of times like has talked a lot about
policy change and we sort of put policy
change into place at Academia we try to
build great systems and different things
but a lot of the challenge is within
organizations how do you change the
culture yes no absolutely and I think we
we went through a big culture Shi when
we first rebranded and that helped us a
lot because not only were we refocusing
what the company was all about but we
were bringing forward key behaviors and
EST in that um how can you say the same
language right to make that level of
psychological safety because one of the
reasons why uh one of the reasons why we
are afraid of change is because things
are different and we also have the
mentality of it can't change right it's
been like this for years it's working
now why mess with it so I think we're
we're having to get everybody involved
and say hey we're looking for better
ways to equip you better ways to do the
work so that you have a more impactful
everybody wants to have meaningful work
everybody wants to make an impact
regardless of where they are in the
organization and I think we're working
to have that culture shift with words
and saying we want you to be impactful
in what your job is what your day-to-day
job is what do you see that can make you
impactful and it does take time to build
some trust but I think it's through
examples and saying hey look at what we
did together and how did it change how
you do the work we still have of course
people that don't join in but we focus
on the Agents of change the people that
get interested in experimenting like the
example you gave with Sam he was
interested in doing things different so
we focus on those and we hope that the
rest will see the impact and
benefit awesome cus anything that you're
bringing into your organization yeah um
you know we have a challenge we're a new
company with new kind of a new whole new
category of Technology right AI for
manual operations and Manufacturing and
so when we first started talking to
customers there was this great uh
resistance fear of change um I was in
many meetings with uh a room of maybe 10
or 20 people all scowling at me and uh
these were the shop stewards Union reps
and they said you're here to take our
jobs away or you're here to make it uh
easier to fire people because you have
all this great data now on AI so we had
a big up uphill battle in the beginning
uh going out there and uh changing how
people think about AI in the workplace
um and luckily we're able to find some
solutions to those ways of managing
cultural change right um and just give
you a couple of solutions that we
discovered one um I think really make an
effort to find the benefits for all
stakeholders y that's one thing that uh
you know if if it only benefits one
group of stakeholders and doesn't
benefit the others may not harm them but
it doesn't benefit them then adoption is
very slow so that was one big lesson
right
away one thing that's interesting about
that where they're worried about getting
fired because the more data yeah that
they they must inherently think that
they're poor performers which it kind of
clicked because the story of you know
Colin Cuts in Ohio that I shared one of
the things that enables Colin to pay his
workers so much is he's able to look at
their performance and he gives them
bonuses for productivity increases so
they have a a Target and if they exceed
the Target and automation is helping
them do that they get a proportion of
the earnings over that Target and I've
talked to a bunch of other companies and
say like well do you have any incentive
programs well we tried something but the
workers resisted why would the workers
resist an incentive program and it's
must because they they're worried that
low performance would be a hindrance
versus good performance leading to
bonuses so yeah we we did this in the
survey I talked about we had two ideas
that might help workers be more open one
was um and this is coming out of a lot
of work in in the Sloan school at MIT is
that that if you they had more voice if
they were able to share more of their
ideas and opinions about how to deploy a
technology maybe they would be more open
they feel more ownership the second was
exactly like Financial incentives like
maybe if you were measure that you got
you were more productive you could pay
so we set up this experiment where we
gave some workers we said there's this
new technology introduced you just have
to live with it some you get to like
shape how it's you get to provide voice
then the third was you have to live with
it but if you improve your performance
you get a bonus and the worker voice and
that you just have to live with it were
exactly the same workers weren't more
open to the technology they treated it
the same way but then the financial
incentives it was off the charts they
thought it was much better and not just
for their pay but also for their job
security and their kind of satisfaction
with it so it did it did kind of lead us
to question some of this idea that
workers just want ownership uh in theory
whereas in practice they they want to
get paid and it makes sense yeah yeah it
really does so I think uh you know
talking whether it's Union shops or
non-union shops talking about how uh
monthly targets are going to get hit
more often right and the other side of
that is that um a lot of times the
reason monthly targets aren't hit is out
of the hands of the front line people
are not lazy they're working their asses
off and they're doing hard hard dirty
jobs sometimes so you know when when
when the company as a whole misses
targets you know there's a lot of blame
going around and so how to figure out
what is the root cause of us missing our
performance targets every month
and sometimes the root cause was really
hard to find it's really hard without
good data especially on uh the data poor
parts of the factory like the manual
parts so what came out of a lot of
discussions with Frontline people that
we Frontline workers that we talked to
they said I've been telling my boss for
10 years there's a better way to do this
it says bass Awards you got to do it
this way but no one ever listens to me
and uh so when we put our system in this
AI that can understand work and then
everyone could see the data they the and
everyone saw the data this is the
democratization it's not like there's
three people who get to see this new
data and then there's 100 people who
don't we we try so hard to get our
customers to understand that there's no
extra cost give every employee access to
this data you just give them a password
they can log in and see the the cycle
times you can see the non-value ad time
so when that happens when the doors open
everybody some very very intelligent
people who are working all day
assembling things see this data they say
look I just did this without anybody
knowing I did it right yesterday and
look at yesterday's data look how we got
20% more output so this kind of flips
the script and creates a new kind of
symmetry where there was some asymmetry
before and that creates uh so many other
KnockOn effects better safety uh better
uh retention um shorter training times
because you can use all this AI data to
help improve training there's all sorts
of other benefits that come along but
the cultural shift has to happen first
it has to be the right kind of cultural
change
uh it's also a change last thing I'll
say is an ownership you know who owns
this problem is it the ship supervisor
is it the uh coo the plant manager or is
it everybody and unless everybody knows
the problems and can really see how to
fix them and do their own root cause
thinking it's never everybody's problem
unless you can do that so that's the
transformation we're seeing with this
data flowing and and everybody thinking
about things differently suddenly
everybody owns a problem and then
everybody can work towards a solution so
that has been a real interesting trans
information we've noticed within our
customers by doing this yeah I would
just add on that one you know everyone
owning the problem um that's at the
heart of continuous Improvement right is
that everybody sees that and so I think
we need to see this almost as an
evolution of the whole you know lean
movement is now you know we have uh
augmented lean as a concept and you know
what is the digital overlay on that and
so building that into the into the
culture is really important and I I've
been in dialogue with a um head of
manufacturing for a large multinational
Life Sciences company and talk about
culture this this guy's ex-marine he is
not messing around 20 years he's been
running operations for this you know
International life science company and
he just has not been able to crack the
code on how to get his quality people to
you know facilitate a little bit more
efficiency in the system because of
course they you know under a regulated
system FDA is checking on your uh GMP
you know all of this um but he has this
idea of buying from the top buying from
the sea Suite is so essential right you
can do a top bottom up and a top down
but you you can't but really I don't
think you can really make the progress
without the top down buyin and um so to
watch him you know just bring his Marine
skill set into the into his operation to
bring along the certainly the quality
people to understand that you don't need
to have a require M for every single
step of the process there are things we
can do to bring in digital to make this
more efficient that people's jobs are
not at at risk I think has been
fascinating to me to you know an eye
opening about exactly the how of this
within organizations
super I want to take do a speed round
like to bring up the pace first I'm
going to ask a question of the audience
I'm very curious how many of you are
using
generative AI in your
work like majority how many of you use
it every
day quite as many and how many of you
using it because it's mandated by your
work ah interesting you're using it
personally because you're adopting tools
that's really interesting okay so the
speed round the first one we're going to
do is what is the most important skill
for the workforce of the future what do
they need to know Liz you want to take
that first uh I'm I'm going to say you
know flexibility flexibility excellent
Ben openness uh interpreting data
interpreting data okay curiosity
open-minded
yes I'm going to say
grit oh we just made an excellent
employee I think with all of those with
all of those pieces excellent anyone
want to shout out something what what
what are other skills that you think are
really important
yes D
yeah
yeah yeah
okay
yeah it's fine I think we're just we're
just sort of shouting out because I'm
going back to next speed round and
cyberus will go with you is what's the
one major
misconception about work of the future
and what that's going to be like do I
get one sentence or you get you you get
you get 15 seconds oh 15 seconds okay um
I think the major misconception is that
uh humans are replaceable ah um there
are I think if you think about it in a
big big picture certain things that will
not technically be uh replaceable with
software or robots in our lifetimes so
let's just think about our lifetimes
right and maybe our kids lifetimes um I
think there's a lot of uh dubious
information out there projecting uh you
know all this technology uh being human
grade or humanik and uh even I'm an AI
practitioner I sell AI software I see on
the inside how slow and difficult things
are so I think there's a a definite
misconception that um the flexibility
and the dexterity and the social
cognition of humans is going to be
replaceable in in in the next two
lifetimes I don't think it is all right
good good to know happy about that one
or so for me misconception is where the
where this technology can be applied I
think sometimes we Overlook some of the
areas that could widely benefit from the
new technology I mean we HR could
benefit from it right uh mult legal can
benefit from it I know we focus on the
new and shiny Technologies for solving
the big problems that we see but there's
a lot of hidden opportunities and I
think
demystifying the technology for
everybody a big believer and stem but I
think there's a lot of other fields
where this can be really lifechanging so
where we apply it needs to open
I think you know looking at short-term
productivity as the main uh objective I
think is a is a misconception and I I
think about long-term skill atrophy as a
big risk of new technology and you know
uh I think you we've all seen it maybe
in our own experiences with AI over the
last 10 years and adopting things like
Google Maps and ways and our ability to
navigate the world on our own um I just
uh think about my my mother-in-law who
is is relatively anti-technology ology
but when her Google Maps went down
trying to drive to New York she had to
pull off and you know go to a gas
station and get directions and it's like
you know it's it's one highway it's all
the way to New York but um I do think
that that we've we've undervalued the
challenges of of skill atrophy in
software community and the these
trade-offs that typically come with with
adopting new technologies the other
comment I'll make is um you know we've
also had now going on 15 20 years of
screens in the classroom and
digitization of educ
and test scores in the United States
have not improved so this idea that you
know technology can make us smarter can
improve um education it hasn't on the
maybe we're measuring it wrong but it
hasn't on the measures that we care
about so um I think we need to look
ourselves in the mirror about how we
educate our our children and what skills
we're developing um if we want them to
thrive in this environment maybe the
tools of the work environment might not
be the best tools for the
classroom um so first I just would um
reiterate or underscore what Cyrus said
about humans in the loop I think that'
be a really interesting discussion with
this group right there's a there's a
voice out there that says we're we're
all heading toward the lights out
Factory and I think there's a a big
question mark about what that looks like
and as we um used to say in one of our
uh projects in MIT you can't innovate in
a lights out Factory and so you know
where is that really heading what what
kind of production will that speak to
versus other production but the the
point I would make on on myth is that is
that somehow this um the the sort of
transformation on the skill set is
really we need to really focus on shop
floor in fact when we spoke to
organizations they say the problem is as
much you know with management and with
our Engineers as it is with the
Frontline worker and that this approach
to changing you know toward a digital um
production system is really a culture
that is goes from top to bottom of an
organization
culture the word okay I've got a lot of
questions but I also want to hear from
you so we've got the mics here and
question
here I'm uh thas Gonzalez I work with
Baker Hughes but I'm an MIT Alum uh
quick plug on Manchester you have one of
the best exports for the world it's
called first oh yes so if you haven't
heard about first robotics gracious
professionalism and coor petition that's
a really good thing to research uh also
open course Weare and edex or we're part
of MIT is there going to be a curriculum
design about the workforce of the future
there well there is right now an
offering from uh Tom Cen um you were you
participating that you you did it with
Tom I I yes I you well so there is you
know it turns out of course this is a
topic for uh you know doesn't matter
where you're coming from this is an
interesting topic so we did actually
translate the work of the future task
Force into an online course uh that Tom
Cen who is now a Meritus from Sloan uh
set up um and I and so people have
access to that but I would also say um
there's a lot going on in the
manufacturing space that that also that
Ben can talk about in terms of specific
skills but all broader skills around
industrial transformation is that fair
to say Ben yeah I think the one kind
this is you know very early stages but
one comment that has stuck with me from
a really you know we've been trying to
study these high performing
manufacturers and look at them as models
of you know they're double the national
level of productivity how would you
replicate them and one had this really
interesting comment about the workers he
was looking for because he had found
these terrific multi-talented people to
work on the shop floor and he said
really what we need is we need kind of
like the MIT of vocational schools or
the Carnegie melon of educational the
Stanford yeah and and what we have is
really a flat um you know not
necessarily centers of excellence for
vocational training so I think there
there's some going to be some
experimentation and work with that of
how we can take MIT curriculum that's
currently directed toward graduate level
engineers and bring them towards someone
who might have 10 to 15 years on the
shop floor and is ready to take the next
step but perhaps also the U of
Excellence of Excellence yeah in the
Texas A&M I know Texas A&M over there
hi um my name is O I work with Chevron I
have a question around nomadic talent
talent particularly with the younger
generation in which people don't stay
longer in positions or in jobs anymore
they hop two three years two three years
two three years it it's significantly
disruptive when it comes to building
deep
skills and it's also maybe I'm dating
myself is also reflective of not being
connected with the misss of whatever
Enterprise or industry they're in and so
it's a case of yeah I do this for a
couple of weeks and I'm gone and so
thoughts around
that W to I want to say something
because uh and CH yes so SLV you know we
I've had many different jobs so I've
been with them 19 years but I've had so
many different jobs it's not uncommon
for me to change job every two three
years we're actually looking to see how
to slow that down so what we see with
the new Talent we tell them you don't
have to leave you want to do something
different look at the wide range this is
something that a company can offer I've
never gotten bored of a job like just
when I feel comfortable they change it
on me so I think that's one of the
things they leave because they want a
new challenge they want to do something
different I think not everybody perhaps
in the new generations wants that but
the ones I do they want the variety and
I think large organizations can look and
see within themselves can we offer the
variety inside before the candidate or
employee comes and says hey I want to do
something different you can say hey like
maybe you have a limited space where you
can move them but I think it's important
for organizations to look and see also
how they can change inside to let's say
Foster the need for change that the new
generation is bringing maybe they're
just wanting to do things differently so
how can we Foster them within large
organizations to allow them to do that
at I think it's a good question to have
versus trying to fix a generation right
each generation feels they have the
answer to everything so I think we just
need to focus on how we can work cross
generation I want to ask the audience a
question and then I see that question
over there how many of you have been in
the same organization for 10
years okay how about
15 20
interesting wow okay yeah um I think
there's a question over here and then if
we can get the mic over
there hello um my name is Le Yar and I'm
a freshman at Texas A&M I'm studying
mechanical engineering and my ultimate
goal is to be a Serial Tech entrepreneur
like Elon Musk I have a question for you
Mr uh Cyrus um one thing that you said
to me that stood out was that uh you
want to benefit all stakeholders whether
it's with the software or is with the
policies and I was wondering if that's
unrealistic um I don't think it is I
don't think it is uh but I do get that a
lot um this idea that uh it's a zero sum
game so if um you know the engineers who
are doing design have a better
technology to help them Design Systems
better well that's going to make the
assembly harder and so the assembly team
will lose or something crazy like that
you know more often it's the idea that
um there's G be big brother watching the
the sort of the the the teams that are
actually doing the work and the
management will have this data set and
then use it to punish people or to uh do
other things that that maybe not so
kosher so you know that that that that
that's something that that we worried
about a lot in the beginning and so
we've tried to make our product built so
that it's hard to do those things so for
example we do a lot of stuff to protect
privacy by blurring video so that you
can't see who's who or by deleting video
so that the data is there but the video
isn't so we've tried to make it harder
and harder to um use this tool in ways
that don't benefit all or that benefit
only a couple of stakeholders so it is
always a challenge but um it's something
that I think you know if you use tools
like AI tools incorrectly you can
destroy your culture and maybe even
destroy your company if you use them
well then you can really uh see that
kind of Big Boost uh and be of course I
think better than the competition like
how does America come back against Asia
right right now talk about the global uh
manufacturing situation uh we have
reshoring going on we have near Shoring
going on in Mexico we have uh a
potential trade war with uh China and
other parts of the world so thinking
about it like that um you know the US is
seeing a lot of great news stories in
the last few years in the manufacturing
sector that could flip around and things
could go right back
to Asia again depending on the way the
wind blows so to make a globally
competitive us manufacturing sector long
term there has to be something that sets
us apart that makes American
manufacturing better and different than
every place around the world to me it's
this uh adoption of better technology
and doing things in a very very smart
way so that even though we pay our
workers 10 times more than somebody in
another country they're 10 or 20 times
more productive so to benefit all s
holders using the best technology and
bringing America to the place where it
can continue to compete for the next
many years on the world stage that's the
way to do it and I think the only way to
do it the only way out of this hole is
better use of technology and uh and
really focusing on productivity I don't
know what do you think Elizabeth yeah I
I mean I agree I think the the point is
we have to do it differently you're not
reshoring from China you know with the
same productive production systems
you're doing it differently and that's
where use of the advanced Manufacturing
Technologies really plays to our
advantage and so that's you know that's
what the game is I think going forward
across all of these areas that we care
about uh from a national and economic
security point of view but also where
you know growth is happening where
Ventures investing you know the that
people see this opportunity and see
where the US you know can um can have a
competitive Advantage y last question um
my name is basil fared uh I'm coming
from software engineering AI background
uh I think this gentleman's question uh
from shevron I don't think it was
addressed in my view I think the way I
understood the question was that in the
backdrop of the H example for example
you know operating complex machine uh
that tendency on the mindset is lost in
the new generation so I think the
question was addressing how can the
companies keep people uh in in that same
profession for a longer period of time
rather than just shifting the roles
because then they're not developing
deepest skills so maybe you can
elaborate on that a few thoughts so one
I don't think that the goal is no
turnover right no turnover is actually
not a good solution you want actually
people with new ideas coming in from
competitors from adjacent Industries Etc
I think just to go to the Elon Musk and
Tesla example one of the really
brilliant things about Tesla was that
they brought in people not just from The
Usual Suspects the Toyotas the GMS but
they also brought in people from the
semiconductor industry and people from
the chemicals industry and then of
course all sorts of software Engineers
from you know Apple and Google that that
brought different sorts of ideas they
had to develop a Common Language and
really a new way of of producing a a car
so so in that case the new ideas from
outside were really valuable but then
the next question is how do you stay at
a place long enough to really gain those
valuable skills that you could bring to
another location I think this is I would
point you to some of zup Ton's work um
at at MIT where she she initially wrote
a book called you know the good jobs
strategy which was all about how
companies I think the threat in her work
is that that corporations can be
systematically irrational irrational and
predictable ways that sometimes they
offer irrationally low wages because
just that they raise those wages they
see productivity gains in their workers
that you know out value the increase in
wages so they actually become more
profitable while increasing wages she
studied this at in retail and fast food
which I think is a remarkable finding
and then more recently she studied how
uh firms they undervalue the cost of
turnover so really what what you're
suggesting is that firms have been
unwilling to raise wages enough or to
offer enough incentives to keep workers
such that they're then spending more on
replacing them than they could have
spent on just keeping them there or
offering them a a career ladder um to
keep them so I think this is really just
an irrational Behavior where we've
allowed High turnover to persist in part
because we've been unwilling to offer
wages bonuses other
incentives just an anecdote to that that
this is a real issue that the Department
of Defense is looking at right that the
defense uh you know and the services
have a rotation systematic rotation for
everybody and that ultimately that's
actually not helping our deeper skill
set and our ability to sort of see
Innovations or you know new production
systems over a longer period of time so
there's there's discussion about how to
change
that horrific
so we are coming to a close final
question and we'll do it
quickly we're back together in five
years it's been a long five years um
what do you hope that we'll be talking
about Cyrus kick us off I think we're
talking about um how the promise of AI
came true but also did not come true and
and how that worked out I'm interested
in singing okay F in the blanks I would
like to see us talking more about cross
collaboration
across Industries how we can foster
because I think there's a lot of benefit
even like with Academia and Industry how
can we benefit from the crossroads in
between the silos so I want to hear us
talk about more collaboration to keep
advancing on the newer technology that
will be here in five years Ben I'd love
to see more uh experiments more you know
risk-taking and positive examples I
don't think A lot's going to change in
in five years uh or a lot can change on
kind of the technology front but um I
think a lot more uh you know momentum
with the experiments would be good I
would love us to be talking about how we
have energized the Next Generation to
enter into career paths in manufacturing
and that we've done it by expanding into
non-traditional communities or you know
areas where we haven't had as much
representation um and we see really
exciting new Pathways to kind of the
middle class um through through these
manufacturing awesome I hope you enjoyed
in 5 years but than that we're going to
move on to our next sess so thank you
panel