it's a great great pleasure to uh to
have salil vadan speaking to us today um
salil was one of our own he was a
graduate student at MIT and once one of
our own always one of our own um he's
now a professor of computer science and
Applied Mathematics uh down the road at
Harvard um and seil has worked on a
range of topics uh you know starting
with uh photography uh zor knowledge
proofs he really kind of um you know
gave shape to the notion of uh
statistical zero knowledge um uh he then
moved on to complexity Theory um where
he constructed his construction of
expander graphs is is a classic uh he
won the gel price for it with uh Omar
rold and AI werson um then he moved on
to uh studying Randomness in computer
science and der randomization uh and so
forth and most recently his fashion is
differential privacy uh he's been
leading the open DP project uh at
Harvard um so uh and and and his talk
will be on yet another facet of computer
science uh so welcome s welcome back
thank
you uh thank you venod for the very
generous introduction it's um yeah one
always wonderful to have an excuse to
come back to MIT and now in this
beautiful new building uh you know
you're getting old when the place where
you did a PhD has changed buildings
twice uh
since um the time so I was a graduate
student in lcf yes U
PRI um and uh yeah about um what I'll be
talking about um it's actually a
collection of topics that uh haven't
been a focus of mine for a long time uh
so multic calibration is something that
has come out of the algorithmic fairness
literature um which is not really an
area um that I work on U but just kind
of follow uh from a distance and then as
ven know IND ated uh I used to work a
lot on cryptography it's been a while um
but thanks to a wonderful undergraduate
Sylvia coberta who um decided to do her
senior thesis with um Cynthia dwar my
colleague at Harvard and and me and
Cynthia as an expert on on fairness um
uh we got I got back into this and we
realized connections between multic
calibration and things that I was very
interested in uh 10 years ago and got me
excited and uh that's what this uh talk
uh will be telling you about and uh in
many ways uh this talk and this work uh
I think of as a tribute to um uh dear uh
friend and longtime collaborator Luca
travison who was um uh tragically and
suddenly taken away from us by cancer uh
last year and as you'll see uh hopefully
I'll convey in the talk I think uh some
of kind of what what we be doing with
somehow trying to realize a vision that
uh Luca had um uh a while
back okay so uh let me begin it's very
much on the foundations side this talk
but I've added some things in the
beginning um to uh kind of at least
convey for those who are on the more
applied side of
cryptography security why we why we
might be interested in these kinds of
questions and why they might be useful
right and so I want to convey how this
concept um from algorithmic fairness
multic calibration uh actually is also a
powerful new tool for security proofs
and
cryptography okay in a short summary the
the way in which it um is such a tool is
that uh it enables Us in some maybe many
cases and hopefully you'll find more to
derive computational security proofs
from information theoretic security
proofs and information theoretic
security proofs are uh typically much
easier and then a lot of the hard work
of getting a computational security
proof is then done by multi
calibration okay and so I'm going to
start to talk with some older examples
of contrasting computational and
information theoretic security proofs
and earlier cases of kind of how we knew
to
obtain a computational security proof
kind of somehow by reduction to an
information theoretic
one um so let's start with a kind of
very old question in the foundations of
cryptography uh and in complexity theory
is the hardness amplification question
all right so I'm given a function uh
let's potentially allow to be a
randomized Boolean function so G from n
Bits to one bit that's slightly hard on
average and I'll be a little more
precise about that in a moment
um how do we construct a harder Boolean
function from it okay and so like one
example might be you know you have a
one-way function and the function G of X
is you you invert the oneway function on
X and you take some bit of the input and
uh all right so if if this is a what's
called a hardcore bit of the oneway
function then little G is already very
harder than average but um often
individual bits of uh the pre-image
oneway function are not necessarily
hardcore full fledged hardcore bits but
might only be uh somewhat weakly Harden
average and kind of motivated in fact by
that particular example uh Yao gave a
method back in 1982 called the uh
captured by Yao's exhort Lemma for doing
this all right so first let's say to
State ya X Orma more precise what do I
mean by slightly hard on average we mean
for all efficient algorithms a all
polinomial time algorithms if I uh now
here capital x is a um a random
input think you can think of it as
uniform on on strings of length n it can
be other another distribution any other
fixed distribution as well um any
efficient algorithm will compute G will
uh with at most you know probability
bounded away from one so it'll error
with probability at least Delta uh in
Computing G right and sometimes we'll
use the language G as Delta hard uh for
that okay so think of Delta you know 0.1
or even you know one over n or something
like that and then what Yao said well
one way we can obtain a very harder on
average function is to ask our adversary
instead to compute the exor of G on many
independent inputs X1 to XK okay so each
of these XIs are um
drawn uh from the same distribution as X
but independently okay and then Yao's
exor Lemma tells you that the um success
probability of efficient algorithms uh
uh tends to a half as you increase K and
it tends to half exponentially fast in K
and then there's some kind of negligible
additive term all right and so our new
function here is a function on K * n
Bits um uh you know that that computes
the xor on those K IND uh K
inputs okay so let's um first look at
the information theoretic version of Yao
xor LMA and see why it's like very easy
to prove it's two lines um the proof I
won't give all the
details um one way so what do I mean by
the information theoretic version I mean
let's remove the polytime constraint in
both the Assumption and the conclusion
we say for every a the probability you
compute G is bounded away from one so
for this to make sense G can't actually
be a deterministic
function because if you have unbounded
computing power and G of X is determined
by X then given X you can compute with
probability one so here it's really
important that we think of randomized uh
functions okay and the randomness of the
function is the only source of hardness
here all right so then you can actually
just write a simple formula for the
maximum success probability of any
efficient algorithm right it's going to
one expression for it um that's very
convenient is for proving the xrm is a
half plus a halftimes this quantity
here um it's the expectation over
inputs of of an expression here that's
the bias of g g remember is a randomized
function on that input X all right and
so um you can write in this form
expectation over the randomness of G of
negative -1 to the G ofx what this is
just doing is taking the absolute value
of the of the probability that g is one
on X and the probability that g is zero
on x
okay so if G is determined G of X is
determined by X this quantity is one if
it's a coin toss it's it's it's uh uh
it's
zero okay and then we just observe if
you look at -1 to G of X1 plus X or G of
X2 and so on um that just becomes a
product of of negative 1 to the G of XI
for the different XIs and then you just
do a little algebra and you get exactly
this exponential decay that we wrote
here really um easy proof uh once you
kind of have the right figure out the
right expression to work
with um but now a computational version
um uh not so obvious to prove um like if
you haven't seen a proof before you
probably stumble around for a while um
before finding one um ya uh as far as
know didn't actually write down a proof
of this um there's a nice survey of gold
Nissan and vigoron from uh little more
than 10 a decade later which gave
several different proofs of ya xor Lemma
um each each a few pages and that's
untrivial um but the one that I want to
focus on is the one that uses imp
palat's hardcore LMA since that will
play play a role later in the talk and
also illustrates this idea of reducing
computational security proofs to
information theoretic ones um okay and
um what the hardcore Lema says is that
if a function is Delta
hard then there's some subset of the
domain some sub hardcore set
H um on which it's really
hard okay so um specifically the subset
of the domain that its size its density
in in in the full domain is related to
the of G it's actually of density to
Delta um imp palat's original hardcore
LMA had just a Delta here this correct
version um is due to hollenstein with
the factor of two and on this set H what
do we mean that g is really hard um I
mean that it's indistinguishable from a
from a random coin toss an unbiased coin
toss all right so if I look at X
together with G of X conditioned on X
being in the hardcore set that's
computationally
indistinguishable from choosing xit
random from the hardcore set and just
out tossing a random
coin the way the hardcore Lim is usually
stated is that G Can't Be predicted with
probability much better than a half on
the hardcore set but by the equivalence
of pseudo Randomness unpredictability
that this is an equivalent formulation
of
that okay so um another
uh sort of a consequence of this is that
if I now look at X and G of X on the
entire domain all right not restricting
to the hardcore
set um uh it's computationally
indistinguishable I can construct a
function H um that's indistinguishable
from G on the entire domain meaning XG
of X is indistinguishable from X H ofx
where H is information theoretically
Delta heart
and what is that function
H um on the hardcore set it just it's a
randomized function that outputs just a
a coin toss a bruli half and elsewhere
it just equals
g okay and so um and so now like if you
try to compute H with whatever your
computing power is outside H you might
be able to compute it with probability
one on H you're going to compute it with
only probability half and since H has
density to Delta you'll have uh error
probability
Delta
yes yes this is H independent of the
distinguisher that's
right right so hardcore Lemma is really
amazing uh
theorem very powerful all right so once
you have this fact you can actually
prove the conclusion of Yao's xor LMA um
by saying okay I take this quantity that
I'm interested in the probability you
compute G on K an efficient algorithm
computes G on K independent
copies by computational
indistinguishability with from h and a
hybrid argument I can replace all these
G's with
H's up to a negligible additive term
which we had in the in the bound and
then apply the information theoretic
Bound for H
okay so uh that's the first example um
I'm going to give one more example and
uh the kind of takeaway message is later
in the talk will be multic calibration
gives you kind of a even more powerful
in general tool for doing these kinds of
reductions from computational security
to information theoretic
security all right um next example is
from leakage resilient cryptography we
have
u a lot of people in the room are much
more experts on this topic than than me
but I'm just do going to do a a very
simplified um uh example from leakage
resilient cryptography suppose I have
some secret U and I'll have actually
have it in in two parts uh a k and r
um uh so they're indistinguishable from
uniform
and um an adversary learns a little bit
of leakage on the K part of my
key okay why might they only learn on
the K part well one of the um uh
common uh axiom's assumptions in leakage
Brazilian cryptography is that um
leakage only computation leaks
and so maybe you did a computation that
only uses K doesn't use R and so that
would be the opportunity for an
adversary um to learn something about K
and not learn anything about R right
that that's the m m raisen I think U
sort of assumption and leakage resilient
cryptography all right and importantly
it's uh the the adversary only learns a
small amount of leakage so now think
even just uh one bit of
leakage um but what I'll say for the
next couple of slides actually holds for
a larger or up to at least logarithmic
number of bits of leakage now the
question is how do I refresh my
secret okay because now given what the
adversary's learned my key is no longer
sudo random if I try to use it for
something useful
cryptographically I may not have
security um and so um uh an answer uh
that I know from this work of zimowski
and pitock maybe it goes back earlier in
the in the leakage Brazilian
cryptography
literature um is the following I can get
a new key and R Pair by um applying
What's called the random extractor to K
so I use r as the seed for the extractor
and uh uh to kind of get good quality
Randomness that's the idea out of out of
this um out of this uh key that there's
been leakage on uh if you're not
familiar with random extraction think of
this as a hash function where R is the
kind of the index of the hash function
from like a universal hash function
family that's telling you which hash
function you're applying that to
K and then because you might get
something shorter out of this you apply
a suseo random generator to stretch back
to the appropriate
length and repeated applications of this
idea with a K and an r and also another
auxiliary L let's say for left um uh uh
repeated applications a were used by zos
and P to construct what's called a
leakage res resilient stream
Cipher all right so let's think about
how do we prove that from this we get a
good new new uh uh KR pair and again
we'll start with the information
theoretic version in the information
theoretic version K the original k&r are
not pseudo random anymore they're
actually uniform
uh and uh I'm not going to better not
use a prg so we'll just tolerate K Prime
and RP Prime being shorter um than K
andr because the prg will immediately
put us in computational security
World
um
so um this proof is also um uh quite
easy in the information theoretic case
so K was originally uniform and now I've
leaked bits on it and so the entropy of
K given G of K should be at least n the
L original entropy minus the length of
my
leakage now it's important to pick the
right way to measure entropy for the
kind of um for for what follows so we
don't use Shannon entropy here we use
the notion of average Min entropy um of
dois ovsky Raisin and Smith um is a is a
very clean one uh uh to use here and so
and and this fact turns out to be true
um for average Min entropy as
well and then the good thing about using
average Min entropy is
um uh that's like what or Min entropy
and it also turns out to work for
average Min entropy uh is that
Randomness extractors can convert things
that have high Min entropy into things
that are close to
uniform and so if I apply a Randomness
extractor to
K uh and K has high average Min entropy
given G of K then then the output of the
extractor is statistically close to
uniform even given G of K right so G of
K together with the output of the
extractor is um statistically close to
gfk in uniform and how how much uniform
bits you get out you get n get the Min
entropy n minus L minus uh something uh
that's kind of house close to uniform
you want to be um and so you know you
can think of this Epsilon as as you know
arbitrarily small polinomial slightly
negligable and so you still get compared
to n you get a lot of entropy
out okay so that's the information
theoretic
proof what about the computational
version um the tool that um enables you
to kind of derive a computational proof
of security from the information
theoretic one um is the dense model
theorem which was um uh done in joint
work with uh Omar reinold Luca and
mother
tosani
um uh which tells us okay we no longer
can say that K given G of K has a lot of
entropy um I mean k even didn't
necessarily it was just only pseudo
random so it doesn't have a lot of
information theor it need not have a lot
of information theoretic entropy may
have actually very low
entropy um but what we can say is
um K is indistinguishable from some M
random variable M that has a lot of
entropy given G of K right so originally
K was indistinguishable from the uniform
distribution so uh but now given leakage
is it still indistinguishable from
something of high
entropy that's what the dense model
theorem tells us it tells us that that
actually even given given the leakage K
will be indistinguishable from something
of the kind of entropy that we expect n
minus
L and uh now again we have a a kind of
very um simple proof of computational
security um uh derived from the
information theor security so by the
dense model theorem the thing we're
interested in what the extractor does
given G of K is
indistinguishable from on on K is
indistinguishable from applying the
extractor on this dense model M this
model distribution M given G of
K uh that's just by the dense model
theorem and now the latter thing we um
is statistically close to to uniform by
the same argument that we had in the
information theoretic proof of
security yes
Yeahs only G is efficient the
information theore verion you can have G
arbitrary uh no G here is arbitrary G
does not need to be efficient so that's
the that's important in this dense model
theorem G does not need to be
efficient how you if G okay so if G is
all powerful it can kind of take off of
like shows that it can be kind of a
container proof that actually K has no
entropy
um let me could you please repeat G G oh
so um y's concern was asking like how
can the dense model theorem be true even
when G is um not efficiently
computable and the point is that the
leakage is
short I think that's the okay the Le so
here okay dense model theorem good thank
you I forgot to write what I wrote on
the previous slide held for any value of
L this only holds for L up to order log
in or log of your security parameter um
yes thank you short
leakage and also M has a is joint
jointly distributed with yes yes m is
sorry um this random variable is jointly
distributed with K so that this this
like it's correlated here with with G of
K
absolutely yes thank
you show up in the there like
degradation and the indistinguishability
and this is exponential in L or
something exactly exactly and that
relates to kind of an open question at
the end of the talk if I have time to
get to
it okay so let me get a little um sort
of kind of History here so um in the
kind of early 2000s
uh there was starting to be a really
fruitful interplay between theoretical
computer science and um arithmetic
combinatorics additive
combinatorics uh it was papers were
starting to use results from those areas
as kind of black boxes to build better
random extractors in the Barack and
patoo of
erson uh to analyze PCP constructions to
build certain kinds of pseudo random
generators for polinomial
um
and Luca had a conviction that there
were there were some things that were
happening in that arithmetic com Comics
literature that really had deeper
connections with the concepts that we
study in theoretical computer science
not not just like okay that's a powerful
tool that we can import um or that their
tools will be useful when we're studying
some problem that involves groups or
polinomial or the kinds of things they
were they were studying uh and
specifically he was uh intrigued by um
one of the main tools uh lemas in the
proof of the green tow
theorem um all right so the green tow
theorem says that the set of prime
numbers um have arbitrarily long
arithmetic
progressions okay doesn't seem like it
has anything to do with you know
complexity Theory but the main um one of
the main
steps key novelties in the in the in the
green green tow proof was um proving
that the set of prime numbers is
indistinguishable in some
sense from a subset of the natural
numbers of constant
density and we already knew from samet's
theorem in the 1970s that um all subsets
of the natural numbers that have
constant density have arbitrarily long
arithmetic progressions
and green to kind of proved such a
indistinguishability result with a kind
of notion of indistinguishability that
then allowed to deduce from samar's
theorem that the prime numbers must also
have arbitrarily long arithmetic
progressions
yes here is ative distinguisher and the
property of being a prime is sort of
multiplicative and so this
distinguish
um I mean
so it's a good
question what do you mean our
indistinguishable I'm not going to try
to uh uh formulate it it's been uh it's
been it's been a long time um
uh let me put both of those questions on
hold because they're not really they're
not important for this is sort of a
detour in the talk and if I spend spend
time kind of reconstructing answers um
uh we'll we'll lose too much time maybe
on the break so um Luca thought this
seems a lot like things that we study in
complexity the notion of we you know
obviously we study IND distinguishably
all the time in complexity and and
cryptography and being indistinguishable
from large subsets that's like having
high ENT
High pseudo
entropy there should be some complexity
theoretic
analog and um in fact it turned out to
be true um so suppose I have a let let
me draw put a picture here um at the
same time as stating theorem suppose I
have a a
distribution um I'm drawing it like a
set so think like uniform Distribution
on some set that's indistinguishable
from the uniform
distribution so a pseudo random s pseud
random distribution and now I have some
event which may not be efficient at all
right it's an arbitrary event of of some
non-negligible probability Delta in x a
subset say of of X of uh probably at
least
Delta then the dense model theorem
says this x conditioned on this
event okay is comput there is some truly
dense model distribution that's
computationally indistinguishable um
from X conditional net
event good question
um yes and no is it constructive was the
question
um uh meaning there are proofs of this
uh that um kind of describe a way to
build M um kind of
using distinguishers uh like you assume
by contradiction that there is not a no
no such thing
um but uh the complexity of whatever
description you get which I I won't bu a
to reconstruct exactly is going to be
higher complexity than the than the
distinguishers that appear in this
computational indistinguishability here
so we'll see another phenomenon like
that later in the talk
um um okay so this is the dense model
theorem I have a a pseudo random set or
pseudo random distribution some subset
or kind of subdistribution of it of of
probability Delta it actually is going
to be indistinguishable from something
that
is truly dense right which is the same
as going like having high men entropy
right you get the formulation I talked
about earlier where I I took X
conditioned on some leakage let's think
one bit
leakage um I I can have the event of
conditioning on on G being the leakage
being zero the event of the leakage
being one and Stitch those together to
get the the model that I I talked about
on the previous
slide okay and now you can see why
shortly Le or having only a small number
of possible values of leakage will be
important
there um also if the leakage is is large
these conditioning on the leakage will
tend to lead to a a set of negligible an
event of negligible probability for
which the dense model theorem doesn't
apply all right so soon the dense model
theorem um was found to
have connections to other things in
complexity and cryptography I already
mentioned uh actually as motivation the
leakage resilient cryptography
application um and I we saw also how it
relates to computational entropy being
indistinguishable from having high
entropy um and then uh uh
impal um showed that actually so in the
dense model theorem paper we proved the
dense model theorem using ideas inspired
by the proof of the hardcore
Lemma and then impal um uh showed a
clever way of actually deriving the
dense model theorem from from the from
an appropriately generalized version of
the hardcore
Lema um but Luca wanded sort of still
felt that there should be some deeper
unifying unifying principle here
um and uh conjectured that the kind of
really the like right unifying principle
had something to do with
regularity so now let me turn to talk
about regularity theorems in in graph
Theory and complexity
um so the classic example of uh kind of
a regularity theorem is Sam's regularity
Lemma uh in graph
Theory
um so uh this says at a high level every
graph right no matter how comple complex
you should think of of G as a dense
graph uh sparse graphs the statement
will just be vacuous uh vacuously true
uh every Gra dense graph
is indistinguishable in some sense from
a graph of low
complexity so what is a graph of low
complexity um all right so we're giving
the graph G and then we have our our
indistinguishability parameter Epsilon
um the graph of low complexity it's
going to be defined by some partition of
the vertex space into a small number of
Parts where here small means depends
only on Epsilon or it doesn't depend on
N the number of vertices in the
graph
and um between every two parts in this
partition VI cross
VJ our graph
G is actually
indistinguishable from a random graph of
the appropriate
density um and the appropriate density
is the density like What proportion of
VI cross
VJ has edges from from in G like G's
density all right and this is true for
all pairs I and J except for some
Epsilon fraction where we kind of
measure you know this this fraction is
where we're measuring the pairs weighted
by their their dens density we the pairs
so um you know the weight we put on VI
cross VJ is the density of VI times the
density of V VJ alpha alpha J so there's
some exceptional Pairs and aside from
that um uh G is indistinguishable from a
random graph between all other
parts all right so it's kind of low
complexity in the sense
that for many
purposes um like we've reduced the
description of this graph G on an
arbitrarily large number of vertices to
this number of par that depends only on
Epsilon like these Alpha parameters that
are the you know if if we're thinking of
just you know sort of graph properties
that are invariant under permutation of
vertices all that matters is the the
alphas the densities and the mui
JS um all right so one downside of Sam's
regularity Lemma is that the number of
Parts is actually it's a function only
of Epsilon but it's an enormous function
of Epsilon it's a Tower of height
polinomial in one over Epsilon and in
fact for some versions of the and it's
known um gowers proved that that that
kind of behavior is necessary and now uh
or I guess a decade ago uh they even
pinned down the right polinomial in
epsilon so one over Epsilon Square I
think a tower of height one over Epsilon
squar for an appropriately formulated
version of the regularity L there
several different you know equivalent
formulations um that might lead to
slightly different um
dependence
Epson okay
so um this Tower by the way is I don't
know at least for me I think was a bit
of a sort of psychological barrier that
we'll come come back to um in a
bit
uh so can there be a complexity
theoretic regularity Lemma um so with
Luca and madur tulsiani
um we Prov the following kind of
complexity theoretic regularity LMA
which is that every Boolean function is
indistinguishable from a low complexity
function
um but it what we mean by low complexity
it's going to be pretty different look
different than what's in in
Sam so for every function G and now um
let me make these uh functions that are
bounded functions between zero and one
where we think of this as a description
of a randomized function so if it if it
says one3 there that means really we're
thinking of if G of X is 1/3 that means
G of X is one with probability 1/3 and
Zer um with probability
2/3 I'll be more precise about that so
for now just think of them as real
valued functions there exists so I have
a fix a function a distribution on the
inputs um a circuit size parameter s and
uh Epsilon and there exists a function
that's low complexity in the sense it's
computable by a circuit of size um just
a little bit bigger than s s * poly 1
over
Epsilon and is indistinguishable from
G by all circuits of size
s okay so if I look at the expectation
for every circuit F of size s
expectation F of x times the difference
between h of X and G of X that's bounded
by by Epsilon all right this is kind of
an unusual way for us to write things in
cryptography this kind of uh
comes um more from the way they do
things in this arithmetic combinatorics
when they talk about regularity they
think of this as like an inner product
between the diff F and the differences
between the functions F being nearly
orthogonal to it but an equivalent form
formulation that's more kind of
cryptographer friendly is instead of
thinking of these real valued functions
that I've written here think of a
randomized the corresponding randomized
function so H Rand on X is one with
probability h of X and zero with
probability 1 minus h of X and then this
is an equivalent way to to write this is
say um The Joint distribution of an
input X and H Ren of X is
computationally
indistinguishable from X and G Rand of X
and computationally IND distinguish
I have this s Epsilon here to Just note
by circuits of size s and with indis
with Advantage
Epsilon okay so um some of this might
look familiar to some of you um this is
actually
um uh another an equivalent this is this
latter thing is the statement of what's
known as the leakage simulation Lemma in
leakage resilient cryptography so also
very like useful for security proofs in
leakage resilient cryptography
um this is the special case for one bit
one bit leakage which is captured
captured here um the full leakage
resilient leakage simulation LMA of jet
petock also considers um more bits of
leakage with like some exponential blow
up in the number of bits of leakage so
they think of the leakage as as as
logarithmic um and kind of optimizes the
dependence on on the leakage and Epsilon
and so on which um uh in some cases is
is better than what you would get using
this um and all right towards it being a
unifying principle it it um we did we're
able to use it to derive the dense model
theorem and the hardcore LMA and it's
seem like a like a a cleaner statement
there's no like Assumption of hardness
here it's like just a structure theorem
about functions every function has a low
complexity approximation and now we use
that to do you know various security
proofs where we might have an assumption
that g is hard or um some distribution
is pseudo
random uh but one sign that it was maybe
not quite yet the right unifying
principle is that um when we tried to
prove the hardcore LMA we didn't get
the optimal Hollin to Delta density we
only got hardcore density Delta was kind
of annoying annoying to
us um like if you in particular if you
wanted to get the right ya exor Lemma
from the proof I told told earlier the
right bound there you you want the right
hardcore
density all right what does it how does
it relate to a samet or graph Theory
because that's what I motivated
regularity Lemma coming from you there
is a version of this and actually what
what what we proves a version that you
know doesn't restrict to circuits and
and bit strings as your input you can
have any domain for your input and any
family of distinguishers that you're
interested in for your second condition
here um and then what low complexity
means is that your function H your low
complexity approximator is a com is
obtained by combining a small polinomial
in one over Epsilon functions from your
distinguisher family and it turns out
that the way you combine them also can
be done by a circuit of size poly one
over
Epsilon and then you can apply it in the
graph theoretic setting by taking your
domain so if I I have a Vertex set of
size N I take my domain to
be um of size n choose two representing
all possible edges that might be present
in a
graph okay and then we can think of the
function G if this is our domain and G
is a Boolean function on the domain as
just the um describing the graph zero or
one according to is an edge present or
not and you can take the family of
distinguishers to be family of all cut
functions like for two sets in the
vertices is there an edge between
them and it turns out if you apply the
this regularity LMA for that special
case you get what's known as the um weak
regularity the freeze conon regularity
LMA for graphs
right so not which is weaker than the
samti regularity Lemma in the in the
kind of indistinguishability it
provides but it's better in the sense
the freeze conon regularity Lemma has
not a tower dependence on Epsilon it has
only a one over Epsilon squar
dependence and somehow I think I
mentioned this psychological
barrier you know one might ask this
question is there a complexity theoretic
analog of of like actual strong semed
regularity and
um uh I would have said of course not
semar regularity has this Tower
dependence and that's makes it useless
for complexity theoretic and certainly
cryptographic applications where we
think of Epsilon as like one over polom
small or neg negligibly small a tower if
you pay that price in a security
reduction game over like nothing you get
nothing useful
out and um the answer um is actually uh
that I want to convey is that actually
yes there is a complexity theoretic
analog of strong
samti uh and that's multic calibration
and that's work from from Cynthia and PR
and uh and Rachel Lynn and Daniel Lee
that I'll mention some of the the
history later
so um all right so what is multic
calibration
um see how we're doing on time
okay uh so the multic calibration
theorem says for every uh uh I'll state
in the complexity theoretic form for
every randomized function on say bit
strings of length and every Distribution
on inputs again I have size and
Epsilon there's a partition of the
domain
uh into only one over Epsilon parts so
no no Tower appearing
there such that on each part G of X is
indistinguishable from a random function
like a a buruli of the
appropriate um parameter mui uh mui
being just the expectation of G on that
part
um that's that's for all right so I have
a i K plus one Parts here p 0 to PK
there's some exceptional part some
Epsilon portion of the domain where
indistinguishability doesn't
hold and finally the partition is low
complexity in the sense that you can
given an input you can tell which piece
of the partition you're in using a
circuit of size um slightly bigger than
s s * po 1 over
Epsilon all right let me draw a picture
to make this U statement still there
um so I have the arbitrary domain and
the multic calibration I have my
function G sorry I lost some of the
animation I used to have here um it
tells us that there's a partition of the
domain right that's given to us so
originally we just given G the zeros and
ones it's partition of the domain into a
small number of Parts um
and on uh a part where you know G is
nearly balanced say here it's
indistinguishable so here it's IND
disting
from you know the XG of X is
indistinguishable from bruli 6 here it's
indistinguishable from bruli point9 so
on
yes the partition you assume like you
have a function that tells you if you're
in the node is in there or not yeah so
it's a one way of doing is there a
circuit that giv an input gives you a
number from zero to K and says I'm in
which piece of the partition you're
in all right this condition is crucial
right so this multic calibration theorem
would be
trivial um if we didn't have this so we
just say okay my partition is one piece
is the zeros of G one piece is the ones
of G clearly on the zeros G is
indistinguishable from a beri zero on
the ones it's indistinguishable from a
beri one right but the point is that's
not an efficiently computable partition
unless G itself is easy to
compute okay and this is this is the
theorem the structure holds for all G
regardless of whether it's easy or hard
to
compute all right so this looks a bit
like uh what the way I formulated the
hardcore LMA let's just
contrast um the hardcore
LMA uh this holds for all functions the
hardcore LMA assumes that the function
is hard in a particular sense that it's
Delta hard to
predict second G the hardcore LMA just
tells you there's some subset of the
domain where G is indistinguishable from
beri
half this is giving you covering the
entire domain and saying everywhere the
function G is kind of indistinguishable
from something very structured a a
random
function and finally the pieces here are
efficiently recognizable and there's no
such guarantee in the hardcore
Lemma okay now let's contrast with Sam
ready so I've put in in blue the places
where um it's the two statements are
really the same or special cases of that
same common generalization the notion of
indistinguishability
um uh can be formulated for both to be
the
same uh and your distinguishability from
something of density given by the
density of of of G your graph or your
function um is is the same and that you
have some
cepal uh set of uh pairs or an
exceptional part of the domain that's
that's really kind of the
same the um two important differences
one is we've gone from a tower
dependence to a polinomial
dependence and the second is what's our
notion of low
complexity uh in samti the crucial
aspect of low complexity is that what we
have is a partition of the vertex set
that induces then a partition of the
edge The Edge space into these VI cross
VJs um which is different than what we
have in our statement where we said your
function on your domain and you have a
partition on that domain that
corresponds in the graph theor exing to
a partition of the potential Edge space
the N choose
two and um to my surprise but this is
really out of out of the work of uh
Cynthia P at
um it's this insistence on a partition
of the vertex set that is what incurs
this Tower dependence in in in
Sam and then finally how does it relate
to the weak
regularity
um uh from this you can get a a kind of
a
uh your your uh indistinguishable low
complexity function to be the one that
that on an input X you first compute
which piece of the domain you're in
because that's efficiently computable by
condition three and then you just output
the expectation of of G on that part
which you can hardwire in if we're
working with non-uniform circuit
complexity which we
are um or you output a coin if you want
to do the randomized uh function of that
bias Okay so
because of time maybe I
won't um this came out of the
algorithmic fairness
literature um in their setting the the
uh G is like some ground truth function
that you're trying to learn and H is a a
predictor um that you've
learned and
uh what what multic calibration is
saying like even conditioned on your
prediction G and H are indistinguishable
and and the way it captures fairness is
that your distinguishers correspond to
like demographic groups subsets of the
population that you might want to have
fairness on but I think since we're
short on time let me skip over that um
and just give because this is not a talk
on algorithmic fairness um so just some
credits here so uh the original multic
calibration theorem as Hebert Johnson
Kim Ry gold and Roth Bloom wasn't stated
quite the way that I stated it the first
partition-based Formula
I believe is in this uh paper of goon
Kai Ry gold Sharon and
weer um another important uh reference
is uh uh connection you know that
psychological barrier I mentioned
um skorski had a paper showing that like
you can use the complexity theoretic way
of proving regularity and so on to give
a another proof of samet's regularity
Lemma and so maybe that should have been
a hint that uh maybe there really is a
complexity theoretic analog of strong
seet regularity uh and then this paper
of um uh dwark Ley Lyn and tankala that
I mentioned is the one that that really
formalized this idea that multic
calibration really is the same
indistinguishability condition uh like
that it is a complexity theoretic analog
of strong regularity and then finally
the U work that um kind of got me into
this with uh Sylvia caserta and Cynthia
um uh was pointing out that multic
calibration is very useful for
complexity and crypto
applications and since we have only a
few minutes maybe I'll just do one just
uh or two quick
examples the point is similar to samur
now we've described our arbitrarily
complex function in terms
of uh just a small number of parameters
these M's and Alphas the densities of
the pieces of the partition and the
expectation of G on those
pieces and in
particular um you can just calculate
like how hard is g to predict um on a
uniformly random input that same
quantity that came up in Delta hardness
in in patoo well it's the
um on each piece what's the best thing
you can do the best thing you should do
if you're trying to predict G with the
highest success probability is predict
the majority
value right if if it's uh sorry think
about H sorry H the random function that
g corresponds to so think of the
information theoretic hardness in h on
each piece the best thing I can do it's
it's a bruli coin toss so my input gives
me no other than what piece of the
partition it's in and then I'm trying to
guess a beri
mui and if mui is bigger than a half I
should guess one and if it's smaller
than a half I should get
zero and then because G and H are
indistinguishable um that strategy the
best strategy for computing H is also
the best strategy for computing
G right up to a plus or minus negligible
success probability and up to a poly one
over Epsilon in circuit
size okay and similarly you can like
derive the hardcore Lemma very nicely by
just saying okay the way I'm going to
get something that's very hard to
compute is just rebalance on each of the
part pieces of the partition so if if if
if G was very biased if H is very sorry
like in a place where G is very biased
towards one if I uh upweight the zero to
make it balanced then I become
indistinguishable from a bruli half just
like you want in hardcore
LMA um but it doesn't just do these
things that are related to the hardcore
LMA and Delta hardness you can
also um for example analyze the pseudo
Shannon entropy of G of x given X in
terms of these parameters by just again
calculating the the Shannon entropy of
the beri um given X um just the average
weighted by the alpha eyes of
the Shannon entropy of a of a beri mui
and this is something that has come up
in kind of work we did a while back on
constructing pseudo random generators
from oneway functions without using
hardcore
bits um and then finally let me just
give a um a teaser I think I won't go
through the details in a new work with
um uh Cassandra marcuson and L Potterman
I think Louie might be here I saw Louie
earlier Cassandra I'm not sure um is we
apply multic calibration to understand
indistinguishability
between uh
distributions and uh in
particular let me not explain how you
apply multic
calibration but basically you can reduce
we have two random variables we want to
understand how does their computational
indistinguishably
indistinguishability degrade as you take
more
samples and we can related to the
information theoretic problem of how
computational indistinguishability
degrades when you take more
samples and in
particular um we're able to
um characterize this in what in terms of
What's called the pseudo what we call
the pseudo helinger distance so helinger
information theoretically helinger
distance tells
if I have two distributions how many
samples do I need to take to distinguish
them with constant advantage that's
given up to a constant Factor by their
the helinger distance between those
distributions and now we have
a um a computational analog of that
statement as again as an easy
consequence of multic
calibration okay so
um hopefully I've convinced you multic
calibration is a um powerful tool for
reasoning about computational hardness
and indust I didn't get to the examples
but I so much but conveyed how it's a
strengthening of these earlier ways that
we had to reduce computational security
proofs to um uh information theoretic
ones and there's a bunch of open
questions that I'll just like leave
for uh discussion on the Break um and uh
another take away from from this is that
there we can continue to draw uh
inspiration um from Luca and the ideas
he had thank
[Applause]
you
Cynthia your work with Cassandra and
Louie you talked about multiple samples
any connections or things that we can uh
get for differential
privacy X is the Distribution on one
database and X1 on the
other great uh since is asking whether
looking at um uh
multiple uh this this fact that we're
looking at indistinguishability under
multiple samples whether there might be
any applications to differential
privacy one
guess is maybe one can derive
composition theorem
for computational differential
privacy from composition theorems for
from for information theoretic
differential privacy um that's
my my first guess on
it you know the the multic calibration
theorem and many of these theorems are
agnostic of the complexity of computing
G right so this works for all G's so if
you now look at you know easy to compute
G's you know ones that have circuits of
size I don't know something does that
you know change the consequences you
know um maybe stronger consequences
somehow yeah so V asking uh you know I
said these These are agnostic of G and
specifically we're using them to
understand
hardness the hardness in G various kinds
of hardness uh various kinds of average
case hardness like which may be this
hardness of prediction it may this
pseudo Shannon entropy that I'm talking
about um in distinguishability
uh now if G is like actually
easy yeah so
[Music]
um I'm I'm not sure yeah so I'm not sure
in that in that region between like if
it's if it's easy then the multi-
calibration theorem is is is just you
know vacu like vacuously true right you
just partition into the zeros and ones
um
one kind of in between thing I mention
here as a as a kind of open problem is
to have a uniform complexity analog so
everything I said in the talk was all in
the kind of non-uniform circuit
complexity circuits of your adversary
polze circuits um I believe there should
be one um the settings in which the
statement should involve some kind of
easiness associated with G so like maybe
G is not easy easy to compute but I can
efficiently sample random pairs XG of X
so if you think of the example I gave of
a uh uh the least significant bit of the
inverse on a oneway function I can't
compute G if you give me an input it's
hard for me to compute the value of G
but if you want me to draw a random
sample from XG of X I can do that I pick
a random input to the oneway function
and then I have the value of G and I
take the take the output
sure
[Applause]