all right uh let's continue our
discussion of factor markets uh remember
to set the stage we are now in the
second half of the course talking about
the various elements that underly the
supply and demand model that we
developed in the first half of the
course and the first question we're
tackling is where to W andr come from
where do these prices that are the price
of firm inputs where do they come from
and they come of course from markets
markets of demand and Supply markets
four factors so let's start by doing the
labor market
equilibrium let's start by doing the
equilibrium and then we'll talk about
what effect a minimum
wage has in that
equilibrium okay so let's look at figure
1 figure 161 puts together the labor
market
equilibrium we have a a demand
curve the demand curve comes from firms
because in Factor markets firms are now
the demanders and people are the
suppliers so we flipped the tables from
a typical Market in a typical Market
cons in a consumer goods Market I'm
consumer goods Market firms Drive the
supply curve and consumers Drive the
demand curve that's no longer true true
now firms Drive the domain curve and
consumers Drive the supply curve so the
domain curve comes from the marginal
product of labor okay so we have uh a
demand curve in labor market equilibrium
here we're saying the demand curve is 70
minus
W we're saying that as the wage goes up
firms want fewer workers and we could
see that from our earlier firm
optimization okay but there's also
supply curve now we talked about last
time is the shape of the supply curve
here is indeterminant and that's because
income effects offset substitution
effects when Leisure is a normal good
okay that's the key lesson from last
lecture is that even when Leisure a
normal good income effects offset
substitution effects so we don't know
the shape of supply curve that said
we're going to pretty much for the rest
of the semester assume upward sloping
labor Supply curves we're going to
pretty much assume substitution effects
offset income effects because they hell
of a lot each to work with it's a mess
when they both slope down so we're
pretty much going to assume that
substitution effects Dominate and the
labor supply curve is upward sloping so
here for example we have a labor supply
curve um uh of the
form uh that uh labor equals um uh wus
10 so a higher wage leads to more labor
Supply okay so this uh uh so a higher
wage leads to more labor SL it should be
L equal 70 so this is the demand curve
the demand curve is L equal 70 minus W
the supply curve is uh Lal wus 10 so to
solve for equilibrium we simply set
those equal we know how to do that now
and you find the equilibrium is at 30
units of Labor with a wage of 40 that's
the point at which firms are happy to
hire workers and workers are happy to
work so it's the same kind of
equilibrium of goods markets
now it's just in a factor market
okay now let's ask what happens when we
add a minimum
wage what happens we add a minimum wage
which is a standard labor market
intervention all around the world okay
some of you may even enjoyed minimum
wage jobs at some point in your past
lives or hopefully not in your future
lives but some point in your past lives
uh it's a common feature of the
developed worlds have minimum wages the
way minimum wage work is the government
just sets a wage floor below which
employers cannot pay their employees
they set a wage floor so for example
imagine the government came in and set a
wage floor of 50 set a minimum wage of
50 above the market equilibrium
wage
okay so the new equilibrium
now is the new outcome the new market
outcome is actually at 0 two
why well because that higher wage firms
want to hire fewer
workers it doesn't matter what workers
want there's no jobs for them so firms
say fine if that higher wage I only want
workers workers say well gee at that
higher wage I want to work actually uh I
want to work much more than
that okay um Andrew in the future uh
diagram we should have the Y inter the x
intercept for the excess Supply um they
want to work much more than that so you
end up with an excess supply of
labor now when we talked about supply
and demand equilibrium we talked about
us how disequilibrium outcomes resolve
themselves through Market adjustments
well here this disequilibrium outcome
cannot resolve itself the market can't
adjust the Market's stuck because of the
regulation so we end up in a situation
we're out of equilibrium we have excess
Supply okay in in in layman's terms we
call that
unemployment we end up with unemployment
we end up with people who want to work
but can't
work okay and that causes an
inefficiency or dead weight loss you see
before the
policy worker
Surplus okay was um or I'm sorry firm
Surplus I'm sorry for the policy firm
Surplus cuz firms the consumers here was
a plus b plus C that was the consumer
surplus or in this case consumers are
firms they really call that more the
demander Surplus the supplier Surplus
was D plus e with the minimum wage we've
now transferred the area
B from firms to workers so the firm
Surplus this the demander Surplus has
fallen all the way to
a so we've transferred the area B but
we've created in doing so a dead weight
loss of C plus a
standard kind of welfare analys we've
done so several times before now okay so
what we've done with this policy is
we've transferred the area
B from the demanders who are firms to
the suppliers who are workers but in
doing so we've created a deadweight loss
C plus e why because those are trades
that would be efficient to make they're
not being made there are workers that
would happily
work at a wage below 50 and firms would
be happy to H them at a wage below 50
but we're not letting that transaction
happen that's wasted economic efficiency
or dead weight
loss this is the pretty standard an of
minimum wage and this says that well
look when you put a minimum wage you get
a
trade-off you get a transfer to workers
which you may like but you create a dead
weight loss because you create
unemployment but actually starting about
30 years ago research started finding
that minimum wages didn't cause
unemployment actually some research
studies suggest you put a minimum wage
employment goes
up but certainly there was very little
evidence that goes
down this was quite striking because how
could that happen now one way it could
happen of course could be if the demand
curve was perfectly
inelastic then a minimum wage would not
lower employment
you can see that in this graph it's I
haven't drawn this out but you see the
162 imagine taking that blue line and
making it vertical you'll see the
minimum wage wouldn't cause unemployment
so one thing that could be going on is
demand could be perfectly in elastic but
in fact there's lots of studies which
say that's not true demand for labor is
not perfectly in elastic so that can't
be the explanation so we said an
alternative explanation which is that
just like Goods markets can be
non-competitive labor markets can also
be non-competitive
and so we think the explanation is
non-competitive labor
markets okay so when we when we thought
about firms selling Goods we said look
at a competitive market firms face
perfectly elastic demand any given firm
faces perfectly elastic
demand okay well
likewise when we think about a firm
hiring workers we think that in a we if
labor markets are competitive
any given firm faed a perfectly elastic
supply curve think about the intuition
the interest perfectly competitive
market is look if I'm selling chachis
next to the other guy selling
chachis then I can't raise my price
above or below his because if I raise it
above I'll sell zero below I'll sell I
won't I won't be able to meet
demand well it's the same thing when
hiring workers a perfectly competitive
market imagine a perfectly competitive
labor market which is fast food
workers okay there's a bunch of fast
food restaurants near each other if
McDonald's pays 50 cents more than
Burger King everyone leaves Burger King
and works at McDonald's if Burger King
pays 50 cents more than McDonald's vice
versa so you have essentially each firm
faces a flat supply curve because
workers can just move it's an easy
substitution between them just like it's
EAS a substitute between statues of the
eiel tower little mini statues it's easy
substitute between working mcdonal and
Burger King it's the same job and
they're near each
other okay however
what we've realized is that may in fact
not be
true what if just like Goods markets can
be
non-competitive what if labor markets
can be
non-competitive remember the assumptions
we required for a perfectly competitive
Goods Market we required perfect
information and no transaction costs and
all Goods being the same well for a
perfectly competitive labor market the
same requirements are in place
you need perfect
information you need no transaction
costs and all jobs to be the same well
that's not true in particular the first
isn't true we don't have perfect
information because jobs don't always
post their wages typically don't post
their wages and typically you don't know
what you can make in another
firm okay once you don't know what you
can make in another firm once it's
costly to learn that that's a
transaction cost that interferes
okay that's one form of transaction
costs that could interfere what we think
is a fairly competitive
market okay now let's go further let's
think about the most extreme case which
was the old mining towns we used to have
in the West in the US in the US the way
it work is you discovered gold you'd set
up a town to around the gold mine and
everyone in that town would work in the
gold mine or they would work selling
stuff to worked in the gold mine okay
well in that case you definitely didn't
face a competitive labor market because
that was the only place to work there
was one employer the gold
mine and they had and if you want to
work you had to work for that one
employer so instead of the case of a
monopoly we had a case of a
monopsony a monopsony a
monopoly is when only one firm sells the
good a
monopsony is when only one firm hires
the workers
okay let's suppose further let's just s
is having a bunch of Gold Mine Workers
let's suppose further that just as we
assume initially the monopolies can't
price
discriminate let's assume monopsonies
can't wage discriminate this is actually
kind of a more reasonable assumption it
was always sort of weird to say why
could monopolis charge different people
different prices it's a more reasonable
sub to think firms can't pay similar
worker different way wages they'd be
pissed right it's sort of you know if if
if you're paying two Works doing the
same job different wages they're going
to get upset people care about Equity
it's sort of more reasonable think for
the same job you sort of have to pay the
same wage I think that's a much sort of
more reasonable assumption than it is a
monopoly
case okay I mean you can pay managers
more than M workers but it's sort of
reasonable to think you kind of have to
pay all the M workers the same
thing what that means is that just as
when you're a
monopoly lowering your price might hurt
your profits through the poisoning
effect when your M
monopsony raising the wage will hurt
your profits through an equivalent
poisoning
effect so let's think about the firm's
decision okay the firm wants to set the
marginal cost of the next worker equal
to the marginal benefit of the next
worker okay what is the marginal
benefit well the marginal benefit is
still the marginal revenue product of
labor that hasn't changed that's true
regardless of the market the next worker
produces the next marginal revenue
produc the marginal product of labor
what changes the marginal
cost before the marginal cost was the
wage in a perfectly competitive labor
market I didn't say last time I was
assuming that but I was in a perfectly
competitive labor market the wage is the
cost but in a monop market that's no
longer true and to see that want to say
what's the marginal cost the mar cost is
the marginal expenditure to get another
unit of
Labor well what's the expenditure to get
another unit of Labor your expenditure
is your what's your total what's your
total wage Bill I'm sorry what's your
total wage bill it's the wage you pay by
times the number of workers you have but
the number of workers you have is a
function of the wage you pay right the
more you pay the more workers will kind
of want to work with you so if we
differentiate this and get marginal
expenditure which is sort of the firm's
marginal cost of hiring another unit of
Labor the marginal
expenditure is W plus DW DL time
l in other
words it's this term which is positive
the marginal expenditure is the wage
plus this second term which is how much
do you have to raise the wage to get
another worker
it's a flip side of the poisoning effect
the poisoning effect was as a monopolist
if I want to sell one more unit I face a
tradeoff I sell the additional unit
that's good but I have to lower my price
to sell it that's bad here if I want to
hire one more unit of Labor there's an
equivalent tradeoff I get one more
worker that's
good but I have to pay all my workers
more to get him that's bad
why because I can't wage
discriminate and it sort of makes sense
if I want to expand the number of it's I
once again I think it's much more intive
the Monopoly case if I want more workers
I got to raise the
wage okay why was this not an issue for
the perfectly competitive firm it's not
an issue firm because they faced a
perfectly elastic firm labor supply
curve workers were different McDonald's
and Burger King so they could just go
back and forth but a a monopsonist
doesn't face that anymore they face the
true market labor supply curve which is
not perfectly elastic so to see this
let's go to figure 164 so
163 that's a perfectly competitive
case the marginal benefit of hiring
another worker is the marginal revenue
product of labor 163 the marginal
benefit the marginal revenue product of
labor the marginal cost is expressed by
the wage which is determined by a
perfectly competitive
market but 164 is a mopsy now we have
the same marginal revenue product of
labor which we defined as 70 minus L we
use the same example did before 70 minus
L uh well we're flipping this so the
marginal so now we can write the
marginal revenue product of labor curve
as simply W equal 70 minus l so just
inverting
that okay that's that's the firm's
demand curve or margin product of labor
curve but what about its marginal
expenditure curve well if you look at
the supply curve the supply curve was w
= l + 10 right so we can now say expend
the firm's expenditure
function labor is W I'm sorry uh the
firm's expenditure
function is L time L + 10 that's its
labor expenditures right stare at that
for a minute the number of workers times
the wage the wage comes from this
equation differentiate that with respect
to L and what do you
get if you different if you differ
respect to L you get that you get two
you get uh 2 L +
10 and that is the firm's marginal
expenditure
curve which is
above the F the supply curve as you see
in figure
164 so what does a monopsonist do the
monopsonist set
goes to the point where marginal cost
equals marginal benefits what's the
marginal cost the marginal cost is the
marginal expenditure curve what's the
marginal benefit the marginal revenue
product curve so it says I want to hire
workers not the 30 I was hiring in the
market was competitive but
20 what wage am I going to pay them well
just like the monopolist needs to
respect the demand curve the monopsonist
needs to respect the supply curve so
ways you can pay them when we read off
the supply curve you're going to pay
them 30 instead of
40 so what's going on here you're hiring
fewer workers at a lower
wage than the equilibrium would dictate
why because if you want more workers you
got to raise the wage and that's not
profitable so if you're if you're at the
point where you're paying 30 to get 20
workers and from that point you want to
hire more workers say well look you know
even at that point it's you know I'm
making money on the next
worker but the problem is to hire that
next work you have to pay higher wages
to all your previous workers and it's
not worth it this is a hard intuition
but it's the flip side of the poisoning
intuition so go back to your Monopoly
case and work it through you'll see it's
all just the
opposite okay now while I need to teach
you the math and the graphs because
that's what we test you on the intuition
here is actually pretty clear I think
clearer than the Monopoly case just
think about the intuition for a second
think about me at
MIT there's many universities I could
work for okay I mean it sound arrogant
but there's a lot of universities out
there presumably some others would want
to hire me
okay yet MIT has monopsony power over me
why what gives MIT monopsony power over
me it's nothing nefarious think about
typically any but any firm has Monopoly
power over their employees
why well
yeah I don't know how much I get paid
anywhere else that's one reason so
there's an information
reason what else now let's actually
let's compare that actually I know how
to get paid in California because
California public schools have to make
their wages public so let's say I could
overcome that actually if you go online
you want know when it's paid at a public
university in America you can figure
that out okay so let's say I could solve
that problem but there's other reasons
why MIT is monop power let's say if they
mov to California
yeah well I'm established I I have to
move right like if I want to go
to California I gotta move that sucks I
gotta pack up the house I got to leave
all my friends uh in particular my wife
might have a job that she likes here my
kids might like being in school here so
there's a huge transaction cost
transaction costs create monopsony power
it's not a mining town me it's not a
mining town but it still has Market
power over me because of transaction
costs do also the fact I like teaching
MIT I've got my lecture set the to some
other univers I have to dumb them down
because the students aren't as smart as
MIT I don't want to do that I've got I
my office has a window view it's pretty
awesome my window has an has a river
view my office has a window view Jesus
my my office has a Riverview through the
window okay that's pretty awesome that'
be hard to replicate a lot of other
universities
basically every job change in jobs comes
with transaction costs transaction costs
create monopsony power MIT does not have
to pay me the market
wage because of these transaction costs
and because of information
limitations okay so it's not crazy to
think indeed we now think that basically
monopsony is a better description of
almost all labor markets than is perfect
competition this is a real SE change in
the last 20 years is a real sort of
takeover the monop city model in labor
economics that we think it's probably
much more likely if firms have monopsony
power than that they're perfectly
competitive okay
yeah in the new higher market so that's
a great Point there's still the
information issue which is I'd have to
go and collect a bunch of offers but
other than that you're right you would
think and indeed if you look at salaries
of
academics new higher salaries if you
look at Sal academics you can basically
predict them pretty well based on two
based on essentially when do they get
their last offer so new higher salaries
are pretty flat and you'll get raises
when they get an offer from another
University so basically MIT will
underpay you until you get an offer from
another University and then they'll then
they'll because that reveals information
and then MIT can then can then do that
okay good question all right now what
does this mean for the government well
this means that there is scope for gains
from regulation because look this
monopis has created a dead weight loss
look at the we we off have 30 workers so
a deadweight loss triangle from only
hiring 20 workers that says their scope
for optimal regulation just like the
scope to Optimal regulation of monop of
monopolis and what would optimal
regulation look like well it could look
like a minimum wage so imagine if figure
165 we set a minimum wage equal to the
market
wage well now think about the firm's
decision for any workers to the left of
LM there's no poisoning effect because
they can't lower the wage so they might
as well higher the competitive level
what has the minimum wage just done it
has raised
employment so this is how you can get
this weird result that a minimum wage
can raise employment because what the
minimum wage has done has essentially
eroded monopsony power or eroded the
negative effects of monopsony by getting
rid of this poisoning effect by saying
well firms might as well hire Elm the
reason they were hiring lower than El
comp before was because they could lower
the wage but now they
can't so that is how a minimum wage can
raise employment now of course so in
subsets you can get a win-win government
policy you can transfer Surplus to
Consumers and raise employment everybody
wins and that's how government policy
can make things better in imperfect Mark
with market
failures now of course that isn't
necessarily
true what would happen if you set the
minimum wage well let me ask first what
happen if you set the minimum wage too
low what if you set the minimum wage
below
W1 what would happen if the government
put a minimum wage in was below
W1 yeah no effect very important the
private Market will always get around
government regulations if it can a
government regulation that doesn't bind
is no government regulation at all it
sounds obvious but it's not it's
important to remember the first thing
after to go regulations is do they
matter okay then basically as you think
about any minimum wage between
W1 and even past W comp they will
actually improve welfare but as it gets
high enough the minimum wage could
actually and cause firms once the
minimum wage gets above
um the level on the marginal revenue
product curve that corresponds to L1 so
you see where the L1 dash line hits the
marginal revenue product curve once the
wage gets above that level then you're
making things worse you end up hiring
fewer workers then the monopus would
hire so once again the way to think
government regulation once again come
take 1441 we'll spend all semester on
this the way to think about it is the
market knows best unless there's a
market failure the market failure raises
the PO potential for the government to
improve things but doesn't prove
government will Pro improve things it
does not prove government will improve
things you need to actually study and
examine the government policy to see if
it makes it better or worse for minimum
wages basically the consensus now is for
minimum wages in the range that minimum
wages are set in America which is being
probably about $8 and12 an hour okay
where most minimum wages are we the
consensus seems to be that they are a
good thing that basically they can cause
benefits to workers without actually
reducing employment once you get above
12 the evidence gets more mixed so we
now are seeing a series of 15-hour wage
dollar minimum wage including
Massachusetts the evidence on those is a
little more mixed we need a little more
time to study but there's some level at
which a minimum wage definitionally is
high enough it will cause unemployment
that doesn't mean minum wage is bad it
just means at that point there's a
trade-off so if you go back to figure 16
um
two 162 does not imply we should not
have minimum
wage 162 just says there is a tradeoff
you lose efficiency but you redistribute
to
workers okay in a standard model that's
bad because we rate consumer and
producer Surplus the same but in the
real world it might not be we might
value consumer surplus more than
producer
Surplus so the bottom line is the
minimum wage isn't in no situation is it
unambiguously bad it may actually be
unambiguously good and depends on the
structure of the labor
market okay questions about
that so once again the idea would be MIT
is making excess money off me because I
don't want to move if the government
came in and raised my wages not too much
that would make me better off and it
would just come out of mit's profits it
would just be a
transfer but I'd be better off and they
would they'd maybe because they pay
higher wage they may hire another
another professor okay and that would
improve efficiency all right so with
with monopsonist minimum wage is just
induce efficient
transfers now that's all I want to say
about Labor markets I want to turn now
to Capital markets which are a degree
more complicated and therefore a degree
more
interesting the main reason they're
complicated is that
capital is not tangible the way labor is
labor you feel it you've done it it's an
hour of work you know what work is
capital what is it it's machines it's
buildings it's vague
thing so we're going to Now define
capital more
specifically by think about where
Capital comes
from where does the money come from to
buy machines to finally to invest what
goes all the way back to our farming
agricultural
economy farmers every year face a
decision are they going to
consume all of their crop or are they
going to save some of the some of it to
plant to create next year's
crop so farmers face a decision of
diverting today's consumption to
tomorrow's consumption or next year's
consumption how much of today's
consumption they want to give up how
much less they want to eat this year to
have more to eat next year and that
determines how many seeds they want to
set
aside that's what capital
is capital is
essentially what you take from
today to have in the future when you buy
a machine you are spending money today
to get the machine so over the next few
years it produces stuff that's no
different than saving your
seeds Okay that's what capital is is
essentially the diversion of current
consumption towards future
consumption now unlike the
farmer firms today don't get the money
necessarily from themselves like the
farmers did firms get their capital in
what's called a capital Market well I
just wrote that there firms get their
capital in a capital Market what is the
capital Market well that's a market with
his demand for
Capital which comes from how much which
I'll derve in a few minutes comes from
how much firms value the capital and a
supply of capital well where does supply
of capital come from what is capital
it's basically the money you
use to invest in the future where does
it come from it comes from us the supply
of capital is
savings so the money firms use to buy
their machines they borrow from
people and that is how the Capital
Market works so we talk about Capital we
really think of it fundamentally as
Financial Capital don't think of it
anymore as machines and buildings think
of it as Financial Capital the money you
want to
invest to divert today's consumption
Mars consumption it comes from the
savings that we do which is our decision
to divert today's consumption to
tomorrow's
consumption okay so just
as work just as workers decide how hard
to work and that drives the supply of
labor people decide how much to save and
that drives the supply of capital so
let's see that in figure
166 figure 166 is the capital market
equilibrium the demand for
Capital comes from the marginal revenue
product of
capital just like the demand for labor
comes the margin Revenue product of
labor the demand for Capital comes the
margin Revenue product of capital
how much will the next unit of capital
the next unit of financial investment
what will it yield in terms of the value
of what I'll
produce how much will the next machine
increase the quantity of goods and what
can I sell those goods for so the same
logic that applies to labor applies to
Capital the supply of capital comes from
workers
saving why do workers save they save
because they can get a return to that
saving in the form of
Interest I is the rate of interest
that's the return that workers get on
their savings so in other words you
could think of I the technical defition
of the interest rate is the rate that
firms have to pay you to get your
money I is the rate that firms have to
pay Savers to get them to
save okay so for example if the interest
rate is 10%
then if a house if I want to borrow a
dollar from a household this period I
have to pay them back a11 next
period let me by the way one
parenthetical comment time is a very
elastic Concept in this class man don't
be uptight in your thinking like the
dude says okay basically time sometimes
I'll say today tomorrow sometimes I'll
say this year next year it's all the
same man just means period one versus
period two so don't get too caught up in
the words I use just think of this as
period one versus period two
okay that's that's the key and I'll try
to use as much as I can but I say today
tomorrow this year next year it's all
the same thing okay so don't do too
caught up on the
terminology now basically the idea is
that the Su demand curve is downward
sloping as the interest rate
Rises firms want less
Capital because why because interest
rate Rising means that the opportunity
cost employing machine has gone up
because what can you do instead with
your money hire a
worker so an up a a downward sloping
demand curve for capital is basically
the rate at which firms are going to
trade off capital for labor as interest
State goes up they'll say fewer machines
more labor and St goes down they'll say
less labor more
machines the supply curve slopes up
because basically the more you pay
people to save the more they'll
save okay now let me pause for a second
we are we have a whole series of courses
in course 15 about the about Finance I'm
doing Finance in like a lecture and a
half here okay and if you find this
interesting you take 1541 1542 the whole
series of course you take course 15 by
the way since all of you should really
go be econ Majors you get economics
elective credit for a couple of those
courses you can Eon major and take some
course 15 courses if you want to learn
more more about Finance okay so
basically um but let's just talk about
this weird thing I'm talking about what
does it mean that people loan money to a
firm because we don't really necess loan
money to a firm in fact firms get their
money from people in three different
ways there's three different ways we can
essentially transfer our money to
firms one
way is we could put it in the
bank okay you put your money in the bank
the bank pays you an interest rate
firms then go to the bank and borrow the
money from the bank so we're not direct
leaving the money to the firms we're
doing it through an through a financial
intermediary which is the bank so the
most common way people get money to
firms is by having money in the bank you
don't know that you just think you're
got a bank account yielding whatever but
that's what you're doing you're just
giving money to
firms the second way you can do it is
you can actually directly loan the money
to the firm by buying corporate
bonds okay a corporate bond is literally
a loan to a firm now typically most of
us who aren't Super Rich won't buy a
corporate bond will buy a financial
instrument that holds corporate bonds
okay so I have a Vanguard bond fund
Vanguard is a company that holds
financial instruments so I own a little
piece of a lot of bonds okay bonds are
like millions of dollars I'm not gonna
own a bond but I own a little piece of a
bunch of them okay so I'm sort of that's
the way you directly loan to a firm and
then finally you can buy stocks which is
another way directly probably the most
direct way to give money to a firm you
can only buy a share in a firm you can
go out tomorrow you can buy a share in
apple you get a piece of paper that says
you own a share of Apple okay you've
given Apple your money what are they
giving you back they're giving you back
two
things the first is they're giving you
back the promise that their price of
that stock will go up that if you buy
what Apple stock let's say Apple stock
today selling at 100 I don't know what
selling at okay it's probably much more
than that selling at a 100 if I buy for
100 then what that means I give Apple
$100 they give me a share why do I do
that because I think in five years Apple
will be worth
150 and then I could sell that share to
someone else and get my
$50 okay in addition some old style
firms not the new firms old style firms
also sometimes will just send regular
checks to people on their stock called
dividends that happens less and less but
basically so I can put my money in the
bank the bank pays me Interest the fir
them borrow from the bank I can buy a
corporate bond the bond pays me Interest
okay it's a Rec direct loan or I can buy
stock in which case I give the money to
the firm and they pay me back by getting
more valuable or paying me a dividend
and that's essentially how I transfer
money to firms okay questions about
that
yeah interest
rate you relate the interest rate to the
slope I don't quite understand
yeah yeah exactly there's a mathematical
function uh essentially the demand curve
will be a negative function of interest
rates supply curve will be a positive
function of interest rates there's a
mathematical function just like other
demand and Supply
curves other
questions okay so
now let's come the demand part is sort
of uninteresting we know how to drive
this what you do is you take a
production function you'd set up a you
you would you would get a cost function
you could solve for the marginal revenue
product of capital okay you know how to
do that the the supply side is more
interesting and why is it more
interesting because once again
substitution income effects are going to
mess things up just like they did for
labor Supply they are going to do it for
savings and they're going to do so in
the framework of what we call
intertemporal
Choice which is your decision of how
much do you consume and how much do you
save so to do that let's go to figure
16 figure
167 and this diagram describes the
person's decision of how much to
save okay I'm just G this graphically in
section you're going to do the
math okay
individuals have a utility fun function
we talked about youtility function we
choose between two goods we always do
two element utility function make the
math easy talk about choos two goods we
talked about choos between consumption
and Leisure now we're talking about
choosing between consumption in Period
one and consumption in Period
two now the
tradeoff instead of being
between pizza and
cookies or being
between or being between work Leisure
and and consumption now between be
consuming today versus consuming
tomorrow and we understand the trade-off
the trade-off is that basically people
are by and large
impatient if you ask them would you
rather something today or tomorrow
they'd rather have it today okay there's
the famous marshmallow test they do on
little kids where they see if they'll
wait to get a marshmallow Okay most kids
don't humans are impatient okay we'll
come back to that in a few lectures talk
about how you model that but for now
let's just say humans are impatient on
the on the other hand humans need money
in both periods so let's do a simple
example imagine my income is $80,000 a
year okay and imagine I I can save that
money at 10% so Y is 80,000 and let's
imagine I only earn the income well okay
management income is 8,000 I can save
that at 10% and next year I want to stay
home take care of my
kids I don't want to
work so what that means my my income imp
Peri period one will be 80,000 but my
income in Period two will be
zero guess more complicate income in
Period two you'll see that in the
problem set okay my Inc in Period two
would be zero okay now my question is
what do I do well you could see that in
figure
167 one option is figure 167 has my
first period consumption on the xaxis my
secondary consumption the y axis one
option would be to consume everything in
Year One
and nothing in year two that's not very
attractive the other oper consume
nothing in year one in which case I
would have 88,000 in year two why
because I would save 80,000 on a 10%
interest so what's the tradeoff the
tradeoff is the interest
rate right or in other words what is the
price of First Period
consumption the price of First Period
consumption okay is minus
okay the price for consumption is minus
1 plus
I okay the price for once again I assume
all Goods have a price of one when I
came to price of goods this is what is
the relative price of First Period
consumption okay so assume the price of
consumption in Period one is one the
price of consumption in Period two is
one we're normalizing everything to make
our math easy throwing prices out okay
every it's just it's just we're thinking
in terms of goods effectively here so
what is the relative price of consuming
in Period one minus 1 plus I why is that
because for every dollar I consume in
Period one I give up one plus I dollars
in Period
two that is the opportunity cost of
first period consumption is not having
second period consumption once again
dismal
science every time you eat something
you're giving up the possibility of
saving that money eating more next year
okay just like there's a the price of
leisures the wage the price of First
Period consumption is minus one plus I
or the interest rate the amount of money
you could have the next
year okay so basically that is the
tradeoff that is representing the
interal Choice problem that's
represented by the slope of this budget
constraint which is minus1 plus I or
minus 1.1 in our example the slope of
the budget create represents the
opportunity cost of first period
consumption in terms of second period
consumption okay okay likewise I have
some indifference curve I have some
indifference curve which represents my
preferences over first and second period
consumption how impatient I am basically
okay so think of the Indi curve
basically being how impatient I am so
like with all these optimization
problems I know what to
do okay I find the tangency between the
indifference curve which is essentially
my impatience period one and two and the
budget constraint which is the market
rate at which I can trade off
consumption period one period two
remember going all the way back to
lecture one the idea of opportunity cost
is kind of like the concept of
alchemy where I'm not literally turning
period one consumption into period two
consumption physically but I'm
effectively doing it through opportunity
cost by not consuming in Period one you
get more in Period two so it's
essentially alchemy that happens through
the concept of opportunity cost in this
case it happens through saving in the
bank by Saving in the bank I turn a
dollar today into a1ar 10 tomorrow
dollar period one into a dollar 10 in
Period
two okay and that's what's happening
here so my optimal consumption in this
case is C1 in Period one so what do I do
I say well look given my impatience
level I want to consume C1 in Period one
in figure
167 what that means I'm going to save
80,000 minus
C1 what does that mean my period two
consumption is it means my period two
consumption is going to be the amount I
saved times one plus the interest
rate so it's going to be 1 plus I times
80,000 minus
C
C1 now once again let's remember the
trick I've done here without mentioning
it this lecture is supposed to be about
savings that's the first time I've
mentioned
savings why because savings is a
bad savings is something you just have
to do to get consumption period too no
one wants to save this one's even a
little more realistic for you guys
although you're probably probably still
frugal people but basically the idea
savings is not a good thing we don't
have a model where people it's not a
Scrooge McDuck model where people want
to swim in their money okay savings is
not a good thing savings is a is a
necessary tool to get consumption from
period one to period two it's a bad we
don't model bads we model Goods so we
don't model savings we model consumption
and then we get savings as a residual
so when you want to solve for savings
you model consumption and you get
savings as the residual just like when
you want to model work you solve for
leisure and get work as the
residual now let's ask what happens when
the interest rate goes up okay once
again I'm sorry I don't have time for
the math here but we'll do it in section
on Friday let's ask what happens when
the interest rate goes up will we move
from bc1 to
bc2 that has guess what two
effects on the one hand you get the
substitution
effect the substitution effect is the
price of First Period consumption has
gone up so you want to do less of it
focus on that remember I'm not talking
about savings I'm not talking about
second period consumption the subsid
income effects are purely in terms of
first period consumption C1 is what
you're maximizing over here the price of
First Period consumption is gone up why
is it gone up because the opportunity
cost's gone up you can have more in
Period two by Saving more so the
substitution effect necessarily says you
have less period one
consumption but what about the income
effect well consumption in Period two is
a normal
good I'm sorry consumption sorry
consumption period one is a normal good
cons period one is a normal good and are
you richer or
poor if the rate goes
up are you effectively richer or poor
effectively go ahead you know richer
you're effectively richer because every
dollar of savings yields more
money so the income effect says since
you're richer you want more of
everything what's one of the things you
want more of
C1 so the income effect goes the other
way you get the same sort of GIF and
good effects without
weirdness so actually whether a higher
interest rate raised or low and saving
is ambiguous once again think of the
intuition it's even easier intuition
here you're a kid you want a bike the
bike's going to cost 200 bucks you can
earn 10 bucks an hour so you work 20
hours to get the bike then you quit well
if you earn 15 bucks an hour you work
few hours because all you want is the
bike that would be a that would be a
downward sloping supply curve in that
case the interest rate rise would cause
you I'm not working I'm sorry let me
back up I did working going too fast
here you want a bike it's 200 bucks so
you got to save
$200 um you got to save $200 so if the
interest rate is
% then you have to save say you know one
you know uh you know 180 roughly this
year okay to get the bike next year this
rate 20% you'll have to save about 160
this year to get the bike next year okay
that's a b forget my old example I was
on labor so if you want the bike next
year for 200 bucks and this rates 10%
you got to save 180 but 20% you got to
save 160 so you're actually savings goes
down a higher interest rate causes
savings to go down that would be a
downward sloping supply curve so just
like labor Supply we don't know which
way the capital supply curve goes and
here unfortunately like unfortunately
unlike labor Supply we don't even have
good evidence we pretty much know that
labor Supply curves slope up but are
almost
vertical with with capital Supply curves
we actually don't
know it's a real empirical weakness in
economics so we are going to go ahead
and assume substitution effects Dominate
and generally draw upward slope opening
Capital Supply Curves in this course but
unfortunately we don't really know what
the capital supply curve looks like okay
I will stop there and we'll come back uh
next time and just continue discussing
we'll discuss how you should invest your
money so come back next time and learn
how you should invest your money