(upbeat music)
(music ending)
- All right, it looks
like we've got a quorum.
Welcome everyone to today's seminar.
I'm Craig Keast from
MIT Lincoln Laboratory,
and I'm actually happy
to introduce our speaker,
Sam Karlson, who is going to be telling us
about the work he and his teammates
have been doing on
using nitrogen vacancies
in diamond for magnetic imaging.
Sam, who's originally
from Denver, Colorado,
is a second lieutenant in
the United States Air Force
and also a master's student
in the nuclear science
and engineering department at MIT.
He holds a military fellowship out here
at Lincoln Laboratory where he is working
with our quantum information
and integrated Nanosystems group.
Sam received his BS in physics
from the United States Air Force Academy,
and he joined the MIT
family in the fall of 2022.
So I'd like to introduce Sam.
I will ask all the folks participating
to hold their questions until the end,
and we'll do the Q&A session
and you can either raise your hand
or write something in the chat,
and we'll make sure to
answer those questions.
So with that intro, Sam,
the screen is yours.
- Thank you, Craig, for that introduction.
As was mentioned, I'm a second lieutenant
in the United States Air Force
and I'm currently a
master's student here at MIT
in the Nuclear Science and
Engineering department.
And as Craig mentioned,
I am specifically working
at Lincoln Laboratory in
the quantum sensing team
with a focus on nitrogen
vacancy centers in diamond.
And in particular, my project specifically
focused on wide field magnetic imaging.
There are numerous applications
for wide field magnetic
imaging in a variety of fields
including biology, geology,
and material science.
Just a few mentioned that
I'm gonna mention here
include efforts to image neurons
and immuno magnetically labeled cells.
There are applications
for failure analysis
for integrated circuits,
as well as studying
the magnetic properties
of superconductivity in detail,
looking at vortices and their dynamics.
Magnetic imaging can also
be used in geophysics
to characterize remnant
magnetization in geological samples.
And there have been
demonstrations of magnetic imaging
for 2D magnetic materials
looking at magnetic (indistinct).
Nitrogen vacancy centers are created
by replacing a carbon with a nitrogen atom
and removing an adjacent carbon
atom in the diamond lattice.
These solid state systems are advantageous
over other quantum sensors,
because they operate at room temperatures
and do not require cryo cooling.
NV centers have stable energy levels
suitable for quantum control.
The ground state for this
system is a spin triplet state.
A green laser excites the system,
a non-radiating decay
pathway, preferentially
repopulates the MS equals zero state,
which enables initialization
of the quantum state.
And one of the advantages
of these quantum systems
is that measurements are
tied to physical constants,
which reduces the need,
which reduces uncertainty and
the need for calibrations.
In addition, as solid state sensors,
the NV centers are fixed in the lattice,
and that is especially important,
because it enables
spatially resolved imaging.
And in addition, the fixed orientation
of the NV centers in the lattice
makes NV diamonds native vector sensors.
So by addressing the different
orientations in the lattice,
you can create the full magnetic vector,
recreate and discover that.
The nitrogen vacancy center
becomes a magnetic sensor
when a resident microwave
field is applied to the system
which transfers population
to the MS = 1 state.
Since more population
is in the MS = 1 state,
fewer optical photons are emitted
as they return to the ground state
through the non-radiating decay pathway.
A static magnetic field
causes a Zeeman interaction
that splits the degenerate +/- 1 states
and increases magnetic sensitivity.
Any change to this external magnetic field
will change the resonant
condition of the system,
so scanning microwave frequencies
for this resonance condition
can be used to determine
changes in the magnetic field.
And as I mentioned previously,
these measurements are
tied to physical constants,
so that reduces the uncertainty
and makes it a more
valuable quantum sensor.
More advanced methods of
detecting the magnetic field
include pulse sequences,
and these pulse sequences
can improve sensitivity
and limit dephasing of the quantum system.
My research has specifically involved
using nitrogen vacancy centers in diamond
and these quantum systems for
wide field magnetic imaging.
Other quantum imaging techniques do exist
that can provide a magnetic image.
However, devices like the SQUID,
the superconducting
quantum interference device
operate at cryogenic temperatures.
And so to make magnetic
images at room temperatures,
they must be separated
from the imaged object,
which limits their spatial resolution.
Other methods like the hull probe, NV tip,
or raster scanning also
can provide an image
that has high resolution,
but they do not demonstrate
time dynamics the way
that a wide field imager can.
And so as I emphasize at the bottom,
only widefield imaging adds
spatiotemporal dynamics
to traditional magnetic
imaging techniques.
So the way that the
magnetic microscope concept
using NV centers and diamond works,
we start with our diamond,
which has a dense layer of
NV centers near the surface
where we put our sample of interest.
We then shine our laser
to optically initialize
and read out the quantum state.
As you can see here,
the laser enters the side of the diamond
and totally internally
reflects off the top surface.
This is advantageous
for a number of reasons,
including preventing
the sample of interest
from being damaged by
overheating from the laser.
We have some imaging optics
and a focal plane that
senses the fluorescence.
Fluorescence from a
specific region will pass
through the optics and land on the sensor.
The fluorescence from
each spot on the diamond
is mapped onto a pixel,
and that happens for each
spot and every pixel.
And so,
we place the sample
generating a spatially
varying magnetic field
on top of the diamond.
In this case, it's a spiral
made of conductive material
that we put a current through.
The NVs process at different rates based
on the magnetic field strength
and the fluorescence is
captured on the sensor
enabling us to map out the
wide field magnetic image.
This is the magnetic image
that we created when we
applied a 1-mil amp DC current
to the spiral structure.
And as I mentioned, so
some of the benefits
of this diamond magnetic microscope
is that you can use it
for temporal dynamics
of a changing magnetic field
and also reconstruct the full
magnetic vector at each point.
Here is a depiction of
the magnetic imager setup.
The bias magnets split the
energy levels of the NV system.
The green laser initializes
the quantum state.
The wires deliver resident
microwaves to the system.
The nitrogen vacancy
centers emit fluorescence
that is captured on a
digital focal plane array,
which is essentially the camera
that we use to detect the magnetic image.
And then here on the right is
an actual photo of our setup.
So we decided to use
our magnetic microscope
on a through silicon via test chip
that we fabricated here
at Lincoln Laboratories.
This is a visual photo of the chip,
and here is a schematic
that shows the chip itself.
As you can see, the current
travels back and forth
across chip in an alternating pattern.
And if you look at the bottom image,
you'll notice that as it does,
it comes in and outta the plane.
A changing in current
creates a magnetic field
leading to the magnetic
image that you see here.
So this is actually the magnetic image
that we were able to take
using our magnetic imager.
The alternating blue and red stripes
reference the direction of
the current through the chip,
creating positive and
negative magnetic field values
that correspond to the projection
along the NV axis we are measuring on.
Here is a video demonstrating the spatial
and temporal dynamics
of our magnetic imager.
We sent a signal current
through silicon via chip
that varies temporally
as a heartbeat signal.
You can see the magnetic field
strength change over time
and spike with each beat at
these two locations on the chip.
You can see the initial signal current
as well as the
corresponding magnetic field
and the upper box and the lower box.
Since the current is going
in opposite directions
at those points, they
have opposite positive
and negative magnetic field values.
This diagram shows accomplishments
of other quantum sensing methods
using nitrogen vacancy centers in diamond.
They have primarily been confined to DC
and low AC frequencies
below about 10 megahertz
or in the gigahertz frequency range.
As you may notice,
there's a fairly large gap
between these frequency ranges.
Recently there was a
paper that was published
demonstrating a method called
quantum frequency mixing,
which enables us to bridge the gap
and detect frequency ranges
previously inaccessible
by other quantum sensing methods
with nitrogen vacancy centers.
We applied this quantum
frequency mixing method
with our magnetic imaging method,
and this enabled us to make
magnetic images of structures
in this previously inaccessible
AC frequency range.
Here is a schematic diagram
of quantum frequency mixing
our magnetic microscope.
Quantum frequency mixing is analogous
to classical frequency mixing,
but it uses the quantum system itself
as the mixer since a classical mixer
is too bulky to be applied.
Here, the NV centers
serve both as the sensors
and as the mixer.
So as before, a green
laser illuminates a region
of nitrogen vacancy
centers in our diamond.
Different regions of the diamond sensor,
here, they're highlighted by
blue and red (indistinct) spins
respond to spatially
varying magnetic fields
from the test structure
and produce magnetic field
dependent fluorescence,
which is imaged onto a
sensor array using a set
of imaging optics all as
we did with the DC imager.
The frequency mixing works
by taking a signal field
and combining it with a bias field that
creates some indifference frequencies,
which allow us to down convert
the resonance frequency,
down convert to the resonance
frequency of our NV system.
At this resonance frequency,
population oscillations occur
between the two spin states,
the NV fluoresce,
such that the photo
luminescence oscillates
with a frequency
proportional to the amplitude
of the signal drive field.
So by obtaining this frequency,
we can determine the strength
of the magnetic field.
And here, our example test structure
generating a spatially
bearing magnetic field
is a Lincoln Laboratory (indistinct) logo
displayed at the sensor plane
with a corresponding image
of the logo projected at the focal plane.
Spatial variations and
field amplitude result
in variations in the Rabi
frequency from pixel to pixel,
allowing wide field
imaging of AC signal fields
at arbitrary signal frequencies.
Using this quantum
frequency mixing technique,
we were able to image
the same spiral structure
at AC frequencies up to 70 megahertz.
So here is a schematic
and a photo of the spiral,
which we created by depositing
conductive materials
on a glass microscope slide.
Here is an example image of
the detected Rabi frequencies
of the spiral at a signal
frequency of five megahertz.
At each pixel, we map
out the Rabi oscillations
of the NV fluorescence
and use a fitting function to
extract the Rabi frequency,
which is proportional to the amplitude
of the magnetic field.
The detected Rabi frequency
is inversely proportional
to the signal AC field frequency.
So at 50 megahertz signal,
the extracted Rabi frequency
is slower by a factor of 10
than for our 5 megahertz signal frequency.
We plotted this detected Rabi,
we plotted the detected Rabi frequency
against the applied signal
frequencies for a given pixel
demonstrating this inverse relationship.
We naively applied this
frequency technique
on the TSV circuit ship that we
had previously used for DC imaging,
and we quickly noticed that even
at low AC input signal frequencies,
we could not detect the same
magnetic field structure
as we could at DC fields
with the structure even less discernible
at higher frequencies.
After evaluating the device
on a network analyzer,
we concluded that the chip
likely had some capacitive
or inductive characteristic
preventing us from seeing the structure,
likely some capacitive short
that caused the input signal
to traverse a different
path through the TSV chip.
In the upper right, we
see the absolute value
of the magnetic field for a DC signal
compared to the detective Rabi frequencies
at AC frequencies below it,
with the Rabi oscillations
for two of the pixels
for our AC frequencies.
And our results here lead us to believe
that there may be some application
for this magnetic imaging technique
from impedance
characterizations in circuits.
You know, as we noticed that the,
we were able to visually
see differences in the DC
and the AC where the
current might be traveling.
So I wanted to just take a moment
and thank my MIT and Lincoln Lab advisors.
They've done an incredible
job in helping me with this,
not only just with our specific project
and this magnetic imaging,
but also just in developing as a scientist
and teaching me how to learn and grow
in the scientific method
and also just for being
incredibly supportive
and helpful throughout my entire venture.
So I wanted to give a special thank you
and shout out to Paula
Cappellaro, Danielle Braje,
Jennifer Schloss, Paul
Kehaylas, Andrew Maccabe,
and Matthew Steinecker.
They've just been
incredibly wonderful to me
and helpful through my
experience here at grad school.
And I wanted to thank everyone else
for listening and for hearing this talk.
- Thank you, Sam.
So we're now open for questions.
You can either do that by
raising your virtual hand
or putting it in the chat.
So as people are thinking about it, Sam,
I'm gonna start with a question.
In terms of spatial resolution,
what is sort of the spot size
that you can image using this technique
or that you've been able to image?
A lot of the features that
you showed were, you know,
reasonably large from a,
you know, sort of a
microelectronic standpoint,
but what kind of spot
size can you achieve?
- Right, right, thanks for that question.
So, and just so you know,
so like for the things
that we did image that we have shown here,
like the spirals,
the spirals are 50 microns in width
and like the actual,
the width of the conductive
material is 50 microns.
Here we, you know,
we initially did a test
on a 20 micron structure
and we actually haven't
characterized completely
the spatial resolution yet.
That's actually one of our next steps.
This is mostly a proof of principle
for the quantum mixing
technique on the imager itself.
And so that's kind of our
next step to determine
what the spatial resolution really
will be for these great mixing techniques.
- Great, thank you.
Any,
there's, again, one question.
Will the recording be
sent to us to watch again?
The answer is yes,
it will be posted in a week's time or so.
So there is a another
question here from May Kim.
Great talk, Sam,
I saw that there's heavy
dampening in the Rabi oscillations
and was wondering what that's due to
and whether that limits
the precision/resolution
of your measurement and
how can it be improved?
- No, that's a great question.
So yeah, the dampening
is due to the phasing
of the quantum system,
and that actually, you know,
was a potential limitation
for us in terms of being able
to detect the Rabi frequency,
especially as we go into higher
signal frequencies, right?
The defacing the system
causes the Rabi oscillations
to decay faster.
And so, you know, especially
up to 70, 80 megahertz,
we don't even get a full oscillation,
and it makes it harder to
extract that Rabi frequency.
And in terms of,
there are a number of things we can do
to improve that, right?
Removing gradients from the system,
we can, you know,
play some tricks and games
in order to kind of reduce
how quickly that gets stamped.
But ultimately that is a problem,
especially as we get into
these higher frequency ranges
that is,
makes it harder to detect that signal.
- Again, so number of questions
rolling in here now, Sam.
Are there limitations,
this is from Emil Patel,
are there limitations today
on diamond substrate size
and the density of the NV sites?
- There are actually,
I don't know the specific limitations
off the top of my head,
but there are limitations
to how, you know,
'cause these diamonds are grown.
It's a chemical CVD, chemical
vapor deposition, process.
That is how these,
the nitrogen vacancy centers are placed
in the diamond and you can only get to,
you know, a specific size.
Our diamond is about four
millimeters by four millimeters,
and it's about one inch in diameter
is like the total
limitation from what I know.
- So this comes, next question comes
from Colin Dunn, awesome talk.
What are the potential
real world applications
of your research?
And I know you actually
showed some of this on the first slide,
but maybe you wanna review those?
- Yeah, yeah, I'll go back.
I did kind of rush through
those a little quickly.
And so there's a number of applications
across a wide variety of fields.
The ones that we've
primarily been looking at
have been for integrated circuits
and seeing if we can use them
for like fault detection.
That's specifically what
we've been looking at.
Although, you know, as you can see here,
there are a number of
particularly biological
and biological applications
and you know, geology.
But yeah, we've been looking at,
especially for this quantum
frequency mixing technique,
it's, you know, circuits
that have signal fields,
you know, above 10 megahertz, right?
I mean, something we were discussing
was potentially like RF components
that might be useful for
seeing the magnetic field
for those components.
- All right, and the next couple
of questions actually come
from an anonymous attendee.
Again, thank you for your
very nice presentation.
Very impressive.
Just two questions for you:
to achieve Rabi oscillations
of some fixed frequency,
we have high or low signal frequencies
to use as well as magnetic
signals correspondingly.
What kind of combinations
will be preferred,
lower signaling frequency
or higher signal frequency?
- I'm sorry, could you
repeat that one more time?
- Yeah, that didn't make
much sense to me either,
so I'll read it again.
And to achieve Rabi oscillations
of some fixed frequency,
we have high or low signal frequencies
to use as well as magnetic
signals correspondingly.
Which kind of combinations
will be preferred,
lower signal frequency or
higher signal frequency?
- I'm still not entirely
sure I understood that,
but I think one thing to
emphasize is, you know,
in terms of this,
at least this mixing method, right?
We're,
try to run through here,
you know, we have a signal frequency
and a bias frequency,
and the combination of those two lead
to the resonance frequency of our system.
And so obviously we're
trying to detect signals
that are outside of the range
of other quantum sensing techniques.
And so, you know, we'd
want to use the combination
of the signal and bias frequencies
that allow us to access those frequencies
outside of that accessible range.
- And the sort of follow up
question here is can you,
I'm sort of translating here,
can you provide a little
bit more deeper details
on the spatial temporal dynamics
in your measurement technique?
- Yeah, the,
yeah, so I mean essentially
the way that it works, right?
And something like, you know,
these other scanning
methods like an NV tip,
you have to specifically
scan across the entire image,
you measure a single point,
and then move it and
measure another point.
And one of the beauties of this
wide field imaging technique
is that you take the entire image at once,
and so it allows you
to measure fast enough
that you can actually get
these temporal dynamics.
And you know, as you can see here, right?
This signal occurs over
the space of about,
you know, several hundred milliseconds
and there you can get a temporal,
sorry, you can get the
time dynamics of, you know,
of about sub millisecond resolution.
- Yeah, thank you.
What are the next steps in the project you
are hoping to achieve?
I think you mentioned some of this,
this is principally for integrating,
for imaging in integrated circuits.
Is that what you really hope to be doing?
- Right, and also, you know, we wanna,
so far we actually are
trying to apply this,
the temporal dynamics to
the AC frequency range.
So, so far we've taken images of our,
taking images at these
higher AC frequencies,
but we are looking to actually make
like a magnetic movie of these
AC frequency ranges as well.
- Next question.
How can you improve the
imaging process with diamond?
Because inside the diamond,
I need light perform multi
reflection by diamond,
so I think this is the fact
that you have multiple passes,
internal reflection through the diamond.
How does that sort of boost your,
I guess your signal,
the fact that you're doing
total internal reflection
within the diamond?
Like that's what they're trying to ask.
- Oh, how does it boost the signal?
I do know that there's a way for it
to actually increase the contrast
by the way that it
totally interlink reflects
and that it's, you know, not,
I mean, part of it is it's not
illuminating the sample itself, right?
Which as I mentioned also
prevents it from overheating,
but also allows more light to actually
fluoresce back down to the focal plane.
- Okay.
Let's go on to this next one here.
How does the measurement of
vector magnetic field work?
Was it using configurations,
the NV diamond centers,
and are these known beforehand?
I think this is probably referenced
to the diamond structure, right? Yeah.
- Yeah, so the way that
works is the NVs are,
there are four different orientations
in the diamond lattice.
And so by addressing different
orientations and you,
but you basically can
measure the amplitude
of magnetic field in
different orientations
and by using that,
you can compile it together
to make the full magnetic vector.
- Okay, the next question has to do
with the temperature of the measurements.
What temperature was the
spiral conductive material at,
and what are the temperature limitations
of the device that you're describing?
- So the,
I mean, the spiral was
measured at room temperature,
although that being said,
we used about,
the laser actually going
through the diamond is
one watt at the diamond.
And so there was some additional heating
of the spiral based off of that,
just kind of it being right next to it.
Although realistically, you know,
we're hoping to kind of
remove that heating element
and make it so that it's just
measured at room temperature.
And sorry, what was that last part?
What are the limitations?
- Yeah, what are the
temperature limitations
of the device?
I would assume that
temperature limitations
for the device under tests, like-
- Oh yeah, I mean,
I think specifically for the spiral,
the spiral is just a,
like I said, conductive, you know,
some metal layers on a
glass microscope slide.
And so I mean it's just as
much heat as that can take,
which is pretty significant.
I mean, I don't think we're
gonna fry the glass slide
or the, you know,
unless you evaporate the
conductive material off the slide.
I think, you know, we're pretty well
within the heat limitations.
- Yeah, yeah, I think the question is,
I mean, is there a
limit to the temperature
of the sample that
you're trying to measure?
I mean, does it have to be
within a certain temperature range?
- Oh, no.
- No, okay, okay.
Next question from Dane.
Great to see the amazing
progress on this project.
In the TSV image,
I was noticing some
heterogeneity across the image.
Is this due to non-uniform excitation
in homogeneous magnetic fields, et cetera?
- I think Dane's referring
specifically to the,
like the specific,
I think he could either be referring
to the bumps or to the-
- I, again, I don't know if these people
can chime in and ask
the question themselves,
but as I look at this image, right?
It does vary as you move
along the signal path, right?
So you move through the VHA,
and it's, you know, much more pronounced
in that top row,
maybe less so the intensity is different
from row to row, right?
- Right, right,
so that in itself could
be a number of things.
I mean, one is how the TSV chip
is actually placed on the diamond.
There might be some spots
that are a little closer,
the beam spot itself,
there has,
it could be how close
the TSV chip is to it.
I mean, we've also
pushed this TSV chip back
and forth on the diamond numerous times.
And so, you know,
the wires themselves might
move just a little bit
creating differences in the magnetic field
at certain points.
So there's a number of
reasons why the chip itself
might have slightly
varying magnetic fields
at different spots.
- And Dane actually has a
follow up question here.
Also, what sensitivity are you getting
for the QFM relative to the
record values on the chart?
- So we haven't characterized
the sensitivity yet
for the AC signals.
It's not gonna be as
good at DC particularly,
mostly because we're limited
by the noise in the signal itself.
And so the, you know,
our ability to make time
average measurements
with greater sensitivity
is limited by how much
noise is in the signal.
- Next question.
What is the impact of boron
and phosphorus, dope diamond,
on NV center properties?
- Could you say that one more time?
- They're asking the question is,
what is the impact of doped diamond,
either boron or phosphorus doped diamond,
on NV center properties?
- Mm, I actually don't
know much about that.
- There's a follow on,
could minute changes in
temperature be detected?
- Mm.
Yeah, so when we make these measurements,
we specifically find
the resonance frequency
for each signal frequency.
And so, you know, if,
basically when we take our measurement,
we make sure that we are on resonance.
And so if the temperature changes,
we'll be able to detect the change
in resonance for the system.
- And the question is how
sensitive a temperature
change do you think
you'd be able to detect?
- Oh, that's a great, like, in terms of,
I mean, yeah, that's
something I'd probably
have to think about it.
The resonance frequency changes,
some number like -70 kilohertz per Kelvin
or something like that, and so,
but I don't know off the top
of my head exactly what that is.
- So, the next question
has to do with the depth
of field of the imaging system.
So you're,
how deep within an object
can you measure the
magnetic field, I guess?
- That's a great question.
So the,
one of the limitations
of this technique is that you actually,
the standoff distance has to be very close
in order for you to be able
to sense the magnetic field
with high resolution.
And so, you know,
we're normally, you know,
for the spiral images,
we're about 60 microns away.
If you are much farther,
say you're 100 or you
know, 200 microns away,
you're better off using a
different sensing technique
like the superconducting
quantum interference devices,
SQUIDs or something else because you know,
that's just one of the
advantages of those systems
is that you need to be further away.
And so yeah, for this technique,
you wanna be as close as you can.
- Yeah.
- To the diamond.
- So question from Arthur Lobo,
has MIT Lincoln Laboratory
developed a low swap NV
center diamond magnetometer
for magnetic anomaly navigation?
- I am not sure.
I'm sure that someone somewhere
is working on something like that.
- Okay, all right.
So,
also what is the temporal resolution
and what controls that?
What controls the temp
temporal resolution? Yeah.
- Oh, that's a great question.
So for the,
I know it can be the temporal resolution
of sub milliseconds.
For, you know,
for
ours in particular, it's about,
you know, what's it's about?
It's on the order of milliseconds
and that kind of depends on
the,
like our,
the length of our pulse sequence,
the camera frame rate, the,
yeah, how many images we take.
- Okay, and in this next question,
I think you've already answered,
but I'll ask it,
what are the environmental conditions
for your measurements, EG
vacuum, cooling, cryo, et cetera?
- This is just room temperature.
No cryo, no vacuum.
- Curious, there appears to be-
- But one point on that I'd like to add is
that you can translate that to a cryo,
you could put it in a cryo environment.
- There appears to be increased emphasis
for high quality visual
output of scientific data
among various scientific research topics.
You mentioned the magnetic movie.
What purpose would this serve?
- Yeah, that's a great question.
I think the,
I think any, you know,
we talked about circuit
and fault detection, right?
And so if you're looking for changes
in the magnetic field for whatever reason,
I think being able to see that,
you know, within a few milliseconds
could be advantageous for
circuit fault detection.
- Okay, next question.
What are the challenges
in building arrays,
ensembles of these NV
diamonds sensor magnetometers?
- What are the,
could you say that one more time?
- The challenges in building
arrays of these devices.
I think you are, you know,
you have a planar surface
of these NV centers
that you're imaging with
a focal plane, right?
So I guess-
- But like multiple diamonds
in a row or like an array?
- I think that's the way I
guess it would interpret it,
arrays of these ensembles.
Maybe that's building a
very large magnetic imager.
So for example, let's say you wanted,
you know, magnetic image of body
or something like tiling
these things together.
- I mean,
well, I think they would get
very expensive very quickly.
I think one of the problems you'd have
is you'd need a lot of
lasers to address each one.
Yeah, the,
yeah, so you'd need,
I mean, you know,
'cause there are limitations to how,
as I mentioned, how large
you can grow the diamond
and if you just put a
bunch of diamonds in a row
and you address them all
with a bunch of lasers,
you'd need a lot of lasers,
had a lot of laser power
or one giant laser,
but that would be very
expensive, very quickly, so-
- Next question, do you have to compensate
for the earth's magnetic field?
- Yeah, so in our calibrations,
we account for the magnetic
field of the earth.
- And the last question.
Great talk.
And again, I agree with that.
What are the methods for
increasing the contrast
in the high frequency range?
- Oh, I mean, the,
so I mean, one of the things,
you know, there are a number of ways
to increase the contrast.
The, I mean, something we've just been,
you know, this is something
we need to explore
on how to do better,
but it's, you know, not a problem.
I mean, you can put more
signal through the device
and obviously that'll lead
to a greater contrast.
You can increase the amplitude of your,
the microwave fields that
you apply to the diamond.
You know, there are a number
of ways that the contrast
can be improved,
reduce, yeah.
- One last question snuck in here
and then we'll call it at this.
How far does the sensor have to be
from the magnetic field
and sort of at what
distance can you no longer
do the imaging?
'Cause you do, in this particular case,
show your device right on
top of the diamond, so.
- Right, yeah, no, you know,
as close as possible after, you know,
if you're, even just a
couple hundred microns away,
you're starting to get
to the point where the,
you start to lose your ability
to make magnetic images
with high spatial resolution.
- Right, hey, Sam, thanks again
for an excellent, excellent presentation
and I do wanna remind everybody
that the next seminar is
scheduled for Tuesday, April 9th
and the slot is open.
So if you know anybody
who might be interested
or if you're interested,
please contact Cherise.
She just put her email contact in the chat
so that we can,
how about a presentation in April.
So again, I thank everybody
for their time today
and have a good day.
Thanks, Sam.
- Thanks, Craig.
(chips falling)