hey everyone my name is Paul Bosco head
of product at project
us. the AI that makes us
better are you a chess player AI can
outplay you are you a web developer AI
can do a week's worth of coding in
nearly 45 seconds yes AI is fast cheap
and quite good at nearly any
job but are we asking the right
questions What If instead of asking how
AI is better than us we ask how AI can
make us
better emerging from the MIT media lab
project US is an AI system designed to
help make us humans the best versions of
ourselves so how does it work project us
sits in the background of any virtual
meeting it ingests a broad range of Bio
signals including word choice body
language breathing and heart rate
the system continually learns about you
and provides ongoing feedback on your
behaviors and as we improve individually
the organizations we work with become
more cohesive creative and
productive so where are we today in
20123 we spun out from the MIT media lab
we raised our first round of funding and
oversubscribed our round we're now
partnering with over 10 organizations to
help support their talent development
initiatives
meet Julie a chief executive at one of
these client companies Julie's been
using project US during her day-to-day
meetings to help support track and
identify Target
behaviors after just one month of usage
on the product we observed a 32%
increase in these targeted
behaviors and this data can be
anonymized and aggregated to help
organizations understand the real
challenges faced by their teams and best
of all this data doesn't come from a
poll survey it's not self-reported it's
real quantitative data from your team
interactions it's been an honor to help
grow this company with my friends and
colleagues and to be recognized by some
of the leading organizations in the
world such as the UN Nvidia uh and the
NSF so now we're looking to partner with
organizations we're sector agnostic we
can work with truly any sized company
and we can deploy in almost any
environment we're looking for companies
to form strategic Partnerships and to
deploy Pilots if you're interested stop
by the booth and please reach out