Hello everyone, I am Daniela Rus, I'm the
Director of the Computer Science and Artificial
Intelligence Laboratory at MIT and I'm delighted
to welcome all of you to this week's edition of
the CSAIL Forum. And so this week I am especially
delighted to welcome Professor Manish Raghavan,
who is a professor at the MIT Sloan School of
Management and also in the MIT Schwarzman College
of Computing. His research focuses on the social
and ethical dimensions of algorithmic decision
making and he is very interested
in a wide range of applications
with social implications like hiring,
admissions, consumer lending and more.
And in order to enable these applications,
he studies how automated systems influence
human decision making and how to
design algorithms that are fair,
transparent and aligned with human
values. And so with this, I would like to
turn the spotlight on to Manish, but before
I do so, I would like to ask you to please
be an engaged audience. Please put
your name and location in the chat.
Please add comments and questions to the
chat and we will have time for Q&A at the
end of the talk. And so I would love
for everyone to contribute at least
one question or one comment during the
talk. And so with that, let's get going.
Manish, please take it away. Great,
thanks so much for having me. It's
great to be able to participate here.
Can everyone see my screen
okay? Yes? Okay, good. So yeah,
I'm super excited to be talking to all of
you. Today I'm going to talk about some
work we've been doing on measuring the
diversity of information present in AI
systems and how to think about how to combine
information effectively from different sources.
So the main question I want to be trying
to answer today is what is the role that
heterogeneous information plays in AI
systems? And I'll give you a couple
illustrations of what this might look like or
what I mean by heterogeneous information. So one
type of application that we like to think about,
especially for those of us who like to think about
societal implications of AI systems, is what
happens when you put AI and humans together,
right? What does the combination of humans
and AI look like and how should you think
about structuring their collaboration to be
effective? And a very simplified view of this
takes the following approach. Your AI systems
know something, right? They have some set of
information that they have access to and they have
some set of things that they're good at doing.
Human agents in your system also have
some information. They have some set
of things that they're good at, they
have a set of things that they know,
and there's some overlap between what a human
knows and what an AI knows or what a human
is good at and what an AI system is good at.
But there's also some disjoint part of that.
And so the question is when we bring these
two different actors with different properties
together, can we create a combined system that
takes advantage of both of their strengths
and use that to complement each other's
weaknesses? A name that you often hear
for this type of interaction is complementarity,
which is when a joint system between an AI model
and a human agent does better than either in
isolation. So that's the the end goal of what
we might be trying to achieve. And you can
see how reasoning about the different sets
of information available to these agents might
allow us to build more complementary systems.
The second thing I'll be talking about a
little bit today is what is the role of
systems that have lots of different AI models
in them? In particular, if we have a system or
an ecosystem where we have lots of AI models
or lots of different AI agents, to what extent
are they actually acting independently from each
other? And if they're all operating on some shared
underlying information set, does that create some
sort of risk or vulnerability or potential for
mistakes that we would want to try to mitigate
somehow? And so an example of this is to say,
yes, you know, we have a bunch of different AI
models, but it actually turns out that they all
know the same thing, or they're all going to
make the same mistakes, they're all going to
behave in the same way. Would it be better if we
swapped out one of those models or some of those
models for a different AI agent or a different
model which maybe knows something slightly
different? And maybe it knows a little bit
less, maybe it's a little bit worse of a model,
but it has non-overlapping information with
the rest of our models, and somehow we might
be able to combine all these things to build
a more robust overall system. So these are the
two different perspectives we're going to try to
take on information diversity in AI systems today.
We're going to talk a little bit about
human-AI collaboration and how to leverage
these complementary information
sets to make better decisions,
and then we'll broaden a little bit to systems
of AI models or ecosystems of AI models and
try to understand what sort of properties do
they have when they interact with each other.
So on this first topic of human-AI collaboration,
I'm going to talk about some of our work that's
partly theoretical, and then I'll talk about a
case study we did in a medical decision-making
context. And this is joint work with Rohan,
who's a student here, Lauren, Derek, and Dennis,
who are doctors at the Yale School of Medicine,
and David Rudd, who is also a PI here at MIT.
And the starting point for this discussion
on human-AI collaboration is a long-standing
paradox that I've been fascinated
with for for quite a while now,
which is this resolution of how we think about
clinical versus statistical prediction. And
so we've known for a very long time, for
decades, that even very simple algorithmic
predictions often outperform humans. If you just
measure the accuracy of a logistic regression,
it tends to be about as good or competitive with
human experts in any decision-making domain.
There's a bunch of recent evidence on this, but
again, it goes back for many decades. And so I'm
thinking about tasks like predicting risk
in a medical context. So given a patient,
how likely is this person to have an adverse
event or to need some sort of intervention?
And yet, despite the fact that our even simple
risk prediction algorithms tend to be quite good,
in many of these contexts, we still
maintain discretion with humans.
And there's a lot of good reasons why we might
want to do this, why we might want humans to
make final decisions. There might be legal
requirements or some liability reasons that
we actually need to have a person accountable
for these decisions. It might be the case that
it's really hard to measure exactly what
is the thing that we're optimizing for.
So when I say algorithms have at least as
good accuracy, that is with respect to one
particular measure that we might care about.
One metric of, let's say, adverse events. But
there might be objectives that we have that go
beyond purely predicting these adverse events.
So perhaps there are other reasons
why we don't want algorithms to have
complete control or autonomy. A different
reason though, and one that's been pointed
out a lot in the literature, is that
algorithms are simply not sufficiently
individualized. That even though they do a
good job of making aggregate predictions,
on any individual case, human experts
might have some subjective information
or contextual information about that case
that allows them to make better predictions.
So maybe they get to observe a patient, they
can talk to them, they can see if they're
acting any differently, the patient can point
to exactly where they're experiencing pain,
anything like that. These are pieces of
information that are just generally quite
hard to encode into algorithms, and as a result
we don't include them typically in the information
set available to an algorithm. And so this is
going to be the reason that we focus on today.
To what extent are algorithms not sufficiently
individualized, and when they're not, how do
we build joint systems that incorporate both
algorithmic and human expertise? So I mentioned
that we're going to talk about differing sources
of information. A simple explanation of why we
have different sources of information is that
typically when we build machine learning models
and AI systems on top of them, the information
that gets fed into these systems come from tabular
data sets for the most part, or standardized data.
And so these are often maybe fairly comprehensive.
We have lots of individual attributes that
get measured, but they're standardized,
which means we have effectively a spreadsheet
with a row for every patient and a column for
every attribute that we're measuring, call it
blood pressure, whatever other sort of standard
markers are relevant for your particular case
in EHR. These are standard columns that we just
measure for every patient, and what that means
is it's necessarily narrow. So even though we've
seen a lot of patients, we don't observe that
many different things about them all the time.
And I'll show you an example in a little bit where
the standard models that we use only use roughly
nine predictors, if I recall, from somebody's
EHR. And so those nine things don't fully
summarize the entire patient. You can't compress
a patient down into nine attributes about them.
In contrast, when a doctor looks at a case, their
information is going to come from the real world,
not just from data that's been
provided. So they can talk to
the patient, they can ask them for more
information. It's often idiosyncratic.
So if the patient points and says it hurts exactly
here, I don't really know how to turn that into a
column in a data set, and not every doctor is
going to get that piece of information. If we
tried to encode all this into a tabular data set,
we would just end up with a lot of missing values,
and it would be really hard to do any machine
learning. And so what you end up with is these
really wide data sets, in a sense, or wide
ranges of observations, but it's heterogeneous.
It's going to be different across patients,
and they're somewhat subjective as to how
these things are being measured anyways.
Okay, as you can see why it might be hard
to combine these sources of information
together. Now a canonical scenario,
and in fact the scenario that we're going
to be describing later, is the following.
A patient shows up at a hospital and talks
to a doctor. This patient has some sort of
problem, and let's say we're talking about
a triage case where they're going into
urgent care. So this person
has some sort of problem.
The doctor gets to look at them and decide, does
this person, is this person healthy enough to be
sent home and just say, you know, wait it out,
it's going to be okay? Or should they be admitted
to the hospital? Okay, so this is an ER triage
decision that gets made at every hospital all
the time. And in the past, this would have been
a purely subjective decision from this expert,
right, from this physician who looks
at the patient, uses their expertise,
uses standards of care to decide what
should we do in this case. Increasingly,
you now have cases where we build risk models
that say, not only does this doctor get to take
a look at this patient, but we can feed their
vital statistics and other information from
their electronic health record into an algorithm,
and that is going to offer us a risk prediction.
But I don't immediately know what to do with
these two pieces of information now, because
the doctor is going to have some subjective
intuition or some belief that gets formed by
interacting with this patient. This algorithm is
going to output some number, and that's going to
represent the algorithm's so-called belief about
this patient's risk, but these are not really
speaking the same language. It's hard to integrate
these these pieces of information together.
And so again, we have this situation where
the doctor has some information, right,
something that they're good at, they know some
stuff about the patient from that interaction,
and our algorithm has some information, right,
whatever we fed it and whatever information comes
from the historical data set on which it's been
trained. And what we want to do is ask, how do we
achieve complementarity between these information
sets and the predictions that are being made on
top of them? Okay, how do we do better than either
of them combined in some sort of joint system?
Now there's some important considerations that we
have to keep in mind here. One is that, you know,
ideally what we would, in a sort of idealized
computer scientist's mind, what you would say is,
well, get the doctor to tell you an estimate
for how risky they think this patient is,
get the algorithm to tell you an estimate
for how risky this patient is, and do some
sophisticated averaging where you say, well, the
true risk is probably somewhere in between those.
The problem with doing this is it's really hard
to get humans to have well-calibrated probability
estimates. Some doctors might overestimate
risk, some doctors might underestimate risk,
people are in general bad about telling
you probabilities that reflect their
actual beliefs. So you can't really rely
on doctors to be able to say, here is a,
you know, 0.5 risk means 50% chance that
this adverse outcome is going to occur.
It's also hard for now to go in the
other direction, to ask this algorithm
to meaningfully explain why it thinks
someone is high risk, and even if you can,
it's really hard to use that information
or expect a doctor to use that information
to reconcile their beliefs with the information
coming out of an algorithm. We also have to worry
about the limitations that we'd have different
objectives. A doctor is balancing lots of things
like availability of ER beds and all sorts
of other considerations with the hospital,
whereas an algorithm is purely designed
to predict one objective or one thing.
And of course, this problem that information
from humans from doctors may not be standardized,
right? Again, one doctor might tell you one
thing, one might tell you another thing,
maybe they don't even really have a good
estimate of risk, but they just say, you know,
the fact that it hurts in this particular spot
seems kind of bad to me, and because it seems
like that could be something that's going to
require surgery or something like that. Okay,
so there's all sorts of things that make this
a hard problem. I'll summarize for you what our
approach has been in this type of setting and then
talk to you a little bit about where that's going.
And so this is on work that Rohan has
really led. Our approach is something
like the following. We're going to
try to extract all the information
that we can using some sophisticated
algorithms from the data that we get.
So we're going to train our own machine learning
model using a pretty large data set and pull out
all the information that we can from that. And
if you're interested in the specific techniques,
we're using ideas from the computer science
theory literature on multi-calibration,
which basically say capture all of the predictive
information available to some class of functions,
some researcher-defined class
of functions. So you could say,
for instance, I am going to train
a model that squeezes out all the
information available to any depth three
decision tree or something like that.
So you specify some family of functions
and say using that family of functions,
I get to pull out all the information that I
can. Now, this still leaves you with a bunch
of residual uncertainty because the data that
you have don't fully explain all the variance in
the outcomes that you see. And so the question
is, can doctors actually explain more of that
variance for you? And in particular, are there
specific groups of patients where they're really
good at telling you, telling apart patients
who are otherwise indistinguishable to us? And
are there groups of patients where they don't
really have a lot of predictive signal? Now,
if we knew the answer to that, we could allocate
physician time more effectively and decide here
are the cases where it's useful to actually
get a doctor to tell you what they think,
and here are the cases for which that's
not going to add a lot of information.
And so then what we can do is selectively
incorporate and selectively elicit that
information. So here are the patients for
which we need a doctor to give an opinion,
here are the patients for which we already kind of
know what's going to happen, and the doctor isn't
going to be able to explain any of that residual
uncertainty. And so effectively what we're doing
is say, what is all the information available
to the algorithm? Let's condition on that,
and then selectively incorporate the
information available to the physician.
And so visually, in this part of the space where
there's overlap between what the doctor knows and
what the algorithm knows, our algorithms already
know enough. There's not a lot of additional
information that we're getting out of physicians.
But in this part of the space, the doctors know
something that the AI doesn't know, and we should
be careful about when we choose to automate.
And if we, and instead we might solicit that
information from doctors and defer to their
expertise. Okay, I'll put to you that this is a
fairly flexible framework, and I'm going to give
you an illustration of how it works in a second.
In the following sense, we don't know a priori how
much overlap there is between what doctors know
and what robots know or what AI systems know.
And so it could be the case that we live in this
world, where eventually we want to automate more
and more of these decisions because the doctor
doesn't really know anything beyond what our
AI systems can do. Or alternatively, most
of the signal that the doctors are using
is already captured by the data observable
to these AI systems. In this type of world,
we would automate more decisions and
there would be less physician discretion.
But we could also live in a world that looks like
this, right, where there actually isn't a lot of
overlap between what doctors know and what our
AI systems know. And maybe our AI systems don't
actually know that much because they simply
don't have enough contextual information.
If this is what the world looks like, we
should be automating fewer decisions and
we should exercise more physician discretion,
okay? And so this is the type of thing that
we're trying to do here, is distinguish
between what sort of world we live in.
Now I promised you I'd give you an application
of this, and so the concrete setting that we're
going to be looking at is GI bleeding
and emergency triage for GI bleeding.
There's a standard risk predictor in this setting
called the Glasgow Blatchford bleeding score,
and these are all of the covariates that go into
it, or all of the information that our algorithm
knows. So it knows one, two, three, four, five,
six, seven, eight, nine things about this patient,
okay? It's not a lot of information,
but it turns out it's still, you know,
enough to make reasonably accurate predictions,
at least on aggregate, right? And actually if
you benchmark this particular algorithm, it does
roughly as well at predicting high risk as your
average doctor, okay? So it's hard to tell whether
your algorithm is better on average than a doctor.
But despite this, what we're going to be looking
for is, are there particular groups of patients
where the doctors know more than the algorithms
do, okay? And so that's what our meta framework
is heading towards here. Instead of using this
off-the-shelf algorithm, we're going to build
our own that's really going to squeeze out
all the predictive performance we can get,
and leave us with these groups of patients
for whom we can't actually tell the difference
based on the data available, right? They
look so similar that no algorithm that we
train is sufficiently good at distinguishing
between their risks, okay? So we're going to
end up with these groups of patients. Now
for each group of patient, we don't really
know how to distinguish between them, and
so we're just going to ask a doctor, right?
Are doctors actually better than random at telling
you which patients are high risk or not? If so,
this is a clear signal that the doctors have
information that our algorithm simply does not.
So I'm going to show you the results of
what happens when you do this. Here I have,
there's this, our algorithm, the way that we've
designed it ended with seven groups of patients,
okay? So it's for every patient it
puts into one of these seven buckets,
and what I'm plotting here is how much
correlation there is between what the
physicians tell us versus the actual outcomes
in each of these buckets, okay? And I'll give
you a second to look at this. What you should take
away from this is in almost all of these buckets,
there's meaningful variation being explained
by the doctors that is otherwise unexplainable
to our algorithms, because remember, everybody
within a bucket looks roughly the same from our
algorithms perspective, but they actually look
quite different from a doctor's perspective.
Now there is one exception to this, which is the
highest risk subset, so subset number seven over
here. You notice that there's actually no
variation that's by physician performance,
and what this means is those are the patients
who are so high risk that physicians consistently
predict that yes, these people need to be
hospitalized, these people are going to have
adverse events. There's actually no point, none
of them in our data set end up getting sent home.
They all get hospitalized, and so this should
already start to make you think that well, if
the physicians consistently say that every single
one of these patients should be hospitalized,
why are they sitting around in the ER waiting
to see a triage doctor before they can then be
admitted to the ER instead of just being directly
admitted because their risk score is so high,
and so that's the kind of thinking that we're
going towards here. We can automate some of
these decisions effectively for free. These are
these highest risk patients that are spending a
lot of time waiting around in the ER when
in fact they could be directly admitted.
No physician is going to disagree
with this high risk estimate,
and so what this allows us to do is effectively
trace out the space of possible policies. What
are the admission policies that a hospital
might have based on an algorithm like this,
and I'll plot this out in terms of a few
objectives that hospitals tell us they
care about. Two of these objectives are pretty
standard in the machine learning literature.
They're objectives related
to the errors that you make,
so what are your false positives and true
positives look like, so basically what is
the performance of the system in terms of its
errors. Now one thing that's pretty common in
this sort of medical setting is that hospitals
require really really high true positive rates,
so policies need to be at least at a 99% true
positive rate, so of the people who really
need to be hospitalized you want to be catching
almost all of those, and so all of the reasonable
policies that a hospital would actually consider
you should think of towards the very top of this
plot. The third axis that I'm plotting here in
color is how many of these cases we can automate.
What fraction of the time do we need
to ask a doctor or have a patient wait
in a waiting room to see a doctor before
they can either be admitted or discharged,
and you can see that there's some variation in
our policies based on this. I've highlighted
two policies here which are in the realm of
what might almost be reasonable to deploy
in a hospital. Now I should stress that we
haven't deployed any of these policies here.
The hospital that we're working with still
has a doctor look at every single case,
so this is more of a forward-looking thing
of what policies in the future might you
be willing to deploy. In the policy
that I've highlighted here in blue,
the summary statistics are as follows. We
automate nearly all of the cases, right,
so 86% of the time we just follow the
algorithm's recommendation for hospitalization.
This achieves a true positive rate of a
little over 97% and a false positive rate
around 50%. Now you remember I told
you that this is not good enough. You
need at least on the order of 99% to be even
willing to deploy a policy in this setting.
So it is a lot of automation, possibly
more automation than we should be doing,
and it gets slightly lower true positive rate
as a result. So this is on the brink of what
might be reasonable, but we would still
need to have a better algorithm in order
to be able to deploy this. We're not ready to
do this level of this scale of automation yet.
On the flip side, we have a much more conservative
policy that only automates a small fraction of
cases, right, and in particular if you recall
that plot I showed you on the previous slide,
it automates all the high-risk cases. So
anyone who's high risk in that highest tier
of risk gets automatically admitted to the
ER. Now this turns out to exactly match up
with the hospital's existing policy, and what
that means is all those high-risk patients,
yes they were waiting to see a doctor, but then
they were all getting admitted to the ER anyways.
None of them were getting sent home, and so this
matches the current policy's true positive rate
of 99.7 percent. So this is in the realm of
what a hospital would consider deploying or
their actual operating characteristics today. Now
the interesting thing about this is in a lot of
the literature it suggests that you might want
to automate some of these low-risk cases where
the AI is very confident that somebody's low
risk, you should be able to send them home,
and that's the type of policy that hospitals are
somewhat hesitant to deploy because you could
imagine if people are getting automatically sent
home and then somebody suffers some complication,
that's not a good place to be, right, but this
policy actually has the opposite flavor that
you're really automatically admitting all
of the highest risk patients, and this is
perhaps in contrast to some of the literature on
what you should expect to see in these medical
risk algorithms, but more importantly it is
conservative, and that conservatism is actually
a good thing from a hospital's perspective, and
so again this is more in the realm of possibility
of what you might be willing to deploy,
and importantly you are automating these
high-risk cases where people would otherwise spend
a bunch of time sitting in a waiting room, okay.
So hopefully this has given you a some taste
of what it looks like to bring together these
information sets in what I would say is a
mathematically and theoretically rigorous way,
so we can, I haven't gone into all the details
here, but you get nice formal guarantees about
what sort of value you're getting out of
your AI system and how confident you can
be that your physician does or does not
add additional expertise beyond that,
okay. So having talked a little bit about human-AI
collaboration, we're now going to talk about
this setting of systems of AI agents, and we're
going to ask what happens when you put these
systems together and how it matters or how much
it matters when they have overlapping information
sets. So I'm going to talk about a few different
lines of work here that we've done I'll broadly
refer to this as work on what I call algorithmic
monoculture, which I'll explain in a little bit,
and I'll talk about work on decision making
and pricing settings and creative settings,
what happens when we have algorithms that all
kind of produce very similar things to each other.
And the conceptual inspiration for some of this
work comes from long-standing knowledge about
crop systems in agriculture. Now the word
monoculture itself comes from agriculture.
Monoculture refers to a setting where,
maybe I'll set it up in contrast to,
I think it's heteroculture is the opposite
of monoculture, which is the setting where
you actually have lots of different
plants growing and they're all sort of
going to succeed or fail independently of each
other or nearly independently of each other.
And this can be good for a lot of
reasons, one of which is the following.
Suppose instead that I put together a crop system
where I just planted the same crop over and over
again. And maybe I looked at the crops that
I have and I plant the most resilient one.
So I've selected this bottom right cactus over
here. This is the one that has a 90% chance of
survival, let's say. And so I say that's the
best plant, I'm going to plant it everywhere.
But the problem is my failures
are now correlated. In particular,
if there's a virus that targets that
particular plant, there's a pretty
reasonable chance that all of my crops are
going to die out. And so monoculture creates
a risk of systemic failure, where if one
component fails, every component fails.
And that has a much more significant impact
over the entire ecosystem. Now this concept
originates in agriculture, but you
actually see it discussed a lot in
the context of computer systems and more
recently in AI. So in computer systems,
the analog of monoculture is something
like we all use the same operating system.
Our operating systems have
vulnerabilities. And so if,
for example, we're all running Windows and some
Windows components, as happened a few months ago,
has a bug in it somewhere and it
goes down, all of our systems are
going to go down simultaneously. And
maybe that's a particular problem.
Maybe it would be better if some
of us use this operating system,
some of us use that operating system,
or we use different versions of those
operating systems. And so now even if
there's a virus that affects some of us,
the entire ecosystem isn't going to go
down. And maybe there's some resilience.
I can use my friend's laptop if mine is broken for
a little while, or if we have different systems,
we can pick the one that's working at
the time. So there's reasons to prefer
avoiding these types of monocultures. Gary Gensler
actually has been talking about this a lot.
Gary Gensler, the former SEC chair, has been
talking about systemic risk in financial systems
as a result of algorithmic monoculture. So
if we're all using the same software that
executes automatic trades or something
like that based on market conditions,
based on information that's coming out,
if there's some mistake in that code or
if there's some weird condition that gets
triggered in which this algorithm starts
doing something weird and unexpected, if it's just
this one trader who is following that algorithm,
maybe the effect of that behavior on the
market is not super high. Yeah, it's not
good for this particular trader, but the rest of
the market at least doesn't get severely affected.
But if we're all trading based on the same
information, based on the same algorithms and
so on, when one of us enters a weird condition, we
all do simultaneously, and that can trigger really
bad downstream consequences for the entire market.
So again, these are conditions where there might
be systemic risks as a result of similarity or
as a result of us all having the same algorithms
or practices. And so what I'm going to talk
about for the rest of today is how should we
think about algorithmic monoculture? How should
we think about the case where lots of people
are deploying and using the same algorithms? Is
it always a bad thing? And what are the forces,
the market forces perhaps in the world, that
are going to push back against it? And the
genesis of this thinking for me started in 2019
to 2021, where John Kleinberg and I had started
to think about settings where people were making
decisions, high-stakes decisions with algorithms.
And the impetus actually came from, I'd been
studying the use of algorithms in hiring,
and I noticed that there were a small number
of providers that were actually serving large
fractions of the market. And as this becomes
more and more concentrated and more and more
ubiquitous, you might worry that if, let's say
we're talking about algorithms used to do resume
screening, if I submit my resume and it gets
rejected because the algorithm doesn't like my
resume, that's fine if it just happens at one job.
It's not great for me, but I could live with it.
But if it happens at every single job that I apply
to because they're all using the same algorithm,
that seems to be a problem. That
systemically locks me out of the
market. And so if we think about a
decision-making setting like that,
firms face a choice between having humans make
decisions and having algorithms make decisions.
Set aside for now the possibility of
creating these joint systems like we
talked about. We're going to think about
the simplest possible version of this. Now,
what happens in a world where firms have these
types of choices and how should we think about
independence of information? My intuition going
into this was something like the following.
If we have two different firms that hire
two different humans to make decisions,
they have some overlap in their information,
but they also have some differences,
right? They maybe read resumes differently.
they have different experiences, these are just
different people, and so there's going to be some
independence to their decisions. One person might
like my resume, one person might not like it,
but there's some heterogeneity across them.
You know, and maybe if one of these firms
starts using an algorithm, that's still partially
true, right? This human is not going to behave
in an identical way to this algorithm, there's
still going to be some independence across them.
But the problem starts to come about when
many firms are using the same algorithm,
and now there's no longer that independence,
they actually have complete correlation,
or a lot more correlation, in their decisions
and the outcomes that they create. And if you
follow this intuition through, and you do some
math, and you do a little bit of modeling,
you get this surprising finding, which I think
should give us some pause. As I've been alluding
to, it seems like algorithmic monoculture is
bad, it is bad for individuals if everybody's
resumes, or if my resumes are getting
rejected by the same robot everywhere.
The interesting thing is it turns out
to be bad for decision makers as well,
right? It is bad for them if they have
this sort of high degree of dependence
or correlation introduced. It's
bad for society more broadly,
it just leads to worse aggregate decisions. And
the weird thing is, despite this fact that it's
bad for everybody involved, if you just let
people make economically rational decisions,
they can still end up in this setting where
everybody decides to use algorithms anyways.
And this is not a question about price or
efficiency or anything, it's a more subtle point
about the externalities created by information
sharing. I'll try to give you a little intuition
for what that means. And there's a nice connection
to Bray's paradox, if you've ever heard about it.
It's a paradox, you can think of it in a traffic
planning setting. It's a paradox that says adding
a road can actually make traffic worse, okay? So
you give people a better option, but despite this,
because everybody chooses to use that better
option, it correlates people's behavior a
lot more and it leads to worse aggregate
outcomes. The same intuition holds here.
So if I decide to use an algorithm, which
is maybe more accurate than it's a human
or more efficient or whatever it might
be, it makes me slightly better off,
right? It gives me better outcomes and I use it
because of that. It has these externalities. It
actually makes everybody else who's using
that same algorithm slightly worse off.
And the intuition for this is, well,
I'm making slightly better decisions,
but now I'm competing over the same set of
candidates with those other people. And so
in aggregate, actually, those people are
worse off because I'm now more directly
competing with them. And if everybody
makes the same choice, right? They say,
well, it's better off for me if I use
the algorithm, so I'm going to use it.
This ends up decreasing social welfare because
every time somebody new adopts that algorithm,
it harms everybody else. It
harms society more broadly. Okay.
And so what this makes me, made me realize
is the negative impacts from monoculture
come from these externalities, come from
these dependencies between people where
one actor in the system behaves in a certain
way, and that's going to influence everybody
else's outcomes. And so we should really be
thinking about what are the relationships
between different agents or different actors in
a system and how do they influence one another,
right? When they start to make similar
choices, when is that bad and when does
that create negative outcomes elsewhere? And so
those are some of the key questions we should
be asking here. When does similar behavior
from different actors lead to these negative
externalities? What are the implications? And
can we then try to reason about when we should
expect to see more or less severe monoculture?
I'll run through two quick examples of settings
where this has shown up, and then we can
have some time for discussion at the end.
One of those settings is algorithmic pricing.
So increasingly you're starting to see firms
use algorithms to price things or offer
discounts or so on. And so we're going
to reason about what happens when you
use similar algorithms to this pricing.
And the second, we'll talk about a more
of a generative AI style of competition
where people are producing things and
that content production is actually
starting to look more homogenous because
people are using more similar algorithms
to each other. And so we're going to reason
about the effects of algorithmic monoculture
in both of these contexts. Let's start
with this algorithmic pricing example.
So I want you to think about contexts like
personalized pricing, where effectively
what you're trying to do is estimate someone's
willingness to pay and price accordingly. Now you
may not be a huge fan of this because many of you
may be on the receiving end of this. For instance,
many travel sites decide what price to show you
based on where you're conducting a search from,
what type of device you're
using, that kind of thing.
And as in any pricing context, there's two
competing forces here. These are sort of
fundamental economic forces. Firms want to keep
prices high because this is how they make money,
but firms also want to increase
their own market share or increase
your willingness to purchase from
them by undercutting one another.
These are sort of very basic economic
forces. And I want you to think of a setting,
actually a very good concrete example is in
ride sharing. So you have services that are
near identical, like something like Uber and Lyft,
then they will offer you a point-to-point price.
But they'll also often send you these
targeted discounts. I don't know if
you've ever seen this. You have a 10%
off coupon for your next five rides,
expires on this day, tap to continue and so on.
So not only are they offering you these
prices, which are based on distance and
time and so on like that, they get to
target you in particular and say, hey,
I think you might be a little bit less willing
to pay, or I might just want to try to undercut
my competitor. Let me offer you a discount.
Now, I want to reason about what happens as
those predictions of your willingness
to pay become more or less correlated.
Right. Now, as you might expect, more
correlation here is bad for consumers,
right? Intuitively, firms might prefer
to correlate because it allows them to
keep prices high. In fact, it's a form
of collusion and it's bad for consumers.
So my simple picture of why it's bad is in
a world where there's two different pricing
algorithms being used on me, I can shop around and
I can pick the one that offers me the lower price.
But if two firms are using the same pricing
algorithm, the same discounting algorithm,
now I don't have that choice anymore
and I'm paying higher prices. So this
should be in line with your intuitions of what
an economic model would say in this context.
I mentioned asking this question about
what are the forces pushing back against
this homogenization or this monoculture.
Now, one force pushing it back against
coordinated behavior by economic actors or by
firms is antitrust law, right? There's specific
ways in which firms colluding to keep prices
high is explicitly illegal, right? It prohibits
certain forms of collusion that raise prices.
And so the question is, does it apply to this
notion of algorithmic collusion? If we decide
to outsource our predictions to the same third
party or we purchase data from the same third
party, that's going to coordinate our behavior.
Is that illegal or is that just rational
market activity? Right. And from our analysis,
the current U.S. and this is, I should say,
I'm not a lawyer. We have legal scholars
on the team, on our research team here.
Our perspective is that current U.S. antitrust
law does not obviously prohibit this form of tacit
collusion. Now, there's a lot of asterisks here.
One of those asterisks is the interpretation of
antitrust law has changed quite radically
in the last few years and is likely to
continue to change as a result of choices by the
previous administration at the FTC and the DOJ.
But two, the second asterisk is these are
somewhat uncharted waters in the sense that
we haven't actually seen a lot of resolution
to this type of litigation yet that says
you are making coordinated decisions via
some third party, via some data sharing,
via some algorithmic prediction. Is that
actually against the law or under what
theory should that be against the law?
Now, one very recent example of this
is many of you may have been following
these slew of antitrust law cases against
RealPage. RealPage is a firm that offers
pricing softwares to apartment complexes.
And so what that means is previously, if
you're going to pick out an apartment,
each of them has their own way of
setting prices. These are all kind
of different from each other and see a lot of
heterogeneity across pricing structure where
you might. But what the government, what
several state AGs are actually alleging is
that many of these apartment complexes are now
effectively hiding behind the same algorithm.
And that's going to allow them to coordinate their
prices in ways that are perhaps illegal. So this
is the allegations that have been made. And these
are the lawsuits that are being pursued today.
So all of this is right on the cutting edge of
what we know about the law. And it's interesting
to think about how these mechanisms from
data sharing and outsourcing to third
parties propagate all the way through
this algorithm monoculture all the way
to the law. I told you I'd give you one more
example of algorithmic monoculture in action.
I'll briefly talk about monoculture in
content production. And there's been a
really interesting body of empirical literature
and RCTs in the last couple of years that have
all come up with the same stylized fact,
which is the use of generative AI tends to
make content more homogenous. I'll give you a
very cartoon picture of what this looks like.
Here's a prototypical study that people will
do. They'll say, come up with some creative
business ideas, and they'll randomize people
into conditions where they either do not get
or do get AI assistance at doing this.
So without AI, maybe you send people off.
They come up with a couple ideas each. And if you
look at the condition where they are allowed to
use AI, they come up with more ideas. So it looks
like they've been more individually productive.
And you might look at this and conclude, OK,
this seems to mean that AI has made people
more productive. Isn't this a good thing? But
the interesting thing that happens is if you
do some sort of aggregate analysis of what are
the set of ideas that have been produced, you
actually find a narrower overall set of things.
And so the cartoon finding here is, yes, people
are individually producing more, but they're
just producing the same thing as each other.
Their behavior has been very coordinated. And so
if you're actually interested in the overall set
of things that gets produced, you've gotten less
novelty because everybody's being forced towards
the same ideas by this AI system. I just
say, I don't think this is inherent to AI,
but there's some piece of it that's at least true
of the current ways that we interact with AI.
Now, the key question that I want to ask here
is, to what extent is this going to be mitigated
by the fact that in the real world, people don't
just create ideas for the sake of coming up with
ideas? They do so because they're competing in
some sort of marketplace of ideas. And to what
extent does this matter? And is it going to push
back against monoculture? Now, one example of this
is if you think of the... Some of this literature
shows that if you look at digital art since the
advent of diffusion models or readily accessible
diffusion models for images, you find less overall
diversity in the set of art that gets produced.
But there's still some amount of diversity.
And intuitively, it's because demand
for art is heterogeneous. Not everyone
likes the same things. And so if you
are producing art for some market,
you actually have different
niches that you're catering to.
And ultimately, you're not going to see
complete homogenization. So this is an
externality where producing...
If we produce the same art,
we split the demand for it. And that
actually makes us each worse off.
These externalities should then
propagate back to how we use AI.
And so I'm going to briefly talk you
through some of the things that we
find when doing this type of analysis.
One is that, just as you might expect,
more competition in any sort of system is
going to encourage more diverse production.
So the stronger competition we have, the more
it matters whether we collide with each other,
whether I beat you, you beat me, and so on, it
encourages us actually to have more diversity.
You find that this is still not as diverse as
would be optimal from a social perspective,
but it is somewhere in between the sort
of naive, we are all going to completely
homogenize things versus we're going to have
this socially optimal as diverse as possible.
A different thing that you find here,
which I think is particularly interesting,
is that the quality of an AI model
is actually multidimensional.
And this is in contrast to a lot
of the ways that we measure the
performance of AI models is we
just benchmark them. We say,
here's a standard benchmark. We're
going to give each model a number.
The best number is the best model, and that one
wins. What I found was slightly more nuanced.
Some models are good at giving you...
Your high probability will give you a
great answer to any question, but there's
other models that may not be as reliable,
but give you a wider range of good answers.
You can think of this as one
makes one single really nice
image. It's very clean. It's beautiful.
Everybody likes it, but it only gives
you that one image over and over again.
Some models might give you a worse image
every time, but they give you a different
image every time. They have a little bit more
diversity to the set of things they produce.
If you're in a really competitive market, maybe
you'd actually prefer the model that gives you
something that's slightly lower quality, but is
at least different. What that means is that this
market for AI tools should encourage information
diversity. In effect, you're creating a market
in which there's gaps being left open by
the monoculture induced by other tools.
The picture I'll give you for that is in
a world where everybody might be using
the same model. Actually, we might all be
better off in a world that looks like this,
where everybody uses a slightly
different model. No model is maybe
as good as the one that everybody was
using before, but they're all different.
The fact that they're different allows us to
capture different parts of the market and fill
different niches. The image I want to leave you
with is the combination of what we described
here. Ultimately, my goal and my hope is that we
end up with worlds that look like the following.
When we build these joint systems between
AI models and humans, we're somehow able
to leverage the complementary strengths of
each one and cover each other's weaknesses,
or put together the information that they have to
build a system with more overall information. When
we think about systems of different AI models
interacting or going out into the world and
doing things, maybe we want a world that looks a
little bit more like the one on the right here,
where everybody gets to use different models,
they have different strengths and weaknesses,
and somehow by combining all of them together,
either at an individual level or across society,
we end up with better overall outcomes. I know
I'm running a little bit over, I'll stop there.
Thanks so much for being here, for participating,
and I'm looking forward to any questions. Of
course, thanks to all my collaborators through
all this work. Thank you so much, Manish.
That was really insightful and interesting.
There are a bunch of questions in the chat.
For those of you who want to ask
questions, please put your hand up.
Before we get to the team, I would just like
to ask you, how can we apply your insights
to the design of multi-agent societies? There
is so much conversation in the field of AI about
bringing agents to do things on our behalf.
There is the issue of how much you want the
agent to actually do for you. Then, when
the agents interact with other agents,
some of the influences and the issues
that you talked about will only amplify.
What kind of wisdom would you like to share
with the rest of us about this problem? I
don't know about wisdom. My perspective on
it is, there's a balance to be had between
building really powerful agents and optimizing
your agent to be as good as it can possibly be,
and recognizing that when you have a
multi-agent system, it's effectively a way
of aggregating different models together. You're
aggregating all the information that they have.
The better aggregation processes that you can
build, the more you should be diversifying
the set of inputs that goes into it. I'll
give you an example. A very simple way of
aggregating outputs from agents is, let's say
you're in some discrete decision-making task.
You could have a bunch of agents run and
take the majority vote across them. That's
a very simple way to aggregate information.
Now, if you're going to do that, would you
want to aggregate the vote of K copies or five
copies of the same agent over and over again,
or would you want five agents with slightly
different properties that some make these
types of mistakes, some make those types
of mistakes, and you aggregate them that
way? You might get a more robust system
if you are able to diversify the inputs.
Now, what that means is we
need to have really good,
reliable aggregation systems. You can actually
show that if the way I'm aggregating is I just
pick a random agent and do whatever it says,
it doesn't matter how many agents I have,
I should make them all the very best agent
that I possibly can. Somehow, the value of
information diversity is going to depend on how
sophisticated our aggregation processes are.
What that means is, in my mind,
the aggregation part is not an
AI problem. It is a social choice
problem, and we have lots of good
ideas from social choice theory on how to do
that. Or maybe it's a task-specific thing where
I have lots of little subtasks that I boil
up together and create an overall solution.
Maybe I should think really hard about
how to design those subtasks such that
even if one of them fails over here, as
long as I get three right over there,
the entire system is going to go well.
Again, that's the sort of structure
that's going to encourage information
diversity. That's really, really awesome.
Now, also, I wonder, you are very interested in
making the models much more aligned with human
ideals. You did highlight about how
performance on a metric is just that
performance on that metric in a benchmark. How
can we think about the debiasing problem looking
towards the future? How can we think about the
problem with uncertainties in machine learning
models as we imagine more and more sensitive
deployments in the future? Should we think
about this in a kind of a task-specific
way where we find the benchmarks and the
axes of bias that are intrinsic to the task? Or
should we aspire to do something more general,
to get a methodology that applies
more broadly and generally? Yeah.
I think this is a really hard problem.
In the past, I've worked a lot on,
when we say debiasing, assuming you
mean sort of social bias and the sort of
demographic biases that we tend to see in
society being reflected in the models that
we build. Actually, Manish, I think that we
can have bias on all kinds of different axes.
It doesn't have to be with respect to people.
There could be all kinds of data biases. If we
want to look at cups, maybe most cups are white,
and then occasionally we have a red or a blue cup.
That's also a kind of a bias that would impact
performance in a non-social space. Yeah. In more
traditional machine learning applications,
it was a little easier to reason about this.
We didn't have great, or I
wouldn't say perfect methods,
but the space of things that you could do
just wasn't that large relative to what it
is for more sophisticated generative models. I
think of measuring bias in a machine learning
system as a more constrained problem than,
let's say, measuring bias for humans. Now,
we have all sorts of psychological methods
to try to profile individual people's biases.
You can measure different slices of the problem,
but you can't really get a comprehensive picture
of all of the biases. Maybe, as you said,
this person may not be able to recognize
a cup that is blue because they've only
seen white cups or whatever it might be.
I think measuring these sorts of biases
and debiasing generative systems is a
little closer to profiling humans than
profiling machine learning models.
That, to me, means that we need to adapt a
lot of the methods from psychology, actually,
to think about them. Not that I think that we
should be reasoning about the theory of mind of
a generative AI model and treating it as if it is
a human. I wouldn't anthropomorphize it that much.
Methodologically, the psychologists are
actually much better than the computer
scientists at operating in this sort of regime
where there's so many degrees of freedom,
so many researcher degrees of freedom. The
measurements that you need to construct are
ultimately less about the model and more about
the task that you want to accomplish with that
model. To some extent, you have to think really
hard about what are the problems that you might
expect to find in that particular context
and look to measure those things precisely.
I don't think it's going to be feasible to debias
a model along every possible axis simultaneously.
I think that's too tall of a goal for us to
have. I think it is much more feasible to say,
for this particular deployment, here are
the types of biases we're worried about.
Maybe it's your cup recognition
environment. Maybe you're not really
worried about biases and weather prediction
or something like that from that model,
which are completely unrelated to the setting
that you're working in, even though those are
going to be present as well. To me, it has to
be a very contextual and task-specific approach.
Even then, I think we're still far from
developing the right methods. We're still
in the phase of trying to not even
mitigate the biases that we see,
but even just be able to get a handle on
measuring them. I think that's at least
for now and for the next couple of years what
the state-of-the-art is going to look like.
That's really great. We have a lot of questions
in the chat. Let me see how many I can get to.
Bhavesh asks, how do we let the model know what
doctors know? It's a good question. One of the
things that we're actually trying to do now is
see if we can incorporate clinical notes into
these actuarial risk predictions. There's
a hope that doctors are actually writing
down in the clinical notes what they know
about a case that is not just present in,
I showed you those nine numerical features
that are available to an AI system.
It's a little bit hard for a bunch of reasons.
One of the reasons that you might think it could
be doable now is we've gotten a lot better
at processing language in the last however
many years. You could say that because we've
gotten so good at dealing with languages and
modality for machine learning, why don't
we just use that natural language to make
predictions? The problem is there's a
lot of heterogeneity across doctors.
When two doctors write similar notes, it may
not actually mean the same thing. Doctor A
might always write this kind of thing, and
maybe it's very rare for Doctor B to say this,
and you should treat those slightly
differently. It also becomes much
harder to validate that this thing is doing
exactly what you think it should be doing.
In more standard machine learning, you can at
least inspect the classifiers that you get and
use interpretability methods to try to understand,
is it roughly capturing the signal that I think
it should be capturing? We know what are the
conditions under which it will capture the right
signal, especially when we have small numbers
of features and relatively big datasets. Again,
it becomes really hard when you try to deal
with something like clinical notes because
it's just so unstructured. We actually don't
really know how much signal there is at all.
There's a separate version of this where
you could say, let me try to develop some
method for communication that says, model
forms an estimate, human says some stuff,
model thinks for a little bit, comes up with a new
estimate, human interacts with that, and so on.
There's some amount of work on this, both
in this theory side and in the sort of
human-computer interfaces side. I think I'm
optimistic that at some point that work will
end up being the right thing to do and we'll
build these more conversational interfaces into
our machine learning models, but I don't
think we have the right answers just yet.
I also think that it still falls into this
subjectivity or heterogeneity across doctor's
problem, where again, you not only have to learn
what it means when a doctor in general says this
person has pain in their abdomen, you have to
learn what it means when this particular doctor
says this patient has pain in their abdomen, and
that's always in a sense a small data problem.
So there's I think some fundamental limitations
there, and maybe the long-term resolution is
that you rely less on the subjectivity of
the doctors for inputs and just have more
sort of direct sensing into these types
of environments. If you have a camera in
the room where it's feeding information
out of that patient-doctor interaction,
that's slightly less subjective than the doctor's
recounting of what that interaction looked like.
So there are ways around this in the
long term. I'm not sure how soon I
expect any of that to happen. So I think
we have time for just one more question,
and I wonder if there is any
question anybody wants to ask live.
I don't see any hands raised. If not, I will
ask how can conformal prediction methods be
integrated with multi-calibration to yield
reliable confidence intervals in high-risk
medical diagnosis? Good question. So one thing
that you can, this is getting into the weeds
a little bit of what we did, but one of the
things that you get out of our framework is
once you build multi-calibrated predictors,
you can get valid confidence intervals.
I mean you don't really need conformal prediction
to do it. You can think of it as within one
of those buckets. You remember we had seven
different buckets that we placed patients into.
Within each one, you should think of it as
effectively a univariate regression problem to
say given information from a doctor, what should
you do with it? It's starting, the methods that I
talked about in terms of using the clinical notes
are starting to look a little bit less like that
because now you're saying, okay, this patient is
in bucket number five. The doctor wrote this in
their clinical notes. What should I predict for
them? That is no longer a univariate regression.
It's an just sort of an embedded machine
learning problem and you could use
a sort of standard conformal prediction there.
I don't know about a more tight integration
of trying to conformalize the actual sort
of partitions that you get or the buckets
that you get out of multi-calibration.
It's not something we've really thought
about in part because it's not clear what
you should do with that uncertainty from a
decision theoretic perspective and in part
because it's just a really hard problem.
So I think the sort of short answer to
your question is you can conformalize,
conditioned on your multi-calibration scheme,
you can conformalize the estimates that you get
on top of that. Right now, again, the method
is simply using sort of single-dimensional
or binary feedback from a doctor. You don't
really need conformal prediction to do that.
You can just get sort of standard confidence
intervals that way. But in the future,
as we try to build out a pipeline that takes
into account more free-form clinical notes,
again, on top of this multi-calibrated partition,
then you could try to conformalize that and that's
probably something that we should do given enough
data to be able to do it. Thanks for the question.
Well, so we are at time. Manish, thank you
very much for this wonderful talk. Thank
you for sharing your insights and thank you for
all the time you spend on this important topic.
I would like to remind you that the
next CSAIL Forum is next Tuesday from
12 to 1. So see you then. Have a
great rest of the day. Bye-bye.
Thanks.