So let's let's
begin. Despite fears that new
technologies will displace workers, the
most common outcome is for new
technologies to transform the jobs we do
and how we do them. The question is, how
can we use technologies to make jobs
more enjoyable and more productive? With
historical examples and recent data,
MIT's Ben Armstrong will identify
strategies and opportunities for
positive sum automation that benefits
firms and workers alike. Please give a
warm welcome to Ben Armstrong.
[Applause]
[Music]
Thank you. Good
morning. I want to start by taking you
back in time a bit to 2010, 15 years
ago. A simpler time in some ways. Uh the
transatlantic alliance was was strong.
You know, we we had mentioned free and
fair trade was thriving, but the
manufacturing economy in the US was in a
really hard place. And I mentioned 2010
because it was really a turning point in
the history of US manufacturing. In the
previous 10 years, US manufacturers had
shed a third of their overall jobs. And
the President Barack Obama had just
bailed out the two two of the leading
automakers in the country. And when he
was signing a piece of legislation to
reinvest in US manufacturing, he
signaled that there would be a shift in
priorities, that the US would now begin
to care more about the future of the
industry. And what he said was the
answer isn't to stop making things. The
answer is to make things better. And I
think that's the big challenge today
where now there's a consensus not only
in the US, but also in Europe to make
things, but it's unclear really how to
make them better. And I think that's
what myself and others uh here today are
really focused on in our work. So I want
to show you a little bit about what's
happened since 2010 um in the US and
also in in Europe. So I'll start with
this where you could see over time
what's happened. This is construction
dollars spent on new factories in the
US. So this isn't manufacturing activity
explicitly. You could think about it as
manufacturing futures investment in
manufacturing to come several years down
the line. Now 2010 this was really the
bottom the the pit of of US
manufacturing performance and what's I
think really surprising is that over the
next 10 years manufacturing construction
steadily grows to a point where it's
about double at the beginning of the
coronavirus pandemic to where it was uh
in 2010 at the depths of the recession
and then there was another turning point
a realization after the pandemic that
the US should should reinvest now I
think the types of reinvestment were uh
were familiar earlier reinvestment in
infrastructure to produce
semiconductors, some infrastructure to
produce batteries for electric vehicles,
some infrastructure for defense and the
motivation I think is is intuitive as
well. There was increasing dependence on
foreign goods. So here I'm going to plot
the factory construction against
advanced technology imports from China.
So this is overall Chinese exports and
and what you could see is that there
there's a parallelism here that
increasing dependence on on advanced
technology products from China is is
becoming higher and higher and as the US
starts to invest there's a flattening of
the curve. Now I know that this this
challenge of of uh of exports and
foreign competition hasn't really gone
away. It's really just shifted forms.
Well, you might be surprised since about
2015 that advanced technology exports
for China have been flat. But there's
been a new challenge and that that uh
folks here uh in Austria and Germany are
very familiar with and that's really the
explosion of Chinese automotive exports.
Really a lot of the energy and the
investment has shifted from advanced
technologies like uh electronics which
is still very large much larger in
scale. This is just a plot of growth not
of scale. But the extraordinary really
extraordinary growth of Chinese
automotive experts after after co I
think has been a shock un unlike even
the the China shock of of 2000 with with
the speed and scale that it's uh that
it's happened. So this is really the
context in which we're talking about
what new manufacturing is required. Now
it looks small now but this this
tripling of US manufacturing investment
in the last three years is significant.
And what I want to say is it's not just
existing companies like Intel or uh
large uh automotive companies like Ford
investing in new factories. It's also
companies that hadn't really been in
manufacturing before. And these
companies represent new models of how to
approach a manufacturing problem. So
here is this is a a mockup, a bit of a
futuristic almost looks like it was
created by Generative AI mockup of a a
site in Ohio, a planned site in Ohio for
a company called Anderil. Has anyone
heard of Anderal here in the US? A few
people. So this is a new company that
began as a software company to create
new technology um some AI based
technology for the US government
particularly for defense and border
security purposes and it was motivated
by several folks out of Silicon Valley
who said Silicon Valley is developing
all sorts of technologies for the
consumer market but not really capturing
this huge opportunity in defense and
government industries. So the first uh
move for this company in about 2016 2017
was to develop software and then after
co they've been increasingly shifting
toward investments in hardware and this
was just a few months ago the
announcement of an enormous campus right
near uh the Columbus Ohio airport to
really expand their manufacturing of
critical defense goods like drones and
and munitions. So this is a a new model
of manufacturing that I'm I'm going to
share more about, but I want to give you
a sense of kind of a visual of what new
factories in the US look like. Now this
is I think a parallel challenge maybe of
a of a different type, but a parallel
challenge to what you know recent news
is coming out of of Europe where there's
in increasing focus on how to invest in
new kinds of manufacturing, different
kinds of manufacturing in in Europe. And
and the question for me really is all
this planned construction of of new
manufacturing facilities, is this
actually going to make the manufacturing
economy better? Will these factories
make products better than the factories
that existed before? And why that's so
important is that US manufacturing in
particular, and I'll show you
comparative numbers for various European
markets in a second, US manufacturing
has been really struggling in its
performance over the last four decades.
So here's that performance in one chart
here. It's a lot. So, I'm going to walk
you through it. So, I'm I'm plotting a
few different variables here. I'm going
to focus on these these lower lines
first. So, this is the the kind of
mustard colored line is the number of
employees, number of workers in
manufacturing, workers on the factory
floor. The green line is the number of
factories overall. So, you could think
about that new factory construction uh
marker is is linked. Red is technology
investment. Then, pink is value added.
You can think about just the growth of
the manufacturing economy overall. And
then blue is is productivity. That's the
value added divided by the employees or
the worker hours. And what I want to
show you here is that over time
beginning in in the 19, you know, uh 40s
and 50s thereabouts, there was really a
positive equilibrium that was happening
here. Employment was going up. It wasn't
going up dramatically, but there was
about um between 20 and 30% of US
workers employed in in manufacturing. Um
wages were going up for those employees.
There was investments in new technology
and also growth in productivity. Very
positive indicators. And then something
happens around the 1980s, 1990s where
investments in technology stop. The
workers go down significantly. I
mentioned about a third of the workforce
had been lost between 2000 and 2010.
That's on top of a big drop between 1980
and 2000. Such that the manufacturing
economy in 2010 was about half of what
it was at its peak. And what you get,
you get a loss of workers, a really stop
investing in new technology, and
productivity continues to go up because
essentially these manufacturers are
doing the same things. They're
maintaining the same level of production
with fewer people, but they're not
growing. And over time, that really the
chickens come home to roost, as we like
to say. And in 2010, productivity begins
going down because we can't really
hollow out the manufacturing workforce
anymore. we start investing a little
more in new factories, start hiring more
workers, but we can't really keep up
with productivity. So that's the
challenge that we face in the US. To
zoom in on kind of the the recent
period, we see productivity since 2010
going down and employees growing just a
little bit and the overall manufacturing
economy, this blue line, is actually in
decline. It's not going to last forever
the decline partly because we know this
new factory investment is coming. But
that productivity curve really needs to
change for US manufacturing to be
competitive. It needs to start going up
again. Now you might wonder and and I
did too. How does this look compared to
other countries? And I had talked to
colleagues in Germany and uh in the US
for a long time uh students of
manufacturing have looked to Germany and
Japan and some other uh models of of
manufacturing excellence and saying well
you know we should we should adopt
practices or institutions like when I
talk to German colleagues they say no
we're actually facing a lot of the same
issues and the data really bear that out
that the uh the figures look a little
different because they're on a different
time scale but really you see high my
pointer's not much visible but this
green productivity line you see high
productivity growth until before this
great recession and then really a
flattening of productivity over time in
Germany and this is with more stable
employment I think part of the
institutional story in Germany is that
employment remain stable it wouldn't uh
it wouldn't really work to lay off a
third of the manufacturing workforce
like happened in the United States so
that's why these curves are a little
flatter um similarly Japan this is a
very similar curve right it's not that
productivity is declining but the rate
of productivity growth is certainly
decelerating. And then finally, I was
curious since we're in in Austria, this
is an Austria, what does Austria look
like? And I was prepared to say that
Austria looks similar given how the
German and Austrian economies are
intertwined. But actually the Austrian
econom economic story looks much better.
So I I I would propose that next year
maybe we have Austrian manufacturers at
MIT teaching us how to have a
productivity curve like this where the
the productivity growth is much steadier
from a different baseline but uh
employment and productivity are actually
growing in the Austrian manufacturing
sector. So what what can we do with all
this kind of what are the the obstacles
that we need to overcome to improve
manufacturing performance? I'm going to
focus on on three. the first and and
what I should say is I'll give you a
short preview of these three and then
the following speakers are going to go
deeper into these topics. So risk for
example which is really how do we um
have more companies that are able to um
to raise money to invest in new
technology to take uh experimental
approaches to growing Hyram Samuel is
going to talk about this a little bit
later different models for approaching
risk. I'll preview that a little bit.
The second is new technology. I think
one of the most striking things and this
comes I think from an MIT perspective.
One of the most striking things about
this chart in the background is that our
level of technology investment in US
manufacturing is at the same rate that
it was in the 1980s. We haven't really
grown our level of technology investment
on the factory floor. Despite all of
these videos about automated lines and
talks about uh lights out factories, the
level of technology investment on a on a
dollar scale is the same. And this is
borne out not just by the the dollars,
but also when we do surveys of
manufacturers. So, here's one survey
where um this is a a federal government
survey that asked US manufacturers
whether they had various technologies
represented within their firms. And it's
only a small minority of firms that say
they have various advanced technologies.
Of course, these aren't only the only
important technologies in manufacturing.
But what's important to say is that not
only is the spending flat, but these
technologies that we're going to talk
about today are in many cases rare. the
technologies exist and have high
potential but they haven't been absorbed
into the manufacturing economy and the
capability for absorbing them on the
right only a minority of companies say
that they have the capabilities to
adjust these technologies versus buy
them off the shelf so it's not just a
you know buy having the capital to take
the risk and buy the technology it's
also having the internal capabilities so
just to give you this is US data but I I
imagine you want the comparative I'm
going to zoom in on on robots here for a
second and here's a plot of robot
adoption over time across the major
markets for for robots in the US
depending on your measure it's about 10
to 12% of American factories have any
robots at all only about half of those
factories have more than one robot um
but and you could see that it's not like
this uh this is growing this is a
growing market in the US so actually um
in in the pandemic era I was expecting
that given a lot of the restrictions in
the pandemic new investments in in
manufacturing and technology that there
would be an up surge in investment in
robotics and actually Germany, Japan,
the US investments in robotics went down
in all three places in in 2020. So
really really striking and of course the
the standout story here um is China and
and I think that's partly a story of
investment in automotive manufacturing
where 50% of all robots reside. Um and
it's also a story of of massive
government subsidies to support
technology adoption within firms. Okay,
the final piece of this puzzle is that
you know you need to have the capital to
take some some risks and invest in new
things. You need to have technology that
helps you become more productive and
develop new capabilities. And then you
also need people. You need people to
figure out how to use these technologies
and deploy them well. And one of the
challenges which is is certainly a
shared challenge between the US and a
lot of European economies is a
demographic one. And one of the real
consequences of losing half of the
manufacturing workforce in the US is
that we went really a generation without
hiring many new manufacturing workers.
So the manufacturing workforce today,
here's a distribution of the ages of
manufacturing workers uh in in 2000 it
looks relatively healthy that the median
manufacturing worker is you know in
their is middle-aged maybe uh in their
early 40s and uh today what you see is
that the now the median worker is
nearing retirement age. That's the you
know the uh sorry this is in in the the
blue case the modal manufacturing
workers nearing retirement age. So this
is a huge challenge and it's a challenge
not only to find workers to to backfill
these jobs to maybe design new jobs for
workers to fill but it's also how do you
transition the knowledge of all the
workers at at the peak of this blue
distribution and transfer them to the
young people on the left. And this is uh
part of the challenge that John Louu my
colleague is is working on is going to
talk about later.
Okay. So now what I've been interested
in is some of these kind of uh I would
say somewhat depressing details about
the challenges facing manufacturing. So
I'm certainly interested in those, but
I'm also interested in finding companies
that defy these trends that really have
been performing really well despite the
overall challenges in the manufacturing
economy. So I go out and search for
these places. I try to visit them and I
found really two patterns of how these
companies behave. Every company's a
little different, of course, but I want
to share with you two approaches that
companies have tried to take to grow
quickly in manufacturing to adopt
technology and develop a really skilled
workforce. And the first approach, I'm
going to go back to Andrew. The first
approach really looks a lot like trying
to apply some Silicon Valley principles
to manufacturing problems. And I I think
this comes with a lot of risks. The the
most prominent risks I think are present
in uh a series of recalls at Tesla and
quality problems associated with Tesla.
that's present at explosions from SpaceX
rockets, right? Like these are these are
really prominent examples of
manufacturers following a different
playbook with serious concerns and and
results that lead to high growth but
also high volatility. But I want to take
a moment to maybe set aside some of
those concerns and just look at the
playbook and how companies are following
it. And and here here's what it looks
like when they think about, you know,
the challenges of risk, technology, and
skill. The risk is taken care of by a
very different financing model than what
a typical uh medium-sized manufacturer
might rely on bank loans or they might
pour uh profits back into the business.
These are companies that are relying on
risk capital and they don't feel the
need to pro to generate short-term
profits. And it's a very different model
that allows them to invest and
experiment in different ways than a
traditional manufacturing firm that's
held by a a private equity fund or one
that's publicly traded. The second is
that they bring a very different type of
technological approach. So I mentioned
Andrew started as a software company and
transitioned into manufacturing. So what
they had when they started investing in
in hardware was a set of software
products that were designed to really
support the hardware that they wanted to
build. So they had not just the
capability of using other technologies
that others had built, they had actually
developed had the capability to develop
software internally that was exactly
what they needed to solve manufacturing
problems. And then finally, one of the
skills, not to mention kind of the
software skills inherent in the
workforce they were hiring, one of the
skills was to experiment and improve
very quickly. So you might have heard
stories um many stories from places like
Tesla and SpaceX that in these companies
there was no boundary between the R&D
lab and the factory floor. In fact, at
Tesla, there is no really separate R&D
department. It is part of the production
team. And that's one of the really
different paradigms between these
companies. They're they're able to move
faster because they have no division
between these this traditional boundary.
There's no challenge of necessarily
translating or throwing something from
R&D over into
production. It's also a potential
explanation for quality problems as some
of you might have guessed. So all right.
So I think that it's important to note
these aren't just uh a few uh errant
examples at the moment. In the beginning
in in before co they were since uh this
is really over the last 5 to 10 years
there has been an extraordinary surge of
people leaving SpaceX and Tesla in
particular you can imagine why they
might leave and starting their own
companies with some uh with some
variation of this model. So trying to
apply the same experimentalism maybe
with less of an authoritarian streak uh
maybe with a little bit more balance and
a little bit more uh focus on process
control focus on on quality but really
you can see I there's no way of
displaying it. I tried to make it each
of these little lines if you could see
each of those is a company that came out
of SpaceX or Tesla and this is an
underestimate because these are just
alumni who are founders. They're also in
and for example the head of
manufacturing came from Tesla. So the
the heads of manufacturing at a lot of
these companies aren't necessarily
founders, but they come with the same
playbook from these companies. So this
is a um and I'm not I'm not trying to
endorse it. I'm just describing here how
this is a playbook that has diffused
really rapidly in the United States in
manufacturing. And you know, you could
see that there are there are a couple
precedents for this type of playbook
expanding. One is after World War II,
there was a a big surge in in the US of
folks leaving the military who had
gained technical skills and actually
learned at arsenals to try to um start
their own companies, many of which
became defense contractors. And the
second example is the founding of
Silicon Valley and and many of you might
already know the story, but if you'll
forgive me, Silicon Valley really
started out of one major semiconductor
company that was founded by the people
who were known as the Traitorous 8. They
were called traitorrists because they
left the lab of of William Shockley who
was a tyrannical eugenicist. Um they
didn't like working with him. So they
left to start their own company and that
company helped give rise to many of the
very important uh software and
semiconductor related firms that really
started this cluster and this boom and
and this is quite similar I think to to
what's happening today with the
diffusion of of SpaceX and Tesla. You
can see AMD, Intel, a lot of familiar
names in this in this bubble. Okay. And
and I I think this almost goes without
saying at this point, but there's a big
trade-off to this model. And and I think
one of the challenges for a lot of these
companies that have have come out and
are receiving venture capital today is
how to essentially use the the blue the
blue features to increase uh quality and
performance without seeing um seeing big
uh dips in big problems like um like
SpaceX and Tesla have seen. Okay. Now I
think the the alternative and and the
big critique of this model and and uh I
hear it often uh is from people who um
are really students of the Toyota
production system, students of of lean.
And this is a methodology that became
common practice in the US in the 1990s.
I I rarely go to any um traditional
manufacturing firm that that doesn't
tell me about how they're lean and what
they're doing to advance their their
lean agenda. Uh but but one of the
challenges of lean over time has been
that it's very good at optimizing
certain processes. It's very good as a
set of tools to help you do the same
with fewer resources, removing waste,
etc. But it's not necessarily a playbook
to help you grow and scale. It's not
really a playbook to help you innovate.
So one of the questions is for companies
that I think are more incrementalist
I'll call them incrementalist versus
kind of the radical approach of Anderil
is how do you take this lean playbook
and then add the tools for growth and
innovation and this incrementalist
approach is is really exemplified by a
company called Danaher which emerged in
in the 1980s one of the first adopters
of lean and I'm just comparing Danaher
to one of the favorite punching bags in
the US recently which is General
Electric in the blue line which is uh
has not really seen any improvement in
stock performance underperformed the Dow
Jones and the S&P whereas Danaher really
experienced extraordinary growth while
the rest of the manufacturing economy
was struggling and the playbook that
Danaher followed was quite different
than than a SpaceX or a Tesla. It was a
playbook of vertical integration so
controlling many different stages of the
manufacturing process. It was uh
investing in the long term. So it wasn't
necessarily going public early but
having a lot of patient capital and a
lot of very smart financial maneuvers to
invest in complimentary businesses over
time and it essentially served as a
holding company for all sorts of
different technological capabilities
software capabilities as well as
manufacturing assets and this I think is
is a incremental approach that now we're
seeing more uh more companies start to
follow and I think there are some
exciting examples that might come up
later that are consistent with this more
incremental approach and of course the
difficulty of this approach and uh one
of my favorite examples of of this is a
a US company called Proctor and Gamble
which is really a remarkable
manufacturing company that makes you
high quality but commodity goods is that
they are slow to change their
manufacturing process but when they do
change their manufacturing process you
know it's going to improve and it's
going to be very fine-tuned. So really
the trade-off here is speed and and
that's where these two models are sort
of the inverse of of the
other. One of the ways we're seeing this
model scale in the US isn't necessarily
from from US-based companies like
Proctor and Gamble, but it's from
foreignowned companies. And one of the
things I was really surprised to see
when I started looking at the data is
that, you know, we've had this upsurge
in in factory construction. Like I
mentioned, it's it's sort of
unprecedented how fast it's grown. And
if you look at the big factories, just
factories that are billion dollars plus
like the Arsenal project, you know,
we've had 40 of these. So in in just a
three-year period, really extraordinary,
40% of those are from foreignowned
companies. So there's been a a real
surge in foreign investment in the US,
perhaps anticipation of of changes to
trade policy or uh improved supply chain
resilience. Whatever the reason, you see
a big surge in in foreign uh in foreign
direct investment. And the blue line
down here is plotting that over time
that it it surged again after 2020, but
it it had been growing for some time as
overall manufacturing capital investment
had been pretty flat. So this is really
remarkable that a lot of companies that
have I would say a more incrementalist
approach and bring a lot of really high
quality manufacturing processes from
their home countries have been moving to
the US and that those practices have
been diffusing. So, so I look at this as
a a a positive development and one that
we should really be um trying to uh
emphasize. And finally, just to to
conclude here, I I want to think about
just the the group we have here today
and kind of the the spirit of this
meeting which uh colleagues talked about
before. And I think there's a spirit of
uh mutual learning and transatlantic
cooperation. And there's actually a
really great history in in manufacturing
of this type of open learning. And I
want to talk about two examples of this
and what I think we can take away from
each and then maybe suggest to you,
let's think about together how we might
be able to do more um cooperation in the
future. So here here are my two
examples. You know, on the left, some of
you might know this is a uh the
headquarters of a company that no longer
exists called NUMI. Um and NUMI was a
collaboration beginning in the uh late
80s, early 90s between uh Toyota and
General Motors. And the story goes um
that General Motor CEO Roger Smith, he
saw the Toyota competition uh in the US
auto market and was very scared. And
first he tried to um develop what he
called the factories of the future. And
the factories of the future were really
G's answer GE GM's answer to lean,
excuse me. And GM's answer to Lean was,
"Let's lean into this software uh
advantage that the US has." This is in
the 1980s. Silicon Valley is just
bubbling up. So he said, "We're going to
start the Lights Out factory." Roger
Smith was the first person to coin this
term. And uh so he's like, "Let's let's
use our software advantage to compete
with Toyota through technology." And it
failed dramatically. It failed
miserably. These factories of the future
uh they tried to introduce tons of
robots, tons of software automation, and
it didn't work. And and it's a separate
talk on why it didn't work, but it
really didn't work. So he said, "All
right, if we can't beat the Japanese
with automation, we should join them. We
should do a joint venture." And that's
what Numei was. So they had Japanese
management and uh Japanese line
managers, production managers, and then
US workers. And what was interesting is
that in this California plant, which was
a GM plant before uh it was the lowest
per one of the lowest performing plants
of all the GM plants and once the
Japanese management came in and they
applied uh lean principles, it became
one of the highest performing plants.
really there was excitement that the
these types of lessons might be able to
spread throughout General Motors and
certainly for the Japanese they it
worked and and now you see multiple
Toyota and other Japanese car makers
producing very effectively in the United
States but the the the real frustration
of this partnership was that GM didn't
know what to do with the lessons. They
had a successful plant with a lot of GM
workers um unionized workers who were in
the plant. They had a group of people
American Americans who had been involved
in it called they called them the NUMI
commandos and they went out to try to
teach other firms these these lessons
and they didn't really stick and GM kept
doing business the same way that it
always did and I think one of the
challenges from from Numei is that well
you have this great success story but
you didn't really capitalize it you
didn't really institutionalize these
lessons and I think that's a very
different story from when BMW came to
South Carolina and BMW um you might know
the story better than I do In 1993, BMW
was looking for the next place to to
move a major manufacturing facility.
They chose South Carolina. Um,
management in Germany here was not
pretty skeptical of the idea. They
weren't really sure, how are we going to
do this in South Carolina? South
Carolina was more textile manufacturing,
even agricultural. Where's the workforce
going to come from? And what happened
was that South Carolina, to their
credit, listened to BMW's strategy for
workforce development, for investment,
new technology, and heads of South
Carolina technical colleges, workforce
development organizations went to
Germany to study how vocational schools
worked in in Germany to try to replicate
it in South Carolina. And the South
Carolina manufacturing economy went from
one of the lowest product lowest
productivity manufacturing economies in
1990 to today one of the highest
productivity manufacturing economies.
Wages have gone up and there's been an
an automotive cluster really a pretty
advanced automotive cluster that's
formed around the BMW plant. And if you
can believe it, South Carolina is the
leading source of apprenticeships in in
the United States um because of BMW's
influence not just over the individual
plant but over the institutions and
surrounding region. So this is really a
case where the lessons of this
partnership really spread and became
institutionalized albeit in in one
region of one state but really
successfully in ways that I fear the
lessons of Numei although they made it
through to a lot of consultants and a
lot of firms that adopted what they call
lean practices it it it hasn't been
institutionalized in the same way around
training and a more general approach to
manufacturing. So I think that the
challenge for us here today is to take
the lessons from a lot of my brilliant
colleagues that'll share about new
technologies and new approaches and
hopefully find ways to to cooperate and
then also we would love to hear lessons
from how how you do things differently
here um and try to learn from them back
at home. Thank you so much.
Do I have time for one question?
Okay, I think we have questions on a
board. Okay,
here. Here we are. I don't know if I've
ever been short. Okay. With with AI
being a huge part of manufacturing
today, what are some practical
approaches to training traditional
workforce to effectively utilize AI in a
way that enhances their performance?
So,
I forgive me question asker. I don't
think AI is a huge part of manufacturing
today. I think it's actually quite a
small part of manufacturing today. And
and the way that AI works in a lot of
the factories that I've seen it in p is
through let's say vision systems or
quality control systems where the main
skill that you would need to use these
tools is the same skill you would always
need is to kind of interpret you know
whether the part is of a high quality.
There might be more interpreting of the
underlying data and to understand when
to trust the algorithm and when not. But
that's really what my colleagues who who
are more expert at this than I focus on
is is not just how do you use AI more,
which I think has been the big focus is
get people to use AI more because some
by some magic it's going to increase
productivity. It's instead how do you
calibrate your use of new technologies
to use them when they might be
productive and and then avoid using them
when they might lead you astray, which I
think is is certainly the case in
manufacturing. You don't want to use
probabilistic tools in manufacturing
that needs to be very controlled and
very tightly refined. Okay. Our second
question, continuous training will help
with the skills gap. How much continuous
in quotes training is needed as we need
workers and lack the ability to always
be thinking about training? I
um I think John John Lou let's maybe
hold this. I'll give a small answer, but
then maybe John can give a a longer
answer. So I have a a problem with this
idea of a skills gap in in the US. I
actually don't think that's the major
labor problem. Um, but I do think
continuous training is good. So, I'm
going to focus on that part. Um, so one
of the things that I think the some of
the highest performing companies I've
seen do is they try to map the skills of
their workers and also map the career
opportunities that their workers have.
So, you see even small companies that
kind of have a spreadsheet of necessary
skills on the factory floor. and they
develop whether it's internal to the
company or through an external
organization ways of training to get
those different skills and then a worker
can see oh by getting these skills I am
able to move up within my career and
that can be beneficial for the company.
I've also seen you recently I was at a a
really remarkable factory in Japan where
there's just an expectation and
requirement of continuous training and
training requirements through the year
and also everyone in the factory needs
to work at know how to work at every
position. So the expectations of
training are just much higher
inherently.
From the BMW moving to South Carolina
example, what issues did they consider
when choosing new locations for
production facilities, regulatory, local
market needs.
So in surveys of companies, and this
this might be US companies, so I I can't
say this was explicit for BMW. In
surveys of manufacturing companies
looking for new locations, there are
three factors that come up consistently
as the top three that kind of change
places sometimes. One is skilled
workforce. So, do you have a workforce
that's able to um you know, able to go
and and fill the jobs that they need?
You know, in BMW's case, it was kind of
funny looking back at some of the
newspaper articles from this around this
decision. they kept coming up with um
that they were, you know, mechanically
mechanically talented farm boys was kind
of the the term that people thought that
BMW was looking for in South Carolina.
I'm not sure how that worked out for
them. Um but that that was the that was
the idea. And and they also uh the
complaint of other states that wanted
BMW to come there like Tennessee um was
that they weren't close enough to the
ocean. So that the port of Charleston
was actually a big uh uh access to the
coast for exports um was a big part of
BMW's decision to move. Fun fact, uh the
largest individual exporter in the
United States is BMW US. That is the
larger largest manufacturing exporter
overall. Um really remarkable and
another reminder that foreign direct
investment is really critical to the
American manufacturing economy.
What can manufacturers with legacy
hardware learn from the software
approach of an Anderil at all?
Yeah, I I think that the um one of the
keys is redesign of work. So I've been
focused on that manufacturers with
legacy hardware typically have the same
job descriptions over time and they
replicate these jobs even as the
underlying technologies that are
available to perform the jobs might
change and you might be able to redesign
a job that now can take on more tasks
than than previously. And when Andre and
and Tesla and others started really from
scratch and this was they started with
frankly engineers and not production
workers doing these roles that engineers
just thought of totally different job
descriptions for how to perform what was
production work. Another story that was
shared with some uh my myself and and
number of colleagues recently was that
when
Tesla encountered its various
manufacturing failures, they needed an
all hands-on deck approach on the
factory floor to solve the problems. And
one of the things was they had to have
actually their software engineers come
to the factory floor to be extra hands
on deck because the robots had failed.
And what happened was these software
engineers hadn't realized that the
manufacturing was done this way and they
said well I can fix that. I can develop
a program for that or an algorithm for
this and and there was new there were
new tools developed because of uh
different skills being exposed to these
processes. So I think we have time for
just one more question. What are ethical
challenges when it comes to the
automation of work? Oh, this is the one
I was hoping you weren't going to ask
me. Um, I think that I'm going to dodge
the question a little bit because I I
don't really have any authority to speak
on on the ethics of it. Um, but I could
we did a a survey recently on workers
perspectives of automation
and I'm I'm torn because I think that
the the the threat of automation to
displace work is frequently overblown.
And one of the challenges really of new
technologies is the question of whether
they're going to make jobs higher
quality, higher wage or lower quality,
lower wage. That's a bigger question I
think than than more jobs or fewer jobs.
And one of the things that I was really
surprised, we did a survey in nine
different countries and we asked
workers, do you think that automation is
going to make your job better in in what
aspects? And workers in the US were
relatively positive but pretty skeptical
that automation would help their job
security or their wages. and workers in
Germany, France, the UK, uh, Poland were
very excited about automation and new
technologies. They were eager. They
were, I think it was a 30 percentage
point gap in the optimism versus
pessimism around automation and new
technologies. And it's unclear. We have
a graduate student who's trying to
explain this transatlantic gap in
perceptions of automation. Unclear
really why. I think one reason is
institutions is that with institutions
that provide a safety net and provide
some semblance of job security, you're
less scared about automation displacing
you and and are maybe more likely to see
it as a as a tool. Um, so so I think
that's potentially one one influence
here. Well, thank you, Ben Armstrong.
[Applause]