that concludes today's
presentations a big thank you to our
speakers and all of you for joining us
the future of smart cities depends on
Innovation collaboration and the board
thinking that MIT and our our industry
partners are striving to
advance the video recording of This
webinar will be available to IOP members
if you are not an IOP member but would
like to engage with MIT please contact
me or one of my one of our program
directors we have several upcoming
events including MIT AI conference on
April April 1st and MIT AI is software
engineering uh Forum um March the oh I'm
sorry April the 2nd and we also have MIT
energy Workshop MIT Europe conference in
VI and sustainable materials webinar con
computationally assisted material
Discovery
webinar join us again at our next M
event take care and stay inspired see
you next time bye