let us look at an application of the
probabilistic method to extremal set
theory the extremal set theory concerns
the study of families of sets that have
certain desirable properties and asking
questions such as what is the largest
set family that you can have with such
with such properties and in this video
we'll focus on the following property of
being an intersecting family this means
a collection of sets A1 through a l such
that these sets pairwise intersect in a
non-empty intersection okay so we want
sets A1 through a l such that whenever
you take any two of these sets and take
their intersection it is never the empty
set so here are two basic questions that
one can ask the first one which will
turn out to be an easy warmup is what is
the largest intersecting family of
subsets of 1 through n so here there are
in total two to the N subsets of 1
through
n but if I want to only keep a
collection of sets that's an
intersecting family what is the largest
family I can get and the second question
which will turn out to be far more
interesting and will involve an
application of the probabilist method is
a question what is the largest
intersecting family of K element subsets
of 1 through n so here n and K are
inputs to the question so they are given
and we're asked to find what is the
largest intersecting family of K element
subsets of 1 through
n all right so the first question as I
mentioned earlier turns out to be a
fairly easy one and we'll solve it as a
warmup so as an example just to
illustrate what we're talking about if
we look at all
sets
containing the element
one well this collection of sets is
intersecting because they all have the
element one so every pair intersects in
some set that contains the element one
in particular non
empty this collection of sets has size 2
to the n minus one because once you fix
the element one the other elements can
be in or not in the sets and they're two
to the N minus one such possibilities
right so a binary choice for each the
elements outside
one okay now this is just an example but
it turns out this is the best that we
can do
because okay so the claims that we
cannot do better or we cannot get an
even larger set
and this is because for
every subset a of 1 through
n and
most one of
a and the complement of
a so the elements 1 through n subtract a
so the complement of a and most one of
these can be
in the intersecting
family so what we're doing here is
pairing up the sets with their
complement and because it's an
intersecting family you cannot
simultaneously have a set and its
complement in this intersecting family
and so this
eliminates so this means that you can
have at most half of all the two to the
N sets thereby showing that this 2 to
the N minus one is indeed the best that
you can
do okay so this
finishes part one question one and now
let's move on to the more interesting
and harder question
two again let's start with some
examples first here's
a easy case if n is less than
2K
then okay so this is the easy setting if
n is less than 2K then by pitching hole
principle any pair of K element subsets
of 1 through n intersect so we can take
all n choose K
sets and they form an
intersecting family
okay so there's nothing really to do
here because we can just take all the K
element
sets so the harder part of the question
the more interesting part is what
happens when n is at least
2K here as an
example we can take as earlier all sets
containing the element one
and this gives us n minus one choose K
minus one
sets Okay and as before these sets they
all this set form set this collection of
sets form an intersecting family because
any pair their intersection contains the
element one and is thus
nonempty right so this is a construction
it gives you n minus1 choose K minus one
sets but is this the best you can do
right perhaps through some other methods
of construction through other examples
maybe there are even larger intersecting
families of K element
subsets that turns out not to be the
case and that is the main theorem that
we'll prove in this video and this
result is known as the aish C rle
theorem
so this is a seminal and a beautiful
result in extremal set
theory and the ERS cor theorem says that
if n is at least
2K
then
any
intersecting
family and we give this family a name
curly
F of sub
sets of 1 through
n okay subsets um
and any intersecting family of K element
subsets of 1 through n
has
size at most n minus1 choose K minus
one in other words the construction that
we gave just now is indeed optimal you
cannot get a bigger intersecting family
of K element subsets of 1 through
n let us now prove the erors corado
theorem and we'll introduce Randomness
into to the problem and use the uh use
some beautiful ideas from the
probabilistic
method so here's how we start the
proof let us
order the numbers 1 2 3 and so on
through n
randomly around a
circle okay so what do I mean by this
take a
circle and then basically take a uniform
the random permutation of 1 through n
and then place the
numbers around the circle in the order
of that permutation so for example I'm
putting down nine numbers here n equal
to 9 in some circular order chosen
uniformly at random
missing a number here six right so here
nine numbers okay uniformly around the
circle and let us
call a
set subset of 1 through
n
contiguous I'm here I'm
defining term
contiguous call this subset contigous us
if its
elements the way they're ordered around
the circle form an
arc in this
ordering so for
example the set of numbers 4 3 9 5 this
Four Element set is
contiguous so 3 4 5 9 is
contiguous because the orders they're
according to the circular ordering these
four numbers form a contiguous block on
the other hand the set 1 three is not
contiguous because they do not form a
contiguous
block okay so that's just a
definition and now for a
given set sub a a subset of 1 through
M
with K
elements so for a given K element subset
of 1 through n what is the probability
so here a is fixed a is not random so we
given this a what is the probability
that a is contiguous
okay so the ordering Is Random so given
a set what is the probability that under
this random ordering is
contiguous well let's think about
that so the ordering is random but here
if a has K elements can think about how
many different ways these K elements can
be placed around the circle
there are n different
positions from where geometrically this
K length K Arc lies and once you fix
that
position the
probability
that the elements the K elements of a
actually falls into the desired
positions
is 1/ K one over and choose
K okay so this is the probability that a
is a contiguous set under this random
ordering and
now by the linearity of
expectations the expected number of
contiguous sets
in this collection
f is equal to the size of f times the
probability that each individual set is
contiguous and that was calculated
earlier to be this quantity so n / n
choose
K on the other hand
the property of f being
intersecting a claim implies that in any
given circular ordering there are at
most K
contiguous
sets
for so in a
given circular ordering okay so let's
pause and think about why this claim is
true if I give you an
ordering and ask well how many
contiguous sets can there be and now
this sets these contiguous sets they
have to be intersecting right so if we
have one set so here let me denote the
elements these circles as think about
them as positions on the circle so these
dots as positions on the circle so if
that's one set well where can the other
sets be well they have to intersect this
block so maybe another set is like this
one but if that set is in then it
excludes if this blue set is in then
excludes this green set from a
possibility and so
on right
and okay so you see that given that this
red set is
in well at most one of the blue and
green on the second line can be in and
the most one of the blue and green on
the third line can be in and the most
one of blue and green on the fourth line
can be in and these are the all the
possibilities of how another contiguous
set can intersect the the red set so
that's an argument that can translate
into this claim that F being
intersecting implies that most K
contiguous sets in any given
order okay so this argument is very
analog to the argument that we did at
the beginning where we pair up
complimentary sets but this time we're
only looking at contiguous sets that
intersect a given
set
okay well if you can only get at most K
contiguous sets in any given order then
this quantity which is a random variable
it is always at most
K so in it's expectation then this
quantity that we got at the end is also
at
most
K
thus the size of f is at most K Over N
time n chose
K which one can then expand the binomial
coefficient to see that the final
quantity is equal to nus1 choose K -1
one and that's exactly what we
claimed all right so this finishes the
proof of the ERS corado theorem which is
a foundational result in extremal set
theory and it's a beautiful application
of the probabilistic method to extremal
set theory and to combinatorics in
general where we start with a claim a
theorem that is not random at all it is
completely deterministic it's about
finding the maximum possible set size
the size of something that satisfies
some constraints and yet the proof goes
by introducing new Randomness into the
setup that allows us then to derive this
beautiful conclusion