And our next speaker is Brock Yordi from
the Geothermal Drilling Association. And
he had the pleasure of collaborating
with Brock this past summer to do um
geothermal driller pre-apprentice uh
program.
>> Should not have taken that.
>> So how does this work? Do I still have
20 minutes or uh
Sorry, Brock.
>> They wanted you to put it on the next
guy.
>> Excellent.
>> So, we're going to do introduction to
geothermal drilling a bridged in 20
minutes. Um, there's plenty of things in
here and we have heard about how
drilling affects us. And I think any of
you that are flipping the television and
you come across FX and you see the movie
Armageddon, you can see that the major
premise is it's easier to teach drillers
to be astronauts than it is to teach an
astronaut to be a driller. When Ben
Affleck asked that question, uh, some
choice words were used by m Michael Bay,
but in reality, suspension of disbelief
is what we're looking at.
jump past that. Okay, here's my warning.
The following presentation features
tribal drilling knowledge acquired by
drilling professionals or under the
supervision of geothermal professionals.
Accordingly, me must insist that
everyone who engages with drilling in
this presentation consider this advice.
Drilling is the imperfect combination of
science, physics, and self-taught tribal
knowledge compounded over years of
success and failure. Drilling is a
disruptive process. We know this. The
key to the success lies in your
conscious choice of the drilling program
that minimizes the impact of the
surrounding environment. That's the bore
hole. That's the neighbors. That's the
project staying on time.
Drillers, contractors, engineers,
scientists, and clients have entered in
a powerful partnership to uncover the
mysteries of the subsurface. We are
discovering the unknown together.
And how are we going to do that? A
bridge version 20 minutes, right?
It's simple. We have a drilling system.
And we've seen this from uh the OG
Garren Eubanks to as we've talked a lot
geology
formation hydraulics depth to water
subsurface challenges. Those are the
things that I'm thinking about when we
say can we drill this next. That's going
to align into my drilling capabilities.
This is my drilling system. So, what can
my rig capable of doing? From horsepower
to rotation to pull down to pullback to
diameter, depth, angle. This is all
going to drive our cost. Next, choice of
drilling method. Back to that drilling
program. Is it going to be using mud
pumps, air compressors, sonic, dual
rotary, reverse circulation? There are
plenty. Hopefully, one day we get a rock
melter, right? Maybe a laser. We keep
seeing things come out all the time.
Finally, as much as we want to say
autonomy is coming and it's really cool
watching the Dragon Rocket go up and uh
there's nobody really at the control,
but they still uh individual can be at
that stick at any moment. And this
processing right here will always be
very important to what we're doing. So
our driller, our drilling company, our
contractor's qualifications, what
special tools do they bring, what
methods, what applied science and
fundamentals.
So as I think of that, the driller and
we talk about workforce development, we
talk about developing this, the liftoff
report talks about where we need to be,
what we need for workforce. He and Ia
and I with Stacy right here in the front
row with the the time and uh we we have
collaborated a ton on workforce
development and developing these
drillers. But the critical system that I
just showed you doesn't work without a
competent drill crew that's working in
safety first because we're rotating,
we're per cussing, we're lifting things
over our heads. So, as that drill crew
steps up into this critical system,
what's their goal for the day, what is
the quality of the installation, what is
the site and environmental impacts and
management, what is the goal for project
completion, staying on time, staying
under budget. Did I say under budget?
And I'm a drill guy. Whoa. preparation
and planning for unseen issues,
for foreseen issues, weather, you know,
those challenging geologies,
roles and responsibilities of that crew,
the driller, rig operation. This is a
complex process that has microscond
adjustments that need to be made at
times. They need to understand this so
they can have effective product
installation and we get effective
resource extraction so we have good
project completion and good
recordkeeping. We have an assistant
driller there supporting that driller
rig support tool handling product
assembly getting into the standards that
we just talked about from pressure
testing to making sure our grout making
sure we're making that right hole. And
then finally, our field technician who
is doing the solids control management
because let's face it, we love this
concept of drilling and putting bore
holes in. We forget about the cubic
yards of material we pull out of the
ground and how we're going to do that
five times to 90 times to 600 to a
thousand times.
And we have to be able to manage that.
So three people we can get away with
two. It depends on the project, the
timeline and the expectations.
Okay, we're all going to become drillers
today.
This is the basic fundamentals. I am
exerting force against our geology. And
then I have to cut it. So is that in
rotation? Is that in percussion? Is that
in velocity? Is that in frequency? As we
see with sonic drilling. Next, I have to
remove those solids or it's not a bore
hole, right? It's just a uh thing that
we got stuck in. And man, we don't drill
more bore holes. So, I have to flush it.
I can do this either mechanically,
that's with augers, that's with uh
frequency, or flushing with water, air,
drilling fluids, engineered solutions.
This is straight air rotary. We can see
one's going into some rock here, and we
have one going into a blue green shale.
Nice, clean, out of the way. No water
table here. How many times are we
intersecting water tables and producing
water? This is a big piece for us in our
cost, in our responsibility as a
driller. Here's mud rotary conventional.
Man, it looks messy. So, we immediately
go, we want to go back to that other
slide, but we can't. We have to select
the right method for the right geology.
So, we get into engineered drilling
solutions. Uh Jordan, I drilled with the
US military to 2400 feet with bubbles.
Got the nickname Captain Bubbles for
that entire project. We can use foam
with low hydraulic hydraulic
conductivity and carry those cutings
out. Mud, mud rotary, why it's been
predominant throughout geothermal is
because again it's low influence to our
ground, but it creates two waist streams
and we've decided those waist streams
are much harder to get rid of.
So, let's look at this. We're going to
talk conventional rotary. We could get
into dual rotary. And I'll say competent
drilling companies, they're good. And
they have invested in lots of different
pieces of equipment. And here's the
deal. They're going to sell you on their
system. And sometimes those systems are
bougie bore holes that go 850 ft at an
angle. And we need that because of the
footprint in the solution. And there's
other times where we can simplify this.
And if you look at the liftoff report
with 80 million B buildings, we need
that holistic approach of everybody
drilling. This is Armageddon, right? We
saw 3 degrees Celsius by 2100. That
meteor is coming here. We all get to be
Ben Affleck and Bruce Willis in this
situation. So as we look at this, we
have mud drilling. I need to be able to
remove solids from the bottom of the
bore hole at the bit face at somewhere
between 60 and 150 feet per minute. Low
conductivity. I'm not going to force on
those fragile formations. I get into
air. I think about Stan Lee and
Spider-Man. With great power comes great
responsibility. Holy cow, I can move
cutings out of the hole at 7500 feet per
minute.
job should be done under budget, on
time, like super fast. We'll have cars
going back over that road, right? But
that's competent rock formations. That's
no water. What happens when we start
those waist streams? So then we start
engineering solutions either in mud or
in foam and we can start changing what
we need. the influence to that borehole
wall. As we talk about that thermal
conductivity test, as we talk about
all of those pieces of influencing and
minimizing that impact come from us
matching the right drilling method to
what we're going to be in.
So what do I need out of that drilling
program? I need an efficient rate of
penetration because let's face it, uh,
with the drilling companies that are in
here, time and diesel fuel, regardless
of our waist stream, because guess what
clients, you're a co-generator, that's
your waist stream. We're just managing
it for us. Time and diesel fuel are the
most expensive pieces for our projects.
So, I need to be able to have good rate
of penetration and good production.
Next, while doing that, I have to
minimize the impact to the bore hole and
think about how I'm influencing that
downhole geology. I talked about geology
next to it. I said, "Formation
hydraulics." I want you to think about
um I was in wood shop. There's this
really cute uh individual next to me.
It's Mother's Day. We're building
birdhouses. I want to ask her to prom.
So, I grab my birdhouse with the pine
and I drive all the screws in it and I
get it done. It fell apart two months
later in mom's yard. Amanda's birdhouse,
I helped her pre-drill all the holes. We
set it. We put the wood glue. Our
geology is the same way. When we break
that fracture gradient, just the same as
if I drive a screw into this right now
and split this table. I can putty that.
I can do things to it, but I can't fix
the damage I've done to mother nature.
So beyond that, we get through those
fragile subsurface formations, we get
into water production.
I want you to watch the news right now.
Thank you. Um
Princeton and Arizona came out with a
connection between surface water and
groundwater talking about fossilized
water. Holy cow, it's the drill guy
talking environmentalism now. It's weird
time. Drill, baby, drill. No drill,
better drill. We need better people
drilling professionally. So we are
pumping fossilized water out of
aquifers. That's going to take 10 years
to 10,000 to 100,000 years to replace.
So we saved the planet by 2100, but we
exploited all our groundwater and went
into the Atlantic. Did we save
ourselves?
So we have to understand as we produce
that water and how much and the
influence. But beyond that, as we go
deeper, we have to start thinking about
volatile gases, CO2, hydrogen sulfide,
methane. And on that minimal impact, as
we step back, dust, noise, drill solids,
as we look at more campuses being done,
man, Ball State, they didn't care how
many dump trucks came through. Those
were all Indiana farm kids.
You go to Yale, you go to um Forom and
you start thinking about how we're
removing cutings and people are like,
"Why are there 10 dump trucks a day
coming through here?" We we have to
think about the impact to our neighbors.
Finally, I need data gathering. I need
real-time analysis of that subsurface as
those formations change as uh we have
challenges as we have loss zones because
I have to effectively be able to grout
that so that I have the right influence
to the loops.
So the results of me doing this right
the hole is going to be open meaning I
can get product into it. It's going to
be gauge again my drilling influencing
my geology. If we specify a six-inch
bore hole and we look at the cubic feet
or the cubic yards of grout we want to
put in there and we end up with this
oblong boiler hole, we just saw what
Garren talked about. We heard what Mark
was talking about. We've screwed up and
now we have an ineffective system. So I
need gauge. I need stable so that I can
get in and out of it. It needs to be
straight in the desired direction.
And we need seamless product
installation. Loop to bottom, drought to
top. So I can have efficient resource
extraction.
Sounds easy. But then we get into this
situation right here. All different
types of drill solids. How mother nature
reacts to us. How our subsurface works.
These spoils as I get them out of the
hole. How do I handle them?
6inch bore hole to 400T. It's 2.9 cubic
yards. Oh, by the way, that's why we
have three people on a drill crew
because there is a lot. If we're going
to increase production, you need to be
able to move this stuff away. 6 inch
850T hole is 6.17 cubic yards. So, as we
start thinking about this, how many dump
trucks and back trucks am I bringing
into this project?
Loop installation. as we specify two
loops, you know, um the BEu building
with the Ryan 1500 ft. We think about
all these different pieces. I need a
good effective drilling program so I can
have good grouting process.
This loop should be in the center and
that trim should be on top of it. But
I'm really bad at paint. And uh this is
what we get. So here's our trim to
bottom, our loop to bottom. My
individual starts mixing the grout to
the specified specifications that we
need. The right amount of water, the
right amount of bentonite, the right
amount of graphite or sand.
I start filling that bore hole. As I
fill that bore hole, that trim needs to
stay 10 feet submerged in the grout. So,
I have continuous grout column coming
out. We talk about now we're going to
leave the trim in at bottom. No, we're
not going to do this. I started my
career after Yordian Sons at
Hallebertton. I studied grouts for 10
years.
I'm bringing this grout column out of
the hole with my Trimmy and that's what
I want to see. I want to see grout to
surface. I need to effectively be able
to look at that grout and know that I
had a good
column come out that I didn't have
channeling in that as we have these
discussions about ah it just needs to be
four feet in the ground. No, I need to
see this because this is protecting us.
I need to see it come to surface.
Why? because I am replacing the native
material that I just destroyed with
something that meets or exceeds Thank
you. our ceiling capability. It's got to
have a better standard. I need to ensure
continuous contact between the loops and
bore holes. We got some brilliant
individuals in here. You ask them what
happens if we have a bad grout column in
that air pocket. I need to completely
seal the annular space to prevent
co-mingling of aquifers and prevent
surface contamination. As we look at
these projects and we go, "Hey, there's
this open area. Let's put a bore field
here. Is it lowland? Is it does it
flood?" My favorite question to ask when
I show up on these projects is why isn't
there a Starbucks here?
If not, my greatest generation, my
grandfather, they were really good at
burying things. And we're gonna find it.
So I need to prevent that surface
contamination. I need to comply with
federal state laws and I need that
thermal conductivity and borehole
integrity to stay. This is my method
when we check out my hour presentation
not abridged. So we can get into this.
This is what I want to talk about.
Success to a drilling project is managed
through these points and whether we're
doing this all because of the climate
change. Right? We have to understand how
this is changing our drill and build
schedule. Next, other construction
operations. What are our regulations?
Location, location, location, project
timeline, and then neighbors. How am I
sharing that site? How am I protecting
mother nature? This is the reality of
projects from downtown Los Angeles for
George Lucas to right here just outside
of Boston to a very tight location,
urban, a church.
This is what kicks our butt, everybody.
And this is if there was a slide to take
a picture of, this is the one because
every time I get on a new call to
troubleshoot a problematic project, I
add to this slide. So if green local
geology should not be an issue, we
should have an effective amount of test
bore holes to know. So if I'm drilling a
600 hole project and I do two bore
holes, is that a rep representative
sample? No. That doesn't get us what we
need. We need that subsurface data.
What's hard? Man-made subsurface
obstructions and contaminants,
problematic subsurfaces as we get into
fragile formations or water or artisian
flow and utilities. And those are the
things that we have to be planning with
the right qualified contractor. So if I
have that right qualified contractor and
we have our pilot team right there, the
pilot tutorial, thank you. uh watching
skillings drill and that was a wonderful
experience with all of them. What am I
doing to choose this project? If you
call me as a contractor, equipment
availability, tooling, drilling method,
compatibility with the location, site
footprint, environmental demand, what is
my timeline, what is the borefield
design and borehole design, project
restoration and cleanup. That's a big
piece is managing our projects so that
CSM or Clark or whoever you're using for
your GC isn't like you're going to drill
another bore hole and we're going to
walk around in 18 inches of slop. You
know what are my licenses? Am I
accredited? These are all pieces.
This is what we can do at test bore
holes when we're surgical.
You can see this project. We had snow
and rain. It was Chicago. It was the end
of October. This is how we left the job
site. So, lessons learned.
Every contractor is going to have an
argument on why their method's the best.
It's your choice how you move along with
that. You know, we need to optimize
drilling every chance we can get.
What do I want? I want qualified
contractors. I want the right drilling
method for the area. I want test bore
holes. I want test wells that give us
the right data. I want us to think about
what we did successfully before and how
we loop and grout that. That was 21ish
minutes. Thank you, Stacy. Thank you,
everybody.