good
afternoon
so the last time we have done uh um the
definition of a simple system
model is very important because we
acquire um the so-called
microscopic limit
which Al when we deal with many
particles in in a
container and which is the framework in
which most of thermodynamics uh has been
developed uh until uh maybe 20 years ago
or and so we will uh review
um just uh quickly what we've done uh
remember that the issue here is
that walls cause raction
effects because the density of the
particles must go to zero at the
wall in most Frameworks we have seen
some
examples and so these raction effects
are important like here because when I
remove a partition
they leave a sort of a hole or L faction
area that will spontaneously be filled
by the
particles as they realize that they wall
is not there anymore and so if you
remove the wall you get a spontaneous
and therefore the reversible process
that takes you as represented on the
evil sucess diagram from this state to
that
state and this is an irreversible uh
spontaneous
process later on today we will talk
about uh just in a few minutes about
going also up this way but for the
moment let me just uh uh recall
that in the limit of many particles
the stable equilibrium State curve for
the composite
system divided into uh two
partitions be gets closer and
closer uh to the stable equilibrium
State curve for the system the same
particles uh but no
partitions and therefore that
effect uh also the raction effect is uh
smaller and it becomes negligible as we
have several particles
fact yes we have seen some examples uh
in that paper that I pointed to you
where there are 10 to the 5ifth
particles
but that is
extremely cold temperatures I believe uh
whereas at normal
temperatures uh as soon as you have uh
maybe 10 20 particles uh these veraction
effects become
already
pretty neg
negligible and that's why we we can use
the
um the many particle the simple system
model uh for most the systems not only
macroscopic but also mesoscopic and even
microscopic as long as you don't go to
Just few
molecules and the idea is that in that
limit we can neglect the uh essentially
the effect of in inserting or removing
partitions from a stable equum
stake nothing ically that
is equivalent to assuming that the
fundamental
relation is a function a homogeneous
function of first degree in all of its
variables meaning
this and as we said from that
mathematical
uh condition which represents the
physics that we we said um we gain one
relation which is the Oiler relation
which I was unable to prove with the
previous uh view graph so here's a new
view graph which does a better
job this is the
condition and in order
to uh to prove
it yeah here's the proof you just have
to take the partial derivative of both
sides with respect to
Lambda and so on the left hand side
there is no Lambda so partial derivative
is zero and on the right hand side it's
Lambda time U so it's
U uh plus Lambda time the derivative of
you with respect to the first uh
variable which is the
temperature evaluated at the same
independent
variables times the derivative of this
um argument here that is s over Lambda
which does depend on Lambda so the
derivative is s over minus Lambda squ
and so on for the other derivatives and
here is what you get and now in this
expression here if you set Lambda equal
to
one outomes the oiler
relation you can also take from this the
fact that
the the the derivatives the partial
derivatives of fundamental relation are
homogeneous functions of degree zero in
other
words uh see there is no Lambda
multiplying in front so the temperature
of a system we've given sdnn is equal to
the temperature of course we're talking
about stable equilibrium States uh for a
system in which the sbnm are divided by
the same number
number as long as it's the same number
it will be the same
temperature so that means small or large
as long as the relative amounts are
equal you get the same temperature for
the stable equum
stage
okay so that's the oiler
relation and we have proved
that thanks to the oil relation we can
define specific spe
properties which for example is the the
specific energy is the energy divided by
uh n and
um and then we can see how this specific
property is a function of the other
specific property so and specific
entropy specific volume and the mole
fractions which are the specific amounts
of constituents
and and as we see here there is a lot of
inde dependence but we prove that the
partial derivative of U with respect to
n is equal to -1 / n
2times this quantity and this quantity
you remember is what we called the uh
Oiler free energy it's the
characteristic function in
fact and uh the
is still valid also for small
systems here is what we how we Define
the oiler free
energy and here it's a
differential from which for example we
can see
that the amount of one constituent is
equal to the partial of the oil free
energy with respect to the chemical
potential of that constituent
when you hold fixed the temperature the
pressure and the chemical potentials of
all the other constituents so if you
have a reservoir that keeps temperature
pressure and also chemical
potentials except this one and uh you
can by changing the chemical potential
and know knowing uh measuring the
amounts you you can measure the oiler uh
free
energy this might be
a possible procedure to measure these or
small systems using molecular
Dynamics well here um what we have
done in the previous slide in order to
compute the derivative of energy we
respect the
amount the derivative of specific energy
we respect to the amounts at fixed
specific uh entropy volume and mole fr
actions to find that it is minus 1 / n *
the
oiler the oiler free
energy uh we have done it also for these
other properties and they those
derivatives turn all to be all equal at
least for the for those that
uh for the specific properties that
emerge from the um from
the theander transform form of the
energy version of the fundamental
relation they all come out to
be Oiler free energy divided by uh n²
negative whereas for the
entropy it's minus one / T all all the
same
result
so
since in the limit of many uh particles
there may be also significance here that
uh you are left with an N at the
denominator which so for many particles
grows up and whereas this is the
specific Oiler free energy the per
particle so this may be an indication
already that this dependence goes down
with
n uh in any
case again these uh relations may be uh
ways to uh
measure uh the
oiler uh free energy for small systems
of course because in the large system
limit uh uh the oer free energy is goes
to
zero the O relation is equivalent to
setting EU equal
zero so now let's go back to this um
issue of partitioning a
system a small system so many few
particles and uh we want to see uh if
there is a cost in uh uh
dividing the system which is in a stable
equilibrium state in this
one and
producing another stable equilibrium
state of a system with Lambda
partitions in which uh all in each of
which there is the same amount the same
uh um it has the same
volume and also the same entropy and the
overall entropy must be the same so if
we do this we can go from here to there
in a reversible weight
process and and uh if we go from
partitioned to without partition you see
we go down so we extract the adiabatic
availability
essentially of that state that is
generated that if we the moment we
remove those partitions the moment we
remove these partitions the this is not
anymore the stable equilibrium State
curve because we've changed the system
so St P becomes this one so yes we could
uh let thing uh evolve spontaneously so
the system will evolve spontaneously at
constant energy uh generating entropy by
reversibility but we could also be if we
are good enough and fast enough faster
than
irreversibility we could attempt to
extract this adiabatic availability and
go all the way down at constant entropy
to to
reach uh this stable
instead but this also says that if I
want to go from here and introduce the
partitions in a weight process so I
cannot
go leftward in a weight process I have
the the the first time I I reach the
stable equilibrium state of the system
curve of the system we partitions is
here so this is the um
the first available uh I mean reachable
uh State partition State others could be
up here and so as you as I go from here
to there I need to spend at least this
much
work or energy from the weight in order
to introduce those partitions and
physically you can think of the idea
that uh since there are raction effects
at the wall as you introduce the
partition the partition moves moves the
particles away because it has to create
that space and that is a
work of
course the mathematics of same idea is
that
you the you can compute the work to
introduce those Lambda partitions which
is the minimum work to go from zero to
from just one to
Lambda
uh it's the maximum you can extract if
you grow from Lambda 2 one and it is the
difference between the energy here which
is e
Lambda which is Lambda times the energy
of each of the partition so it's E1 E1
is the is the system with the
fundamental relation of the system
without partitions
that you
evaluate at the values
of of
the entropies volume and and amounts
that are present in in one
partition so e Lambda minus E and this
is
instead uh
E1 fundamental relation of a system
without partitions
evaluated at the value of the entropy of
of the overall system which is the sum
of all the ENT it's essentially Lambda
times the entropy that is in each
partition okay so this is this
difference and for example we could
uh see how it changes as we go from
Lambda to Lambda + one or which is
essentially the same from Lambda to
Lambda minus one so minimum work to add
or remove uh one uh
partition and notice that it's not
exactly so obvious because when I add
one Lambda it's not just just have to
push in I have to also rearrange the
particles in the other lambdas so that
they all divided in uh in equal
amounts but with that understand
standing if you if you see that this
work so it's essentially the work of
going to Lambda + one minus the work of
going to Lambda partitions divided by
one and this is a fancy way of writing
one but to make this ratio look like the
the partial derivative of w with respect
to Lambda and so we can uh since we have
an expression for w we can take the
partial derivative with respect to
Lambda do the math and outcomes so that
that work is the oiler
um free
energy of the uh each partition in the
Lambda subdivided
system so that's
another uh physical interpretation of
the oil of free
energy okay
good
so now that we have the UL System
model there are a number of
results that
you
uh have seen in uh previous courses of
thermodynamics so I will do a very brief
uh review of
those because it also helps um brushing
up uh a
bit considering
um that the other day you didn't
remember the value all gamma for
a all right um so the first idea is that
of an extensive
property and here notice I keep
repeating in these titles the this is
now within the simple system model all
right what do we mean by an extensive
property for example the
energy is an extensive property this is
a a precisely
the definition of of this the
mathematical definition of the simple
system model now the homogeneity of
first degree of first degree of the
function that
represents um of that was for the energy
this is for any
other any other function that has that
property we call it extensive and you
can prove that examples in the list of
these extensive properties you find and
of course you find entropy find volume
the amounts the total amount which is
the sum of the amounts of the various
different
constituents the
enthalpy the enthalpy is not an additive
property
because if you have two systems that are
different
pressures uh enal is U plus
PV uh
the the P is different and therefore uh
uh u and v are additive but the P that
is is different doesn't make that linear
combination of u and v
additive
but if you have U
um a simple system in which you can
assume that um you see uh this independ
dependent
properties are all divided by the same
number we have uh said before that um
the partial derivatives of the
fundamental relation including pressure
temperature and
pressure uh do not change if you change
all this particular change of of
variables and that is why you find the
enpy uh here in this list if this
extension
also the Gibs free
energy it's missing in this list but it
is another
example as well as the specific and the
heat
capacities and the
mass okay now if I take any two
extensive properties and take the ratio
I
obtain uh specific
properties so for example the first line
here represents the specific
properties uh when I divide so these are
the mol specific processes because I
divide by
n or I could have the mass specific
properties when I divide by
m or I could have the volume specific
properties when I divide by V for
example the mass divided by the volume
is the
density of course they are
related between one
another and
sometimes here I try to uh differentiate
by using a different symbol like the the
the the star here is there just uh just
in case you need uh to make sure you
don't get confused but in most of uh uh
the treatments once you set the
definition it's and the context makes it
clear that you're working with uh
Mass specific properties you just use a
lowercase letter without the star and
you let the context uh Define what
you're
doing for
example the amounts if you divide it if
you divide them by n you get the mol
fraction I call I use the letter Y subi
but not everybody uses that
letters of
if I have the mass so I take the take
the the number of particles multiply by
their molecular
weight capital M of part
Mi and divide by the total mass that is
becomes the um Mass fraction of that
constit I divide the total the amount of
constituents divided per unit volume
what I get is a concentration of those
constituents which in in the
chemistry uh business sometimes is also
denoted this way this is the volume
concentration of particles of type
I so
notation varies depending on the various
fields in which you apply
thermodynamics uh remember
that we Define extensive property when
the for properties when the there is a
relation like this but there is a Lambda
here multiplying if there is no
Lambda like as we have said for the
partial derivatives the fundamental
relations so for TP and the chemical
potentials but also
for all of the specific properties that
we just defined
you can
prove that uh there is no Lambda there
and this relation holds we call these
properties intensive
properties also here I have to warn you
that I may be using a definition which
might differ from uh what you've seen uh
um
elsewhere so just uh me and careful when
you see the word intensive property uh
check how the author defines uh that
intensive this is our
definition there are many properties so
we said uh not just TP and uh and
chemical potentials but also all the
specific properties all right so if you
take the list of the values of all these
intensive
properties which is using an infinite
number of of of
properties but most of the times there
is an indep a smaller inde set of
independent properties okay the list of
those of all properties of this kind for
a stable equilibrium state is called the
Intensive
State and you can show that you have if
you have the Intensive
State then you and you also have the
value for one extensive
property then you have completely fixed
the
state so you must in order to get the
state uh we're talking about stable
equilibrium States within the simple
system model if you uh want the state
you can start from the Intensive State
and add a an extensive property
the other idea that is very
U important is a very important
consequence of the simple system model
is that the fact that you can add and
remove partitions allows you to describe
uh stable equilibrium States in which
you have the coexistence of parts of the
system that are in different intensive
States for example think of uh
a
pot
uh with water
inside and it's on the
stove and so you have a heating below
and there is boiling you you no boiling
will uh produce
bubbles these
bubbles will go to the
surface and may generate drops
if there is if the boiling is
sufficiently vigorous generate drops so
this is
a it's not really a stable equum state
but you can approximate the
properties uh with those of of a stable
equilibrium
State uh at least after a while that you
have um stopped the heating so you don't
have a as you get a sort of uniform
temperature uniform uh pressure but you
still have some drops and uh and Bubbles
drops in the in the vapor and bubbles in
the liquid okay so this is a complicated
system to describe but conceptually the
simple system model allows you to do the
following uh I can imagine
to take another
pot my my model pot so to
speak it's a mental image of that thing
and let me take a uh a physical
partition that um
runs at the interface between liquid and
vapor and as you know includ in
inserting that
partition doesn't
cost so you will already see that that
doesn't cost means you're neglecting the
simple system model is neglecting also
the the surface tension effects
because that interface does
matter but not within the simple system
model so I can take this and uh and
think of putting it
here then I take another um um Bubble
and uh and uh sorry let me let me put
them up here okay so I take all the
bubbles and I put them
there I also need to change the shape a
bit so that it feels the same space and
also here this I can take larger areas
essentially all the continuous area that
doesn't contain drops and put it there
So eventually what I managed to do is to
put all the vapor here and all the
liquid
here usually we use use these letters to
to represent
that okay so I've
generated two
regions in which there are no
inhomogeneities whereas here the
inhomogeneity stands from the fact that
as you know there is a huge difference
in density for example which is one of
the Intensive uh
properties uh like a factor of a
thousand between the density of the
liquid and the density of the vapor
so um this is an an inhomogeneous or
erogeneous uh situation that can be
represented uh certainly not in a
uniform um intensive state but I can
group the various intensive states that
are present in my multiple phase state
into just uh areas that we call
phases that are locally homogeneous so
the
F phase is the collection of
all the uh parts of my uh system that
have the same intensive State like the
liquid high
density uh and this G is the collection
of all the other uh parts that share
this other intensive
State and if you have a triple
point suppose you also have ice here
because we are at the proper
pressure okay if I have also ice I need
also to uh produce a third
phase okay
so that defines the idea of
phase and then as you know there is this
uh famous Gibbs phase
Rule and here is how uh it
follows all
right one one way of looking at at this
is that let's see what
happens let's choose this set of
variables that are uh the variables that
describe uh
this equilibrium
State temperature and pressure I select
them because I assume that all the
various parts are in a um the various
phases must be in mutal equilibrium
therefore they must be at the same
temperature for the overall system to be
uh in a uh stable equum State because as
we said we consider the overall system
as composite of the
phases and they are in mutual
equilibrium so the conditions for Mutual
equilibrium are equality of pressures
pressure because they can exchange
volume equality of temperature because
they can exchange
energy and the quality of chemical
potentials the Intensive
States uh that are present
here the number of independent
properties that Define intensive state
is this much
is uh TP plus plus the um
composition uh of each of the
the of each of the
phases because yeah here I consider a
simple system in which a simple
situation which the substance is only
water but you could have also a mixture
uh uh we will do that uh as we uh
approach the the second part of the
course this is already useful for that
part
so so these
are the Bas
variables uh
however they're not all truly
independent because first of all the mo
fractions by alus
definition must sum up to
one so so for each of the
phases for example for the summation
here is I only have R minus one more
fractions that
are
independent because the the LA the last
one can computed can be computed by as
one minus the summation of the
others
plus we also have the fact that the
chemical potentials
must be
equal so I need to have a quality of
chemical potential between the F the
phases for each of the constituents that
can be exchanged and here there are no
membranes or things that uh disallow the
exchange of types of particles they can
all be
exchanged and therefore I know I have
have to satisfy the chemical potential
equality for Mutual stable
equilibrium for each type of
constituents you see actually here the
reason why I have uh chosen as
independent uh as candidates for
independent variables a temperature
pressure and the mole fractals because
we proved the the that the chemical
potentials are functions of this TP and
Y and as we know
from the chemical potentials we can
compute uh we will see that we can
compute all uh the
properties at least
the yeah all the
properties
and because we proved that
the chemical potentials are derivatives
of the G free energy which is one of the
characteristic functions the transforms
of the fundamental
relution all right so now it's just a
matter of counting how many do I did I
start with so it's Q * R is the mo
fractions plus two temperature and
pressure then I have to
subtract Q relations because of this
condition here and then I have to
subtract as many equations I have here
now the equal sign each equal sign
counts for an equation so uh I have q
phases so it's Q minus one and I have R
lines here because I have have one one
line like this for each type of
constituent so so it's Q - 1 * R and
then so if you subtract from that 2 + RQ
subtract q and subtract subtract Q -1 *
R you are
left with uh this r + 2 minus Q which is
the soall variance it's the real number
of independent variable intensive
properties and this is assuming that we
have no chemical equilibri chemical
reactions if we also have chemical
reactions
we will see that there is a um one
additional uh equation which we will
call the chemical equilibrium uh
condition for each independent reaction
in play in your system and so you'll
have to subtract also let call it Z that
number of independent chemical reactions
you have to
subtract uh this to get the
actual variant
for
example we take a pure substance like um
like
water so pure substance means only one
more fraction and of course one M
fraction is equal to one that's 100% of
that
substance so that's not really a
variable the Gibs um phase rule says
that the in defended variables are 3
minus
Q
so so for
example if I have a single
phase now single phase means that it's
all water for example
homogeneous it means that every every
point in my stable equilibrium State no
matter where I go and make my little
partition I I will find an intensive
state that it is equal to every where
else so homogeneous single phase is
homogeneous same intensive State
everywhere so with Q equals 1 one
phase uh the variance is 3 minus one so
it's it's two that means that if I have
if I am in that uh if I have a liquid
state
I can and I want to change that stable
equilibrium state to a neighboring
stable equilibrium State I can
move in two directions I can change two
variables so I can change for example
the temperature and the pressure
independently if I have two
phases like
this well without the eyes
and I want to move to another
neighboring stable equilibrium state
with the same two phases so for example
liquid and Vapor I want to move to an
adjacent stable equilibrium State again
with liquid and
Vapor I cannot do it by arbitrarily
changing both the temperature and the
pressure I can change only one and the
other must be tuned the the the change
of the other must be tuned in in a
proper way because
because that's because I need to follow
the condition for the imposed by the
chemical potential
equality and which is written here I
need that chemical potential equality to
remain satisfied and therefore if I
change
t uh that imposes a change in p and in
fact this relation between temperature
and pressure for two phase States is
what we call the saturation relation
pressure and temperature are related by
saturation if I have three
phases and I want to move from a stable
equilibrium state with those three
phases to another stable equilibrium
state with the same three
phases and
different temperatures or pressure I
cannot because the values is zero there
are no neighboring states with different
values of
tnp
because the equality of the chemical
potentials here I I have two equalities
and the two variables are T and P so
that fixes uniquely the value of TP at
which you can have those three
phases that's the triple
point this is better represented for
example this is the pressure temperature
diagram for
water so if we have um in this
area uh this is the vapor area and if we
have uh some vapor in this state I can
move to
adjacent uh conditions in which I still
have a
vapor but different pressure and
temperature and I can move in both
directions here so I have two directions
in which I can move that mean that's the
meaning of variance variance equals
two along here are the the line of
coexistence of liquid so inside the
liquid also the Varian is too and also
inside the
solid these are the homogeneous single
phase
States along these curve which is
represented by the P saturation uh
relation between pressure and
temperature
uh we have the coexistence of liquid and
vapor and as you see the variance is one
if I want to move to a neighboring
equilibrium state with different
pressure I also have to adjust the
changing temperature so as to follow
this
curve up to the critical point above
that there is no uh distinction between
the liquid and the vapor phase and
therefore it is possible as you know
to go all the way from liquid to vapor
and vice
versa by going uh this path in which
there is
no
sharp uh there is no two-phase uh
conditions you so the the liquid becomes
uh smoothly uh vapor and vice versa
without phase separation butas if if you
if you if you if you do if you go from
here to there at a certain
stage like we do when we boil uh we boil
at
constant atmospheric pressure so I think
let's see where is there should be one
somewhere uh
for bar one bar is atmospheric pressure
more or less so if
I go from here and then I heat up at
constant pressure I move to the right in
the diagram at a certain stage I'll
reach the two-phase uh condition in
which the the water begins to
boil and uh as you know it U the
temperature gets stuck to that value
until it's over boiled and then you can
still heat up and the temperature will
begin to increase so here essentially
when you
have the two phases the the the only way
in which the
system likes to stay in equilibrium is
to separate into vapor and uh uh and uh
and
liquid triple point is this one as you
know there is no adjacent values of
temperature and pressure but there are
other triple
points if ice
has many
uh stable some are also meta stable for
example ice 4 is not present here
because it's metast stable but uh these
are stable forms and um and therefore
you may find several uh triple points
you can have no more than three
coexisting phases for a pure substance
because the variance cannot go negative
okay now
remember that we gave these
relations uh that allow to reconstruct
the fundamental relation and in
particular energy entropy and uh
enthalpy which is useful for Bulow
applications uh when you start
from
um if you have the expressions of
how uh the coefficient of thermal
expansion
is isobaric expansion is ismal
compressibility with capacity of
constant pressure how these things
depend on tnp and this was were the
relations if we
have a pure subst
for example we could simply divide by
the
mass of that uh that we have in our
system and so we can rewrite so
e becomes little
e which I write U because we said that
we use the letter U for energy just to
remind ourselves that we are within the
simple system model
uh so the the heat capacity becomes the
specific
heat or specific heat
capacity uh this the volume becomes a
specific volume here and
here okay and so you get this expression
that allow you to
compute for any substance any pure
substance in the simple system model the
various properties
and from
that we have some
extreme simple examples that simple
behaviors that we call Ideal
Behavior the first one is the uh model
the ideal incompressible solid or fluid
model in which we
assume that the specific volume is
approximately constant
because of the
incompressibility uh it's not it is not
strictly true because the solid as you
know can be compressed the young modulus
of elasticity describes precisely that
but for
some applications or for some purposes
so for thermal aspects you may neglect
uh that changing volume and if you can
neglect that changing volume then
the compressibility and the
um coefficient of expansion are
approximately zero so if you take the
limit that they assume that they are
exactly
zero and they and that they go to zero
in such a way that from the my relation
you also have that
um it doesn't
um so so it is well behaved that because
there is a r ratio in the mayor relation
there is a ratio of where there is a
alpha P I think squared at the at the
numerator divide by Capa T and so you
have a zero over
zero so if that limit is is appropriate
then the specific Heats become
equal and I you can show that it's they
also just a function of
temperature how do you show that well
here it is if
uh if Kappa and
Alpha are
zero this coefficient here is always
zero so that means that the internal
energy is a function of temperature but
not a function of of
pressure and since the specific heat at
constant volume is the partial of the
energy with respect to temp
temperature
um it is a function it's also a function
of of of temperature Since U is a
function of T
only and if if we go here for
entropy that's true also for entropy so
if Alpha is equal to
zero entropy is a function only of the
temperature it's not true for the
enthalpy though if Alpha is equal equ Al
to zero the enthalpy depends on both
temperature and
pressure so for a
liquid the enthalpy depends on
tnp and here is the expressions for the
D DS DH
which uh are
the come from these relations here when
you substitute um with assumptions for
sorry
oops okay
all right now of course if you have from
these Expressions you may if you need to
compute the differences you just do the
integral because C varies with
temperature do do some
integrals uh sometimes U you're lucky
and the specific Heats are not functions
of temperature then in that case if you
in the range of your application you can
assume constant specific heat the
integral is easy and U sometimes you'll
also call that perfect Behavior
it's perfect only for the purpose of the
calculation because it makes it easy not
that there is anything better uh from
the physics point of
view now the ideal gas model is another
uh of course a very well known uh and
useful
model if you assume this relation for
the equation of State
we already proved that Capa T is one of
the pressure Alpha p is one of the
temperature and the mayor relation
becomes that CP is equal to cv+
R in that
case
um let's go back once more
here since Alpha is 1 / t
this coefficient in front of the of the
pressure variation is zero so it means
that the enthalpy is a function of
temperature
only and here also for the
energy Capa is 1 / P so P * 1 / p is 1
Alpha is 1 / T So T
minus t * 1 T is 1 so 1 - 1 is zero so
also the energy is a function of
temperature only whereas for the entropy
uh this Alpha is one / p and from that
you see that the entropy in the case of
an ideal gas is a function of both
temperature and pressure and here you
can integrate that I mean this is how
that formula appears comes
out and um if you use the um mayor
relation to switch from
H sometimes it is useful instead of
working with a specific at constant
pressure uh using um that constant
volume because maybe in your problem uh
one of these variables remains zero and
so it it you can choose either of these
Alternatives and again if the specific
kits are not function of temperature
which happens
in some uh cases
um then you can integrate easily
otherwise you have to do the integrals I
didn't write them
explicitly within this ideal gas
model you may realize that um the way um
uh the molecules of the
gas accumulate uh or carry the energy uh
is mainly through their degrees of
freedom so uh certainly there is the
translational and the rotational degrees
of freedom and then if you go to
sufficiently high temperatures you also
have the vibrational degrees of freedom
as well as the electronic degrees of
freedom
so at relatively low temperatures not
too low um the vibrational and
electronic degrees of freedom are less
active there is sufficient ability to
for for your molecules to accumulate
whatever energy has to be distributed
within the system by using the
translational and um
rotational uh
structure
and each degrees of freedom contributes
to the specific
heat uh a factor of 1 half remember the
famous 1 half KT that's the energy that
is carried is the equip partition energy
that is carried by h degre of Freedom at
equilibrium
so uh if you divide by T if you take the
derivative respect to t you left with 1
half of K and K is the bman constant
which one when you multiply it by the
avocad number becomes the gas constant
so for a gas that only
has translational degrees of freedom so
it can move the the
molecules are pointwise and can move in
the three directions you have the three
translational degrees of freedom so you
have one half of our contribution for
each of them so the specific
heat uh contributed by those degrees of
freedom is just three um
half of
R and then if this is CV then CP is CV
plus r so the three becomes five halves
gamma the
famous ratio of specific he is therefore
5 over three which is
1.67 right
now other molecules for example uh
oxygen or nitrogen they're be
Atomic and uh these molecules also have
the ability to uh car to to to put
energy uh yes in the vibration but most
important here we said that we
interested in the
rotation so the rotation of the
molecule
okay so if you look at
um the principal axis of uh uh
this thing
here uh the moment of universal for for
for rotation uh is large in uh uh in two
directions and very small in the other
one because along when the molecule
rotates along the axis of alignment of
X2 atoms it doesn't have uh since the
atoms are concentrated in very small
radi uh the mass is concentrated there
so the moment of inertia is small so if
you multiply like
uh moment times the uh angular
um
velocity probably squared
and U that since that m is important
only in the two directions where the the
molecule
rotates uh uh perpendicular to the axis
of alignment and so you have only in
this molecule with aligned atoms you
have only two uh additional degrees of
freedom in which the molecule can carry
the energy and that's why you go from
three plus two to five five
halves and that makes gamma equals 1.4
this is typical of oxygen nitrogen
therefore
air more complex molecules like CO2
where the
atoms are not um
aligned enjoy the possibility of uh um
of storing energy uh also in the
rotations in The three principal axis of
rotation all three have a non-
negligible moment of
of and therefore you add another three 3
+
3 have like six halfes that's three R
that's gamma equals
1.33 for example the products of
combustion also
H2O is uh
similar and as the products of
combustion are
mainly uh done with uh uh well not
exactly because
um you have
Co but okay let's say that if you have
uh
water uh in carbon dioxide uh then they
are belong they both belong to this
category uh if you have like most of the
times also air you are somewhere in
between here and there so it's a
weighted sum of 1.4
1.33 so these numbers allow you just by
looking at the the molecule to to get a
good uh rough
immediate idea of what the specific heat
is but of course as you go higher in
temperatures various thresholds you can
U activate also the various vibrational
modes of the molecule uh and even higher
you can also uh shift the electrons from
the lower uh shell to the higher shells
and that adds
to specific heat so the specific heat as
we are interpreting it as is the
capacity represents the capacity of our
molecule
to store the
energy yeah these are expressions that
are U often used when
you assume is anthropic uh uh
change so if the entropy doesn't change
um you just set from those equations
here how that the entropy remains
constant and you get these expressions
and since R is CP minus
CV um that's how you can express the
setting equal to zero this in terms of
just the ratio of the Heat capacit gamma
that's why gamma appears
here
now going back to two
phases how do
we
for well actually how do we prove this
relation here uh that um connects the
pressure and the
temperature this is called the clus
claperon relation and it gives the slope
of the saturation line on that pressure
temperature diagram that we have
uh shown
before and it it it allows you to
compute
it
using the
ratio of the enalia of the change of
phase and the volume of the change of
phase and the
temperature and the way you obtain this
relation is uh well it follows again
from the condition of equality of
chemical potentials of the single
substance we have water in the two
phases so it's it's this relation here
so one way to write it is to
take the
differential of the left hand
side and put it equal to the
differential of the right hand
side so it's the
MU because we have uh you
see the differential of uh D mu can be
written
uh if you if
you this is not written as in terms of
differential but you can see that it
also represents the differential this is
the Gibbs DM
relation okay but it's also viewed as
the differential of the chemical
potential as a function of temperature
and
pressure and the Gib relation shows that
those the partial derivatives of mu
respect to T is minus s and partial
derivative of mu with respect to P is V
okay so if I want to move from a state
in which I have these two phases
coexisting one and two could be liquid
and Vapor or ice and water
or vapor and
size and I want to move move to another
state in which I Chang the temperature
therefore also change the
pressure then it means that these the
two differences also the the the change
in chemical potential must be must be
the same so that if they were equal at
the beginning they are equal also after
and and therefore the two phases are
still in mutal
equilibrium okay so if you equate D mu y
d mu1 to with the mu2
here so eliminate these two because they
must be equal uh and you see you get a
relation between D DT and DP that
involves the differences in the specific
entropies for the two phases and the
differences in the specific volumes
which are the coefficients
here then how do we go from here to
there well again the equation
the equality for Mutual equilibrium of
the chemical
potentials remember that the chemical
potentials uh for a pure
substance is equal to the Gibs free
energy specifically Gibs free energy so
it's
I which can also be written as enthalpy
minus TS okay this is true
only for the pure substance
so if the chemical potentials are equal
it means that H minus TS must be equal
in the two phases and therefore with
this equality I can extract T and it's
equal to the ratio of the enthalpy of
the change of phase uh over the entropy
of the change of
phase and so I can substitute instead of
the entropy I I put the enthalpy of the
change of phase divided by
T let's be even more specific suppose we
just have a liquid and vapor and then
how do we compute the properties of a of
a system in which I have two
phases or three well as we said thanks
to the simple system model and this idea
of inserting and removing partition for
free uh we have represented this kind of
complex situation into a simpler one it
is a composite system of as many
subsystems as there are
phases in the in the slide here we have
only
two it's a composite system so for the
properties of the composite
system the additive properties it's easy
for example the
volume it's the volume of uh one plus
the volume of the other the energy is AD
is an additive property so the energy of
one phase plus the energy of the other
the entropy also is an additive
properties property the entropy of one
plus entropy the
enthalpy here it's also in general it is
not an addictive property but here
because the both systems have the same
uh pressure
then it it becomes
additive and then we we we would be done
except that uh in terms of expressing
how
much of the substance we have in one
phase and how much we have on in the
other sometimes we it is often used I
mean sometimes it's useful to um work in
terms of fractions
so we call for example Vapor fraction or
steam
quality uh the ratio the amount of mass
that we that is in the in the in the
vapor phase over the overall mass of our
system and uh by doing
that and substituting in dividing here
the in this uh properties the additive
properties we can compute the specific
uh properties in terms of this Mass uh
fraction and of the property specific
properties that are that characterize
each of the phases at that temperature
and
pressure so these are typically called
the with the S with the subscript gnf
and the difference is called the uh
vaporization for for for example hfg is
the enthalpy of vaporization sfg is the
entropy of vaporization and if we go
back to this expression here we have two
and one is f and g this says that the
temperature is equal to the ratio of the
eny of of the vaporization over the
entropy vaporization
these properties VG and
VF are listed in the sting tables for
the for for for water or in the
equivalent of a stin tables for other
substances or maybe they are represented
by
correlations for example the stin tables
that were developed by K and K based in
the in the in the 30s
1930 uh were correlations were based on
correlations with some
40 uh parameters that were were used to
correlate the experimental data for
water over the full range of um
applicable I mean
important um values
so we needed a lot of experimental data
and with with those four paramet 40
parameters you can uh actually construct
the entire s
tables now
pictorially uh you can represent
properties of
substances of course
yes you could do it in
a at most
three-dimensional uh
visualization and pictorially this is
what uh uh an energy versus volume
versus entropy diagram would look so
it's like uh remember the E versus S
diagram all right here we also add
volume so if I fix volume this curve
curve
here is the curve that we uh usually
would represent on aners Suess diagram
for that particular value of the volume
here is for another value of the
volume we fix the entropy then you have
energy versus volume and you follow this
line the slope of this
line is the negative of the
pressure whereas the slope of that one
is the
temperature notice that um when you when
we
have for example at the triple
point the triple
point which is a a point on the pressure
temperature
diagram becomes
a a planner region of triangle
shape called the triple triple point
triangle
here
because
uh it's true that you can have a three
the three phases only at one uh
particular set of values of p and t but
you may have uh many different states
like that for example you you we have
more ice less water and so on so all the
various
combinations give you uh two Mass
fractions so I got two degrees of
freedom and you can span within that
triangle for example
here you have almost all the
vapor here you have almost all the
liquid and here you almost on S and in
between you have all the other all the
uh possible
combination this is the region for
liquid and Vapor coexistence this is
solid and Vapor
coexistence this is the value of the
critical isotherm so this is points that
have the same temperature equal to the
critical
temperature and above that critical
isotherm we change name from Vapor we
call it gas there's no real physical
distinction but
conventionally usually you use the term
gas
where something like the ideal gas
applies now if you this is a pictor
pictorial representation if you uh try
to do it for
water and with the real property using
the steam
tables um this is how it looks and you
have to realize that
uh since the specific volum volume spans
over uh how many or maybe eight orders
of magnitude in the interesting uh Parts
not only
because there is a factor of a thousand
between the the the density of so the
specific volume of the vapor and the the
liquid but also you you as
you so that would count only for uh
three orders of magnitude here but at
lower uh pressures that this difference
becomes even more
important um it's it's inconvenient you
cannot do this on a linear scale so uh
so that you see that the this which supp
to be straight
lines have become distorted into
exponentials because uh we have used the
logarithmic SC for for for a specific
volume okay but so this this is still
the triple
Point uh
triangle and excuse the Italian here but
that was done for a booklet I have in
Italian and obviously working with
threedimensional diagrams is not uh
useful so most people have uh people who
work are with water have the DI a
diagram of this sort
um which is called the M diagram in the
form of a poster on the wall of their
offices and uh this is how the they
compute the properties of of
water and this is how uh I'm sure you
you've probably done some homeworks for
using this diagram in the old days of
your undergraduate
thermodynamics this is
another view it's like pressure versus
volume and
um yeah so I should change this because
that uh uh I forgot to to update this
Okay the reason I'm mentioning this is
because sometimes yes so you is in order
to to do this calculation here uh I I
needed all the
parameters that Kenan used for the steam
tables to obtain the real properties of
water in the full range including
drawing this Dy so this is the true
thing for
water uh there is a a much simpler model
that covers at least qualitatively uh
the liquid Vapor um
State uh which is the Vander Val
equation of
state which looks like PV * R equals RT
if it weren't for this additional term
here and this additional uh subtracting
term
here the uh this would be like the ideal
gas equation so R RS with the simple
modification of the of of the equation
of equation state for a gas for a
perfect gas for an ideal gas uh
correcting the volume we subtracting the
co volume so it's essentially something
that represents the volume not available
uh to the particles because the
particles themselves occupy some
volume and this one that has to do with
the
attractive uh forces that
that happen that are important and we'll
return to this for example when we talk
about the Leonard johnes uh potential
but the electr
electrostatics of molecules make it such
that the electrons are attracted by the
nuclei of the other molecule and so
there are some attractive forces up to a
certain stage and uh so this makes uh um
an additional contribution here so if
you if you use this expression
here it gives you um a curve which is uh
similar to the actual
curve for the actual
substance of course you cannot match
everything so one way to is to choose it
does
uh in
um a critical point and the critical
point for the Wonder vales has this
values that depends on the values of A
and B so if I have
a if I choose to select a and
b uh using um the actual values for
water for this for the critical pressure
and the critical temperature I get two
values of A and B I can uh have um a
representation of
water it's not exactly good
because there is also an expression for
the Vander vals models of the uh
specific volume at the critical point
which is also a combination of A and B
and uh if I use these
values I it will not match so that's
already a first error
that I do
but you see that sometimes simple models
capture at least qualitatively part of
the uh the
physics it actually captures also an
additional uh interesting
part in this curves here are the
isotherms okay this is the critical
ISO and these are the other ISO terms as
you go further away from the saturation
region of the two-phase region this
becomes
iperol and that's the ideal gas
behavior but the thing happens here
inside somehow this model allows you to
extrapolate also inside of the
saturation
Dome and uh so you you may go this
way then the model takes you
up and then down again so we got to a
minimum and the maximum here
so that
suggests that the for for as much as
this uh equation represents some
Physics uh it may be possible to have
States this
way the only problem is that they are
not stable equilibrium
States
because uh you see if you impose the
quality of chemical potentials here if
you look at the chemical go the chemical
potential uh the equality is obtained
only if you stop here with the liquid
and you start here with the vapor and
this
is
why uh when you do things in practice
and you like boil water in a noisy
situation uh this this is exactly the
path that is followed the system
realizes the liquid
realizes that there is a vapor with the
same chemical equilibrium in which it
could it could
boil and stay in mutual equilibrium
with
but in a less uh noisy environment you
could also go down here so it is
possible to generate these that would be
metastable
States states
that uh in which the
liquid didn't realize yet that there is
a vapor in which it it could
transform uh and also going back the
other side she could go up this way
The
Vapor can go metast stable super
saturated means it
goes uh it it remains uh Vapor even if
in in the region where in a noisy
environment it would
condense and this is actually
experimentally uh
achievable only up to this dotted line
This dotted line is called the soal is
called the
spinodal
curve and it is the locus of all the
Minima on this side and the Maxima on
that
side
and is is because in the to the left so
outside in this region
between the spinodal curve and the
saturation
dome in this region the conditions for
stability those second derivatives that
we have
developed uh are still
satisfied so the liquid can exist
there and of
course
uh it is a it is not completely stable
so it's metast stable so if you to give
it a perturbance which is large enough
it will collapse it will jump the the
liquid will immediately flash into vapor
uh or the vapor will condense uh
explosively into uh into
liquid and this flashing and uh and
U oh
um Senor moment I don't remember the
name of uh the the collapse the it's a
typical phenomenon
that can cause the erosion of for
example Blades of steam turbines
cavitation
thanks um all
right because the vapor The Vapor goes
to um to this region and then it
immediately realizes that it has to
condense and it does it in a in a in an
Abrupt way and that creates uh that's a
shock that's creates damage to the
structure
okay all right
so yeah we still have uh
few moments and uh maybe we can
go uh ahead with the what we the subject
that we left on the side but now we have
to return we did the first part and
today we'll do just a little bit more
remember we were talking about exergy
and this second LW efficiency we uh
talked about cogeneration the last time
and you told me that an it has
cogeneration which make me very happy
and uh uh and District uh and District
uh
heat okay so now that we have developed
U the simple system model and uh the
bulk
flow model for the exchange of
mass we can ask uh the question if I
have a certain
flow at certain conditions well say
pressure temperature and therefore
enthalpy
entropy and possibly also in this case I
forget about uh gravitational potential
and kinetic
energy uh so we we ask ourselves what is
the
maximum work that I can OB aain by using
that
flow in a given
environment and here I use the
environment in two
ways the first way is that I want my
Machinery to process the flow without
accumulating the material
so the mass that goes in must also go
out and must be uh given to the
environment
and I will give it to the environment at
conditions
where I have extracted as much as I
could so when it is mutual equum with
the environment
essentially at least from the thermal
point of
view and typically also the pressure
point of view so the environment here uh
provides it's also uh ambient
pressure and the other way is that I
need the environment as a damp for
damping the entropy because if I have to
change the state of my flow from one to
this ambient to environmental
conditions most likely it will have to
change entropy from S1 to
SAA and that change of
entropy suppose it's a reduction in
entropy it means that I have to extract
entropy from the
flow that's the purpose of the
machinery and of course the Machinery
will have to give it somewhere because
the Machinery operates cycle cannot
accumulate entropy
so the
um the environment is there to accept
the and at least the entropy that I must
extract from the flow in order to
exploit it but uh it may also be there
to dump also the entropy that may be
produced by irreversibility uh by the
Machinery but if we are asking for the
maximum we can do we suppose the
machiner is reversible so at least that
contribution of the entropy produced by
is not there and uh so this is the
setup as as usual you solve the problem
by making an energy balance and an
entropy
balance and setting the entropy produced
by reversibility equal to
zero this is the
result so the maximum work is the linear
combination of changing enthalpy and
changing
entropy represented here this is called
the
exergen of the flow of that bu Flow
State with respect to enir
temperature
ta and with Outlet conditions that are
ambient
conditions they noted
by of
course
uh I may also have the opposite problem
this is exactly the same situation
simply that now I don't want to exploit
a certain Val Pro State one but I want
to produce use B FL state which is at
conditions different from
uh neutal equilibrium with the
environment for example this is material
processing I want to uh or maybe I want
to heat up some
water what is the
minimum work that is needed by this
Machinery to do
it well
again we use the environment in two ways
we we we take the material from on the
environment for example we go to a mine
for raw materials or we go to a lake or
Reservoir the water res for fresh
water and we also use the environment as
a provider of the entropy that may need
be needed needed in order to achieve
that task because if uh The Bu flow
conditions one have more entropy than
ambient conditions then I need to um
give entropy to this flow and that
entropy the best way to do it is not to
generate it by
reversibility but that is to uh Pro get
it from the environment for example when
we hit up water from 20° to say
60° um I mean uh
Celsius
um yes we could also do it without
environment we just could use an
electric boiler the electric boiler
would use some
work dissipated by jeel effect so as to
generate the
entropy necessary to heat up the
water okay not use doesn't use the
environment whereas this reversible
situation is like a heat pump setup in
which I do uh
take the entropy from the environment
and the environment gives me that
entropy only if I take only also some
energy and that energy gets pumped to my
my fluid and that fluid will will
receive exactly the entropy and the
energy needed in order to go from here
to
there this is again the same exergy as
before
okay we uh I think time is up isn't it
so we'll take it from uh from here next
time