um thanks so much for sticking around
for the last Talk of the day I'm really
excited to have Nadia heninger here from
UC San Diego um for those of you who
don't know Nadia's work she's done some
of the most influential work in applied
crypto over the last um say 10 years in
both analysis and crypt analysis of
deployed protocols so lots of factoring
discrete log analysis of TLS um and has
had a ton of impact both in research and
in what systems are used in practice um
she's won best paper awards from all the
conferences and test of time Awards and
is also a wonderful speaker so thanks
for
coming so thank you so much for having
me um and it's always nice to be back in
Cambridge um enjoying your lovely
weather
uh um so uh this talk I heard some
grumbling about the title like how do
you pronounce that um so I uh I made up
this title it is a combination of two
words Crypt analysis and economics so
this talk is about sort of the structure
of our field and the different
incentives in play and how they
influence the kind of research that gets
done so this is a meta talk which is a
bunch of inside baseball so I apologize
to people who are a little bit outside
of the field some of this may be
intelligible and some of it may be like
too
obscure academic politics so um but this
this talk is going to be a mix of semi-
spicy opinions which you may or may not
um agree with and uh you can if you want
to Sidetrack me like that's cool we can
we can get totally sidetracked if you
want that that might be fun um so that
will be that will be so that that's kind
of the plan here is I will give you
semiformed semi- spicy opinions on a
variety of topics that I have a varying
amount of expertise on but I have
opinions because I've been doing this
for uh 15 years I guess um okay so
here's my madeup title with madeup word
um and yeah okay so crypto analysis and
economics and it's the economics in the
sense of markets um and incentives
rather than money strictly speaking
although money is part of it okay so the
starting point here is if we think of
ourselves as a research field um we have
some input which are essentially we get
funding from like governments and
companies and like our institutions and
the states and whatnot um and then we
have a bunch of human effort from
researchers professors students so on
and so forth and like any academic field
we produce outputs and generally the
outputs from any academic field are we
write papers and we train students who
then go like contribute to the workforce
and are like part of the development of
our civilization so that's like Academia
as a whole and then like within
cryptography as a field we have another
output which is a set of cryptographic
algorithms that we say these are good
algorithms that everybody should be
using um that we should use in this
protocol which is like proven secure and
and whatnot and like with these
parameters and like we have proven it
secure in this way and we say world go
out and use this do not invent your own
cryptography we know what you're doing
you don't so use this stuff so like as a
field we have this EXT output which is
we say like we're a science we know what
we're doing here's the algorithms that
you should be using so this is our sort
of like extra thing so this is our like
super simplified version of the world
that you know and clearly there are like
incentives and structures in play here
in what gets funded and what people
choose to work on um the other thing
that's interesting about cryptography as
a field of study is that not all fields
have such the sort of Duality that we do
so um cryptography security there
there's a constructive side and there's
a destructive side and one side in the
field of cryptography builds
cryptography the other side destroys it
that is not a typo some of you may get
the joke who gets the
joke some of you get the okay
um so yes and um you might think okay
like we we actually heard some very nice
talks about complexity Theory and lower
bounds and so you might think like um
really like the way okay so we have a
side that constructs cryptography and
then we have a side that like tries to
attack cryptography because that's
really the only way that we know how to
show that something is secure is like
people have looked at this for some
number of years and nobody has broken it
yet um and you might think like maybe
it's really only necessary to research
do research in Crypt analysis because
complexity Theory this is a failure of
complexity Theory really like if we had
strong lower bounds for certain problems
like we would not need all of these
people to try to break things because we
could just like have some concrete
complexity lower Bound for some
fundamental problem that we could then
build cryptography off of well I mean we
would also have to like resolve P versus
NP first in order to like do something
like that so it's pretty far out of
reach but even in in a fantasy world
where we could do that um we still need
attack work period because you have to
have the attacks in order to inspire the
security models that you want to prove
things to be secure in um so this is my
like argument for why attack work in
general and crypt analysis in general
isn't done and why like sort of we need
that to be a healthy side of the field
um okay and I also want to draw a sort
of analogy to um this super interesting
essay by Tim goers who's read this essay
it's like really enlightening actually
if you if you like math I recommend like
looking it up and reading it because
it's it's um it's very interesting and
very beautiful so so he writes this
essay about the two cultures of
mathematics and um many people have
written about this topic in various
formulations um but he sort of um
divides mathematicians into two worlds
one of them um like one set of of
mathematicians lives to solve problems
um and then the other sort of set of
mathematicians want to build and
understand theories um and I think other
thinkers have have called these like
frogs and Eagles for example
um and so um what goard does in his
essay is he talks about how um this way
of dividing up mathematicians ends up
influencing the the way that the field
regards certain subfields of of
mathematics so there are fields that are
largely problemsolving like
combinatorics um and there are fields
that are much more Theory building like
algebraic geometry and what ended up
happening in mathematics is that the um
sort of combinatorics fields was
generally result like thought of as like
less prestigious than algebraic geometry
because they were not doing all of this
beautiful Theory building um and that
that Prestige influences the kinds of
research that gets done and what
students study um and then I want sort
of if we go back to being in
cryptography Crypt analysis is much more
towards the problem solv in side than
the theory building side of our field
and so I think there is like a similar
structural issue going on there that um
it is somehow like less highly regarded
in a way and um if I make a super
simplistic sort of caricature of the
kinds of messaging that happens from the
different sides of the field um if you
listen to people who give talks about
sort of constructive cryptography um I
mean it's beautiful they're like
exploring the underlying truth of the
computational universe and they're
building like a bright future full of
privacy preserving technologies that
will allow companies to collect and
process all the data they want without
any legal liability whatsoever um and I
mean clearly this is like companies love
this stuff they are building the future
and they can and they can do whatever
they want because magic technology will
let them do it um whereas like on the
other side like I mean researchers are
just destroying perfectly good
cryptographic algorithms with like
one-off tricks and like okay like some
somebody screwed up their parameters
okay you fix the parameters and really
and then you like end up in this sort of
like cycle but like really it's just
like a question of parameters like
there's some parameters that work surely
um and like this is not building the
future this is destroying the future so
like why would any company want to fund
that like there's no reason why would
they do that they they want to fund the
future not the past and they don't want
to fund destruction they want to fund
things that are building the future okay
and um this this extends to like there
are certain people in the field who do
not think that attack work is like valid
science um this applies more to like
security than like cryp Crypt analysis
at least with Crypt analysis if you're
doing stuff that requires like a PhD in
math to understand um it's hard to claim
that that's not like valid research uh
but like there's kind of this notion
that it's like less scientific and it's
less valuable um and just as like
comfort for any students who are in the
room um I want to provide some anecdotes
from when I was on the job market the
first time around as a junior Professor
um this
was uh an embarrassing long time I guess
this was like 13 years ago so this was
this was a while ago but the the kinds
of questions that I got there there was
this notion that like what we really
needed was like a science of security
and in breaking things this is not
scientific you're just finding bugs like
really we need to solve this by making a
science of security and then we will no
longer have to deal with all of these
bugs is that a hand yeah I was confused
about something go back
slides yeah um I'm confused why um this
implied that privacy preserving
Technologies would allow companies to
like help companies collect data you
would think that you know privacy like
stops them data protect privacy like us
it wait I can't hear all the words
you're saying so it's it's implied for
my understanding that it says privacy
preserving technologies will help
collect and process a lot of data right
like just part from like Association
like word association it feels like you
would think that privacy preserving
technology stops them from collecting
data from like you know servers people
so like I'm just curious what's the
connection why does
that I'm being a little bit provocative
here um I mean you could you could hear
the you can hear the you could hear the
Snickers when when um half the room got
got the the implication here so
basically so what the companies so the
reason that compan are interested in
something like fully homomorphic
encryption is because what they want is
to continue collecting all the data that
they can on their customers and then be
able to like do all the metrics that
they want without like having to share
the data across departments having to
share the data like to other companies
but also like to basically tell
um like whenever they get hacked that
they they don't need to like actually
report any data breaches because no
information was revealed because it was
all encrypted so you still want to have
all of the surveillance capitalism that
is like sort of funding the internet but
without any of the problems that come
from the lack of fundamental security
that we have um with computers basically
um yeah so like I mean we know that
companies they they want fully
homomorphic encryption because they want
a magic box and the magic box is going
to solve all of their cybercity problems
that is that is what they think that
they are going to get
um okay which they you know maybe maybe
someday they will I don't know um okay
so basically the the underlying thesis
for my talk is that um like all good
dualities there is no light without the
dark and I think that in some areas of
cryptography the two sides of our field
are out of balance and this imbalance is
leading to insecurity um I don't have
necessarily solution but I want to pose
the problem and be like you know
provocative here and maybe maybe
somebody will come up with a solution or
maybe I'll just encourage you to like
break some more stuff because it's fun
um so I think basically every talk that
I give there is some XKCD cartoon at
least one in it because there's always
an appropriate XKCD cartoon so um this
is the relevant XKCD cartoon for um this
talk which is basically all modern
structure is this amazing tower that is
built upon some project that some random
person in Nebraska has been thanklessly
maintaining since 2003 yeah what is the
left pad of
cryptography the the what the the left
pad sorry uh there ComiCon reference to
a job script package left pad oh um what
what is which does exactly what it
sounds like uh do
we so um actually I'm gonna get my water
for a second um this
is a great question yes uh you you
predicted exactly the structure of my
slides this is great um so uh i' I've
got a few more variants of this but um
sort of in line actually with the
previous talk which I think LED very
very well into like the first half of
this talk that I'm going to be giving
um basically uh yeah all modern digital
infrastructure which is that like you
know we we we will be relying on RSA for
decades to come and everything does rely
on decades RSA for like has been relying
on RSA for
decades the security of RSA relies very
closely on the fact that we believe that
classical factoring costs precisely L
1/3 with cube root of 64 over 9 if you
change either of those numbers it's a
bad time
so I'll talk about that more um Okay so
for this project which I started this
project and like with as as with all
good projects I was like over ambitious
and I I actually talked to a large
number of people over the past year um
who do either relevant things and most
of these people have done some kind of
attack work um in various areas of
cryptography um and this is not a
representative sample at all this is
just like who I thought of to talk to
and the people that I thought you know
would respond to my email or whatever um
so we had super interesting
conversations which I should have
recorded more carefully and I didn't um
but I have recorded sort
of parts of them and I have Incorporated
parts of the things into this talk so
this talk these people are not to blame
for anything that is in this talk but I
do have quotes that I attribute to them
and um various ideas but yeah okay the
you know these conversations um were
quite wide ranging but um among other
things okay um Martin alre complains
that you're you're asking all these
weird introspection questions that are
kind of hard to answer so it may or may
not have been uh you
know useful or coherent um and the other
thing that I want to say is that I live
in the open research World um and so one
of the things that um Paul CER mentioned
is that the balance is really different
in the government and classified world
where offense gets the Lion Share of the
budget and Glory um and they may have
the opposite imbalance from the academic
world um and
we have some evidence in the open world
that prioritizing offense over defense
in the government has led to problems so
things like um you know famously I mean
I I teach this every year to my students
in like intro crypto classes like the
story of the NSA shortening the key
strength of Dez um which caused it to
become obsolete quite a bit earlier than
it would have otherwise um and then um
we have the dual EC drbg debacle um and
there's continuing mistrust around
standardization algorithm
recommendations um that have definitely
influenced the like ongoing M
postquantum
process so okay um so I am talking about
incentives mostly in the open
cryptography research World um so now I
have a collection of thoughts about
different areas um so this also so my
first is quantum Computing and I want to
say I am not a Quantum Computing person
I live purely in the classical World um
I in fact only understand Quantum
Computing at like a super Cartoon Level
so these are like things that I have
like gathered but you may disagree with
what I'm going to say but I think the
last talk um before the break um
introduced this quite nicely which is
essentially that the looming threat of
quantum computers is just about the
biggest thing in our field in the past
several years and when we think about
Quantum comp computers we think of sh's
algorithm because sh's Al algorithm is
going to break all classical public key
cryptography um the thing that's
interesting so you go into a group of
cryptographers and they talk about
quantum computers as like Shores
algorithm Shores algorithm sh Shores
algorithm factoring disree log elliptic
curve discreet log or hosed um but if
you go to a talk by like the people who
are actually building quantum computers
they don't want to talk about Shores
algorithm they only talk about it as
like a proof of concept or like maybe
like some like academic demonstration
they do not talk about it as like the
killer app for Quantum Computing um what
they talk about is quantum chemistry
simulations so um they don't care about
sh Shores algorithm because who cares
about Shores algorithm when you can
solve world hunger by building better
fertilizer or you're going to like solve
Disease by doing drug Discovery or
you're going to like solve energy
Problems by like building better
batteries and solar cells like this is
this is what the people who are like if
you go to these talks where they're like
actually like we built a cubid like this
is what they talk about um and like if
you're if you're like hey so when are we
going to have sh Shores algorithm like
they avoid that question like they do
not want to answer it um which is like
this weird disconnect because like
crypto versus like the quantum
people yeah talking about incentives
right uh you one reason for this might
be that uh you know NSA or Mist just put
out this refective that's said 203 by
2035 please stop using RSA so by the
time we build AUM computer that could
Factor would be that nobody in the world
is using uh
RSA at all which decreases significantly
the incentive to build a computer that
factor in the first place people are
still going to be using RSA in 2035
people are still going to be using RSA
for decades after quantum computer is
built New Uses of uh of Photography are
not going to be I mean people are going
to start slowly shifting
argue about the magnitude of that shift
um but you know um you know that could
be a reason why you know there isn't
more but there are all these
archives enough so okay so there's data
centers in Utah full of um information
that is uh encrypted in yeah is that
information valuable when it's who knows
I mean that's that's a great question uh
so but you know if if nobody actually
build ever builds a computer where you
could use shores algorithm then like do
we need to transfer like you know change
all of our cryptography maybe we should
just keep using RSA choice right I mean
uh the government systems apparently
supposed to use one of these new things
by crane 35 so yeah so it's clear that
we will have a we will have a transition
um I uh I'll get through this this like
section um
because I think that there's like a
weird there's a little bit of a weird
disconnect um that I want to like um to
point out and and like maybe maybe the
people who know more about Quantum
Computing can like uh help solve this
disconnect um I think so one of the most
enlightening things that I read about
Quantum Computing was this this is a
National's report which is now getting
quite old it's like six years old um I
don't think the conclusions have changed
even though we have had like some
progress in
building quantum computers um so I guess
the most recent like sort of news making
progress uh progress was like the Google
announcement that like they think that
they may be able to do error correction
like nobody has actually demonstrated
Quantum error correction yet but they
like think that they can probably do it
in the future um so that's like that's
the current state so so we're still at
the point where we cannot simulate a
single logical Cubit um and uh this um
this National's report the first couple
of chapters I think are like really
super well written um and like I found
them very enlightening um basically the
um the introduction is like um sort of a
history of the like classical
semiconductor industry in the 20th
century and talking about like how
transistors were were developed and
essentially that like the development of
classical computers um is the story of
like in order to get an expan IAL like
rate of progress in like building
classical computers we had this virtuous
cycle where the first computers were
like extremely useful and people bought
them because you needed to do that kind
of computation even with like room-sized
computers and then the companies
building those computers rolled all of
their um profits back into R&D and then
improved their computers and then we had
this virtuous cycle which is what led to
Mo's law which is what led to the
amazing developments in technology that
we have now um
and the argument made in this report is
that to build an entirely new
um computer architecture like a quantum
computer we need to have the scale of
engineering challenges is such that the
investment required to do all of that
engineering is probably beyond the scale
of a single government acting alone so
like beyond the scale of like the NSA or
the Chinese government um even though
they may be willing to put in billions
of dollars you actually need probably
need more on the order of trillions of
dollars like an entire economy's worth
of virtuous cycle in order to actually
fund that um that kind of engineering
progress and so um sort of the the like
conclusion is that like um it may be
beyond the scale of a single government
to like actually build like a fully
scalable like quantum computer you may
need like um a real virtuous cycle which
means that you need applications for
Quantum Computing um
and so that so the question is what
applications do we have
um and okay so like we we've also like
heard about this from from previous
talks So like um you know I talked to
Scott arenson He estimates that there's
billions of dollars of investment in in
Quantum Computing right now um and the
question is for
what because it's not Shores algorithm
because there's no market for Shores
algorithm um it's really I mean the only
people who want to run Shores algorithm
are the NSA and China um so like what do
like what do Google and IBM think that
they are investing in um and really the
only real application for quantum
computers is this quantum chemistry
simulation um which means that there
there certainly is a market for like
specialized scientific equipment being
sold to like biotech companies and and
whatnot um so like you know if you have
a quantum computer that's like $100,000
machine that can get a speed up on
quantum chemistry simulations there's
definitely a market for that but for
everything else we don't I mean we we
actually just heard a a great talk about
this we don't have like exponential time
speedups for most problems um so all the
stuff about like machine learning or
optimization like you get some
polinomial time speed ups but it's sort
of unclear whether there's actually like
a real Market or need for that um
and so I there's this weird disconnect
where like the only thing quantum
computers are good for is breaking
cryptography but the only people who
care about breaking cryptography are
governments um and so like just
realistically like for you know we can
do some threat modeling like for you
know any entity who's using cryptography
um if your attacker is breaking
cryptography they're either pirating
copy protected content or they're a
government like essentially nobody cares
nobody else cares enough to break
cryptography um and like this is this is
great news because like cryptography is
doing way better than the rest of
security where it's just a constant
disaster all the time um so like I mean
essentially like this is like you know
how you just have to outrun your other
colleagues in front of the bear like
then you're doing great right like um so
um essentially like cryptography
essentially makes like you know we we
know that real systems get compromised
by like fishing and social engineering
and not really breaking cryptography
most of the time um unless your
adversary is a government um and so like
those are somebody else's problem really
like cryptography we're doing great um
but that means that
like normal people don't need to run
Shores algorithm on their cell phones so
we don't need a
Quantum like we don't need a a Quantum
co-processor on every smartphone in the
world so what are quantum computers for
essentially like there's no Mass market
for sh Shores algorithm um the C the
customers for sh Shores algorithm are
handful of large governments the people
who are building quantum computers think
of Shores algorithm as a proof of
concept and not an end
product and so um if Shores algorithm
ever becomes feasible it's going to be a
byproduct of other things that the
market cares more about and so if it is
a b it is if it is a direct byproduct of
quantum chemistry simulations then we
may be in trouble but if you need
something much beyond that then I don't
know is it ever going to be built like
because the market incentives just
aren't
there so I just wanted to point out this
disconnect so this is my first like
spicy opinion on Quantum Computing which
is not my research area yeah there's if
they're going to build like invest and
do research and build this F for or
whatever reason whether it's chemical
simulation or whatever then they'll be
able to implement your's algorithm once
they have the technology there then it
will be like so if the if the cubits you
need to do quantum chemistry simulations
work in the same way and like the the
circuits that you need to build and the
air correction that you need to do if
that is all the same then yes it will
happen if you need if you need to
do something else
architecturally then it seems less
likely to
happen just heard of I'm not going to
attribute to one of the faulty members
here that uh Quantum factoring is is an
easier problem completely in terms of
building than quantum chemistry again
this is a blackbox statement uh I don't
know any details and I'm not even
attributing to anybody so this is
interesting this is the first time that
I've heard that factoring is easier than
quantum chemistry H I priv tell you that
okay we
will we will talk offline then
um yeah the uh the the statement was
that um an unknown source uh says an
unnamed Source um says that um factoring
is easier than quantum chemistry
simulation so if that's the case um I
guess that set that sets up an
interesting set of incentives so if
factoring goes along the way to build
like the $100,000 specialized like um
scientific equipment that you can sell
to like biotech companies
um if there's enough of a market to sell
the specialized scientific equipment to
like um to biotech companies Plus sell
your facturing machines to the NSA then
then like yeah maybe maybe the the
things are maybe maybe the incentives
are aligned so another incentive is to
be richer than S
okay so so yes uh you were you were
saying there's a market for stealing
Bitcoin and
[Laughter]
um uh so this this yeah I mean the
question is um is there anything that
could get Bitcoin to go away um
and I don't I don't think the security
claims of um cryptocurrencies are why
people keep in investing in
them
uh so so yeah
um I so I I don't know like whether the
engineering challenges can be overcome
in building a quantum computer I mean I
think none of us do right and like this
is also not our area because we do like
the cryptography and like maybe the
algorithm side but not the like you know
deep Frozen Cubit side um so but it's
yeah
um it is an entirely new Computing
architecture and we've had proposals for
very compelling entirely new Computing
architectures in the past like you talk
to gray beards and they'll talk about
like Optical Computing in the 90s and
like we don't have Optical computers now
even though they could do like super
awesome things so yeah
um I think I think it's just worth
thinking about like what good is an
entirely new Computing architecture for
um and clearly like we have some
applications but we don't have general
purpose Computing applications and so
the question is like is there a market
for the special purpose Computing
applications that they are good for um
that is enough to fund the engineering
developments the financial industry is
very dependent on traditional
cryptography if they don't change then
there's certainly an incentive for a
malan actor to to go after the whole
thing I don't think cryptography is
really the thing that is protecting the
financial industry think regulation is
the thing that's protecting the the
financial industry
um uh I mean you know a lot large
portions of the fin Finance industry are
still using single de from what I hear
so like
um I don't know so um okay actually so
if we go to um this the topic of who is
willing to bet on um factoring like
quantumly versus classically um and I
made this slide before I heard of any
bets that um that venod was was willing
to put money towards um so I asked my
various panelists their opinions of
whether 20 48 bit RSA would happen
classically or quantumly first um and
they were split so some people said
Quantum some people said classical um
Antoine J has a running bet against Dan
Bernstein um on this
topic Quant have
quantumly yes 24 days
um and um actually like on the topic of
the talk that just preceded mine um I
think uh it is a compelling argument um
this was this was raised by Tomas PTO um
that um you know the original Shores
algorithm was clearly sort of infeasible
to build with a reasonable number of
physical cubits um but uh perhaps we
will actually sort of meet in the middle
with algorithmic improvements um that
this is like a compelling line of
research yeah you have a timeline on any
of
these no so it could be so so this this
is this is yeah instead of saying like
by 2040 we're going to have like 20 40
40 bit RSA this is just Quantum versus
classical who who gets to 20 uh who gets
to 20 48 bits
first um and uh so this this seems like
a a compelling Direction essentially
like in order for shor's algorithm to
actually become feasible we really need
to get the the complexity down we've
heard this from multiple angles um so
that's cool
um so short little interlude um one
thing like I'm a little bit too young
for this but like my favorite papers are
like all written in the 90s cuz it was
like super fun then like it was like all
the stories that you hear of like crypto
like people were like proposing schemes
and then they get like broken in the
rump session and it's like um and
there's all these like beautiful attacks
that are like Elementary number Theory
and you're just like a this is so great
um and like it is not that fun anymore
like the papers are like so long and
they're like so complicated and like the
attack techniques are like so long and
it's so complicated like it's really
it's like way less fun um and uh like
talking to some of the people that I
interviewed um you know for example like
Paul cotcher okay he like invented side
Channel attacks like against
cryptography and basically he said that
like you know he started by doing
classical Crypt analysis but then that
got too hard and so like when the actual
like classical crypto analysis like when
people improved their implementation so
much that you couldn't just like break
them out right you needed stronger
attack techniques so you needed a better
attack technique invent side Channel
attacks turns out that like nobody can
protect against side Channel attacks um
so uh that's kind of um um like One
Direction um yeah Emanuel to had like um
sort of points out that there's been
this shifting balance so like there used
to be a lot more Crypt analysis papers
25 or 30 years ago um and we see like
you know um far fewer now um and some of
that so antoan J um says like with
provable security people are making
fewer and fewer stupid mistakes the
kinds of things that made Crypt analysis
possible without breaking the algorithms
um sometimes there are things left over
but it's really getting harder to get
interesting resultss so in some sense
this is good news for the constructive
side that there are better tools there
are better proof techniques there's
better analysis um so you can publish
papers without making like super
embarrassing mistakes but this also
means there's fewer targets for upand
cominging researchers to like you know
sharpen their teeth on
essentially um
and if you want to have like a pipeline
of people who know how to do Crypt
analysis they have to publish papers on
something so the question is what like
are we training the next generation of
of um like Crypt analysis researchers
and um kind of I mean clearly we still
are because there are still like you
know young people who are working on the
on these kinds of things so like Tomas
PTO you know he got his PhD a few years
ago so I guess is like fairly young um
and like his philosophy towards breaking
lattice schemes is there's like three
things that you can do you can look at
the scheme and you can get like an
incremental algorithmic Improvement on
some fundamental hard problem like lwe
or whatever um you can look at the crazy
new assumptions that people have to come
up with because if you actually want to
build like fully homomorphic encryption
or like zero knowledge proofs or
whatever like you need some like some
special variant of like ring LW you
can't just use like the the main scheme
and so like those variants are more
subject to attack but like if you can't
break that then you just do a side
Channel and you know that the side
channel is going to work so like that's
how you publish the paper and um that's
why there's so many side Channel papers
right but this means that like people in
the popular press think that side
channels are an actual real
problem even though
like it's a super strong like threat
model that like your adversary is
running a process like collocated on the
same processor as yours um so like this
is one of these weird incentive things
that like people have to publish papers
somehow people are not publishing nearly
as many papers on like social
engineering techniques even though we
know like that's actually how companies
get hacked and not side Channel attacks
but then the companies are like oh we
really have to fix this like whatever
this new like meltdown variant that is
coming out so that's like a weird thing
that's coming out like the imbalances in
our field that we have to keep
publishing papers mean that companies
are focusing on the wrong things in a
weird way um so from a paper publishing
perspective like if you're a student
here's one way to think about like how
to look at a solve a problem is like you
have some Target problem you want to
solve you have a collection of attack
techniques and you iterate through your
collection of attack techniques and you
try to just whack your problem with with
each of them and see if you get a hit so
that's one way to to do something yeah
is it actually true that the companies
are focusing on these things that people
publish
or they know better I think a lot of
companies are freaking out about like
patching against like the most latest
like side Channel
attack but that's also easier to catch
against that than to prevent social
engineering attacks yes so I mean there
there may be an effect of like you do
what you can and certainly you will look
irresponsible if like somebody if you
like don't patch against a thing that
somebody told you were vulnerable
against but like maybe that's not the
best use of time
so was there a hint you since we're
saying Pap like things you know like
side tax like and the companies are like
looking at them getting worried can you
just at the end say you know don't
worry that not is that not nobody will
yeah I mean if you if you don't say your
paper is like the most important thing
to happen like the reviewers are
definitely not going to accept it
your University is going to be much
happier if you got a lot of press about
your article um and the Press they have
to say that it's like the newest and
greatest attack because like that's why
it's novel so there's a whole there's
whole layers of incentives here where
like we know the game that we're playing
but not everybody else knows the game
that we're
playing um
I have thought about how to write the
paper of like is anybody actually
exploiting a side Channel attack
ever um it's a good title is anybody
exploting a side Channel attack so
um I have I have asked around if anybody
has ever seen exploitation of a side
Channel attack um
and there okay so the um and and people
people are always like yeah we saw some
like CCC talk from like whenever where
somebody did a side Channel attack um so
I have seen so there was
one super fun
paper like a couple years
ago what was the name of the scheme it
was it was like a broken
European um
proprietary uh encryption scheme where
in order to reverse engineer the scheme
they had to do a blind AES cachee attack
um against the encrypted firmware that
they were trying to break so that is
clearly a case where like those kinds of
vulnerability researchers like it turns
out that like doing a an ases cach
attack can actually be the way that you
you get your keys in order to like
decrypt the firmware that you're trying
to reverse engineer so that is that is a
a side Channel attack threat model that
I will absolutely accept that like you
have the hardware you can you can do all
the side channels you want um also like
apparently the like people stealing payv
and stuff were were totally like doing
side Channel attacks to to steal um the
um whatever the encryption key of the
day was um so like that kind of threat
model where like the attacker has like
unlimited physical access to like a
machine that is like doing encryption
that's definitely like a real side
Channel model but then the the case of
like General software the most that I've
heard is that apparently like the
Spectre and meltdown code code was
included in like metlo or like some some
like version of that that appeared in
some malware um but I've never heard of
like a
real Attack of that
form ipes are stolen it's like one of
the ways to steal technology is to do an
attack on the the Cryptor which loads
the software onto the
fpga uh so that's a practical one uh and
there are some other government
sectors where they probably do this type
of thing but they're not going to
publish it yeah I I I I believe that so
um yeah that's that's another that's
another example of of like in order to
do yeah reverse engineering or other
kinds of stealing like you actually have
like an encrypted Target and you have
like physical access to it and um and a
side Channel attack is actually the the
right thing to do point
it's when these attacks happen
that's that's that's one of the
difficulties in in like writing this
paper is like how do you prove that
something was or was not a side Channel
attack um so yeah I I don't know how to
like it could be that I'm totally wrong
and people are exploiting them all over
the place but usually it's not the
easiest way to to get
data um okay um for the students I want
to say there's another approach to
solving problems that you can adopt
which is um this is an anecdote about
Fineman from this um fun uh talk SL
essay um from uh Roa 10 lessons I wish
i' had been taught so he he tells this
anecdote about Fineman um he was fond of
giving the following advice on how to be
a genius you keep a dozen of your
favorite problems in constantly in your
mind and every time you hear read a new
trick or new result test against your 12
problems and see whether it helps every
once in a while thebody hit people say
how did he do it he must be a genius so
this is like the opposite direction
where you like um have some dictionary
of Target problems and then every time
you learn a new technique you like whack
all of your target problems with it and
every once in a while you get a you get
a technique um I think I accidentally
ended up doing this except it turned
down to like I would read some like
paper from the 90s and then like scan
the internet and find somebody who
screwed it up and publish a paper that's
how I got a job
[Music]
um okay um anyway that's how I got
interested in this stuff um so I want to
tell you about classical and factoring
and discret log a little bit so yes
people still use RSA and Diffy Helman
like um mod primes and they will be for
a long time and basically okay so uh if
we look at the data going across ucsd's
Network um right now about 22% of SSH
connections use RSA host Keys um 83% of
TLS 1.2 connections use RSA signatures
um we can't see the signatures in TLS
1.3 because they're encrypted good job
TLS 1.3 um but uh
certificates are like basically this is
the fraction of certificates that are
using RSA public keys so there their
signatures are going to be RSA like no
matter whether you're using TS 1.2 or
1.3 um and TS 1.3 also everybody is is
only using elliptic curve Diffy Helman
but um the protocol itself supports a
list of named finite field Diffy Helman
groups that are like specified
hard-coded smallest size is 20 48 bits
so like these are there um
and most implementers are skeptical
enough about the postquantum schemes
that they are going to be doing hybrid
so we actually are going to still be
seeing these schemes for a long
time okay so going back to our um
cartoon here um all modern digital
infrastructure if you look at who's
actually studying this problem it's five
underpaid French
researchers that's it okay so um we have
heard that uh factoring and discrete log
are well understood and well studied
problems the best algorithm that we have
for these is called the number field Civ
there is a spooky connection between
factoring and finite field discreet log
um that the they're like analogous
algorithms for like both in in many
cases um so number field Civ um this is
like a picture of the structure of this
algorithm it's a super complicated
algorithm with a billion different
parameters that you have to optimize
just right in order to get it to work at
all um if you optimize everything
correctly ASM totically your running
time is this like ugly looking function
like L of 1/3 there's a parameter n
which is either the modulus or like your
Prime that you're doing discret log mod
um and then you have this uh constant
which is in the exponent which is like
cube root of 64 over 9 um and so this L
function comes up whenever you need to
do heuristics involving the prime number
theor to like get bounds on the
smoothness of like random numbers of a
particular size so basically it's like
exponential in like log n the 1/3
there's this ugly constant in the front
which is in the exponent so it really
matters and then there's this log log n
to the 2/3 so like basically the running
times of all of these algorithms have
this
structure um all right and then if you
look at like concrete progress uh this
is essentially what factoring discret
log algorithm progress looks like um
over the past few decades you you can
see there was like constant progress and
then people kind I don't know sort of
petered out um but like factoring is
like a little bit it's like a constant
Factor harder than discret log turns out
for like it's hidden by the astics but
um it's slightly harder apparently um
and the way that these records work um I
think Arian ler was involved in like
most of the ones down
here um and then but like the way it
works is like every few years some
academics are like hey do we do another
factoring record and everybody like
pulls out their like supercomputer
access or their own custers and then
they like you know run the software for
a little while like transfer some files
over and then like publish a paper
that's basically like a trip report of
like here's what we did and like doing
doing this kind of computation honestly
is kind of a drag like so okay I I had
like a small part in in like that little
um most recent bubble which basically
consisted of like babysitting a
computation like part of the computation
on on my cluster um and like you have to
deal with like file system stuff and
like you get like Corruptions and then
like you know we have like some ungodly
like SSH Tunnel open to France and it
like you know the stuff just like goes
down and like um like maintaining
Hardware is like a giant drag um so it's
yeah it's just kind of painful to do um
and so it's really like a a collection
of like funky little academics most them
in France who actually do this stuff so
if you actually want to compute like
factorizations of integers the software
that you're going to use is called K NFS
um it is written by this team in inria
um they credit many people but like
there's varying I mean there's varying
amounts of of contribution or whatnot um
but like this is this is the software
you want to use
um and um there have actually been
improvements in uh this area um by
recent I mean I guess this past couple
of decades um so the running time as we
heard of the the general number field C
um is this uh ugly function here which
has been the same since like 1993 or
1991 whatever um and but there actually
have been improvements so for discret
log the Final Phase of discret log there
was an ASM totic Improvement that
improved the constant in this exponent
from cube root of 64 over 9 to basically
Like This
1.2 um and this makes a huge difference
this is the difference between for
like
um 512 to 1024 bit numbers like this is
like years of computation this this is
like years of computation to like
minutes of computation um and um more
spectacularly in 2013 there was a series
of improvements um that brought the
running time for discret log in a fin
field of small characteristic from this
subexponential running time like L of
1/3 to quasi polinomial so like
basically end to the like o of login um
and this freaked a bunch of people out
but there was no sort of obvious
extension to large characteristic finite
field which is what we actually use for
cryptography or to factoring so like
that sort of petered out um but I want
to say like even if you had a tiny
looking Improvement in the running time
so like if you could improve this cube
root of 64 over9 to cube root of 32
over9 so this is the running time of the
special number what's called the special
number field cve um this is academically
easy for 1024 bit factoring this like
this was done 15 years ago um by
academics um if you had if you improved
this 1/3 to a 1/4 this would take out
2048 bits so if you think that 2048 bit
RSA is is not going to be done anytime
soon you are putting a bet that this 1/3
can never be improv to
1/4 um which this is an ugly looking
running time like do you really think
that's the running time for such a
fundamental sounding problem is
factoring like how willing are you to
bet on
this yeah some well why is it I mean
who's working on it 500 PA French
people um okay uh so just back at the
envelope it's like why has nobody done
1024-bit RSA um the answer is because
like I mean somebody could have like
clearly this was done by the NSA like 15
years ago like if they didn't do it like
what are tax dollars for this
is this is like without any algorithmic
improvements and this is running on CPUs
so like you know um call up sheny and
like build some like special purpose
hardware and then like you know you
bring this down by a factor of 100 and
like your golden basically
um so like yeah it's it's clearly
feasible it's just that like this is a
pain for academics so like we're talking
about doing it you know we'll probably
do it soon I don't know um but like okay
why hasn't there been any Improvement um
and the the thing is nobody's working on
this problem so as I said it's five
underpaid French people they're like in
non and then if you want to count antoan
J he's in like Zar broken now um but
like basically one of the things that
happened with like provable cryptography
is that we had this separation between
constructions and crypt analysis and
people focused a lot more on the
constructions um and they were insulated
from the actual mathematical structure
of the problems that they were working
on which meant that like they just said
assumption factoring is hard we're done
and we don't need to learn all of this
like complicated math that's involved in
the number field Civ and so you don't
have a pipeline of students who
understand these things nobody studies
this in the US um and so the work has
like sort of gone elsewhere um so like
literally really nobody is sort of
thinking about this within France it's
kind of an interesting structure that um
the structure of inria as like a
scientific lab they actually like the um
researchers are actually supported like
doing software development is part of
their job and so they can be like oh I
only published like one paper this year
but I like built this software package
and so like they get evaluated on that
this is not something that you can do in
the US as a professor like you have to
like pump out papers you can't be like
oh I publish the software package um but
sort of more fundamentally like one of
the reasons I think nobody's working on
this is like within computer science
this is not a good topic for grad
students to work on because you're not
going to get a job the jobs are if you
study cryptography you're going to go
work for a company who wants to build
fhe or like wants somebody to help them
with their postquantum transition
studying something like the number field
Civ is not going to get you a job and so
like I can't in good faith like
recommend grad students work on this
topic which means that nobody except
these five underpaid French people is
working on it everybody's like oh
factoring is a super well-studied
problem but really the people who were
studying it in the early 90s they're all
retiring and there isn't another
Generation Um so I think yeah that's
that's like one of the structural issues
um so if you compare the like billions
of dollars a year being put into Quantum
Computing to the current investment in
the kinds of research that would lead to
factoring discret log improvements
classically it's at most hundreds of
thousands of dollars a year to like fund
like a team of a handful of French
researchers and like a few grad students
um so that's where the incentives are
not aligned um and so like if you know
if you talk to the people who actually
understand this topic like Emanuel to is
willing to put out there that he thinks
the correct running time for factoring
in discret log is quasi polom
but we don't know how to do it like
obviously if they knew how to do it like
you would do it um so like you could you
could like get some increased investment
but it's unclear what the payoff would
be because maybe the technology to do it
doesn't exist I don't know like we can't
actually say that we're going to to have
it so Emanuel says that like if there
was more investment like um in the field
maybe you could have found the small
characteristics ofet log improvements
like 5 to 10 years earlier so possibly
something like that is true for
factoring but maybe maybe it's just
maybe actually that is the running time
we don't actually
know
yeah the number of sa and the quadratic
and so forth came up uh it was
congressman's algorithm which only
worked for small characteristics and uh
right and got the right time so so to
the extent that history is uh
repeats so I mean there could be a real
difference between small characteristic
and large characteristic discret log um
because yeah I mean there
were there were like structural there
are structural things that you can do in
small characteristic that you just
cannot do um in large characteristic
so yeah might
be um what about the problem and Cur I
have a little bit about that later yeah
yeah a couple yeah okay I will I can
speed up um
maybe I will I'll speed through the
isogeny part but like you know we had we
had this amazing spectacular break on um
on psych um and like uh but the isogeny
people are like don't worry the field is
healthy we're super happy um and the
thing is like right now it's the same
people doing constructive cryptography
and crypt analysis in isogenes um and um
the there's like a feedback loop between
the constructions and the Crypt analysis
that is actually much healthier than in
other areas um which this was just
posted the other day and it's amazing
like this pre-print was posted and then
it was broken the next day so this is
like going back to the 90s so if you
want an exciting area um isogenes the
the isogeny club people are like
deliriously happy um and so they're like
don't worry higher dimensional isogenes
are great um so we're going to build
everything the spicy thing that I want
to say that um was brought up by
um castri and J crew who I talked about
um uh or talked to um is that if you
look at elliptic curve discreet log
versus factoring um the people are
worried about elliptic curve discreet
log from a Quantum perspective because
our key sizes are so so much smaller for
elliptic curves than for factoring
um but there's another thing which is
going on which is sort of this
dictionary between number Theory and
algebraic geometry
um which exists like sort of all the way
through mathematics which is that um
there's a lot of problems on the number
theory side that are hard so problems
over the integers are hard for some
reason so like factoring integers is
hard like SVP over an integer lattice is
hard um the reman hypothesis is pretty
hard to resolve if you look at the
analogous problems in like the function
field World um everything is easier over
po nomials and their extensions so like
factoring pols is easy um solving SVP is
easy over a lattice of polinomial in any
lattice with like a non- archimedian
norm um like the analog of the reman
hypothesis was resolved quite some time
ago for function
fields and so elliptic curve discreet
log lives on this side of this
table and so like from the mathematical
perspective and this is way beyond my
math knowledge um the elliptic curve
disre log problem has a lot more
structure than factoring it's an isogen
finding problem and as we've seen there
um improvements that have been made in
isogenies um the existing isogeny
attacks fail because the degree of the
isog is is secret but in general what
was pointed out is sort of the geometry
of elliptic curves is easier over finite
Fields some people will argue like maybe
like elliptic curve groups are the
closest to like abstract groups that we
could get but this is Food For Thought
if you like um sort of academic uh
conspiracy theories so I think I am over
time so I
will maybe skip to the end yeah there's
this perhaps academic question of you
know can can you find any way in which
elliptic CS behave differently from a
generic tic groups behave differently
from a generic that could be like a
contrived problem that can show as hard
in the generic one would you have an
attack have such an example right to the
best of my
knowledge is there any that's for super
singular
curves okay so is there any way in which
elliptic curv groups behave differently
from from generic
groups
do I guess if you Ru out all the attack
on special cases no no no no that's one
time one but there's there's there's
other okay so yeah you could you could
take okay you could take the entire
space of elliptic curves and and carve
it up into classes of curves for which
you have attacks or behaviors and the
curves that we are using for
cryptography have basically been chosen
so that like none of those
characteristics apply and so then okay
we don't know but like yeah I guess yeah
to your point we do have cases of
elliptic curves that behave differently
but those curves have sort of a hard
potentially diff helment problem right
I'm saying make up your own G to the
powers of some X and then something
something something can you come up with
a contr problem which is harder the
generic group work than for these curves
that are used in
practice perhaps an academic question
but would to give some incited to why
these guys behave differently from a
generic group right that would be yeah
that's that's an interesting question I
don't know if anybody has done that
there was a little bit of an argument I
guess I sped by it the the riddle
wrapped in an enigma um article by um
coas and menzes um sort of talking about
like you know is it possible that the
NSA has back doored the um elliptic
curve standards um they have sort of an
argument maybe it's a little bit
different in flavor than what you're um
suggesting that like um if you wanted to
essentially back to our family of
elliptic curves like how would you
generate it such that like there is like
a dense enough set that you would be
able to find one um and sort of they
they they argue that it seems unlikely
that that would have been possible um so
uh but yeah I don't know anyway um I
think I'm over time so I will I will um
wrap up here and then I guess yeah
there's stuff that I sped through that
didn't talk about but essentially like I
think that there's an imbalance in
incentives um between constructive
cryptography and crypt analysis that
leads to late surprises um and
um I sped through the lat stuff uh but
if you're a student lattice assumptions
great project um and a focus but a focus
on constructions is probably best if you
want to actually be employed um and
there is a serious lack of number
theorists in cryptography in in the
United States um for various structural
reasons and um I think that we do not
have the end of the story for classical
factoring discreet log and elliptic
curve discreet log but there is a real
incentive gap for research we need to
have a healthier um population of like
real number theorists and I'm not a real
number theorist uh working on this stuff
and this is not also not a good project
for grad students um although perhaps if
you work with venod he can come up with
like a compelling story that may help
like make make progress I don't know but
anyway so that is my shortened version
of of spicy opinion so thank you very
[Applause]
much yeah um maybe another spicy
question but I'm wondering like I think
there a lot of things in the world that
are very productive that we have decided
are not meant in the academy and do
think like is this something that's like
just a public good and the government
just fund separately like there should
be like this should have like an
analysis section and this is not really
a good pit for research or is this
actually a good pit for research we like
restructure
incentives um I mean I think it is it is
a good uh it is a good idea to call
crypto analysis like a public good um
that should be sort of funded like
separately from like the market or like
we shouldn't rely on Commercial
incentives to to fund this kind of thing
I guess um the US government's approach
for a very long time was that like this
is the job of the NSA and so like they
do fund large numbers of like very very
good mathematicians to think about these
problems all day and not all night um
but then they wouldn't tell the rest of
us about it I mean like the the
relationship between nist and the NSA
was supposed to be that like nist would
be like hey and the NSA would be like
don't do this or this or this and then
like they would go back but now we no
longer trust the NSA to like be truthful
in doing that so there is an argument to
to be said that like yeah maybe we
should have like a public
um like a more public
facing um research group uh who does
that kind of thing and like we do have
National Labs um but you know
cryptography tends to be like a very
high clearance level and so stuff
doesn't like come out of like out of
that direction um so this is one way
where I I think Europe really does do a
better job because if like you look at
France you look at all the people at
inria like a lot of the people that I
that I mentioned are like at inria or
like were in Europe um because like you
know Germany has Max plank institutes
and and like France has has inria and
like we have these other you know
basically like government funded
organizations where they're like we're
going to do fundamental research and
computational number Theory and it will
be good for the world um so yeah it
might be nice to have that um
structurally I mean I think one one
issue in the US is it's great that the
like most of our universities are funded
by the governments in a lot of ways but
it's led to weird incentives like I'm at
the University of California which like
originally was generously funded by the
state of California but they've like
been cutting funding over
the um over the decades and then it's
been made up for by NSF funding but like
if we have political instability that is
like causing our grants
to come into question then like it's
hard to yeah but then then people are
making up that for that by like let's
get corporate funding but now the
corporations are like we only want to
fund AI um so yeah I mean it's it's a
mess a little bit Yeah AB question so
you talk about how there's um some like
a lot of attack know things that um
there not enough money cost so cost a
lot of money cost need a lot of
expertise need a lot of you know effort
that is like just kind of not for plot
of to do it doesn't this also mean that
like are so hard not wor doing like
nobody want you try to do it and so like
it's going to be secure for a while
well so okay is is um if the attack is
is too much of a pain for academics to
carry out does that mean that the scheme
is
secure um so I would argue that um the
incentives of uh different organizations
are different and so we know that there
we know that there are governments who
have have a very strong incentive to
break cryptography um and so if the I
guess the question is like if you are
Google and you consider both the NSA and
the Chinese government to be a potential
adversary in this area and these
governments are willing to put in
hundreds of millions of dollars towards
Crypt analysis in the private in in
their government um uh organizations um
but they are they are a threat but you
are Google so you're relying on what the
public research Community is telling you
to use um then there's a misalignment
there so say it's possible the
government like you know solve whatever
the problems
thats
are uh absolutely I mean basically as
like as I said if the NSA wasn't
factoring 1024b RSA 15 years ago or more
where are my tax dollars going like I
will be personally disappointed if they
do not have like their their machine
just set up like crunching um well both
1024 but just discret log and and
factoring um and like they have people
who can build special purpose Hardware
they have the best people in the world
who can design algorithmic improvements
um even like get constant Factor
improvements that that
like come on it has to be feasible like
if they're not doing I'm I'm I'm I'm
very disappointed in them um but like
yeah they they have
and we know that they they want to do it
and that they have an actual incentive
to do it and they have the budget to do
it whereas
like five underpaid French researchers
um are very interested in the topic but
do not have the resources of the
NSA we should there yeah cool
[Applause]