I'm from a city called
Valencia in eastern Spain,
in the Mediterranean.
So very nice weather, very nice food.
I come from a family
where there's no scientists.
My parents didn't go
to college or anything.
So I'm first generation.
And, you know, my
parents, they read a lot.
So they were well-educated people
despite not having gone to college.
I was always very naturally curious.
I was always asked, and
why, and why, and why.
And I also kind of remember
my parents in the car rides,
getting a little bit
annoyed by my constant asking,
why is this, why is that?
You know, why is the
moon following us, you know,
when we're in the car?
It turns out that I like science.
And I started to take
college classes in physics
when I was in high school.
And I liked it.
Ended up at the University of Valencia
where I studied physics in my hometown.
I was going to do my PhD in the
University of Valencia
because that's what 99% of my friends
did, but then one of my teachers,
one of my college professors told me,
you know, you're doing quite well.
I think you would be
able to do better research
abroad than in Spain.
The most exciting physics was
going on in the US at the time.
And UCSD was one of the
places where this was quite good.
I intended to do my PhD in
theoretical particle physics,
but there I got
exposed to all of physics,
very high quality research
in all fields of physics.
So I slowly and gradually
became more and more interested
in other areas of physics.
At the ultimate level, it is physics
just responsible for everything that
happens in the universe
and that explains it.
That power of using
math and a few concepts
to kind of explain everything,
that is super
appealing to me intellectually.
I had heard about MIT obviously before,
but by the end of my PhD and postdoc,
I knew what MIT really meant.
First week or two that I was at MIT,
they have this thing for faculty called
their random faculty dinners.
And I had next to me on one
side sitting Wolfgang Ketterle,
who's Nobel Prize in physics.
And on the other side, Peter Schor,
who has gotten about every prize,
but is the inventor of the
field of quantum computing.
And I remember thinking,
well, if this is what happens
when you sit randomly, you know,
between two faculty at MIT, where am I?
I almost feel a little bit
awkward or selfish saying,
but it's largely having fun, you know.
It is really the people
that make this place great.
It feels very different
intellectually from other places.
Many of my colleagues,
despite who they are,
they're actually very humble, you know.
Most people are very open-minded.
They're happy to learn from others.
They are intellectually curious.
Being part of a big community
that is doing interesting research
and advancing the frontiers of knowledge,
that's something that's also very
stimulating and rewarding.