Welcome to this evening's broad
discovery series event. My name is Tom
Olrich. I'm the associate director for
science communications here at the Broad
and I'm thrilled to have you all joining
here in the room and also folks watching
online.
If you're not familiar with it, um the
Broad Discovery series explores the
genetic and biological roots of human
health and disease, the mechanisms that
govern how our cells and our bodies
function, new technologies that are
changing what's possible in science, and
the progress that's being made to
translate new discoveries into
treatments for both common and rare
diseases. For this evening's event,
we've partnered with our friends at the
Broad Ignite program, which if you're
not familiar with it, champions the
early career researchers at Broad with
Bold who have bro bold innovative
ideas and Carpenter who is an institute
scientist, senior director of the
Broad's imaging platform, a past
Broadign Ignite awardee, and the current
Broad Ignite co-chair will tell you a
little bit more about the program.
She'll also introduce tonight's
speakers, Raldon Name and Shere Wang,
who are two of the program's talented
awardees. If you have any questions for
our speakers tonight, I encourage you to
flag down one of our micr runners during
the Q&A portion of the evening. And if
you're watching on YouTube, I'll be
keeping an eye on YouTube chat. You can
type your questions in there, and I'll
work do my best to try to work them into
this evening's discussion.
If you're a Brody or a scientist with a
deep scientific question, um I'm going
to ask you to please hold your questions
until the reception so that members of
the community get a chance to have their
questions
answered. And speaking of the reception,
if you're in the room, I invite you all
to join us in the Broad Discovery Center
right out here in the lobby after the
talks are over uh to join us for some
late
refreshments. And with that and over to
you.
Thanks, Tom.
Hi everyone and thank you um to the
folks online also who are with us today.
I am uh want to welcome you and to
specifically describe a bit about the
broad Ignite program which funded the
two awardees who are going to be
speaking tonight about their important
work in brain cell communication. Broad
Ignite launched about 10 years ago. It's
a philanthropic program that supports um
innovative early career research. So
really going for the uh the folks that
are early on in their career, haven't
had a chance to really make their mark
or um try their own innovative ideas. We
really want to give them the footing to
be able to to try something a bit risky
and a bit new. Um and that really pay
that that uh investment really pays off.
We have funded 76 projects over the past
decade with the program and we've seen
many of the awardees who are graduate
students, postocs, early career go on to
become leaders in their fields uh across
the globe and that's really such a
delight to see our impact on global
science through this um program of of of
awards here at the Broad. Um, in
addition to the ca the grant funding
that goes to each awardee to support the
research that they're most excited
about, each awardee has uh a a kind of
customized program of career support to
help them learn how to speak um to
audiences better um and to convey the
excitement of the research that they do
as well as mentoring and that kind of
thing. So, introduction to myself. I'm
an carpenter. I am an an awardee in 2018
through the broad Ignite program and
then um became the co-chair together
with Robi Badata and Bronwin McKinnus.
Um and I'm also a donor to the Broad
Institute because I I believe so
strongly in what we're doing here and as
you'll meet many of the scientists so if
you talk one-on-one we're just
absolutely passionate about what we're
doing trying to make the world a better
place through scientific research. Uh
today I um well I'll just describe a
little bit about my own project um which
is on this theme as well um in
psychiatric um disease. The project that
I was awarded for was a very out there
kind of idea. We were working on um
looking for the underpinnings of
schizophrenia and other conditions that
lead to psychosis. And we collaborated
at McClean Hospital. Many of you are
aware of this um really premier
psychiatric research hospital that we
have here in the in the Boston area. And
our collaborators there, Bruce Mlan and
Donna McI had collected a group of
patients that experienced psychosis and
a set that did not. And by taking cells
from those patients and studying them uh
by microscopy, we were able to identify
through my broadite project uh that the
mitochondria had an unusual localization
in the case of um patients that were
experiencing psychosis. And we're very
excited now that the um National
Institutes of Health has adopted the
project and is now doing drug screens to
try to find are there any novel
compounds that might do a good job of
shifting that localization and trying to
normalize the the mitochondria. So
really exciting um project that um that
would not have been funded by any other
route and that's really the point of the
Broad Knight um program. So for our
speakers tonight, we have um they'll be
sharing the the current research project
pro progress that they have from their
recent awards and we'll have a Q&A
afterwards. So the theme of tonight is
just the flow of information between
brain cells. When communication is
disrupted, all kinds of things can
happen and we end up with different
conditions like um Alzheimer's,
schizophrenia, bipolar and so on. And
what's really exciting is some of the
research that um that these uh
innovative young people have taken on.
And I'll begin um by announcing um Ralda
Name who is an institute scientist and
directs the stem cell program um at the
Stanley Center which is part of the
Broad Institute. And she's going to tell
us about new ways of studying brain cell
communication and the importance of um
of her findings for treating psychiatric
disorders. Um she is an awardee from
2021 and is studying a particular
deletion syndrome called
22q11.2. Perhaps you've never heard of
it. Um most of us have not. And while it
is itself a rare disease, it can inform
us about brain mechanisms that are in
common across many different disorders
and really is she's pushing the the
field forward in understanding brain
development in healthy conditions as
well as unhealthy conditions. After
that, we'll have Shaye Vong, who is a
graduate student very early in his
career in Laura Keesling's lab across
the street at MIT, and he will be
telling us about his work in the role of
sugars in brain disorders. And um all
kinds of jokes can be made about um how
sweet that work is. Um but he will be
telling us about the importance of those
sugars as a signaling component for
brain cell communication and again how
does that function in normal brain
development as well as um in
neurogenerative diseases. Uh he just
received their award last year. So you
know give him some time uh that well
there will be a lot of potential
described in his talk as well as um what
he's accomplished so far developing
technologies to visualize and study
sugars in the brain. So with that, I'm
very pleased to invite Ralda up to
speak.
Please thank you an so much for this
lovely introduction and thank you um
everyone for being here today and I'm
very pleased to be able to share what my
lab um is working on in trying to
understand complex brain conditions such
as uh psychiatric conditions or mental
illnesses. So mental illness is really a
major global health challenge.
Conditions such as schizophrenia and
bipolar bipolar disorder can cause um
severe symptoms including mood swings,
hallucinations and also really increased
risk for suicide. And these conditions
affect millions of individuals and they
actually contribute to homelessness to
unemployment as well as incarceration.
And really um kind of uh like something
to take seriously is that current
treatment are really outdated. There
haven't been new effective therapies
that have been developed. Um in fact
many of the therapies have not changed
in decades and over half of the people
that live with these conditions still
really struggle with daily functioning.
However, there's really um hope on the
horizon because large-scale human
genetic studies have recently uncovered
hundreds of gene variants that they were
able to confidently link to these
conditions such as schizophrenia and
bipolar disorder. So, for the first time
we know what these gene variants are,
these um like differences in the genes,
these mutations. However, we don't know
what these um gene variants are doing.
We don't know. We and we would like to
understand how these gene variants
affect cells and cellular programs and
how they shape brain development and
function and how in some individuals
when we have these changes then this
leads to disease. So really my lab is
interested in understanding and bridging
the knowledge gap between what the gene
variants are and what they do at the
cellular level.
And I think it's fair to say that um
progress in developing effective
therapeutics for these psychiatric
develop conditions has stalled in large
part because these conditions are highly
complex and heterogeneous. I just told
you that this is the case at the genetic
level. So we have not only one gene but
hundreds of genes that have been linked
to a given condition. But this is also
true at the clinical level because
patients and patient symptoms are really
different from one patient to the other.
So the the constellation of symptoms and
presentations in a given individual with
schizophrenia for example is can be
quite different from the other patient.
So we really thought to more deeply
understand what is going on and how the
complexity and heterogeneity might
manifest at the cellular level because
we think that once we understand what's
not working properly at the level of the
cell then we can develop better ways to
correct
it. And ideally to understand this we
would need to be able to study and
manipulate the living human brain.
However, for many obvious reasons, this
is not ethical or also possible. We
don't really have access to human brains
throughout development, throughout a
person's life and we can't really do
experiments on living people. Um,
however, what we can do is that we can
study human brain cells um in the lab
and the way to do that is by actually
using human stem cells. So, um what are
stem cells? Stem cells are really
special cells that have unique
properties in that they can indefinitely
divide. So they can make more of
themselves but they can also turn into
specialized cells. So they can turn into
any given cell in the body uh what we
call differentiate. So they can become a
muscle cell, a neuron or a nerve cell um
a heart cell. And another really cool
aspect about human stem cells is that so
we can derive them from any given
individual anywhere in the world. So we
can take a blood sample or a skin biopsy
and then from these cells we can grow
them and by adding special factors to
them we can turn them into stem cells in
just a couple of months. And then once
we have these stem cells then we can
turn the stem cells into any cell type
we're interested in. You'll hear me
talking a lot today about brain cells.
So we can turn these stem cells into
brain cell. And again the cool thing is
that these when we um when we take the
blood sample for example from person A
and then make stem cells and then make
brain cells during all of this process
we preserve the whole genetic makeup of
that individual. So all of the genetic
information in that person is still
captured in the derivatives that we then
study.
So in order to enable the kind of
approaches to be able to study complex
psychiatric conditions um in cells from
many different people with and without
the diseases, we needed to first develop
um several tools and resources. And we
are fortunate to have been able to do
that here in our lab at the Broad
Institute. And I'll use this one slide
to take you through kind of three uh
kind of critical resources and tools
that we've developed.
So the first one is that we uh assembled
through a large international
collaboration we assembled stem cell
lines from over a thousand unique
individuals a thousand donors and for
each and every um stem cell line not
only have we really kind of grown very
high quality stem cells and were able to
freeze them and bank them here at the
broad but we also for every single um
stem cell line we have generated genetic
sequencing data
So we can link the genetic information
to what we observe at the cellular
level. The other key thing is that we
also uh over the last few years have
been able to develop ways to turn these
stem cells into different types of brain
cells very effectively. So we can now
take stem cells from hundreds of people
and turn them into specific brain cells.
We can do this very well and at scale in
the lab. And last but not le not not
least, I've just told you that we have
now a resource from over a thousand um
stem cell lines from a thousand people.
But actually stem cell work, the kind of
work that we do is very expensive and
it's ve it's very time consuming. So if
we wanted to examine cells from each of
these people carefully um all at once,
it could take us a really long time and
it could cost us a lot of money. And it
also each time we start an experiment
with one person's cells um separately it
also we could have some what we call
technical variability. Each time we
start an experiment there could be
little differences that we might not be
aware of and we have to take into
account in our um analysis. So to get
around this and be able to study cells
from a lot of people all at once we
develop different tricks to do that. And
one I'm highlighting here is called the
cell village experimental system. In
this system, we can mix cells from many
different people all together in one
dish. So instead of having a 100 dishes
to study cells from 100 people, we can
have just one. And that way all the
cells are exposed to exactly the same
conditions in the same dish and we can
then score them for different behaviors.
And then we actually can then use the
fact that each person the genome of each
person is unique. So it's almost like a
barcode that we can then use on the back
end to identify the person that the cell
belongs
to. Okay. So now that we have these
tools and resources in hand, how can we
then leverage them to uh unravel the
complexity of psychiatric
conditions? If we revisit um all what
human genetics have taught us when it
comes to schizophrenia and psychiatric
conditions, we can see that there's a
very strong signal that emerges and that
is uh that genes that encode synaptic
proteins seem to be highly involved in
these
conditions. So what are synapses?
Synapses are actually the connections
between two um nerve cells or two
neurons. And this is how neurons
communicate or talk to each other in the
brain. So one neuron neuron one which is
also called presinaptic neuron will send
a chemical signal to neuron 2 or post
synaptic neuron and that's how they talk
to each other and the field has largely
focused over the last decades on really
studying neurons when it comes to
psychiatric conditions and
schizophrenia.
However, we wondered if other cells
could also be involved in this process.
And we know for example that there's one
uh important cell type that is present
at the syninnapse and this is the
astrite cell type. And astrittes are um
are basically they make up almost half
of the cells in the brain and they are
not neurons but they provide really
important support for the neurons. They
enable neurons to develop and mature
properly. And again, they are this is
what they look like. They're beautiful
cells and they are a key component of
the synapse. So they are really
essential for synapse or communication
between neurons to happen
properly. So we wondered if um astroite
neuron interactions, the way these two
cell types talk to each other, if these
could be different in psychiatric
conditions. And so we wanted to study
that. And how do we study um aststery
neuron interaction in the dish in the
lab? And so we can um actually we can
grow neurons and aststerytes in the lab.
We can grow them separately each cell
type individually in what we call
monoculture or we can grow them together
in the same plate so that they can touch
each other and this is called a
co-ulture um
format. And so we did this, we studied
cells from roughly 80 people and um
their neurons um in the dish. And then
what we found was that when the two cell
types touch each other when they make
physical contact, we observed that at
that time synaptic genes are increased
in their expression in neurons. And that
was perhaps not too surprising based um
on what we knew about synaptic biology.
But the surprising part was that
actually when the two cell types touch
each other other genes are really
dramatically increased in astroytes as
well. So there's a lot of changes in the
astroite cell type and this these genes
included genes in cell adion. So genes
that enable cells to stick to each other
as well as genes in cholesterol
production. And that was surprising. Now
we see that when the two cell types
touch each other cholesterol is
increased in aststerytes as well as
sticky genes.
basically and I want to highlight two
such genes here. The first is Nurexen
one and Rexen one is known to be a high
confidence so we're quite sure that is
involved in schizophrenia but also in
autism and it has been studied for many
years in neurons but here we're showing
that actually this gene is changed in
the astroite cell type. So again um
further evidence that merits to be
studied in this cell type. And then the
second gene that's changed is um HMGCR
which this is a key enzyme in producing
cholesterol and
aststerytes. And um coincidentally soon
after we had made these observations
similar observations were being made
from studying the human brain but by our
colleague Steve McCarol here at the
broad and in a study led by Emiling and
Steve's lab they studied roughly uh
brains from 200 people um after they had
died and they found that these exact
gene expression programs were also
coordinated or co-regulated across
neurons and astrittes in the human
brain. So not only in the dish but also
in the human brain and postmortem brains
you can see the same interactions. They
actually termed these this program the
synaptic neuron aststerite program and
then they went on to show that these um
expression programs were reduced in the
brains of schizophrenia
individuals. All right. So what is
astrite doing there? So it turns out
that a uh astroytes are the major source
of cholesterol in the brain. Um
aststerytes make cholesterol and then
secreted outside the cells and then it's
taken up by neurons and it becomes a key
component of uh the membranes in neurons
and thus it contributes to synapsis.
Now when we looked at the genes that are
involved in making cholesterol in
aststerytes and and um pumping it out of
the cells or at the genes that are
involved in taking up cholesterol by
neurons and storing it, we noticed that
for many of these genes, they happen to
to be near regions of the genome that
are associated with schizophrenia.
So then we wondered well what would
happen if then we prevent neurons from
taking uh cholesterol that's made by
aststerytes. So we can do that by using
a gene editing technique called um
crisper interference or crisper eye. So
uh by doing this then we block the
expression of the receptors that take up
cholesterols. And when we did this we
observe that um there's now less
expression of synaptic genes and
neurons. So this further solidifies this
link between cholesterol production in
aststerytes and synaptic gene expression
in
neurons. And from there we now wanted to
understand if these genetic variations
that are have been documented by the
genetic studies to be present in in
individuals with schizophrenia if these
may affect how astroytes and neurons
talk to each other.
So to study this we first started by
examining one um genetic variant that is
considered to be the highest um genetic
risk factor for schizophrenia and this
is the 22q1 1.2 deletion that n
mentioned. So this is actually not only
uh that does it confer a high risk for
schizophrenia it is actually one of the
most common it is the most common human
chromosomeal deletion in human in
humans. So this removes a part of
chromosome 22. Um and we were able to
assemble a cohort of stem cells from
individuals that either carry or do not
carry the deletion and for the ones who
carry that also have
schizophrenia. And what we found was
that when we looked at the at their gene
expressions, we found that in neurons
the um genes that have been linked by
the genetic studies um to schizophrenia
and that are also synaptic genes, we saw
that they are decreased in their
expression in the neurons. And in a more
recent study, we also showed that the
astrite component of the synaptic neuron
astroite program that was also decreased
in aststerytes that carry the deletion.
So now we wanted um to also understand
if we could detect changes other than
just how um the expression levels of the
genes. So we wondered if we could uh
really measure how these genetic
influences these genetic risk factors
change how cells look or or cell
morphology. And to do that we took
advantage of a wonderful assay that has
been developed here by Anne Carpenter
and and Stu Shriber here at the broad
and that an mentioned in her talk. And
in this assay cell painting, you can use
different cell dyes to label different
um cell compartments or
organels. And so we adapted this assay
to make it specific to brain cells. And
we called this
neuropainting. And then we screened um
neuronal progenitor cells, neurons and
astroytes from our cohort with or
without this um risk factor, the 22q1
1.2 deletion. And um when we did this we
were able to identify that there are
many traits many morphological features
as we call them that are different in
stem cells in progenitor cells in
neurons and aststerytes some were
similar across all the different cell
types and some were unique to each cell
type these differences and um I wanted
to highlight one here that is a change
in how um the ER which is one organal
and the mitochondria how these two
organels are distributed in the cells.
You may be able to appreciate here how
their distribution in control cells. So
cells from people who do not carry the
deletion versus cells who carry the
deletion, how these look different. They
are distributed differently in the
cells. So the deletion is affecting
that. And then we went on to link um
these changes in how the cells look and
how these organels are distributed. we
could link these to changes in um in
expression of specific cell adion genes,
genes that make cells stick to each
other. And because of all of our f find
findings on cholesterol, we actually
then wondered well can we look at um you
know cholesterol or lipid features in
this system. So we then incorporated
lipid profiling. We looked at um lipid
expression in um into our neuropainting
assay and then we screened our cohort
again. And what we found was that
actually just by looking at lipids
alone, by looking how these lipid
related traits are distributed in the
cells, we could tell whether a cell has
the deletion or not. So, um I'm sorry
here the the graph is a little messed up
here, but um in this case it shows that
there's much fewer lipid spots in the
deletion versus um without
it. And so the last vignette I'll tell
you about tonight is that is about our
work on um antiscychotic medications. So
we wanted to understand then can um
drugs that are typically used to treat
psychiatric conditions like
schizophrenia can these change how
neurons and astroytes talk to each other
or what programs are are involved there
and so to do that we then um took
neurons and astrittes that were derived
from many people 140 people in total and
we treated them with many different
antiscychotic medications at different
doses and to make a long story short
here I wanted to highlight one main
finding from the study
and that is that the antiscychotic
cloopene which is one of the most
effective antiscychotics and I'll come
back to that that clipene increases
cholesterol production by aststerytes
and we found that this was true in cells
from every single person we looked at so
in this plot that I'm showing you here
each color corresponds to um cells from
a different person and how they and how
much cholesterol is expressed in in the
cells from that person and as you can
see the condition in the here is is um
cloopene and you can see that when we
treat cells with cloopene we see much
more cholesterol in cells from all the
people we looked at. So, as I mentioned,
Cloopene is a really effective
antiscychotic, but people don't really
understand why it works so well. And so,
we wondered if effects on cholesterol
production may provide an explanation.
And so um when we again examined our our
um gene expression data in our co-ulture
system, we found that not only does
cloopine in increase cholesterol
production in a nice dose dependent
manner, but it also um increases oops
sorry increases the expression of
synaptic genes and neurons also in a
dose dependent manner. So here we by
manipulating the levels of cholesterol
and cloopene we can also see a
corresponding um increase in synaptic um
gene expression in the
neurons and so and the um kind of last
thing I'll show you is that well what
happens when uh what what happens if we
add cloopene to then these um the 22q1
1.2 two deletion cells. I just told you
that we can see that there are many
changes that we can measure in how cells
look in cells with this deletion. And
well, we found that clipopine at least
to some extent appears to rescue some of
these morphological defects that are
related to the 22q11.2 deletion. And
again, so cloopene is not an ideal um
drug treatment. it doesn't work for
everyone and it also doesn't it it's
associated with many side effects
because um many metabolic side effects
and it effects it turns out that a lot
of the patients that take have increased
levels of lipids in their plasma perhaps
related to what we're showing again
effects on cholesterol production so can
we then use the tools we develop to then
develop eventually better treatments so
to sum up I've told you today that
astroy neuron interactions play
previously unappreciated roles in
psychiatric disorders the bi The
biological programs we discovered are
consistent with genetic studies and are
altered in cells from people who harbor
variation that's related to psychiatric
conditions. And finally, the fact that
we can manipulate these programs in
living human cells and modulate them
with drug treatment holds great promise
for therapeutic discovery. And I'll end
by thanking you for your attention,
thanking everybody um uh who has
contributed to this work. Uh especially
people in my lab. Um a couple of them
are present here. I'll give a special
shout out to Derek Halls who has been my
co-conspirator, our lab manager since I
uh started my lab and Jack Su as well
who's here and contributed to this work.
Our our funders obviously brought Ignite
and other funders and and here are the
people who did the work. Thank
you. Thank
you. And we'll we'll wait for questions
till the end. We'll we'll next give uh
Shay the chance to speak. Okay.
Hi everyone, thank you for being here.
My name is Shuer. I'm a PhD candidate at
MIT. I'm also a broad ignite awardee at
the Broad Institute. And today I'm it's
my pleasure to be here to tell you about
our work to unveil brain cells
sugarcoated secrets. So I want to begin
my talk in the country of Colombia where
a family suffers from a rare and
devastating condition. So around a
thousand people that lives in central
Columbia, almost everyone develops
Alzheimer's disease. And not only that,
everyone develops Alzheimer's disease,
they develop Alzheimer's much earlier
than the general population. And a
doctor has been working with this family
to provide care and to find out why they
are having this condition. And it turns
out they have a very rare genetic
mutation. And in this family, so this is
called a survival curve where every is a
way to depict how a population develop
disease over time. So when everyone's
healthy, the curves at 100 and as people
start to be diagnosed with conditions,
the curves start to drop. So as you can
see um by their mid4s most people would
have been diagnosed with cognitive mild
cognitive impairment which suggests
noticeable cognitive decline and suggest
that's an onset of Alzheimer uh symptoms
and by their mid50s they would have been
diagnosed with dementia. So it's a very
unfortunate devastating condition and a
team of Colombia doctors have been
working with this family to provide care
and to trace the family tree to figure
out what is happening. And what's really
interesting is that over the few the
past three three decades um the doctors
start to realize that there's some
outliers in this family that develop
this disease much later than others. And
in particular there's this woman that's
named Yria. She has this mutation that
would guarantee she will get Alzheimer's
but for some reason she didn't develop
any symptoms until 72. So that's almost
a three decade delay of symptoms symptom
onset compared to other members of the
family. Of course the doctor and
scientists become very interested in
this case because understanding what's
protecting her could inform us to
develop therapeutics can benefit the
over 30 million patients who are
suffering from Alzheimer's in the world
today.
And so she unfortunately she passed away
in 2020 from cancer and she generally
donated her brain for science. But while
she was still alive they invited her to
come to Boston to get some brain scans
in the Massachusetts General Hospital.
So this is PET scans of her brain when
she was just starting to have cog
cognitive impairment and the the redder
brain region is suggest she has a higher
level of the toxic proteins in that
region. So when they looked at amaloid
beta which is the most well-known
hallmark for Alzheimer's disease she has
exceptionally high level of amaloid beta
compared to patients that from that
family in their mid-4s when they're
starting to develop symptoms. However,
when they looked at the T protein named
Tao, also another well-known marker for
Alzheimer's, she has relatively moderate
level of TW compared to other patients
and they did more test and she showed
that she has very minimal cell
degeneration which explains her avoiding
the disease. So what this suggests is
that for some reason the disease
progression is impeded in her brain and
that causes a resistance to the
Alzheimer pathology and that's really
interesting. So the doctor performed all
kinds of test including sequencing her
whole genome to identify so she has this
mutation that causes Alzheimer maybe she
has something else that's protecting her
from Alzheimer's. and they found a very
interesting hit. Um, so if you're paying
attention, so Rod's talk also mentioned
this protein called APOE. So this is a
protein that's very important for lipid
metabolism. So this protein helps to
shift lipid around your body including
cholesterol. But interestingly, the gene
that encodes this protein, the gene APOE
is also the best predictive gene we have
for Alzheimer risk. So when you have a
genetic testing based on your gene
composition for APOE, they can predict
your risk of getting Alzheimer's in the
future. So this is a very interesting
hit because that suggests this could be
a major reason why she has this
resistance to Alzheimer's disease. And
the mutation in this APOE which is named
Christ Church uh happens to be in the
region of APOE where the APOE protein
uses to bind a self-s surface sugar on
the uh brain cells. And indeed when the
researchers tested whether the
interaction is intact it turns out this
mutation which is called AP3 it's Christ
church does affect the interaction
between APOE and the brain sugar. Um so
this is a biochemistry essay that test
the binding between protein and sugar.
Um however of course this is very
exciting which this is a new direction
for us to look into to understand
Alzheimer and potential therapeutics but
at the same time um the sugar they use
in this case called hperin is only an
analog of the actual sugar in the brain
suggest they might not be representative
of what's actually happening in the
human brain and also this is just about
chemical essay and a lot more work is
needed to actually understand the
biology of how this sugar works in the
human brain.
So I want to give a little introduction
of the sugar in your brain. Um so it's
not very well known but all of the sugar
in your brain and actually in your body
are covered all the cells are covered by
sugars and I want to introduce a new
term here. So for a biochemist when a
series of sugars that's connected into a
sombo we call this a glyen and every
cell has all kinds of glycans on the
surface and they all have different
functions and they all interact with
different partners but very
interestingly apo mainly interacts with
this particular sugar called hyperin
sulfate and that will be the topic of my
talk and here's a picture of a group of
cells with hypernulfate visualized on
the surface
And you can see we're looking down on
this population of cells and we can see
the nucleus where DNA is and you can see
the hyper sulfate on the surface that's
pointing out and you can see this sugar
acts as a barrier between the cell and
the
outside and we know that this sugar
plays very important roles in the brain.
So one example is when your brain is
developing. Um so when your brain is
developing from embryo to a person a lot
of communication is require required for
the cells to know where to go and what
type of cell they should become. And
here's the study in the mouse brain. If
we remove the sugar as a channel for
cells to communicate with each other we
we actually see major disruptions in the
formation of different brain regions.
You can see this is the alactory bulb
and that's completely missing in the
mouse that's missing this sugar and we
also observe significant uh disruption
in the connection between different
brain regions. So this sugar is critical
for for brain development. We also know
that this sugar is very important for
synapse formation. So synapse is how
your brain cell connect with each other
and if we remove this sugar the synapse
will become dysfunctional and the signal
cannot be transmitted as efficiently.
And here we also have the example
showing this sugar is very important in
the process of neuro degeneration.
Understanding that can be very valuable.
However, our understanding is still
quite limited mostly because we don't
have good tools to study the sugar in
the brain. If you notice how I describe
these studies, the best tool we have
right now is to remove this sugar from
its biological context and see how the
system dysfunctions. However, just by
removing it, so say this is important
because the system's broken doesn't
really doesn't help us to fully
understand what it's doing in the brain.
So what what my PhD is focused on is to
develop tools to actually start to
visualize this sugar in the brain
context so we can understand how it
works. And the technology that we use is
called expansion microscopy. So the
major challenge of studying molecules in
the brain is because they're too close
to each other to be distinguished from
each other. So why don't we just move
them apart from each other? So that's
what this technology does. By forming a
polymer that's commonly used in baby
diapers and contacts in the brain
tissue, we're able to physically magnify
the brain by bringing all the molecules
apart from each other while still
preserving the overall organization. So
now using a conventional microscope we
can get state-of-the-art images of how
molecules are organized in the brain
tissue and we apply this technology to
visualize these sugars. So this is human
potent stem cell is a cell that's in the
development stage and I show this image
before. Um so we can see this hyper
sulfate glycans um as very hairy
extended structures on the cell surface
and very interestingly when we
differentiate the cells into motor
neurons so neurons that's uh more ter in
terminal state all of these sugars
become very curled up on the cell
surface and this is very surprising
because for a long time scientists have
always saw these sugars are just
floating uncontrollably on the cell
surface but what this means is that
there the cells actually control the
structure of these sugars on the surface
to make sure that they function as
they're intended to. However, this is
these samples are expanded around four
four-fold. So, it's still quite limited
in terms of resolution. Um, so one thing
I developed during my PhD is I
engineered the polymer that's used to
expand this tissues. So, this is just a
pure polymer. We will in reality we'll
embed biological samples in these
hydrogels to actually blow them up. But
you can see this is the same gel before
and after expansion in the same dish. So
this gel is able to expand up to 20fold
while still holding its shape and
holding all the spatial relationship
intact. And with the more advanced
expansion technology, we're actually
able to start to zoom in on the fine
details of molecules. So this is uh
different synapses in the mouse brain
and I zoom in on to three different
synapses. So we mentioned the synapses
connection between neurons neurons. So
there's a cell that's sending the signal
and there's a cell that's receiving the
signal. And if we look at the proteins
that's sending the signal and the
proteins receiving the signal, we see
the shape of the synapse very clearly
with this technology. And we can also
see the space between the synapse.
That's the distance the signal that
needs to travel.
So we start to apply this technology to
the sugar and another advancement of the
technology we start to use is to
recognize that actually there are
different flavors of this same sugar. So
it's the same type of molecules but they
actually go through extensive
multiplications. So they interact with
different kinds of partners and we
haven't really had the ability to
recognize how these different flavors
work in the biological context. So we
start to apply these different protein
probes that can recognize these
different flavors in the same cell to
start to look at how the these different
sequences distribute. Um so on the left
we have two different probes on
different population of cells and on the
right we have a different probe and then
just visually you can see there's a
difference where these two probes start
to recognize these glycans that's
pointing outside of the cell. This probe
only looks at glycans that's very close
to the cell surface. And when we zoom in
onto this population, you can see these
two probes really don't overlap in terms
of what they recognize. And if we when
we expand these samples 20fold, what we
start to see is that these different
sequences, different flavors, they
actually arrange spatially different
along this one glycan. So what that
suggests is that not only the structure
of these glycans are controlled on the
cell surface, even the different
modifications are very carefully placed
on the glycans by the cells which was
previously not observed. And what this
really shows is that there's a very
complex machinery that the cell deploys
to control the sugars to accomplish the
critical roles they need in terms of
cell cell communications.
And on top of that, we start to apply
this technology to study Alzheimer's. So
this is the same human brain tissue from
a patient after they passed away. And
we're starting to visualize this sugar
hyper sulfate as well as other proteins
that's significant for Alzheimer's. And
what we're starting to visualize is that
this sugar is collocicalizing with the
key players of Alzheimer's. And we're
going to look into how they're
interacting and also look into what
other potential partners like proteins
the sugar is interacting with and if we
disrupt the APOE sugar interactions like
in that patient how will the system
change which will hopefully like lead to
deeper understanding of the disease and
well as potential therapeutic
directions. So in conclusion of my talk
I would like to present three takeaways.
The first is every cell in your brain is
covered by sugars and evidence indicate
that they play critical roles in cell
cell communications as well as diseases
such as Alzheimer's
disease. Our understanding of biology
and disease is driven by the development
of different tools such as the tool of
physically enlarging a brain to look at
things clearer and breakthrough in our
understanding. Our sincere hope is that
that can lead to diagnostics and
therapeutics for different diseases such
as therapeutic cancer and even
potentially aging. So with that I would
like to thank my PhD adviserss for
providing like great opportunity to work
on these problems. I want to thank our
collaborators collaborators also both in
the lab and around the world and I want
to thank all the donors who donated
their body for science and also all the
funding sources especially bro ignite
which enabled this work. Thank you for
your attention.
Wonderful. Thank you so much. Um I I
find this really fascinating as an
example. the pair of you are um and
please get ready to ask questions. Raise
your hand and a m microphone will come
to you. I just find it fascinating that
there are so many different styles of
science. Um so you are clearly zooming
in very very far to look at the synapses
at the tip of a little arm that is at
the end of a very large neuron um inside
a brain inside a human. Whereas Ralda,
you're sort of zooming out. let's get
this population of patients and look at
lots of different samples um and and to
look at the the structures there. So
just I just find this really
fascinating. The one thing you had in
common though is each of these projects
involved quite a cast of characters and
I think that's pretty typical. Um so
let's turn to questions from the
audience.
Uh very interesting from both of you. I
was wondering when you mentioned the uh
uh cell colonies or villages um how the
mixture of cells from different people
in the same dish
uh whether these cells interact in some
way and how do you account for that?
Yeah. Um so it's it's something that we
are studying right we can take a little
bit to our advantage if we kind of study
how cells from a person that don't have
a particular genetic variant how they
interact with the cells with a person
that has. So these kinds of
interactions we can study if we can
control them but for the most part in
the village system we study um what we
call cell intrinsic behavior. So
behavior within each cell. So when it
comes to the gene expression programs,
we tend to avoid looking at um what is
expressed outside of the cells or
secreted um or cell extrinsic behaviors
because this is too complicated to
measure with the village system. That's
a good rock heat may affect your overth.
Yep. Was it that um so yeah so the the
kind of really important thing which I
didn't really discuss is that we also
have repeated a lot of what we
established first the system and
whenever we make a finding we also
repeat the same experiments um to what
we what we say validate them to make
sure that we make the same observations
when we culture cells from each person
separately. So yeah, absolutely.
Um I I totally understand your research
is extremely necessary in both your
cases, you know, squidia, Alzheimer's.
My question
is is this pie in the sky kind of
research or how far are you from
practical real world therapeutics? I
mean is it you know are you at the nent
level you know are you 20 years away
that's a that's I love this question so
let me first give some context that it
currently takes somewhere between$1 and6
billion dollars to develop a new drug um
as you can imagine the the broad's
entire operating budget is uh not quite
that huge um and um and it typically
takes something at a absolute absolute
minimum about 10 years um typically more
like 15 to to go from an idea of what
might make a good drug and and onward.
So the broad usually sits at pretty
early in that that spectrum, but I'm
very curious to to hear the answer of um
how what are what are maybe what are the
next steps and kind of how long do you
foresee till something could come of
your research in your patients? Yeah,
maybe I can start by saying that so in
in psychiatry for example for
schizophrenia in the last 60 50 60 years
there really has have not been any major
new drugs that have come on the market
and this is for many reasons like I said
because uh like these are brain diseases
it's very hard to access the human brain
and we know people have typically
studied mice for example animal models
but there are so many differences in
both the the genes but also kind of how
the brain like structurally and you know
mice and humans. So that we really
needed an animal a human system to be
able to study these disorders. I mean
not exclusively right but this is one of
the reasons and and um and the the other
thing here is that with the tools and
technology for the first time right now
we really have the tools in hand to be
able to study such complex disorders. So
with assays such as you know the cell
painting that an has developed first and
that we are really trying to leverage we
can cheaply and quickly screen. So now
we know you know we we are starting to
understand what to look for what are the
defect at the cellular level. So now we
actually can screen drug libraries to
figure to try to identify ways to
correct them and then hoping to get
closer to a treatment that actually
works in patients. Right? So there's
always back and forths but we hope that
with the tools present today that that
we are getting closer. Yeah. And I can
answer from the perspective also of
seeing startups that um that in that
incubate and launch out of the broad um
when you do a drug screen and get a
promising first chemical. It usually
takes a couple of years to optimize the
chemical and then it takes a couple of
years to test its safety in usually
mouse models but now other alternatives.
um but still a couple of years. Um and
then you file with the FDA and go to
human trials. So it's probably about
let's say five years total from from
having a good starting point. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. And I think I would add that
if you have been following therapeutics
in the Alzheimer's space, I think there
have been several drugs that's been
approved, but there's no evidence
showing that they're super effective. So
I think a lot of what we're doing is
also like we of course we want the cure
as fast as possible but at the same time
we need to do it the right way and to
make sure we actually fully understand
the disease y to know what we're going
after. Once it gets to human clinical
trials that can be usually years
especially if it's a disease that takes
a while to develop. Um it takes a while
to know if your drug is working. So if
it takes several years and usually tens
to hundreds of millions of dollars for
that human clinical trial stage we don't
want to blow it having having messed up
at an earlier stage. That's a really
great point. Another question here. Uh
yeah, thank you both of you for the
wonderful presentation. My question is
very simple. How do you convert a stem
cell into a neuron or any other type of
cell? So you can take a stem cell and
make it into any other form of cell. How
do you do that? What's the process? And
yeah, so actually we can add um to the
stem cells. We can try to make some
genes become expressed and other genes
stop to be expressed. So we know what
these are based on our understanding of
human development, human brain
development. And so we can what we call
our transcription factors. So these are
like gene products that control how
other genes are expressed. So we can add
these transcription factors to the cells
for example and push them to become
neurons or we can block other genes from
being expressed by adding some chemicals
or small molecule.
Leard.
Hi. Uh you mentioned that cloopene by
increasing cholesterol uh production
affects neuron communication. I was
wondering does it distinguish between
low and high density cholesterol and uh
other aspects of are lipids somehow
involved in the communication? So yeah,
so this is something that we have not
really studied what we call lipid
species. I have to say that the kind of
version of cholesterol that's present in
the brain is a little different right
but what I can say I mentioned that
clipopine is associated with side
effects in patients and these are um
often metabolic side effects including
more um lipids in their in their blood
that can be measured. So my guess would
be that it does not um so these side
effects are because they affect the
heart. So we aspire and we hope to be
able to develop a drug that would kind
of increase cholesterol in the brain but
not somewhere else so that would not
cause these you know heart issues
eventually.
Yeah. Great. And we'll take one last
question here. Thank you. Hi very
interesting talk. Thank you so much. Uh
I have a question around clinical
trials. So if I understand correctly uh
determining end points is somewhat
difficult in such diseases like
Alzheimer's. So some of the techniques
you are developing would that make it
easier because now you have more of a
analytical techniques though what
exactly is happening with the brain
cells and can you describe what is an
end point a clinical endpoint?
Um yeah I I guess I'll start but then
you can go back to him. Um, so I think
yeah, exactly. This is so by basically
being able to quickly be able to access
cells from different people that have or
do not have a certain genetic like a
certain mutation. For example, our hope
is that we can screen quickly because in
the dish it takes, you know, just only a
few weeks to be able to screen. We can
measure um how the the communication
between the uh like the synapses between
the nerve cells. We can count them. We
can measure the cholesterol production
and we can then quickly screen for drugs
that Yeah. So these are the end points
or the the phenotypes that we measure
but yeah or the sugars right that I
think just to disclaimer my PhD is not
in like clinical size I don't know as
much about clinical trials but I would
say yeah I think just more methods to
analyze what's happening in patients in
model systems would help us to at least
have a better idea to set end point
before the trial begins because I think
that's what that's the challenges you
see with Alzheimer's is that a lot of
clinical trials were complete first and
then they start to just the criteria to
make the drug effective which is not
science supposed to be done like I
understand clinical trial is complicated
and real world changes things but at the
same time like that's what we should
avoid. Wonderful. Thank you so much for
sharing your science clearly tonight.
Please join me in thanking these folks.
[Applause]