(bright music)
- Just like everyone in
the room is different,
every cell and every single
molecule is different.
I have always been fascinated by biology.
What excites me the most is
really the ability to see
how molecules move around and interact.
My research group focuses
on developing new photostable probe
that allows us to do long-term
single-molecule tracking
inside living systems.
We know that diseases are often caused
by mutations in certain proteins,
and so now if we can really
visualize the differences
of the molecular dynamics,
we can potentially screen
for small molecules
that can help revert
this kind of behavior.
This will be very useful
information to guide our design
of the next generation of therapeutics.
Because this is a
relatively new technology,
we need to optimize many different fields.
I'm really fortunate to be
able to recruit our students
with very different skills.
Students who can synthesize
and optimize these nanoparticles.
We also have students
who are good at optics
and can build the microscopes.
And so these students are really talented
and they're really driven
to really push the frontier
of our scientific research.
(uplifting music)
Our goal is really to solve important
and challenging biological questions,
and so this is very hard
to do in a more traditional
and pure discipline.
Traditionally, people use
dyes and fluorescent proteins
to look at individual molecules,
but these kinds of probes
bleach within tens of seconds,
so we can't look at processes
much longer than that.
With our photostable probe,
we can really visualize with great spatial
and temporal resolutions, great detail.
And so whenever you have a new technology
that can allow you to image faster
with higher spatial resolution
and with longer periods of time,
you are bound to see something new.
So I'm really excited that
we are entering this region
where we can really investigate
many unexplored territories.
Broad is really the perfect
place for my research group
because I get to interact
with the very best biologists in the world
to really know the most challenging
and pressing questions
so that we can come up
with new ideas in
developing new technologies
to help answer these questions.
To me, the point is not to publish
as many papers as possible
but really is to make a bigger impact.
And I feel like developing something new
can really offer you the opportunity.
(uplifting music)