Um, so today we're going to be talking
about Huffman codes which is a pretty
elegant topic. So I just want to give
you a reminder from last time. So what
did we talk about last time was we
talked about this notion of a first
order source that defines a distribution
on an alphabet of size K. So you think
about the entries in the set A as being
all the symbols that could arise. And
then what we wanted was we wanted a way
to compress the outputs of our first
order channel. So we did last time was
we had this crucial definition which was
called a coding function. So we talked
about a function which maps from length
n sequences of the alphabet into some
binary code of some varying length. So
just the sequence of zeros and ones. And
we want the crucial property that it can
be decoded. So we want the property that
for any two sequences that our channel
could generate, as long as they're
different, they map to different
outputs. And last time what we talked
about was we talked about Shannon's
theorem that gave us both upper and
lower bounds on how well we could do. So
in particular, the main thing we proved
was this upper bound that we defined
this quantity called the binary entropy
of the channel. And we showed that the
expected length of our code is at most n
times the per symbol entropy plus little
o of n.
So that was the context of what we did
last time and today we're going to
drastically improve upon this. So first
of all you can wonder you know how small
we can make this little o of n. But
there's another point which is a little
bit more subtle. See this scheme is not
really so computationally efficient
because if I think about what I have to
do, I might in principle have to write
down uh one you know code word for each
possible output of my channel. So as the
length of my channel becomes larger and
larger now I have k to the n possible
strings. So, I'm writing down this giant
table of what are all the possible
outputs? And that might be a very
inefficient way to do these things
because maybe I don't want to come up
with my coding scheme by brute force by
writing down everything that could
possibly output from the channel and
mapping it to, you know, what the coding
function would send it to. So, we're
going to do a lot better today with uh
something called Huffman coding. In
fact, let me tell you a bit of the
history of Huffman coding. So Huffman
coding was invented back in 1951
by Huffman
and it was invented you know right here
at MIT in fact not by a professor but by
a grad student. So what happened here
was that the grad student was taking a
graduate seminar and as is often the
case with these types of things you know
students don't want to take final exams.
I'm sure you guys don't.
And so his uh professor uh Bob Fano,
who's still here, uh he offered him the
choice of whether he could write a term
paper or do the final. So he chose, of
course, writing a term paper. And the
term paper had to be about improving
something in the state-of-the-art in
coding theory. Coding theory was a topic
that was just developing around that
time.
uh he was pretty stuck and then uh he
thought okay I better cut my losses and
start studying for the final and then at
the very last minute he came up with
this amazing new algorithm which we
teach in a lot of our undergraduate
classes as you know a a neat example and
a powerful example so that's what we'll
be covering today is you know some of
the work that went into Huffman's PhD
thesis so uh as I mentioned we'll come
back to the comparison to Shannon uh
Shannon uh later on. But let me give you
a crucial definition. So we're going to
be interested in a stronger notion of an
encoding. We'll define what's called a
prefix code. Now in comparison to the
coding function that took an entire
sequence of symbols of length n and it
outputs some binary string. A prefix
code is just going to take one single
symbol from our alphabet and it's going
to output some binary string of variable
length. But now we have a stronger
condition on what we want out of this
code.
So we want it to satisfy the condition
that for any two input symbols AI and AJ
that are different, we want that five of
AI
is not
a prefix
of five of AJ. So this is a stronger
condition than them merely being
different in terms of their binary
strings. We want that whatever AI is
mapped to, we want that that binary
string doesn't occur in the in the front
in the beginning of what uh AJ is mapped
to and vice versa. Of course, we want
this to be true for all pairs of
distinct symbols.
So, in fact, what I claim is that
there's a nice way to think about a
prefix code as a binary tree. So, let's
develop a way to think about binary
codes. uh prefix free codes as uh sorry
prefix free codes.
Uh let's develop a way to visualize them
as binary trees.
So first let me give you an example of a
prefix free code.
So let's imagine and this will be our
running example today as we see the
algorithm under the hood of Huffman
coding.
So, let's imagine that we have symbols
A, B, C, D, E, and F. And I'm going to
map these to the code words 1 0 0
1 1 0
0 1 0 0 1 and one one one.
So you can check that this is a prefix
free code because you can check for each
of the possible outputs for your
encoding function. One zero doesn't
appear at the start of any of these
strings. And that's true for all of the
other, you know, encodings for each of
these symbols. And one of the ways that
we can think about this is we can think
about it as a binary tree in which each
branch in the binary tree tells us
whether the next symbol is either a zero
or one. So in this case, let's arrange
these into a binary tree where the
leaves are going to represent what the
actual symbols are. So when I have a
symbol like D that my prefix free code
is mapping to the string 01 then I get
that just by tracing from my root to
that leaf. I concatenate these symbols
in order and I get 01. And let me do
this for all of the different symbols in
my prefix free code.
And every time going left down the tree
is going to correspond to concatenating
with a zero. And every time going right
with a one. So when I put this all
together, I'll get a binary tree that
looks like this.
And you can check me on the details that
you know indeed each symbol is mapped to
the position in the binary tree where
its associated word comes from just
following the roottoleaf path. Right?
And now what is the condition that this
code is prefix free? Well, you know, if
I had one leaf, if I had one symbol
appear right here, right in the middle
of this tree, I would have another
symbol that's a descendant of it. And
that would correspond to some a code
that's not prefix free because in that
case, the way that I would reach this
symbol would be a prefix of how I reach
this later symbol. So in fact what this
constraint on prefix freess is another
way to think about it is that when I
arrange all of the symbols into this
binary tree describing their encoding. I
want the property that each position in
the tree that describes the encoding of
a symbol has no other descendants that
are symbols beneath it. So that's an
equivalent way to think about prefix
free. So any questions about this key
definition? Does this make sense? Yeah.
All right.
So now uh we can talk about what's the
important thing about prefix free codes.
So what I claim is that it actually
makes decoding much much easier. So
let's see why that is.
See, when I talked about Shannon, I had
to specify how the entire string of
length n was mapped to a binary output.
But now what I can do is I have a much
simpler code that operates on a symbol
by symbol basis. So all I'm going to do
is I'm going to take my sequence of
symbols and I'm just going to map them
to 01 strings using my prefix free
encoding and then I'm going to
concatenate them all together.
So let's do an example, right? What if I
tell you I started off with a word and I
ended up with this binary string.
How would I figure out what was the
sequence of symbols that I started off
from? So, we're going to have to use the
fact that it's prefix fe crucially,
right? So, how can I go about figuring
out what the first letter is? Any
guesses for the first letter?
F. Right? So in fact what I can do is I
can see that you know if I chop off
these first three symbols that's the
encoding of f what's my next uh symbol
a. So you can see what's tricky here is
that because my output has variable
length I don't know where the breaks
are. Right? I smooshed everything
together when I did this. But how did I
know that the next break should be
distance two?
How did you guys figure that out?
>> Yeah, youverse down the tree.
>> That's right. That's right. And so if I
traverse down the tree and hit a leaf,
that's right. So we can continue this.
We'll get the next letter is D. And last
but not least, we'll get E. So it
started off with the word fate. But now
here's the crucial question.
Why couldn't there be some other way
hypothetically to break up the string
into pieces in a different way
that results in a totally different
decoding of what my original string was?
You see, when I started off with
Shannon's encoding theorem, right, I was
doing it on the entire string. And the
property was that two different strings
map to different outputs. Now I'm doing
this on a symbol by symbol basis. Why am
I guaranteed you know with my prefix
free encoding that there's no other way
to break this up that makes sense is
really because of the prefix freess
right so what if the break point had
really happened at this yellow line so
that I pulled out the first two symbols
well if that really mapped to another
symbol if there was a symbol whose
associated code word was one one then
the trouble is that my code word my
encoding scheme would not be prefix free
because that symbol would have an
encoding that's a prefix of that of f.
Right? So prefix freess is just the
constraint that you can sequentially do
decoding symbol by symbol in an
unambiguous way. I always know where the
breaks are even when I erase them. So
does that make sense?
All right. So prefix freess is an
awesome property. um it's not obvious
you know how it compares to what the
fundamental limits were that we proved
last time using Shannon right we also
don't know what's the best way to you
know what's the way to choose the prefix
free code that minimizes the expected
length so that'll be our goal today is
we're going to be interested in the
following very basic algorithmic problem
we want to design
a prefix
free code
that minimizes
expected length.
And just to be clear, what is our
expected length here? It's just on a by
symbol basis, right? We're thinking
about outputs of our first order source
that are just length one for simplicity.
And what I want is I want that the sum
over all of the symbols in my alphabet
the probability that the symbol is
chosen times LA a where LA is the length
of the encoding of five of A. I want to
minimize this quantity because
intuitively now when I really care about
the case where n is large and is not
one. Well, my expected length is just
going to be n times whatever I can
achieve for a single symbol, right? And
we know how encoding and decoding work.
So our goal is just to solve this
algorithmic problem and then we're going
to compare it back with Shannon.
So are there any questions?
Make sense?
All right. So, as I told you, you know,
Huffman, uh, you know, in lie of taking
a final exam at MIT, he designed a
simple greedy algorithm for optimally
solving this problem. And that's what
we're going to do. We'll explain how the
approach works through a running
example. Okay? And our running example
will be the same one that I wrote up
there. Uh, you know, our running
example, let me just write it here so
that we have it.
We'll consider the problem with symbols
A, B, C, D, E, and F. And their
associated probabilities because of
course the optimal encoding depends
crucially on these probabilities will be
0.4
0.05
0.18
0.07 07
0.20.10
and if I did this right they all sum up
to one. So what we want to do is we want
to understand what is the optimal prefix
free encoding for this particular first
order source and we'll see that you know
in solving this problem we're going to
come up with a general algorithm that
works really for any channel.
Okay. So now uh let's get started.
So let's imagine let me tell you uh you
know what our strategy is going to be.
We're going to start off with some
encoding which we remember we think
about as a binary tree and we're going
to pretend that this encoding is optimal
and we're going to derive structural
properties about this optimal encoding
that will be enough to figure out what
the encoding is. So that's our game
plan. So I'm going to pretend that
someone has given me already an optimal
prefix free code.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to
reverse engineer
uh you know properties of this binary
tree. Now just for simplicity I'm going
to assume
that there are no ties.
What I mean by that is when I start off
with all of these symbols, none of the
symbols have exactly the same
probability. It'll just be a bit more of
a pain to talk about what the structural
properties are when we allow ties, even
though the same algorithm is essentially
going to work as is. So I'll assume that
none of these symbols have probabilities
that are tied. And we're going to create
new synthetic symbols along the way. And
I'm going to assume that there are no
ties even after we make those
operations.
So now let's state the first key lema
that's going to get us started in terms
of structural properties of this tree T.
So what I claim is that the smallest
probability symbol, so whichever symbol
has the smallest probability in our
first order source, has the property
that it's at least tied
for
the longest encoding.
So what I'm claiming is that whatever is
the symbol with the smallest
probability, in this case it's the
symbol B right here, I claim that that
symbol had better be in one of the
deepest
nodes in my binary tree that corresponds
my prefix free code. Okay, so let's
prove this fact and then we're going to
prove a related fact about the symbol
with the second smallest probability.
So this thing is very easy to prove once
uh you know what you're trying to prove.
Does anyone have any intuition for how
we could try and prove this lema?
>> Why should it be true? Yeah,
>> if like if it is not tied for the
longest, then you could swap it with
something with higher probability.
>> That's right. That's right. So that's
exactly how our proof is going to go
because you can see the way that this
proof is structured, it makes it a lot
easier to, you know, have the algorithm
fall out at the end because I'm not in
one shot trying to tell you what the
optimal tree is. I'm just trying to say
if you gave me the optimal tree, I could
find some interesting structural
properties that constrain something
about the tree that I'm looking for. So
that's exactly right. Our proof is going
to be, you know, if not, we're going to
swap and contradict the optimality of T.
So let's do a proof by contradiction
following exactly that logic. So suppose
that this lema is not true.
Well, let's let you know B be the symbol
with the lowest probability
like in our example. And let's let C be
the symbol which is tied for
longest encoding.
Now the crucial thing is that if we swap
the encodings
of B and C. Well, first of all, that's
still a valid prefix free code, right?
Because the property of being a prefix
free code doesn't actually depend on how
the symbols are mapped to the binary
strings. It's purely a property of the
binary strings I've selected. When you
think about graphically how we visualize
the prefix free code, it just had this
property that all of these nodes which
were boxes that correspond the symbols
being mapped to them. We needed the
property that no box had another box as
its descendant. And now if I interchange
the contents of these boxes, if I swap B
and C, then it doesn't actually change
this cominatorial condition of being
prefix free. So this is a valid move.
We're allowed to swap the encodings. And
what we can do is if we swap these
encodings, we can track how the expected
length changes.
So let's in particular compute how the
expected length changes.
So we have originally well our new uh
you know new encoding is going to have
the probability of the symbol B times
the length of the encoding for symbol C
plus the probability of the symbol C
times the length of the encoding for B.
That'll be some sort of contribution to
the new expected length because you know
every time I sample the symbol B, its
encoding is what the encoding of C
previously was. And every time I sample
the symbol C, its length will be the
length of the encoding of what B
previously was. But now I have to
subtract off what it was before. Right?
So I'm going to get PB * the length of
the encoding for B minus
PC * the length of the encoding for C.
So in particular when I have my formula
for the expected length which is right
here. Notice that for none of the other
symbols am I changing their probability
or the length of their encoding. The
only changes are happening between B and
C. So when I look at the difference in
the expected length of my old prefix
free code and my new one, the change in
the length is you know this quantity
right here because all of the other
things cancel out.
So let's figure out you know what's
going on here.
[clears throat] So this is
we can write this out in a more
convenient way. This is just PB * delta
minus PC * delta where delta is equal to
the length of the encoding of
C minus the length of the encoding of B.
And we know by assumption, you know,
because we're trying to prove something
by contradiction that by assumption
that uh C is the symbol with the longest
encoding, right? So B is not tied for
the same length of the encoding. So we
know that the difference between these
encoding lengths is at least one, right?
So it's strictly positive. And we also
know
that PB is less than PC.
Why is that true? Because of the way
that I defined PB. PB was the symbol
with the smallest probability and I
assumed that there were no ties. So
whatever PB is, PC is strictly larger
than that. So if you look at these two
quantities together, then what this
means is that you actually have a change
that's strictly
negative. So I've actually decreased the
expected length of my code. So that's
the proof of the first key lema. It
tells us this really nice structural
property. And you can see that the proof
is a very simple proof by contradiction
where I just have to figure out that I
want to use the swap and make the
calculation of how much I've improved
the length and argue that it really is
an improvement. So are there any
questions so far?
Good.
All right.
So I claim that there's a companion lema
that the same lema holds also for the
symbol with the second smallest
probability. So let me state what I mean
exactly by a version of this lema that
holds for the second smallest
probability and then we'll prove it. The
proof will build on our proof of lema
one and then we'll be off to the races.
So what I claim is that this lema
holds
for second
smallest
probability
two.
So let's formally state what this lema
is.
The second smallest
symbol
I claim is second smallest probability
symbol because that's how we're
measuring their contribution is tied
for the longest encoding.
Okay. And so the proof for this lema is
going to very closely mirror the proof
for lema one, but it's just going to
build on it. So let's prove this fact.
Actually, in my example, what is my
second smallest probability? Let's
double check.
Okay, so it's
D.
So now what I'm claiming between lema
one and lema 2 is that these two symbols
both had better be tied for the longest
encoding.
So let's you know follow our lema. So
let's let
B be the symbol
with the lowest probability.
Let's let D be the symbol
with the second lowest probability.
And now what we know from lema one,
what we already proved
is that if we look in our optimal tree,
we start off at the root, we follow some
path,
and then we reach our symbol uh B, which
is the symbol with the smallest
probability.
And let's imagine that we call P the
parent.
So whoever comes before
So this is not the image of a symbol
because we have this prefix free
constraint but it's still a node in our
binary tree. There is some parent of
wherever B gets mapped to.
And now what I claim is that
but P you know the way that I've drawn
it I claim must have another child.
I claim that there must be some node in
my binary tree that's the sibling of P.
So let's make sure we're on the same
page. So why is this claim true? Why can
I assert that P has another child?
If it didn't, what would it contradict?
Yeah.
>> Would it not be a binary tree then?
>> Well, it would still be a binary tree.
So, we'll allow, you know, zero, one or
two children. But there's something else
that's really crucial. So, think back to
my proof strategy. What am I trying to
do? I'm trying to say that T is an
optimal prefix free code. And then my
first lema was a structural statement
about some property that must be true of
that optimal binary tree.
Lema 2 is an even stronger structural
property about that optimal binary tree.
So what would happen if P really didn't
have another child right here?
>> Yeah.
>> No longer be an optimal code.
>> Yes. It would no longer be optimal. Why?
because you have an empty space,
>> right? But another way to think about it
is that you know I know that there's no
symbol that's mapped to P because it's
prefix free. If P didn't have another
child, I could just promote this node
and delete everything underneath. Right?
So in this case I would be strictly
improving the expected length of my
prefix free code because I'm not
changing anything except for the length
of the encoding of B which is decreasing
by one. So what I claim is that P must
have another child otherwise
T is definitely not optimal.
Does that make sense? Okay. So now I
know that this child really must be
there. And let's call this child C,
which is just the sibling, right? And so
what I claim now is that if I look in
this tree and I have some path that goes
to my other symbol, which is D, my
second smallest probability. Well, what
could I do if D was not tied for the
second not tied for the longest
encoding? You know, we know that B has
the longest encoding. So, D better have,
you know, an encoding length that's less
than or equal to it. But what if it was
strictly less than the length of the
encoding of B? We know that there's
another child C that has the same length
encoding as B. So what should I do if
you know D wasn't tied for the second
longest encoding? I can do the same
trick as before, right? I can swap. So
what I claim is that now
if
uh D
has a strictly shorter encoding.
What I claim is that I can swap
C and D,
right?
And improve the expected length.
So this is the same proof as before,
right? So this is a bit subtle, but it's
a purely combinatorial proof. Are there
any questions? So you know the way that
this worked logically from lema one, we
know that B is tied for the longest
encoding. So nothing can have an
encoding length that's strictly longer.
We we argued that B has a parent P and
that P had better have another child.
And if P has another child, this would
better be some other symbol in terms of
the encoding. And if D were strictly off
this line and the length of its coding
were shorter than the length of the
encoding of B and C, what we could do is
we could just swap D and C. And then the
same type of computation that we did in
the proof of lema one will show us that
we've strictly improved. Why? Because
the probability of D is strictly less
than the probability of C. Okay, so
these are our two key structural lemas.
And now we're actually almost in good
shape. So we're almost uh ready to talk
about Huffman's algorithm.
So let me do one more claim. The slash
structural property is the thing that's
going to make Huffman's greedy algorithm
work. So I claim building off of lema
one and lema two, we can say something
even stronger.
What I claim is that without loss of
generality, these two symbols B and D,
which are the smallest and second
smallest probabilities respectively, I
claim without loss generality they're
siblings.
in the tree.
So why is this true? Well, from lema one
and lema 2.
What do we know? We can draw it out
pictorially. We know that we start off
from the root. We take some path to the
parent P and then we reach our symbol D,
right? And we know that P has some other
child maybe it's C and then we know that
there's a path that reaches
the other symbol B which has the second
smallest probability according to our
channel and we know that all of these
things are tied for the same length. So
what could I do in this case is I could
just swap the positions of B and C. That
doesn't change anything about the
lengths of the encoding, but it has the
property now that B and D are siblings
of each other. Right?
So the proof for all of these structural
statements lema 1, lema 2 and this claim
is really just if not swap. Lema one was
if B isn't the longest then swap and
you'll improve the length. Lema two was
well we know where B is but if B is also
not the same length then swap and
improve the length and finally even
knowing that they're tied for the same
length of the encoding swap so that
they're siblings.
So this is the key structural property
that we're going to use. Without wash
generality, B and D are siblings. And
now we can come back to our running
example and we can build up what the
optimal tree is and we'll be able to,
you know, Huffman's algorithm is just
going to fall out as a consequence.
Okay,
so let's do the same, you know,
intuition on this, right? So we don't
know what our optimal tree looks like.
I'll just draw it as a big blob. Right?
But we know from our claim that without
loss of generality, B and D are siblings
of each other.
And so now here's the idea. What I'm
going to do is I'm going to take these
two symbols and I'm going to replace
them with a new symbol. So I'm going to
write down a new symbol alpha. And so
here's the step in my Huffman coding
algorithm. I'm going to replace these
symbols
B and D
with a new symbol
which I'm going to call alpha.
And I'm going to have the property that
my probability of this new symbol is
going to be the sum of the probabilities
of the symbols that I've merged. So
that's the key idea. So, I'm going to
set its probability to be equal to the
sum of the two old probabilities. This
way, when I get rid of these two symbols
from my list and instead add my symbol
alpha at the bottom, I'm still going to
have a valid distribution because I've
just merged those two probabilities. But
now, what we're going to do, the main
idea behind Huffman
is we're going to solve the optimal
problem on this smaller uh set of
symbols, right? And then from the
optimal binary tree for this new
problem, we're going to derive what the
optimal binary tree was for our original
problem. So are there any questions
about the strategy? Does this make
sense?
All right. So let's do that and let's
see what Huffman would do.
So the corresponding transformation on
the tree.
We started off with this tree T and now
we're going to have this tree T prime.
And what's going to happen is I've
replaced the parent of B and D instead
with this new symbol alpha that occurs
in the same exact place in the tree. But
then I've changed nothing else about the
tree.
So now we get to the key lema.
What I claim
is that this new tree t prime is also
optimal
for our new problem where our new
alphabet is a prime. So we take our old
alphabet A, we add in this new element
alpha, we subtract off the two symbols B
and D. And we've already talked about
how we update the probabilities.
So this is the key property that I pro
you know I was assuming that someone
gave me the optimal tree T for my
original problem. Now I said something
structurally about without loss
generality where B and D have to occur
in relation to each other. And now I've
created a subpros on a smaller number of
symbols. But I claim that just this new
tree uh t prime that I get had actually
be an optimal uh answer to the new
problem that I've constructed.
So does this make sense intuitively?
Okay. So let's prove this lema.
So just for notation, let's let L be the
expected length
of T. I'm going to let L prime be the
expected length of T prime, this new
tree that I've constructed.
And let's prove this lema that T prime
is optimal.
So to make sure you guys are following.
So does anyone have any intuition for
how I can prove this lema that t prime
is again optimal?
There's basically only one proof we have
today.
>> Yeah. Um I was thinking you could like
swap it, but I was a little bit
concerned cuz if you like swap the
probabilities together, maybe it gets
big.
Okay, so let's think about what we're
trying to prove, right? We're trying to
prove that T prime is an optimal prefix
free code for this new sub problem I've
constructed on a smaller alphabet,
right? So uh what proof strategy do you
think makes sense to prove that T prime
is optimal?
Greedy induction some other proof
strategy
proof by contradiction.
Yeah.
>> Okay, that's right. Um because in fact
like the easiest way to prove this is
what if t prime is not optimal then what
I can do is I could hope to construct
you know I could take whatever tree is
optimal for this sub problem and then
what would I want to do with that tree
you know let's say that proof by
contradiction is the right way to do
this right so suppose not
suppose there's is a better
tree.
Let's call this tree, I don't know, S.
What should I do with my better tree?
How am I trying to prove a proof by
contradiction?
So you can either answer the question or
ask me a question about what we covered
so far. So it's your choice, but
someone's got to answer.
>> Yeah,
>> I presume you can show that S is
actually just T prime.
>> Uh S is actually T prime.
That's true, but it's harder than I
want.
So some of these things you kind of have
to have a little bit of intuition about
which proof technique would be the
easiest. So we already agreed it's proof
by contradiction. But the question is
what am I trying to contradict and how?
Because that's how proof by
contradiction works.
So what can I do with S? Yeah.
>> Can you backtrack to make another
version of T.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, let's think about S. I
like that. So, S is some other blob,
right? And it's better.
Um, what are the symbols that occur in
S?
Well,
A, C, E, F, and alpha. My new symbol.
So, alpha appears somewhere,
right?
What should I do with alpha now?
Well, maybe I can try and construct a
better encoding for my original problem.
Right? So that's the idea is that
there's a proof by contradiction. So we
suppose that there's a better tree s.
Right? And this better tree is a better
tree for this particular problem on this
new alphabet A prime. And what I want to
do is I want to use this S to construct
a better answer to my original problem
that contradicts the optimality of T.
Right? So think about how the logic of
this proof worked. Someone gave me an
optimal tree T. I proved a structural
property about you know where B and D
occur. And now what I'm doing is I'm
saying that I want that when I contract
B and D the result I get is optimal for
the corresponding subpro because if it
weren't optimal for the corresponding
sub problem then my original tree T
could not have been optimal to begin
with. Right? So this is the key point
for the logic of the proof. Even though
the proof is very simple, it takes a
little bit to wrap your head around the
logic. All right? So let's imagine that
there's a better prefix code S and the
associated tree and let's say that it
has expected length
which is LP prime. Okay, remember L
prime was the expected length of T
prime. So we're assuming for the purpose
of contradiction that LP prime is
strictly less than L prime that it does
strictly better. So in this case what we
can do is we can convert we can invert
the operation that we just did right.
So we can invert the operation
which took us from the problem on the
full alphabet A to the sub problem on
alphabet A prime. We can replace the
symbol alpha that was our new synthetic
symbol by
this gadget right here. Right? And so
when we do that, let's track what the
new expected length is. Right?
So the new expected length
is LP prime because I still pay the
expected length you know until I um you
know for this answer S right but now by
replacing alpha with B and D every time
I incur encounter either B or D
I'm going to pay one extra unit of
length.
because previously I stopped at the
symbol alpha and now I have to continue
wherever alpha was that's not the end I
have to go further down to either B or D
that happens with probability PB plus PD
respectively so this is my new expected
length when I take my you know new
better answer for this sub problem and
replace it
with inverting this operation that's my
new expected length. But when I think
about how this compares to my old
expected length, see if I had the
original tree prime here, right? Then I
pay expected length L prime. And the way
that I get from T prime to T was I do
that same operation where I take alpha
and replace it with B and D. So my old
expected length was actually L prime
plus PD uh sorry plus PB
plus PD and this is just equal to L. So
does everyone see how I got this? This
is the crucial point in the proof. If
you don't understand this, you don't
understand Huffman coding. Okay. And so
the crucial thing right here is that now
I've come up with a better solution for
my original problem. And this
contradicts
the optimality
of T. Okay. So this is the proof
and I'm not going to go on further until
you convince me you understand the
proof. Okay. So who can explain to me
how this proof works in your own words?
the one that's on the board
or ask me a question. Those are your two
options.
I guess the third option is try and
avoid eye contact, but that won't be as
effective.
>> Yeah, go for it.
>> So, basically, we're trying to do it by
contradiction by saying that there's a
more optimal tree S. Yeah. And we're
going to show that the expected um that
when we like make S back into the same
alphabet with T that S like finds that
another shape is more optimal.
>> Yeah.
>> My prediction because our first
assumption is
>> that's right. So to do that we
calculated the new expected length for S
and then given that S is like more
optimal than T prime um we can we know
that that optimal length is less than L
prime plus the like reverting L prime
which is equal to T.
>> Okay. Yeah. Very good. That was that was
perfect. Uh let's stress test our
understanding. You know I think the
right way to understand proofs is to
think about them like an engineer to
look at each individual piece, right? So
we proved a bunch of things today uh all
you know getting to this key lema right
um and uh you know one of the key things
we had was this claim that without los
generality in the optimal tree B and D
the symbols with the smallest and second
smallest probability
are siblings.
Where in the proof of this uh or in the
setup of this lema 3 did I use this
claim?
>> Yeah, they have to be siblings in order
for you to like remove B and D and
>> that's exactly right because I used it
even in the setup the definition. So how
did I define T prime? T prime was what I
got from taking an optimal tree T and
then taking the symbols with the
smallest and second smallest probability
and replacing them with alpha.
And in the tree, the only way that that
can make sense is if they're actually
siblings of each other. So I invoked
this claim implicitly when I said that
let T be an optimal tree without loss
generality. The two symbols B and D are
siblings of each other. And then this
operation makes sense, this contraction
operation where I replaced B and D with
the new symbol alpha. And that was what
allowed me to proceed with this proof,
right? Because once I had that that
operation made sense, the key point was
exactly as you said that if this new uh
tree t prime weren't optimal, then I
could do better by inverting my
operation, calculating the expected
length, and that would contradict the
optimality of t. Okay.
So now are we all on the same page?
We're good. Happy. Okay. All right. So,
uh, this is, you know, when you're
trying to learn things yourself, I think
this is a good way to try and do it
because you should stress test yourself.
All right. So, but I claim that now
we're basically done. So, we're going to
have, you know, Huffman's main result
because it'll just be a lot of pretty
pictures.
So, let's do the pretty pictures.
And don't fear, I still have more
questions for the audience as we do
this.
So let's just keep track of applying
this lema again and again, right? What I
know is that when I replace the symbols
with the smallest and second smallest
probabilities with a new symbol, I know
that you know my finding the optimal
solution to that problem will help me
solve my original problem. So let's just
track it through and figure out you know
what happens to our original problem. So
our original problem that we cared about
was just you know we have A B C D E and
F
and they had associated probabilities
0.4
0.05
0.18
0.07
0.20 200.10.
And then what I'm going to do in my next
problem is I'm going to have symbols A,
C, B 108, E, F, and alpha. And they're
associated probabilities. Well, A stays
the same. We haven't touched it. Ste C
stays the same. E stays the same. F
stays the same. and alpha is now 0.12
because I added up the probabilities of
B and C.
What's my next step in this uh
procedure? Can anyone help me out?
What should I do?
I'm trying to reduce my, you know,
original problem down to smaller
problems in such a way that I can back
out what the optimal solution is.
What should I do now? I've got this new
problem here on this alphabet A prime.
>> Yeah.
>> Do a similar operation with F and alpha.
>> F and alpha. That's right. So these
become the two symbols with the smallest
and second smallest probability. And I
can replace them with a new symbol beta.
So I get a C, E, and beta. And now their
associated probabilities are
Still point4 for a I haven't touched it.
0.18
0.2 and 0.22
and after this my symbols with the
smallest probabilities are C and E. So
I'm going to replace them with a new
symbol gamma. So I have a gamma beta
and they have associated probability 0.4
0.38
0.22 22. And last but not least, I take
the two ones with the smallest
probabilities right here and I replace
them with the new symbol delta.
So what's my optimal prefix code for
this?
If I gave you a problem with just an
alphabet of size two and the two symbols
had probability 04 and 6,
you know, my goal is to try and take my
original problem, which I didn't know
the optimal solution for, and hopefully
reduce it to a problem that's so simple
that I can solve it. So, I'm done
reducing it. I ran out of board space.
Um, what's the optimal solution to this
last problem at the very end of the
chain? What's my optimal prefix free
code?
>> Yeah.
>> Can you say like just like gamma like
one and then a 01?
>> That's right. Perfect.
Because you know remember what's going
on these prefix free codes I can think
about them as binary trees. There's only
one binary tree I can do on these two
things. So my optimal code is just this
guy right here. I have the root and then
my two symbols get encoded with either a
zero or one. Doesn't matter which one is
which. Right? And now for you know the
question for the audience, right? Okay.
My goal wasn't to get down to a trivial
problem that I can solve. You know, if
we give you on your exam three a
question like this, you can't just
replace it with your own favorite
trivial question and solve it. Um I care
about the solution to my original
problem.
So, how can I try and get the solution
to my original problem? Maybe let's
start simple. Uh, what's the optimal
solution to this problem right here?
Slightly harder. Uh, there's an alphabet
of size three. We know what the optimal
solution is on the associated sub
problem. So, how can I get my next
optimal solution? Trying to go the other
direction
or what would the optimal solution be?
Yeah.
>> Adding a branch off of delta.
>> That's right. That's right. Because how
do we get delta? It was merging gamma
and beta. What we did was we invoked the
claim that says that the optimal tree
for this had better have the symbol with
the smallest and second smallest
probabilities be siblings. And now I can
undo my operation where I merge them
together into a new symbol delta. And
what I'll get is I'll get this new
binary tree. A stays where it is. It's
still encoded as zero. But now we get a
deeper binary tree where I replace delta
with beta
and gamma.
So beta gets mapped to zero z uh one
zero and gamma gets mapped to one one.
Right?
Okay. Just to make sure that we're
really on the same page. What should I
do next? What's my next uh optimal
solution?
What should I do?
>> Yeah, split up.
>> Split up gamma. Perfect. So now I think
you guys see how this works, right? So
my new solution right here would be a is
over here.
I still have beta where it was before. I
split up gamma into
c
and e, right?
And then I go backwards once more. Uh,
I'm going to run out of space soon. So,
this will be the last one that I'll do.
Actually, maybe I'll do one more. That's
fine.
And my last one, which I'll need a bit
of space to draw. Uh,
okay.
I guess I'll draw it over here.
So my last one is this binary tree.
So this is a valid prefix free encoding,
right? Um what can I say about this tree
T?
It's optimal, right? Why is it optimal?
I claim that this is an optimal solution
to the original running example I gave
you at the beginning of class. Why is
this tree optimal?
Because in each step, right, all we did
was we reasoned about any tree that's
optimal without loss generality had the
property that B and D were siblings. And
then for the new problem on my alphabet
A prime without loss generality, it had
the property that you know F and alpha
were siblings. And for my new sub
problem, it had the property that
without loss of generality and so on. So
in fact we argued in each step that
without loss generality our optimal tree
could take this form. Now there could be
other ways of doing it because I could
swap f and c together. But we argued
that whatever we get out of this
procedure had actually better be
optimal. So this was you know huffman
coding. Um in fact we're not done.
There's one more crucial question that
we want to ask and answer about it. But
right now what we did was we gave you a
simple greedy algorithm that finds the
optimal prefix free code. It's not like
Shannon where I say it's approximately
optimal up to some additive terms. It is
the optimal prefix free code. But
there's one more crucial question which
is you know how good is this code right?
So when we talked about Shannon you know
I have it conveniently up here. It's not
just that you know we argue that there's
a coding function and we constructed it.
it's that we actually argued about how
good it is. We bounded its performance
and we saw that the binary entropy fell
out from the end of that. Right? So our
last step is to bound the performance of
the Huffman code and show that it's very
good. In fact, it'll really beat what we
proved in Shannon last time. So that's
the last part of today's lecture.
So let me state one helper lema which um
you're going to
give an alternative proof for in
recitation and talk about you know what
are figures to illustrate this proof.
This proof is called the craft
inequality and once we have this craft
inequality we'll be able to get a very
nice bound on the performance of Huffman
codes.
So this is a purely cominatorial lama
and it's called the craft inequality.
So what I claim is that for any
natural numbers L1 L2
all the way up to LK. So of course
natural numbers just means uh non-
negative integers. So any non- negative
integers. I claim that there is
a binary tree
with leaves
at depths given by these values. So at
depths L1, L2 all the way up to LK.
If and only if the following condition
holds, the sum of i = 1 to k of 2 the
minus l i is at most one. Okay, so this
is a little bit of a mouthful. So what
I'm asking you is some sort of packing
constraint. Obviously, you can't have
three leaves at depth 2 because it's a
binary tree, right?
And what this craft inequality tells you
is it tells you a necessary and
sufficient condition if you give me the
sequence of depths whether or not there
is a tree you know with leaves at those
depths.
So you know let's do a simple example
just to make sure that uh we're on the
same page.
So let's start off with some depths of
the leaves
that satisfy the craft inequality.
Let's say L1= 2, L2= 3, L3= 3. You can
check when you add up the craft
inequality that uh you know you're good,
right?
Actually, sorry, this should be uh depth
one, two, two. Okay,
depth one, two, two. Okay.
And so what would be the associated tree
here? Well, you know, here's one example
of a binary tree that satisfies these
conditions as promised by craft
inequality.
So I take this associated binary tree.
It has one leaf of depth one because
we're going down distance one from the
root. It has uh one leaf of depth two
and its third leaf is also of depth two.
And you can check that you know a half
plus a quarter plus a quarter is less
than or equal to one. So this is an
example which both satisfies this craft
condition and has an associated binary
tree.
So this is just one illustration. But
what if instead I take you know L3 and
replace it by L3 is equal to
uh
let's see three
and L4 is equal to three. This still
satisfies the craft inequality. What
would I do is I would just replace this
part with a deeper binary tree with A3
here and A4 here.
So the proof for the craft inequality
essentially goes, you know, the way
you'd expect it to is you just build up
a binary tree.
The key point is that, you know, if I
had all of the same lengths, right? like
I had L1 equals 1 and L2 equals 1 then
it's just you know a regular binary tree
and every time what's going on is that
you know when I have larger depths it
really corresponds to replacing the leaf
with uh some deeper binary tree exactly
as I did in this example. So you're
going to prove this in recitation. So
I'll just leave the proof as to be
continued. You're going to work on both
understanding the proof of this and
drawing diagrams to illustrate the
proof. But for us, we're going to take
this for granted and we're going to
prove our main theorem about Huffman
codes, which is, you know, not just that
there's an algorithm for building
Huffman codes, but we're going to give a
bound on their performance, and we're
going to relate it back to what we
proved on Thursday,
uh, using Shannon.
So, here's our last statement for today
that we're going to prove, and we're
going to build on this craft inequality.
What I claim is that the Huffman code
has expected length
L
which is between H and H + one.
So this is an incredibly strong
statement because I'm saying that you
know the binary entropy really tightly
controls what the expected length of our
optimal prefix free code is. I'm not
going to prove this part. This part in
effect we already proved through Shannon
but I'll argue about why we already
proved that. Let's prove the other side
that the Huffman code is good.
Okay,
so here's our idea.
Let's let
LA a
be the length of the encoding for symbol
A. And we're going to, you know, uh,
very cleverly choose it to be the
ceiling of log of PA. Okay. So what's
going on here is that the depths of my
leaves had better be, you know, natural
numbers. They're non- negative integers.
And you know, PA is the associated
probability of the symbol A, right? So I
take log of PA, I'm going to get a
negative number. I multiply it by minus
one, I'm going to get a positive number.
And I'm just going to round up that
number.
And those are going to be my depths LA,
right? And so the first thing I have to
argue about is you know that these are
valid depths for the leaves because
that's where I want to put each of these
symbols. So how do I argue that these
are valid depths is I appeal to the
craft inequality. So the craft
inequality tells me I just have to check
a particular inequality. So let's verify
craft
that the conditions of craft inequality
hold. So I want that the sum over all
symbols in my alphabet of 2 the minus la
I want to show that this is at most one.
Right? So let's write out what this
thing is. Well, by definition, the way
we've constructed LA, this is still the
sum over all symbols in our alphabet of
2 to the minus ceiling of minus log PA.
And I claim that this is upper bounded
by the sum over all the symbols in our
alphabet of 2 to the log PA.
So what's going on here, right, is that
remember inside I have a positive number
because it's minus log PA. Log PA is
negative. So when I'm rounding it up and
then I'm multiplying by minus one, I'm
making this associated number smaller.
So I can make the number only bigger by
removing the ceiling function. When I
remove the ceiling function, the two
minuses cancel and I get log PA. And now
two to the log PA is very simple. It's
just PA. So I get sum over all of the
symbols in my alphabet of PA which is
one. So this verifies the craft
inequality because all of these lengths
LA that I've conveniently
part I have to do is I just have to
analyze how good this particular uh you
know construction is and then because
the Huffman code is optimal it'll only
ever be better than whatever I get for
this particular code that follows by
appealing to craft.
So now let's calculate the performance
of the code.
So we know you know by lema 4
we know that there is a binary tree
with these depths the depths that I've
guessed
and let's calculate its expected length.
Right? So, I know that L, the expected
length of my Huffman code, is only ever
better than whatever expected length I'm
going to get for this tree that I'm
guessing from Craft.
And this right here is the sum over all
symbols in my alphabet of PA time LA,
the length of the associated symbol.
Well, I can replace this again. This is
the sum over all symbols in my alphabet
of PA times the ceiling of minus log PA.
And now I claim that this is upper
bounded just by adding one instead of
taking the ceiling, right? Because at
most I bump it up by one. So this is the
sum over all symbols in my alphabet of
PA time minus log PA + 1. But now I'm in
good shape, right? Because this term
should look familiar. This is the binary
entropy and this term right here when
I'm summing up all the PAS I get one. So
in total the thing that I get as my
upper bound is the binary entropy plus
one. So that's the proof.
The Huffman code is very very good
because it's optimal and because there
exists a good code by the craft
inequality whose performance is H+ one.
Now in the last couple minutes I want to
take this way further and connect it
back to Shannon. So you know we proved a
bunch of things. We proved you know that
we found an algorithm Huffman's uh
coding algorithm for finding the optimal
prefix free code. We analyzed its
performance in terms of its expected
length. But now what I want to argue
about is you know how we can do much
better than Shannon. Right? So we talked
about you know how Shannon I think I
still have it here.
It gets a bound you know when you apply
it to length n sequences instead of a
single length you know single symbol it
gets n * entropy plus some other term.
So if I naively use my Huffman code,
it'll sound like I'll get, you know, n
times entropy plus n because I'm paying
that plus one every time, right? But
there's a trick where we can replace
that. So that's the last thing I want to
show you.
And this is one of the really cool
punchlines.
So let's imagine you know and then the
length end case will follow immediately
from this. What if we want to encode
outputs of length two okay?
So what if our source outputs two
symbols instead?
Well, we can still think about them
as a single symbol just on a larger
alphabet,
right?
Because originally we had, you know, six
symbols, but now we'll have 36 in our
alphabet. Each of these pairs of
characters is a new symbol in my
alphabet. A AB acce
has a larger value for K.
What I can do is I can compute the
entropy, right? So what's the entropy
of this source?
Well, you know, now it's minus the sum
over all I, the sum over all J because
I'm taking two symbols I and J. the
probability that our first symbol is I,
the probability that our second symbol
is J times log of PI PJ.
But now something amazing happens which
is that I can just algebraically
manipulate this statement. I'll get
minus the sum over i the sum over j of p
i pj log pi
plus p i pj log pj. This is just using
properties of the log.
And now look at this term right here.
I can sum up over j and then I can
replace the pj with one because the pj
sum to one. So I'll get the sum over i
of pi log pi. And the same way here I
can sum up over i because i doesn't
appear inside the log. So I can replace
this pi with one and get rid of the sum.
So this entire thing is then equal to
minus the sum over i of pi log pi minus
the sum over j pj log pj.
All this is is two times the entropy,
right?
It's two times the entropy because each
of these terms is computing the entropy.
So this is one of the amazing facts
about entropy is that you know when you
look at the entropy of the output at
length two, it's just twice the entropy
of the per symbol entropy that you
started with H. Right? And now something
amazing happens which is if I think
about this theorem, right? And instead
of encoding my output for my channel
symbol by symbol,
what if I encode it, you know, as a
pair. So instead when I look at, you
know, the output as being two symbols,
you know, my new entropy is 2 h, right?
So I'll have that my expected length is
at most 2 h but still plus one.
When I do it for an output that's size
n, it'll be n * h, but still + one. that
plus one is just a fixed thing that we
add independently of how large our
alphabet is. So this result that we had
from Shannon where there was a you know
bound and the suboptimality that's some
little o of n that's like n over log n
or root n it turns out that we can
replace this with plus one.
So this is an amazingly sharp thing that
follows immediately from our proof of
Huffman codes. So we improved upon two
things here. First of all, we have a
more explicit coding function because it
follows just from this greedy algorithm.
And second of all, we drastically
improve this additive loss in our
original bound. So, you know, Huffman is
really um one of the crown jewels in
coding theory. And it was proven really
uh by a grad student, which is pretty
amazing, who wanted to get out of taking
a final exam. So, with that, I'll leave
you as an invitation. If you also want
to get out of your exam three, just
prove something else that we're going to
teach in lecture next semester and I
will happily give you an A for the
class. If not, come to office hours and
we'll help you study. All right. Um, so
we'll continue next time with Shannon's
noisy coding theorem. That'll probably
be the hardest lecture in the coding
theory unit. Uh, but you know, come
prepared, be awake, and ready to answer
questions. See you then.